<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig1">
 <label>Figure 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Characterization of JEV, YFV and CHKV protein expression and VLP release. 
   <bold>(A)</bold> 293 T cells were transfected with JEV CprME expression vector. Cells were analyzed for E protein and Capsid protein expression after staining with respective antibodies followed by fluorescence microscopy. 
   <bold>(B)</bold> 293 T cells were transfected with JEV CprME expression vector alone or the JEV CprME vector along with Zika NS2B-3 expression plasmid. Culture supernatants were ultracentrifuged and analyzed for E protein and Capsid protein expression by western blotting. 
   <bold>(C)</bold> 293 T cells were transfected with YFV CprME expression vector and analyzed for E protein and Capsid protein expression by immunofluorescence microscopy. 
   <bold>(D)</bold> 293 T cells were transfected with YFV CprME expression vector alone or the YFV CprME vector along with Zika NS2B-3 expression plasmid. Culture supernatants were ultracentrifuged and analyzed for E protein and Capsid protein expression by western blotting. 
   <bold>(E)</bold> 293 T cells were transfected with CHKV expression vector and analyzed for E1-E2 protein expression by immunofluorescence microscopy. 
   <bold>(F)</bold> 293 T cells were transfected with CHKV expression vector. Culture supernatants were ultracentrifuged and analyzed for E1-E2 protein expression by western blotting. Images A, C and E were analyzed using NIS Elements AR software version 3.2 (Nikon; 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nis-elements-viewer.software.informer.com/3.2/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://nis-elements-viewer.software.informer.com/3.2/</ext-link>). Images B, D and F were analyzed using GENETOOLS gel analysis Software version 4.03 (f) (Syngene, 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.syngene.com/software/genetools-automatic-image-analysis/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.syngene.com/software/genetools-automatic-image-analysis/</ext-link>).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_61103_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e371" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
