<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>EGFR single- and two-color STORM imaging were performed using a recently developed flat-field epi illumination microscope [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Briefly, two lasers with wavelengths of 642 nm (2RU-VFL-P-2000-642-B1R, MPB Communications) and 750 nm (2RU-VFL-P-500-750-B1R, MPB Communications) were used to switch off fluorophores on the sample, while a 405 nm laser (OBIS, Coherent) controlled the return rate of the fluorophores to the fluorescence-emitting state. A custom dichroic (ZT405/561/642/750/850rpc, Chroma) reflected the laser light and transmitted fluorescence emission before and after passing through the objective (CFI60 PlanApo Lambda Å~60/NA 1.4, Nikon). After passing the respective filter (ET700/75M, Chroma or ET810/90m, Chroma), emitted light from the sample was imaged onto the sCMOS camera (Zyla 4.2, Andor). Axial sample position was controlled using the pgFocus open hardware autofocus module (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://big.umassmed.edu/wiki/index.php/PgFocus" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://big.umassmed.edu/wiki/index.php/PgFocus</ext-link>). Typically, 20,000 frames at 10 ms exposure time were recorded using Micromanager[
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Imaging was performed using an optimized STORM buffer as described previously[
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Image stacks were analyzed using a custom CMOS-adapted analysis routine[
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Lateral sample drift was corrected using either image correlation (Thunderstorm[
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]) or gold fiducial markers (B-Store, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/kmdouglass/bstore" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/kmdouglass/bstore</ext-link>). Two-color datasets were analyzed using LAMA[
 <xref rid="ppat.1008656.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Random datasets for CBC analysis were generated in MatLab.
</p>
