<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For many RNA polymerases, biochemical studies have been performed in order to explore template requirements for homologous RNA recombination, without the bias generated by selection of RNAs that are more competent for replication [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007706.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1007706.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. The strength of base pairing regions between the donor and the acceptor RNA strands is believed to modulate genome propensity for this process. In this regard, not all viral variants have the potential to generate diversity through RNA recombination. For instance, previous studies show that CHIKV-La Reunion carrying the deletion of both DR1 and both DR2 copies does not introduce changes at the 3’UTR during adaptation. Instead, it acquires compensatory mutations in protein coding regions, so as to improve viral fitness in mosquito cells [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007706.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. It seems reasonable that a minimum number of DR copies should be maintained to drive RNA recombination between homologous strands. Here, although bearing certain sequence variations, we have detected recombination events when viruses containing the 3’UTR from different CHIKV lineages coexist in the same cell. During outbreaks, coinfections of mosquitoes and patients with different arboviruses have been extensively documented, supporting the notion that simultaneous exposure of mosquitoes to multiple arboviruses during one feeding episode is highly frequent [[
 <xref rid="ppat.1007706.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1007706.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], for review see [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007706.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]]. Given the fact that ECSA and Asian derived lineages co-circulate in the same geographic areas [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007706.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1007706.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1007706.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], we propose that RNA recombination may occur in mosquitoes that are simultaneously infected with different CHIKV lineages, resulting in the emergence of new viral variants. The ability of viral genomes to recombine within mosquitoes could clearly have implications on CHIKV epidemiology and evolution.
</p>
