<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>After the nationwide EV71 epidemic that occurred in Taiwan in 1998, multiple and real-time national enterovirus surveillance systems have been established by the Taiwan Centers for Disease Control since 2000 and include viral lab network; outpatient, inpatient, and emergency room visits for HFMD and/or HA from National Health Insurance claim data; and mandatory notification of enterovirus severe cases [
 <xref rid="pone.0224110.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0224110.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0224110.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The real-time EV surveillance makes early detection of EV71 possible, and strict implementation of preventive measures during EV71 circulation periods are applied, so these preventative measures may limit the spread of EV71 [
 <xref rid="pone.0224110.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. For example, to reduce the risk of enterovirus clustering, class suspension has been executed for the pre-school education and care institutions. Strengthened implementation of infection control measures is applied in hospitals and postpartum nursing care centers to reduce the risk of enterovirus clusters. For medical care of severe enterovirus cases, Taiwan Centers for Disease Control have constructed a medical service network for recent 2 decades and workshops are held on the clinical treatment of critical enterovirus complications to enhance doctors’ skills every year. There has been a marked decrease in severe and fatal EV71 cases after 2012 [
 <xref rid="pone.0224110.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], and the results of this seroepidemiology study also endorse the impact of a well-established real-time enterovirus surveillance system and all the preventive measures to limit the spread of EV71 in Taiwan. Other speculations may include viral evolution, as evidenced by EV71-like gene elements appearing in other cocirculating EV-A viruses by intensive recombination [
 <xref rid="pone.0224110.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The virulence of EV71 could thus be modified. Overall, the viral (recombination and mutation), host (low birth rate) and environmental (increased surveillance) factors might change transmission dynamics of EV71. However, with the accumulation of a susceptible high-risk group during the past 20 years, new epidemics could occur in the years to come. Careful monitoring and preventive measures are still necessary.
</p>
