<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Current medical treatments include various methods. Most patients with recently diagnosed melanoma have early-stage disease and can be treated by surgical excision, which is curative in the majority of cases. Some treatment methods involve lymph node biopsies in addition to standard surgical excision. Unfortunately, 10% of all melanoma cases are diagnosed at an advanced/late stage and are already metastatic, including visceral and brain metastases [
 <xref rid="B2-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. These patients have a poor prognosis and the probability of treatment success is lower. For patients with advanced stage disease, revolutionary therapy agents including RAF (Rapidly Accelerated Fibrosarcoma) and MEK (Mitogen-activated Protein Kinase) kinase inhibitors as well as immune checkpoint inhibitors like anti-CTLA4 and anti-PD1 have been approved, in 2011 and 2016, respectively [
 <xref rid="B5-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Anti-PD1 and anti-CTLA4 antibodies (nivolumab, pembrolizumab and ipilimumab) as well as BRAF and MEK inhibitors (vemurafenib and trametinib) have shown promising results in clinical trials [
 <xref rid="B9-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Today, the presence of the BRAF
 <sup>V600E</sup> mutation is verified in clinical settings, since it determines the correct treatment strategy. Mutations like NRAS, NF1, CKIT, CDKN2A and PTEN have not been included in clinical practice yet.
</p>
