<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0085">Cells are best cultured in microenvironments in vitro, which can mimic the original environment where the cells grow. Previously, cell cultures were done on 2D substrates monolayers of cells on a glass plate [
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] but had limitations as cell microenvironments were 3-Dimensional (3D). 3D microenvironments can bridge the gap between animal models and monolayer cell cultures [
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] Hence, to develop 3D microenvironments with functional phenotype were developed using micro-engineering techniques like photolithography, replica modeling and micro-contact printing [
 <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>]. The material used in these techniques was synthetic polymers which were limited and required complicated fabrication processes and expensive instruments [
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. To prepare cell culture scaffolds, smooth polymers are used, but to develop such scaffolds with topographical features, time-consuming methods such as hot embossing and soft lithography had to be used. One such example of the 3D microenvironment is spheroids. Spheroids are hydrogel scaffolds that are widely used to assess therapeutic efficacies and toxicities. These microenvironments mimicked the poorly vascularized tumor tissue due to the presence of chemical gradients. These chemical gradients formed zones viz., necrotic cells at the core, quiescent cells in the interior and proliferating cells along the exterior [
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. However, spheroids had certain limitations: Firstly, histological sections had to be made to study these spheroids; Secondly, they offered limited experimental control over the formed chemical gradients; and lastly, only a small subset of cell lines are capable of forming aggregates [
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. Hence, paper-based-cultures (PBCs) emerged as a promising alternative to polymer-based-cultures. 
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> shows a pictorial representation of the different zones of cells in tumors, spheroids, and Cells-in-Gels-in-Paper (see 
 <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> ).
</p>
