<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0010">The 2019 novel coronavirus [severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2)] was first documented in December 2019 in Wuhan, China, and has resulted thus far in significant global morbidity and mortality.
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> SARS-CoV-2 is genetically related to SARS-associated coronavirus (SARS-CoV), which caused an epidemic in 2002 to 2003. Although not proved, it is believed that the epidemic of SARS-CoV was successfully contained through public health interventions; nonetheless, besides differences in policy timeliness and effectiveness between the two epidemics, SARS-CoV-2 has proved to be significantly more difficult to contain. Both viruses utilize the same receptor for cell entry; however, SARS-CoV-2 uses a modified spike protein, which has a higher avidity for the corresponding human receptor and likely amplifies viral infectivity.
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>2</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> Moreover, the two viruses appear to have different shedding kinetics. SARS-CoV viral load (VL) peaks on average 10 days after symptom onset; in comparison, a recent study with 94 subjects from the Guangzhou Eighth People's Hospital in China showed that SARS-CoV-2 viral load peaks at 0.7 days before symptom onset, suggesting that transmission occurs early in the course of the infection.
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> As a result, disease containment may require strategies different from those utilized in the containment of SARS-CoV. In addition, authors compared viral load kinetics in mild and severe cases of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) and reported no differences between the two groups.
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref> In a similar manner, a study with 5000 subjects from Lombardy, Italy, showed no difference in viral loads between asymptomatic carriers and symptomatic COVID-19 patients.
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref> On the other hand, a study with 76 patients in Nanchang, China, showed that hospitalized patients with severe disease tend to have a high viral load and a longer virus-shedding period compared with milder cases.
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
