<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>Chikungunya virus (CHIKV), a mosquito-borne alphavirus of the 
  <italic>Togaviridae</italic> family, is part of a group of emergent diseases, including arbovirus, constituting an increasing public health problem in tropical areas worldwide. CHIKV causes a severe and debilitating disease with high morbidity. The first Colombian autochthonous case was reported in the Colombian Caribbean region in September 2014. Within the next two to three months, the CHIKV outbreak reached its peak. Although the CHIKV pattern of clinical symptomatology has been documented in different epidemiological studies, understanding of the relationship between clinical symptomatology and variation in phenotypic response to CHIKV infection in humans remains limited. We performed a cross sectional study following 1160 individuals clinically diagnosed with CHIKV at the peak of the Chikungunya outbreak in the Colombian Caribbean region. We examined the relationship between symptomatology and diverse phenotypic responses. Latent Class Cluster Analysis (LCCA) models were used to characterize patients’ symptomatology and further identify subgroups of individuals with differential phenotypic response. We found that most individuals presented fever (94.4%), headache (73.28%) and general discomfort (59.4%), which are distinct clinical symptoms of a viral infection. Furthermore, 11/26 (43.2%) of the categorized symptoms were more frequent in women than in men. LCCA disclosed seven distinctive phenotypic response profiles in this population of CHIKV infected individuals. Interestingly, 282 (24.3%) individuals exhibited a lower symptomatic “extreme” phenotype and 74 (6.4%) patients were within the severe complex “extreme” phenotype. Although clinical symptomatology may be diverse, there are distinct symptoms or group of symptoms that can be correlated with differential phenotypic response and perhaps susceptibility to CHIKV infection, especially in the female population. This suggests that, comparatively to men, women are a CHIKV at-risk population. Further study is needed to validate these results and determine whether the distinct LCCA profiles are a result of the immune response or a mixture of genetic, lifestyle and environmental factors. Our findings could contribute to the development of machine learning approaches to characterizing CHIKV infection in other populations. Preliminary results have shown prediction models achieving up to 92% accuracy overall, with substantial sensitivity, specificity and accuracy values per LCCA-derived cluster.
 </p>
</abstract>
