<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The CoVs genome is a single-stranded positive-sense RNA (+ssRNA) molecule. The genome size ranges between 27–32 kbp, one of the largest known RNA viruses (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-09-00331-f001">Figure 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B20-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The genomic structure of CoVs contains at least six open reading frames (ORFs). The first ORFs (ORF1a/b), located at the 5′ end, about two-thirds of the whole genome length, and encodes a polyprotein1a,b (pp1a, pp1b) [
 <xref rid="B25-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Other ORFs are located on 3′ end encodes at least four structural proteins: envelop glycoprotein spike (S), responsible for recognizing host cell receptors [
 <xref rid="B26-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Membrane (M) proteins, responsible for shaping the virions [
 <xref rid="B27-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The envelope (E) proteins, responsible for virions assembly and release [
 <xref rid="B28-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The nucleocapsid (N) proteins are involved in packaging the RNA genome and in the virions and play roles in pathogenicity as an interferon (IFN) inhibitor [
 <xref rid="B29-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In addition to the four main structural proteins, there are structural and accessory proteins that are species-specific, such as HE protein, 3a/b protein, and 4a/b protein [
 <xref rid="B24-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Once the viral genome enters the cytoplasm of the target cell, and given it is a positive-sense RNA genome, it translates into two polyproteins 1a, b (pp1a, pp1b). These polyproteins are processed into 16 non-structural proteins (NSPs) to form a replication-transcription complex (RTC) that is involved in genome transcription and replication. Consequently, a nested set of subgenomic RNAs (sgRNAs) is synthesized by RTC in the form of discontinuous transcription [
 <xref rid="B24-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].
</p>
