<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pbio-1001571-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001571.g003</object-id>
 <label>Figure 3</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Fossil MMTV-like endogenous retroviruses (ERVs) identified in divergent rodent taxa.</title>
  <p>(A) A diagram of the MMTV genome is shown, with genes drawn on three levels to indicate different reading frames. Proteins produced from each gene are listed underneath. An MMTV-like ERV was found in the genome of the deer mouse, 
   <italic>Peromyscus maniculatus</italic>. Five MMTV-like ERVs are also evident in the genome of brown rat, 
   <italic>R. norvegicus</italic>, as has previously been noted 
   <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Baillie1" ref-type="bibr">[67]</xref>. Multiple rat ERV copies allowed us to construct the consensus sequence approximating the sequence of the exogenous rat virus (“RMTV”) that gave rise to these ERVs. Genetic distances between each rat ERV and the RMTV consensus (0.008–0.018 substitutions/site), combined with the neutral substitution rate observed in the rat genome (0.00506 substitutions/site/MY) 
   <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Gibbs1" ref-type="bibr">[91]</xref>, support an RMTV infection of rats that lasted from 3.6 to 1.6 million years ago. A diagram of the RMTV genome is also shown. LTR, long terminal repeat. (B) A beta-retrovirus phylogeny constructed from an alignment of approximately 900 nucleotides in the region of 
   <italic>pro-pol</italic>. In bold are exogenous viral sequences. All others are endogenous viral sequences found integrated in the genomes of the indicated host species. The tree shows that the brown rat and deer mouse (green star) ERVs discussed in the text are more closely related to MMTV than any other virus reported in GenBank. The predicted position of the ancestral RMTV virus is shown (red star). The red branches indicate a family of viruses that we refer to as MMTV-like viruses. A maximum likelihood tree is shown. On each node are bootstrap values, given as percentage of 1,000 replicates. The tree was rooted with feline immunodeficiency virus (FIV), a lentivirus that is not in the beta-retrovirus family. JSRV, Jaagsiekte sheep retrovirus; SRV4, Simian retrovirus 4; MPMV, Mason-Pfizer monkey virus. See also 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.1001571.s001">Figure S1</xref>. (C) A small portion of the aligned Pol protein translation is shown to demonstrate the degree of sequence similarity between the three MMTV-like viruses discussed.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pbio.1001571.g003" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
