<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The population of long-term excretors changes over time, and consequently modeling the risks should involve appropriate characterization of the dynamics of accumulation of excretors and their progression through different stages of infection until they ultimately either stop excreting spontaneously or die. Based on our understanding of how PID patients move through various clinical and OPV infection stages (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), we developed a DES model to estimate long-term poliovirus excretor prevalence over time following each PID patient for life. The model uses a discrete time step of 1 month. We use the stratification from an integrated global model (i.e., the global model) that assigns all countries to epidemiological blocks of approximately 100 million people in 2013 classified by polio vaccine use as of 2013 (i.e., OPV-only, sequential IPV/OPV, or IPV-only), geographic proximity, and economic status [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. We estimated poliovirus basic reproduction number (R
 <sub>0</sub>) values for each block based on prior modeling experience and use R
 <sub>0</sub> as a proxy for many factors that affect poliovirus transmission and the health system quality by correlating R
 <sub>0</sub> with vaccine coverage and take rate, extent of fecal-oral transmission, and costs. Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> provides the resulting global R
 <sub>0</sub> distribution for the different strata of income levels and polio vaccine use as of 2013. Because the accumulation of PID patients increases relatively slowly in the model, we use a long burn-in period, assuming the same general population death rates throughout, but increasing treatment fractions (see below). Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> includes the assumptions about when IPV-only or IPV/OPV starts during the burn-in period for different income levels.
</p>
