<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Viral vectors have been frequently used as delivery vehicles for immunization against infectious agents such as pathogenic viruses [
 <xref rid="B159-biomedicines-08-00109" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>]. In many cases, strong humoral and cellular immune responses have been observed as well as protection against challenges with lethal doses of pathogenic viruses. In the context of coronaviruses, a recombinant adenovirus vector expressing the heat-labile enterotoxin B (LTB) and the core neutralizing epitope (COE) of PEDV was administered intramuscularly or orally into BALB/c mice and piglets [
 <xref rid="B150-biomedicines-08-00109" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>]. Three vaccinations at two-week intervals generated robust humoral and cellular immune responses. Cell-mediated immune responses were seen in mice and neutralizing antibodies inhibited both the vaccine strain and emerging PEDV isolates. Strong immune responses were observed in piglets, but further studies are required to verify the protection against challenges with highly virulent PEDV strains. In another study, the modified vaccinia virus Ankara (MVA) strain was utilized for the expression of recombinant MERS-CoV S protein [
 <xref rid="B151-biomedicines-08-00109" ref-type="bibr">151</xref>]. Immunization of dromedary camels elicited mucosal immunity. Immunized camels showed significantly reduced excretion of infectious virus and viral RNA transcripts and protection against MERS-CoV correlated with the presence of neutralizing antibodies in the serum. In another application of MVA, the MERS-CoV N was used for induction of cellular immune responses [
 <xref rid="B152-biomedicines-08-00109" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>]. Identification of MHC-I- and MHC-II-restricted T cell responses was carried out on overlapping peptides spanning the whole MERS-CoV N polypeptide in BALB/c mice immunized with MVA-MERS-CoV N. An H2-d restricted decamer peptide epitope showing CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cell antigenicity was identified, which will be further subjected to protection studies in mouse models for MERS-CoV. In the context of SARS-CoV, the N and S protein genes were cloned between the glycoprotein G and polymerase L genes in a highly attenuated safe rabies virus (RV) vector [
 <xref rid="B153-biomedicines-08-00109" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>]. A single injection with the RV-SARS-CoV S vector induced strong neutralizing antibody responses in mice, which makes it a promising candidate for eradication of SARS-CoV from animal reservoirs.
</p>
