<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since we sequenced virus from the blood from mice infected in the footpad, it is also conceivable that bottlenecks within the mice accounted for the observed differences. It is plausible that the virus replicated in the blood of obese mice more slowly later in infection due to the host immune response or other factors, which could account for both the reduction in viral titer on day 3 post-infection and the reduced genetic diversity. Obesity is known to alter the relative amounts of different leukocytes, potentially altering the availability of susceptible cells during infection or leading to a skewed cytokine response [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008089.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008089.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. It is possible that differences in the immune status of mice from each group result in different selective pressures on the virus population. Several studies have shown that the innate immune system is involved in viral evolution [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008089.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008089.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Finally, obese mice are expected to have more adipocytes (i.e., fat cells) while undernourished mice are expected to have fewer. Adipocytes secrete a variety of cytokine-like molecules called adipokines that alter immune response and energy utilization [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008089.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008089.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Furthermore, adipocytes differentiate from fibroblasts [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008089.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], which are known targets of alphavirus replication [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008089.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008089.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], potentially making them targets for alphavirus replication. Future studies will aim to uncover the mechanism behind the differences in viral genetic diversity observed in mice fed different diets.
</p>
