<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Vaccination is the best strategy to prevent infections and diseases by exposure to specific pathogens, especially in vulnerable populations (Ralph et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0079" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Therefore, it is absolutely critical to develop safe and efficient vaccines to control the spread of the pandemic and prevent the recurrence of outbreaks of SARS‐CoV‐2. In the early stages of the outbreak, the Chinese government said that at least five vaccine technologies would be explored in China, including an inactivated vaccine, a subunit protein vaccine, a nucleic acid vaccine, an adenoviral vector vaccine, and a recombinant vaccine (Zhang, 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0115" ref-type="ref">2020a</xref>). On January 23, 2020, the Coalition for Epidemic Preparedness Innovations (CEPI) declared that they would fund three vaccine technology platforms to develop effective vaccines against SARS‐CoV‐2 in the shortest period including DNA, mRNA, and “molecular clamp” platforms (Lu, 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). It was encouraging that on March 16, 2020, the NIH announced that the first vaccine against SARS‐CoV‐2, named mRNA‐1273, entered Phase I human study (NCT04283461), which represented a total of 63 days from sequence selection to first human dosing by using the mRNA platform (Moderna, 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0070" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Subsequently, on the same day, another exciting development of a subunit vaccine (adenovirus Type 5 vector) against SARS‐CoV‐2 was created by experts of the Academy of Military Medical Sciences of China and was approved for clinical trials (Zhang, 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0116" ref-type="ref">2020b</xref>). The subunit vaccine, which has been approved in terms of safety, efficacy and quality by a third party, is a type of vaccine containing only a fragment of the SARS‐CoV‐2 pathogen to induce a protective immune response, according to the WHO. Since the start of the SARS‐CoV‐2 outbreak, the world's major academic institutions and biopharmaceutical companies have joined the race to develop a safe and effective prophylactic vaccine through multiple platforms such as mRNA, DNA, adenoviral vector, and recombinant protein platforms (Pang et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0073" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). On April 6, 2020, Inovio Pharmaceuticals pronounced that the FDA had accepted their investigational new drug application of a new DNA vaccine (INO‐4800). INO‐4800 is the third approved vaccine candidate worldwide and the first DNA vaccine against SARS‐CoV‐2. Meanwhile, SARS‐CoV‐ and MERS‐CoV‐related vaccine experience may accelerate the design and development of anti‐SARS‐CoV‐2 vaccines, due to the remarkable sequence homology among SARS‐CoV‐2, SARS‐CoV, and MERS‐CoV (Lu et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). We believe that there will soon be good news regarding SARS‐CoV‐2 vaccines, as a result of the joint efforts in scientific research.
</p>
