<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">Emerging infectious diseases (EIDs) could be defined as infectious diseases which increase (their prevalence or threaten) over time. They include (1) new unknown diseases which are first diagnosed and (2) old diseases which evolved or mutated from already existing agents and gained new features (i.e. adaptation to new hosts or target population, new geographic distribution, new clinical picture, new epidemiological profile, new spread pattern or resistance to used therapeutics). The events that drive emerging of infectious diseases were illustrated in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. Endemic diseases may also re-emerge where they are endemic (i.e. release epidemics or their prevalence increases clearly). Meanwhile, the re-emerging diseases could be defined as new infections resulting from unknown or newly introduced pathogen to a new geographic area (Dikid et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2013</xref>; Epizooties OId 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2014</xref>; Ogden and Gachon 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135">2019</xref>). The major emerging and re-emerging infectious agents in the last decade included Ebola virus (Africa), Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (Middle East) and Zika, chikungunya, yellow fever and dengue viruses (North and South America) (Ogden and Gachon 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135">2019</xref>). The CDC listed at least 50 emerging/re-emerging diseases worldwide. Some common examples of emerging and re-emerging diseases infecting human, animals or both were listed in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The list included Bovine spongiform encephalopathy, campylobacteriosis, Chagas disease, cholera, 
 <italic>Cryptococcus</italic>, cryptosporidiosis, cyclosporiasis, cysticercosis, dengue fever, diphtheria, drug-resistant infections (antimicrobial resistance), Ebola haemorrhagic fever, 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> infection, group B streptococcus, hantavirus pulmonary syndrome, Hendra virus, hepatitis C, histoplasmosis, HIV/AIDS, influenza, Lassa fever, Legionnaires’ disease, leptospirosis, listeriosis, Lyme disease, malaria, Marburg haemorrhagic fever, measles, monkeypox, MRSA, Nipah virus, norovirus, pertussis, plague, poliomyelitis, rabies, Rift Valley fever, rotavirus, salmonellosis, severe acute respiratory syndrome, shigellosis, sleeping sickness (trypanosomiasis), smallpox, tuberculosis, tularemia, valley fever (coccidioidomycosis), vancomycin-intermediate or vancomycin-resistant, 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, West Nile virus and yellow fever which are mainly insect-borne, airborne, water-borne and foodborne diseases (Smith et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR174">2017</xref>). The published disease list includes mainly of the so-called neglected tropical diseases (NTDs). NTDs are a group of bacterial, viral, parasitic and fungal pathogens usually endemic in tropical and subtropical developing countries. As these diseases are usually limited to poor countries, the pharma industry did not invest enough money to solve these problems until they started to expand and represent a real threat to the developed world. According to WHO, 20 core NTDs are candidates to re-emerge in the developed countries due to global warming namely; the dengue fever and rabies (viral diseases), buruli ulcer (
 <italic>Mycobacterium ulcerans</italic> infection), trachoma (
 <italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic>), yaws (spirochete), treponematoses, and leprosy (bacterial diseases), Chagas disease, trypanosomiasis, leishmaniasis, dracunculiasis, cysticercosis, echinococcosis, foodborne trematodiases, lymphatic filariasis, onchocerciasis (river blindness), schistosomiasis, and soil-transmitted helminthiases (ascariasis, hookworm, trichuriasis) (parasitic diseases) (El-Sayed and Awad 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2018</xref>; Mackey et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">2014</xref>; Mitra and Mawson 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR123">2017</xref>). These neglected tropical pathogens may re-emerge again due to the expansion of the vector hosts (insect/rodent-borne diseases), by wind (airborne diseases), floods (water-borne diseases), migration of human/domestic or wild populations, even melting the accumulated snow due to the global warming may liberate the (sleeping) spores (e.g. anthrax). Importation of exotic pets may also play a role in the introduction of new pathogens or parasites to free locations (Andreassen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2012</xref>, Dhimal et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2015a</xref>, Mackey et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">2014</xref>, Mitra &amp;Mawson 2017). However, it was observed that the effect of the climatic changes on the vectors is not equal. For instance, the geographical expansion of mosquitoes is affected not only by the increase in temperature but also by the wind intensity and direction, relative humidity and rainfalls in opposite to ticks. This is attributed to the life cycle of mosquitoes which depend on one stagnant water for laying eggs and for the development of larval stages. Reports concerning the increase in the prevalence of malaria due to climatic changes are already published in Iran (Babaie et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2018</xref>) and Zimbabwe (Gunda et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2017</xref>).
</p>
