<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Similar in principal to the role of the microbiome in vector competence, the role of the vector virome also deserves special consideration. The role of insect-specific viruses (ISVs) in affecting vector competence should be considered, as well as their potential use in reducing transmission. Most ISVs have been detected in mosquito samples, which is due in part to sampling bias in arbovirus surveillance, as well as the existence of a susceptible mosquito cell line (C6/36, 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>) carrying a defective RNAi response [
 <xref rid="B118-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. To date, insect-specific viruses have been discovered as members of the order Bunyavirales, and the families 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic>, 
 <italic>Togaviridae</italic>, 
 <italic>Reoviridae</italic>, 
 <italic>Rhabdoviridae</italic>, and 
 <italic>Mesoniviridae</italic>, and the proposed taxon 
 <italic>Negevirus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B118-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B120-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>,
 <xref rid="B121-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>], of which the latter two are comprised solely of ISVs. These viruses are often detected during arbovirus surveillance studies upon the screening of mosquito samples in insect cell cultures [
 <xref rid="B122-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. Despite their intrinsic host restriction, often limiting their ability to infect and/or replicate in vertebrate cells, these agents are often closely related to pathogens of clinical and veterinary importance [
 <xref rid="B118-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B120-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>]. For example, Eilat virus (EILV), an alphavirus within the 
 <italic>Togaviridae</italic> family that is a sister clade to the western equine encephalitis virus (WEEV) serocomplex, was originally isolated from a pool of 
 <italic>Anopheles coustani</italic> mosquitoes from the Negev desert near the city of Eilat region in Israel [
 <xref rid="B122-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>,
 <xref rid="B123-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>]. EILV is restricted to replication in arthropods/mosquitoes at both the viral attachment/entry as well as the genomic replication levels, and exhibits limited ability to orally infect mosquitoes. It cannot infect 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> at a bloodmeal titer of 9.0 log
 <sub>10</sub> PFU/mL; it only infects 
 <italic>Cx. quinquefasciatus</italic> and 
 <italic>An. gambiae</italic> with this same high titer, but can infect 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> at oral doses of 7.0 log
 <sub>10</sub> PFU/mL [
 <xref rid="B124-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]. EILV induces the homologous and heterologous interference of superinfecting alphaviruses in both insect cell culture as well as during in vivo infections of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> with CHIKV. Specifically, the pre-infection of C7/10 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> cells with EILV 24 hours prior to superinfection with either VEEV (TC-83) or Sindbis virus (SINV) significantly decreases titers of the superinfecting virus and delays peak replication [
 <xref rid="B123-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>]. Similarly, intrathoracic (IT) infection of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> with EILV 7 days prior to oral exposure to CHIKV decreases the infection rate observed at 3 and 5 days post-infection (DPI) compared to PBS-inoculated controls, although this decrease disappears by 7 DPI [
 <xref rid="B123-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>]. In the case of insect-specific flaviviruses (ISFs), there exist two distinct clades, one which lies well outside the clade of arboviruses. This group includes viruses such as cell fusing agent virus (CFAV), Culex flavivirus (CxFV), and Kamiti River virus (KRV), while the other clades lie within the mosquito-borne arboviruses as close relatives of Japanese encephalitis virus (JEV), DENV, ZIKV, and WNV, among many others [
 <xref rid="B119-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B125-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. One in the latter group, called Nhumirim virus (NHUV), has also demonstrated an ability to interfere with infection by heterologous flaviviruses, reducing replication kinetics in C6/36 cells of SLEV, JEV, and WNV whether the second virus was inoculated simultaneously (co-infection), or superinfected 1, 3, or 5 DPI [
 <xref rid="B126-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. This effect was reproduced with ZIKV and DENV-2, and IT inoculation of NHUV into 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> 6 days prior to a ZIKV-infectious bloodmeal caused a significant decrease in ZIKV infection and dissemination. The co-inoculation of both ZIKV and NHUV to 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> significantly decreased ZIKV transmission in saliva compared to mosquitoes solely inoculated with ZIKV [
 <xref rid="B127-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>]. Similar observations have been made in 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> infected IT with CFAV. Specifically, 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> were IT inoculated with CFAV two days prior to oral exposure to either ZIKV (PF2013, French Polynesia, 2013) or DENV-1 (KDH0026A, Thailand, 2010), and heads were removed and tested independently for both the presence of virus and titer 2, 5, 7, and 13 DPI [
 <xref rid="B128-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. Although there were no differences in the rate of DENV infection between CFAV-infected and mock-infected mosquitoes, both the rate of dissemination and the titer of DENV present in the head were significantly lower in CFAV-infected mosquitoes when infectious output assays were conducted in C6/36 mosquito cells. Similar results for DENV-1 were observed in an identical experimental paradigm utilizing infectious assays conducted on Vero cells (to preclude CFAV-induced cytopathic effects in C6/36 cells as a confounding element). Strikingly, ZIKV infection and dissemination rates were unaffected by prior CFAV infection (only assayed in Vero cells), although head titers 13 DPI were significantly lower in CFAV-infected 
 <italic>Ae. aegyti</italic> [
 <xref rid="B128-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. Given that infection with ISVs has been demonstrated to alter kinetics of arboviral infection in vitro and in vivo, their presence in established mosquito colonies likely acts as a confounding variable in competence analyses. Indeed, in an analysis conducted on 16 established laboratory colonies of mosquitoes, three were found to be persistently infected with ISVs [
 <xref rid="B127-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>], underscoring the necessity of the routine screening of laboratory populations for ISVs.
</p>
