<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Vaccines, despite their proven value in protecting against disease and their much‐heralded pivotal importance for lockdown exit and herd immunity, are the Cinderellas of clinical practice and, in normal times, not only attract little interest from governments but also are controversial, due to negative publicity from vociferous anti‐vaccine groups propagating unfounded claims. The development and use of a number of current vaccines/vaccine candidates are orchestrated and funded, not by industry and public health systems, but by philanthropic organizations, like the Gates Foundation, working with agencies like CEPI (Coalition for Epidemic Preparedness Innovations) and GAVI (Global Alliance for Vaccines and Immunizations). Indeed, the Gates Foundation is also playing a leading role in the search for, and development of, a vaccine against COVID‐19 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gatesfoundation.org/Media-Center/Press-Releases/2020/02/Bill-and-Melinda-Gates-Foundation-Dedicates-Additional-Funding-to-the-Novel-Coronavirus-Response" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.gatesfoundation.org/Media-Center/Press-Releases/2020/02/Bill-and-Melinda-Gates-Foundation-Dedicates-Additional-Funding-to-the-Novel-Coronavirus-Response</ext-link>). However, it is the duty of national governments and international organizations, as part of their pandemic preparedness, to finance vaccine development platforms that are able to rapidly create new vaccines in response to an outbreak. Once a new vaccine candidate is shown to be safe and protective, its rapid large‐scale production and distribution requires the infrastructure of large pharmaceutical companies. As epidemics cannot be planned, industrial managers cannot be expected to promote projects without a market. Governments must therefore intervene to maintain the interest and technical capacity of industry in developing vaccines and antibiotics (a smouldering fire) by creating a market in form of governmental orders. Assessments of value‐for‐money of these strategic alliances must be made in the context of the global costs of pandemics like that of SARS‐CoV‐2.
 <list list-type="bullet" id="emi15029-list-0014">
  <list-item id="emi15029-li-0018">
   <p>
    <italic>Pandemic preparedness requires rapid creation, production and distribution of effective materials for diagnosis, prophylaxis and therapy. This necessitates significant long‐term investment in research and development involving unconventional alliances of disparate academic science and medical research groups, industry, philanthropic foundations, vaccine enabling coalitions, and crisis preparedness taskforces</italic>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
