<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0085">Several logistic regression models were constructed to predict the binary outcome death/survival from the demographic, clinical (signs and symptoms), and laboratory data (viral load and malaria rapid test results) collected at triage. The predictors for the models were selected in a machine learning variable-selection process, where an initial set of candidate factors associated with death in EVD were submitted to penalized logistic regression using the R package Glmnet 
 <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref> with Elastic Net regularization. To define a non-redundant, parsimonious subset of predictors, variables with a coefficient &gt; 0 in at least half of the penalized models were retained. As marginal associations can become less significant when accounting for confounding dependencies in such multivariate models, the process tended to include variables with weak correlations to the outcome in bivariate analysis, such as bleeding and dyspnea, and elimination of variables that had a low P-value, like conjunctivitis. Using these variables, we constructed a family of non-penalized logistic regression models using the lrm function from the R package rms 
 <xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. This included a parsimonious model (using all the variables obtained from the selection process), and several fallback models that can be applied on smaller subsets of demographic information, clinical features and laboratory results, for use when more limited data is available at triage. This approach has been shown to outperform predictive value imputation, which consists of having only one full model and imputing missing values at prediction time using the data distribution from the training set 
 <xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Each final model in the family was obtained by fitting N copies of the model on each imputed dataset, and then averaging those copies into a single model using the fit.mult.impute function in Hmisc. Internal validation was performed using bootstrap resampling and model performance is presented by the area under the curve (AUC), McFadden's pseudo-R
 <sup>2</sup>, Brier score, accuracy, sensitivity and specificity. A prediction was classified as death when the score from the model was over the 0.5 threshold. Confidence intervals (CI) of all the performance estimates were calculated using Fisher's transformation 
 <xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Odds ratios (OR) from logistic regression were converted to risk ratios (RRs) according to Zhang and Yu 
 <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>.
</p>
