<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Antibodies (Abs) have been shown to play a critical role in the protective immune response against infectious diseases and have been used for passive immunization, in the prevention and treatment of both bacterial and viral infections, for more than a century. Immune animal sera were first used in the late 1800’s for treatment of disease, followed by an era of immune human serum therapy for both viral and bacterial diseases. Notably, during the 1918 influenza pandemic, serum from recovered patients was used successfully to treat acutely ill patients
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>. The role of convalescent serum therapy expanded to many infections beyond influenza during the first half of the 20th century with clinical benefit demonstrated for other viral diseases like measles
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup> and polio
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>, and for invasive bacterial pathogens, including pneumococcus, 
 <italic>Haemophilus influenzae B</italic>, and meningococcus
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. Passive immunization with antibody-based therapies has emerged as a promising strategy for treating emerging infectious diseases, and include both monoclonal (mAb) and polyclonal antibodies (pAb), each of which has its advantages and disadvantages. For example, mAbs can be easily manufactured in large quantities and have a greater inherent biological consistency due to their epitope specificity as compared to pAbs. However, mAbs have limitations, including development of escape mutants and high production costs. In comparison with mAbs, pAbs can have more robust activities, neutralizing several virus strains even after viral mutations
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup>. Although several studies have demonstrated that mAbs can provide therapeutic protection against ZIKV in various human and mouse models
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>, only a single study to date has shown therapeutic potential of human pAbs produced from transchromosomal cows against ZIKV infection in mice. As no study has as yet assessed the efficacy of pAbs isolated from humans as a potential therapeutic against ZIKV, herein, we evaluate the therapeutic potential of a pAb preparation from human plasma containing high anti-ZIKV titers (ZIKV-IG).
</p>
