<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par33">Kilifi HMPV subgroup prevalence patterns partly mirrored global patterns, there was predominance of A2b and B2 in 2007–2010 and subsequent rise of B1 and A2c in years that followed. B2 viruses persisted over the 9 years. A1 and A2a were the least commonly detected subgroups globally and this could probably explain why they were not detected in Kilifi. In contrast to continued circulation of clade A2b [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], in Kilifi, A2b circulated from 2007 to November 2012 and no longer. Occurrence of the clade A2c [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>] has increased in Kilifi in recent years, as similarly reported in Bangladesh and Croatia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], suggestive of global spread of HMPV variants. Based on F and G phylogenies, some of previously reported sequences from Europe, Asia and USA that either had not been sub-grouped or assigned to clade A2b, clustered within A2c, consistent with findings from a previous report [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Similarly, previously reported sequences of the unique A2 clade reported in Malaysia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] also clustered in this clade (A2c). Recently, two novel HMPV A2 strains with 180 or 111 nucleotide duplication in the G gene have also been reported [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. These strains were not observed in Kilifi. In the phylogenetic trees they clustered within A2c together with other A2c sequences without duplication including Kilifi A2c strains. Our findings reaffirm the circulation of A2c clade and point out the need for proper methods for classification of HMPV lineages. The replacement patterns of HMPV subgroups could be attributed to subgroup-specific herd immunity offering protection against circulating homologous strains but not against heterologous strains. This observation is not unique to Kilifi, as similar patterns were reported from long-term surveillance studies in Germany and France [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Consistent with earlier studies, G gene exhibited higher rates of evolution compared to F gene [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. F gene is more conserved and our findings concur with previous studies on F protein diversity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The rates of G gene evolution were in the range of 3.42× 10
 <sup>− 3</sup> to 9.57× 10
 <sup>− 3</sup>, similar to findings from previous studies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Among the subgroups, the rates of evolution for A2b and B1 were at least 2 fold higher than other subgroups, this concurs with the findings from a similar study [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. In general, higher polymorphism has been reported in HMPV G gene and further within the subgroups resulting from events such as changes in alternative transcription termination codons and insertions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. This could explain the differences in evolution rates. Further investigations are required to give more insights on the differences in evolution rates and its implication. Compared to other 
 <italic>Pneumoviruses</italic>, such as human respiratory syncytial virus (HRSV), HMPV G gene has been shown to have higher rates of evolution [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Our estimates show comparable results, the rates for HMPV A2b and B1 were 3 to 4 times higher than those reported for HRSV (3.58× 10
 <sup>− 3</sup>, 95% HPD = 3.04× 10
 <sup>− 3</sup> to 4.16× 10
 <sup>− 3</sup>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. The difference in the rates of evolution can be linked to strong association between neutralizing epitopes and positively selected sites reported for RSV G gene [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. In contrast to the case for other paramyxoviruses, such as RSV, the HMPV G protein is not a major neutralizing or protective antigen [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>].
</p>
