<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While the placenta serves as the first checkpoint to protect the fetus and support its normal growth and development of the fetus, the BBB provides the second checkpoint critical to protect the fetal brain and ensure healthy brain development (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Coyne and Lazear, 2016</xref>). The BBB is a boundary that separates the circulating blood from the brain and the extracellular fluid in the central nervous system (CNS) (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Daneman and Prat, 2015</xref>). The BBB is made up of endothelial cells of the vasculature forming cell-to-cell tight junctions to limit the passage of circulating molecules, cells, and pathogens to the CNS (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Stamatovic et al., 2008</xref>). Tight junctions containing more than 40 proteins with both transmembrane and cytoplasmic domains generate a continuous, circumferential, belt-like structure at the luminal end of the intercellular space, where it serves as a gatekeeper of the paracellular pathway (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Mateo et al., 2015</xref>). Three major transmembrane proteins, claudin, occluding, and junctional adhesion molecule (JAM), interact with cytoplasmic proteins including ZO-1, cingulin, afadin and α-catenin, which anchor strands to the cytoskeleton, resulting in the formation of cellular tight junctions (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Hartsock and Nelson, 2008</xref>). Disruption of the BBB enhances permeability of endothelial cell and is a hallmark of CNS infection (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Daniels and Klein, 2015</xref>). However, recent studies reported that no barrier disruption was observed when ZIKV gained access to the CNS (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Papa et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Alimonti et al., 2018</xref>), suggesting that the endocytic transport system is required for the ZIKV to cross the BBB barrier. Given the existence of endosomal sorting pathways in different cell types, it is possible for the BBB cells to employ a similar process of endosomal transportation (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Ayloo and Gu, 2019</xref>). However, there is no investigation on these pathways in BBB endothelial cells, particularly in the condition under viral infection.
</p>
