<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Available in near-real time, disease-related Internet search activity has been shown to track disease activity (a) in seasonal mosquito-borne disease outbreaks, such as those caused by dengue [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007065.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], and (b) in unexpected and emerging mosquito-borne disease outbreaks such as the 2015–2016 Latin American Zika outbreak [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007065.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Here, we investigated whether we could find a meaningful relationship between Internet search activity and the local chikungunya outbreak in Roraima. Indeed, novel Internet-based data sources have the potential to complement traditional surveillance by capturing early increases in disease-related search activity that may signal an increase in the public’s perception of a given public health threat and may additionally capture underlying increases in disease activity. Internet searches may be particularly important and indicative of changes in disease transmission early during an outbreak, when ongoing information on the virus transmission is obfuscated by a lack of medical surveillance. In addition, Internet search trends may also help track disease activity in populations that may not seek formal medical care. We used the Google Trends (GT) tool [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007065.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007065.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] to compile the monthly fraction of online searches for the term “Chikungunya”, that originated from Boa Vista municipality (Roraima state), between January 2014 and July 2018. For comparison, GT search activity for the term “Chikungunya” was collected for the same time period for Manaus municipality (Amazonas state). The synchronicity of GT time series and notified and confirmed case counts from Boa Vista and Manaus was assessed using the Spearman’s rank correlation test in the R software [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007065.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>].
</p>
