<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>SARS‐CoV‐2 causes imbalanced and exuberant immune responses termed as cytokine release syndrome or cytokine storm, which triggers lung impairment and reduces the survival of the infected patients (Pedersen &amp; Ho, 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0133" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>; Tisoncik et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0170" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). The inflammatory cytokines are usually produced by different macrophages, which are associated with cytokine storm (Luo et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0116" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>; Pedersen &amp; Ho, 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0133" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). SARS‐CoV‐2 significantly increases levels of proinflammatory cytokines such as IL‐6, IL‐10, and TNFα in infected patients (Channappanavar et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Diao et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>; Nikolich‐Zugich et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0131" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Furthermore, SARS‐CoV‐2 induced activation of a cluster of differentiation four positive (CD4
 <sup>+</sup>) T cells stimulate the generation of T helper cells and secrete interleukin (IL)‐6, and granulocyte‐macrophage colony‐stimulating factor (GM‐CSF). GM‐CSF triggers monocytes to further release of IL‐6 and other factors, resulting in the generation of a cytokine storm. This cytokine storm results in acute respiratory distress syndrome, multiple organ failure, and even death (Chen, Zhang, et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2020a</xref>; Zhou et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0202" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Targeted immunomodulation to decrease cytokine storm might be a feasible option to reduce pulmonary inflammation and mortality. Since only antiviral candidates may not be enough to combat such cytokine storm or complications in the respiratory tract, identifying effective targets for immune therapeutics along with antiviral agents could be a potential strategy. Preliminary results from a study suggest that Hydroxychloroquine might have anti‐cytokine storm properties (Yao et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0195" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Additionally, Lenziluman has been reported to be protective against cytokine storm and neurotoxicity in mouse models. Furthermore, Lenzilumab, an anti‐GM‐CSF monoclonal antibody, can be considered as a viable therapeutic option as COVID‐19 patients (Sterner et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0160" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>).
</p>
