<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We used boosted regression trees (BRTs) [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] with Bernoulli-distributed error for binary responses (Ebolavirus exposure, as indicated by any diagnostic method reported in primary literature). Boosted regression trees are a technique for learning the mapping between high-dimensional inputs and a unique response variable that has proved an effective approach to identifying functional trait associations in multi-host multi-pathogen systems [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The learning process consists of iterating regression trees, each defined by a series of recursive binary splits on randomly sampled predictor variables of mixed data types (e.g. categorical, numerical, binary). As this process is repeated, resulting trees are combined to create an ensemble model. We built 50 000 trees for each analysis reported here and present the most important variables for predicting Ebolavirus hosts. Because the dataset was relatively small (
 <italic>n</italic> = 119 species tested), we did not partition the data into training and holdout test sets. Instead, we applied fivefold cross-validation during model building to prevent overfitting and used permutation procedures to generate relative importance scores for each predictor variable. In these analyses, species that have not tested positive for Ebolavirus infection (
 <italic>n</italic> = 96) were designated non-hosts. This represents a conservative approach that minimizes type II error in a system where host status remains unknown without extensive field sampling. Analyses were performed using the 
 <italic>gbm</italic> package [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] in R [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. To gauge the effect of sampling bias on trait patterns, we also included sampling effort as covariates in the BRT model to predict host status by species. Finally, we restricted the BRT model to the top 10 most important covariates.
</p>
