<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Discrete phylogeographic modelling in BEAST used country of viral origin as a categorial trait and was set to infer asymmetric rates between countries [
 <xref rid="RSPB20191527C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Models were run for 150 million generations with trees sampled every 10 000 generations (electronic supplementary material, file S2). Given the potentially complex demographic histories within the international dataset, we specified the Bayesian skyline demographic model as a flexible prior of viral effective population size through time [
 <xref rid="RSPB20191527C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Bayesian stochastic search variable selection was used to estimate BF support for transitions between countries, and discrete Markov jumps recorded the magnitude of strongly supported transitions. Continuous phylogeographic models used the latitude and longitude of samples to reconstruct historical diffusion within Costa Rica [
 <xref rid="RSPB20191527C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Costa Rican viruses had different geographical origins which would have obscured reconstructed ancestral locations, but the limited number of sequences precluded independent analyses of each lineage. We therefore modelled each of the two largest monophyletic Costa Rican lineages (
 <italic>n</italic> = 13 and 14 sequences, respectively) as separate data partitions in the same BEAST analysis [
 <xref rid="RSPB20191527C36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Specifically, tree topologies and spatial reconstructions were independent, but evolutionary models and parameters were shared across lineages (electronic supplementary material, file S3). Given the limited data, this analysis used simpler demographic models of constant viral effective population size. Among four models of spatio-temporal diffusion, the gamma-distributed rates model was favoured over Brownian motion, Cauchy distributed and lognormal distributed rates (BF &gt; 8.6–15.1; electronic supplementary material, file S1). Dispersal velocities (mean branch velocity) were calculated using 1000 randomly sampled, post burn-in trees from the posterior using the 
 <italic>Seraphim</italic> package in R [
 <xref rid="RSPB20191527C37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20191527C38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. We modelled 1 year of uncertainty on the date of samples for which only the year of collection was available (precision = 1). We used T
 <sc>racer</sc> v. 1.7.1 to verify parameter convergence, check that effective sample sizes on parameters exceeded 200 and select appropriate burn-ins.
</p>
