<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0035">This begs the question of how to license a vaccine in the midst of an ongoing pandemic like SARS-CoV-2. Might reasonable “accommodations” be made for such a scenario? Several seem worth immediate discussion:
 <list list-type="simple" id="l0005">
  <list-item id="o0005">
   <label>–</label>
   <p id="p0040">Could a vaccine be provided through an EUA mechanism for mentally competent adults who meet certain risk guidelines, and in the context of study enrollment and data collection, and enhanced informed consent?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0010">
   <label>–</label>
   <p id="p0045">Could a vaccine be provided through a revised definition of a compassionate use mechanism in the highest risk subjects after signing waivers of responsibility and enhanced informed-consent procedures? Who should be included—perhaps healthcare providers and first responders who share the highest risk of infection as a starting point?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0015">
   <label>–</label>
   <p id="p0050">What, if any, animal models might be developed that allow the “animal rule” to be utilized in an effort to accelerate research and licensure?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0020">
   <label>–</label>
   <p id="p0055">If phase I and II trials are conducted earlier than normal procedure, could a phased initiation of studies from highest risk to lowest risk subjects be utilized?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0025">
   <label>–</label>
   <p id="p0060">Might one conceive of differential regulatory pathways for vaccine candidates using well-understood antigens, vaccine methodology, adjuvants, manufacture, and routes of administration (TBD) versus those using novel delivery technology and novel antigens or adjuvants?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0030">
   <label>–</label>
   <p id="p0065">As mentioned above, human challenge studies have been advanced as a method to rapidly determine efficacy in discussions I have had with other vaccinologists. Could this be a viable strategy in accelerating licensure? To date, no ethical framework has been advanced to support such an idea.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0035">
   <label>–</label>
   <p id="p0070">What will be the endpoint for determining vaccine efficacy—prevention of infection? Prevention of severe disease? Prevention of viral shedding? Other?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0040">
   <label>–</label>
   <p id="p0075">Will different vaccines and different regulatory pathways be feasible for different members of the population with differing risk:benefit ratios? For example, administering a vaccine to a healthy and robust 18-year-old with no underlying co-morbidities should require an exceptionally high safety and efficacy threshold. Might that safety profile be somewhat different (to be defined) in an exceptionally high risk 80-year-old with multiple co-morbidities? What about for pregnant women or younger but immunocompromised persons?</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
