<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>At present, PPSV23 is effective for preventing diseases associated with 23 common 
 <italic>S pneumoniae</italic> serotypes, and reductions in incidence, hospitalization, and mortality rates of streptococcal diseases, such as CAP and IPD, have been documented.
 <xref rid="agm212102-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>44</sup>
 </xref> Xu et al
 <xref rid="agm212102-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>66</sup>
 </xref> investigated 600 cases aged ≥ 60 years who were divided into a PPSV23 group and a control group. In that study, vaccination with PPSV23 was associated with reduced incidence of lower respiratory tract infection (69.7%), use of antibiotics (72.6%), and hospitalization (65.9%) during the subsequent year. Subgroup analysis indicated that PPSV23 could reduce lower respiratory tract infection, antibiotic use, and hospitalization frequency in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and coronary heart diseases, and reduce lower respiratory tract infection and antibiotic use in diabetes and hypertension patients. In a prospective study of a cohort followed from 2008 to 2011 involving 27 204 individuals aged ≥ 60 years in Spain, the risk of CAP in a recently (&lt;5 years) PPSV23‐vaccinated vaccine group was lower than that in a group that had never been vaccinated. The protective effect applied to bacteremic pneumococcal CAP, non‐bacteremic pneumococcal CAP, overall pneumococcal CAP, and all‐cause CAP.
 <xref rid="agm212102-bib-0067" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>67</sup>
 </xref> Maruyama et al
 <xref rid="agm212102-bib-0068" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>68</sup>
 </xref> reported that in a randomized double‐blind trial involving 1006 adults aged ≥ 55 years, the incidence of all‐cause pneumonia and pneumococcal pneumonia was significantly lower in a vaccinated group than in a placebo group, and mortality from pneumococcal pneumonia was significantly higher in the placebo group. In a meta‐analysis performed by Moberley et al,
 <xref rid="agm212102-bib-0069" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>69</sup>
 </xref> the PPSV23 vaccine was effective for preventing pneumonia and IPD in adults, and it was effective for preventing IPD in recipients aged ≥ 65 years. In a modeling study that added PPSV23 to the immunization schedule for elderly people in Shanghai, China, the incidence of pneumococcal disease in the PPSV23 vaccination group was lower than it was in the control group.
 <xref rid="agm212102-bib-0070" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>70</sup>
 </xref> The respective cumulative incidences of CAP, IPD, and hospitalization were reduced by 3.57%, 0.02%, and 1.06%.
</p>
