<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recent studies have focused on the modelling of face masks during the COVID-19 pandemic. One investigation was carried to examine the efficacy of face masks with regard to respiratory virus shedding in exhaled breath [
 <xref rid="B13-materials-13-03363" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Here, three groups of respiratory viruses were chosen due to their high infection rate (coronavirus, influenza virus and rhinovirus). The model is based on respiratory virus viral shedding of two groups: those wearing face masks and those without. Frequency of detection was studied by using a two-sided Fisher’s exact test and by measuring viral load through the use of an unadjusted Tobit regression model [
 <xref rid="B13-materials-13-03363" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. This model was also used to measure viral shedding without the use of a face mask. Results show that respiratory droplet influenza-transmission may be greatly reduced if a face mask is used. However, this is not the case for aerosol transmission. Results also highlight that the use of face masks by an ill person can greatly reduce the risk of onward transmission [
 <xref rid="B13-materials-13-03363" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] which correlates to the study by [
 <xref rid="B71-materials-13-03363" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>] described above. Within the samples collected without a face mask, the majority of individuals with influenza virus and coronavirus infection did not shed detectible virus in respiratory droplets or aerosols, whereas detectible virus in aerosols was seen in 53% of people with rhinovirus [
 <xref rid="B13-materials-13-03363" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. For those who did shed the virus through respiratory droplets and aerosols, viral load in each tended to be insignificant (after 30 min of exposure). This signifies that extended close contact with an infected individual would be required for transmission to occur [
 <xref rid="B13-materials-13-03363" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].
</p>
