<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, we assessed for the first time the ability of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> collected in different ecological settings in Central Africa to transmit a ZIKV strain isolated from sylvatic mosquitoes, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>africanus</italic>, collected in Dakar in 1984. We demonstrated that this ZIKV strain was able to replicate, disseminate, and be secreted in saliva of both 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic>. The results of these experiments indicate that ZIKV could be transmitted during blood feeding. Our analysis showed high infection, dissemination, and transmission rates in both species which is in agreement with previous experiments using ZIKV from the African lineage [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Disseminated infection and transmission rates varied significantly according to 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> populations. This result is consistent with previous studies showing the level of infection varied among mosquito populations [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Overall, transmission efficiency and ZIKV titre in saliva were significantly higher in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> than in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> corroborating the main role of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> in ZIKV transmission compared to 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Nevertheless, lower transmission rates and saliva ZIKV titres in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> were found for two populations from northern part of Cameroon, Benoué and Maroua, probably due to the presence of specific refractory genes [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Beside the mosquito genetic background, mosquito microbiome can modulate arbovirus transmission [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. In addition, refractoriness of mosquito to ZIKV can also be caused by mosquito immune responses since it was demonstrated that anti-viral immunity in mosquito vectors is critical to prevent virus replication and transmission [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].
</p>
