<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par105">It is relatively easy to collect CSF, but always exclude any contraindications before it is performed. These contraindications are summarized by Kneen et al. and Boyles et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. The first group of contraindications, which necessitates imaging before an LP, includes the following:
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par106">A change in the level of consciousness, or coma. There is no consensus on the depth of the coma, but the British Guidelines recommend that prior imaging is indicated if the Glasgow coma scale is less than 13 or fluctuates more than 2 [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par107">The presence of papilledema. Clinicians should bear in mind that papilledema may take time to develop, and will not be observed in the initial clinical assessment [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par108">Relative bradycardia in the presence of hypertension or abnormal doll’s eye movements [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par109">New-onset focal neurological deficits including unequal, dilated or poorly responsive pupils [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. If the level of consciousness is normal, isolated cranial nerve palsies are, however, not regarded as a contraindication to performing an LP [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par110">Inexplicable seizures. These should first be stabilized [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] and stabilization should be followed by imaging
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par111">Patients with ventriculoperitoneal shunts in situ [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par112">Immunocompromised patients [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
