<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While previous studies have estimated the costs of HIVST delivery strategies, to the best of our knowledge, this is the first micro-costing study of secondary distribution of HIVST. One study in Malawi conducted a costing of door-to-door HIVST to individuals in the community as part of a randomized clinical trial [
 <xref rid="B9-diagnostics-10-00318" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] and estimated the cost of HIVST distribution to be $8.78 per person; costs included HIVST provision and clinic-based confirmatory testing (USD 2014) [
 <xref rid="B21-diagnostics-10-00318" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-diagnostics-10-00318" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. This cost fell between our estimates for the as-studied and MOH roll-out scenarios. Another study assessing the cost of door-to-door community-based HIVST found the cost per individual given a kit was $8.15, $16.42, and $13.84 in Malawi, Zambia, and Zimbabwe, respectively, which are similar to our findings [
 <xref rid="B23-diagnostics-10-00318" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The majority of HIVST costing studies were conducted in the context of cost-effectiveness analyses, which found that HIVST is cost-effective when used for testing high-risk sub-populations in settings where the undiagnosed prevalence is above 3%, and if HIVST promotes linkage to PrEP and voluntary male medical circumcision (VMMC) [
 <xref rid="B21-diagnostics-10-00318" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. A modeling study evaluating HIVST in low-income countries projected that HIVST would save $75 million USD in healthcare costs and avert up to 7000 disability-adjusted life-years (DALYs) over 20 years [
 <xref rid="B24-diagnostics-10-00318" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-diagnostics-10-00318" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-diagnostics-10-00318" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. However, we did not find cost or cost-effectiveness studies on secondary distribution of HIVST from PWLHIV, limiting our ability to compare our results with others in the literature. 
</p>
