<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The infection of some immune cells is an important pathological feature of HSV that leads to a negative effect on the antiviral immunity induced by the virus and represents a challenge for HSV vaccine development. Previous data have confirmed that the viral infection of peripheral DCs induces vesicle lesions in the skin or mucosa and have suggested the virus impacts the transduction of antigen signals from the innate immune system to the adaptive immune system via classic antigen presentation. These studies observed that the expression of some coactivating immune molecules, including CD1a, CD40, and intercellular adhesion molecule 1 (ICAM‐1), on the surface of HSV‐infected DCs is limited, while the expression of other DC surface molecule, including CD83, C‐C motif chemokine receptor 7 (CCR7), C‐X‐C motif chemokine receptor 4 (CXCR4), and IFNGR1, was downregulated during the transition of infected immature DCs into a mature state.
 <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0142" ref-type="ref">142</xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0143" ref-type="ref">143</xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0144" ref-type="ref">144</xref> Thus, infected DCs might present variable immunological phenotypes during their transition from a physiologically immature state to a mature state. On the other hand, viral infection might induce damage to the DC membrane and lead to the release of immune signals and spreading of virus. This event might cause not only further viral infection of other cells but also abnormal immune signaling in various immune cells, which could reshape the immune response. Further study of infected DCs has revealed that the transfer of antigen from the cytosol to the endoplasmic reticulum is blocked by HSV infection, which could downregulate antigen presentation to T cells by DCs through restricting the binding of antigen to the major histocompatibility complex 1 (MHC‐1) molecule in cells.
 <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0144" ref-type="ref">144</xref> The data have also suggested that HSV is capable of interacting with caveolin‐1 to alter the activity of nitric oxide synthase and limit the production of NO
 <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0145" ref-type="ref">145</xref> and that the migration rate of infected DCs moving from the local tissue to the lymph nodes was decreased because of an increased death rate.
 <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0142" ref-type="ref">142</xref> All of these data suggest the hypothesis that by interfering with DCs, a major antigen‐presenting cell in the immune system, HSV infection might lead to abnormal immune signaling in T cells and induce weakened adaptive immunity. Our unpublished work suggests that HSV infection of ILCs located in epithelial tissue can modify the ILCs phenotype. Both DCs and ILCs are functional cell subsets that link the innate and adaptive immune systems by interacting directly with T cells and/or presenting antigens to them. Viral infection of both cell groups could be recognized as part of a strategy of immune evasion. In this sense, the specific immunity induced in HSV‐infected individuals might be inferred to be a type of incomplete immunity.
</p>
