<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The 
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic> genus (family 
 <italic>Flaviviridae)</italic> includes fifty-three taxonomically recognised species and at least nineteen ‘tentative’ species (
 <xref rid="vey021-B35" ref-type="bibr">King and Am 2014</xref>). The flaviviruses display an exceptional diversity of ecological networks that widely correlate with the phylogenetic relationships within the genus (
 <xref rid="vey021-B79" ref-type="bibr">Zanotto et al. 1995</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B19" ref-type="bibr">Gaunt et al. 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B22" ref-type="bibr">Grard et al. 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B21" ref-type="bibr">Gould and Solomon 2008</xref>). To date, the majority of recognised flaviviruses are arthropod-borne viruses (arboviruses). They are transmitted among vertebrate hosts by mosquitoes (MBFV), ticks, or sandflies (TBFV). The genus also includes viruses with no known vector (‘NKV’) and some that infect only insects (insect-specific flaviviruses, ‘ISFV’) (
 <xref rid="vey021-B40" ref-type="bibr">Kuno et al. 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B56" ref-type="bibr">Moureau et al. 2015</xref>). Several important (re)-emerging human pathogens fall within the MBFV and TBFV groups, notably dengue virus (DENV), yellow fever virus (YFV), tick-borne encephalitis virus (TBEV), Japanese encephalitis virus (JEV), West Nile virus (WNV), and the recently emerged, Zika virus (ZIKV). Flaviviruses are spherical, enveloped particles (virions) of 
 <italic>ca.</italic> 50 nm diameter, incorporating single-stranded positive sense RNA genomes. The capped, eleven kilobase genome includes a single open reading frame (ORF), flanked at its 5′ and 3′ termini by structured, non-coding regions, essential for viral RNA translation and replication (
 <xref rid="vey021-B59" ref-type="bibr">Ng et al. 2017</xref>). ORF translation gives rise to a polyprotein that is cleaved co- and post-translationally into the structural (C-prM-E) and seven non-structural proteins (NS1-2A-2B-3-4A-4B-5) (
 <xref rid="vey021-B6" ref-type="bibr">Bell et al. 1985</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B63" ref-type="bibr">Rice et al. 1985</xref>).
</p>
