<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The first rationale for codon usage bias was that codon abundance correlated with that of isoaccepting tRNAs and could influence the level of protein production within a given host (
 <xref rid="vey021-B30" ref-type="bibr">Ikemura 1985</xref>). Several other possibilities have been proposed since then, including implication in mRNA structure and its folding (
 <xref rid="vey021-B67" ref-type="bibr">Shabalina, Ogurtsov, and Spiridonov 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B39" ref-type="bibr">Kudla et al. 2009</xref>), microRNA-targeting (
 <xref rid="vey021-B9" ref-type="bibr">Brest et al. 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B8" ref-type="bibr">Birnbaum et al. 2012</xref>) and enhanced recognition by the immune system (
 <xref rid="vey021-B75" ref-type="bibr">Tulloch et al. 2014</xref>), that may vary according to the host (
 <xref rid="vey021-B23" ref-type="bibr">Greenbaum et al. 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B32" ref-type="bibr">Jimenez-Baranda et al. 2011</xref>). Specific and random re-encoding approaches have been efficiently applied to several human RNA viruses including poliovirus, influenza A virus, human immunodeficiency virus, respiratory syncytial virus, chikungunya virus (CHIKV), JEV, TBEV, and DENV (
 <xref rid="vey021-B10" ref-type="bibr">Burns et al. 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B57" ref-type="bibr">Mueller et al. 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B60" ref-type="bibr">Nougairede et al. 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B15" ref-type="bibr">De Fabritus et al. 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B45" ref-type="bibr">Martinez et al. 2016</xref>). Considering a major role of genome-wide mutational processes in the shaping of synonymous sites (
 <xref rid="vey021-B13" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. 2004</xref>), specific re-encoding approaches include codon and codon-pair deoptimisation as well as increase of CpG/UpA dinucleotide frequency. On the other hand, the efficiency of random codon re-encoding strategies for the attenuation of CHIKV 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and of TBEV 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> suggests an important influence of local constraints (e.g., cis-acting sequences, miRNA targeting) on genome encoding (
 <xref rid="vey021-B74" ref-type="bibr">Thurner et al. 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B77" ref-type="bibr">Watts et al. 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B60" ref-type="bibr">Nougairede et al. 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B15" ref-type="bibr">De Fabritus et al. 2015</xref>).
</p>
