<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0460">With the advancement of systems and synthetic biology and the ease of genetic modification, biothreats are becoming more complex and there is a growing need for novel treatments that can have broad-spectrum activity against new, remerging, and engineered pathogens. Developing novel countermeasures that can effectively treat and prevent massive casualties is an ongoing challenge that remains a central priority for future research. The development of novel therapies relies on an improved understanding of the host–pathogen interactions. Key virulence factors have been identified and targeted for potential treatment options, including biofilm and T3SS inhibitors for bacterial infections, and viral entry or polymerase inhibitors for viral infections. Combining HTS with systems biology provides a robust, coordinated approach to identifying therapeutic targets. Since stand-alone antibiotics or antivirals may not be sufficient to overcome resistant or engineered biothreat infections, a focus on combination therapy, antibodies, and HDTs is the key countermeasure. Although many challenges are faced when developing novel therapies for biothreat pathogens and no FDA-approved HDTs are yet available for treatment, there is potential for novel small molecule host-targeted immunomodulators to be developed. Screening of FDA-approved drugs is a powerful approach to possibly repurpose drugs for new disease indication and/or identify compounds that are safe and effective in humans, which can also have antibacterial or antiviral capabilities. Three FDA-approved drugs have shown potential in mice against pneumonic plague 
 <xref rid="bib1040" ref-type="bibr">[207]</xref>. Serious challenges still remain with the prevalence of antibiotic resistance that jeopardizes the effectiveness of our current treatment options for bacterial threats. In addition, the complex intracellular life cycle of many biothreat pathogens requires therapeutics that can penetrate the host cell. There are limited FDA-approved viral countermeasures for prevention and treatment. None of the filoviruses or henipaviruses has approved therapeutics or vaccines available for human disease. Some vaccines exist for new world alphaviruses, but no current therapeutics are effective for treatment after infection. Focused efforts using HTS to develop novel, effective, and broad-spectrum medical countermeasures will provide a robust response capability against rapidly evolving biothreats.
</p>
