<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">The authors have noted a significant discrepancy in the recommended level of respiratory PPE globally. Far-eastern countries, who have had to endure respiratory epidemics in the last 20 years, prioritise mask wearing universally, with less cultural stigmata and consider it a part of hygienic practice [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. In Hong Kong, under the emergency COVID-19 response, masking of all patients has been enforced. Surgical masks alongside protective eyewear were worn by both ophthalmologists and patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. A recent publication by Ophthalmologists at National University Hospital, Singapore, informs healthcare workers in eye-care settings to use PPE including N95 respirators, eye protection, gown and gloves when providing direct care to patients displaying COVID-19 symptoms [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. American Academy of Ophthalmology suggests the use of N95 masks to protect the mouth and nose; and goggles or shields to protect the eyes when seeing patients infected with COVID-19 and those under investigation in line with the US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention guidance [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Italian Ophthalmologists’ recommendations published on 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.eurotimes.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.eurotimes.org</ext-link> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] advise, amongst social distancing and hand hygiene, that all patients should wear a mask during the entire time of their visit to the clinic including during the various examinations. They also recommend all staff to always wear a mask to reduce droplet spread, even in the presence of colleagues and other staff members. In the UK, the Royal College of Ophthalmologists respiratory PPE guidance broadly echoes Public Health England recommendations which state FFP3 respirator use only during high-risk procedures (delivering or assisting with an AGP). For other settings, a fluid repellent face mask is the advocated respiratory cover for ophthalmologists within 1 m of a patient with possible or confirmed COVID-19 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>].
</p>
