<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0060">The CoV N protein is a multifunctional RNA-binding protein necessary for viral RNA transcription and replication [
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. It plays many pivotal roles in forming helical ribonucleoproteins during packaging the RNA genome, regulating viral RNA synthesis during replication, transcription and modulating infected cell metabolism [
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. The primary functions of N protein are binding to the viral RNA genome, and packing them into a long helical nucleocapsid structure or ribonucleoprotein (RNP) complex [
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. 
 <italic>In vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> experiments revealed that N protein bound to leader RNA, and was critical for maintaining highly ordered RNA conformation suitable for replicating, and transcribing the viral genome [
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. More studies implicated that N protein regulated host-pathogen interactions, such as actin reorganization, host cell cycle progression, and apoptosis [
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. The N protein is also a highly immunogenic and abundantly expressed protein during infection, capable of inducing protective immune responses against SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>]. The common domain architectures of coronavirus N protein are consisting of three distinct but highly conserved parts: An N-terminal RNA-binding domain (NTD), a C-terminal dimerization domain (CTD), and intrinsically disordered central Ser/Arg (SR)-rich linker. Previous studies have revealed that the NTD are responsible for RNA binding, CTD for oligomerization, and (SR)-rich linker for primary phosphorylation, respectively [
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>]. The crystal structures of SARS-CoV N-NTD [
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], infectious bronchitis virus (IBV) N-NTD [
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>], HCoV-OC43 N-NTD [
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] and mouse hepatitis virus (MHV) N-NTD [
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] have been solved. The CoVs N-NTD have been found to associate with the 3′ end of the viral RNA genome, possibly through electrostatic interactions. Additionally, several critical residues have been identified for RNA binding and virus infectivity in the N-terminal domain of coronavirus N proteins [
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>]. However, the structural and mechanistic basis for newly emerged novel SARS-CoV-2 N protein remains largely unknown. Understanding these aspects should facilitate the discovery of agents that specifically block the coronavirus replication, transcription and viral assembly [
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Kang et al. [
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>] reported the crystal structure of SARS-CoV-2 nucleocapsid N-terminal domain (termed as SARS-CoV-2 N-NTD), as a model for understanding the molecular interactions that govern SARS-CoV-2 N-NTD binding to ribonucleotides. This finding will aid in the development of new drugs that interfere with viral N protein and viral replication in SARS-CoV-2, and highly related virus SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>].
</p>
