<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite decades of research, a broadly protective, commercially available vaccine for ASFV remains elusive. Multiple vaccine development strategies have been employed, with varying levels of success. Inactivated whole viral antigen does not induce protective immunity (
 <xref rid="B152" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>). Subunit, vector-based, and DNA vaccines targeting specific viral proteins have produced inconsistent results, ranging from variable protection to enhancement of disease and accelerated mortality (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B113" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B153" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>–
 <xref rid="B155" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>). Attenuated modified live virus (MLV) vaccines, derived from extensive viral passaging in cell lines or through targeted gene deletions, have been extensively investigated and can confer protection against homologous parental virus challenge (
 <xref rid="B156" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>), but generally provide little to no cross-protection against heterologous virulent strains (
 <xref rid="B157" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>). Additionally, MLV vaccines usually have a limited safety profile with modest to severe side effects causing arthritis, skin necrosis and chronic infections. Further research into the correlates of protection and basic ASFV immunology is needed to facilitate targeted, rationally-designed vaccine development (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B157" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>–
 <xref rid="B159" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>). A number of highly immunogenic ASFV antigens have been identified, yet the role of ASFV-specific cellular and humoral immune responses in protection from ASF is still not completely clear. Results regarding the role of ASFV-specific neutralizing antibodies in protection are conflicting, and high levels of non-neutralizing antibodies appear to have a detrimental effect (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B160" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>). For example, the presence of neutralizing antibodies does not always confer protection and in some cases immunization with ASF proteins is associated with enhanced ASFV infection and pathology, despite induction of antibodies which are neutralizing 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B113" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B153" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>). Importantly, cell-mediated immunity, including induction of CD8+ T-cells and natural killer cells, appears to play an important role in protection against ASF (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B161" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B162" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>), since pigs exposed to the low-virulence OUR/T88/3 strain and subsequently depleted of CD8+ lymphocytes were no longer protected from challenge with the virulent OUR/T88/1 isolate.
</p>
