<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <title>Acknowledgments</title>
 <p>We thank Andrew Rambaut for his comments on the design of the exercise; the PANGEA-HIV steering committee and participants of the PANGEA-HIV satellite workshop of the 21st and 22nd HIV Dynamics &amp; Evolution conference for their comments during the exercise; and three anonymous reviewers and associate editors for their comments that improved an earlier version of the article. Regional simulations were designed and generated using resources at the Imperial College High Performance Computing Service (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www3.imperial.ac.uk/ict/services/hpc" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www3.imperial.ac.uk/ict/services/hpc</ext-link>). Team Cambridge-London thanks the MRC Centre for Outbreak Analysis and Modeling for support. Team Vancouver thanks Rosemary McCloskey for help with tree reconstructions; their contribution was enabled in part by support provided by Westgrid (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.westgrid.ca" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.westgrid.ca</ext-link>) and Compute Canada Calcul Canada (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.computecanada.ca" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.computecanada.ca</ext-link>). This work was supported by the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation through the PANGEA-HIV consortium (to O.R., E.H., A.L.B., and C.F.); the NIH through the NIAID cooperative agreement UM1AI068619 for work on the HPTN 071 trial (to A.C., M.P., and C.F.); the Wellcome Trust (WR092311MF to O.R.); the European Research Council (PBDR-339251 to C.F., PhyPD-335529 to T.S.); the National Institutes of Health (NIH MIDAS U01 GM110749 to E.V. and A.L.B., NIH R01 AI087520 to E.V.); the Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council (BB/J004227/1 to S.J.L.); the Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR HOP-111406 to A.F.Y.P., New Investigator Award 175594 to A.F.Y.P.), the Michael Smith Foundation for Health Research/St. Paul’s Hospital Foundation/the Providence Health Care Research Institute (Scholar Award 5127 to A.F.Y.P.); the ETH Zürich Postdoctoral Fellowship Program (to D.R. and D.K.); the Marie Curie Actions for People COFUND Program (to D.R. and D.K.); the University of Edinburgh Chancellor’s Fellowship scheme (to S.J.L.); the Centre of Expertise in Animal Disease Outbreaks (to S.J.L.); and the Swiss National Science Foundation (162251 to G.E.L.). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the article.
 </p>
</ack>
