<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>FIG 3</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Structure-based mapping of sites identified under selection and previously unreported N-linked glycosylation sites onto the Gc protein. (a) Schematic of the OROV M segment polyprotein, which includes the Gn and Gc components of the viral membrane proteins. The Gc protein is subdivided into a head domain (blue), two stalk domains (green and orange), and a C-terminal region, which encodes a putative fusion loop (dark gray). Sites identified as being under positive selection using the MEME approach are shown in red (lighter colored arrows indicate sites falling outside the Gc head and stem domains). Site 269 was identified as being under positive selection through multiple approaches and is marked with an asterisk. All N-linked glycosylation sites are shown in white, and the two previously undescribed sites are highlighted in blue and pink. (b) Estimated 
   <italic>dN</italic>/
   <italic>dS</italic> ratio of each domain in Gc, obtained for the whole M segment, and for each M segment lineage. (c) Crystallographically observed trimeric spike structure of the Gc head domain, with sites under positive selection shown in red. The cartoon representation of each chain is embedded in a transparent surface representation (gray). Glycosylation sites are shown as in panel a. (d) Sites under positive selection and residues corresponding to N-linked glycosylation sites mapped to a composite model generated from previously reported OROV Gc (head domain, PDB ID 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.rcsb.org/pdb/explore/explore.do?structureId=6H3X" assigning-authority="pdb" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">6H3X</ext-link>) and SBV Gc (stem domains, PDB ID 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.rcsb.org/pdb/explore/explore.do?structureId=6H3S" assigning-authority="pdb" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">6H3S</ext-link>) crystal structures. The OROV head domain is shown in blue, with the C terminus loop residues shown in light green (taken from the SBV head domain) and SBV stem domains I and II shown in green and orange, respectively. (e) Putative N-linked glycosylation sites identified in this study are mapped onto the phylogeny of the M segment, showing the independent presence the two sites in the two M segment lineages.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="JVI.01127-19-f0003" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
