<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="brief-report"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Chest</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Chest</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Chest</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0012-3692</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1931-3543</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American College of Chest Physicians</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7094599</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S0012-3692(15)31961-9</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.125.3.1155</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Dispersal of Respiratory Droplets With Open vs Closed Oxygen Delivery Masks</article-title><subtitle>Implications for the Transmission of Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome</subtitle></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au10"><name><surname>Somogyi</surname><given-names>Ron</given-names></name><degrees>BSc</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au20"><name><surname>Vesely</surname><given-names>Alex E.</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au30"><name><surname>Azami</surname><given-names>Takafumi</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au40"><name><surname>Preiss</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au50"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>Joseph</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au60"><name><surname>Correia</surname><given-names>Joe</given-names></name><degrees>RT</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au70"><name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>Robert A.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, MS</degrees><email>rob.fowler@sw.ca</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>University Health Network, Toronto General Hospital, Toronto, ON, Canada</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Medicine, Sunnybrook &#x00026; Women's College Health Sciences Centre, University of Toronto, Toronto, ON, Canada</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Correspondence to: Robert Fowler, MD, MS, Assistant Professor, University of Toronto, Departments of Medicine (General Internal Medicine) and Critical Care Medicine, Sunnybrook &#x00026; Women's College Health Sciences Centre, 2075 Bayview Ave, Room D478, Toronto, ON, Canada M4N 3M5 <email>rob.fowler@sw.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>125</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1155</fpage><lpage>1157</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2003</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2004 The American College of Chest Physicians</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="ceab10"><p>Nosocomial transmission of droplet-borne respiratory infections such as severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) may be influenced by the choice of oxygen face mask. A subject inhaled saline mist and exhaled through three oxygen masks to illustrate the pattern of dispersal of pulmonary gas. In two commonly used masks, exhaled gas formed a plume emanating from the side vents, while a third mask with a valved manifold, which was modified by adding a respiratory filter, retained the droplets. Maintaining respiratory isolation during the administration of oxygen may reduce the risk of the nosocomial transmission of respiratory infections such as SARS.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="cekeyws10"><title>Key words</title><kwd>droplets</kwd><kwd>nosocomial</kwd><kwd>oxygenation</kwd><kwd>oxygen mask</kwd><kwd>severe acute respiratory syndrome</kwd><kwd>ventilation</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group id="cekeyws20"><title>Abbreviation</title><kwd>SARS, severe acute respiratory syndrome</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="para10">Severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) is a newly recognized illness that has spread rapidly throughout Asia, North America, and Europe. As of June 20, 2003, 8,461 people in 30 countries had developed SARS, leading to 804 deaths.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> The transmission of SARS from patients to health-care workers and other patients has been a prominent and worrisome feature of existing SARS outbreaks.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> The transmission of infection is thought to be through exhaled viral-laden droplets.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> Because many patients with SARS require supplemental oxygen administration by face mask,<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> we imaged patterns of droplet dispersal with various oxygen masks to investigate the potential for possible nosocomial spread and reported our preliminary observations.</p><sec id="cesec10"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p id="para20">After ethics board approval was obtained, the subject inhaled aerosolized 3% saline fluid droplets that were produced by an ultrasonic nebulizer (DeVilbis Ultra-Neb-99 Large-Volume Ultrasonic Nebulizer; Sunrise Medical; Somerset, PA). The breath was then held briefly (approximately 2 s), while one of three oxygen masks was fitted to the face. The subject then exhaled smoothly for &#x0003e; 2 s through the mask while a series of photographs were taken. Photographs were not altered except for adjustments to brightness and contrast.</p><p id="para30">The procedure was repeated three times with each of three oxygen masks. Two of the masks had side vents for exhaled gas (a nonrebreathing mask [Airlife Adult Oxygen Mask; Allegiance Healthcare Corp; McGaw Park, IL] and a Venturi-type mask [Airlife Percento<sub>2</sub> Mask; Allegiance Healthcare Corp]). The third mask had no vents. All exhaled gas exited through a single 22-mm port in the attached manifold (Hi-Ox80; Viasys; Yorba Linda, CA). The Hi-Ox80 was tested without and with a respiratory filter (Barrierbac &#x0201c;S&#x0201d;; Mallinckrodt; Mirandola, Italy) on the expiratory port. No oxygen flow was supplied to any of the masks during testing.</p></sec><sec id="cesec20"><title>Results</title><p id="para40">A good fit was achieved with all masks: no exhaled gas was observed leaking between the edge of the mask and the face. With the nonrebreathing and Venturi-type masks, plumes of exhaled droplets could be seen exiting the side vents (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>
). In the mask without vents, all exhaled vapor was directed through the exhalation port (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>
, <italic>left, A</italic>). Placing the respiratory filter on the exhalation port appeared to prevent droplets from leaving the mask (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>, <italic>right, B</italic>). There was no increased positive pressure or increased end-tidal carbon dioxide discovered using the modified oxygen delivery system.<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Subject exhaling previously inhaled saline aerosol mist while wearing nonrebreathing oxygen mask (<italic>top, A</italic>) and Venturi-type oxygen mask (<italic>bottom, B</italic>). The plume represents only exhaled breath because there was no oxygen flow into the masks.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Subject exhaling previously inhaled saline aerosol mist while wearing Hi-Ox80 oxygen mask without an added filter placed on the exhalation port (<italic>left, A</italic>) and with added filter placed on exhalation port (<italic>right, B</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="cesec30"><title>Discussion</title><p id="para50">These preliminary observations from an ongoing study suggest the presence of a mechanism by which the method of oxygen administration can contribute to the spread of droplet-borne respiratory infection, including SARS (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://isocapnia.com/SARS.htm" id="interrefs10">http://isocapnia.com/SARS.htm</ext-link>). Throughout exhalation, both the nonrebreathing mask and the Venturi-type mask channeled the exhaled gas through the side vents, forming a plume of exhaled gas (marked here by the previously inhaled aerosol) that was directed to the side of the patient. This potentially infectious plume could be directed toward caregivers, visitors, and other patients at face level. The extent of the plume might be greater with oxygen flows or when expiratory flows are increased by coughing, sneezing, or hyperventilation.</p><p id="para60">Does this model accurately reflect the droplet spread associated with respiratory infections such as SARS? The plumes visible in the figures are composed of the previously inhaled mist that marks the distribution of exhaled gas. We assumed that endogenously produced droplets would be within the distribution of the exhaled gas. The spread of the exhaled gas may be greater than shown, as evaporation and reduction in density of the droplets at the margin of the plume may limit their effectiveness as markers. On the other hand, the visualized cloud does mark the minimum distribution of gas that originated in the lung.</p><p id="para70">In the mask without side vents, all exhaled gas traverses a manifold containing three valves and exits through a single port. Placing a bacterial/viral filter on this port may provide effective respiratory isolation during oxygen administration to spontaneously breathing patients.</p><p id="para80">The current recommendations for the management of SARS patients acknowledge the importance of the isolation of exhaled gas to prevent the release of infected droplets into the atmosphere.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> This can be accomplished with N95 or equivalent masks in spontaneously ventilating patients who do not require oxygen supplementation, and by the placement of bacterial/viral hydrophobic filters on the end of the endotracheal tube and/or the exhalation port of the self-inflating bag or breathing circuit in ventilated patients. However, when oxygen supplementation is required for spontaneously breathing patients, guidelines often condone open oxygen delivery systems that do not retain respiratory droplets.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> In light of reports of SARS patients infecting other patients and health-care workers during the preintubation phase of their treatment, despite the use of protective equipment by health-care workers, we think that additional measures should be considered.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> The administration of oxygen using the delivery systems described in this article may further reduce the risk of the nosocomial transmission of respiratory infections such as SARS.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bibl10"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>World Health Organization</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Communicable disease surveillance and response: cumulative number of reported probable cases of SARS</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/csr/sars/country/2003_06_20/en/" id="interrefs20">Available at: http://www.who.int/csr/sars/country/2003_06_20/en/</ext-link><comment>Accessed February 17, 2004</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A major outbreak of severe acute respiratory syndrome in Hong Kong</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>348</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>1986</fpage><lpage>1994</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12682352</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Cluster of severe acute respiratory syndrome cases among protected health-care workers&#x02014;Toronto, Canada, April 2003</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><volume>52</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12807083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lapinsky</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallett</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Critically ill patients with severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS)</article-title><source>JAMA</source><volume>290</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12865378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yap</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS): infection control [letter]</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>361</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>1386</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref60"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ontario Medical Association</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Directives to all Ontario acute care hospitals for high-risk procedures involving SARS patients critical care areas: SARS Provincial Operations Centre; May 13, 2003</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.oma.org/phealth/sars/high_risk_procedures_in_critical_care.pdf" id="interrefs30">Available at: http://www.oma.org/phealth/sars/high_risk_procedures_in_critical_care.pdf</ext-link><comment>Accessed February 17, 2004</comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ceack10"><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</title><p>We thank Steve Iscoe, PhD, and Arthur S. Slutsky, MD, for their review of the manuscript, Allan Coates, MD, and Gerald Smaldone for their guidance on droplet dispersal, and Agnes Ryzynski and Jon Hendrix for photography services.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="d32e306"><p id="cenpara10">This study was funded by the Ontario Thoracic Society. Dr. Fisher and Mssrs. Vesely, Somogyi, and Preiss participated in the development of the Hi-Ox80 and receive royalties on sales.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>