<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>LAMP is another isothermal nucleic acid amplification method that is extensively utilized for sensitive, specific, rapid, and cost-effective detection of both DNA and RNA viruses in human specimens. The method was first developed by Notomi et al. [
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>] and rapidly gained popularity in diagnostic virology. The method employs four to six unique primers and DNA polymerase with strand-displacement activity to amplify target DNA [
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. The addition of RT in LAMP reaction (RT-LAMP) permits the amplification of RNA target [
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Primer sets for LAMP initially reported by Notomi et al. [
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>] include the forward inner primer (FIP), backward inner primer (BIP), forward outer primer (F3), and backward outer primer (B3). The primers are specifically designed to recognize six precise regions from a targeted nucleic acid sequence. Nagamine et al. [
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>] later added two loop primers, namely, forward loop primer (LF) and backward loop primer (LB), to accelerate LAMP assay. Owing to the use of four to six specific primers, LAMP assay has outstanding sensitivity and specificity in the detection of target nucleic acids [
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. A detailed description of the LAMP reaction mechanism is available in reviews by Becherer et al. [
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>], Tomita et al. [
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>], and Silva et al. [
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>], which use illustrations to explain the mechanism. The LAMP reaction is performed in constant temperature between 60–65°C, alleviating the need for expensive specialized equipment. The method requires only inexpensive heating block or water bath, making it very useful under poor laboratory settings [
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. The LAMP reaction takes turnaround time of &lt;1 hour and the amplified product can be detected by several methods, including the real-time measurement of the turbidity caused by precipitated magnesium pyrophosphate using a turbidimeter, visual detection of magnesium pyrophosphate precipitation following completion of the reaction, detection of fluorescence under ultraviolet light or natural light by adding an intercalating fluorescent dye to the final reaction mixture, and visualization of the bands with various sizes using agarose gel electrophoresis [
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>–
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>].
</p>
