<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue archivearticle.dtd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?><?SourceDTD.DTDName archivearticle.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Emerg Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Emerging Infect. Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EID</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Emerging Infectious Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1080-6040</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1080-6059</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6433041</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30882303</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">18-0750</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid2504.180750</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="TOC-title"><subject>Sand Fly&#x02013;Associated Phlebovirus with Evidence of Neutralizing Antibodies in Humans, Kenya</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sand Fly&#x02013;Associated Phlebovirus with Evidence of Neutralizing Antibodies in Humans, Kenya</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Sand Fly&#x02013;Associated Phlebovirus in Humans, Kenya</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Tchouassi</surname><given-names>David P.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marklewitz</surname><given-names>Marco</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chepkorir</surname><given-names>Edith</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zirkel</surname><given-names>Florian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Agha</surname><given-names>Sheila B.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tigoi</surname><given-names>Caroline C.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koskei</surname><given-names>Edith</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Drosten</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Borgemeister</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Torto</surname><given-names>Baldwyn</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Junglen</surname><given-names>Sandra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sang</surname><given-names>Rosemary</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">International Centre of Insect Physiology and Ecology, Nairobi, Kenya (D.P. Tchouassi, E. Chepkorir, S.B. Agha, C.C. Tigoi, B. Torto, R. Sang); </aff><aff id="aff2">Charit&#x000e9;-Universit&#x000e4;tsmedizin Berlin, Berlin, Germany (M. Marklewitz, F. Zirkel, C. Drosten, S. Junglen); </aff><aff id="aff3">German Center for Infection Research, Berlin (M. Marklewitz, F. Zirkel, C. Drosten, S. Junglen); </aff><aff id="aff4">Center for Virus Research, Kenya Medical Research Institute, Nairobi (E. Koskei, R. Sang); </aff><aff id="aff5">University of Bonn, Bonn, Germany (C. Borgemeister)</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Address for correspondence: David P. Tchouassi, International Centre of Insect Physiology and Ecology, Nairobi, Kenya; e-mail: <email xlink:href="dtchouassi@icipe.org">dtchouassi@icipe.org</email>; Sandra Junglen, Institute of Virology, Charit&#x000e9;-Universit&#x000e4;tsmedizin Berlin, Charit&#x000e9;platz 1, 10117 Berlin, Germany; e-mail: <email xlink:href="Sandra.junglen@charite.de">Sandra.junglen@charite.de</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>25</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>681</fpage><lpage>690</lpage><abstract><p>We describe a novel virus, designated Ntepes virus (NPV), isolated from sand flies in Kenya. NPV has the characteristic phlebovirus trisegmented genome architecture and is related to, but distinct from, Gabek Forest phlebovirus. Diverse cell cultures derived from wildlife, livestock, and humans were susceptible to NPV, with pronounced permissiveness in swine and rodent cells. NPV infection of newborn mice caused rapid and fatal illness. Permissiveness for NPV replication in sand fly cells, but not mosquito cells, suggests a vector-specific adaptation. Specific neutralizing antibodies were found in 13.9% (26/187) of human serum samples taken at the site of isolation of NPV as well as a disparate site in northeastern Kenya, suggesting a wide distribution. We identify a novel human-infecting arbovirus and highlight the importance of rural areas in tropical Africa for arbovirus surveillance as well as extending arbovirus surveillance to include hematophagous arthropods other than mosquitoes.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords: </title><kwd>arbovirus</kwd><kwd>phlebovirus</kwd><kwd>sand flies</kwd><kwd>virus discovery</kwd><kwd>Kenya</kwd><kwd>viruses</kwd><kwd>neutralizing antibodies</kwd><kwd>Ntepes virus</kwd><kwd>Gabek Forest phlebovirus</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Disease outbreaks caused by Zika, dengue, yellow fever, chikungunya, and Rift Valley fever viruses illustrate the threat posed by arthropod-borne viruses (arboviruses), which affect millions of patients worldwide each year (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><italic>3</italic></xref>). Major epidemic arboviruses are thought to have originated in tropical Africa, where they are known or thought to have caused local outbreaks before epidemic or pandemic spread. Early recognition of local outbreaks, including precise identification of the disease-causing agent, is key to effective preparedness against epidemics. However, active surveillance is poorly implemented in most seeding countries.</p><p>Monitoring programs for vectors of arboviral diseases often prioritize mosquitoes and ticks (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><italic>4</italic></xref>), neglecting other blood-feeding vectors, such as sand flies. Sand flies transmit protozoan parasites that cause leishmaniasis as well as phleboviruses (order <italic>Bunyavirales</italic>, family <italic>Phenuiviridae</italic>, genus <italic>Phlebovirus</italic>) (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><italic>5</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr"><italic>6</italic></xref>). Sand fly&#x02013;borne phlebovirus infections are known to occur in the Mediterranean basin (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><italic>7</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><italic>8</italic></xref>). Some of these, such as sandfly fever Naples, Sicilian, and Toscana viruses, are of public health importance, especially Toscana virus, which causes meningitis and encephalitis in humans (<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><italic>8</italic></xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><italic>10</italic></xref>).</p><p>The International Committee for the Taxonomy of Viruses (ICTV) currently recognizes 10 viral species within the genus <italic>Phlebovirus</italic>: Rift Valley fever virus (RVFV), severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome (SFTS) virus, Uukuniemi phlebovirus, Bujaru phlebovirus, Candiru phlebovirus, Chilibre phlebovirus, Frijoles phlebovirus, Punta Toro phlebovirus, Salehabad phlebovirus, and sandfly fever Naples phlebovirus (<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><italic>11</italic></xref>). The last 7 species are vectored by sand flies. Novel unclassified phleboviruses (e.g., Fermo, Granada, Punique, and Massilia viruses), as well as recently discovered flaviviruses in sand flies, underline the importance of these neglected vectors of arboviral diseases (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><italic>12</italic></xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><italic>16</italic></xref>).</p><p>Sand fly&#x02013;borne phleboviruses have been studied mainly in the Mediterranean region. Prevalence data for sub-Saharan Africa remain scarce. Studies have found serologic evidence of human infections with Karimabad, sandfly fever Naples, and sandfly fever Sicilian viruses in patients from Sudan with febrile illness (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><italic>7</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr"><italic>17</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr"><italic>18</italic></xref>). Human infections with sandfly fever Naples and Sicilian viruses have been reported in Uganda, Somalia, Djibouti, and Ethiopia (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><italic>7</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><italic>19</italic></xref>). However, serologic surveys may be compounded by antigenic cross-reactivity between phleboviruses (except in neutralization assays), thereby precluding the unequivocal identification of the circulating sand fly&#x02013;borne virus (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><italic>5</italic></xref>). Few studies have incorporated viral genetic characterization.</p><p>We describe a previously unknown phlebovirus discovered during vector surveillance in Kenya, which we designate Ntepes virus (NPV), after the place of sampling of virus-infected sand flies. The complete genome of NPV was sequenced, viral species tropism in cell culture assessed, and pathogenicity in vertebrates proven by infection of mice. Human serum samples from Ntepes and other communities yielded evidence of human infection based on specific virus neutralization.</p><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Sandfly Trapping and Virus Isolation</title><p>We trapped sandflies using CDC light traps (John W. Hock, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://johnwhock.com">https://johnwhock.com</ext-link>) in villages of the Marigat district, Baringo County, Kenya, in February 2014 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). We homogenized pools of 5&#x02013;50 female specimens in minimum essential medium (MEM), inoculated an aliquot of the clarified supernatant (50 &#x003bc;L) into Vero cells, and incubated it for up to 14 days with daily monitoring for cytopathic effect (CPE). We passaged CPE-positive supernatant onto fresh Vero E6/7 cells; virus stock solution was generated from the first passage and used for all further experiments. We determined the infectious titer by 50% tissue culture infectious dose (TCID<sub>50</sub>) assay using 10-fold serial dilutions from<sup>&#x02013;</sup> 10<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> to 10<sup>&#x02013;12</sup> of the virus stock inoculated in 5 wells each of subconfluent Vero cells seeded in a 96-well plate. We calculated the virus titer according to Reed and Muench (<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><italic>20</italic></xref>). We estimated the minimum infection rate (MIR) in sandflies using the formula [number of positive pools/total specimens tested] &#x000d7; 1,000.</p><fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Geographic location of sand fly collection site (Ntepes) and district hospitals of Marigat and Sangailu, where human serum samples were collected, Kenya.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="18-0750-F1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Broad Reverse Transcription PCR Screening</title><p>We extracted RNA from cytopathic cell culture supernatant (200 &#x003bc;L aliquot) using the Viral RNA Mini Kit (QIAGEN, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.qiagen.com">https://www.qiagen.com</ext-link>) and eluted it in 50 &#x003bc;L of buffer. We performed cDNA synthesis using SuperScript III reverse transcription (Invitrogen, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.thermofisher.com">https://www.thermofisher.com</ext-link>) and random hexamer primers (TIB Molbiol, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.tib-molbiol.com">https://www.tib-molbiol.com</ext-link>), followed by reverse transcription PCR (RT-PCR) for orthobunyaviruses, alphaviruses, and flaviviruses (<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr"><italic>21</italic></xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><italic>24</italic></xref>). We screened for sand fly&#x02013;borne phleboviruses by targeting the RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp) gene using degenerate primers (<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr"><italic>25</italic></xref>). We compared the nucleotide sequences to GenBank using blastn (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi">https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi</ext-link>) and subjected them to initial phylogenetic analysis in MEGA6 (<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr"><italic>26</italic></xref>). We further extracted RNA from pooled sand flies and tested it by real-time PCR using NPV-specific primers (forward, 5&#x02032;-GCAAGAAAGCACTGTGGTGG; reverse, 5&#x02032;-CGTATGATGATCGGCCACCA; probe, 5&#x02032;-6-FAM-ACAGCCACCTCTGATGATGC-IBFQ). </p></sec><sec><title>Genotyping of Sand Flies and Blood Meal Analysis</title><p>We amplified the barcode region of the cytochrome <italic>c</italic> oxidase subunit I (<italic>COI</italic>) gene using published primers (<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><italic>27</italic></xref>). We extracted genomic DNA from individual bloodfed sand fly specimens using the QIAGEN DNeasy Blood and Tissue Kit (QIAGEN). We amplified a 500-bp fragment of the 12S mitochondrial rRNA gene as described (<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><italic>28</italic></xref>), sequenced the PCR products, and compared them to GenBank database data. We inferred species-level identification on the basis of &#x02265;98% identity spanning <underline>&#x0003e;</underline>300 bp, as described by Valinsky et al. (<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr"><italic>29</italic></xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Next-Generation Sequencing, Genome Annotation, and Phylogenetics</title><p>We purified and concentrated virions from the supernatant of infected Vero cells by ultracentrifugation through a 36% sucrose cushion. We extracted viral RNA using the QIAGEN RNeasy Kit according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. We generated cDNA using the Maxima H Minus Double-Stranded cDNA Synthesis Kit and random hexamer primers (Thermo Fisher Scientific, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.thermofisher.com">https://www.thermofisher.com</ext-link>). We prepared DNA libraries using the Nextera XT DNA Sample Preparation Kit and analyzed them on an Illumina MiSeq instrument with the MiSeq Reagent Kit v3 (Illumina, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.illumina.com">https://www.illumina.com</ext-link>). We identified viral reads by reference mapping to phleboviruses as well as by BLAST comparisons against a local amino acid sequence library containing translations of open reading frames (ORFs) of phleboviruses. We closed sequence gaps by conventional RT-PCR followed by Sanger sequencing. We performed genome assembly using Geneious (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geneious.com">http://www.geneious.com</ext-link>) and confirmed genome terminal sequences by rapid amplification of cDNA ends (RACE-PCR; Life Technologies, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.thermofisher.com">https://www.thermofisher.com</ext-link>). We identified ORFs using Geneious, compared nucleotide and amino acid sequences with other sequences by blastn and blastx searches against the GenBank database, and identified protein motifs by web-based comparison to the Pfam database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pfam.janelia.org">http://www.pfam.janelia.org</ext-link>). We identified putative transmembrane regions by prediction of the hydropathy profile using TMHMM (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TMHMM-2.0">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TMHMM-2.0</ext-link>) and predicted N-linked glycosylation sites using the NetNGlyc 1.0 server (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/NetNGlyc">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/NetNGlyc</ext-link>).</p><p>We aligned nucleotide and amino acid sequences of the ORFs of the respective genome segments with related viral sequences in Geneious using MAFFT (<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr"><italic>30</italic></xref>). Phylogenetic trees were inferred by the maximum-likelihood (ML) method using the best suitable substitution matrix (LG) identified by Modeltest, as implemented in MEGA. We performed confidence testing based on 1,000 bootstrap iterations (<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr"><italic>31</italic></xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>In Vitro Viral Growth Kinetics</title><p>We infected cell lines from insects (LL-5, sand fly; C6/36, mosquito), humans (HEK293-T), small mammals (BHK-21, hamster; VeroE6/7, primate; MEF, mouse; EidNi, bat) and livestock (PK-15, swine; ZN-R, goat; DF-1, chicken; KN-R, cattle) in doublets, at a multiplicity of infection of 0.1. We harvested aliquots of infectious cell culture supernatants every 24 h for periods of 7 d and quantified viral genome copies by real-time RT-PCR with plasmid-based quantification standards.</p></sec><sec><title>In Vivo Pathogenesis in Suckling Mice</title><p>We intracerebrally inoculated 100 &#x003bc;L of the viral stock of the first passage, as well as 3 consecutive 2-fold dilutions, into 3&#x02013;4-day-old Swiss Albino suckling mice. The doses used in the experimental infection were quantified by plaque assays in Vero cells as described previously (<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr"><italic>32</italic></xref>) and corresponded to viral titers of 4 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup>, 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup>, 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup>, 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>, and 2.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> PFU/mL. We included noninfectious MEM as a negative control. We observed all mice 2 times/day for up to 14 days for signs of disease. We homogenized brains from recently dead mice in 1 mL of cell culture media and plaque-titrated them on Vero cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Human Serum Samples and Neutralization Tests</title><p>Archived serum samples from the Marigat district hospital, taken during 2010&#x02013;2011, and from Sangailu Health Centre in the Hulugho subcounty in northeastern Kenya, collected during 2010&#x02013;2012, were available (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). We performed a virus neutralization test using 2-fold serial dilutions of serum samples (1:20 to 1:640). We mixed 50 &#x003bc;L of the serial serum dilutions with 70 TCID<sub>50</sub> of NPV. Mixtures were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C in the presence of 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 1 h, then used for infection of a confluent Vero E6/7 cell monolayer seeded in 96-well culture plates with 2 wells/dilution. After 7 days of incubation, we recorded the highest serum dilution at which no CPE was observed in at least 50% of the wells as the neutralization titer.</p><p>We tested NPV-reactive human serum samples with RVFV, Gabek Forest virus (GFV), and Karimabad virus (KARV) for serologic cross-reactivity, as described earlier in this article. In addition, we tested GFV- and KARV-positive serum samples with NPV in 2-fold serial dilutions from 1:5 to 1:20 (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table</label><caption><title>NT reactivity with NPV, GFV, KARV, and RVFV of serum samples from febrile persons and healthy controls in Kenya*</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="33" span="1"/><col width="47" span="1"/><col width="36" span="1"/><col width="54" span="1"/><col width="144" span="1"/><col width="45" span="1"/><col width="40" span="1"/><col width="40" span="1"/><col width="41" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="bottom" align="left" scope="col" colspan="1">Sample ID</th><th rowspan="2" valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" colspan="1">Origin</th><th rowspan="2" valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" colspan="1">Age, y/sex</th><th rowspan="2" valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" colspan="1">Occupation</th><th rowspan="2" valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" colspan="1">Acute febrile infection&#x02020;</th><th valign="bottom" colspan="4" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">Reactivity against<hr/></th></tr><tr><th valign="bottom" colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup" rowspan="1">NPV</th><th valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RVFV</th><th valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GBV</th><th valign="bottom" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KARV</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marigat</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/F</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Student</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever/chills, head/joint/muscle aches</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marigat</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/F</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Student</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever/chills, cough, head/joint/muscle aches, eye pain, diarrhea</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marigat</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18/F</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Student</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever/chills, cough, head/joint/muscle aches, jaundice, abdominal pain</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marigat</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19/M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shop attendant</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acute febrile illness&#x02014;fever/chills, cough, head/muscle aches</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marigat</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29/M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Driver</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever/chills, head/joint/muscle aches</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:80</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangailu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17/F</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Housewife</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangailu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25/M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Herdsman</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever/chills, headache, diarrhea</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:320</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:1,280</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangailu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42/F</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Housewife</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever/chills, headache, abdominal pain</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangailu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50/F</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Housewife</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever/chills, cough, head/joint/muscle aches</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangailu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24/M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Herder</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever/chills, head/joint/muscle aches, diarrhea</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:320</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None </td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangailu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53/F</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Housewife</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever, cough, headache, abdominal pain, muscle ache</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangailu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26/M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shepherd</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy control</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangailu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30/F</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Housewife</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy control</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:160</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangailu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65/M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pastoralist</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy control</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:320</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangailu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62/M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Herdsman</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy control</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:80</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:640</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangailu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34/F</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Housewife</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy control</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:80</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangailu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52/F</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Housewife</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy control</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangailu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50/M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Herdsman</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy control</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:1,280</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangailu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57/M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Herdsman</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy control</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:320</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangailu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Herder</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever/chills, head/joint/muscle aches, abdominal pain</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:160</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:160</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangailu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18/M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Student</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever, cough, headache, abdominal pains</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:80</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangailu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/F</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Student</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever/chills, cough, abdominal pains, joint/muscle aches</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:160</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangailu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19/F</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Housewife</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever/chills, headache, abdominal pains</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangailu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30/F</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Housewife</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever, head/joint/muscle aches, abdominal pain</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:160</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sangailu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17/M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Herder</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever/chills, head/joint/muscle aches, abdominal pain</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:160</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marigat</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17/M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Student</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever/chills, head/joint/muscle aches</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*GFV, Gabek Forest virus; ID, identification; KARV, Karimabad virus; NPV, Ntepes virus; NT, neutralizing test; RVFV, Rift Valley fever virus.&#x02028;&#x02020;Fever defined as body temperature <underline>&#x0003e;</underline>38&#x000b0;C.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Ethics Considerations</title><p>Approval for the study was granted by the Scientific and Ethical Review Unit and Animal Care and Use Committee of the Kenya Medical Research Institute (SSC Protocol nos. 1560 and KEMRI/SERU/CVR/003/3312). All animal experiments were carried out in accordance with the regulations and guidelines of the Kenya Medical Research Institute.</p></sec><sec><title>GenBank Accession Numbers</title><p>The NPV genome was deposited in GenBank under accession nos. MF695810&#x02013;MF695812. The <italic>COI</italic> sequence obtained from the virus-positive sand fly pool was deposited in GenBank under accession no. MG913288.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>NPV Isolation and Characterization </title><p>In total, 6,434 sand flies were trapped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). A subset of 5,481 sandflies was pooled and the resulting 111 pools individually inoculated in VeroE6/7 cells. One pool consisting of 8 females induced CPE 4&#x02013;5 days postinfection. Sequence analysis of the <italic>COI</italic> gene of the sand flies of this CPE-positive pool suggested that sand flies were of the genus <italic>Sergentomyia</italic>. We identified blood-meal hosts for 62 blood-fed specimens sampled at the same place and time as the pooled specimens. Results revealed that 56 (90.3%) had fed on humans, 2 (3.2%) on snakes, and 1 (1.6%) each on a frog, lizard, cow, and ostrich. The infectious cell culture supernatant tested negative for RVFV, orthobunyaviruses, alphaviruses, and members of genus <italic>Flavivirus</italic>. We amplified a 0.5-kb fragment of the RdRp gene of sand fly&#x02013;borne phleboviruses using degenerated primers (<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr"><italic>25</italic></xref>). The sequence showed the highest pairwise identity of 79% to GFV and 75% to KARV. We sampled a subset of 953 individual sand fly samples 2 years after the initial study and tested it in pools of 10 by specific RT-PCR for the cultured virus; results were negative.</p><p>Analysis of the complete genome by next-generation sequencing confirmed isolation of a novel phlebovirus. The virus was tentatively termed Ntepes virus, after the location where the sand flies were collected. The virus exhibits the characteristic tripartite-segmented genome organization of phleboviruses, comprising the large (L) segment, which encodes the RdRp protein; the medium (M) segment, encoding a glycoprotein precursor protein (GPC) that is posttranslationally cleaved into 2 viral surface glycoproteins (Gn and Gc) and a nonstructural protein (NSm); and the small (S) segment, encoding the nucleocapsid (N) protein and a nonstructural protein (NS) in an ambisense manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Highest sequence similarities to GFV were 93% to RdRp, 88% to GPC, 79% to Nsm, 85% to N, and 90% to NS. NPV has the typical conserved genome termini shared among phleboviruses (5&#x02032;-ACACAAAG and CUUUGUGU-3&#x02032;) (<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><italic>8</italic></xref>).</p><fig id="F2" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Genome organization of novel sand fly&#x02013;associated phlebovirus Ntepes virus identified in Kenya. Sequence length of the L, M, and S segments (in bp) and encoded predicted proteins RdRp, Gn, Gc, N, and nonstructural proteins NSm and NSs (in kDa) are indicated; ORF positions (length in bp) are also indicated. GFV, Gabek Forest virus; L, large segment (encoding the RdRp protein); M, medium segment (encoding the nonstructural protein NSm and the 2 glycoproteins Gn and Gc); N, nucleocapsid protein; ORF, open reading frame; RdRp, RNA-dependent RNA polymerase; S, small segment (encoding the N protein and nonstructural protein NSs in an ambisense manner); vRNA, virus RNA.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="18-0750-F2"/></fig><p>Phylogenetic analyses of NPV RdRp, Gn, Gc, and N proteins and all available sand fly&#x02013;borne phlebovirus sequences indicate that NPV forms a strongly supported clade with GFV and KARV. NPV branches as a sister taxon to GFV in all genes, suggesting NPV to be a member of the Karimabad species complex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). However, the designation of the Karimabad species complex is not yet officially approved by the ICTV. For a provisional genetic classification, we analyzed the intragenetic distances among established phlebovirus species and unclassified isolates based on the RdRp gene. Pairwise nucleotide and amino acid distances between established species ranged from 38% to 62% for nucleotide distances and 39% to 68% for amino acid distances (<xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref> Figure). For example, amino acid distance between Punta Toro virus and Candiru virus was 39% and between SFTS virus and sandfly fever Naples virus was 68%. Pairwise nucleotide distances ranged from 20% to 59% and amino acid distances from 6% to 69% when unclassified tentative species and variants pertaining to established species were included. For example, amino acid distance between Ponticelli virus and Adana virus was 6% and between Naples virus and SFTS virus was 69% (<xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref> Figure). NPV showed 7% amino acid distance to GFV and 19% amino acid distance to KARV.</p><fig id="F3" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic relationship of novel sand fly&#x02013;associated phlebovirus Ntepes virus from Kenya (red bold text) in relation to other selected members of the <italic>Phlebovirus</italic> genus. A) RNA-dependent RNA polymerase; B) nucleocapsid protein; C) glycoprotein Gn; D) glycoprotein Gc. The phylogenetic trees were inferred based on complete large, medium, and small protein sequences, applying maximum likelihood analysis in PhyML version 3.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.atgc-montpellier.fr/phyml/versions.php">http://www.atgc-montpellier.fr/phyml/versions.php</ext-link>) using the LG substitution model. Statistical support of the tree topology was evaluated by bootstrap resampling of the sequences 1,000 times. Sequences are identified by virus name and branch colors. Bootstrap values &#x0003e;70 are indicated at the nodes. Scale bar represents numbers of substitutions per site. </p></caption><graphic xlink:href="18-0750-F3"/></fig><p>Classical criteria for species demarcation in phleboviruses are based on serology, with established species showing at least 4-fold differences in 2-way neutralization tests (<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><italic>11</italic></xref>). We confirmed that NPV did not react with antiserum against its next closest relatives, GFV and KARV, in neutralization tests (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). NPV Gn protein was 13% different and Gc 4% different from GFV. The Gn protein of phleboviruses is the key component for neutralization and is recognized by specific neutralizing antibodies (<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr"><italic>33</italic></xref>).</p><fig id="F4" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Neutralizing activity of novel sand fly&#x02013;associated phlebovirus Ntepes virus from Kenya in relation to other selected members of the <italic>Phlebovirus</italic> genus. Anti-GFV and anti-KARV samples were tested along with 26 human serum samples. GFV, Gabek Forest virus; H, human; KARV, Karimabad virus; NPV, Ntepes virus; NT, neutralizing test; RVFV, Rift Valley fever virus.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="18-0750-F4"/></fig><p>Although sequence-based species demarcation criteria have not been determined for phlebovirus species, such criteria exist for the related orthobunyaviruses. Species demarcation criteria are now based on the RdRp gene, which shows <underline>&#x0003e;</underline>6% difference to the closest related virus. Previously unique orthobunyavirus species were defined on <underline>&#x0003e;</underline>10% difference in N protein sequences (<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><italic>11</italic></xref>). The N proteins of NPV and GFV differ by 15% (GFV itself is not formally classified as a species, and any of the formally classified phlebovirus species are markedly more distant from NPV in this and other genes; <xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref> Figure). We conclude, upon cumulative evidence, that NPV constitutes a putative novel species within the phlebovirus genus.</p></sec><sec><title>Permissiveness in Vertebrates</title><p>To obtain initial data on permissiveness, we performed in vitro growth analyses in a broad range of cell lines derived from different insect species (sand fly and mosquito), peridomestic wildlife (rodent, nonhuman primate, and bat), and livestock (swine, goat, chicken, and cattle) species, as well as from humans. Results revealed a broad susceptibility to NPV, with peak genome copy numbers in cells derived from swine and rodents (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>, panel A). Cells derived from sand flies but not from mosquitoes were permissive, despite using C6/36 mosquito cells that are normally broadly susceptible to arboviruses because of a defect in their antiviral RNA interference response (<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr"><italic>34</italic></xref>). These findings suggest a host range for NPV similar to those of KARV and GFV, which are transmitted by sand flies and infect rodents (<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><italic>35</italic></xref>). It is not known whether rodents are amplificatory or dead-end hosts.</p><fig id="F5" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>In vitro growth kinetics of novel sand fly&#x02013;associated phlebovirus Ntepes virus from Kenya in different cell lines. A) Insects: LL-5, sand fly; C6/36, mosquito. B) Human: HEK293-T. C) Peridomestic wildlife: hamster, BHK-21; primate, VeroE6/7; mouse, MEF; bat, EidNi. D) Livestock: swine, PK-15; goat, ZN-R; chicken, DF-1; cattle, KN-R. Cells were infected with a multiplicity of infection of 0.1; supernatants were collected every 24 h for 7 d postinfection. Viral genome copies were measured at indicated timepoints by real-time reverse transcription PCR. E) Pathogenicity of Ntepes virus infection in mice. Litters of 2-day-old Swiss Albino suckling mice (8 mice/litter) were intracerebrally inoculated using the indicated virus titers or cell culture media as a control. Animals were monitored daily for signs of disease. Titers are shown in PFU/mL.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="18-0750-F5"/></fig><p>Because GFV is known to induce fatal disease in laboratory mice (<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr"><italic>36</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr"><italic>37</italic></xref>), we explored similarities in pathogenicity with NPV. We intracranially inoculated 3&#x02013;4-day-old Swiss Albino suckling mice, causing tremors, hind-limb paralysis, prostration, and death 5&#x02013;8 days postinfection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>, panel B). Time to death was clearly correlated with virus dose. All animals had high infectious virus concentrations in the brain (mean 2.9 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> PFU/mL). Taken together, the in vitro and in vivo pathogenicity studies of NPV, including the pathogenicity in suckling mice, may suggest that rodents and sand flies may be involved in the maintenance cycle of NPV.</p></sec><sec><title>Evidence for Human Infection with NPV</title><p>To test whether NPV infects humans, we analyzed 187 archived serum samples: 59 samples from the Marigat district hospital in the area where NPV-infected sand flies were trapped, and 128 samples collected in northeastern Kenya at Sangailu Health Centre (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). All patients from Marigat, as well as 98 patients from Sangailu, had symptoms compatible with acute infectious diseases. The remaining 30 samples from Sangailu came from healthy controls.</p><p>Twenty-six (13.9%) serum samples neutralized NPV, with titers ranging from 1:20 to 1:320 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). Women and men were infected at equal rates. Positive samples originated from Marigat (10.2%) and Sangailu (15.6%), without statistical differences in rates (Fisher exact test odds ratio [OR]&#x000a0;0.6, 95% CI&#x000a0;0.19&#x02013;1.70; p = 0.37). Detection rates in Sangailu did not differ between healthy and febrile patients (Fisher exact test OR&#x000a0;1.4, 95% CI&#x000a0;0.40&#x02013;4.3; p = 0.58) (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). No NPV nucleic acids were detected in serum samples by NPV-specific RT-PCR, suggesting no causative link to the present symptoms with NPV. The detection of NPV neutralizing antibodies in geographically unlinked regions of Kenya suggests widespread previous human exposure and infection.</p><p>Because NPV is genetically most closely related to GFV and KARV, we tested all NPV-positive serum samples for ability to cross-neutralize GFV or KARV. All tests yielded negative results, providing further support for the classification of NPV as a separate serotype (and species). Because RVFV frequently causes outbreaks in East Africa, we also tested against RVFV, which, according to its phylogenetic relationship with NPV, is not expected to cross-react with NPV. Seven of 26 NPV-neutralizing serum samples were also reactive with RVFV, showing titers that did not correlate in height with titers against NPV (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). Absence of correlation of titers suggests previous RVFV infection rather than cross-reactivity between RVFV and NPV.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>We identified a high percentage of neutralizing antibodies to NPV in humans living in the NPV-endemic area by neutralization assay, confirming that NPV represents a distinct phleboviral species that causes infection in humans. The fact that the virus was isolated through an exploratory sampling effort is an indicator of the existence of undetected and uncharacterized viruses in this part of Kenya. Although mosquitoes have been the focus of studies on emerging arboviruses, the discovery of a novel sand fly&#x02013;borne phlebovirus with evidence for human exposure across Kenya indicates the need to broaden vector surveillance activities.</p><p>Toscana, sandfly fever Sicilian, and sandfly fever Naples viruses are distributed in the Mediterranean region and northern Africa. GFV has been reported from Sudan, Senegal, Central African Republic, Nigeria, and Benin (<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr"><italic>38</italic></xref>). KARV occurs in eastern and central Asia (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><italic>7</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr"><italic>39</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr"><italic>40</italic></xref>), as well as Sudan, Egypt, and Nigeria (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><italic>7</italic></xref>). According to this geographic distribution, GFV seems to be the most likely sand fly&#x02013;borne phlebovirus to co-occur in Kenya. Our results show that NPV-immune serum samples do not react with GFV or KARV, suggesting that the reactivity of the positive human samples was the result of previous infection with NPV.</p><p>NPV in Kenya may occupy a niche that is taken by GFV and KARV in northern Africa or eastern and central Asia. Several characteristics of NPV suggest parallels between the host ranges of NPV and GFV. GFV has been detected in rodents (<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr"><italic>38</italic></xref>) but has been detected in arthropods in only a single study in sand flies (<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><italic>35</italic></xref>). Further, the virus was shown to be able to infect <italic>Phlebotomus</italic> species under laboratory conditions (Tesh R. Studies of the biology of phleboviruses in sand flies. Paper presented at Yale University School of Medicine, New Haven, CT, USA, 1983), suggesting that GFV is maintained in a transmission cycle that involves rodents and sand flies and that it occasionally infects humans (<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><italic>35</italic></xref>). NPV was isolated from sand flies and replicates in vitro in sand fly&#x02013;derived cell lines but not in mosquito cells, similar to sandfly Sicilian and Naples viruses (<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr"><italic>41</italic></xref>). Infection studies with cell lines derived from livestock and peridomestic wildlife species showed that NPV replicates &#x02248;10&#x02013;100 times better in rodent and swine cell lines than in cells derived from other animals, suggesting the involvement of rodents or swine as potential amplificatory hosts for NPV. </p><p><italic>COI</italic> gene analyses from the virus-positive sand fly pool suggests that species of the genus <italic>Sergentomyia</italic> have been infected with NPV. Blood-meal analyses revealed that 90% of the analyzed blood-fed sand flies had fed on humans, confirming a likely role as vectors of NPV to humans. Our findings provide new evidence that <italic>Sergentomyia</italic> flies do not strictly feed on reptiles but also feed frequently on humans (<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr"><italic>42</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr"><italic>43</italic></xref>).</p><p>The NPV antibody prevalence rate in humans (13.9%) is comparable to that of GFV, which is 17%&#x02013;60% in Sudan, 3%&#x02013;10% in Egypt, and 3% in Nigeria (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><italic>7</italic></xref>). KARV antibody prevalence is 1%&#x02013;11% in Sudan, 2% in Egypt, and 1%&#x02013;62% in regions of Iran and Russia (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><italic>7</italic></xref>). Human serum samples from northern Kenya have been tested and yielded no antibodies against GFV or KARV, which matches our results (<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><italic>7</italic></xref>). </p><p>NPV appears to have a wide distribution in Kenya; we found equal exposure rates in 2 geographic sets of humans sampled &#x0003e;600 km apart. The serum samples from this study were collected during 2010&#x02013;2012, suggesting that NPV has been present in humans since at least 2010. Sand fly pools collected in 2014 had low infection rates (MIR&#x000a0;0.18, 1/111 pools, 5&#x02013;50 sand flies/pool), possibly resulting from collection during a period with low transmission rates. The estimated MIR is lower compared with previous sand fly infections with phleboviruses such as Punique (MIR&#x000a0;6.7) (<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><italic>14</italic></xref>), Massilia (MIR&#x000a0;3.7) (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><italic>12</italic></xref>), and Toscana (MIR&#x000a0;2.2) viruses (<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr"><italic>44</italic></xref>), although comparable to Toros (MIR 0.26) and Zerdali (MIR 0.35) viruses (<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr"><italic>45</italic></xref>). The significance of just 1 isolate of the novel phlebovirus from 111 sand fly pools may seem limited, but it is noteworthy that circulation of RVFV, a phlebovirus with huge epidemic potential, is generally detected at low rates in vectors during interepidemic periods. For instance, multiple surveillance efforts sampling and analyzing thousands of primary and secondary RVFV vectors from outbreak hotspot areas failed to yield any RVFV isolates (<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr"><italic>46</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr"><italic>47</italic></xref>), yet RVFV infection rates in mosquitoes during the 2006&#x02013;2007 outbreak in Kenya were high, ranging between 0.8 and 10.65 per 1,000 for primary vectors (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><italic>2</italic></xref>). </p><p>The outcome of infection experiments in mice suggests that NPV could cause diseases such as GFV and RVFV infection (<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr"><italic>36</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr"><italic>37</italic></xref>). The neglect of sand fly&#x02013;borne phleboviruses in Africa is exemplified by outbreaks of acute febrile illness associated with sandfly fever Sicilian virus in Ethiopia, which, for a long time, had remained misdiagnosed as malaria (<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr"><italic>48</italic></xref>), as well as an outbreak of febrile illness probably associated with sandfly fever Naples virus in Sudan (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr"><italic>17</italic></xref>).</p><p>The symptoms reported among most of the tested patients in this study cannot be conclusively linked to NPV infection, as indicated by antibodies in symptomatic patients and healthy controls, demanding further studies of possible disease association. Clinical studies using specific real-time PCR are necessary to detect viral RNA in humans and to measure the clinical impact of NPV.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title/><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><caption><title>Appendix</title><p>Distance matrix and distance plots of phleboviruses used in the study of sand fly&#x02013;associated phleboviruses, Kenya.</p></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="18-0750-Techapp-s1.pdf" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e1321" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="citation"><p><italic>Suggested citation for this article</italic>: Tchouassi DP, Marklewitz M, Chepkorir E, Zirkel F, Agha SB, Tigoi CC, et al. Sand fly&#x02013;associated phlebovirus with evidence of neutralizing antibodies in humans, Kenya. Emerg Infect Dis. 2019 Apr [<italic>date cited</italic>]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3201/eid2504.180750">https://doi.org/10.3201/eid2504.180750</ext-link></p></fn><fn id="FN1"><label>1</label><p>Current affiliation: Biotest AG, Dreieich, Germany.</p></fn><fn id="FN2"><p>
<sup>2</sup>These authors contributed equally to this article.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank Mark Rotich for logistical support during field collection of sandflies in Marigat district and Robinson Okiro and Julia Wanjiru for support in the laboratory to sort and pool sand fly samples. Special thanks to John Gachoya for help in mice inoculation, Jackson Kimani for GIS design of the map of the study sites, and the chief and community members at Ntepes for their cooperation and support. We thank Diane E. Griffin and Armanda D.S. Bastos for critical review of the manuscript.</p><p>The research is an output from an International Centre of Insect Physiology and Ecology seed grant, awarded to D.P.T. and B.T. D.P.T. also received postdoctoral support through the International Centre of Insect Physiology and Ecology from the UK Department for International Development and the Swedish International Development Cooperation Agency. We also acknowledge financial support from the Swiss Agency for Development and Cooperation and the Kenya government. Work at Charit&#x000e9; Berlin was funded by the German Center for Infection Research (grant no. TTU 01.801) as well as by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (grant nos. JU 2857/9-1 [to S.J.] and BO 1116/8-1). </p></ack><bio id="d35e1352"><p>Dr. Tchouassi is a disease vector ecologist working as a research scientist at the International Centre of Insect Physiology and Ecology, Nairobi, Kenya. His research interest is in developing and evaluating complementary innovative vector control tools and monitoring of pathogen&#x02013;vector dynamics for epidemiological assessments. </p></bio><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sang</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dunster</surname>
<given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The growing threat of arbovirus transmission and outbreaks in Kenya: a review.</article-title>
<source>East Afr Med J</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>655</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4314/eamj.v78i12.8936</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12199448?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12199448</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sang</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kioko</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lutomiah</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Warigia</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ochieng</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>O&#x02019;Guinn</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Rift Valley fever virus epidemic in Kenya, 2006/2007: the entomologic investigations.</article-title>
<source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>83</volume>(<issue>Suppl</issue>):<fpage>28</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.2010.09-0319</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20682903?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20682903</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wilder-Smith</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gubler</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weaver</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monath</surname>
<given-names>TP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heymann</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scott</surname>
<given-names>TW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epidemic arboviral diseases: priorities for research and public health.</article-title>
<source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>e101</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(16)30518-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28011234?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28011234</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Junglen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Drosten</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Virus discovery and recent insights into virus diversity in arthropods.</article-title>
<source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>507</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mib.2013.06.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23850098?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23850098</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maroli</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feliciangeli</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bichaud</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Charrel</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gradoni</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Phlebotomine sandflies and the spreading of leishmaniases and other diseases of public health concern.</article-title>
<source>Med Vet Entomol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>123</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2915.2012.01034.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22924419?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22924419</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alkan</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bichaud</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Lamballerie</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alten</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gould</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Charrel</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sandfly-borne phleboviruses of Eurasia and Africa: epidemiology, genetic diversity, geographic range, control measures.</article-title>
<source>Antiviral Res</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>100</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.antiviral.2013.07.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23872312?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23872312</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tesh</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saidi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gajdamovi&#x0010d;</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rodhain</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vesenjak-Hirjan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Serological studies on the epidemiology of sandfly fever in the Old World.</article-title>
<source>Bull World Health Organ</source>. <year>1976</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>663</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>.<?supplied-pmid 829416?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">829416</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Elliott</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brennan</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Emerging phleboviruses.</article-title>
<source>Curr Opin Virol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coviro.2014.01.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24607799?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24607799</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tesh</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The genus <italic>Phlebovirus</italic> and its vectors.</article-title>
<source>Annu Rev Entomol</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>169</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.en.33.010188.001125</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2829707?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2829707</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Charrel</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gallian</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Navarro-Mar&#x000ed;</surname>
<given-names>J-M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nicoletti</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Papa</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Seco</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Emergence of Toscana virus in Europe.</article-title>
<source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1657</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid1111.050869</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16318715?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16318715</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><string-name><surname>Maes</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Adkins</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alkhovsky</surname>
<given-names>SV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Av&#x00161;i&#x0010d;-&#x0017d;upanc</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ballinger</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bente</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Taxonomy of the order Bunyavirales: second update 2018.</article-title>
<source>Arch Virol</source>. <year>2019</year>. [epub ahead of print]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Charrel</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moureau</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Temmam</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Izri</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marty</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parola</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Massilia virus, a novel Phlebovirus (Bunyaviridae) isolated from sandflies in the Mediterranean.</article-title>
<source>Vector Borne Zoonotic Dis</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>519</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/vbz.2008.0131</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19055373?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19055373</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Collao</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Palacios</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Ory</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sanbonmatsu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Ruiz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Navarro</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Granada virus: a natural phlebovirus reassortant of the sandfly fever Naples serocomplex with low seroprevalence in humans.</article-title>
<source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>760</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.2010.09-0697</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20889862?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20889862</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhioua</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moureau</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chelbi</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ninove</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bichaud</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Derbali</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Punique virus, a novel phlebovirus, related to sandfly fever Naples virus, isolated from sandflies collected in Tunisia.</article-title>
<source>J Gen Virol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>1275</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/vir.0.019240-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20089800?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20089800</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Remoli</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fortuna</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marchi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bucci</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Argentini</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bongiorno</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Viral isolates of a novel putative phlebovirus in the Marche Region of Italy.</article-title>
<source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>90</volume>:<fpage>760</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.13-0457</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24534812?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24534812</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ayhan</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Charrel</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Of phlebotomines (sandflies) and viruses: a comprehensive perspective on a complex situation.</article-title>
<source>Curr Opin Insect Sci</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cois.2017.05.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28805633?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28805633</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Watts</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>El-Tigani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Botros</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salib</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olson</surname>
<given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCarthy</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Arthropod-borne viral infections associated with a fever outbreak in the Northern Province of Sudan.</article-title>
<source>J Trop Med Hyg</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>228</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8064945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McCarthy</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haberberger</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salib</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Soliman</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>El-Tigani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khalid</surname>
<given-names>IO</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Evaluation of arthropod-borne viruses and other infectious disease pathogens as the causes of febrile illnesses in the Khartoum Province of Sudan.</article-title>
<source>J Med Virol</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>141</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1096-9071(199602)48:2&#x0003c;141::AID-JMV4&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8835346?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8835346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rodhain</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gonzalez</surname>
<given-names>J-P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mercier</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Helynck</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Larouze</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hannoun</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Arbovirus infections and viral haemorrhagic fevers in Uganda: a serological survey in Karamoja district, 1984.</article-title>
<source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>851</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0035-9203(89)90352-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2559514?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2559514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Reed</surname>
<given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muench</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A simple method of estimating fifty per cent endpoints.</article-title>
<source>Am J Epidemiol</source>. <year>1938</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>493</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.aje.a118408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kuno</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mitchell</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>GC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Detecting bunyaviruses of the Bunyamwera and California serogroups by a PCR technique.</article-title>
<source>J Clin Microbiol</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>1184</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<?supplied-pmid 8727900?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8727900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kuno</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chang</surname>
<given-names>G-JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsuchiya</surname>
<given-names>KR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Karabatsos</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cropp</surname>
<given-names>CB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Phylogeny of the genus <italic>Flavivirus.</italic></article-title>
<source>J Virol</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>73</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>.<?supplied-pmid 9420202?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9420202</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shoemaker</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boulianne</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vincent</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pezzanite</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Al-Qahtani</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Al-Mazrou</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Genetic analysis of viruses associated with emergence of Rift Valley fever in Saudi Arabia and Yemen, 2000-01.</article-title>
<source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1415</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid0812.020195</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12498657?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12498657</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Eshoo</surname>
<given-names>MW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whitehouse</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zoll</surname>
<given-names>ST</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Massire</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pennella</surname>
<given-names>T-TD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blyn</surname>
<given-names>LB</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Direct broad-range detection of alphaviruses in mosquito extracts.</article-title>
<source>Virology</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>368</volume>:<fpage>286</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2007.06.016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17655905?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17655905</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Seco</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Echevarr&#x000ed;a</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Est&#x000e9;vez</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Navarro-Mar&#x000ed;</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tenorio</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Detection and identification of Toscana and other phleboviruses by RT-nested-PCR assays with degenerated primers.</article-title>
<source>J Med Virol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>71</volume>:<fpage>140</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmv.10465</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12858420?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12858420</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tamura</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stecher</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Peterson</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Filipski</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>MEGA6: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 6.0.</article-title>
<source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>2725</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mst197</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24132122?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24132122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Folmer</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Black</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoeh</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lutz</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vrijenhoek</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>DNA primers for amplification of mitochondrial cytochrome c oxidase subunit I from diverse metazoan invertebrates.</article-title>
<source>Mol Mar Biol Biotechnol</source>. <year>1994</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>294</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<?supplied-pmid 7881515?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7881515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Roca</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bar-Gal</surname>
<given-names>GK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eizirik</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Helgen</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maria</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Springer</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Mesozoic origin for West Indian insectivores.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>429</volume>:<fpage>649</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02597</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15190349?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15190349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Valinsky</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ettinger</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bar-Gal</surname>
<given-names>GK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Orshan</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Molecular identification of bloodmeals from sand flies and mosquitoes collected in Israel.</article-title>
<source>J Med Entomol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>678</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/ME13125</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24897862?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24897862</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Katoh</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Misawa</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuma</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miyata</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>MAFFT: a novel method for rapid multiple sequence alignment based on fast Fourier transform.</article-title>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>3059</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>66</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkf436</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12136088?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12136088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Guindon</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gascuel</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A simple, fast, and accurate algorithm to estimate large phylogenies by maximum likelihood.</article-title>
<source>Syst Biol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>696</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>704</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10635150390235520</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14530136?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14530136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Agha</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chepkorir</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mulwa</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tigoi</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arum</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guarido</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Vector competence of populations of <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> from three distinct cities in Kenya for chikungunya virus.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e0005860</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005860</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28820881?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28820881</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oladejo</surname>
<given-names>BO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chai</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Structures of phlebovirus glycoprotein Gn and identification of a neutralizing antibody epitope.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>114</volume>:<fpage>E7564</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1705176114</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28827346?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28827346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brackney</surname>
<given-names>DE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scott</surname>
<given-names>JC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sagawa</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Woodward</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schilkey</surname>
<given-names>FD</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>C6/36 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> cells have a dysfunctional antiviral RNA interference response.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e856</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000856</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21049065?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21049065</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Traor&#x000e9;-Lamizana</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fontenille</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Diallo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>B&#x000e2;</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zeller</surname>
<given-names>HG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mondo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Arbovirus surveillance from 1990 to 1995 in the Barkedji area (Ferlo) of Senegal, a possible natural focus of Rift Valley fever virus.</article-title>
<source>J Med Entomol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>480</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/0022-2585-38.4.480</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11476327?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11476327</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tesh</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duboise</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Viremia and immune response with sequential phlebovirus infections.</article-title>
<source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>662</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.1987.36.662</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 3034088?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3034088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fisher</surname>
<given-names>AF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tesh</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tonry</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guzman</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>S-Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Induction of severe disease in hamsters by two sandfly fever group viruses, Punta toro and Gabek Forest (Phlebovirus, Bunyaviridae), similar to that caused by Rift Valley fever virus.</article-title>
<source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>269</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.2003.69.269</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14628943?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14628943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kemp</surname>
<given-names>GE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Causey</surname>
<given-names>OR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Setzer</surname>
<given-names>HW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moore</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Isolation of viruses from wild mammals in West Africa, 1966-1970.</article-title>
<source>J Wildl Dis</source>. <year>1974</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7589/0090-3558-10.3.279</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 4210769?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4210769</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tesh</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saidi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Javadian</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nadim</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Studies on the epidemiology of sandfly fever in Iran. I. Virus isolates obtained from Phlebotomus.</article-title>
<source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>. <year>1977</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>282</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.1977.26.282</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 192092?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">192092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Gaidamovich</surname>
<given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khutoretskaya</surname>
<given-names>NV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Asyamov</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsyupa</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Melnikova</surname>
<given-names>EE</given-names></string-name>. Sandfly fever in central Asia and Afghanistan. In: Calisher CH, editor. Hemorrhagic fever with renal syndrome, tick- and mosquito-borne viruses. Vienna: Springer; <year>1991</year>. p. 287&#x02013;93.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Karabatos</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. International catalogue of arboviruses including certain other viruses of vertebrates. 3rd ed. San Antonio (TX): American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene; <year>1985</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jaouadi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Haouas</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chaara</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boudabous</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gorcii</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kidar</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Phlebotomine (Diptera, Psychodidae) bloodmeal sources in Tunisian cutaneous leishmaniasis foci: could <italic>Sergentomyia minuta</italic>, which is not an exclusive herpetophilic species, be implicated in the transmission of pathogens?</article-title>
<source>Ann Entomol Soc Am</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/AN11186</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maia</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parreira</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crist&#x000f3;v&#x000e3;o</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Freitas</surname>
<given-names>FB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Afonso</surname>
<given-names>MO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Campino</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Molecular detection of <italic>Leishmania</italic> DNA and identification of blood meals in wild caught phlebotomine sand flies (Diptera: Psychodidae) from southern Portugal.</article-title>
<source>Parasit Vectors</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>173</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-015-0787-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25889732?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25889732</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Charrel</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Izri</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Temmam</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Delaunay</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Toga</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dumon</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Cocirculation of 2 genotypes of Toscana virus, southeastern France.</article-title>
<source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>465</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid1303.061086</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17552102?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17552102</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Alkan</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Erisoz Kasap</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alten</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Lamballerie</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Charrel</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sandfly-borne phlebovirus isolations from Turkey: New insight into the sandfly fever Sicilian and sandfly fever Naples species.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e0004519</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0004519</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27007326?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27007326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ochieng</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lutomiah</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Makio</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koka</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chepkorir</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yalwala</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Mosquito-borne arbovirus surveillance at selected sites in diverse ecological zones of Kenya; 2007 - 2012.</article-title>
<source>Virol J</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>140</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1743-422X-10-140</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23663381?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23663381</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sang</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arum</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chepkorir</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mosomtai</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tigoi</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sigei</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>Distribution and abundance of key vectors of Rift Valley fever and other arboviruses in two ecologically distinct counties in Kenya.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e0005341</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005341</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28212379?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28212379</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Woyessa</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Omballa</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lambert</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Waiboci</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ayele</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<article-title>An outbreak of acute febrile illness caused by Sandfly Fever Sicilian Virus in the Afar region of Ethiopia, 2011.</article-title>
<source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>1250</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.14-0299</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25266349?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25266349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>