<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par200">Pandemics are unforeseen. National and international preparedness are crucial to tackle a pandemic. World over, humanity is grappling with COVID-19. The pandemic preparedness charter prescribed by international and national agencies to tackle COVID-19 is evolving on the go. The key facets of pandemic preparedness emerging from global success and failure scenarios are:
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par300">Active surveillance employing state-of-the art technology:
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par400">Development of mathematical models for simulating the infection of CoV-2 in a given country. The models can help predict the basic reproductive number which in turn facilitates monitoring the pandemic on day-to-day basis.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par505">Incorporation of contactless artificial intelligence-based technologies for mass thermal screening, track and forecast community outbreaks, implement public hygiene and use of masks, and contact tracing.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par600">Expanding the diagnose capacity/testing for CoV-2 (the infectious agent) to catch any asymptomatic carriers, but at the same time ensuring:
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par700">Precision of the test.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par800">Test is adaptable to processing bulk samples.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par900">Easy procurement of sample from suspected infected individuals.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par1001">Management of bulk antiviral interventions and vaccines:
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par1101">National or regional priorities need to be fixed for rational use of antiviral/emerging vaccines</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par1201">Prioritizing the population has been recommended: the healthcare workers and essential service providers are top priority.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par1301">Medical stockpiles should be established.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par1401">Promoting facilities for healthcare/healthcare workers and facilitating public disinfection and hygiene via:
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par1501">Rapid expansion of hospitalization facilities for treatment and isolation/quarantine centers.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par1601">Ensuring minimal nosocomial infections to the healthcare workers.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par1701">Issuing and implementation of guidelines for ensuring good hand and respiratory hygiene.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par1801">Public disinfection (and personal household as well) based on the established life of CoV-2 on different surfaces.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par1901">Globally successful strategies are:
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par2001">Social distancing and lockdowns to ensure minimal human–human contact.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par2100">Travel restrictions to facilitate containment.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par2200">Trifecta of test–isolate–contact tracing.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par23001">The economic cost of the COVID-19 pandemic management is expanding due to:
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par24001">Disruption of economic activities due to implementation of social distancing via lockdowns.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par25001">Battling the diseased and the increasing mortality.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par2601">Diversion of resources to expansion of healthcare systems.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par2707">International and national relief funds are being constituted.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par2808">Fiscal reliefs and aid from developed nations to the developing or under-developed countries can release the surmounting economic pressure.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
