<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>Among the strategies targeting vector control, the exploitation of the endosymbiont 
  <italic>Wolbachia</italic> to produce sterile males and/or invasive females with reduced vector competence seems to be promising. A new 
  <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> transinfection (AR
  <italic>w</italic>P-M) was generated by introducing 
  <italic>w</italic>Mel 
  <italic>Wolbachia</italic> in the AR
  <italic>w</italic>P line which had been established previously by replacing 
  <italic>w</italic>AlbA and 
  <italic>w</italic>AlbB 
  <italic>Wolbachia</italic> with the 
  <italic>w</italic>Pip strain. Various infection and fitness parameters were studied by comparing AR
  <italic>w</italic>P-M, AR
  <italic>w</italic>P and wild-type (S
  <sub>ANG</sub> population) 
  <italic>Ae</italic>. albopictus sharing the same genetic background. Moreover, the vector competence of AR
  <italic>w</italic>P-M related to chikungunya, dengue and zika viruses was evaluated in comparison with AR
  <italic>w</italic>P. AR
  <italic>w</italic>P-M showed a 100% rate of maternal inheritance of 
  <italic>w</italic>Mel and 
  <italic>w</italic>Pip 
  <italic>Wolbachia</italic>. Survival, female fecundity and egg fertility did not show to differ between the three 
  <italic>Ae</italic>. 
  <italic>albopictus</italic> lines. Crosses between AR
  <italic>w</italic>P-M males and S
  <sub>ANG</sub> females were fully unfertile regardless of male age while egg hatch in reverse crosses increased from 0 to about 17% with S
  <sub>ANG</sub> males aging from 3 to 17 days. When competing with S
  <sub>ANG</sub> males for S
  <sub>ANG</sub> females, AR
  <italic>w</italic>P-M males induced a level of sterility significantly higher than that expected for an equal mating competitiveness (mean Fried index of 1.71 instead of 1). The overall 
  <italic>Wolbachia</italic> density in AR
  <italic>w</italic>P-M females was about 15 fold higher than in AR
  <italic>w</italic>P, mostly due to the 
  <italic>w</italic>Mel infection. This feature corresponded to a strongly reduced vector competence for chikungunya and dengue viruses (in both cases, 5 and 0% rates of transmission at 14 and 21 days post infection) with respect to AR
  <italic>w</italic>P females. Results regarding Zika virus did not highlight significant differences between AR
  <italic>w</italic>P-M and AR
  <italic>w</italic>P. However, none of the tested AR
  <italic>w</italic>P-M females was capable at transmitting ZIKV. These findings are expected to promote the exploitation of 
  <italic>Wolbachia</italic> to suppress the wild-type 
  <italic>Ae</italic>. 
  <italic>albopictus</italic> populations.
 </p>
</abstract>
