<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Case 3, an instance of a higher initially infected population (
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="IM43">
   <msubsup>
    <mi>I</mi>
    <mrow>
     <mn>0</mn>
    </mrow>
    <mi>A</mi>
   </msubsup>
   <mo>=</mo>
   <mn>1</mn>
   <mo> </mo>
   <mn>000</mn>
   <mo> </mo>
   <mn>000</mn>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> and 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="IM44">
   <msubsup>
    <mi>I</mi>
    <mrow>
     <mn>0</mn>
    </mrow>
    <mi>B</mi>
   </msubsup>
   <mo>=</mo>
   <mn>1</mn>
   <mo> </mo>
   <mn>000</mn>
   <mo> </mo>
   <mn>000</mn>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>), further strengthens the argument for a strong vector control programme regardless of vaccine availability. When a high initial disease burden was considered (
 <italic>S</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> = 2 000 000, 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="IM45">
   <msubsup>
    <mi>I</mi>
    <mrow>
     <mn>0</mn>
    </mrow>
    <mi>A</mi>
   </msubsup>
   <mo>=</mo>
   <mn>1</mn>
   <mo> </mo>
   <mn>000</mn>
   <mo> </mo>
   <mn>000</mn>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>, 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="IM46">
   <msubsup>
    <mi>I</mi>
    <mrow>
     <mn>0</mn>
    </mrow>
    <mi>B</mi>
   </msubsup>
   <mo>=</mo>
   <mn>1</mn>
   <mo> </mo>
   <mn>000</mn>
   <mo> </mo>
   <mn>000</mn>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>), a consistent maximum application of modified mosquito release was considered optimal, as well as a strong initial supply of vaccines. The epidemiological reasoning behind this is that the two million hosts that begin the case study with a primary infection, will never be able to benefit from a vaccine, as the framework does not provide them with an option to then receive such treatment. Biologically, this can be interpreted by drawing parallels from cost-effective inventions to control epidemic and endemic cholera [
 <xref rid="RSOS181843C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. While cholera vaccines proved very cost-effective treatments in small epidemic outbreaks, under endemic parameters vaccines were ineffective and it was considered more cost-effective to focus on the provision of safe drinking water and clearing the surrounding environment of the bacteria. While the epidemiology is different, the phenomena is the same, where vaccines are no longer capable of providing a herd immunity effect [
 <xref rid="RSOS181843C36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] alternative solutions to mitigate disease burden need to be sought.
</p>
