<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although the research on Malaria vaccines started in 1930, no human vaccine is currently licensed. There is, however, a prudent enthusiasm for the use of the RTS,S AS02 vaccine, which was developed by the Vaccine Initiative MVI of PATH, Glaxo Smith Kline (GSK), and several academic and research institutions (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). The RTS,S vaccine has been in development since 1987, and its Phase III trials were concluded in 2014. These assays were performed under Good Clinical Practice (GCP) and Good Laboratory Practice (GLP) regulations. There was a large multi-national trial enrolling 15,459 infants carried out at 11 clinical centers in seven African countries (Burkina Faso, Gabon, Malawi, Mozambique, Ghana, Tanzania, and Kenya). The RTS,S vaccine was most effective on 5 to 17-month-old children and showed a 36% reduction of severe cases of malaria (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). However, this study raised a number of safety concerns (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>–
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). The trial was followed up for 3 and 4 years in order to check the sustained efficacy. Vaccine efficacy against severe malaria was sustained and proved after 6 or 7 years in children who received a booster. In fact, the VE (vaccine efficacy) was 36.7% in the older group (5–7 years) and 31% in younger children (3–5 years). However, VE against mild malaria was 23.7% in the older children and 15.5% in the younger group. In addition, in the highest transmission center, an increase in clinical malaria was measured in older children (VE = −30.3%). Fifteen deaths (ten girls and five boys) were recorded in the RTS,S AS/01 vaccinated children group and seven in the controls. Hence, this study concluded that RTS,S/AS01 vaccine induces protection against severe malaria. However, a gender-associated frequency of deaths was observed, which was previously detected in the open phase III trial (
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). Although an increase in the incidence of uncomplicated cases of malaria was noticed in the vaccinated subjects, a delayed peak for the incidence of severe malaria was also detected. This bias trend of increasing clinical malarial cases was not expected for a Pre-erythrocytic vaccine such as RTS,S, which was designed to prevent the infection at the very early stage of liver infection. Therefore, clinical malaria was not expected to occur in vaccinated subjects. It may be argued that natural exposure to repeated malaria is needed to acquire immunity. However, chemoprevention of malaria only promoted a small increase in clinical cases (
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>).
</p>
