<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig1">
 <label>Figure 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Characterization of MAYV disease in immunocompetent mice. (
   <bold>a</bold>) Experimental scheme. 6-week-old BALB/c mice were infected or not with wt MAYV (2 × 10
   <sup>5</sup> PFU/50 μL, i.pl.) and several analyses were performed along the kinetic of infection. (
   <bold>b</bold>) Mechanical hypernociception was assessed daily. Results are shown as the differences (Δ) between the force (g) necessary to induce dorsal flexion of the tibio-tarsal joint, followed by paw withdraw, calculated by subtracting zero-time mean measurements before MAYV inoculation from the time interval mean measurements after infection. (
   <bold>c</bold>) Total and differential cell counts of inflammatory cells in the blood. (
   <bold>d–h</bold>) Plaque assay analysis of hind paw (
   <bold>d</bold>), LNP (
   <bold>e</bold>), quadriceps muscle (
   <bold>f</bold>), spleen (
   <bold>g</bold>) and serum (
   <bold>h</bold>). (
   <bold>i</bold>) Anti-MAYV IgM and IgG titers of pre- and post-infection serum samples collected on day zero and every 7 days until day 49. (
   <bold>j</bold>) MAYV-induced footpad swelling was assessed daily by measuring the height and width of the perimetatarsal area of the hind foot. Results are shown as mm
   <sup>2</sup>. (
   <bold>k</bold>) Neutrophil influx to the hind foot was measured indirectly by evaluation of MPO activity. (
   <bold>l</bold>) Macrophage influx to the hind foot was measured indirectly by analysis of NAG activity. (
   <bold>m</bold>) Shows semi-quantitative analysis (histopathological score) of hind paw sections of mock- and MAYV-infected mice, 1, 3, 7, 14 and 21 d.p.i. Representative pictures from hind paw sections. Results were expressed as median (
   <bold>d–h</bold>) or mean ± SEM (
   <bold>b</bold>,
   <bold>c</bold> and 
   <bold>i–m</bold>) and are representative of two experiments. Original magnification: 200×. Scale bar: 100 µm. *p &lt; 0.05 when compared to control uninfected mice (MOCK), as assessed by two-way (
   <bold>b</bold>,
   <bold>i</bold>,
   <bold>j</bold>) or one-way ANOVA followed by Newman-Keuls post-test (k-m). 
   <sup>+, &amp;</sup>, ^p &lt; 0.05 (for lymphocytes, neutrophils and monocytes, respectively) when compared to control uninfected mice (MOCK), as assessed by one-way ANOVA followed by Newman-Keuls post-test (
   <bold>c</bold>).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_62084_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e645" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
