<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Sixteen clinical trials relate to the supplementation of a single micronutrient or a micronutrient combination. Seven trials involve the co-therapeutic use of vitamin C (No. 1, 2, 7, 9, 10, 11, and 15) for different purposes, including symptom reduction, mortality reduction, increase in ventilator-free days, and prevention of COVID-19 progression. In clinical trial No. 1, vitamin C and zinc gluconate are being administered alone or in combination in 520 patients of both sexes (18 years and older, treated with the standard therapy) in order to evaluate the reduction of COVID-19 symptoms. In all other clinical trials on vitamin C, it is being administered alone. In clinical trial No. 2, 500 hospitalized COVID-19 patients with pneumonia (ranging from children to elderly patients, treated with standard therapy) are being treated with vitamin C intravenously to observe a possible reduction of mortality and symptoms. In clinical trial No. 7, 200 COVID-19 patients of both sexes (18 years and older, treated with standard therapy) with acute lung injury and hypoxemia have been recruited and are being treated with early infusion of vitamin C to evaluate reduction of the lung injury caused by SARS-CoV-2. In clinical trial No. 9, 140 SARS-CoV-2-infected patients of both sexes with severe acute respiratory infection (18 years and older, treated with the standard therapy) have been recruited to evaluate a coadjutant protocol based on daily intravenous infusion, with the aim of improving the prognosis of patients. In trial No. 10, the effect of vitamin C infusion is being evaluated in 20 COVID-19 patients with both mild and severe deoxygenation problems (18 years to 99 years) to evaluate the effect of vitamin C in reducing respiratory failure. Another clinical trial (No. 11) aims to study the effect of vitamin C supplementation, orally or intravenously administered, in addition to a comparative treatment (two drugs and three supplements), on 200 COVID-19 patients (18 years and older, both sexes), with the aim of reducing disease progression. Finally, in trial No. 15, 66 hospitalized COVID-19 patients of both sexes (18 years and older, treated with standard therapy) are being treated with vitamin C infusions to observe a possible improvement of health status.</p>
