<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Regarding HIV–EV cargo, different viral proteins have been reported to be encapsulated in extracellular vesicles, including the virulence factor Nef, which has gained a great attention. Nef acts as molecular adaptor in both infected and uninfected cells by exerting multiple effects depending on its intracellular localization. The most important and best characterized functions of Nef are: (a) modulation of the expression of different surface receptors; (b) induction of a pre-activation state in CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells, resulting in the increase in their susceptibility to the infection and promotion of viral gene expression; (c) regulation of apoptosis by inducing it in bystander uninfected cells meanwhile protecting infected cells; (d) regulation of the cytokine network contributing to chronic inflammation and, finally, (e) the increase in the infectivity of released HIV virions by preventing the incorporation of two antiviral proteins, SERINC3 and SERINC5 [
 <xref rid="B87-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>,
 <xref rid="B90-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>,
 <xref rid="B91-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. Interestingly, Nef also plays an important role in the vesicular network; it can influence the endosomal trafficking, being incorporated into MVBs, and induce late endosome formation. Not by chance, Nef binds and activates the PI3 kinase involved in vesicular formation [
 <xref rid="B92-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. In particular, Nef influences the production of vesicles and exploits them for its transport [
 <xref rid="B93-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. Different studies have shown how Nef increases vesicular production [
 <xref rid="B94-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>,
 <xref rid="B95-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>] and its association with EVs, which was observed both in in vitro and in vivo studies [
 <xref rid="B94-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>,
 <xref rid="B95-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>,
 <xref rid="B96-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. Interestingly, vesicles containing Nef turned out to exert multiple pathogenic effects: the induction of T-cell apoptosis [
 <xref rid="B94-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]; the down-modulation of cell surface molecules (i.e., MHC-I and CD4) to favor immune evasion [
 <xref rid="B97-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>], and the restoration of the infectivity of HIV particles defective in Nef protein [
 <xref rid="B98-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. Furthermore, Nef binds and incorporates into vesicles the TNFα converting enzyme (ADAM17 or TACE) [
 <xref rid="B99-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>,
 <xref rid="B100-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>], a metalloprotease that cuts the pro-TNFα present in cell membranes, causing the release of the active form of TNFα. Nef–EVs, by inducing TNFα release, promote the activation of resting cells, such as CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T lymphocytes, making them competent for HIV expression and replication [
 <xref rid="B101-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>,
 <xref rid="B102-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>,
 <xref rid="B103-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. A similar mechanism was also found to be involved in the reactivation of cells latently infected with HIV-1 [
 <xref rid="B104-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. These mechanisms have probably a great relevance in vivo, since Nef–EVs charged with ADAM17 and other pro-inflammatory factors appear to correlate with HIV-associated immune pathogenesis in both viremic and non-viremic chronic infection [
 <xref rid="B99-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>,
 <xref rid="B103-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. Noteworthy, HIV infection can also cause chronic neurological diseases and neurocognitive disorders (HIV-1 associated neurocognitive disorders (HAND)). Nef-containing EVs seem to be involved in the progression of these neuroimmune diseases. In chronic neurological diseases related to HIV infection, Nef–EVs released by infected microglia can disrupt the integrity of the blood–brain barrier, thus increasing its permeability, and can enhance the levels of some cytokines and chemokines such as IL-2, IL-8, IL-6, RANTES and IL-17A [
 <xref rid="B105-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. EVs isolated from the plasma of HAND patients can transport Nef protein and its correspondent mRNA is also able to induce the expression of the viral protein in a neuroblastoma cell line. This expression increases the production and secretion of beta amyloid protein, probably contributing to the cognitive impairment of HAND patients [
 <xref rid="B96-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. Overall, these data suggest that Nef–EVs are key mediators of the neuroimmune pathogenesis of HIV infection. Among the viral components transported into EVs, there is also Gag protein, which was found inside vesicles collected from infected Jurkat T cells, but its effects in uninfected cells are currently unknown [
 <xref rid="B106-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]. Even gp120 envelope protein was found in EVs isolated from infected cells that seem to significantly increase the viral infectivity in human lymphoid tissues [
 <xref rid="B107-viruses-12-00571" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>].
</p>
