<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par31">It is an investigational nucleotide adenosine analog developed by Gilead Sciences, USA, and is a monophosphoramidate prodrug of remdesivir-triphosphate. It has shown broad-spectrum antiviral activity against filoviruses, paramyxoviruses, pneumoviruses, and many animal and human coronaviruses including SARS and MERS [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Also, it was well tolerated in a phase 3 study for the treatment of EBOLA virus disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Currently, remdesivir is one of the most promising drugs under trial and is the center of attention for the treatment of COVID-19. It acts as an RdRp inhibitor and blocks viral RNA replication [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. It has shown its therapeutic potential against SARS-CoV-2 in various in vitro and animal studies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The published report of treatment of first COVID-19 patients in the USA and remdesivir’s use in a 53-patient case series have also documented the efficacy of remdesivir for COVID-19 patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. But, a recently published report of a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, multicentre trial at ten hospitals in Hubei, China, has documented the statistically non-significant clinical benefits in the remdesivir group, although the numerical reduction in time to clinical improvement in those treated earlier was numerically shorter in the remdesivir group than the control group [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. The dose used in this study was a single 200-mg loading dose, followed by a 100-mg daily infusion, and the most common adverse events seen in the remdesivir group were constipation, hypoalbuminemia, hypokalemia, anemia, thrombocytopenia, and increased total bilirubin. Moreover, the preliminary report of a double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled trial of remdesivir in 1059 hospitalized COVID-19 patients (538 in remdesivir and 521 in the placebo group) has reported that remdesivir was superior to placebo in shortening the time to recovery in COVID-19 patients. In this study, remdesivir was administered intravenously at 200 mg loading dose on day 1 and 100 mg daily from day 2 to day 10 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Another randomized, open-label, phase 3 trial in 397 (200 patients for 5 days and 197 for 10 days) COVID-19 patients not requiring mechanical ventilation has reported no significant difference between a 5-day course and a 10-day course of remdesivir. All the patients received 200 mg of intravenous remdesivir on day 1 and 100 mg once daily on subsequent days. The limitation of this study was the open-label design and the absence of a placebo control group [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. However, whether remdesivir is associated with more benefit or might cause harm needs to be confirmed in a randomized control trial (RCT) of a larger sample size. Fortunately, above 20 randomized trials involving remdesivir are registered on 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> and are recruiting participants globally [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Recently, remdesivir is certified for an emergency use authorization (EUA) for treating hospitalized COVID-19 patients by the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA). Promising signals from various studies are available yet more data are needed to conclude its efficacy for COVID-19. The risk–benefit ratio needs to be optimized in a larger population size with an early start of remdesivir treatment in COVID-19 patients. Moreover, the adequate dose should be selected, which produces clinically beneficial effects and causes less harm.
</p>
