<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0013">According to the pathological findings, the first report on the pathological results of severe COVID-19 revealed that diffuse alveolar injury on both sides of the lung was accompanied by cellular fibromyxoid exudates 
 <xref rid="bib0053" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. The right lung displayed significant lung cell shedding and hyaline membrane formation, suggesting ARDS. Moreover, the left lung tissue showed pulmonary edema and hyaline membrane formation, implying early ARDS. Interstitial mononuclear inflammatory infiltrates, dominated by lymphocytes, were found in both lungs. Another study reported that acute kidney injury and proteinuria might also occur during the progression of COVID-19 disease. ACE2 was seen to be upregulated in COVID-19 patients, and immunostaining with the SARS-CoV nucleoprotein antibody was positive in tubules 
 <xref rid="bib0054" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>. Additionally, only a few interstitial mononuclear inflammatory infiltrates were found in the heart tissue, meaning that this virus may not directly induce heart impairment 
 <xref rid="bib0053" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. Aside from the acute respiratory distress syndrome, exuberant inflammatory responses during the infection process were also observed in clinical, giving rise to unrestrained pulmonary inflammation. Of note, the virus-induced ACE2 downregulation, rapid virus replication and cell damage, and antibody-dependent enhancement may lead to aggressive inflammation aroused by SARS-CoV-2 
 <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>. The initial stage of rapid viral replication would induce a large number of epithelial and endothelial cell death, thereby facilitating the generation of raging pro-inflammatory cytokines and chemokines (
 <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> ) 
 <xref rid="bib0056" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>. Intriguingly, a recent research compared the transcriptional responses of SARS-CoV-2 with other respiratory viruses to identify the transcriptional features that might form the biological basis of COVID-19 
 <xref rid="bib0057" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>. Their work demonstrated that the overall transcriptional induction of SARS-CoV-2 is abnormal. Despite viral replication, the host's response to SARS-CoV-2 failed to initiate powerful responses of type I and III interferons (IFN-I and -III), and at the same time induced high levels of chemokines required to recruit effector cells. In other words, this unique inflammatory response was defined by low levels of IFN-I and -III juxtaposed to elevated chemokines and high expression of IL-6. The reduced innate antiviral defenses coupled with exuberant inflammatory cytokine production may be the defining and driving features of COVID-19 
 <xref rid="bib0057" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>. Moreover, because the weakened immune response will further enable sustained viral replication, this critical finding may explain why severe cases of COVID-19 are more frequently observed in patients with comorbidities 
 <xref rid="bib0058" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>.
</p>
