<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The introduction of the RV vaccine altered the prevalence of RV infection, but it continues to be frequently detected during AGE. A study of enteric RNA virus co-infections in diarrheic children and adults in Southwestern Canada found that 2.8% of total RNA virus-positive samples showed combinations of NoV GII-SaV, NoV GII-RV, NoV GII-AstV, SaV-AstV, and SaV-RV at varying percentages [
 <xref rid="B101-viruses-12-00904" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>]. A similar study focused on pediatric AGE in Spain identified more than half of children as being infected with at least one virus, including AdV, RV, SaV, AstV, and NoV, with co-infections detected in 21% of cases [
 <xref rid="B102-viruses-12-00904" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. In Turkish children under the age of 5, RV was present in about one-third of AGE samples, and co-infections were found in 10.4% of samples with RV-NoV and NoV-AdV as the most frequently observed [
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-12-00904" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In China, RV and NoV-GII co-infections were reported in 14% of children suffering from severe diarrhea [
 <xref rid="B39-viruses-12-00904" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. A study conducted to determine the agents associated with AGE in children in Nepal reported that nearly all children tested had at least one enteric viral agent detected, and approximately half were co-infected with RV and enterovirus [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-12-00904" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Overall, these studies support that in healthy children and adults experiencing AGE episodes, between ~3–50% may have more than one viral pathogen present. Some reports indicate that RV co-infections, at least in healthy children, are not associated with greater symptom severity than single RV infection [
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-12-00904" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-12-00904" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], while another reported that co-infections with NoV may lead to more severe AGE with enhanced comorbidities, such as vomiting and fever, compared to NoV alone [
 <xref rid="B94-viruses-12-00904" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. Further clinical studies exploring the effects of co-infection on symptom severity are needed to better clarify the relative contribution of co-infection to disease outcomes.
</p>
