<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="f0025">
 <label>Fig. 5</label>
 <caption>
  <p>
   <italic>Structural models of viral enzymes involved in RNA capping. RTPase folds:</italic> (I) the triphosphate tunnel metalloenzyme (TTM) fold is examplified by the structure of the RTPase (PDB code 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:2QZE" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">2QZE</ext-link>) from the genus 
   <italic>Mimivirus</italic>, which consists of double-stranded DNA (dsDNA) viruses; (II) the helicase fold of the RTPase from the single-stranded positive-sense RNA (ss(+)RNA) dengue virus (PDB code 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:2BHR" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">2BHR</ext-link>); (III) the histidine triad (HIT)-like fold of the RTPase from dsRNA rotaviruses (PDB code 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:1L9V" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">1L9V</ext-link>). 
   <italic>GTase folds:</italic> (I) Structure of the dsDNA virus 
   <italic>Paramecium bursaria</italic> chlorella virus 1 GTase, showing the loading reaction: GTP onto the active site, with the GTase in an open conformation (PDB code 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:1CKO" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">1CKO</ext-link>); (II) GTase domain of the Cypovirus (PDB code 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:3IZ3" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">3IZ3</ext-link>, residues 1–366). 
   <italic>MTases folds</italic>: (I) N-7-MTase: the (guanine-N-7)-methyltransferase (N-7 MTase) domain of protein D1 from the dsDNA virus vaccinia virus (PDB accession code 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:2VDW" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">2VDW</ext-link>) in complex with a molecule of 
   <italic>S</italic>-adenosyl-
   <sc>l</sc>-homocysteine (AdoHcy). II) 2′-O MTase: VP39, the 2′-O MTase of the dsDNA virus vaccinia virus, in complex with a capped RNA and AdoHcy (PDB code 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:1AV6" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">1AV6</ext-link>). III) N-7/2′-O methyltransferase: the N-7 MTase-(nucleoside-2′-O)-methyltransferase (2
   <italic>’</italic>-O MTase) domain of NS5 from dengue virus (ss(+)RNA) in complex with the cap analogue 7-methyl-G (m7G)-pppGm2′-O and AdoHCY (PDB code 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:2P41" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">2P41</ext-link>). 
   <italic>Endonuclease fold</italic>: (I) endonuclease (N-terminal) domain of L protein of lymphocytic choriomeningitis virus (PDB code 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:3JSB" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">3JSB</ext-link>). Structures are colored cyan for α-helices and red for β-strands. All figures were prepared using PyMOL.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="gr5" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
