<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>More generally, the fine-grained spatial genetic structure evident in wildlife rabies that is lacking for dog rabies may be due to differences in time frame. The best-studied wildlife rabies dynamics come from invasions that originated a few decades ago (Bourhy 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">1999</xref>; Real 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref60">2005
  <italic>a</italic>
 </xref>; Biek 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">2007</xref>), compared to endemic foci in domestic dogs, thought to have persisted for centuries (Bourhy 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">2008</xref>). Factors influencing persistent endemic cycles are likely to differ from those determining epidemic expansions, with viral population turnover, increased mixture of lineages and the greater role of human-mediated movement resulting in less clearly defined fine-grain viral structure. Again, metapopulation models that capture population connectivity at appropriate spatial and temporal scales may shed light on the genetic structure of endemic foci. Characterizing the landscape connectivity between rabies endemic areas (or individual rabies cases, given the resolution of spatial data) may be facilitated using techniques applied in conservation genetics that have yet to be exploited for disease dynamics. For example, the program Fractionnator, (
 <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.unil.ch/biomapper/frictionnator/frictionnator.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.unil.ch/biomapper/frictionnator/frictionnator.html</uri>), provides a ‘strip statistic’ quantifying the effect of landscape features on the relatedness of all possible pairs of individuals sampled. This entails defining grid cells within a strip across the sampled landscape and assessing the abundance of landscape features within each strip. In addition, advances in the development of spatial analysis software such as python-based customised GIS tools (e.g. Etherington, 2001) that allow the visualisation and measurement of genetic relatedness and landscape connectivity based on least cost path analysis, R packages such as Maptools (Lewin-Koh 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48">2012</xref>) and alternative open-source software such as PASSaGE 2 (Rosenberg and Anderson, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref64">2011</xref>) provide utilities for measuring connectivity between patches, quantifying patterns in spatial data and potentially identifying barriers to dispersal.
</p>
