<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Host transmission is typically heterogeneous, often described by the 80/20 paradigm in which individuals differentially carry and transmit pathogens i.e. 80% of infections are carried by 20% of the population (Woolhouse 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref86">1997</xref>). In the most extreme case this heterogeneity can exist in the form of 
 <italic>superspreaders</italic> (Lloyd-Smith 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref49">2005</xref>). There have been no in-depth studies of superspreading in domestic dogs carrying rabies and the contribution of superspreaders to rabies spread and persistence is controversial (e.g. Hampson 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">2007</xref> vs. Talbi 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref76">2009</xref>), but large variations in biting frequency have been observed (Hampson 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">2009</xref>). An important distinction must be made between superspreading in a restricted area, e.g. the same village, and a ‘spatial superspreader’ that has dispersed infection over large distances and multiple settlements (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2</xref> for visual example). Although the number of secondary cases caused by such individuals may be equivalent, spatial superspreaders are more important from an epidemiological perspective if they are responsible for connecting sub-populations. Tracing resulting infections to their source through genetic sequence data may identify hotspots where certain patch features promote greater dispersal ability i.e. spatial superspreading events (as suggested by Cross 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">2007</xref>). Ideally, this would utilise retrospective genetic tracing of networks of infection, similar to that used for identifying source infections in foot-and-mouth disease (FMD) (Cottam 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">2008</xref>). Statistically robust methods are yet to be conceived, but accounting for missing links in transmission chains is an important area for future development. As a major advantage compared to FMD, contact that may have lead to transmission is much easier to define for rabies. Contact tracing data, if available, could therefore complement genetic data to offer a more comprehensive view of how individual heterogeneity can impact on dynamics. 
</p>
