<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To assess the sensitivity of RT-PCR tests and for confirmation purposes, CHIKV isolations from plasma specimens were attempted in epithelioid cells derived from African Green Monkey kidneys (Vero E6, ATCC CRL-1586). The Vero E6 cells used for virus isolation were maintained in cell culture medium comprised of aDMEM (advanced Dulbecco’s modified essential medium) supplemented with 10% low antibody, heat-inactivated, gamma-irradiated fetal bovine serum (FBS, Hyclone, GE Healthcare Life Sciences, Pittsburgh, PA), L-alanine and L-glutamine supplement (GlutaMAX, Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA), and 50 μg/ml penicillin, 50μg/ml streptomycin, 100μg/ml neomycin (PSN antibiotics, Invitrogen) with incubation at 37°C in 5% CO
 <sub>2</sub>. Confluent cell cultures were split into 25cm
 <sup>2</sup> flasks 24 hours prior to inoculation to attain 60% confluent cell monolayers the following day. Prior to inoculation, the culture medium was removed and inoculum containing 100μl of plasma that had been filtered through a sterile 0.45 filter and mixed with 400μL aDMEM with 3% FBS, GlutaMAX, and PSN antibiotics was added to the monolayer. The inoculated monolayer was incubated at 37°C in 5% CO
 <sub>2,</sub> and rocked every 15 minutes for 1 hour. A negative control (mock-infected) cell culture was inoculated with 500ul of DMEM without virus or plasma and handled in parallel with the other cultures. After allowing for virus adsorption for 1 hr, the inocula were removed and replaced with 3ml of aDMEM with 3% FBS, GlutaMAX, and PSN antibiotics, and thereafter incubated at 37°C in 5% CO
 <sub>2</sub>. Cell cultures were refed every 3 days by the replacement of 1.5ml of spent media with aDMEM with 3% FBS. The cultures were observed for up to 21 days’ post-inoculation, or until CHIKV-induced cytopathic effects (CPE) were observed in the cell monolayers using an inverted microscope. When CPE were observed throughout 50% of the monolayer, a final collection of 2ml spent media, and 1ml of scraped cells in spent media, were cryopreserved at -80°C for future tests.
</p>
