<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Currently, synthetic surfactants are studied as potential drug candidates for the acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS). This is a multifactorial condition, also caused by pulmonary surfactant deficit and prolonged inflammatory responses. Importantly, COVID-19 can lead to ARDS as SARS-CoV-2 can infect and impair the function of type II cells in the lungs, affecting the production of pulmonary surfactants, at the third stage of the infection [
 <xref rid="B140-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>]. Current therapeutic approaches include anti-inflammatory agents, vasodilators and surfactant replacement therapy, among others [
 <xref rid="B141-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">141</xref>,
 <xref rid="B142-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>]. The most commonly used are porcine lung surfactants. However, major limitations in their use include: (i) the difficulty of isolation and (ii) their limited production, thereby reflecting the inability of high-dose administration. To this end, synthetic SAAs with anti-inflammatory potential are being studied for their use as pulmonary surfactant substitutes in ARDS patients. For instance, CHF5633 is a novel synthetic surfactant, consisting of: (i) analogues of surfactant proteins B (SP-B) and C (SP-C) (both possessing changes in size and amino-acid sequence) and (ii) a 1:1 phospholipid mixture of dipalmitoyl phosphatidyl choline (DPPC) and palmitoyl oleyl phoshatidyl glycerol (POPG). SP-B and SP-C are the lipid-associated protein components of the pulmonary surfactant that protect the alveoli shape during breathing. CHF5633 has been thoroughly examined for its ability to elicit an anti-inflammatory response in naive or activated neonatal or adult monocytes. In each model used, CHF5633 decreased the expression of the inflammatory mediators like tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α) and interleukin-1β (IL-1β), but had no effect on the expression levels of interleukin-8, -10, Toll-like receptor 2 (TLR2) and 4 (TLR-4) [
 <xref rid="B143-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>,
 <xref rid="B144-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>]. Similarly, the activated CD4+T human lymphocytes that were exposed to CHF5633 exhibited higher transcriptional levels of the anti-inflammatory cytokines, interleukin-4 and -10 [
 <xref rid="B145-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>]. 
</p>
