<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our study has limitations. We focused on the identification of drivers of dengue and chikungunya emergence. All events of autochthonous transmission were therefore considered, irrespective of their size. However, one may suppose that the factors explaining the size of the foci of transmission may be different from factors which only explain the occurrence of transmission. Furthermore, DENV and CHIKV were considered to be similar, despite differences in transmission efficacy. However, these vector-virus interactions are already highly heterogeneous for each of these pathogens due to the existence of different viral genotypes [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008320.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008320.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>] and these two arboviruses exhibit a similar ecology calling for a similar public health response. These different considerations justify, in our view, treating both similarly. Furthermore, if we had had more events, we could have had studied the importance of virus genetic factors in more detail. Host and viral genetic factors may have a major impact on arbovirus transmission, as illustrated by the increased efficacy of transmission observed after the adaptation of chikungunya virus to 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008320.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. The results of this work could be extended to the risk of transmission of other arboviral diseases, especially Zika, as the first case of autochthonous vector-borne transmission was recently reported in France [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008320.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Only events detected by the national surveillance system are reported here, and we cannot exclude that autochthonous transmission events—particularly of modest size—may have gone unnoticed, due to the absence of symptoms, medical consultation, proper diagnosis and reporting. The subclinical infection rates of dengue and chikungunya infections is also a possible limitation of the study, as the real incidence rates of imported cases were probably higher than those observed. Accordingly, the different risk factors identified were potentially overestimated. However, we assume that the impact of under-detection and under-diagnosis was limited given the efficiency of the surveillance system dedicated to dengue and chikungunya infections. 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> is still expanding its range throughout the world, including Europe. However, it is difficult to extrapolate our results to other bioclimatic zones. It is therefore essential to update this type of approach in the light of new transmission events and in different environmental and climatic settings. Moreover, the presence of nested data (as a unique case introduction could lead to several observations) would have justified the use of mixed methods, but the limited number of transmission events did not contain any sufficient information for parameters estimation in such a framework. This limited number of transmission events is explained by the epidemiological situation and requires to consider the results with caution. In this global perspective, both routine documentation of viremic cases (from a meteorological, environmental, socio-economic point of view) and routine integration of data into surveillance system databases is paramount. The development of these anticipatory tools will be useful to reduce the risk of multiple autochthonous arboviral transmission events.
</p>
