<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13">Seasonal influenza epidemics are known to result in substantial morbidity and mortality worldwide, particularly in regions with temperate climates, and the mechanism of seasonal influenza activity and transmission has not been elucidated. Influenza seasons are determined by climate regions. Worldwide, influenza epidemics always follow low seasonal temperatures, suggesting that low temperatures may change seasonal crowding, viral survival in respiratory droplets and host susceptibility
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. Moreover, humidity may be a critical driver of influenza outbreaks. Absolute humidity has a regulatory effect on airborne influenza transmission, and this effect can be modulated by temperature
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>. Generally, the northern and southern regions in China experience different influenza seasonality and evolutionary dynamics. Usually, the northern region experiences an influenza season during the winter months (with a median peak in Jan., ranging from Dec. to Jan.), while the southern region experiences influenza during the summer months (with a median peak from May to Jun.). Because Shanghai has a subtropical climate but is located in the intermediate-latitude region, the influenza seasonality in Shanghai is atypical
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>. Between 2006 and 2016, the annual seasonality in Shanghai was irregular. Two influenza peaks were observed in 2008 and 2010, and only one epidemic occurred during the other years. However, in 2017, the following two influenza epidemics occurred in Shanghai: one epidemic between Nov. 2016 and Mar. 2017 and one epidemic between May 2017 and Sep. 2017. These epidemics were consistent with the influenza epidemics observed in Hong Kong and Guangdong in 2017. Although influenza epidemics occur frequently during summer in the southern region, the mechanism underlying summer influenza epidemics has not been elucidated
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>. In this study, we performed genomic and replication analyses for viruses obtained during both the winter and summer of 2017 in an attempt to investigate the evolution of the influenza virus during 2017 in Shanghai and the effects of mutations on viral replication in these two epidemic viral strains.
</p>
