<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">Nanotechnology is a fast-growing field that provides the development of materials that have new dimensions, novel properties, and a broader array of applications. U.S. National Nanotechnology Initiative defines nanoparticles (NPs) in the range 1–100 nm (National Nanotechnology Initiative 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR158">2008</xref>). Microbial, fungal, and viral infections represent an increasing worldwide threat that is caused by both general immunosuppression of the world population and the growth of resistance of pathogens to clinically used drugs as well as development of cross-resistant or multidrug-resistant strains (Jampílek 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">2018</xref>). In particular, viruses caused a number of diseases worldwide, many of them with fatal termination. Although smallpox has been eradicated and for some of them vaccines were developed, viruses continuously indicate to us that conventional antiviral drugs/strategies directly targeting viral or cellular proteins have been limited, due to frequent virus variation resulting in drug resistance, because many of drugs show high specificity (e.g., De Clercq and Li 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2016</xref>; Takizawa and Yamasaki 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR214">2018</xref>; Wang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR231">2018a</xref>; Deng and Wang 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2018</xref>). It can be stated that design and discovery of structurally new anti-infectives with a new/innovative mode of action is time consuming and relatively risky (Jampílek 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">2016a</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">b</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">2018</xref>). Moreover, many of the existing antivirals demonstrate also human toxicity and rapid clearance from the body. Thus, design and development of new safe and potent antivirals with activity against viral infection at multiple points in the viral life cycle remains a major challenge (Al-Ghananeem et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2013</xref>; Li et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">2016</xref>; Kos et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">2019</xref>).
</p>
