<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The efficiency of TuMV and CMV seed transmission depended on the 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> accession-virus species/isolate interaction, indicating that traits controlled by the host and/or the parasite determine this process. Global multivariate models identified the virus speed of within-host movement and its level of multiplication in the plant inflorescence as the best estimators of percent seed transmission. These variables can be considered proxies for the ability of the virus to reach and invade gametic tissues, respectively (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Bivariate analyses indicated that the faster the virus spread across the reproductive structures, the higher its efficiency of seed transmission. Seed transmission requires reaching the plant reproductive structures during a particular window of time that in general is quite narrow: the embryo is accessible after fertilization and before the suspensor’s programmed cell death, and pollen and ovule invasion must occur prior to fertilization (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). These periods last only a few days in 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Hence, faster within-host movement would allow the virus to reach the reproductive organs within the required time frame in a larger number of flowers/siliques. This is compatible with experimental analyses showing that, in general, earlier virus infection leads to a higher efficiency of seed transmission (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Reaching the reproductive organs at the right moment does not guarantee seed transmission, as the virus also needs to gain entry into the seed (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). It has been proposed that a higher level virus multiplication in the plant reproductive structures favors embryo/gametophyte invasion by promoting virus crossing of the boundary between the maternal and progeny tissues (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). In line with this prediction, our results indicate that a higher level of virus multiplication in the inflorescence increases the percentage of infected seeds. This observation also agrees with previous work showing that a higher percentage of seed transmission correlates with high virus titers in flowers, ovules, and/or pollen (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Moreover, the only host genes identified as genetic determinants of plant virus seed transmission are involved in small RNA-mediated gene silencing, which modulates virus multiplication (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Note that in our experiments, plants were inoculated at an early developmental stage. Virus inoculation of older plants would reduce the number of flowers/siliques that the virus can reach during the appropriate window of time, especially for the most basal ones (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). In this context, the speed of within-host movement would likely become critical for seed transmission, increasing its relative importance in the multivariate models.
</p>
