<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Virus-specific multivariate models confirmed that the speed of within-host movement and the level of multiplication in the inflorescence were major determinants of virus seed transmission. Interestingly, these models identified other traits as minor estimators of virus vertical transmission, which differed between TuMV and CMV. For TuMV, the combination of the two above-mentioned factors and virus virulence explained 91% of the variation in percent seed transmission. TuMV is regarded as a sterilizing parasite because it frequently prevents seed production in a number of 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> accessions, in which no vertical transmission is attained (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Hence, the identification of TuMV virulence as being negatively associated with seed transmission efficiency likely reflects that it determines the presence/absence of vertical transmission rather than having a role in the mechanism of this process. For CMV, the third trait (negatively) associated with the efficiency of vertical transmission was the long-term survival of infected seeds. Note that seed aging is posterior to our measures of the efficiency of vertical transmission. Thus, a lower long-term seed survival rate is likely a consequence of infection and suggests that the presence of the virus in the seed reduces its viability. We did not determine whether the seeds dying during the 48-h accelerated-aging treatment were mostly those harboring the virus. However, bivariate analyses using averaged values of the six accessions indicated that the percentage of CMV seed transmission explained 66% of the variance in the percentage of dead aged seeds. Hence, our results suggest that long-term seed survival could be a modifier of the efficiency of seed transmission in the long run. Alternatively, a lower long-term survival rate of seeds from infected plants could reflect maternal effects, but we did not find a significant difference in the weights of single seeds between infected and mock-inoculated plants, which argues against this possibility. The negative relationship between the efficiency of CMV seed transmission and long-term seed survival is in apparent contradiction with experimental analyses showing that infection of 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants by Fny-CMV renders seeds with improved tolerance to deterioration (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). However, those authors used Col-0 and a 24-h accelerated-aging treatment, an accession not included in our work and conditions for which we showed that the effect of Fny-CMV infection on seed survival significantly varies between accessions.
</p>
