<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0510">The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic, caused by the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), has led to over 13 million cases. COVID-19 vaccines development is occurring with unprecedented speed. This is partially due to the Coalition for Epidemic Preparedness Innovations (CEPI) 
 <xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. CEPI, formed in 2017, is a novel partnership between private, public, philanthropic and civil society organizations. It aims to develop vaccines for future epidemics and enable equitable access to vaccines for people during epidemics. CEPI is mandated to accelerate the development and manufacture of vaccines against previously unknown pathogens with 16 weeks from identification of antigen to vaccine candidate release for clinical trials 
 <xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. CEPI has announced the initiation of nine COVID-19 vaccine programs 
 <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Rapid response platforms for vaccine development supported by CEPI are being utilized. Platform technology use systems with the same basic components as a backbone and insert new protein or genetic sequences to adapt for use against different pathogens 
 <xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. The vaccine candidates include a DNA vaccine (administered with electroporation); a molecular-clamp vaccine (synthesis of viral surface proteins, which attach to host cells during infection and clamps them into shape, so that the immune system can recognize them as the correct antigen); recombinant protein nanoparticle technology to generate antigens derived from the coronavirus spike (S) protein (proprietary saponin-based adjuvant); a recombinant protein vaccine with the S Trimer, a replication-deficient simian adenoviral vaccine (ChAdOx1-S); a measles-vector vaccine, a live-attenuated influenza vaccine and two mRNA vaccines. A pandemic vaccine adjuvant will be available to enhance development 
 <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>.
</p>
