<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since the explosive ZIKV outbreaks, the vector competence of several mosquito species and populations for this virus has been tested. Previous results highlighted some heterogeneity in the ZIKV transmission, especially due to the ZIKV lineage [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006637.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. In this study, the aim of the experiments was to test the vector competence of Pacific mosquitoes for the ZIKV which circulated during the outbreak (Asian/Pacific lineage). Our results corroborate previous findings that mosquito vectors, whatever the area they originate from (Pacific, America, Europe), are mostly poorly competent for the Asian/Pacific sublineage of ZIKV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006637.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006637.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006637.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. We did not have the opportunity here to test 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> from the Pacific region. Although, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> could be relevant to Public Health as a potential invasive species in the region, it might not have sustained an outbreak by its own as it is not present in New Caledonia and French Polynesia [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006637.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] and as it appears to be a poor ZIKV vector in other region [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006637.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. All together, these observations support that the emergence of ZIKV in the Pacific region and other regions, did not solely rely on the competence of the vectors to transmit this virus. Several other factors, notably the vector density, the mosquito lifespan and non-entomological parameters like the large immunologically naive fractions of the population may have contributed to the unexpected globalization of ZIKV. This work highlights the necessity to characterize the interaction between mosquitoes, arboviruses and humans in the areas recently affected in order to better assess the risk for such arboviruses to emerge and to limit the burden of future outbreaks.
</p>
