<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is well-known that the infection of cells with ZIKV induces the upregulation of antiviral genes (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Carlin et al., 2018</xref>). Our study also found that in CHME3 cells ZIKV infection resulted in upregulation of type I interferon (IFNβ), interferon-stimulated genes (MX-1 and ISG15), pattern recognition receptors (RIG-I and MDA5) and IRF7. This upregulation was not significantly affected by addition of celgosivir, despite celgosivir reducing magnitude of ZIKV infection. Since the results of misfolded viral proteins includes not only reduced successful virus assembly and maturation but also protein accumulation in the ER and eventual ERAD, iminosugar treatment can induce ER stress and the unfolded protein response (
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Zakaria et al., 2018</xref>). Such a response can lead to stimulation of antiviral innate immune response pathways as well as apoptosis to limit viral infection (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Smith, 2014</xref>). We found a significant increase in activated caspase 3/7 in ZIKV-infected CHME3 cells compared with mock-infected cells at 48 and 72 hpi, indicating significant activation of apoptosis in virus-infected cells. Our findings are in accordance with an earlier report that showed significant activation of caspases in neural progenitor cells at 24 h after infection with ZIKV (
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Souza et al., 2016</xref>). Notably, there was no statistically significant difference in the levels of caspase 3/7 between celgosivir- and vehicle-treated cells after ZIKV infection. The significance of apoptosis of microglia is unclear, particularly in the developing brain. Primary astrocytes, the cell type that is most abundant in developing brain (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Reemst et al., 2016</xref>), that supported persistent ZIKV infection of both African and Asian lineage ZIKV were relatively resistant to virus-induced apoptosis, suggesting that lack of apoptosis could lead to persistence of ZIKV infection in developing brain cells and lead to ZIKV-induced damage such as microcephaly (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Limonta et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
