<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0075">The plaque-reduction neutralization test (PRNT) was subsequently developed as the gold-standard for JE diagnosis, using paired acute and convalescent sera and comparison with other endemic flaviviruses, and it remains so today (
 <xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">Hills et al., 2009</xref>). The demonstration of increasing anti-JEV neutralizing antibody titer in the convalescent serum and the absence, or at least fourfold lower titer for neutralizing antibodies against control-related flaviviruses, provides a robust diagnosis. However, this is laborious, time-consuming, and requires high-level containment facilities for safe manipulation of infectious JEV in cell culture. Mainly for these reasons, the anti-JEV IgM capture ELISA (JEV MAC-ELISA) was developed during the 1980s and has been incorporated as the WHO standard procedure for JE diagnosis (
 <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">Burke et al., 1982</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0820" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization, 2007</xref>). Although commercial JEV MAC ELISAs are manufactured, they may be hard to access in endemic countries (for example, there is no supplier in Laos), relatively expensive, and require costly ELISA readers and significant technical training. The performance of the kit requires specialized laboratory equipment, and thus are by no means point-of-care tests. In addition, field studies suggest that the sensitivity is 50-70% (
 <xref rid="bib0620" ref-type="bibr">Robinson et al., 2010</xref>), and concerns have been raised regarding the diagnostic specificity (
 <xref rid="bib0230" ref-type="bibr">Dubot-Peres et al., 2015</xref>). In the last two decades, there has been increased availability of molecular testing, providing crucial data on molecular epidemiology. As well, the aforementioned low and brief viremia limits the role of screening for JEV RNA for diagnostic purposes. Similarly, advances in techniques such as near-atomic resolution cryo-electron microscopy contribute to our understanding of the detailed viral structure, but not to the routine detection of human infection (
 <xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>).
</p>
