<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A biological feature relevant to emergence is the overlap that has been identified in several viruses between receptor-recognition sites and antigenic sites. The fact that some exposed amino acid residues are part of one or several epitopes for antibody binding, as well as part of the receptor-recognition domain, may favor the coevolution of host cell tropism and antigenicity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R83">83</xref>]. Such overlap is, however, double-edged. It opens the possibility of pleiotropic effects of single mutations (that may affect positively or negatively more than one viral function), and of coevolution of phenotypic traits. However, it may also introduce additional evolutionary constraints to the virus, as will the overlap of domains (in viral proteins or nucleic acids) in general. Structural and biochemical studies have indicated that residues located at the surface of viral particles tend to be subjected to less structural constraints than residues located in the interior of viral capsids or envelopes and, therefore, they may be prone to accept amino acid substitutions. Tolerance to change of surface amino acid residues may facilitate the emergence of new cell receptor specificities mediated by antigenic change with obvious implications for viral disease emergence and re-emergence [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R90">90</xref>]. Partial immunity to FMDV, evoked by synthetic peptides that mimicked the major antigenic site of the virus, produced the selection of antigenic variants in cattle, and the variants displayed alterations of cell tropism [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80">80</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R81">81</xref>]. Escape mutants selected by ineffective vaccines have been reported in other viral systems [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R85">85</xref>]. In addition, tolerance to amino acid substitutions at surface sites of capsid or envelope proteins may result in antigenic variation independent of immune selection, as documented with several DNA and RNA viruses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>].
</p>
