<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<notes>
 <title>Notes</title>
 <fn-group>
  <fn id="fn1">
   <label>1</label>
   <p>Viral hemorrhagic fevers are caused by one of four families of RNA viruses—Arenaviridae, Filoviridae, Bunyaviridae, and Flaviviridae. These viruses are found around the globe in a number of different forms. This article concentrates on African strains of Ebola, Marburg, and Lassa fever. Although these share some key epidemiological and ecological characteristics (e.g., the role of small mammals in hosting the pathogen and of hospital settings in viral spread), our focus follows from the research objectives outlined by a multidisciplinary consortium on which we had the opportunity to collaborate, thus it reflects the analytic scope of this project and the interests of our collaborators. We hope that this article will lead to development of a methodological approach that will help open up these categorizations for reflection and reconfiguration.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn2">
   <label>2</label>
   <p>In 1999, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) classified VHF as high-priority (Category A) bioweapon agents, determined by their ease of dissemination, potential public health impact, and requirement of special requirements containment (
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bt.cdc.gov/Agent/Agentlist.asp" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.bt.cdc.gov/Agent/Agentlist.asp</ext-link>).
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn3">
   <label>3</label>
   <p>With the exception of Lassa, which is endemic in a number of West African countries, VHF infections are rare. When outbreaks do occur, the virulence of these diseases inhibits widespread transmission, as the majority of sufferers die before they can infect others (M. Borchert, personal communication). Despite this epidemiological reality, social theorists have argued that these diseases are emblematic of the new and unruly connectivities (ranging from terrorism to economic crises) that shape national security concerns and prompt imperialistic approaches to global health (Clarke 
    <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Hinchliffe and Bingham 
    <xref rid="b55" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>).
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn4">
   <label>4</label>
   <p>In particular, our reflections stem from the ways in which the distribution of research was imagined by the collaboration: Theme one focused on the viral reservoirs of VHF; theme two, the practices and situations that might bring people into contact with those reservoirs; and theme three examined the human to human transmission of the virus. We were granted considerable freedom to describe the nature of an anthropological contribution, though there were some key objects (e.g., hunting practices, burial rituals) that were expected to seize our attention. This article takes both that empirical latitude and that collaborative spirit seriously by aiming to extend ethnographic engagement across the three themes.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn5">
   <label>5</label>
   <p>Thinness is a measure of interpretive depth and not empirical accuracy; a “thick” description elaborates the nuances of cultural meaning on a small scale; it “grows out of the delicacy of its distinctions not the sweep of its abstractions” (Geertz 
    <xref rid="b41" ref-type="bibr">1973</xref>:25).
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn6">
   <label>6</label>
   <p>This approach is characteristic of the One Health Agenda that seeks to “enhance cooperation and collaboration between physicians, veterinarians, other scientific health and environmental professionals” (
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.onehealthinitiative.com/about.php" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.onehealthinitiative.com/about.php</ext-link>).
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn7">
   <label>7</label>
   <p>This approach shares some concerns with Rappaport's work (e.g., 
    <xref rid="b104" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>) in anthropological ecology. However, where Rappaport argues for an expanded understanding of environment through his concept of human systems, our concern is with the particular way in which the social is conceptualized.
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn8">
   <label>8</label>
   <p>See CDC: 
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/ncidod/dvrd/spb/mnpages/dispages/lassaf.htm." xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.cdc.gov/ncidod/dvrd/spb/mnpages/dispages/lassaf.htm.</ext-link>
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn9">
   <label>9</label>
   <p>Airborne transmission has been observed in the lab, though not yet documented in a real-world setting (CDC 
    <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>).
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn10">
   <label>10</label>
   <p>Lassa fever can be treated with an intravenous administration of Ribavarin, but its success hinges on an early diagnosis, which, owing to varied symptoms and limited availability of reference laboratories in endemic countries, can be very difficult.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn11">
   <label>11</label>
   <p>For instance, armed conflict not only disrupts local networks of trade, but also allows greater access to weapons that can be used to hunt (de Merode et al. 
    <xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>); commercial logging has not only fragmented habitats, but also created the infrastructure to enable the transportation of meat over wide distances (Karesh and Noble 
    <xref rid="b62" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>).
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn12">
   <label>12</label>
   <p>In a slightly different vein, anthropologists have also explored the connections between hunting, display of animals, and conservation as deeply embedded in the colonial enterprise (Haraway 
    <xref rid="b48" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>; MacKenzie 
    <xref rid="b82" ref-type="bibr">1988</xref>).
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn13">
   <label>13</label>
   <p>For instance, the genetic sequencing of HIV strains suggest that the virus had been transmitted from primates to humans a number of times in the last century before the virus emerged globally (Karesh and Noble 
    <xref rid="b62" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>).
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn14">
   <label>14</label>
   <p>The importance of asymptotic infections resonates with Gonzales et al.'s 
    <xref rid="b45" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref> recuperation of Mirko Grmek's term “pathoecenosis” to capture the interactivity of infectious agents within a given territory across human and animal species (Grmek 
    <xref rid="b46" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>).
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn15">
   <label>15</label>
   <p>Lassa fever, endemic in parts of Sierra Leone, does not fully correspond to what (Leach and Dry 
    <xref rid="b74" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) have called the “outbreak narrative” characteristic of other VHFs like Ebola and Marburg. However, Lassa can produce epidemic exacerbations (often through hospital amplification), and involves the mobilization of new forms of hospital-based care (e.g., Donaldson 
    <xref rid="b25" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Further, like Ebola and Marburg, the virus is present in animal hosts and “jumps species” through particular kinds of human–animal interaction.
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn16">
   <label>16</label>
   <p>However, this literature has largely failed to engage with broader social science literature on rumor and medicine in Africa (e.g., Geissler 
    <xref rid="b43" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; White 
    <xref rid="b120" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>).
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn17">
   <label>17</label>
   <p>This research is often circumscribed to the locales where public health work takes place. For instance, Merlin, the U.K.'s leading international health charity and responsible for managing Lassa fever during the Sierra Leonean civil war (Kirkland 
    <xref rid="b67" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Merlin 
    <xref rid="b87" ref-type="bibr">2002a</xref>, 
    <xref rid="b88" ref-type="bibr">2002b</xref>, 
    <xref rid="b89" ref-type="bibr">2002c</xref>), produced detailed accounts of transmission drawn from their base of operations, the town of Kenema.
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="fn18">
   <label>18</label>
   <p>Fears that use of IV medications would increase the risk of transmission to health professionals discouraged the use of IV fluids in many VHF epidemics. However, the failure to provide treatment recognized as constituting good care became viewed in a number of settings as a policy of letting people die, with Ebola wards labeled as “death houses” in some contexts (M. Borchert, personal communication).</p>
  </fn>
 </fn-group>
</notes>
