<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Because of some possible technical errors, we had to adjust our data. Consequently, we were not able to estimate genetic differentiation, as our data adjustments cannot cope with functions such as, for example, the estimation of gene flow. When the data are adjusted for null alleles (alleles that do not amplify), multilocus estimates of gene flow are no longer possible because the different loci are now made independent. Instead we used so-called private alleles (i.e. alleles only found in one population; 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0030">30</xref>) assuming that there were a number of private alleles that did not amplify (null alleles). With help of GenePop and by using private alleles, we estimated the number of migrants per generation across all populations. The aim of estimating the gene flow with this method was to test if the observed amount of divergence was affected by gene flow or if it was what we could expect when no gene flow has occurred since separation. To implement this, we calculated expected 
 <italic>F</italic>
 <sub>ST</sub> by simulations using POWSIM with 
 <italic>N</italic>
 <sub>e</sub> values ranging from 100 to 10,000 and time since separation (
 <italic>t</italic>) ranging from 100 to 5000 generations and allele frequencies taken from the observed data. This will give us a range of expected 
 <italic>F</italic>
 <sub>ST</sub>-values for different combinations of 
 <italic>N</italic>
 <sub>e</sub> and 
 <italic>t</italic> (for results, see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0004">Fig. 4</xref>). Populations from Romania, Turkey, and France were excluded from this calculation since they probably belong to another group of Culex. To estimate 
 <italic>N</italic>
 <sub>e</sub>, we used the method of Xu and Fu 2004 (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0031">31</xref>) designed for highly variable markers such as microsatellites, where θ = 4 
 <italic>N</italic>
 <sub>e</sub>µ, and µ is the mutation rate. If the parameter values needed to get the observed 
 <italic>F</italic>
 <sub>ST</sub>-values are outside what is realistic in this system, we can reject the hypothesis of no gene flow between them.
</p>
