<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The accumulation of hepatic macrophages has been observed in the portal tracts of ALD patients. EVs stimulate the activation of macrophage activation and the induction of inflammatory cytokines, as demonstrated in an unbiased microarray-based antibody neutralization experiment [
 <xref rid="B92-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. Alcohol-exposed, monocyte-derived EVs activate naive monocytes to polarize M2 macrophages by increasing the expression of surface receptors CD68, CD206, and CD163, and the secretion of IL-10 and TGFβ, which elevates phagocytic activity [
 <xref rid="B89-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. Furthermore, the levels of CD40L-rich EVs were elevated in the sera of AH patients. The proteins detected within EVs during macrophage activation suggests that CD40L may stimulate the activation of macrophages in experimental alcoholic hepatitis models [
 <xref rid="B92-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. Chemotaxis is the initiating step in neutrophil recruitment, and requires chemokines such as IL-8, which is essential for neutrophil recruitment [
 <xref rid="B93-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. IL-8 levels are extremely elevated in both circulating and hepatic neutrophils, which are associated with alcoholic hepatitis and disease aggression [
 <xref rid="B94-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>,
 <xref rid="B95-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>,
 <xref rid="B96-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. CXCL1 is an IL-8 homologue that has been demonstrated to promote the recruitment of neutrophils in a mice model. Studies in a mouse model of ALD have shown that elevated levels of CXCL1 in the serum and hepatocytes exacerbate liver injury [
 <xref rid="B58-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B97-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. In endothelial cell-derived extracellular vesicles, ethanol stimulates the upregulation of lncRNAs HOTAIR and MALAT1, which facilitates the pro-angiogenic effects of endothelial-derived vesicles [
 <xref rid="B98-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. The alcoholic hepatitis-related liquid biomarkers are listed in 
 <xref rid="ijms-21-03732-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.
</p>
