<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<boxed-text id="b1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
 <label>Box</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Imprint-regulated effect of vaccine (I-REV)</title>
 </caption>
 <p>
  <bold>Supporting rationale:</bold>
 </p>
 <list list-type="bullet" id="L1">
  <list-item>
   <p>The first (priming) influenza virus infection in childhood imprints the immune system, leading to long-lived memory responses focused towards pivotal epitopes of the imprinting virus.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Most people have had a first influenza virus infection before the age of 4–5 years [
    <xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
    <xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Position 159 of the influenza A(H3) glycoprotein is a focal point for immune system interaction; position 193 may play an accessory role [
    <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Until about 30 years ago, for two decades following the 1968 pandemic, influenza A(H3N2) viruses bore S159; no glycosylation site shielded position 159 from the immune system during that period.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Contemporary 3C.2a viruses
    <sup>a</sup> possess Y159; however, position 159 is shielded from the immune system because of adjacent T160 glycosylation.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Contemporary 3C.2a vaccine strains
    <sup>b</sup> also possess Y159; however, position 159 is exposed to the immune system because of adjacent T160K loss of glycosylation following adaptation for egg-based manufacturing [
    <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Contemporary 3C.3a viruses possess S159; position 159 is also exposed to the immune system because clade 3C.3a viruses are naturally K160-non-glycosylated.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
 <p>
  <bold>I-REV hypothesis:</bold>
 </p>
 <list list-type="bullet" id="L2">
  <list-item>
   <p>Distant childhood priming and memory back-boosting of S159 responses following the 1968 pandemic conferred long-lasting immunity to imprinted cohorts, protecting unvaccinated adults aged 35–54 years in 2018/19 (birth cohorts 1964–83) from clade 3C.3a viruses that also bore S159.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Mismatched vaccination with egg-adapted 3C.2a antigen
    <sup>b</sup> instead bearing Y159 may have negatively interacted with imprinted immunity
    <sup>c</sup>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>The underlying immunological mechanisms for the I-REV hypothesis require further investigation.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
 <fn-group>
  <fn>
   <p>
    <sup>a</sup> Clade 3C.2a1b viruses in particular predominated during the 2018/19 influenza A(H3N2) epidemic.
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn>
   <p>
    <sup>b</sup> In addition to the 2018/19 clade 3C.2a1 vaccine, the egg-adapted 2016/17 and 2017/18 clade 3C.2a vaccine strains were also non-glycosylated at Y159 (bearing T160K) and also bore F193. Repeat vaccination effects may have played a role in I-REV.
   </p>
  </fn>
  <fn>
   <p>
    <sup>c</sup> Although not unique to adults older than 30 years, S193 imprinting may have played an accessory role. 
   </p>
  </fn>
 </fn-group>
</boxed-text>
