<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our findings that environmental factors were the most important determinants of geospatial heterogeneity is strengthened by the observation that all high HIV prevalence areas among young adults are in locations with known high levels of economic activity: characterised by high production and flow of goods and services [
 <xref rid="pmed.1003042.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="pmed.1003042.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. This suggests that high-risk dynamics (involving seasonal work and commercial sex) in these areas might be important in generating this heterogeneity [
 <xref rid="pmed.1003042.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="pmed.1003042.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. For instance, the fishing communities around Lake Victoria in Uganda (circle 1 in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed.1003042.g003">Fig 3</xref>) have frequently been reported as sites with high levels of transactional sex and HIV [
 <xref rid="pmed.1003042.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="pmed.1003042.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Furthermore, many high-prevalence areas in our analyses cluster around border crossings, major highways or major ports (e.g. circles 2 to 5 in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed.1003042.g003">Fig 3</xref>). Long distance truck driving and associated commercial sex have been documented as important contributors to HIV transmission [
 <xref rid="pmed.1003042.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="pmed.1003042.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. In addition, some of the high-prevalence areas are in regions known to have high levels of migration, either work-related (seasonal) migration or other types of migration. For example, the Copperbelt mining area (circle 7 in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed.1003042.g003">Fig 3</xref>) or Nchelenge district in Zambia (circle 8 in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed.1003042.g003">Fig 3</xref>) in Zambia, which is known for its active fishing industry and a big refugee settlement. Mining and fishing areas have long been recognised as high risk settings for HIV transmission, as domestic or foreign male workers often work long stints, separated from their families surrounded by an active sex industry [
 <xref rid="pmed.1003042.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>–
 <xref rid="pmed.1003042.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].
</p>
