<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0035">Viral nucleic acids can also be used for early diagnosis. The following are some of the new coronavirus detection methods. Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) is a molecular biological diagnosis technology based on the sequence of nucleic acids. The full gene sequence of 2019-nCoV has now been obtained [
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], so patients who are suspected of being infected with 2019-nCoV [
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] can be diagnosed by pan-coronavirus PCR for virus identification [
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) is a technology combining RNA reverse transcription (RT) with polymerase chain amplification (PCR) of cDNA. A duplex RT-PCR assay can be used to detect SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV using pUC57SARS-pS2 and pGEM-MERSS2 as templates, respectively [
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Also, samples collected from the upper respiratory tract (oropharyngeal and nasopharyngeal) and lower respiratory tract (endotracheal aspirate, expectorated sputum, or bronchoalveolar lavage) of suspected 2019-nCoV patients can be diagnosed by RT-PCR [
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Reverse transcription-insulated isothermal polymerase chain reaction (RT-iiPCR), quantitative real-time reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR), Real-time RT-PCR (rtRT-PCR), and one-step rtRT-PCR were all further optimized [
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>]. These optimized RT-PCR methods were used to detect the MERS-CoV envelope gene (upE) and the open reading frame 1a (ORF1a) or open reading frame 1b (ORF1b) genes separately. However, rtRT-PCR was used to identify 2019-nCoV through preliminary and validation detection of its E gene, RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp) gene, and N gene [
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].
</p>
