<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0045">Above mentioned studies clearly indicate that having Vit D deficiency predisposes sensitive population (elderly and individuals with underlying health conditions) to an attack by it’s own immune system and exacerbate the RTI by damaging the lung tissue. Therefore, in order to maintain an appropriate Vit D status and reduce the mortality, supplementation is needed to restore the Vit D levels reduced due to inadequate exposure to sunlight. There is currently no scientific consensus about the optimal dose of Vit D supplementation for COVID-19. Currently, The Institute of Medicine has placed the recommended dietary allowance, or RDA, for vitamin D at 600 international units (IU) per day for young adults and 800 IU per day for adults older than 70 years [
 <xref rid="bb0165" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. But this recommendation was issued in context with bone health. Based on observational studies, concentrations of atleast 40-50 ng/mL are desired [
 <xref rid="bb0170" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Another study reported that 38 ng/mL was suitable for reducing the risk of community acquired pneumonia [
 <xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. In order to achieve the above concentration range, dose of 2000-5000 IU/day of Vit D
 <sub>3</sub> could be taken [
 <xref rid="bb0180" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. A study reported increase in 25OHD concentrations from 20 ± 6 to 39 ± 9 ng/mL for 4000 IU/day and from 19 ± 4 to 67 ± 3 ng/mL for 10,000 IU/day for 8 weeks administration of Vit D [
 <xref rid="bb0185" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The U.S. Institute of Medicine noted that for daily doses of &lt; 10,000 IU/day no adverse effects have been reported for Vit D supplementaion. However, the value for upper limit (UL) was corrected to 4000 IU/day based on all-cause mortality and chronic disease outcomes [
 <xref rid="bb0165" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. So, we recommend that keeping daily dose of Vit D below 4000 IU/day could be beneficial in improving the immunity to combat COVID-19 infection more effectively.
</p>
