<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In contrast to their response to the 2002 SARS outbreak, China has shown immense political openness in reporting the COVID-19 outbreak promptly. They have also performed rapid sequencing of COVID-19 at multiple levels and shared the findings globally within days of identifying the novel virus (
 <xref rid="B225" ref-type="bibr">225</xref>). The move made by China opened a new chapter in global health security and diplomacy. Even though complete lockdown was declared following the COVID-19 outbreak in Wuhan, the large-scale movement of people has resulted in a radiating spread of infections in the surrounding provinces as well as to several other countries. Large-scale screening programs might help us to control the spread of this virus. However, this is both challenging as well as time-consuming due to the present extent of infection (
 <xref rid="B226" ref-type="bibr">226</xref>). The current scenario demands effective implementation of vigorous prevention and control strategies owing to the prospect of COVID-19 for nosocomial infections (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>). Follow-ups of infected patients by telephone on day 7 and day 14 are advised to avoid any further unintentional spread or nosocomial transmission (
 <xref rid="B312" ref-type="bibr">312</xref>). The availability of public data sets provided by independent analytical teams will act as robust evidence that would guide us in designing interventions against the COVID-19 outbreak. Newspaper reports and social media can be used to analyze and reconstruct the progression of an outbreak. They can help us to obtain detailed patient-level data in the early stages of an outbreak (
 <xref rid="B227" ref-type="bibr">227</xref>). Immediate travel restrictions imposed by several countries might have contributed significantly to preventing the spread of SARS-CoV-2 globally (
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B228" ref-type="bibr">228</xref>). Following the outbreak, a temporary ban was imposed on the wildlife trade, keeping in mind the possible role played by wild animal species in the origin of SARS-CoV-2/COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="B147" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>). Making a permanent and bold decision on the trade of wild animal species is necessary to prevent the possibility of virus spread and initiation of an outbreak due to zoonotic spillover (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>).
</p>
