<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In normal physiology, the endogenous pro-coagulant and anti-coagulant pathways are interwoven with multiple regulatory interactions that promote hemostasis (stopping bleeding) while minimizing thrombosis (pathological clotting). NFTs exert their hemostatic effect by circumventing these regulatory interactions in order to therapeutically “rebalance” the coagulation cascade to account for the underlying bleeding disorder 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>
 </sup>. However, the new balance provided by NFTs between hemostasis and thrombosis is likely not as stable as occurs in normal physiology or with targeted factor replacement. This instability is illustrated by the observation that five of the 18 patients on emicizumab prophylaxis who experienced breakthrough bleeding and required management with aPCCs developed thrombotic complications 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>
 </sup>. aPCC is a concentrate of plasma-derived zymogen and activated coagulation factors that has been used for more than four decades to treat bleeding in inhibitor patients 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, 
  <xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>
 </sup>. Thrombotic complications are rare (&lt;10 per 100,000 infusions) but are a well-recognized risk, especially when combined with other hemostatic therapies such as rFVIIa 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, 
  <xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>
 </sup>. It is, therefore, not surprising that the thrombotic complications with emicizumab also occurred when emicizumab was combined with one or more additional bypassing agents. Nevertheless, the increased susceptibility of subjects receiving emicizumab and aPCC to thrombosis suggests a synergistic interplay 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>– 
  <xref rid="ref-74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>
 </sup>. aPCC contains FIXa 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>
 </sup>, whose enzymatic activity is enhanced 20,000-fold by emicizumab 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>
 </sup> in a biochemically unregulated manner. Emicizumab, unlike FVIII, does not require activation to exert its pro-hemostatic effect, which has been suggested to result in an earlier acceleration of coagulation 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>
 </sup>. As such, there is a biochemical rationale why the concomitant use of emicizumab and aPCC may be especially prothrombotic 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>
 </sup>. These thrombotic complications all occurred in emicizumab prophylaxis subjects who received &gt;100 units/kg/day of aPCC, which is within the typical dosing recommendations of aPCC (&lt;200 units/kg/day). As FIX and FX provided by aPCC have half-lives of 18 and 40 hours, respectively, the potential for accumulation due to multiple administrations raises safety concerns. To date, the risk-mitigation strategy of limiting aPCC doses below this threshold has been successful, and emicizumab was recently approved by the FDA for HA patients with inhibitors.
</p>
