<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the space of just six weeks, a new coronavirus, from a family that his torically was not viewed as a global health concern, has become daily headline news around the globe. The 21st century marked its arrival with the emergence of three previously unknown coronaviruses. SARS‐CoV (severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus) was recognized in November 2002,
 <xref rid="ijcp13488-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijcp13488-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2</xref> MERS‐CoV (Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus) in June 2012,
 <xref rid="ijcp13488-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijcp13488-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">4</xref> and 2019‐nCoV in December 2019.
 <xref rid="ijcp13488-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">5</xref> Previously, human coronaviruses, known since the 1960s, were viewed as being only marginally relevant to the clinic, except for infants, the elderly, and immunocompromised individuals.
 <xref rid="ijcp13488-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijcp13488-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijcp13488-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">7</xref> What these, and several other recent outbreaks have in common, is how fast they circled the world. Outbreaks that centuries ago needed weeks or months to spread globally can today reach any continent within days.
 <xref rid="ijcp13488-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">8</xref> The first, spring wave of the 1918 Spanish Flu, at a time when travel by ship was the fastest way of transportation around the world, spread through the United States, Europe, and possibly Asia over six months.
 <xref rid="ijcp13488-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijcp13488-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref> The pandemic affected over a quarter of the world's population, caused 50‐100 million deaths, more than the two World Wars combined, and caused life expectancy at birth in the United States to drop by 11.8 years between 1917 and 1918.
 <xref rid="ijcp13488-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijcp13488-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ijcp13488-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">12</xref> In comparison, in 2002‐2003 the SARS‐CoV spread to 5 countries within 24 hours,
 <xref rid="ijcp13488-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">13</xref> and in 2009 the H1N1 influenza virus spread to 30 countries within 6 weeks.
 <xref rid="ijcp13488-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">14</xref>
</p>
