<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Coagulopathies are also a prominent aspect of severe Covid‐19 patients. Thus, anticoagulant treatments may decrease mortality (Kollias et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>; Tang et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0076" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>) in an ACE/ACE2 dependent and sex‐related way (Gemmati et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). While waiting for vaccines and new therapeutic strategies to fight this terrible pandemic, different antiviral options are under clinical trial as combination therapies. These include hydroxylchloroquine alone or in combination with 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/LigandDisplayForward?ligandId=6510" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">azithromycin</ext-link>, and remdesivir, as well as 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/LigandDisplayForward?ligandId=9502" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">lopinavir</ext-link>/
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/LigandDisplayForward?ligandId=8804" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">ritonavir</ext-link> alone or with 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/LigandDisplayForward?ligandId=4955" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">interferon</ext-link> (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> identifier: NCT04332094, NCT04332107, NCT04322123, NCT04335552, NCT04336332, and NCT04339816). To the best of our knowledge, none of these studies considered different therapeutic approaches for men and women. Moreover, for many of these drugs, the effects on ACE/ACE2 ratio are unknown. Even in vaccination, sex is a variable that should be considered. Indeed, pathogen‐specific and non‐specific effects of vaccines present differences between sexes that can be exploited in fighting COVID‐19 (Aaby et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Of note, the antibody response to vaccinations is actually thought to be greater in women than men, and possibly, this might underlie future protection. However, women display more adverse events than men following vaccinations (Fischinger, Boudreau, Butler, Streeck, &amp; Alter, 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>).
</p>
