<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine are widely used for the treatment of malaria and certain autoimmune diseases. These drugs have an established safety profile and are readily available at relatively low cost. Hydroxychloroquine sulphate has been demonstrated to be less toxic than chloroquine phosphate in animal studies.
 <xref rid="b68-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">68</xref> Both these drugs have been reported to have antiviral effects against SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 
 <italic>in vitro.</italic> Their potential mechanisms of action include blocking viral entry into cells by inhibiting glycosylation of host receptors, reducing viral replication, and blocking the export of newly constructed virions.
 <xref rid="b45-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="b69-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">69</xref> A trial in China involving more than 100 patients with Covid-19 showed that chloroquine was better able to inhibit exacerbation of pneumonia and improve lung imaging findings compared to the control treatment.
 <xref rid="b70-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">70</xref> A recent small open-label nonrandomised clinical trial showed patients given daily hydroxychloroquine had significantly reduced viral load measured by nasopharyngeal swab on day 6.
 <xref rid="b5-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> However, the results in this study may have been confounded by other factors, as some patients also received azithromycin.
 <xref rid="b71-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">71</xref> The combination of hydroxychloroquine and azithromycin should be used with caution in patients at risk for QT prolongation. The use of chloroquine alone is also a risk factor for QT prolongation. A phase IIb clinical trial assessing the safety and efficacy of high-dose chloroquine was terminated early due to prolonged QTc (&gt;500 ms) and high lethality in the high-dose group compared to the low-dose group.
 <xref rid="b72-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">72</xref> A recent analysis of a multinational registry of 96,032 hospitalised COVID-19 patients revealed that hydroxychloroquine or chloroquine was associated with decreased in-hospital survival (mortality of 11.1 
 <italic>versus</italic> 9.3%) and increased frequency of ventricular arrhythmia.
 <xref rid="b73-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">73</xref> However, concerns have been raised about the veracity of data and analyses in this study and has led to retraction of the article.
 <xref rid="b74-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">74</xref> Other adverse effects of chloroquine include retinopathy, rash, nausea, glucose fluctuation and diarrhoea, and use of chloroquine is contraindicated in patients with porphyria. Chloroquine or hydroxychloroquine should not be used to treat COVID-19 until they have been tested in clinical trials to determine the optimal dosage to balance efficacy and safety. Chloroquine or hydroxychloroquine has been suggested as candidate prophylactics for COVID-19 in populations at high risk of COVID-19 infections, such as Italy and New York.
 <xref rid="b75-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>
</p>
