<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Avian influenza A (H5N1) and (H7N9) viruses occasionally cross species barrier to infect humans, causing severe respiratory disease and posing pandemic threats. In 1997, human infection with H5N1 virus in Hong Kong caused 6 deaths out of 18 infected individuals presented with viral pneumonia, acute respiratory distress syndrome and multiple organ failure [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008611.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1008611.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Since then, H5N1 has become a global epidemic with a case mortality of 55%, although the transmission route is restricted to avian-to-human contact [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008611.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In 2013, another novel avian subtype H7N9 emerged in humans in mainland China, presented with similar severe disease with 40% case mortality [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008611.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1008611.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. At least four later H7N9 epidemics following the first wave in 2013 were recorded in mainland China from 2014 to 2017 with expanded geographical distribution and genetic diversity [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008611.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Although no evidence supports human-to-human transmission [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008611.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], studies using ferret model suggested H7N9 transmissibility between ferrets through respiratory droplets [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008611.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. This is alarming and the pandemic potential of H7N9 and similar avian viruses in humans should not be underestimated. It remains elusive as to why H5N1 and H7N9 viruses are highly pathogenic in humans, but a robust innate immune response including a cytokine storm [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008611.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1008611.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], in which proinflammatory cytokines such as tumor necrosis factor (TNF) α are induced to very high levels for a long period of time [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008611.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], is thought to play an important role. Understanding the virulence factors of H5N1 and H7N9 viruses and how they dysregulate innate immunity might hold the key to the development of specific and effective therapeutics.
</p>
