<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Natural HLA class I ligands have mostly 9–11 residues long and display the canonical anchor residues (usually at position 2 and the C-terminus of the peptide ligand) for specific MHC binding (SYFPEITHI database [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]). These canonical peptides include the CHIKV CP
 <sub>17-25</sub> epitope restricted by HLA-B*07:02 and 68 of the 69 VACV HLA class I ligands identified in the current report (Tables 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.t001" ref-type="table">1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.t002" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Two exceptions were found: the CHIKV E1
 <sub>1-16</sub> ligand identified both JY and HOM-2 cells, and the VACV D12
 <sub>99-111</sub> ligand from HOM-2 cell line with 16 and 13 amino acid long, respectively. The existence of these viral ligands, with bioinfomatically predicted 9 or 10 canonical cores for binding to their respective HLA class I molecules, and N- and/or C-terminally extended residues that probably protruded out of the corresponding HLA class I binding groove as described in other non-canonical HLA class I ligands [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], can be explained for absence of the peptidase trimming. Usually, long peptides generated by proteasome and other cytosolic proteases are trimmed by ERAP1 and/or ERAP2 aminopeptidases in the ER to 9–11 mer ligands [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. ERAP1 binds long substrates for both terminal residues, where the lateral chain of the C-terminus residue interacts with a hydrophobic pocket away from the active site. Thus, the N-terminal residue is accessible to the active site and then, this enzyme trims the longer precursors in a nonprocessive manner: the "molecular ruler" mechanism [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. The presence of basic residues in the C-terminus of peptide substrate prevents their interaction with ERAP1, and thus, removal of N-terminal residues is abolished [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. In both CHIKV E1
 <sub>1-16</sub> and VACV D12
 <sub>99-111</sub> ligands the C-terminal residue is a Lys and thus, these long peptides are protected from ERAP1 activity. In contrast, this hydrophobic pocket is absent in the ERAP2 protease and thus, the C-terminal residue of substrate is not relevant for the activity of this proteinase [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Nevertheless, the high preference of ERAP2 for some amino acids in the N-terminal position, among which the Val and the Tyr amino acids are not included [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], would explain the presence of CHIKV E1
 <sub>1-16</sub> and VACV D12
 <sub>99-111</sub> ligands in virus infected cells. In addition, this absence of aminopeptidase trimming over these two long viral ligands would allow the formation of five different HLA-peptide complexes in the cell surface of infected cells, if the theoretical binding prediction by bioinformatics tools showed in Tables 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.t001" ref-type="table">1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.t002" ref-type="table">2</xref> is accurate. In contrast, if these long ligands would have been substrates of ERAP1 and/or ERAP2 proteases, the resulting 9-11mer products of trimming could only have bound to HLA-A*03:01 molecules since the anchor motifs at position P2 for HLA-C*01:02 and -C*07:02 would lack the binding. Thus, absence of aminopeptidase activities could, in some cases, increase the repertoire of HLA class I-peptide complexes exposed to T cell recognition in the surface of the infected cell. These data reinforce the need to identify the natural ligands versus other experimental strategies as is the analysis with synthetic peptides.
</p>
