<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The different HLA class I and II molecules analyzed in this study are very common in the different human ethnic groups. For example, HLA-A2 is the human MHC with higher allelic frequency in human population. This allele together with the other HLA class I and II molecules from the two human cell lines analyzed here represent about half of the human population [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>], indicating that the data obtained in this study may have great relevance in the study of both CHIKV infection and in the context of the poxvirus-based vaccines that are currently being developed against this emerging pathogen [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. In addition the current report is also relevant about the nature of HLA class II response. So far, it is a common assumption that HLA-DP is less important in the immune response than other HLA class II molecules as -DR or even -DQ proteins, because their lower cell surface expression level [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. However, although for example more than ten thousand T cell epitopes restricted by HLA-DR class II molecules have been reported (Immuno Epitope Database, IEDB; 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iedb.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.iedb.org/</ext-link>), a growing body of literature indicates that HLA-DP encodes fully functional molecules, restricting epitope responses in the context of cancer, allergy, and, of course, infectious diseases. Thus, more than a hundred of viral ligands or epitopes restricted by HLA-DP class II molecules have been collected in the IEDB database in the last years. In addition, as a presenting molecule, HLA-DP shows two very interesting features: first, its limited polymorphism regarding HLA-DR locus and second, the existence of a DP supertype that include &gt;90% of the human population [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], where about the three quarters of peptide repertoires are common to four or five HLA-DP class II molecules included in this supertype [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. In the current report, one and seven CHKV HLA-DR ligands from JY and HOM-2 cells were identified, respectively. In addition, other three CHIKV peptides from HOM-2 cells were also identified as HLA-DPB1*04:01-restricted ligands, allele included in the HLA-DP supertype. Thus, in the antigen presentation by HLA class II of some viral proteins, similar number of HLA-DP vs -DR ligands can be obtained despite the higher cell surface expression of HLA-DR molecules than HLA-DP proteins [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007547.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>].
</p>
