<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para650">The PERCH study results can be compared with other childhood pneumonia aetiology studies.
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref> The multisite BOSTID study
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref> from the 1980s, an important historical reference, detected viruses and bacteria from upper respiratory specimens and bacterial antigens from urine specimens and found high prevalence of RSV, 
 <italic>S pneumoniae</italic>, and Hib. The PERCH study differed substantially from BOSTID in study design through the inclusion of controls, in strict standardisation of case definitions and methods, and in the breadth and types of laboratory testing. The multicountry GABRIEL pneumonia case-control aetiology study,
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>65</sup>
 </xref> done in low-income settings and published in 2017, also highlighted RSV as a major causative pathogen. However, the aetiological attribution for RSV was substantially lower in the GABRIEL study than in the PERCH study (18% 
 <italic>vs</italic> 31%).
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>65</sup>
 </xref> This discordance appears mainly attributable to differences in the prevalence of RSV in GABRIEL (20% of cases) compared with that in the PERCH study (29% of cases), rather than a result of different analytical approaches. Study design and methodological differences probably affected the rate of RSV detection; specifically, the age distribution of cases enrolled in GABRIEL was older than that of cases in PERCH, and GABRIEL controls were enrolled from facilities, rather than from the community. Although 
 <italic>S pneumoniae</italic> detection in NP specimens in cases was similar between the two studies (68% in GABRIEL 
 <italic>vs</italic> 73% in PERCH [any detection]), the control prevalence was considerably lower in GABRIEL (48% 
 <italic>vs</italic> 77%), resulting in a high OR and attributable fraction in the GABRIEL study. The difference in pneumococcal findings between the PERCH and GABRIEL studies is unlikely to lie in the case definitions used, which were similar between studies. Instead, notable differences existed in PCV use (nearly absent in GABRIEL, but widely used in PERCH) and in control eligibility (facility-based recruitment and no respiratory symptoms in GABRIEL 
 <italic>vs</italic> community controls regardless of respiratory symptoms, if not case-defining, in PERCH). Additionally, the proportion of cases and controls who had detection of both viruses and bacteria was substantially higher in PERCH (83·5% cases and 75·8% of controls had mixed bacterial-viral detection) than in GABRIEL (59·6% cases and 36·1% controls), suggesting that other differences in the selection of participants or in clinical or laboratory methods might have also contributed. In the EPIC study
 <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>38</sup>
 </xref> of childhood pneumonia aetiology from the USA, RSV and human rhinovirus were the most commonly detected pathogens from the upper respiratory tract among young children hospitalised with radiographic pneumonia, and a larger proportion of children had no pathogen detected compared with that of PERCH (18·9% in EPIC 
 <italic>vs</italic> 0·9% in PERCH). In the South African Drakenstein case-control substudy
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>29</sup>
 </xref> of pneumonia aetiology (using the same multiplex PCR assay as PERCH), cases were predominantly children with non-severe pneumonia, managed in outpatient settings, and with a median age of 5 months. Nevertheless, a range of pathogens similar to that of the PERCH study was associated with pneumonia case status, but the prevalence of influenza was higher. Unlike the PERCH study of severe pneumonia with hospital admission, the Drakenstein substudy found that cytomegalovirus, bocavirus, and adenovirus were associated with case status.
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>29</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
