<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Electrospraying has been studied extensively in biomedical research for its ability to form droplets containing sensitive biological material such as cells and to produce drug-loaded particles with a narrow size distribution [
 <xref rid="B20-pharmaceutics-12-00388" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-pharmaceutics-12-00388" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In 2003, core-shell structures were obtained by coaxially aligning two capillaries in an electrospraying system [
 <xref rid="B22-pharmaceutics-12-00388" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Since then, coaxial electrospraying has demonstrated successful encapsulation and controlled release of proteins that retain high levels of bioactivity after processing [
 <xref rid="B23-pharmaceutics-12-00388" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. However, whilst it is known that electrospraying can be used with proteins and cells with little or no effect on bioactivity, there has been very limited investigation of its use with viruses [
 <xref rid="B23-pharmaceutics-12-00388" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-pharmaceutics-12-00388" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Electric fields of the magnitude required for electrospraying (typically kV) could potentially affect viral viability through reactive oxygen species (ROS) generation and/or irreversible electroporation. In a standard electrospraying setup in which corona discharge and dielectric breakdowns are avoided, ROS, specifically ozone and hydrogen peroxide, are generated in vanishingly small quantities [
 <xref rid="B25-pharmaceutics-12-00388" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Even so, biomolecules that are especially susceptible to oxidation and are electrosprayed in solution at sub mg/mL concentrations can undergo substantial denaturation via heavy metal-catalysed oxidation [
 <xref rid="B25-pharmaceutics-12-00388" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Similarly, the electric field may itself damage the virus. To the best of the authors’ knowledge, the first report of inactivating microorganisms, namely bacteria, with strong electric fields dates back to 1967 [
 <xref rid="B26-pharmaceutics-12-00388" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The mechanism of inactivation was more fully understood later as irreversible electroporation, wherein a membrane acting like a capacitor becomes charged and induces a permeabilizing transmembrane potential that either increases osmotic potential to the point of lysis or ruptures the membrane outright [
 <xref rid="B27-pharmaceutics-12-00388" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The membrane radius is an important factor, as the magnitude of the transmembrane potential increases with the radius at a constant field strength [
 <xref rid="B28-pharmaceutics-12-00388" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Moreover, it is important to consider the ability of the material being encapsulated to respond to changes in the microenvironment. For instance, cells can have complex membrane machinery in the form of protein ion pumps that allows for the active regulation of ion balance and eukaryotic cells employ rGSH to alleviate oxidative stress [
 <xref rid="B29-pharmaceutics-12-00388" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Viruses generally lack the capacity to respond to osmotic and oxidative stress with the same sophistication. 
</p>
