<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ppat.1008103.s004">
 <label>S4 Fig</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Survivorship curves for uninfected WT and TADV-A mosquitoes and for DENV-infected WT, 
   <italic>w</italic>Mel, and TADV-A mosquitoes.
  </title>
  <p>The x-axis indicates the number of days elapsed after the start of the experiment, and the y-axis indicates the percent of mosquitoes surviving on each elapsed day. (
   <bold>A</bold>) For the uninfected panel, where the survivorship curves for WT and TADV-A male and female mosquitoes are shown separately, each line represents the accumulated results of 120–180 adult mosquitoes combined from 3 biological replicates. Significant differences in survivorship were observed between WT and TADV-A females, with WT females surviving, on average, 4.5 days longer (
   <italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.01). (
   <bold>B</bold>) For the infected panels, WT, 
   <italic>w</italic>Mel, and TADV-A females were given a blood meal infected with DENV-1, DENV-2, DENV-3, or DENV-4 (as indicated on respective plot titles). The survivorship of infected mosquitoes was determined over the course of 14 days (the time it takes for the virus to disseminate past the midgut and eventually become transmissible). No significant differences in survivorship were found between WT and TADV-A mosquitoes when infected with DENV-3 and DENV-4, but significant differences were observed upon infection with DENV-1, with more WT mosquitoes (80%) surviving at 14 dpi than TADV-A mosquitoes (~40%; 
   <italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.01). When infected with DENV-2, more 
   <italic>w</italic>Mel mosquitoes (&gt;90%) survived at 14 dpi compared to WT and TADV-A mosquitoes (both ~70%; 
   <italic>p &lt;</italic> 0.0001). The Mantel-Cox test was used to determine statistical significance. *
   <italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.01, ***
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001.
  </p>
  <p>(TIF)</p>
 </caption>
 <media xlink:href="ppat.1008103.s004.tif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <caption>
   <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
  </caption>
 </media>
</supplementary-material>
