<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Patrolling monocytes and tissue‐resident macrophages are part of the first line of defense upon viral infection. These specialized phagocytic cells play the role of first responders against a wide range of pathogens and, upon activation, release immune modulators such as TNFα, IL‐1β, and IL‐6 which trigger localized inflammation.
 <xref rid="imr12825-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">33</xref> Macrophages and monocytes are one of the first immune subsets identified in the synovial tissue cellular infiltrate of CHIKV‐infected patients.
 <xref rid="imr12825-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="imr12825-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">34</xref> In line with this observation, mouse studies of CHIKV and RRV suggested that the monocytes/macrophages subset represents an important fraction of the cellular infiltrate in mouse swollen joints.
 <xref rid="imr12825-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="imr12825-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="imr12825-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="imr12825-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">37</xref> One of the first clues on the functional role of macrophages in CHIKV‐induced inflammation was reported by Rulli et al.
 <xref rid="imr12825-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">38</xref> In this study, treatment with Bindarit, an anti‐inflammatory small molecule that modulates the NFκB pathway and inhibits, among others, the synthesis of monocyte chemotactic protein (MCP)‐1,
 <xref rid="imr12825-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">39</xref> ameliorated CHIKV‐induced joint swelling in mice. In a parallel study, targeted depletion of macrophages by clodronate liposomes treatment in CHIKV‐infected mice yielded a similar outcome.
 <xref rid="imr12825-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">13</xref> Although these results indicate that monocytes and macrophages might contribute to the CHIKV inflammatory pathology, a separate study suggested that infection in mice deficient of CCR2, a receptor involved in monocyte chemotaxis, resulted in aggravated and prolonged swelling manifestation due to an increased and persistent neutrophil infiltration.
 <xref rid="imr12825-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">40</xref> Taken together, these observations suggest a model in which monocytes and macrophages could act as a double‐edged sword by mediating localized inflammation while restricting excessive infiltration of neutrophils in infected joints.
 <xref rid="imr12825-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">41</xref>
</p>
