<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par44">As a consequence, the exploitation of Internet data as a source to characterize epidemiological patterns for communicable and non-communicable diseases has been promoted since the mid-90’s under the concept of digital epidemiology [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. These efforts have focused on leveraging freely available information from Twitter, Google, Wikipedia, among others, to follow traces of disease patterns in the population [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Following the pioneering work of Eysenbach G. on using web-based search queries to track influenza [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] and other efforts that used Google-derived data for influenza in the United States [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] and dengue in different countries [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], Google developed Google Flu Trends (GFT) in 2009 and Google Dengue Trends (GDT) in 2011, as specific disease surveillance tools for digital epidemiology. However, a close examination of the predicting power of these algorithms, specifically GFT, showed signs of over and under prediction and low performance [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] cautioning against the broader implementation and applicability of these tools. As a consequence, both GFT and GDT were shut down in 2015 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Nevertheless, two portals remained open to harvest search queries from Google, Google Trends (GT, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://trends.google.com/trends/?geo=US" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://trends.google.com/trends/?geo=US</ext-link>), and Google Health Trends (GHT). GT was released in 2006 as a free and publicly available source, whereas GHT, although free, it requires access through an application private interface (API, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.google.org/flutrends/about/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.google.org/flutrends/about/</ext-link>). Many researchers have continued using Google-derived data to assess epidemiological patterns and inform epidemiological models for different pathogens with encouraging or conflicting results [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>].
</p>
