<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A number of results from this model are consistent with what has been predicted with previously published rotavirus transmission models; high rotavirus vaccine coverage (&gt;85%) resulted in reductions of annual severe RVGE incidence by 56% [
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], 70% [
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and 84% [
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] for children under 5 years of age, compared to pre-vaccination levels in different model studies. One modeling study for Germany [
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] predicted no rotavirus biennial epidemic patterns even after high national rotavirus vaccine coverage (90%). However, other models had different predicted effects on rotavirus epidemic patterns after high national rotavirus vaccine coverage (90%) [
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. These models predicted biennial epidemic patterns in medium vaccine coverage (70%) and elimination of rotavirus at 90% coverage, whereas other models predicted potential biennial epidemic patterns with 90% vaccine coverage. Differences in the assumptions and parameters of these models may explain the different predictions for epidemic patterns. For example, in our model we assumed vaccines and natural infection induce partial immunity (i.e. subsequent infection can still occur but at reduced rate) and a long duration of immunity. Another modeling study that predicted high vaccine coverage with biennial patterns assumed one-year duration of complete immunity after previous infection, then, individuals were assumed to be susceptible to infection again with partial immunity [
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Moreover, our model fit to data from the U.S. whereas other rotavirus models were fit to rotavirus data from England and Wales. Differences in demographic conditions between the U.S. and England and Wales may also partly explain the differences in these results.
</p>
