<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although some historians consider the first influenza pandemic to have occurred earlier [frequently mentioned candidates include the European epidemics of 927, 1173 and 1386–1387
 <xref rid="b5" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="b45" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>45</sup>
 </xref>], there is little doubt that the three pandemics of the 16th century, occurring in 1510, 1557, and 1580, ushered in a major influenza pandemic era (
 <xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). Although several writers commented non‐specifically about ill animals,
 <xref rid="b43" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>43</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="b47" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>47</sup>
 </xref> to our knowledge none of them reported specific influenza‐like illnesses in large domestic animals. A curious footnote was however recorded by Daniel Sennert (1572–1637), the physician who first scientifically described scarlet fever, in noting that: “…names applied to [the 1580 pandemic disease] included febrile catarrh, suffocating fever, epidemic catarrh, coughing epidemic, [and] contagious headache. The Germans called [it] ‘the chirp’, the sheep cough, the sheep disease, [and] the chicken malady, because sick persons were suffering [as with] the coryza of chickens” [(
 <xref rid="b48" ref-type="ref">48</xref>); 
 <xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>]. The identity of the disease causing “chicken coryza” noted in 1580 is not known, although the same term had been used at the time of the 1557 pandemic, possibly in referring to croup‐like respiratory signs in children.
 <xref rid="b49" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>49</sup>
 </xref> Neither HPAI nor Newcastle disease was recognized until more than 300 years later. We are unaware of other reports of similar avian illnesses in the voluminous literature on the 1580 pandemic which, however, has rarely been examined systematically, and never to our knowledge for evidence of animal disease.
</p>
