<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, 24 near-complete genomes were generated from SAV3-positive samples, more than doubling the publicly available genome sequences of Norwegian SAV. We show that SAV3, similar to other alphaviruses (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Tan et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Ling et al., 2019</xref>), evolves relatively slowly in comparison to many RNA viruses with an estimated evolutionary rate of 7.351 × 10
 <sup>–5</sup> substitutions per site per year. This substitution rate is similar to previous whole genome estimates but slower than reported for shorter fragments of the genome (e.g., E2) (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Karlsen et al., 2014</xref>). However, sufficient genetic variation exists within Norwegian SAV3 strains to make genome sequences informative for fine-scale reconstructions of SAV evolution and phylogeographic patterns. Additionally, the temporal signal of SAV3 determined by a TempEst analysis showed strong clock-like signal, and thus further supports the use of genomic sequences in epidemiological studies. The contemporary SAV3 sequences sampled in 2016–2019 were distributed into five distinct clades that were estimated to have had a common ancestor 15 years ago, likely in Hordaland (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). These five clades were all represented in a relatively limited geographical area of Western Norway during the same timeframe. The clades did not show any clear, long-term geographical pattern within Western Norway, and sequences from Sogn og Fjordane and Rogaland all shared a common ancestor with sequences from Hordaland, which was less than 8 years old, again likely in Hordaland (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>; indicated by the green node). This is much more recent than the first reports of SAV3 in these counties and suggests repeated reintroductions to these areas; our phylogeographic analysis suggested that a Hordaland reservoir was the more likely source. Furthermore, we could not find evidence for long-term (&gt;10 years) persistence of local SAV3 reservoirs in Sogn og Fjordane and Rogaland, suggesting that local epidemics (i.e., outbreaks of related strains that have persisted in a geographic region for longer than any individual cohort of salmon is out to sea) eventually burn out in these areas. While the presence of defective viruses may affect the infection dynamics of individual fish due to strong antiviral responses (see below), the accumulation of defective viral genomes is unlikely to affect epidemic dynamics. A more likely explanation to these apparent local epidemic burn outs is that the density of hosts in “sink” regions (i.e., Rogaland and Sogn og Fjordane) is too low to support long-term SAV3 epidemics. However, it is possible that older SAV3 strains still persist in these sink regions, though no evidence of this was detected in this study.
</p>
