<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We demonstrated the ability of a phylogeny-based analysis pipeline to correctly infer transmission relationships and infection dates from routinely collected low resolution Sanger derived HIV consensus sequences of HIV infected individuals, as well as an ability to identify novel unsuspected transmission clusters. The transmission-optimized parameter combination (adjusted BEAST2 and adjusted TransPhylo) was able to recover on average, 48.56% of clinically reported person-to-person transmission relationships with a high of 63.89% and a low of 33.33% at a 95% confidence interval. Despite the presence of pol sequences from other randomly selected SAC patients and without pinpointing infection dates accurately, the pipeline still identified the direction of transmission in a majority of verifiable relationships. Of note, 22.2% of the verifiable P2P instances still involved the correct pair of patients, but just had the wrong direction of transmission. The correct patient pair was identified by genetic similarity, but the within-patient evolution model predicted an erroneously earlier infection date for the secondary (recipient) patient. Our pipeline uses solely Sanger sequenced data of one HIV region (
 <italic>pol</italic>) and less computational intense approaches. Despite this, it performs quite close to the more expensive NGS based prediction pipelines combined with extensive mathematical models and more complete HIV genome sequences [
 <xref rid="B31-microorganisms-08-00196" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. It should also be noted that we used what we called a “gold standard dataset”, which was confirmed by thorough and extensive public health tracing and followed up by the Southern Alberta Clinic, whereas some other work on assessments of prediction accuracy did not have access to similar thorough “gold standard” datasets [
 <xref rid="B31-microorganisms-08-00196" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. As a follow up, integrating within-host HIV diversity in the models [
 <xref rid="B46-microorganisms-08-00196" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] as well as extending to sequences beyond the HIV polymerase region will allow for further fine tuning of the pipeline, and increase its predictive power. With these additions, the pipeline will be able to be used in low resource settings. We also encourage researchers to perform these analyses in their settings with readily available data sets to examine how well the pipeline can be applied to different settings and recapitulate the HIV infection dynamics.
</p>
