<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0002">At the time of the severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS)-associated coronavirus epidemic 
 <xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> in 2003, several molecules were tested to assess their effectiveness against this virus. Among these, teicoplanin 
 <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, an antistaphylococcal agent, had proven efficacy 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>, and this was also the case for chloroquine, at a 50% effective concentration (EC
 <sub>50</sub>) of approximatively 8 µM, and when added to the cell culture either before of after exposure to the virus 
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[5</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. These findings ended up being forgotten because of the disappearance of SARS for reasons that are neither clear nor explained 
 <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. The novel coronavirus currently isolated in China has been, with staggering speed, evaluated regarding its sensitivity to already used drugs 
 <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Thus, the new antiviral drug remdesivir 
 <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref> as well as chloroquine, at an EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 1.1 µM, were found to be effective in preventing replication of this virus 
 <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Chloroquine is perhaps one of the most prescribed drugs in the world 
 <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">[14</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">15]</xref>. As a matter of fact, all Europeans visiting malaria-endemic geographic areas for decades received chloroquine prophylaxis and continued it for 2 months after their return. In addition, local residents took chloroquine continuously, and treatment of malaria has long been based on this drug. In addition, hydroxychloroquine has been used for decades at much higher doses (up to 600 mg/day) to treat autoimmune diseases 
 <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. It is difficult to find a product that currently has a better established safety profile than chloroquine. Furthermore, its cost is negligible. Hence, its possible use both in prophylaxis in people exposed to the novel coronavirus and as a curative treatment will probably be promptly evaluated by our Chinese colleagues. If clinical data confirm the biological results, the novel coronavirus-associated disease will have become one of the simplest and cheapest to treat and prevent among infectious respiratory diseases.
</p>
