<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Coronaviruses are a large group of viruses that causes respiratory and enteric infections in both animals and humans. The virions are large in size (100–160 nm), spherical in shape and have an envelope. There is a capsid of 27–32 kb, which contained a single-stranded RNA genome with positive polarity protected by the envelope [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Coronaviruses contain four types of spikes; many long (20 nm) glycoprotein S-spikes in all the coronaviruses, small hemagglutinin-esterase (HE) spikes in some viruses, few transmembrane glycoproteins and envelope protein spikes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The Coronaviruses can be classified into three serogroups on the basis of their genome structure. Serogroups 1 and 2 viruses can infect mammalian and seven of them (229E-CoV, NL63-CoV, OC43-CoV, HKU1-CoV, SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV and, COVID-19) can infect man while serogroups 3 contains avian viruses only. The 229E-CoV, NL63-CoV, OC43-CoV, HKU1-CoV are responsible for 30% or more mild upper respiratory tract illnesses in human, while SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV and, COVID-19 are well known for serious humans infection. Recently, adapted animal coronaviruses causes a more fatal infection in humans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. The majority of coronavirus are species-specific. They can expand their genetic diversity by nurturing recombination and mutation during peridomestic animal infections and sometimes a virus can jump a species barrier and start an infection in humans also [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. The COVID-19 may be animal originated virus as majorities of its initial cases were associated with local fish and wild animal market of Wuhan, China. Some early local studies suggested the possibility of human-to-human transmission via droplets or direct contact and nosocomial infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. The incidences of COVID-19 infections are rapidly increasing, due to transmission from symptomatic/asymptomatic carriers, high mobility rate and rapid expansion through the world travel system. High transmission power and considerable mortality rate are responsible for the high potential of COVID-19 to become a pandemic agent [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. In India, the majority of COVID-19 cases have travel history in the infected parts or close contact with an infected person, community transmission is doubtful till now. 
</p>
