<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Standard Enzyme Linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA) was performed for detection of antigen-specific Abs in sera. 96-Well MaxiSorp
 <sup>TM</sup> Nunc Immuno plates (Nalgene Nunc International, Naperville, IL, USA) or Ni-NTA HisSorb plates (QIAGEN, GmbH, QIAGEN, Hilden, Germany) were coated with whole PR8 virus particles, M2e or chimeric HA protein (cH9/1) at a concentration of 2 µg/mL (100 μL per well). Plates were then treated with or without 0.2% of formaldehyde. Coated plates were blocked with PBS containing 0.1% Tween-20 (
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>) (TPBS) with 3% Bovine Serum Albumin (BSA). Each serum sample was pre-diluted 1:100 and serially diluted 1:5 in blocking buffer, and then adsorbed onto plates for 2 h. The bound immunoglobulins were detected with goat anti-mouse Ig (H+L) horseradish peroxidase-conjugated Abs, goat anti-mouse IgG, goat anti-mouse IgG1, goat anti-mouse IgG2A, goat anti-mouse IgG2B, and goat anti-mouse IgA (Southern Biotechnologies Associates, Inc., Birmingham, AL, USA) diluted 1:400 or 1:5000, respectively. As controls, the assays included mAbs 6F12, PY102, and 7B2 diluted to 2µg/mL and anti-M2 Ab diluted 1:1000. After the final wash step, tetramethylbenzidine (TMB) substrate was added and the reaction was stopped with an equal volume of 1M sulfuric acid. Absorbance was measured in a SPECTRAmax photometer (Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, CA, USA) at 450 nm. Assay results were expressed as end-point titration values that were determined by the last dilution above the cutoff for the assay (Optical density (OD) 450 nm reaches plateau). To examine the effect of formaldehyde treatment on binding of epitope-specific mAbs, a modified ELISA was setup with influenza-virus-infected MDCK cells. Briefly, 1.5 × 10
 <sup>4</sup> MDCK cells were added to each well of 96-well MaxiSorp Nunc Immuno plates (Nalgene Nunc International, Naperville, IL, USA) and incubated for 4 h at 37 °C, 5% CO
 <sub>2</sub>. The cells were then infected with 100 TCID
 <sub>50</sub> of PR8 virus overnight. The plates were washed and fixed with 80% cold acetone in PBS and then treated with or without 0.2% formaldehyde. Binding of anti-NP or M2e-specific mAb (Millipore) was detected with goat anti-mouse IgG horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated Ab (BD) diluted 1:1000. The reactions were developed by addition of tetramethylbenzidine (TMB) substrate was and then stopped by addition of an equal volume of 1 M sulfuric acid. Absorbance was measured in a SPECTRAmax photometer at 450 nm. Secondary HRP Ab alone was used as a negative control.
</p>
