<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Experimental studies of other bat derived viruses and their non-bat hosts have been used to try to tease apart spillover transmission mechanisms. Horses can be infected with HeV through intranasal infection, suggesting inhalation may be a potential route of infection [
 <xref rid="B141-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">141</xref>], but epidemiological studies of human filovirus infection suggest more close contact is required for human transmission. Pigs, hypothesized to have been infected with NiV following ingestion of excreta contaminated/partially eaten fruit, have been shown experimentally to be susceptible to infection following ingestion of NiV, with nasopharyngeal shedding [
 <xref rid="B142-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>]. Following the discovery of swine as a potential host for 
 <italic>Reston ebolavirus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B39-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], pigs have been used as experimental models. The significance of pigs in filovirus transmission has been discussed elsewhere [
 <xref rid="B143-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>,
 <xref rid="B144-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>], however, experimental studies have shown that 
 <italic>Zaire ebolavirus</italic> can be transmitted from pigs to cynomolgus macaques without direct contact [
 <xref rid="B145-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>]. The mechanism(s) of transmission to primates, which are epidemiologically linked to several filovirus outbreaks and are severely affected by infection, remain unknown. Again, these studies are useful for understanding whether transmission to target, novel hosts is possible, but do not necessarily elucidate the mechanisms for transmission of filoviruses between putative reservoir bat hosts or bats and non-bat species. Studies of transmission mechanisms between and from bats to target species, such as pigs and primates, are a priority for experimental studies. The examples from other systems, in particular the henipaviruses HeV and NiV, suggest that similar studies could be used to identify potential transmission pathways (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-06-01759-f001">Figure 1</xref>). While there are many inherent difficulties with performing such studies for filoviruses, including extensive field situations, BSL-4 level facilities, and ethical issues, these experiments could greatly improve our understanding of filovirus ecology.
</p>
