<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0075">Concerning HBV, different theories were proposed to explain its origin, but all of them have some sort of limitation. HBV was initially thought to have emerged quite recently in the New World from genotypes F/H infecting Amerindians 
 <xref rid="b0240" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref> (
 <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>A and B). However, the discovery of an ancient strain in a 16th century Asian mummy, as well as the worldwide diffusion of hepadnaviruses in NHPs, questioned this hypothesis 
 <xref rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref> (
 <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>A). An alternative theory suggests that HBV followed the Out-of-Africa migration of modern humans, which occurred approximately 60,000 years ago 
 <xref rid="b0255" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0260" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0265" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. In particular, Paraskevis et al. found a good correspondence between the demographic histories of HBV and those of human populations 
 <xref rid="b0265" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. These authors also showed that the substantial divergence of the F and H genotypes (
 <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>A), a major evidence in favor of the New World origin hypothesis 
 <xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>, was probably due to positive selection acting on those branches 
 <xref rid="b0270" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>. Nonetheless, the extensive application of ancient DNA sequencing revealed a more complex scenario. In fact, two European Neolithic HBV genomes did not cluster with any extant human strain in the phylogenetic tree, but did cluster with NHP viruses 
 <xref rid="b0275" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref> (
 <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>A). Other authors 
 <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, who sequenced 12 ancient HBV genomes of different ages (800–4500 years old), obtained a similar result, with the ancient strains clustering with known modern genotypes or forming new clades (
 <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>A). This implies that some HBV lineages of the past went extinct (
 <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>A). Moreover, Muhlemann and coworkers showed that the geographic distribution of ancient samples does not match the modern genotype distribution 
 <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. They thus suggested that early evolutionary scenarios can be concealed and overwritten by more recent migratory events 
 <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>.
</p>
