<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Epidemiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Am. J. Epidemiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">aje</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>American Journal of Epidemiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0002-9262</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1476-6256</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5860156</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28641373</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwx251</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">kwx251</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Systematic Reviews, Meta- and Pooled Analyses</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Estimating Influenza Vaccine Effectiveness With the Test-Negative Design Using Alternative Control Groups: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Shuo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cowling</surname><given-names>Benjamin J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="kwx251cor1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><!--<email>bcowling@hku.hk</email>--></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>Heath</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>Sheena G</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0004">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0005">5</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>WHO Collaborating Center for Infectious Disease Epidemiology and Control, School of Public Health, Li Ka Shing Faculty of Medicine, University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong Special Administrative Region, China</aff><aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label>National Center for Epidemiology and Population Health, Australian National University, Canberra, Australian Capital Territory, Australia</aff><aff id="AF0003"><label>3</label>WHO Collaborating Center for Reference and Research on Influenza at the Peter Doherty Institute for Infection and Immunity, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia</aff><aff id="AF0004"><label>4</label>Department of Epidemiology, Fielding School of Public Health, University of California, Los Angeles, Los Angeles, California</aff><aff id="AF0005"><label>5</label>Centre for Epidemiology and Biostatistics, School of Population and Global Health, University of Melbourne, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia </aff><author-notes><corresp id="kwx251cor1">Correspondence to Dr. Benjamin J. Cowling, WHO Collaborating Center for Infectious Disease Epidemiology and Control, School of Public Health, Li Ka Shing Faculty of Medicine, University of Hong Kong, 21 Sassoon Road, Pokfulam, Hong Kong Special Administrative Region, China (e-mail: <email>bcowling@hku.hk</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2017-06-21"><day>21</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>01</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 12 months and
						0 days and was based on the <pub-date
						pub-type="ppub"/>. --><volume>187</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>397</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>07</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2017. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health. All rights reserved. For permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oup.com.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="kwx251.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>One important assumption in case-control studies is that control selection should be independent of exposure. Nevertheless, it has been hypothesized that virus interference might lead to a correlation between receipt of influenza vaccination and increased risk of infection with other respiratory viruses. We investigated whether such a phenomenon might affect a study design commonly used to estimate influenza vaccine effectiveness (VE). We searched publications in MEDLINE, PubMed, and Web of Science. We identified 12 studies using the test-negative design (2011&#x02013;2017) that reported VE estimates separately derived by 3 alternative control groups: 1) all patients testing negative for influenza (FLU), VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;</sub>; 2) patients who tested positive for other/another respiratory virus (ORV), VE<sub>ORV+</sub>; and 3) patients who tested negative for all viruses in the panel (PAN), VE<sub>PAN&#x02212;</sub>. These included VE estimates from 7 countries for all age groups from 2003/2004 to 2013/2014. We observed no difference in vaccination coverage between the ORV-positive and PAN-negative control groups. A total of 63 VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;</sub> estimates, 62 VE<sub>ORV+</sub> estimates, and 33 VE<sub>PAN&#x02212;</sub> estimates were extracted. Pooled estimates of the difference in VE (&#x00394;VE) were very similar between groups. In meta-regression, no association was found between the selection of control group and VE estimates. In conclusion, we did not find any differences in VE estimates based on the choice of control group.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>epidemiologic methods</kwd><kwd>influenza</kwd><kwd>test-negative design</kwd><kwd>vaccine effectiveness</kwd><kwd>virus interference</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">National Institutes of Health</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/100000002</named-content><?release-delay 12|0?></funding-source></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">National Institute of General Medical Sciences</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/100000057</named-content><?release-delay 12|0?></funding-source></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Harvard Center for Communicable Disease Dynamics</named-content><?release-delay 12|0?></funding-source><award-id>U54 GM088558</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Areas of Excellence Scheme</named-content><?release-delay 12|0?></funding-source></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">University Grants Committee of Hong Kong</named-content><?release-delay 12|0?></funding-source><award-id>AoE/M-12/06</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Health and Medical Research Fund</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/501100005847</named-content><?release-delay 12|0?></funding-source></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Government of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/501100005407</named-content><?release-delay 12|0?></funding-source></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Australian Government Department of Health</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/501100003921</named-content><?release-delay 12|0?></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>Influenza vaccines are the most effective measure available for reducing the substantial annual disease burden associated with <italic>Influenzavirus</italic> infections. Influenza vaccines generally have moderate-to-good efficacy, estimated to fall within the range of 60%&#x02013;70% in children and 50%&#x02013;60% in adults based on randomized controlled trials (<xref rid="kwx251C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). However, influenza vaccine efficacy and vaccine effectiveness (VE) can vary from year to year depending on the degree of antigenic match between strains selected for inclusion in the vaccine and circulating strains, as well as the intervals between vaccination and influenza epidemics (<xref rid="kwx251C3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). VE can also vary among subpopulations&#x02014;persons of different ages, for example (<xref rid="kwx251C4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). These factors may affect both experimental and observational study designs. Thus, annual estimates of influenza VE can provide ongoing evidence on the performance of influenza vaccines in the community.</p><p>Although randomized controlled trials are considered the gold standard for measuring vaccine efficacy, for the purpose of making annual VE estimates, observational studies are carried out more commonly because of feasibility, efficiency, and ethics. The test-negative design (TND) has been widely applied for measuring influenza VE on a routine basis in Europe, North America, Australia, and Asia since 2005 (<xref rid="kwx251C6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). In this study design, patients with signs and symptoms meeting predefined clinical definitions (e.g., acute respiratory infection or influenza-like illness) are swabbed and tested for influenza viruses. In some cases, testing may be done against a panel of respiratory viruses. Persons testing positive are defined as cases, while those testing negative for influenza viruses (influenza (FLU)-negative) are classified as controls. Persons who test negative may test positive for another respiratory virus (other/another respiratory virus (ORV)-positive) or may test negative for all viruses in the panel (panel (PAN)-negative). VE is estimated as VE% = 1 &#x02212; OR<sub>adj</sub>, where OR<sub>adj</sub> is the odds ratio comparing the odds of vaccination among cases with the odds of vaccination among the controls, adjusted for potential confounders such as age. This design can be embedded within existing surveillance systems to enable timely estimation of VE in both inpatient and outpatient settings at a reasonable cost (<xref rid="kwx251C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p><p>Although the number of studies using the TND has been increasing, the theoretical underpinnings and inherent assumptions of the TND need further evaluation (<xref rid="kwx251C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). As a type of case-control study, the TND should follow the basic principles of control selection: 1) controls should be selected from the same population as cases and 2) controls should be selected independently of exposure, within each stratum of factors included in stratified analysis (<xref rid="kwx251C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). By restricting cases and controls attending outpatient clinics or hospitals to the same clinical case definition (e.g., influenza-like illness (<xref rid="kwx251C9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>)), the TND includes controls from the same source population as cases, and thus reduces bias from differential health-care-seeking behavior.</p><p>However, TND studies conducted in inpatient settings could be complicated by acute exacerbation of chronic respiratory conditions, which could be difficult to distinguish from respiratory virus infections requiring hospitalization. Furthermore, if this population were more likely to receive influenza vaccination than the source population, selection bias would be introduced. Nevertheless, in a meta-analysis comparing inpatient and outpatient VE, Feng et al. (<xref rid="kwx251C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) observed similar VE estimates by setting when the analysis was restricted to the same season, country, and age group. In a simulation study examining the validity of the TND for inpatient settings, Foppa et al. (<xref rid="kwx251C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) concluded that VE estimates would be biased if chronic respiratory conditions were not well-controlled in the analysis. Under this assumption, vaccination coverage and VE estimates might differ according to different control groups; that is, higher vaccination coverage, and thus higher VE estimates, would be observed with the use of PAN-negative controls.</p><p>An assumption of case-control studies is that control selection should be independent of exposure. For influenza VE studies, this assumption may be violated if the risk of infection with a noninfluenza virus is not independent of vaccination status (<xref rid="kwx251C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). In a randomized controlled trial, Cowling et al. (<xref rid="kwx251C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) observed increased risk of ORV infection among 2008&#x02013;2009 trivalent influenza vaccination recipients. Several epidemiologic studies have observed &#x0201c;viral interference,&#x0201d; a phenomenon in which infection by one virus alters susceptibility to infection by another virus. This has been reported, for example, for influenzavirus and rhinovirus (<xref rid="kwx251C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) and influenzavirus and respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) (<xref rid="kwx251C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p><p>The purported underlying mechanism behind these phenomena might involve both nonspecific immunity and influenzavirus-specific immunity (<xref rid="kwx251C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). After a viral infection, temporary nonspecific immunity against a second infection is induced, which could last for several weeks (<xref rid="kwx251C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Given its brief duration, investigators might be unlikely to observe a population or cohort effect. In contrast, the influenzavirus-specific interference may involve T-cell-mediated immunity, which may last for months because of broad heterotypic cross-reactivity. The immune response might vary across different influenza strains and could possibly be more evident during an influenza pandemic wherein specific influenza strains predominate during the season (<xref rid="kwx251C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Although the nonspecific and specific immunity against influenza and other infectious diseases has been broadly described, the potential nature and biological mechanisms of virus interference remain unclear (<xref rid="kwx251C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>).</p><p>For the TND, virus interference may be important if, by preventing influenza infection through vaccination, nonspecific and influenzavirus-specific immunity is not induced and leaves the vaccinee susceptible to infection by cocirculating viruses he or she might otherwise have been protected from. This would result in higher influenza vaccination coverage among controls with ORVs detected than in controls with no virus detected. Therefore, selection of controls could then lead to biased estimation of VE; that is, the VE estimates derived using the ORV-positive group would be higher than those for the PAN-negative group and the FLU-negative group. Simulation studies have suggested that while this phenomenon can produce biased estimates, that bias is trivial except under extreme conditions (<xref rid="kwx251C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). However, simulations are often simplistic representations of real studies and may not be able to capture the nuances of immunological phenomena. For example, immunological responses may be less apparent in the elderly than in children or young adults, possibly because of immunosenescence (<xref rid="kwx251C23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Thus, any evaluation of the potential bias caused by virus interference should consider the age of the population.</p><p>In this review, we aimed to assess whether virus interference could affect VE estimates generated from studies using the TND. First, we compared vaccination coverage using alternative control groups. Second, we compared VE estimates according to the choice of control group. Third, we summarized the total difference in VE estimates and assessed deviations from zero. Finally, we assessed whether any differences in VE were equally apparent among all age groups and in different study settings.</p><sec sec-type="methods" id="kwx251s2"><title>METHODS</title><sec id="kwx251s2a"><title>Study search and selection</title><p>We previously reviewed TND studies that estimated influenza VE (<xref rid="kwx251C6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). For the current review, we reassessed all papers derived from our previous searches (last performed on December 28, 2015 (<xref rid="kwx251C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>)) and conducted an online update on April 18, 2017. Following the previous search strategies, papers were searched on PubMed (National Library of Medicine, Bethesda, Maryland), MEDLINE (National Library of Medicine), and Web of Science (Clarivate Analytics, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania) for the following combination of keywords: 1) &#x0201c;influenza&#x0201d; <italic>or</italic> &#x0201c;flu&#x0201d;; 2) &#x0201c;vaccine effectiveness&#x0201d; <italic>or</italic> &#x0201c;VE&#x0201d;; 3) &#x0201c;test-negative&#x0201d; <italic>or</italic> &#x0201c;test negative&#x0201d; <italic>or</italic> &#x0201c;case-control&#x0201d; <italic>or</italic> &#x0201c;case control&#x0201d;; and 4) sets 1, 2, <italic>and</italic> 3. Articles were independently screened by 2 of the authors (S.F. and S.G.S.). Studies estimating influenza VE for any season, any influenza type/subtype, or any type of influenza vaccination by VE were considered. Only articles published in English were considered. Studies or subanalyses of studies which reanalyzed previously published data, reported interim estimates, or did not use the TND were excluded. All studies meeting these inclusion criteria were further screened and were included if influenza VE was estimated using alternative control groups, including FLU-negative, ORV-positive, and/or PAN-negative controls.</p><p>Study design information was extracted for each included study using a standardized form. This included: author, publication year, study country, influenza season, population ages, study setting, surveillance system, case definition, time intervals since symptom onset, type of swab, laboratory methods, ORVs tested, vaccination coverage in each control group, covariates included in statistical models, and all VE estimates using alternative control groups.</p></sec><sec id="kwx251s2b"><title>Assessment of potential influence of virus interference</title><p>Differences in influenza vaccination coverage and estimates of VE against influenza A or B according to alternative control groups were compared by paired <italic>t</italic> test. Adjusted VE estimates obtained using all available control groups were extracted, including the FLU-negative group (denoted VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;</sub>), the ORV-positive group (denoted VE<sub>ORV+</sub>), and the PAN-negative group (denoted VE<sub>PAN&#x02212;</sub>). Stratified VE estimates were also extracted by influenza type/subtype for each age group, influenza season, and setting (inpatient or outpatient). For each study, the differences in available VE estimates (&#x00394;VE) were defined as:
<disp-formula id="kwx251M1"><mml:math id="kwx251DmEq1"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">VE</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">FLU</mml:mi><mml:mo form="prefix">&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mo form="prefix">,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">ORV</mml:mi><mml:mo form="prefix">+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">VE</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">FLU</mml:mi><mml:mo form="prefix">&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">VE</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">ORV</mml:mi><mml:mo form="prefix">+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="kwx251M2"><mml:math id="kwx251DmEq2"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">VE</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">FLU</mml:mi><mml:mo form="prefix">&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mo form="prefix">,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">PAN</mml:mi><mml:mo form="prefix">&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">VE</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">FLU</mml:mi><mml:mo form="prefix">&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">VE</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">PAN</mml:mi><mml:mo form="prefix">&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="kwx251M3"><mml:math id="kwx251DmEq3"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">VE</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">ORV</mml:mi><mml:mo form="prefix">+</mml:mo><mml:mo form="prefix">,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">PAN</mml:mi><mml:mo form="prefix">&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">VE</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">ORV</mml:mi><mml:mo form="prefix">+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">VE</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">PAN</mml:mi><mml:mo form="prefix">&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>We calculated 95% confidence intervals for each &#x00394;VE by bootstrap, using 1,000 resamples (see the Web Appendix, available at <uri xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/aje">https://academic.oup.com/aje</uri>). We excluded studies with large uncertainty, as defined by a 95% confidence interval range for VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;</sub> of more than 100 percentage points. The remaining studies were pooled, and estimates of &#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;,ORV+</sub>, &#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;,PAN&#x02212;</sub>, and &#x00394;VE<sub>ORV+,PAN&#x02212;</sub> against influenza A or B were calculated. Where studies provided both overall estimates and estimates for subgroups, we removed the overall estimate to avoid any overlap. We performed Egger&#x02019;s test on &#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;,ORV+</sub> and its standard error to assess publication bias. A fixed-effects model was assumed, and heterogeneity was examined by means of the <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> statistic and Cochran&#x02019;s <italic>Q</italic> test. The inverse of the variance of &#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;,ORV+</sub> was used to weight the studies.</p><p>To test our hypothesis that virus interference may vary by age, we further estimated &#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;,ORV+</sub> by age group&#x02014;that is, children (ages 6 months&#x02013;17 years), young adults (ages 18&#x02013;49 years), and older adults (ages &#x02265;50 years). Since inpatient studies may be biased due to recruitment of patients with chronic respiratory disease rather than viral infection, we also examined &#x00394;VE by setting, whenever possible. We evaluated whether pooled &#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;,ORV+</sub> differed from zero among children or young adults more than among elderly adults. To further examine whether any study design feature was associated with VE estimates, we also conducted meta-regression by means of univariate and multivariate random-effects models. The predictors included age group (children, adults, elderly, and all ages), study setting (inpatient/outpatient/mixed), season (single/multiple), restriction of patients to those presenting for health care within 4 days (yes/no), exclusive use of polymerase chain reaction (PCR)/reverse transcription PCR for testing (yes/no), number of ORVs tested, and type of control group (FLU-negative, ORV-positive, or PAN-negative). All analyses were conducted using R, version 3.3.1 (R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria) and the <italic>metafor</italic> package.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="kwx251s3"><title>RESULTS</title><p>A total of 120 publications were retrieved from the previous study (<xref rid="kwx251C6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), and 35 articles were obtained from the new search. Based on 155 test-negative studies, 12 articles that met the inclusion criteria were identified (<xref rid="kwx251C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="kwx251C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="kwx251F1">1</xref>). Two studies reported estimates from the same population (<xref rid="kwx251C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Kelly et al. (<xref rid="kwx251C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) estimated VE for children recruited from both a hospital emergency department (ED) and general practices in 2008, with estimates reported separately by setting; Blyth et al. (<xref rid="kwx251C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) conducted analysis for children recruited from the same ED from 2008 to 2012. To avoid this overlap, the ED results reported by Kelly et al. were excluded.
</p><fig id="kwx251F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Identification of eligible studies that used the test-negative design (TND) to estimate influenza vaccine effectiveness (VE) by means of alternative control groups. FLU, influenza; ORV, other/another respiratory virus; PAN, panel.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kwx251f01"/></fig><p>The first study estimating VE using alternative control groups was a 2011 study from Australia (<xref rid="kwx251C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Study characteristics are summarized in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="kwx251TB1">1</xref>. The studies covered the 2003/2004 to 2013/2014 influenza seasons and 7 countries, including Australia (4 studies (<xref rid="kwx251C27" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C27" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C27" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>)), the United States (3 studies (<xref rid="kwx251C3" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C27" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C27" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>)), Japan (1 study (<xref rid="kwx251C1" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>)), China (Hong Kong; 1 study (<xref rid="kwx251C1" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>)), Portugal (1 study (<xref rid="kwx251C1" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>)), New Zealand (1 study (<xref rid="kwx251C1" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>)), and the Netherlands (1 study (<xref rid="kwx251C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>)) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="kwx251TB1">1</xref>). Five studies reported estimates for a single year (<xref rid="kwx251C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="kwx251C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), while others reported estimates across multiple years (<xref rid="kwx251C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="kwx251C26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Among 7 studies reporting pooled estimates across more than 1 year/season, 3 studies also provided season-specific estimates (<xref rid="kwx251C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>).
<table-wrap id="kwx251TB1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Design Features of 12 Studies Selected to Analyze Whether Virus Interference Can Affect Vaccine Effectiveness Estimates Generated From Test-Negative Designs, 2011&#x02013;2017</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First Author, Year (Reference No.)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Season</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age Group</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Setting</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Case Definition</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Interval Since Symptom Onset, days</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of Swab</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Laboratory Method(s)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other Respiratory Viruses Tested</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blyth, 2014 (<xref rid="kwx251C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>)<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008&#x02013;2012<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#x02013;59 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ILI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR, VC, IF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RSV, PIV 1&#x02013;4, hMPV, RV, AdV (B&#x02013;D), CoV, BoV, EV</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cowling, 2014 (<xref rid="kwx251C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">China (Hong Kong)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009&#x02013;2013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months&#x02013;17 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IF, VC, RT-PCR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RSV, PIV 1&#x02013;3, AdV</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feng, 2017 (<xref rid="kwx251C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010&#x02013;2013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NP, OP, nasal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RT-PCR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RSV, PIV 1&#x02013;3, hMPV, RV, AdV</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grijalva, 2015 (<xref rid="kwx251C26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010&#x02013;2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospital admission with pneumonia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NP, OP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RT-PCR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RSV, PIV 1&#x02013;3, hMPV, RV, CoV</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kelly, 2011 (<xref rid="kwx251C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>)<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#x02013;59 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient (general practice and emergency department)<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ILI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nasal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VC, RT-PCR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RSV, PIV 1&#x02013;3, hMPV, RV, EV</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Levy, 2014 (<xref rid="kwx251C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010&#x02013;2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ILI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nasal, throat</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VC, PCR, RT-PCR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RSV, PIV 1&#x02013;3, hMPV, RV, AdV, EV</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nunes, 2014 (<xref rid="kwx251C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Portugal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012&#x02013;2013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ILI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NP, OP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VC, RT-PCR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RSV, PIV 1&#x02013;3, hMPV, RV, AdV</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pierse, 2016 (<xref rid="kwx251C30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">New Zealand</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient and outpatient<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SARI/ILI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NP, throat</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RT-PCR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RSV, PIV 1&#x02013;3, hMPV, RV, AdV</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sullivan, 2014 (<xref rid="kwx251C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ILI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nasal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RT-PCR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RSV, PIV 1&#x02013;3, hMPV, AdV, EV</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sundaram, 2013 (<xref rid="kwx251C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">United States</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2004/2005&#x02013;2009/2010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months&#x02013;5 years, &#x02265;50 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient, urgent-care departments, and acute-care hospitals</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;10 and &#x02264;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nasal, NP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RT-PCR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RSV, PIV 1&#x02013;4, hMPV, RV, AdV, CoV</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suzuki, 2014 (<xref rid="kwx251C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Japan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011&#x02013;2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;10 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ILI + RIDT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCRs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RSV, PIV 1&#x02013;4, hMPV, RV, AdV, CoV, BoV</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">van Doorn, 2017 (<xref rid="kwx251C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">The Netherlands</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2003&#x02013;2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARI or ILI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nasal, throat</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RT-PCR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RSV, RV, EV (varied by season: PIV 1&#x02013;4, hMPV, CoV, ADV)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="kwx251tfn1"><p>Abbreviations: AdV, adenovirus; ARI, acute respiratory infection; BoV, bocavirus; CoV, coronavirus; EV, enterovirus; hMPV, human metapneumovirus; IF, immunofluorescence; ILI, influenza-like illness; N/A, not applicable; NP, nasopharyngeal; OP, oropharyngeal; PCR, polymerase chain reaction; PIV, parainfluenza virus; RIDT, rapid influenza diagnostic test; RSV, respiratory syncytial virus; RT-PCR, reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction; RV, rhinovirus; SARI, severe acute respiratory infection; VC, viral culture.</p></fn><fn id="kwx251tfn2"><p><sup>a</sup> Results reported by Kelly et al. (<xref rid="kwx251C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) for children presenting to an emergency department in 2008 were removed from further analysis.</p></fn><fn id="kwx251tfn3"><p><sup>b</sup> Data for 2009 were not included.</p></fn><fn id="kwx251tfn4"><p><sup>c</sup> Separate estimates are provided for each setting.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Patients of all ages were investigated in 7 studies (<xref rid="kwx251C26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="kwx251C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C35" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>), children in 4 studies (<xref rid="kwx251C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), and children, adults, and elderly persons in 2 studies (<xref rid="kwx251C30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Eight studies were carried out exclusively in outpatient settings (<xref rid="kwx251C35" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="kwx251C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="kwx251C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>), including 1 in an ED (<xref rid="kwx251C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>); 2 were carried out in inpatient settings (<xref rid="kwx251C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>); 1 used both inpatients and outpatients, with estimates broken down by setting (<xref rid="kwx251C30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>); and 1 recruited outpatients (including ED patients), urgent-care patients, and acute-care patients (<xref rid="kwx251C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Various case definitions were identified. Some studies used an influenza-like illness definition (<italic>n</italic> = 6 studies), others an acute respiratory infection definition (<italic>n</italic> = 3); one used either an influenza-like illness or acute respiratory infection definition, while another required hospitalized pneumonia (<italic>n</italic> = 1); and 1 Japanese study required use of rapid influenza detection tests. The case definitions used are summarized in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Web Table 1</xref>. All studies included fever or history of fever in the clinical case definition, with the exception of 1 study which enrolled hospitalized pneumonia patients (<xref rid="kwx251C26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Various restrictions were applied to the inclusion of patients based on the interval between symptom onset and clinical presentation, including presentation within 4 days, 7 days, and 10 days; 2 studies did not specify such a restriction (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="kwx251TB1">1</xref>).</p><p>All studies estimated VE using both FLU-negative and ORV-positive controls. Seven also reported VE estimates obtained using PAN-negative controls (<xref rid="kwx251C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="kwx251C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). All studies performed PCR/reverse transcription PCR for influenza diagnosis among all patients or in a subset of patients. Some studies also used immunofluorescence and/or virus culture (<xref rid="kwx251C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="kwx251TB1">1</xref>). The number of ORVs included in the respiratory panels ranged from 3 to 8. All included studies tested for RSV. Other commonly included viruses were human metapneumovirus (<italic>n</italic> = 9 studies), adenovirus (<italic>n</italic> = 8), and rhinovirus (<italic>n</italic> = 9) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="kwx251TB1">1</xref>). Only 2 studies reported the number of specimens testing positive for each ORV tested (<xref rid="kwx251C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="kwx251C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). In these 2 studies, the most commonly detected ORVs were RSV and rhinovirus, accounting for 66.5% (<xref rid="kwx251C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>) and 73.1% (<xref rid="kwx251C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) of total ORVs detected, respectively. There was a weak negative correlation between the number of ORVs included in the panel and the proportion of patients identified as PAN-negative (<italic>r</italic> = &#x02013;0.37), but this was not statistically significant (<italic>P</italic> = 0.13). The proportion of controls identified as PAN-negative was lowest among children: 17.3% in 1 US study (<xref rid="kwx251C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), 26.8% in 1 Australian study conducted in an ED (<xref rid="kwx251C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>), and 21.3% from another Australian study conducted in an outpatient setting (<xref rid="kwx251C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="kwx251TB2">2</xref>). The proportion of patients testing positive for ORVs in the FLU-negative group ranged from 13.5% among people aged &#x02265;10 years in Japan (<xref rid="kwx251C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) to 80.2% among children aged 6&#x02013;59 months in the United States (<xref rid="kwx251C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). The interquartile range was 27.5%&#x02013;45.5% for all studies (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="kwx251TB2">2</xref>).
<table-wrap id="kwx251TB2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Vaccination Coverage Estimated Using Alternative Influenza-Negative Control Groups, 2011&#x02013;2017</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" align="center" colspan="1">First Author, Year (Reference No.)</th><th rowspan="3" align="center" colspan="1">Setting</th><th rowspan="3" align="center" colspan="1">Age Group</th><th rowspan="3" align="center" colspan="1">Season</th><th align="center" colspan="9" rowspan="1">Type of Control Group</th><th rowspan="3" align="center" colspan="1">Difference (ORV+, PAN&#x02212;), %<sup>a</sup></th><th rowspan="3" align="center" colspan="1">PAN&#x02212;, %<sup>b</sup></th><th rowspan="3" align="center" colspan="1">ORV+/FLU&#x02212;, %<sup>c</sup></th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">FLU-Negative</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">ORV-Positive</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">PAN-Negative</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of Persons Vaccinated</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total No.</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Vaccinated</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of Persons Vaccinated</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total No.</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Vaccinated</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of Persons Vaccinated</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total No.</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Vaccinated</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blyth, 2014 (<xref rid="kwx251C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02013;59 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008&#x02013;2012<sup>d</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,200</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">794</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">406</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feng, 2017 (<xref rid="kwx251C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010&#x02013;2011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">957</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,784</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">422</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,176</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">528</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,591</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feng, 2017 (<xref rid="kwx251C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011&#x02013;2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">721</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,692</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">343</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">701</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">375</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">984</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feng, 2017 (<xref rid="kwx251C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012&#x02013;2013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">907</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,430</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">379</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">958</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">526</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,461</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kelly, 2011 (<xref rid="kwx251C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02013;59 months</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Levy, 2014 (<xref rid="kwx251C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">302</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">213</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Levy, 2014 (<xref rid="kwx251C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">246</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;9.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Levy, 2014 (<xref rid="kwx251C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">177</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">758</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">191</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">137</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">567</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;3.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nunes, 2014 (<xref rid="kwx251C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012&#x02013;2013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">183</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pierse, 2016 (<xref rid="kwx251C30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">677</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">299</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">378</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sullivan, 2014 (<xref rid="kwx251C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">218</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">821</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">313</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">141</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">508</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;3.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sundaram, 2013 (<xref rid="kwx251C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient, UCDs, and ACHs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months&#x02013;5 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2004/2005&#x02013;2009/2010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,759</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">782</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,411</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">232</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">348</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;11.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sundaram, 2013 (<xref rid="kwx251C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient, UCDs, and ACHs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;50 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2004/2005&#x02013;2009/2010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">937</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,359</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">439</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">659</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">498</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">736</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suzuki, 2014 (<xref rid="kwx251C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;10 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2011&#x02013;2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">193</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.2<sup>e</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.2<sup>e</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">167</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.3<sup>e</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">van Doorn, 2017 (<xref rid="kwx251C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2003&#x02013;2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">579</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,754</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">142</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">676</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">437</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,078</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cowling, 2014 (<xref rid="kwx251C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months&#x02013;17 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009&#x02013;2013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">428</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,737</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,185</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">321</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,552</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grijalva, 2015 (<xref rid="kwx251C26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010&#x02013;2012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">766</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,605</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">368</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,196</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">398</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,409</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pierse, 2016 (<xref rid="kwx251C30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inpatient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All ages</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">267</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">735</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">248</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">210</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">487</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;20.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.7</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="kwx251tfn5"><p>Abbreviations: ACHs, acute-care hospitals; FLU, influenza; ORV, other/another respiratory virus; PAN, panel; UCDs, urgent-care departments.</p></fn><fn id="kwx251tfn6"><p><sup>a</sup> Defined as vaccination coverage in the ORV-positive group minus vaccination coverage in the PAN-negative group.</p></fn><fn id="kwx251tfn7"><p><sup>b</sup> Percentage of participants who were PAN-negative among influenza-negative participants.</p></fn><fn id="kwx251tfn8"><p><sup>c</sup> Percentage of participants who were ORV-positive among influenza-negative participants.</p></fn><fn id="kwx251tfn9"><p><sup>d</sup> Data for 2009 were not included.</p></fn><fn id="kwx251tfn10"><p><sup>e</sup> There were 4 subjects in the ORV-positive control group and 18 subjects in the PAN-negative control group with missing data on vaccination status. Persons with missing vaccination status were not excluded; their vaccination status was categorized as &#x0201c;unknown,&#x0201d; and they were included in the analysis.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><sec id="kwx251s3a"><title>Vaccination coverage</title><p>Vaccine coverage was reported by all studies for the various control groups considered. In addition, vaccine coverage by age group and control group was calculated for each study, where sufficient detail was provided. Because Pierse et al. (<xref rid="kwx251C30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) reported results by study setting (inpatient and outpatient), Feng et al. (<xref rid="kwx251C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>) and Levy et al. (<xref rid="kwx251C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) reported results by season, and Sundaram et al. (<xref rid="kwx251C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) reported results by age group, we were able to calculate estimates for a total of 18 triplets from 12 studies (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="kwx251TB2">2</xref>). The vaccination coverage estimated from the FLU-negative group ranged from 9.0% among inpatient children aged 6 months&#x02013;17 years in Hong Kong, China, in 2009&#x02013;2013 (<xref rid="kwx251C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) to 68.3% among outpatient children aged 6 months&#x02013;5 years in Australia in 2008 (<xref rid="kwx251C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). The differences in vaccination coverage between the ORV-positive and PAN-negative groups ranged from &#x02212;28.4% to 16.0% (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="kwx251TB2">2</xref>). However, the paired <italic>t</italic> test comparing mean vaccination coverage between these groups suggested no statistical difference (<italic>P</italic> = 0.61). Of 18 differences in vaccination coverage point estimates, 6 were higher than 10%. We did not identify any age- or setting-specific pattern larger or smaller than 10% by univariate analysis.</p></sec><sec id="kwx251s3b"><title>Difference in VE (&#x00394;VE)</title><p>We extracted 63 VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;</sub> estimates, 62 VE<sub>ORV+</sub> estimates, and 33 VE<sub>PAN&#x02212;</sub> estimates for further comparison. The distributions of VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;</sub> and VE<sub>ORV+</sub> estimates are shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="kwx251F2">2</xref>A, while the distributions of VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;</sub> and VE<sub>PAN&#x02212;</sub> estimates are shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="kwx251F2">2</xref>B. We observed VE estimates to be correlated and mostly distributed close to the identity lines. Among the 63 VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;</sub> estimates, 38 estimates were for persons of all ages, 18 were for children, and 4 were specifically for older adults; 44 were estimates of VE against influenza A or B viruses, while others were calculated for a specific influenza type/subtype (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Web Figures 1 and 2</xref>). All studies estimated VE after adjusting for potential confounders, including age, and 9 in 12 adjusted for calendar time as a proxy for changing influenza activity. We calculated &#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;,ORV+</sub>, &#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;,PAN&#x02212;</sub>, and &#x00394;VE<sub>ORV+,PAN&#x02212;</sub> from each available estimate. We did not find evidence of publication bias by assessing &#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;,ORV+</sub> and its standard error (<italic>P</italic> = 0.64). No statistically significant differences were observed for any of the &#x00394;VE estimates except those reported by van Doorn et al. (<xref rid="kwx251C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>).
</p><fig id="kwx251F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Comparison of influenza vaccine effectiveness (VE) estimated using influenza (FLU)-negative controls (VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;</sub>) with VE estimated using other/another respiratory virus (ORV)-positive controls (VE<sub>ORV+</sub>) (A) and comparison of VE estimated using influenza-negative controls (VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;</sub>) with VE estimated using panel (PAN)-negative controls (VE<sub>PAN&#x02212;</sub>) (B) from all available VE estimates. Dotted lines represent the identity line. Ninety-five percent confidence intervals are shown in gray (point estimates and lower confidence limits below &#x02212;110% are not shown).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="kwx251f02"/></fig><p>After restriction of the VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;</sub> estimates analyzed to those with confidence intervals spanning 100 percentage points or less, 48 VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;</sub> estimates, 48 VE<sub>ORV+</sub> estimates, and 24 VE<sub>PAN&#x02212;</sub> estimates remained for further analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Web Figure 1</xref>). The 48 point estimates of &#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;,ORV+</sub> ranged from &#x02013;43% to 18%. Forty of these estimates had an absolute value of less than 10% (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Web Figure 1</xref>). The VE estimates excluded from meta-analysis are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Web Figure 2</xref>. In the meta-analysis, we removed pooled &#x00394;VE estimates if &#x00394;VE estimates by age stratum/influenza season were available (<italic>n</italic> = 21) and estimated pooled &#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;,ORV+</sub> against influenza A or B viruses. <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> and Cochran&#x02019;s <italic>Q</italic> test implied no concerning heterogeneity (<italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0, <italic>Q</italic>(20 df) = 8.4, <italic>P</italic> = 0.99). The pooled &#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;,ORV+</sub> was &#x02013;4% (95% confidence interval (CI): &#x02013;10, 2) as estimated from 21 pairs of differences in VE estimates (&#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;</sub> and &#x00394;VE<sub>ORV+</sub>), consistent with no substantial difference for VE estimates between the FLU-negative and ORV-positive groups. Similarly, the pooled estimate for &#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;,PAN&#x02212;</sub> was &#x02013;1% (95% CI: &#x02013;8, 5) (<italic>n</italic> = 13), and that for &#x00394;VE<sub>ORV+,PAN&#x02212;</sub> was 5% (95% CI: &#x02013;2, 12) (<italic>n</italic> = 13). <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Web Figure 2</xref> shows the confidence intervals of VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;</sub> estimates spanning over 100 percentage points.</p><p>We further conducted meta-analysis on &#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;,ORV+</sub> estimates for children (7 &#x00394;VE estimates), adults (3 &#x00394;VE estimates), and elderly (2 &#x00394;VE estimates). The pooled &#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;,ORV+</sub> was 0% (95% CI: &#x02013;9, 8) for children, &#x02013;4% (95% CI: &#x02013;21, 14) for young adults, and 1% (95% CI: &#x02013;20, 22) for older adults. We were not able to identify any trend among age groups. We also performed sensitivity analysis by restricting VE estimates to specific influenza types/subtypes (H1N1, H3N2, and B) and settings (inpatient or outpatient). The pooled estimate was &#x02013;2% (95% CI: &#x02013;19, 15) from 3 &#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;,ORV+</sub> estimates for inpatient settings and &#x02013;6% (95% CI: &#x02013;13, 1) from 17 &#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;,ORV+</sub> estimates for outpatient settings. We did not observe a pooled &#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;,ORV+</sub> that was statistically different from zero.</p></sec><sec id="kwx251s3c"><title>Meta-regression</title><p>We performed meta-regression to explore factors that may contribute to VE using univariate and multivariate random-effects models. In univariate models, VE estimates were higher if the estimate was for children (<italic>P</italic> = 0.001), persons of all ages (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), or inpatients (<italic>P</italic> = 0.04) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Web Table 2</xref>). No association was observed between VE estimates and choice of control group. Similarly, we did not observe an interaction between age group and selection of control group (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05; results not shown). In the multivariate regression, we also did not observe a significant association between the choice of control group and VE (<italic>P</italic><sub>(ORV+)</sub> = 0.24, <italic>P</italic><sub>(PAN&#x02212;)</sub> = 0.93) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Web Table 2</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="kwx251s4"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Based on 12 studies identified from 155 TND publications providing 63 VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;</sub> estimates, 62 VE<sub>ORV+</sub> estimates, and 33 VE<sub>PAN&#x02212;</sub> estimates, we did not find any statistical differences in VE by type of control group. The paired <italic>t</italic> test assessing vaccination coverage also did not demonstrate any difference by choice of control group. Although we observed a &#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;,ORV+</sub> less than zero reported in 1 study, the difference was not consistently observed in each season (<xref rid="kwx251C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). The pooled &#x00394;VE<sub>FLU&#x02212;,ORV+</sub> estimate for 21 pairs of observations was &#x02013;4% (95% CI: &#x02013;10, 2), suggesting that the choice of control group is unlikely to significantly affect VE estimated using the TND.</p><p>The nonspecific immune response to influenzavirus involves the activation of natural killer cells, macrophages, and dendritic cells, the immune functions of which are known to decrease with age (<xref rid="kwx251C23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Therefore, we assumed that the phenomenon of virus interference may be more prevalent among younger, rather than older, age groups. However, our analysis did not strongly support this hypothesis; although age group was correlated with VE estimates, we did not observe an interaction between any age groups and choices of control groups in multivariate meta-regression. We acknowledge that our sample size was small, and as the number of studies examining this phenomenon increases, evidence for virus interference may arise.</p><p>Virus interference may act differently by type/subtype. For example, interference between RSV and influenza A may be more pronounced than interference between RSV and influenza B (<xref rid="kwx251C36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>; Dr. Karen Laurie, WHO Collaborating Center for Reference and Research on Influenza at the Peter Doherty Institute for Infection and Immunity, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia, personal communication, 2016). However, we identified no statistically significant &#x00394;VE estimates among types/subtypes. Again, our analysis of these effects was limited by the sample size.</p><p>Selection bias may arise from inpatient studies if patients hospitalized due to chronic underlying conditions other than infection are also more likely to be vaccinated. In this study, we identified 3 studies reporting inpatient results and did not observe any such trend. The pooled VE estimates by setting did not differ from zero.</p><p>We found that the proportion of PAN-negative controls varied substantially among studies. These differences could partially be explained by the number of ORVs tested. However, we only observed a nonsignificant, weak, negative correlation between the number of ORVs tested and the proportion PAN-negative. The types of viruses included in the panel may also affect the proportion PAN-negative. For example, in the 2 studies reporting the detection rates of each ORV, rhinovirus and RSV were most commonly detected. Only 1 study from Hong Kong (<xref rid="kwx251C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) did not include rhinovirus, which could explain why this study had the highest proportion PAN-negative. The differences in proportion PAN-negative are likely to also be associated with viral load and shedding. With the exception of the Hong Kong study (<xref rid="kwx251C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>), the studies involving children presented low proportions of PAN-negative subjects among all eligible subjects, which is consistent with observations of higher viral load and shedding from children (<xref rid="kwx251C37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). The heterogeneity of viral shedding by age suggests potential misclassification bias in the PAN-negative group, where results may be more likely to be false-negative among samples taken from older patients. Other reasons for false-negative influenza results may be associated with suboptimal swab quality, imperfect laboratory testing methods, or long intervals from symptom onset to presentation (<xref rid="kwx251C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). All of these factors could contribute to misclassification of infection status and contribute to larger &#x00394;VE<sub>ORV+,PAN&#x02212;</sub> values. Under this circumstance, the ORV-positive group could be considered the one providing more accurate VE estimates, because it demonstrates that the swab and swabbing method were of sufficient quality to detect virus (<xref rid="kwx251C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p><p>In conclusion, based on 12 studies estimating VE using alternative control groups, we did not find evidence of virus interference, suggesting that VE estimates obtained by means of the TND are not biased by virus interference. Using FLU-negative controls is likely to produce VE estimates that are as reliable as those of ORV-positive and PAN-negative controls. From a resource-saving perspective, investigators in surveillance systems or research schemes using the TND to measure influenza VE may consider not testing further for ORVs when estimating influenza VE. Further simulation studies that incorporate multiple sources of bias and examine this phenomenon in different age groups could help confirm or refute our findings.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1"><label>Web Material</label><media xlink:href="kwx251cowlingwebmaterialfinal.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="kwx251ack1"><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>Author affiliations: WHO Collaborating Center for Infectious Disease Epidemiology and Control, School of Public Health, Li Ka Shing Faculty of Medicine, University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong Special Administrative Region, China (Shuo Feng, Benjamin J. Cowling); National Center for Epidemiology and Population Health, Australian National University, Canberra, Australian Capital Territory, Australia (Heath Kelly); WHO Collaborating Center for Reference and Research on Influenza at the Peter Doherty Institute for Infection and Immunity, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia (Sheena G. Sullivan); Department of Epidemiology, Fielding School of Public Health, University of California, Los Angeles, Los Angeles, California (Sheena G. Sullivan); and Centre for Epidemiology and Biostatistics, School of Population and Global Health, University of Melbourne, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia (Sheena G. Sullivan).</p><p>This work was financially supported by the Harvard Center for Communicable Disease Dynamics (grant U54 GM088558 from the National Institute of General Medical Sciences, US National Institutes of Health), the Areas of Excellence Scheme of the University Grants Committee of Hong Kong (grant AoE/M-12/06), and a commissioned grant from the Health and Medical Research Fund of the Government of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region. The WHO Collaborating Center for Reference and Research on Influenza is funded by the Australian Government Department of Health.</p><p>We thank Julie Au and Vicky Fang for technical assistance.</p><p>The funders played no role in study design, data collection and analysis, the decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p><p>B.J.C. has received research funding from Sanofi Pasteur (Lyon, France).</p></ack><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list list-content="abbreviations"><def-item><term id="term1-doi">CI</term><def><p>confidence interval</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term2-doi">ED</term><def><p>emergency department</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term3-doi">ORV</term><def><p>other/another respiratory virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term4-doi">PCR</term><def><p>polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term5-doi">RSV</term><def><p>respiratory syncytial virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term6-doi">TND</term><def><p>test-negative design</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="term7-doi">VE</term><def><p>vaccine effectiveness</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="kwx251C1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Osterholm</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Efficacy and effectiveness of influenza vaccines: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>36</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22032844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jefferson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Demicheli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Assessment of the efficacy and effectiveness of influenza vaccines in healthy children: systematic review</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>365</volume>(<issue>9461</issue>):<fpage>773</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>780</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15733718</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tricco</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chit</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soobiah</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Comparing influenza vaccine efficacy against mismatched and matched strains: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>BMC Med</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>153</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23800265</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flannery</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gubareva</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Enhanced genetic characterization of influenza A(H3N2) viruses and vaccine effectiveness by genetic group, 2014&#x02013;2015</article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>214</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1010</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1019</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27190176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kissling</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valenciano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Early influenza vaccine effectiveness results 2015&#x02013;16: I-MOVE multicentre case-control study</article-title>. <source>Euro Surveill</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>30134</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cowling</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Potential of the test-negative design for measuring influenza vaccine effectiveness: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Expert Rev Vaccines</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1571</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1591</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25348015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carville</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Estimation of influenza vaccine effectiveness from routine surveillance data</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e5079</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19333374</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cowling</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Concordance of interim and final estimates of influenza vaccine effectiveness: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Euro Surveill</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>30202</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The test-negative design for estimating influenza vaccine effectiveness</article-title>. <source>Vaccine</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>2165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2168</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23499601</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipsitch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simonsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Observational studies and the difficult quest for causality: lessons from vaccine effectiveness and impact studies</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2060</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2074</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27453361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tchetgen Tchetgen</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cowling</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Theoretical basis of the test-negative study design for assessment of influenza vaccine effectiveness</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>184</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>345</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>353</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27587721</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothman</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greenland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lash</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group>
<chapter-title>Case-control studies</chapter-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothman</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Greenland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lash</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group>, eds. <source>Modern Epidemiology</source>. <edition>3rd ed</edition>
<publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &#x00026; Wilkins</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>:<fpage>111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>128</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cowling</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Influenza vaccine effectiveness by test-negative design&#x02014;comparison of inpatient and outpatient settings</article-title>. <source>Vaccine</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1672</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1679</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26920469</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foppa</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferdinands</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The case test-negative design for studies of the effectiveness of influenza vaccine in inpatient settings</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>2052</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2059</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26979985</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cowling</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishiura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Increased risk of noninfluenza respiratory virus infections associated with receipt of inactivated influenza vaccine</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1778</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1783</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22423139</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cowling</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nishiura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Virus interference and estimates of influenza vaccine effectiveness from test-negative studies</article-title>. <source>Epidemiology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>930</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>931</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23038121</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>&#x000c5;nestad</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nordb&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Virus interference. Did rhinoviruses activity hamper the progress of the 2009 influenza A (H1N1) pandemic in Norway?</article-title><source>Med Hypotheses</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>77</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1132</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1134</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21975051</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>&#x000c5;nestad</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Surveillance of respiratory viral infections by rapid immunofluorescence diagnosis, with emphasis on virus interference</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Infect</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>523</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>531</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2824225</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laurie</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Seasonal influenza vaccination and the risk of infection with pandemic influenza: a possible illustration of non-specific temporary immunity following infection</article-title>. <source>Euro Surveill</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>47</issue>):<fpage>19722</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21144441</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skoner</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whiteside</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Effect of influenza A virus infection on natural and adaptive cellular immunity</article-title>. <source>Clin Immunol Immunopathol</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>79</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>294</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>302</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8635289</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kandasamy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Voysey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McQuaid</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Non-specific immunological effects of selected routine childhood immunisations: systematic review</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>355</volume>:<fpage>i5225</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27737830</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foppa</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferdinands</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The case test-negative design for studies of the effectiveness of influenza vaccine</article-title>. <source>Vaccine</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>30</issue>):<fpage>3104</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3109</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23624093</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ongr&#x000e1;di</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>K&#x000f6;vesdi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Factors that may impact on immunosenescence: an appraisal</article-title>. <source>Immun Ageing</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20546588</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blyth</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacoby</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Effler</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Effectiveness of trivalent flu vaccine in healthy young children</article-title>. <source>Pediatrics</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>133</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e1218</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>e1225</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24753525</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cowling</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The effectiveness of influenza vaccination in preventing hospitalizations in children in Hong Kong, 2009&#x02013;2013</article-title>. <source>Vaccine</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>41</issue>):<fpage>5278</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5284</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25092636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grijalva</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Association between hospitalization with community-acquired laboratory-confirmed influenza pneumonia and prior receipt of influenza vaccination</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>314</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1488</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1497</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26436611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacoby</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Vaccine effectiveness against laboratory-confirmed influenza in healthy young children: a case-control study</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Infect Dis J</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>111</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21079528</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tempone</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Influenza vaccine effectiveness estimates for Western Australia during a period of vaccine and virus strain stability, 2010 to 2012</article-title>. <source>Vaccine</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>47</issue>):<fpage>6312</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6318</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25223268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guiomar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Estimates of 2012/13 influenza vaccine effectiveness using the case test-negative control design with different influenza negative control groups</article-title>. <source>Vaccine</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>35</issue>):<fpage>4443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4449</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24962756</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pierse</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Influenza vaccine effectiveness for hospital and community patients using control groups with and without non-influenza respiratory viruses detected, Auckland, New Zealand 2014</article-title>. <source>Vaccine</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>503</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>509</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26685091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chilver</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Influenza vaccine effectiveness in Australia: results from the Australian Sentinel Practices Research Network</article-title>. <source>Med J Aust</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>201</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>109</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>111</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25045991</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sundaram</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McClure</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>VanWormer</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Influenza vaccination is not associated with detection of noninfluenza respiratory viruses in seasonal studies of influenza vaccine effectiveness</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>789</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>793</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23748138</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ariyoshi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Potential effect of virus interference on influenza vaccine effectiveness estimates in test-negative designs</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Infect</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>142</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2642</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2646</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25372226</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fowlkes</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steffens</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Assessment of virus interference in a test-negative study of influenza vaccine effectiveness</article-title>. <source>Epidemiology</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>514</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>524</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28362642</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Doorn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Darvishian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dijkstra</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Influenza vaccine effectiveness estimates in the Dutch population from 2003 to 2014: the test-negative design case-control study with different control groups</article-title>. <source>Vaccine</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>2831</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2839</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28412077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laurie</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guarnaccia</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carolan</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Interval between infections and viral hierarchy are determinants of viral interference following influenza virus infection in a ferret model</article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>212</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1701</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1710</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25943206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="kwx251C37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrat</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vergu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Time lines of infection and disease in human influenza: a review of volunteer challenge studies</article-title>. <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>167</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>775</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>785</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18230677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>