<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The world is currently experiencing its third outbreak with a highly virulent coronavirus causing severe pneumonia in humans, with all three taking place in the 21
 <sup>st</sup> century. The first epidemic had origins in Guangdong Province, China, during late 2002 and lasted until 2004 (
 <xref rid="bKsiazek2003" ref-type="bibr">Ksiazek et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bQin2003" ref-type="bibr">Qin et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bRota2003" ref-type="bibr">Rota et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bThe2004" ref-type="bibr">The Chinese SARS Molecular Epidemiology Consortium, 2004</xref>). The outbreak, caused by Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus (SARS-CoV), killed at least 700 people and infected over 8 000, and cases were reported in all six permanently inhabited continents with 29 countries affected (
 <xref rid="bde2016" ref-type="bibr">de Wit et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bStadler2003" ref-type="bibr">Stadler et al., 2003</xref>). Aside from a few instances of laboratory-linked infections, SARS-CoV has not been reported in the human population ever since (
 <xref rid="bLim2004" ref-type="bibr">Lim et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bOrellana2004" ref-type="bibr">Orellana, 2004</xref>). The second epidemic was first characterized in a man with pneumonia in Saudi Arabia in 2012 (
 <xref rid="bZaki2012" ref-type="bibr">Zaki et al., 2012</xref>), in which sporadic cases, small clusters, and large outbreaks have been reported over subsequent years in 24 affected countries, mostly located in the Middle East, but with imported infections to North America, Africa, Europe and Asia (
 <xref rid="bAssiri2013" ref-type="bibr">Assiri et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bGuery2013" ref-type="bibr">Guery et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bHijawi2013" ref-type="bibr">Hijawi et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bShehata2016" ref-type="bibr">Shehata et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bZumla2015" ref-type="bibr">Zumla et al., 2015</xref>). The aetiological agent was named Middle East Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus (MERS-CoV), in which over 800 deaths and close to 2 500 cases were reported to date (
 <xref rid="bShehata2016" ref-type="bibr">Shehata et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bZumla2015" ref-type="bibr">Zumla et al., 2015</xref>). The third pandemic was first reported in Hubei Province, China, in late 2019 and is still ongoing as of April 2020 (
 <xref rid="bLi2020" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bLu2020a" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al., 2020a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bWu2020" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bZhou2020a" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2020a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bZhu2020" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2020</xref>). Caused by another novel coronavirus, known as the human coronavirus 2019 (HCoV-19, also named by various bodies as SARS-CoV-2 or 2019-nCoV) (
 <xref rid="bJiang2020" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et al., 2020</xref>), intense and widespread transmission was observed worldwide, with over 80 000 deaths and 1 400 000 cases reported from over 200 countries, areas or territories as of 08 April 2020 (https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019). From sequencing results, it was determined that HCoV-19 had over 75% genomic similarity to SARS-CoV (
 <xref rid="bWu2020" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bZhou2020a" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2020a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bZhu2020" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2020</xref>). To date, there are no licensed prophylactics or therapeutics available to prevent or treat Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS), Middle East Respiratory Syndrome (MERS), or Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), the diseases caused by infection with SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV or HCoV-19, respectively. 
</p>
