<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mitochondria possess their own genome, mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA), which is a 16.6 kbp closed, circular, double-stranded DNA genome. Most cells contain hundreds to thousands of copies of mtDNA, which encodes two ribosomal ribonucleic acid (RNA) and 22 transfer RNAs which are necessary for translation of the 13 mtDNA-encoded mRNAs that comprise key subunits of the oxidative phosphorylation (OXPHOS) complexes [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Despite the ability of the mitochondria to carry out DNA replication, mtDNA transcription and protein translation independently of the nucleus, these functions are, in fact, semiautonomous in nature [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Mitochondria require nuclear DNA-encoded genes for function, and indeed, all of the DNA replication, transcription, ribosomal protein machinery and most of the OXPHOS subunits are nuclear encoded [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Furthermore, anterograde and retrograde signalling between the mtDNA and the nucleus allows mitochondria to change bioenergetics and biosynthetic output to match cellular needs or respond to cellular stress [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. MtDNA contains no introns and histones, and only low levels of repair mechanisms such as mtDNA damage, depletion or mutation may have a very large impact on mitochondrial function. The mtDNA copy number per cell varies greatly with over 150 000 in an oocyte to only several hundred in cells found in lung tissue [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Generally, cells with the highest energy demand have the highest number of mitochondria [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] and mtDNA copy number [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The cellular distribution of mitochondria varies between cell types. Large cells such as motor neurones, being over 1 m long, reposition their mitochondria to the site of the neuromuscular junction where the most ATP is required [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. This provides a further complication of moving mitochondria (dynamics) from the cell body along the axon to the synaptic terminals. An inability to maintain mitochondrial function at the synapse potentially leads to neuronal dysfunction and neurodegeneration [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] with a disruption in mitochondrial distribution at synaptic/neuromuscular junctions associated with motor neurone diseases such as amyotrophic lateral sclerosis and Huntingdon's disease [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].
</p>
