<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>With the death toll increasing daily, we considered the mortality rates reported by the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>) as of April 20
 <sup>th</sup>, 2020 wherein reported deaths are provided in parentheses after a country’s name: Africa: the five countries reporting most deaths are Algeria (375), Egypt (239), Morocco (141), South Africa (54) and Cameroon (42). Asia: the five countries reporting most deaths are Iran (5,118), China (4,636), Turkey (2,017), Indonesia (582) and India (543). America: the five countries reporting most deaths are United States (US) (40,682), Brazil (2,462), Canada (1,580), Mexico (686) and Ecuador (474). Europe: the five countries reporting most deaths are Italy (23,660), Spain (20,453), France (19,718), United Kingdom (16,060) and Belgium (5,683). Oceania: the four countries reporting most deaths are Australia (70), New Zealand (12), Guam (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) and Northern Mariana Islands (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Interestingly, countries like the US, Spain and Italy have more fatalities than China, the epicentre of the outbreak with a much bigger population. In addition to several factors such as the preparedness of countries like South Korea and Japan due to their earlier fight against SARS and MERS, the emphasis these countries put on developing 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> diagnostics and therapeutics against the disease (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), co-operation of the public (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), small but significantly contributing factors such as sense of Life Worth Living (Ikigai) in Japan (which actually has been proven to decrease the risk of mortality (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>)) etc., which potentially decreased fatalities in these countries compared to Italy, Spain, USA etc., cross-protection against COVID-19 conferred by the encephalitis vaccine also seems to be a key parameter worthy of further investigation. This connection is well illustrated by comparing the large number of fatalities in Italy with the small number of deaths in their neighbouring country, Austria (452 deaths) (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), where, unlike Italy, encephalitis vaccination is included in its national immunization schedule (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). This hypothesis is further supported by several additional reports. 
</p>
