<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Viral-induced encephalitis is associated with four different kinds of viruses i. Arboviruses (e.g., eastern equine encephalitis, Japanese encephalitis (JE), La Crosse encephalitis, St. Louis encephalitis, western equine encephalitis, West Nile virus encephalitis), ii. Enteroviruses (e.g., coxsackievirus, polioviruses), iii. Herpes viruses and iv. Other viruses such as measles, mumps, and rubella, which cause secondary encephalitis (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Of these, JE is the leading cause of viral encephalitis worldwide, with an estimated 50,000 cases and 15,000 deaths annually. It is a member of the genus Flavivirus, which also includes the dengue, yellow fever and West Nile viruses and is transmitted by Culex mosquitoes. In northern Europe and northern Asia, flaviviruses causing encephalitis have evolved to use ticks as vectors because of their abundance in cooler climates and hence the encephalitis caused by flavivirus is termed tick-borne encephalitis (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). It is interesting to note that CoVs, though primarily recognized as respiratory pathogens, are also encephalitis-inducing infectious agents; especially, HCoV-229E, HCoV-OC43, and SARS-CoV, which possess neuroinvasive properties and their viral RNA has been detected in human brains. A few years after the 2002-2003 SARS-CoV epidemics, associated viral particles were identified in the brain tissue of infected individuals with central nervous system (CNS) issues associated with oedema, neurodegeneration, and gliosis. The viruses accessed the brain through the olfactory bulbs, where they infected neuronal cells, and induced a lethal disease in an area of the body with restrained immune infiltration (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Immunization with inactivated JE vaccine (INV) and live attenuated vaccine (LAV) induces a cross-immune response that confers cross-protection against dengue viruses (DENVs) (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Tripartite motif-containing (TRIM) proteins are active players in antiviral innate immunity and overlapping molecular determinants govern the antiviral activities of TRIM56 against infections by yellow fever virus (YFV), dengue virus serotype 2 (DENV2) and human CoV (HCoV-OC43) (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). The neuroinvasive properties of SARS-CoV2 may also underlie respiratory failure in patients with COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Furthermore, a case of meningitis was recently attributed to COVID-19 in Japan (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>).
</p>
