<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">Many studies test the hypothesis of high emissions of monoterpenes under high temperatures using the leaves of 
 <italic>Quercus ilex</italic>, also known as evergreen oak (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">15.1</xref>). The evergreen tree is native to the Mediterranean area where it has to survive under hot and dry conditions and synthesis of these monoterpenes may have been an adaptive mechanism for the plants to survive under heat stress.
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn2">2</xref> This tree does not emit isoprenes but it emits monoterpenes and is able to handle different environmental stresses such as drought, salt, and heat (see footnote 2). A particular study done by Loreto et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2002</xref>) were conducted to visualize monoterpene production in response to high temperatures and to see if thermotolerance is increased with monoterpenes (Loreto et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2002</xref>). In this study, the leaves were exposed in 5 
 <bold>°</bold>C intervals ranging from the temperatures 30 
 <bold>°</bold>C to 55 
 <bold>°</bold>C and leaves were kept under conditions in which inhibited or allowed monoterpenes to synthesize (Loreto et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2002</xref>). The results that were found in this experience was a discovery of seven most abundant monoterpenes which was emitted at the maximum temperature of 35 
 <bold>°</bold>C and decreased its abundance over time as the temperatures increased and α-pinene had the greatest abundance of emittance at 35 
 <bold>°</bold>C as well as other terpenes but greatly reduced over higher temperatures (Loreto et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2002</xref>). At 55 
 <bold>°</bold>C the monoterpenes, myrcene and limonene had higher emission rates compared to temperatures around 35 
 <bold>°</bold>C (Loreto et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2002</xref>). Photosynthesis was also decreased when the leaves were exposed to any temperature that was higher than 30 
 <bold>°</bold>C and at 55 
 <bold>°</bold>C showed a loss of CO
 <sub>2</sub> and recovery occurred around 30 
 <bold>°</bold>C (Loreto et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2002</xref>). Overall, the monoterpenes showed that their optimal temperature for emission was around 30–35 
 <bold>°</bold>C (Loreto et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2002</xref>). Researchers prove that the emission of monoterpenes is under enzymatic control due to their optimal temperatures (Loreto et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2002</xref>).
</p>
