<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.29820.012</object-id>
 <label>Figure 3.</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Estimated epidemiological and ecological parameters.</title>
  <p>MCMC posterior distributions, based on model fitting to notified case data between 2015–2017 and obtained from sampling 1 million MCMC steps after burn-in. (
   <bold>A</bold>) Posterior of the introduction date with median 
   <inline-formula>
    <math id="inf66">
     <msup>
      <mn mathcolor="#404040">10</mn>
      <mrow>
       <mi mathcolor="#404040">t</mi>
       <mo mathcolor="#404040">⁢</mo>
       <mi mathcolor="#404040">h</mi>
      </mrow>
     </msup>
    </math>
   </inline-formula> December 2014 (95% CI [01–16 Dec]). (
   <bold>B</bold>) Posterior of the observation rate with median 0.0039 (95% CI [0.0038–0.0041])). (
   <bold>C</bold>) Posterior of the human infectious period with median 5.9 days (95% CI [5.47–6.14]). (
   <bold>D</bold>) Posterior of the human (intrinsic) incubation period with median 5.8 days (95% CI [5.6–6.15]). Representative samples of 500 MCMC chain states are available in 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary files 1</xref>–
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp6">6</xref>. See 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s1">Figure 3—figure supplement 1</xref> for sample chain behaviour.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="elife-29820-fig3" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 <p content-type="supplemental-figure">
  <fig id="fig3s1" specific-use="child-fig" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
   <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.29820.013</object-id>
   <label>Figure 3—figure supplement 1.</label>
   <caption>
    <title>Sensitivity output for MCMC chains.</title>
    <p>(
     <bold>A</bold>) The last 1.5 million states of a 5 million run were sampled (25,000 samples), and the correlation of the states was calculated between the chains of particular parameters (windows of 50 samples for visualization purposes). The correlations present a highly stable behaviour in the MCMC chains. Some parameters, such as the human infectious and latency periods, show no correlation; others show consistently positive or negative correlation. The non-zero correlation is expected between some of the parameters, since fine tuning of certain parameters by the MCMC can be balanced by similar/opposite changes in other parameters, resulting in the same dynamic output; i.e. small identifiability issues are difficult to eliminate from complex ODE models. These correlations may have biological meaning as similar changes in the natural system could follow the relationships herein found. Red dotted lines mark correlation equal to zero. (
     <bold>B</bold>) MCMC chains for the 8 estimated parameters. The last 1.5 million states of a 5 million run were sampled (1000 samples). The green dotted lines mark the mean. A subsample of 500 was used to run deterministic and stochastic simulations, submitted in spreadsheet tables as supplementary material.
    </p>
   </caption>
   <graphic xlink:href="elife-29820-fig3-figsupp1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </fig>
 </p>
 <p content-type="supplemental-figure">
  <fig id="fig3s2" specific-use="child-fig" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
   <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.29820.014</object-id>
   <label>Figure 3—figure supplement 2.</label>
   <caption>
    <title>Eco-epidemiological factors and model fit to notified cases when using 2 observation rates.</title>
    <p>(
     <bold>A</bold>) Resulting Bayesian MCMC fit to weekly (black line: data, purple line: model fit) and cumulative incidence (black line: data, grey line: model fit). The grey area highlights the period before the Zika outbreak, the white areas highlight the period for which notified case data was available.(
     <bold>B</bold>) Climatic series and estimated 
     <inline-formula>
      <math id="inf67">
       <msub>
        <mi mathcolor="#404040">R</mi>
        <mn mathcolor="#404040">0</mn>
       </msub>
      </math>
     </inline-formula> for the period of the outbreak (2015–2017), normalised to 1 for visualization purposes (
     <inline-formula>
      <math id="inf68">
       <msub>
        <mi mathcolor="#404040">R</mi>
        <mn mathcolor="#404040">0</mn>
       </msub>
      </math>
     </inline-formula> absolute values in suplot B). (
     <bold>C</bold>) Fitted and projected epidemic attack rate (
     <inline-formula>
      <math id="inf69">
       <mo lspace="0pt" mathcolor="#404040" rspace="3.5pt">%</mo>
      </math>
     </inline-formula> population infected, green), basic reproduction number (
     <inline-formula>
      <math id="inf70">
       <msub>
        <mi mathcolor="#404040">R</mi>
        <mn mathcolor="#404040">0</mn>
       </msub>
      </math>
     </inline-formula>, red) and effective reproduction number (
     <inline-formula>
      <math id="inf71">
       <msub>
        <mi mathcolor="#404040">R</mi>
        <mi mathcolor="#404040">e</mi>
       </msub>
      </math>
     </inline-formula>, blue). Grey shaded area represents the period after the last available notified case. (
     <bold>D</bold>) Posteriors for the observation rate of 2015 (left) with median 0.0034 (95% CI [0.0033–0.0035]) and the observation rate for 2016 and onwards (right) with median 0.01395 (95% CI [0.0089–0.0264])).
    </p>
   </caption>
   <graphic xlink:href="elife-29820-fig3-figsupp2" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </fig>
 </p>
</fig>
