<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Spray application reduced the expression of pro-inflammatory cytokines and increased the level of IL-1 and IL-12p40 receptor antagonists, which are known to have anti-inflammatory action in the nasal lavage of patients with respiratory viral infections [
 <xref rid="B56-marinedrugs-17-00373" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. It is known that IL-12p40 is necessary for inhibiting the hyperactivity of airway and peribronchial fibrosis [
 <xref rid="B58-marinedrugs-17-00373" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. The expression of inflammatory mediators during viral infection may complicate underlying diseases in the form of asthma [
 <xref rid="B59-marinedrugs-17-00373" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-marinedrugs-17-00373" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. In this regard, a decrease in the intensity of the immune response due to a lower viral load seems to be an attractive property of treatment of ι-carrageenan. To increase their efficiency, oligosaccharides and their sulphated derivatives having a lower molecular weight were obtained from the high molecular weight ATP carrageenan [
 <xref rid="B61-marinedrugs-17-00373" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. So, the oligosaccharide CO-1 with a molecular weight of 1–3 kDa effectively dose-dependently inhibited the replication of influenza A (H1N1) virus in MDCK cells (selectivity index &gt;25.0). CO-1 did not bind to the cell surface, but it was bound to viral particles during the pre-treatment process. Unlike high molecular weight native carrageenan, this oligosaccharide can penetrate into MDCK cells and inhibit the expression of viral proteins and mRNA after its internalization into the cell, but before it leaves the cell, i.e. in one replication cycle. The main factors affecting the antiviral activity of oligosaccharides are the degree of sulphation and Mw. The most active oligosaccharide CO-1 contained 0.8–1.0 mol/mol sulphate, and its molecular weight was 1–3 kDa. The preparation CO-1 and its full sulphated derivative (COS) significantly increased the survival rate of mice infected with a lethal dose of influenza virus and reduced the viral load in the lungs of these animals [
 <xref rid="B62-marinedrugs-17-00373" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Taking into account these findings, the authors proposed using low molecular weight oligosaccharides of carrageenan in the treatment of influenza as an alternative strategy to combat this infection.
</p>
