<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="viruses-11-01114-f003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 3</label>
 <caption>
  <p>The viral NP is responsible for the sensitivity to eqMx1. (
   <bold>A</bold>) Schematic representation of the assortment of viral polymerases. The four polymerases (PB1, PB2, PA, and NP) from chicken H7N9
   <sub>ZJ13</sub> were swapped one by one with the equivalent polymerases from A/equine/Jilin/1/1989 (H3N8
   <sub>JL89</sub>), and each group of assorted plasmids was co-transfected into HEK293T. (
   <bold>B</bold>) Relative Luciferase activities of combination sets of IAV against eqMx1. Cells were co-transfected with expression plasmids of the polymerase PB1 (40 ng), PB2 (40 ng), PA (20 ng), and NP (80 ng) in six different groups, (i) all polymerases of H7N9
   <sub>ZJ13</sub>, (ii) all polymerases of H3N8
   <sub>JL89</sub>, (iii) PB2, PA, NP of H7N9
   <sub>ZJ13</sub> and PB1 of H3N8
   <sub>JL89</sub>, (iv) PB1, PA, NP of H7N9
   <sub>ZJ13</sub> and PB2 of H3N8
   <sub>JL89</sub>, (v) PB1, PB2, NP of H7N9
   <sub>ZJ13</sub> and PA of H3N8
   <sub>JL89</sub>, (vi) PB1, PB2, PA of H7N9
   <sub>ZJ13</sub> and NP of H3N8
   <sub>JL89</sub>, together with 40 ng of minigenome reporter (FF-luc) and 10 ng of 
   <italic>Renilla</italic> luciferase expression plasmids (pRL-TK, as an internal control) in the presence of HA-tagged pcDNA-3.1 eqMx1 or an empty control vector at an increasing concentration 0, 50, 100, and 200 ng each. After 24 hr of transfection, cells were lysed using a 1X reporter lysis buffer. Firefly and 
   <italic>Renilla</italic> luciferase activities were measured. The resulting relative activity in the presence of either H7N9
   <sub>ZJ13</sub> or H3N8
   <sub>JL89</sub> was set to 100%. The western blot analysis shown in (
   <bold>B</bold>) was performed to determine the expression levels of eqMx1 and NP. (Statistical differences between samples are indicated, according to a one-way ANOVA followed by a Dunnett’s test; NS = not significant, * 0.01 ≤ 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, ** 0.001 ≤ 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01, *** 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001. Error bars represent the SEM within one representative experiment).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-01114-g003" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
