<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The occurrence of common respiratory virus infections in patients with HM is closely related to viral activity in the community. However, nosocomial outbreaks have been described in haematologic wards, often within a few days after an outbreak in the community [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31_21">31</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43_21">43</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44_21">44</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46_21">46</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR158_21">158</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR160_21">160</xref>]. Preventing nosocomial transmission of common respiratory viruses requires a multifaceted approach (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab4_21" ref-type="table">21.4</xref>) that targets not only the modes of transmission, but also the source of the viruses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43_21">43</xref>]. Nosocomial outbreaks are believed to originate from infected patients and from infected health-care workers. Infection control measures include screening symptomatic patients for common respiratory viruses, early isolation of infected patients, screening health-care workers and visitors for respiratory symptoms, and avoiding contact of symptomatic individuals with patients. Most haematologic wards do not allow children to visit patients, as children are highly prone to common respiratory virus infections and may exhibit viral shedding long after symptom resolution [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39_21">39</xref>]. Continual reinforcement of standard hygiene measures, especially hand hygiene before and after contact with patients, is also strongly recommended. Awareness of the usefulness of these measures, and therefore adherence to the measures, are low, but can be enhanced by educational programs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR161_21">161</xref>]. Most of the common respiratory viruses are transmitted by droplets or direct contact of infected secretions with the nasal mucosa or conjunctiva. Indirect transmission via contaminated fomites or devices is also possible, since these viruses may survive several hours on these surfaces [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6_21">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7_21">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58_21">58</xref>]. Consequently, contact isolation of infected patients combined with droplet precautions is mandatory [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR162_21">162</xref>]. A gown, gloves, and a mask with eye protection must be worn for all contacts with infected patients. Airborne transmission of influenza is suspected [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR163_21">163</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR164_21">164</xref>] but not yet proven, and two recent studies suggest that surgical masks may be as effective in preventing influenza transmission as masks with greater filtration capacity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR165_21">165</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR166_21">166</xref>]. Infection control measures have not been evaluated in randomised control trials, but a before-and-after study suggests they may help to prevent the transmission of common respiratory viruses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43_21">43</xref>]. It must be pointed out that asymptomatic viral shedding, when present, limits the effectiveness of infection control measures [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30_21">30</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65_21">65</xref>]. The optimal duration of isolation is unknown. Whether isolation should be prolonged in asymptomatic patients with persistent low-titre viral shedding detected only by molecular methods remains unclear. Since adenovirus acquisition is known to result also from endogenous reactivation, adenoviral infections may be chiefly related to the level of immunosuppression [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39_21">39</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86_21">86</xref>] and, therefore, may not be effectively prevented by standard infection control measures. 
</p>
