<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">To determine whether APN is critical for PEDV infection, we created APN KO pigs by using CRISPR/Cas9-mediated gene editing and somatic cell nuclear transfer (SCNT). Two candidate guide RNAs (gRNAs) were selected in the immediate downstream area of the start codon of 
 <italic>APN</italic>. One was located in exon 2 and the other was in exon 3 (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A). Pig fetal fibroblasts were transfected with a targeting vector based on pX330 (Addgene # 42230) containing a hU6-driven gRNA and a CAG-driven humanized 
 <italic>Cas9</italic>. Transfected cells were grown in a low density to form single-cell colonies, which were individually cultured and genotyped to identify the positive ones. A total of 72 and 50 well-propagated single-cell colonies were collected from exon 2- and exon 3-targeting groups, respectively. Among these colonies, 60 and 45 presented targeted insertions and/or deletions (indels) with various patterns in the genome. Four biallelic APN KO colonies, namely, # 2–1, # 2–2, # 2–5 that carried out-of-frame indels in exon 2, and # 3–6 that carried out-of-frame indel in exon 3, were used as nuclear donors for SCNT (Supplementary Table S1). A total of 2,494 embryos were constructed from the selected positive cells and transferred into 11 surrogates. Four surrogates were pregnant to term and delivered 18 live piglets (2 died at day 1 due to weakness at birth) and 5 stillborns (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B and Supplementary Table S2). Genotyping of the live cloned piglets showed that all of them were biallelic or homozygous KO with out-of-frame indels in exon 2 of 
 <italic>APN</italic> (Supplementary Table S3 and Supplementary Fig. S1). Intriguingly, the cloned piglet groups derived from # 2–1 were divided into two genotypes, homozygous 1-bp deletion (FF23, FF30, FF35, FF36) and homozygous 1-bp insertion (FF21, FF31). This result indicated that # 2–1, which was originally considered biallelic KO with a 1-bp deletion (Δ1) in one allele and a 1-bp insertion (+1) in the other allele, was definitely a mixed colony composed of two homozygous KO colonies. We next determined the APN protein expression status in the cloned piglets. Western blot with a rabbit anti-APN antibody (ab183358, Abcam) showed no APN expression in the small intestines of two dead piglets (# 1 &amp; # 2 with Δ1/Δ7 genotypes), whereas wild-type (WT) control displayed significant APN expression level (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C).
</p>
