<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the context of human coronaviruses, it was thought that they caused only mild self-limiting infections until the SARS-CoV outbreak in 2002–2003 [
 <xref rid="B2-biomedicines-08-00109" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Two human α-coronaviruses (HCoV-229E and HCoV-NL63) and two β-coronaviruses (HCoV-OC43 and HCoV-HKU1) were identified as endemic in human populations, responsible for 15%–30% of annual respiratory tract infections [
 <xref rid="B18-biomedicines-08-00109" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-biomedicines-08-00109" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. However, a more severe disease has been detected in neonates, elderly people and in individuals with pre-existing illnesses. Moreover, HCoV-NL63 has also been associated with acute laryngotracheitis [
 <xref rid="B19-biomedicines-08-00109" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Interestingly, human coronaviruses differ in genetic variability, as HCoV-229E isolated from around the world showed only minimal sequence divergence [
 <xref rid="B23-biomedicines-08-00109" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-biomedicines-08-00109" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-biomedicines-08-00109" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-biomedicines-08-00109" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-biomedicines-08-00109" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-biomedicines-08-00109" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-biomedicines-08-00109" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-biomedicines-08-00109" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], while HCoV-OC43 isolated from the same location in different years demonstrated significant genetic variability [
 <xref rid="B31-biomedicines-08-00109" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. For this reason, HCoV-229E does not cross species barriers and is incapable of infecting mice, while mice and several ruminant species are susceptible to HCoV-OC43 and the closely related BCoV. As mentioned above, although MHV possesses the ability to cause demyelinating disease, no evidence exists of human coronaviruses being associated with MS.
</p>
