<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Molecular methods of viral detection have superior sensitivity and specificity compared to cell culture-based methods (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">McErlean et al., 2010</xref>). In the setting of acute exacerbation, the reverse-transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) method can detect viruses in approximately 80% of wheezing episodes in school-aged children and in approximately one-half to three-quarters of acute wheezing episodes in adults (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Jackson and Johnston, 2010</xref>). With respect to sample collections for viral detection, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B118">Xiang et al. (2002)</xref> reported that nasopharyngeal secretions and induced sputum during acute exacerbations of asthma in adult patients were equal, while 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Falsey et al. (2012)</xref> found that the diagnostic yields using RT-PCR for detection of any virus in adults hospitalized with respiratory illness were superior in sputum samples (36%) than in nose and throat swabs (23%). However, the study had some limitations in that no test for HRV or AdVs was used. Another report showed that the sensitivity rates for oropharyngeal swabs (OPS), nasopharyngeal swabs (NPS), and nasopharyngeal washings (NPW) obtained from hospitalized patients with acute febrile lower respiratory tract (LRT) infections were 54.2, 73.3, and 84.9%, respectively (for OPS vs. NPS and NPW, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.00001; for NPS vs. NPW, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.003; 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">Lieberman et al., 2009</xref>). Taken together, these studies appear to suggest that induced sputum and NPS/NPW are better methods for identifying respiratory viruses. Regarding HRV, bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) cells were positive for HRV RNA during infection in 80% of samples, whereas nasal lavage fluid was positive in the same patients in 100%, and BAL fluid was positive in only 37%. This suggests that HRV is able to infect the lower airways, and that HRV RNA is largely cell-associated (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">Murray et al., 2004</xref>).
</p>
