<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Vector competence was estimated by measuring virus infection, dissemination and transmission rates. Infection rate was estimated as the proportion of YFV-positive mosquitoes among all mosquitoes tested. Dissemination rate was estimated as the proportion of infected mosquitoes with YFV-positive wings and legs (experiment 1) or head (experiment 2). Transmission rate was estimated as the proportion of mosquitoes with a disseminated infection that had YFV-positive saliva. In addition, transmission efficiency was calculated as the proportion of mosquitoes with infectious saliva among all mosquitoes tested. Vector competence indices were analyzed with a logistic regression model in which each individual mosquito was associated with a binary variable (1 = YFV-positive or 0 = YFV-negative), followed by an analysis of deviance with the R package 
 <italic>car</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007783.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. An initial analysis showed that infection rates were not statistically significantly different between 10 and 14 days post blood meal and both time points were subsequently combined. The analysis of dissemination and transmission rates was restricted to 14 days post blood meal because the two time points differed and there was too little data on day 10 for a meaningful analysis. The experiment effect was statistically non-significant overall and removed from the model. For infection and dissemination rates, the final regression model included the infectious dose (log
 <sub>10</sub>-transformed blood meal titer), the mosquito species (
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>malayensis</italic>), and their interaction. The 50% oral infectious dose (OID
 <sub>50</sub>) and 10% oral infectious dose (OID
 <sub>10</sub>) values and their respective 95% confidence intervals were derived from the logistic fits of infection rates using the R package 
 <italic>MASS</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007783.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The analysis of transmission rate was restricted to the highest infectious dose and the final regression model only included the mosquito species. All statistical analyses were performed using the R software version 3.5.2 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007783.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] and graphical representations were generated with the R packages 
 <italic>ggplot2</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007783.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] and 
 <italic>ggpubr</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007783.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].
</p>
