<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Genetic variation is likely to contribute substantially to the variation in drug response observed across human populations. The field of pharmacogenomics, which relates genetic variability to variability in human drug response, has evolved considerably from candidate gene studies to studies of variation across whole genomes of human populations containing individuals who exhibit a range of responses to different drugs. The initial successes in the field were often the identification of genetic variants within drug-metabolizing genes that had large effects on sensitivity to a given drug. The field has since broadened in scope to encompass regulatory mutations, and refined techniques have made us able to identify the mutations with smaller effect sizes. Whereas early pharmacogenomics studies sought primarily to identify associations between common genetic variation and drug response, more recent approaches have begun to identify mRNAs, miRNAs, and other downstream events that are influenced by genetic variation and may underlie variation in pharmacologic responses. The primary aim of pharmacogenomics has been to uncover novel human genetic variants that affect therapeutic response phenotypes and to identify the genes responsible for those phenotypic differences. The ultimate goal of the field has been to use an understanding of these relations to devise novel personalized pharmacological treatment strategies that maximize the potential for therapeutic benefit and minimize the risk of adverse effects for any given medication. Advances in DNA sequencing and polymorphism characterization technologies have enabled the field to evolve from the sole reliance on hypothesis-driven approaches to the use of discovery-oriented, genome-wide approach that requires fewer a priori assumptions regarding genetic variants. Candidate gene approaches resulted primarily in the identification of genetic variants in drug-metabolizing genes with large effects on toxicity or response (Weinshilboum and Sladek 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR177">1980</xref>); however, many genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have identified novel associations between drug response and genetic variants with unknown functional relevance and often with relatively small effect sizes (Daly 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2010</xref>). The recent development of high-throughput sequencing techniques has enabled researchers to begin to examine the contribution of rare variants to drug sensitivity (Ramsey et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR142">2012</xref>). Genetic screening of HIV for prediction of resistance is recommended by experts and is being increasingly used in the clinical setting (Hirsch et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2000</xref>). Testing for mutations in the HIV genome that are predictive of resistance can be done before therapy or after failure of an initial regimen. Genotypic resistance testing has been judged to be cost-effective, even with the relatively high current costs of the tests (Weinstein et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR178">2001</xref>). At present, the majority of genetic resistance testing for HIV drugs involves sequence-based approaches; however, kit-based tests are expected to become common and testing costs should fall automatically. These tests are also likely to expand beyond the viral genome, as additional polymorphisms in the host genome are linked to HIV treatment outcome.
</p>
