<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Based on the episodic timing of VEEV outbreaks in the past, outbreaks of VEEV will almost certainly happen. To predict and understand the characteristic of these outbreaks, it is paramount that additional studies are done to understand the interaction of VEEV with different hosts, vectors and reservoirs, as well as virus evolution and phylogenetics. Several mechanisms were proposed for the emergence of VEEV epidemics. The most prominent hypothesis is that periodic evolution of IAB and IC VEEV strains facilitate for these epizootics. This is supported by phylogenetic studies [
 <xref rid="B62-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] and laboratory experiments demonstrating that point mutations are able to cause changes in virulence and determine whether the virus can establish viremia in equines [
 <xref rid="B21-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. High level viremia in equines (10
 <sup>6</sup>–10
 <sup>8</sup> plaque forming units (PFU)/mL) is an important factor for epidemic potential, as it results in many new mosquito infections in the region [
 <xref rid="B45-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Vector competency is another aspect that may profoundly influence the chances of new outbreaks of VEEV. Although 
 <italic>Culex</italic> (
 <italic>Melanoconion</italic>) is the main vector for VEEV during the enzootic cycle and 
 <italic>Ae. Ochlerotatus taeniorhynchus</italic> is the main vector during the epizootic cycle there is evidence that many other mosquito species could be competent vectors and may yet become important natural vectors once new adaptive mutations arise or mosquito distribution expands [
 <xref rid="B27-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].
</p>
