<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Both animal‐ and human‐linked coronaviruses were well known by at least the 1960s, and knowledge of their diversity quickly became apparent.
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> Differentiation of these viruses depended largely on serological assessments of antigenicity and cross‐reactions. Whereas human coronaviruses appeared initially limited to a few serologically distinct clusters, a larger spectrum became known in the veterinary field in short order. Before SARS‐CoV‐2, six human coronavirus groups were established in human infection represented by the designations OC43, 229E, NL63, HKU1, SARS‐CoV, and MERS‐CoV.
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>2</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> Although antigenic and genetic distinctions prevail, these viruses nevertheless share many structural and behavioral characteristics that rightfully justify their inclusion in a common family of viruses, the Coronaviridae. Four genus clusters have been proposed for coronaviruses generally, but the human coronaviruses, including the newly recognized SARS‐CoV‐2, all belong to two so designated 
 <italic>Alphacoronavirus</italic> and 
 <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic>. The origin and evolution of these pathogens has now been studied considerably, and there is good reason to believe that animal origins and recombination events have been instrumental in giving rise to the human coronaviruses that we find today.
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref> Four of these viruses were believed to have been endemic to humans—OC43, 229E, NL63, and HKU1; the remaining three (SARS‐CoV, MERS‐CoV, and SARS‐CoV‐2) putatively represent a more contemporary presence. The 
 <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic> lineages can be further subdivided by comparative genomics; lineage A includes OC43 and HKU1, lineage B includes SARS‐CoV and SAR‐CoV‐2, and lineage C includes MERS‐CoV. 
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref> Despite several differences in genome, phenotype, cellular attachment, or intracellular multiplication, there are equally many commonalities that are apparent thus giving justification to comparative discussions. One such commonality as we discuss herein is the ability for these viruses to be associated with enteric disease. As becomes apparent from this review, this aspect of pathogenesis may lead us to rethink the standard approaches taken thus far if not only provide for some stimulating and/or sobering thought.
</p>
