<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ebolavirus is a member of the filoviridae family, and infection by ebolavirus in humans and non-human primates (NHPs) results in onset of severe hemorrhagic fevers with high mortality rates (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Feldmann and Geisbert, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Li H. et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Ye and Yang, 2015</xref>). Since their first identification in 1976, five different ebolavirus species have been isolated from outbreaks in humans or NHPs including Ebola virus (EBOV), Sudan virus (SUDV), Bundibugyo virus (BDBV), Tai Forest virus (TAFV), and Reston virus (RESTV), and these viruses differ significantly in their amino acid sequences by as much as 40% (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Towner et al., 2008</xref>). Notably, the RESTV has been found only in non-human primates from the Philippines, whereas the other four filovirus species are only detected in tropical areas of the equator Africa, and studies in recent years have shown that the African green fruit bats may serve as the natural reservoir of these ebolaviruses (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Leroy et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Groseth et al., 2007</xref>). It is noted that in recent years ebolavirus infection of humans has become more frequent (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Chowell and Nishiura, 2014</xref>). Of particular concern, the 2013–2016 EBOV outbreak that infected over 28000 human infections and resulted in over 11000 deaths. Moreover, the current ongoing 2018 Kivu outbreak has a mortality rate around 67% and has thus far resulted in over 2000 individuals killed. These large-scale outbreaks demonstrates that the serious threat of EOBV infection to public health is urgent and real. Furthermore, evidence also suggests that EBOV may also infect dogs during outbreaks in addition to infect humans and NHPs (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Allela et al., 2005</xref>). On the other hand, RESTV has also been indicated to infect domestic pigs in Asia based on serological analyses (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Barrette et al., 2009</xref>). Further, EBOV has been demonstrated to infect pigs in experimental settings with causing pathogenesis, and virus from infected pigs were shown to transmit to NHPs with no direct contact, demonstrating that this highly lethal virus may be capable of aerosol transmission from a infected host to another susceptible host (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Reed et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Weingartl et al., 2012</xref>). The potential of EBOV to cause non-pathogenic infection in domestic pigs poses a grave danger for these viruses to become endemic and infect humans through zoonotic transmission.
</p>
