<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0265">We reduced the model complexity to look at RSV as a single pathogen without distinguishing between groups. This resulted in skewing the parameter estimates away from within household transmission and towards spontaneous infection from external sources, as a result of introductions due to RSV A and RSV B being treated as multiple introduction of the same pathogen thus compounding the effect of community transmission. This, in addition to the reduced protective effect of previous infection due to misclassification of re-infections, led to the within household transmission parameter being underestimated in order for the model to account for the observed number of infections. In addition, temporally linking RSV A and B cases as a result of misclassification also led to the effect of symptoms on transmission being overestimated. This suggests that the estimates obtained in the present analysis are likely to change if we further classified the cases into RSV subgroups. This goes to illustrate the importance of making distinctions between pathogens in order to obtain accurate estimates of transmission parameters. At any given moment multiple pathogens are co-circulating in a host population, this household study alone had multiple viruses spreading in large numbers during the time of data collection (
 <xref rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr">Munywoki et al., 2018</xref>). How these pathogens interact could have dramatic implications for parameter estimates, and ultimately on how control strategies are implemented. We have seen the effect of the pneumococcal vaccine on the non-vaccine serotypes and how it might mitigate vaccine effectiveness (
 <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">Kwambana-Adams et al., 2017</xref>) and a study on influenza has shown evidence of its controlling effect on other pathogens (
 <xref rid="bib0230" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al., 2017</xref>). There is an increasing call from such observations to understand how multiple pathogens interact at the host population level.
</p>
