<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While there is a dearth of epidemiological data on coinfections because estimating the role of co-transmission epidemiologically is difficult, some studies have attempted to estimate the proportion of cases with coinfection of those with at least one infection [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. These studies vary in their design—from outbreak reports to prospective studies—and on their definition of the denominator (e.g., some use the number with dengue-like illness and others use the number with a positive test for either virus). Coinfection with chikungunya and dengue virus has been the most frequently studied. For this combination, the proportion with both viruses has been reported to be as high as 38% [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], and is often 5%–10% [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. These high prevalences suggest that co-transmission may contribute to the observed prevalence of coinfection. Because laboratory studies have shown that mosquitoes can be simultaneously coinfected and can co-transmit, the rate of coinfections in humans raises the possibility of chains of co-transmission. Conversely, just one coinfected mosquito has ever been found in the wild, in this case coinfected with chikungunya and dengue virus [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. While this could reflect a lack of coinfections in mosquitoes, it could also be due to infrequent mosquito surveys during simultaneous outbreaks, the fact that mosquitoes are often tested in pools rather than individually, and the low detection of mosquito infections in the field (sometimes only approximately 1:1,000 tested mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]).
</p>
