<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Compartmental models and statistical models such as time series estimation and machine learning can characterize dengue transmission dynamics. Compartmental models model infection as a function of separate compartments, and the evolution of the epidemic may be described by ordinary differential equations [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007839.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, parameter estimation and inputting initial values for compartmental models often only estimate an epidemic curve, but usually cannot explicitly model different endemic and epidemic dynamics [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007839.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Statistical frameworks often characterize time series through autoregressive integrated moving average (ARIMA) modelling or machine learning. ARIMA and machine learning both explain the current realization of infectious disease dynamics by its past observations and past exogenous variables. ARIMA type models have been widely used to fit dengue time serieses [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007839.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] due to the ease of interpretability. Lagged climatic variables have been assessed to affect dengue and influenza transmission counts linearly in temperate climates [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007839.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], but the signal for climatic variables on dengue transmission counts has been found to be weak in tropical climates [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007839.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. A combined approach using time series subsceptible-infected-recovered (TSIR) models takes into account the evolution of population across time as well as autoregressive disease dynamics, was first introduced by Finkenstädt and Grenfell for measles [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007839.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. It was then further developed for modelling multi-strain diseases such as dengue by including cross-immunity dynamics [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007839.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007839.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]
 <sup>,</sup>. A limiting factor of these models is that they cannot account for the plausibly nonlinear and time varying structure of infectious disease transmission across time. Calibration of multi-strain TSIR models also require virological surveillance data, which may not be always available. Machine learning tools such as random forest and least squares shrinkage operator (LASSO) have been proven to outperform ARIMA type models in predictive metrics such as root mean square error for H5N1 [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007839.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] and the ROC in classifying dengue outbreaks respectively [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007839.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. However, these tools have difficulties in inferring the variables driving infectious disease transmission counts and do not have standard confidence intervals to determine model compatibility with data. The variable importance factor calculated for ensemble methods such as random forest remains only asymptotically valid and may not be useful for small count infectious disease time series data [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007839.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].
</p>
