<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recent analyses of the risk of seasonal influenza infection have illuminated the role of birth year imprinting at the HA and NA subtype levels [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat.1008583.g002">Fig 2C</xref>). Those primed by H1N1 (born before 1957) experience partial protection against all seasonal influenza H1N1 viruses throughout life but no advantage against H3N2 infections. The converse is true of those primed by H2N2 or H3N2. It is difficult to disentangle from seasonal data whether this type of subtype-level protection originates from priming with HA and NA, or both, as both hypotheses have similar statistical support. However, seasonal influenza data do not support the contribution of immunity at the HA group level. Computational models are particularly useful here as they take into account age-differences in susceptibility and behavioral factors that drive the risk of influenza infection and propensity to seek care and, in turn, affect the data collected by surveillance systems [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Models of seasonal surveillance data [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] have tested for complex combinations of biological hypotheses such as age-specific risk for finely resolved age groups; birth year risk related to imprinting by HA, NA, or both; antigenic distance from the last season; and demographic age distribution. Existing surveillance data support birth year imprinting by HA and NA, superimposed on age-specific risks and demography [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>].
</p>
