<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The antiviral findings suggest that purified anthocyanin isolated from rich-anthocyanin plants may have an effective role against viral infections (
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">Jassim and Naji, 2003</xref>). Swaminathan et al. reported the anti-InfV effects of cyanidin-3-sambubioside (C3S) isolated from black elderberry (
 <italic>Sambucus nigra</italic>) extract. From the pharmacological mechanistic point of view and according to the molecular docking of this compound, it bound with the 430-cavity adjacent to the residues of InfV neuraminidase. Since this antiviral compound bound remote from Asp 151 and Glu 119, two residues known to regulate the neuraminidase resistance, this compound was shown to have potential as a new class of antiviral drugs against the InfV without this susceptibility (
 <xref rid="B218" ref-type="bibr">Swaminathan et al., 2013</xref>). In their following study on C3S, Kannan et al. indicated that it possessed a high inhibitory activity against H274Y mutation. The inhibitory activity of C3S, oseltamivir and their mechanisms against H274Y mutant-type (MT) and wild-type (WT), were clarified using the quantum chemical methods, molecular dynamics, and molecular docking reasons of drug resistance. Oseltamivir was found to have less binding affinity with MT, while C3S possessed more position and affinity with the proteins of MT and WT. The evidence suggested that C3S had a stronger binding affinity with MT based on the energy of electrostatic interaction and was more potent against the oseltamivir-resistant virus strains (
 <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">Kannan and Kolandaivel, 2018</xref>). In another study, Calland et al. attempted to discover new and novel natural compounds with potent anti-HCV activity and quantify their mode of action. Amongst the eight selected compounds, delphinidin was found to belong to the anthocyanin family and be a proper choice as a new class of flaviviridae inhibitors. The mechanism of action of this compound is that it disrupts the HCV attachment and adsorption by using the E1E2 gp of the envelope of different genotypes for HCV harboring. The time-response activity of delphinidin was also evaluated, and it was shown that its activity against HCV occurred just in the inoculation phase (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Calland et al., 2015</xref>).
</p>
