<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The introduction of highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART) has significantly decreased the rate of Human Immunodeficiency virus (HIV)–related morbidity and mortality [
 <xref rid="pone.0235958.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. However, with the new goal currently endorsed by the joint United Nations program on AIDS (UNAIDS) aimed at ending AIDS by 2030, through the 90-90-90 treatment target by 2020 [
 <xref rid="pone.0235958.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0235958.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], and coupled with the WHO recommendation to test and treat [
 <xref rid="pone.0235958.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], there have been an increase in the on-going scale-up of antiretroviral treatment (ART) most especially in sub-Saharan Africa (SSA) [
 <xref rid="pone.0235958.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. However the increased scale-up has led to undesired consequences like the selection and emergence of HIV drug resistance (HIVDR) variants, which remains a major obstacle, limiting the efficacy of commonly available antiretroviral (ARVs) [
 <xref rid="pone.0235958.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0235958.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. HIVDR remains a huge problem as it currently involves not only patients on antiretroviral-treatment, but equally drug-naïve individuals carrying HIV-resistant strains [
 <xref rid="pone.0235958.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Based on the World Health Organisation (WHO) classification of HIVDR, it is classified into three main categories; pre-treatment drug resistance [PDR, (among ART initiators or re-initiators)], transmitted drug resistance (TDR, among recently-infected individuals), and acquired drug resistance [ADR, (at ART failure)] [
 <xref rid="pone.0235958.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. ADR occurs when HIV mutations emerge as a result of viral replication in individuals receiving ARV drugs. Transmitted HIV drug resistance (TDR) are resistances detected in ARV drug-naive patients with no history of ARV drug exposure. While pre-treatment HIV drug resistance (PDR) is resistance detected in ARV drug-naive people initiating ART or people with prior ARV drug exposure initiating or reinitiating first-line ART. PDR can either be transmitted or acquired drug resistance. It may have been transmitted at the time of infection (TDR), or it may be acquired by virtue of prior ARV drug exposure [
 <xref rid="pone.0235958.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The transmission of HIV-1 drug resistance from treatment-experienced patients to newly infected individuals has been observed in developed countries with access to antiretroviral therapy [
 <xref rid="pone.0235958.ref010" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0235958.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In 2015, a meta-analysis conducted in sub-Saharan Africa (SSA), South/Southeast Asia(SSEA), Upper-income Asian countries, Latin America/Caribbean, Europe and North-America showed the median overall prevalence of transmitted HIV drug resistance was 2,8%, 2,9%, 5.6%, 7.6%, 9.4% and 11.5% respectively [
 <xref rid="pone.0235958.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].
</p>
