<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Rising antimicrobial resistance (AMR) is a threat to modern medicine and it also represents a major economic burden on healthcare systems. In the European Union, antibiotic resistant infections determine an economic burden of ~€1.5 billion per year. The US health system spends 20 billion USD in excess each year to treat resistant infections (
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>). By 2050, it is foreseen that USD100 trillion will be the economic damage due to AMR. According to the World Bank simulation, the global economy could lose as much as 3.8% of its annual gross domestic product by 2050 in a worst-case scenario. However, estimating the incidence and attributable mortality is challenging. This cost depends on a wide variety of factors: which drug and pathogen are involved, the mechanism of antibiotic resistance, the prevalence of that pathogen, the types of infections, the level of transmissibility, the health burden of those infections and whether alternative treatments are available. AMR can result in treatment failures and previously uncomplicated infections become more complex and severe (
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>). It has recently been estimated that a 30% reduction in the efficacy of antibiotic prophylaxis for surgical procedures and chemotherapy would result in 120,000 additional infections and 6,300 infection-related deaths per year only in the United States. There is a risk of the cost being far higher than current best estimates. As already mentioned, vaccines represent a valuable and extraordinary tool to tackle the AMR problem. Besides being able to protect against serious diseases, vaccines may also reduce avoid mild disease episodes that may not receive medical attention, but which have important societal consequences. Vaccination decreases the disease incidence, the number of deaths, the longer hospital stays, and the need for more antibiotics if others fail owing to resistance. Unvaccinated individuals also benefit from wider societal benefits such as the lower transmission rates. This can be translated into a reduced risk of epidemics. In health economics, Incremental Cost–Utility Analysis (ICUA) is a method of financial analysis that can drive procurement decisions. The purpose of ICUA is to perform a cost-effectiveness analysis based on a careful evaluation of the ratio between the cost of an intervention and the benefit it generates in terms of increase in life expectancy. Value of vaccines and drugs is calculated based on the ICUA financial method resulting in an underestimation of the former. The added value of vaccines such as the induction of herd protection, reduction in time of hospitalization and reduction in anti-microbial resistance are difficult to measure in the short term. Therefore, since in the ICUA analysis, the benefits of medical interventions are evaluated during the period of medical observation, important benefits of vaccines which are only measurable in the long term are not considered. Although the ICUA analysis has generated more comprehensive models for financial evaluation, all the benefits of vaccination still need to be included in the analysis for the measurement of a full vaccine value (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>). In 2015, the burden of resistant infections in countries of the European Economic Area (EEA) was measured in terms of number of cases, attributable deaths, and disability-adjusted life-years (DALYs) providing useful information for public health decision-makers prioritizing interventions for infectious diseases (
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>). The contribution of various antibiotic-resistant bacteria to the overall burden varies greatly between countries, thus highlighting the need for prevention and control strategies that are tailored to the needs of each country. Evaluation of the economic cost of AMR is important for decision-making and should be estimated accurately. Only combined efforts in the fields of antibiotics, new technologies for vaccine development and monoclonal antibodies will provide affordable solutions to tackle antimicrobial resistance.
</p>
