<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Neurological complications following ZIKV infection are not limited to cases of congenital infection [
 <xref rid="B18-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Mounting clinical evidence show that ZIKV infection in adult patients may result in encephalitis [
 <xref rid="B18-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], encephalomyelitis [
 <xref rid="B18-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], acute myelitis [
 <xref rid="B18-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], chronic inflammatory demyelinating polyneuropathy [
 <xref rid="B21-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], and Guillain-Barre syndrome [
 <xref rid="B19-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pharmaceuticals-12-00060-f001">Figure 1</xref>B). Episodes of septic shock were also reported, and in rare cases these complications were shown to be fatal [
 <xref rid="B21-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In addition, ZIKV-associated Guillain–Barre syndrome may, in some cases, lead to development of chronic pain [
 <xref rid="B18-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. One study found that 40% of patients still showed some kind of neurological alteration after 1 year of symptom onset, and after two years some patients had not yet fully recovered [
 <xref rid="B25-pharmaceuticals-12-00060" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Collectively, these reports demonstrate that ZIKV infection is also detrimental to the mature nervous system and is associated with a spectrum of neurological syndromes that may culminate in long-term consequences and even mortality. Whether these neurological consequences are a direct effect of ZIKV replication or are secondary to the host immune response still need to be investigated; a question that could lead to important clues on how to prevent long-term consequences of infection. Different research groups have shown beneficial effects of both antiviral and anti-inflammatory strategies in preventing long-term behavioral consequences of infection. These findings are reviewed in the following sections.
</p>
