<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This study is subject to several limitations. Using reports of antecedent illness may lead to several sources of bias, such as the non-specific nature of the symptoms, possible underreporting of acute illnesses by controls, and recall bias in reporting of symptoms by case-patients. Although selection of controls with non-febrile illness risks bias toward over-estimation of the significance of the predictive value of Zika-associated symptoms, analyses including only GBS case-patients who had no febrile illness within 5 days prior to onset of GBS were statistically significantly different from the controls. The limited number of subjects who had ZIKV-specific IgM antibodies tested for is another limitation, as is the inability to do serologic testing for DENV and CHIKV. The finding of up to 22% of GBS case-patients and controls having PCR-positivity for ZIKV was admittedly surprising; ordinarily, it would be expected that persons developing GBS would be outside of the time window for continuing to have ZIKV viremia. In the absence of confirmatory ZIKV-specific neutralization assay testing, we cannot say for certain that a certain amount of false-positivity may not have been present in our PCR results. However, the PCR positivity seemed specific for ZIKV; one might expect that if the problem was general false-positivity, one would observe unusually high percentages of DENV and CHIKV positivity as well, which was not the case. In addition, one might expect that false positivity would have been present in both GBS case-patients and controls; rather, the PCR results seemed preferentially present in the GBS case-patients rather than both case-patients and controls. Controls were obtained to account for geographic location, sex, and age, but other factors such as socioeconomic condition were not controlled for and may have affected some of the findings. Finally, given a finding of 44% of case-patients reporting a diarrheal illness, we were unable to test for enteric pathogens, such as 
 <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic>, which may have contributed to the overall burden of GBS in this group. The lack of a commercially available and standardized ELISA test for detecting anti-
 <italic>Campylobacter</italic> antibodies made pursuing this diagnosis logistically challenging.
</p>
