<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The epidemiological study on hepatitis B showed that the prevalence of HBsAg in the Chinese population was 7.2% [
 <xref rid="B48-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], and it was 3.5% in the Shaanxi population [
 <xref rid="B50-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. In this study, we found that the positive rate of HBsAg for HIV-infected patients in Shaanxi Province was 11.7%, which was higher than the general population in either China or Shaanxi Province. A number of domestic studies have shown that the positive rate of HBsAg in the HIV-infected patients was higher than that of the general population, and it ranged from 13.1% to 19.4% [
 <xref rid="B30-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. However, on the contrary, some studies have reported that in HIV-infected patients, the HBsAg positive rate was slightly lower than that of the national general population. He et al. found that the prevalence of HBsAg was 6.3% through a survey which enrolled 1110 cases of HIV-infected patients in central Shanxi, eastern Zhejiang, southwest Yunnan, and northwestern Xinjiang [
 <xref rid="B51-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Ding et al. reported that the positive rate of HBsAg was 5.3% through a retrospective cohort study of HIV-positive individuals receiving combination antiretroviral therapy (cART) between 2004–2016 [
 <xref rid="B34-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The reasons for the inconsistency may be related to many factors such as region, age structure, ethnicity, time of investigation, and transmission routes, indicating that there are certain differences in HBV infection status among HIV-positive individuals in different areas, and further confirmed the necessity of HBV survey in HIV-positive cases of this region.
</p>
