<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In recent years, the co-infection of HIV and syphilis has been on the rise in China, especially in MSM. The rate of syphilis was 26.0% in this study, which was the highest of the three monitored diseases, especially as high as 37.1% in MSM. The result was consistent with foreign studies on syphilis epidemics in both HIV-positive MSM and MSM [
 <xref rid="B58-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. In China, Li et al. found that the rate of syphilis was as high as 32.8% in HIV-positive MSM [
 <xref rid="B35-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Among the HIV-positive individuals with antibodies of TP, the infection rate of homosexual transmission was so higher but heterosexual transmission was lower (OR = 0.549 95% CI: 0.382–0.789), suggesting that homosexual transmission might be a risk factor resulting in HIV co-infection with syphilis. HIV and syphilis are both sexually transmitted, and lots of people are infected with both pathogens. On one hand, HIV has several effects on the presentation, diagnosis, disease progression, and therapy of syphilis. On the other hand, syphilis can increase the risk of HIV transmission by causing genital ulcers [
 <xref rid="B62-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Therefore, syphilis is a special and important infection because of the morbidity it can enhance the transmission of HIV [
 <xref rid="B63-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. In patients co-infected with HIV and syphilis, cutaneous lesions become more severe, symptomatic neuro-syphilis may be more likely to develop, the latency period before the development of meningo-vascular syphilis may be shorter, and the efficacy of standard therapy for early syphilis may be reduced [
 <xref rid="B64-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Moreover, it is worrying that studies show that about 50% of individuals co-infected with syphilis were asymptomatic for syphilis in HIV-positive MSM [
 <xref rid="B65-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Therefore, screening for syphilis should be strengthened in both MSM and HIV-positive MSM. In this study, the infection rate of syphilis was 38.8% in college education or above, followed by 26.3% in high school/technical secondary school. Overall, there is no evidence that high education is a risk factor for syphilis infection, through multivariate logistic regression analysis or literature reports. This phenomenon may be caused by the high proportion of MSM in the group with high education.
</p>
