<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Tea polyphenols from green tea mainly consist of catechins ((−)-epigallocatechin gallate (EGCG), (−)-epicatechin gallate (ECG) and (−)-epigallocatechin (EGC)). Their ability to inhibit several different viruses was evaluated. Among the catechins, the EGCG and ECG were found to be potent inhibitors of influenza virus replication in MDCK cell culture and this effect was observed in all influenza virus subtypes tested, including A/H1N1, A/H3N2 and B virus (Demeule et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42_3">2002</xref>). However, the sensitivity in hemagglutination inhibition was widely different among three different subtypes of influenza viruses tested. Quantitative RT-PCR analysis revealed that, at high concentration, EGCG and ECG also suppressed viral RNA synthesis in MDCK cells whereas EGC failed to show similar effect (Song et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR166_3">2005</xref>). Similarly, EGCG and ECG inhibited the neuraminidase activity more effectively than the EGC (Song et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR166_3">2005</xref>). The results show that the 3-galloyl group of catechin skeleton plays an important role on the observed antiviral activity, whereas the 5′-OH at the trihydroxy benzyl moiety at 2-position plays a minor role (Song et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR166_3">2005</xref>). In addition, EGCG has not only potential use as adjunctive therapy in HIV-1 infection (Williamson et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR184_3">2006</xref>), but has greater anti-HSV activity than other green tea catechins and inactivates multiple clinical isolates of HSV-1 and HSV-2 by binding to gB, gD, or another envelope glycoprotein, it appears to be a promising candidate for use in a microbicide to reduce HSV transmission (Isaacs et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71_3">2008</xref>). Among green tea chatechins, EGCG was the most effective when added to the cells during the transition from the early to the late phase of adenovirus infection, suggesting that EGCG inhibits one or more late steps in virus infection (Webster et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR183_3">2006</xref>). It is worth to mention that Veregen (80% catechins) as a prescription drug for condyloma treatment was approved by US FDA in 2006, suggesting that medicinal plants will open up new prospects for the pharmaceutical industry (Reuter et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR144_3">2010</xref>).
</p>
