<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The discovery of defectiveness in RSV was an exciting and important event in the evolution of tumor virology. However, there were other strains of avian sarcoma in circulation, notably in Europe. These included the Prague strain of RSV [
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], the Carr–Zilber and Schmidt–Ruppin strains [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] and the independently isolated avian sarcoma virus referred to as Bratislava 77 (B77) [
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Several of these strains were studied for their activity in mammals [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. In contrast to the Bryan high-titer strain, they showed significant ability to induce tumors in rodents and other laboratory animals and to transform mammalian cells in culture. Jan Svoboda was a pioneer in this area. In one of his groundbreaking studies, he showed that rat cells transformed by the Prague strain of RSV failed to release infectious virus. However, co-cultivation of these cells with chicken embryo fibroblasts led to the production of infectious RSV [
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. This observation on mammalian cells provided more compelling evidence than could be derived from chicken “non-producing” cells for the general conclusion that infectious virus replication was not required for oncogenic transformation. Since no helper virus had to be added to achieve virus replication in the chicken–rat co-cultures, these experiments also suggested that the Prague strain of RSV was non-defective, capable of both replication and transformation. The non-defectiveness of the Prague strain of RSV was soon confirmed in avian cell culture [
 <xref rid="B38-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. RNA analysis also showed the Schmidt–Ruppin and Carr–Zilber strains of RSV and the B77 avian sarcoma virus to be non-defective [
 <xref rid="B39-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].
</p>
