<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In conjunction with the above, HERV elements are known to trigger innate immune responses due to their viral features (viral mimicry effect). HERV antigens (including nucleic acids or proteins) that are expressed in cells may act as pathogen-associated molecular patterns (PAMPs) that could be detected by the innate immunity pattern recognition receptors (PRRs), leading to the activation of innate immune responses, including downstream pro-inflammatory signals and the induction of subsequent adaptive immune responses [
 <xref rid="B5-viruses-12-00852" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B76-viruses-12-00852" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. Essentially, the host cell interprets the induced expression of HERV molecules as a sign of infection by an exogenous virus and mounts an antiviral innate immune response. For instance, it has been shown that the ERV avian leukosis virus-derived antisense long ncRNA in the chicken embryonic fibroblasts can stimulate the TLR3 pathway to induce an antiviral innate immune state against infection by other exogenous retroviruses [
 <xref rid="B45-viruses-12-00852" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Another example is the HERV-W Env, which can interact with receptors of the TLR4-lipopolysaccharide (LPS) pathway, including TLR4 and CD14, and induce pro-inflammatory cytokines such as IL-1β, IL-6, and TNF-α [
 <xref rid="B77-viruses-12-00852" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Finally, with implication for cancer treatment, it has been recently shown that radiation-induced ERV-associated dsRNA transcription in mouse melanoma cells promotes the activation of the innate antiviral MDA5/MAVS/TBK1 pathway, leading to the downstream transcription of IFN-stimulated genes and resulting in anti-tumor response [
 <xref rid="B78-viruses-12-00852" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. The overall consequence of this viral mimicry is thought to weaken the cancer cells and attract cytotoxic T cells to the previously “immune-cold” tumor microenvironment, leading to tumor destruction.
</p>
