<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Four routes of transmission are widely described for influenza viruses: droplet, aerosol, faecal-oral and direct contact [
 <xref rid="B89-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. Droplet transmission describes exhaled particles &gt;10 µm which are deposited into the upper respiratory tract, whereas aerosol droplets are typically less than 5 µm and can reach the lower respiratory tract [
 <xref rid="B89-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. Contact transmission relies on the transfer of particles to mucous membranes directly, or via a fomite intermediate. For a successful transmission event to occur, enough virus must persist long enough in the external environment to reach the target tissue. Transmission is therefore determined via several viral, host, and environmental aspects, including: (i) The major site of viral replication and viral titres shed; (ii) The distance and frequency between contacts and (iii) Environmental conditions and virus stability. In wild aquatic birds such as ducks and gulls AIVs generally exhibit gastrointestinal tropism and are thought to be spread primarily through the oral-faecal route. In poultry adapted AIVs, there exists some heterogeneity in tropism and transmission routes. HPAIV, such as H5N1, have a systemic distribution and are probably transmitted by a combination of the oral-faecal route and airborne transmission, whereas, LPAIVs in chickens tend to show more respiratory tropism, though some strains also show gastrointestinal tropism [
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B84-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>,
 <xref rid="B90-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>,
 <xref rid="B91-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>,
 <xref rid="B92-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>,
 <xref rid="B93-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. One of the key molecular markers that facilitates adaptation of an AIV from wild aquatic birds to poultry is the deletion of amino acids from the stalk domain of NA, which have been shown to mediate the switch to respiratory tropism in chickens [
 <xref rid="B94-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>,
 <xref rid="B95-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. There is good evidence to suggest that many LPAIV strains transmit by the airborne route, the oral-faecal route and the waterborne route [
 <xref rid="B84-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>,
 <xref rid="B92-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>,
 <xref rid="B96-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. However, the favoured mechanism of transmission between individuals varies by host species and viral strain. 
</p>
