<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">As far as it concerns the demographic history of this mosquito, six gene pools/lineages (clusters) were detected across the invaded regions at the macrogeographic level. The data clearly suggest that the invasion process of this mosquito fits a demographic model of historical lineage diversification through admixture events among different genetic compositions as summarized in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>. The lineage divergence times we inferred from genetic data (ABC, STRUCTURE) are congruent with the available historical documentation on the different steps of the invasion process, thus providing a picture of the history of this mosquito outside its home range over the last 200 years. In Southeast Asia, a high level of lineage-sharing is displayed by the ancestral Chinese and, to a lesser degree, by the derived Thai and Japanese populations, supporting high coancestry in this home range area (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The historical trade networks across East Asian maritime space, the ‘China seas’, may have promoted the diffusion of propagules to Thailand and Japan resulting in an increase in diversity and favouring expansion and adaptation. As illustrated in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, we inferred that 
 <italic>K</italic>6 (red) and 
 <italic>K</italic>4 (green) were the first ancestral lineages that historically emerged from Southeast Asia. 
 <italic>K</italic>6, highly represented in China, is the lineage that may correspond to the primary invasion route within East Asia (Thailand and Japan) and, out of this area, to Indian Ocean La Réunion in the 18th century, to Hawaii in 1895, to the Mediterranean area starting from 1979 and to the USA in 1985
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic>K</italic>4 is highly present in Thailand and contributed to the ancient colonization of the west coast of La Réunion, to the USA, and to the recent outbreaks in the Mediterranean area, Greece and partially to Cesena (IT1)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>. A spatial extension of 
 <italic>K</italic>6 and 
 <italic>K</italic>4 from the western side of La Réunion (St Pierre, RE) to the eastern part of the island (PROV and STD) gave rise to the 
 <italic>K</italic>2 lineage diversification (orange). Habitat structuring and strong climatic differences between the east and western coasts of La Réunion may have supported this diversification
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic>K</italic>2 expanded its range out of La Réunion and became established in the French Mediterranean area of Bar Sur Loup (BL) in 2004. La Réunion is a major trading partner of Continental France and most of this international trade passes through the main port and the international airport at St Denis on the north-east coast where 
 <italic>K</italic>2 was established (PROV and STD). 
 <italic>K</italic>6 and 
 <italic>K</italic>4 were almost lost in the invasion process of the Americas. In North America, they contributed to the diversification of the 
 <italic>K</italic>3 lineage (grey in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) which is the major component of the 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> genomes in Florida and Missouri. Indeed, within a year of its introduction in Texas in 1985
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup>, it was found in Florida and then rapidly expanded throughout the south-east coast and part of north-central and north-east USA due to internal trade and multiple introductions from Japan/South Asia and Hawaii. According to our data and historical records, Florida played a key role in introducing this mosquito in South America in 1986 and later, in Central America, Mexico and Panama in 2002 and 2004, respectively
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, Florida can be considered as a successful bridgehead invasive population which favoured the extension of 
 <italic>K</italic>3 (grey in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) in Central America and the divergence of 
 <italic>K</italic>1 (cyan) in Brazil with its subsequent diffusion within that country and in Argentina. In South America, the Rio Grande do Norte (PNM) and Rio de Janeiro (JRB) states appear to have played a role in the spread of the 
 <italic>K</italic>1 lineage. A particular case is provided by the genetic signature of Brazilian mosquitoes present in the Central Amazonian state (Manaus) since 2002. Unlike the other Brazilian mosquitoes, they display a higher proportion of the ancient Southeast Asian 
 <italic>K</italic>5 lineage (0.450), with respect to the 
 <italic>K</italic>1 Brazilian component which is unexpectedly low (0.240) and that of North Central America, 
 <italic>K</italic>3, is even lower (0.167). The high 
 <italic>K</italic>5 lineage component may be explained by the contribution that Southeast Asia/Japan provided to the origin of Manaus mosquitoes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>
 </sup>. Manaus is one of the four free trade areas in Brazil and its port is a commercial centre for ocean-going shipping and the main transport hub for the Amazon basin. We found the 
 <italic>K</italic>5 lineage well established in mosquitoes from Congo in Central Africa as a derivation from Amazonian Manaus. How this area could be implicated in the introduction of this mosquito to Congo is an open question although it is noteworthy that this inference was derived from a sample collected in 2011; the year of the first record of this mosquito in this area. Several authors have also proposed that propagules originating from South America could have contributed to an expansion in Africa.
</p>
