<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">The most recent divergent American lineages, 
 <italic>K</italic>1 (South America) and especially, the North and Central American lineage 
 <italic>K</italic>3, displayed the lowest CHIKV dissemination and transmission efficiencies of all studied populations. Indeed, 
 <italic>K</italic>3 is a heterogeneous lineage with USA populations such as Florida/Vero Beach that displayed lower CHIKV dissemination and transmission efficiencies (Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref>; Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>). Vega-Rúa and colleagues
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup> and Honório and colleagues
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup> using the three CHIKV strains of this study (ASIA, ECSA E1-226A and ECSA E1-226V) performed comparative analyses of vector competence using 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> populations across the Americas. All the populations of both species were susceptible to infection and dissemination of the different CHIKV genotypes. However, the transmission rates were heterogeneous even among populations from the same species with 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> from Brazil, and generally from South America, having higher transmission efficiency for ECSA genotypes when compared to their counterparts from Florida, USA. The first detection of CHIKV in the Americas was recorded in the Caribbean in late 2013, followed by a dramatic spread of the virus throughout the continent. It has been stated that CHIKV arrived in Brazil through two independent introductions: the Asian genotype from the Caribbean entered through the northern region, while the African ECSA genotype was imported through the north-east region
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>
 </sup>. Following their initial introduction, both genotypes established and expanded their range with CHIKV-ASIA being the prevalent genotype causing several outbreaks in relation to the presence of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> that was the main vector implicated in the transmission
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>. In 2014, local transmission of CHIKV-ASIA was detected in the Amazon region. A distinct lineage CHIKV-ECSA was detected simultaneously and it rapidly spread inducing replacement of the Asian genotype in the Brazilian Amazonian region
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>
 </sup>. Whether this replacement was due to the spread of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> in this region and its transmission capacity for these particular ECSA strains, which do not harbour the E1-226V mutation, is an open question that deserves further investigation.
</p>
