<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Unlike previous studies in which the growth of WNV mutants in AMCR monocytes predicted viremia potential and virulence[
 <xref rid="pntd.0007473.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], all viruses grew relatively well in chicken (HD11) monocytes herein, indicating fundamental differences in the relative utility for avian cells from alternative avian sources with lessened susceptibility (chickens) to WNV to model avian virulence phenotypes in highly susceptible birds (AMCRs). In previous reports, HD11 cells had demonstrated restricted growth for a Mexican isolate of WNV lacking a glycosylation motif (NYP) with limited avian virulence potential in AMCRs[
 <xref rid="pntd.0007473.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. The attenuated phenotype was subsequently attributed to both the NYP mutation in addition to a prM mutation and full attenuation effects were observed in the presence of both mutations in AMCRs, HOSPs and House finches[
 <xref rid="pntd.0007473.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Significantly lower viral loads in young chicks inoculated with a non-glycosylated (NYP) WNV plaque variant when compared to glycosylated (NYS) WNV have also been reported[
 <xref rid="pntd.0007473.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] leading the investigators to ascribe the phenotypic differences to the loss of glycosylation; however, other sequence alterations in the plaque variants and the specific effect of the amino acid polymorphism, independent of glycosylation, could mediate these phenotypes. Herein, the most significantly debilitated phenotypes in AMCRs were observed in birds inoculated with the KYS and NYP mutants that both lacked glycosylation signals but were imparted by different mutations within the glycosylation signal sequence. Alternative mutations that also ablated glycosylation by different amino acid substitutions at these same loci, SYS/NYF, had minor effects on avian viremia potential in AMCRs. Similar observations were made with HOSPs with the exception of the SYS mutant which showed an attenuated viremia much like KYS and NYP.As potential further support of the role of the amino acid identity at these positions for dictating phenotypes independent of glycosylation status, it is intriguing that both mutants that showed the most significant mosquito and avian competence differences KYS and NYP also encoded the most non-conservative amino acid substitutions. These consisted of a polar, uncharged asparagine substituted with a positively charged lysine (E-N154K) or a polar uncharged serine substituted with an aromatic ringed, hydrophobic proline (E-S156P) for KYS and NYP mutants, respectively.
</p>
