<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Testing compounds that have anecdotal evidence suggesting that they may have antiviral activity often revolves around natural products. Various natural products have been reported to have anti-HCMV activity linked to inhibition of IE expression or function, but most remain largely unsubstantiated beyond initial observations. However, a considerable body of evidence has been generated with respect to the anti-HCMV activity of natural product artemisinin, its semi-synthetic derivative artesunate and various related compounds. Artemisinin is a natural product derived from the plant 
 <italic>Artemisia annua</italic> (Sweet Wormwood), a herb used in traditional Chinese medicine [
 <xref rid="B317-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">317</xref>,
 <xref rid="B318-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">318</xref>]. Artemisinin and its derivatives are best known for effective antimalarial activity and treatment [
 <xref rid="B317-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">317</xref>,
 <xref rid="B318-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">318</xref>], which provided the premise for testing artesunate for anti-HCMV activity [
 <xref rid="B319-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">319</xref>]. Artesunate, along with various related compounds, exhibit in vitro inhibitory activity against laboratory, clinical and drug-resistant strains of HCMV in a range of cell types with EC
 <sub>50</sub> values generally in the low micromolar to sub-micromolar range [
 <xref rid="B319-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">319</xref>,
 <xref rid="B320-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">320</xref>,
 <xref rid="B321-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">321</xref>,
 <xref rid="B322-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">322</xref>,
 <xref rid="B323-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">323</xref>,
 <xref rid="B324-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">324</xref>,
 <xref rid="B325-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">325</xref>,
 <xref rid="B326-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">326</xref>,
 <xref rid="B327-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">327</xref>,
 <xref rid="B328-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">328</xref>,
 <xref rid="B329-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">329</xref>]. Chemically linking artemisinin-related molecules into dimers and trimers significantly improves antiviral potency [
 <xref rid="B320-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">320</xref>,
 <xref rid="B324-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">324</xref>,
 <xref rid="B325-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">325</xref>,
 <xref rid="B326-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">326</xref>,
 <xref rid="B330-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">330</xref>,
 <xref rid="B331-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">331</xref>]. Examples include artemisinin-derived dimer diphenyl phosphate (838), a potent, selective HCMV inhibitor with irreversible activity [
 <xref rid="B332-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">332</xref>,
 <xref rid="B333-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">333</xref>] and trimeric artesunate derivative TF27 [
 <xref rid="B326-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">326</xref>], which exhibits potent in vitro and in vivo activity in the MCMV model [
 <xref rid="B329-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">329</xref>]. Hybridization of artemisinin-derivatives with bioactive molecules, such as quinazoline, has produced novel compounds with potent anti-HCMV activity significantly better than parental compounds and GCV [
 <xref rid="B334-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">334</xref>,
 <xref rid="B335-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">335</xref>,
 <xref rid="B336-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">336</xref>,
 <xref rid="B337-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">337</xref>].
</p>
