<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0035">Choline is present in some dietary supplements/foods and belongs to the Vitamin B family. Choline is naturally found in many plant-based products like beans and cruciferous vegetables including dried nuts, whole grains, and seeds 
 <xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. It’s also found in animal-based products like poultry, dairy products, meat, eggs, and fish. It is one of the phytoconstituents extracted from herbal plants like 
 <italic>tinospora cordifolia</italic>, 
 <italic>withania somnifera</italic>
 <xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Choline is endogenously produced in human liver as phosphatidylcholine. However, the amount of endogenously produced choline is not enough to meet our needs 
 <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. Choline plays a very significant role in forming of human genes, various metabolism process, and lipid transport. Choline:Urea (1:2) eutectic mixture is used as a reaction medium known as deep eutectic solvent (DES) for different nucleic acids 
 <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. Due to its water free storage capacity the mixture can be used as reaction medium for different biocatalytic reactions and as long-term storage medium at high temperature also 
 <xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. It can act as a nano-crowder to protect protein structure from denaturation 
 <xref rid="b0170" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. It helps the cell membranes to connect and communicate within the whole body. Choline composed DES can be used in different enzymatic reactions to obtain the green chemical processes 
 <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. Choline is an important component of breast milk on which the fetal development of a child is dependent during the early birth stages. Medical studies reveal that proper intake of choline supplements by would be mothers can protect the infants from neurodegenerative diseases like Down syndrome, Alzheimer’s diseases 
 <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. Choline is a direct precursor of Ach (acetylcholine) which is a neurotransmitter that controls a large number of autonomic, cognitive, and motor functions 
 <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. As per the medical studies, if choline is taken by the mother during pregnancy, this would make the newborn baby capable enough to mitigate the risks of CoV2 infections 
 <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. Reports also suggest that prenatal choline supplement is capable of brain development of unborn child by decreasing the effect of various viral respiratory infections like deficit disorder, schizophrenia including COVID-19 
 <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. Like other coronaviruses, COVID-19 disease can destroy a child’s respiratory organs and also hamper brain development adversely by inciting the maternal immune response 
 <xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. As per Freeman et al higher maternal choline levels at 16 months gestation can diminish the effects of inflammation in the children’s behaviors at 3 months of age 
 <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. Though the effects of choline in COVID-19 infection on infant development are still unknown, still all available medical data validate the fact that choline supplements may help to maintain the higher prenatal choline level to protect the early fetal brain development of the infants so that infants may survive in a healthy manner though the mother get affected by the CoV2 infection 
 <xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0205" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. However, not much research justifying this hypothesis has been conducted until now. Rigorous investigation is still needed to explore the connection between choline and SARS CoV2 infections and to determine whether choline can act as a potential inhibitor against the receptor protein CoV2 main protease and to be used as potential drug so that choline supplements might benefit patients with COVID-19 disease. For understanding the stability and activity of a specific inhibitor on a receptor enzyme at different experimental conditions is known as bottleneck for successful drug designing. Counteraction effects of choline as DES mixture have already proved their effectivity in maintaining native conformational stability and activity of proteins and enzymes in aqueous solutions 
 <xref rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. For the present study we have downloaded the structure of choline in PDB format from Drugbank (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.drugbank.ca/drugs" id="ir005" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.drugbank.ca/drugs</ext-link>) (
 <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>b). We have also done the proper virtual screening by evaluating their drug-likeness, pharmacokinetics and lipophilicity properties which are a set of guidelines for identification of potential drug compounds (
 <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> ). Some mostly industry applicable drug-likeness rules are: “Lipinski's rule”, “MDDR-like rule”, “Veber’s rule”, “Ghose filter”, “Egan rule”, “Muegge rule”, etc 
 <xref rid="b0220" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0225" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0235" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. SWISS-ADME software (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.swissadme.ch" id="ir010" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.swissadme.ch</ext-link>) has helped us in applying different virtual screening methods. For Molecular docking study, ligand choline has been saved in pdbqt format by Auto Dock Tools 1.5.6 
 <xref rid="b0240" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>.
</p>
