<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In light of meaningful global action for the public good, at what level should one come to terms with rabies in the 21st century? Management, control, prevention, elimination, eradication, and so on are often freely bandied about together in today’s lexicon of disease deliberations but are not synonymous terms. Unlike smallpox or rinderpest, rabies is not a candidate for actual eradication today, given the extent of host breadth and diversity. However, rabies has at least three major attributes in common with those other two extinct viral pathogens: validated diagnostic protocols, safe and effective vaccines, and the epidemiological insight to apply those laboratory tools and licensed biologics for sound prevention and control practices. Somewhat paradoxically, based upon a century of experience, modern rabies management accomplishes, in a truly One Health capacity, what no other comparable zoonosis program can achieve in tandem: human cases prevented by avoiding defined exposure and seeking prophylaxis after exposure; primary canine and secondary species infections eliminated, by mass immunization; and significantly, wild carnivore viral perpetuation interrupted via oral vaccination efforts on a landscape scale. Building upon such apparent progress, this review aims to provoke renewed discussions on several of the current issues and challenges related to modern lyssavirus taxonomy, phylogeny, surveillance, prevention, treatment, control, and elimination, based in part upon the opinions of the authors, representing more than a century of collective person-years of introspective knowledge, skills, and abilities in the field—not as an historical aside alone, but rather within the context of evidence from the peer-reviewed literature, focusing upon relevant publications primarily within the past few years 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>– 
  <xref rid="ref-115" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>
 </sup>. Our hope is, in some small manner, to educate, enlighten, engage, and enable others to participate meaningfully in these remaining endeavors, within the realm of a ‘science of conviction’.
</p>
