<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recombinant technology has been employed to engineer live vector vaccines to express target antigens. The vectors usually have minimal replicative ability to allow immune stimulation without causing infection. Delivery of vector vaccines via the mucosal routes mimics the natural infection, inducing strong mucosal, systemic, and cellular immunities against micro-organisms. Many candidate vectors. e.g., bacillus subtilis [
 <xref rid="B127-viruses-12-00862" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>], Fowlpox virus [
 <xref rid="B128-viruses-12-00862" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>], herpesvirus of turkey (HVT) [
 <xref rid="B129-viruses-12-00862" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>], Newcastle disease virus (NDV) [
 <xref rid="B130-viruses-12-00862" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>] were used for AIVs defenses. For mucosal vaccination, live vector vaccines can simultaneously express different antigens to prevent and treat a variety of diseases. The antigen presenting system can be targeted to the mucosa in which it survives and multiplies, and then carried antigens of the vaccines are expressed as the bacteria or viruses proliferate in the body. As one of the most characterized viral vectors, NDV has been utilized for expressing diverse influenza antigens, including HA and NA [
 <xref rid="B130-viruses-12-00862" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>,
 <xref rid="B131-viruses-12-00862" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>]. Studies on H5N1 or H7N9 HA expressing NDV have obtained positive results [
 <xref rid="B130-viruses-12-00862" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>,
 <xref rid="B132-viruses-12-00862" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>]. H5 and H7 vaccines using NDV as the vector can elicit high levels of Abs against HI and protect chickens from infection with H7N9 or HPAI H5N1 virus, indicative of the effectiveness of NDV-vectored influenza vaccines. Likewise, HVT has been used as a viral vector for constructing avian influenza vaccines. A recombinant vector vaccine rHVT-H9 expressing the H9N2 HA was shown to be capable of inducing robust cellular and humoral immunities in chickens. Strikingly, it was found that rHVT-H9 causes no severe adverse effects, showing its potential as a universal influenza vaccine [
 <xref rid="B129-viruses-12-00862" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>].
</p>
