<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Many prospective serological and clinical studies were used to investigate HIV infections and the development of AIDS and related clinical syndromes among high-risk populations such as gay men, injection drug users, persons with hemophilia, and their contacts. Some of the earliest studies were based on cohort methods using sera originally collected for evaluation of HBV vaccine, and others started afresh with a new cohort [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. The findings in the New York [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>] and San Francisco cohorts [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] were as follows: (1) the prevalence level of HIV antibody was 6.6 % in New York at entry into the study in 1978, and rose to 10.6 % by 1984; (2) in San Francisco the entering prevalence was 4.5 % in 1978, but rose dramatically to 73.1 % by 1985; and (3) the rate of viral infection (seroconversion) among those lacking antibody on entry was 5.5–10.6 % per year in New York and 11.2 % in San Francisco. Among gay and bisexual men entering the Multicenter AIDS Cohort Study (MACS) in Baltimore, Chicago, Los Angeles, and Pittsburgh in late 1984 and early 1985 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>], seroprevalence ranged from 23 to 49 %. In a pattern similar to those in other cohorts, the incidence rate of new infection in the MACS, documented at 3–5 % per year in early 1985, declined rapidly during the next 3 years to about 1 % [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. In Africa and Thailand, measurements of seroprevalence and incidence among prostitutes and other high-risk groups have repeatedly demonstrated the alarming increases that have taken place over a very few years. Transfusion-associated HIV infection systematically documented through serosurveillance of hemophiliacs and other recipients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>], soon after known parenteral exposure, provided an important resource for comparative research on the natural history of HIV infections and the development of AIDS. Further details of serological studies of HIV infection can be found in 10.1007/978-1-4899-7448-8_43.
</p>
