<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">Already in the early 1900s, autopsies from patients who succumbed during major influenza epidemics showed mostly secondary effects of hypoxemia, shock, or the consequences of secondary bacterial pneumonia leading to bacterial meningitis. Some reported 
 <italic>“neurologic and mental disturbances</italic>” and coma, leading to the umbrella term “influenza encephalitis” [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Few studies published autopsy details on brain cutting but reported a “hemorrhagic encephalitis” (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]: 
 <italic>The cut surfaces of the brain in practically every instance presented an excessive number of bleeding points. They were most pronounced in the white matter of the hemispheres, but occasionally the corpus thalamus was especially involved …“Microscopically, intense congestion of the vessels and numerous minute hemorrhagic foci were encountered.”</italic> (Furthermore, 
 <italic>“the brain was generally congested,</italic> [with] 
 <italic>hyperemia and focal hemorrhages being very frequent… The changes were more marked in the cerebrum, while the cerebellum, medulla, pons, and spinal cord showed relatively slight alterations.”… “Suppurative meningitis, due to secondary invaders, was present in 20 per cent.”</italic>) In autopsies performed during the 1957 Asian Flu pandemic, “convulsive seizures and coma” were noted “without localizing signs occurring after several days of mild respiratory symptoms” [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Grossly, the brain showed severe diffuse swelling but without inflammatory cell infiltrate. The coroners from the greater Cleveland area concluded, “In none of the cases reported in the literature or in this series are there any changes that satisfy the criteria for a diagnosis of encephalitis.” The manner in which the nervous system was involved remained unknown.
</p>
