<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Bunnik et al. suggested this hypothesis first and found pieces of evidence of this repercussion at the population level [
 <xref rid="B72-vaccines-07-00074" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Comparing HIV-1 variants isolated shortly after seroconversion from patients of the Amsterdam Cohort either early in the epidemic (1985–1989) or later (2003–2006), they found an increasing resistance of subtype B viruses to NAbs during the course of the epidemic. We confirmed the phenomenon in another cohort of seroconvertors in France, among individuals infected by subtype B viruses at three periods of the epidemic, spanning more than 20 years (1987–2010) [
 <xref rid="B62-vaccines-07-00074" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-vaccines-07-00074" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. The same trend was observed using either sera from HIV-1 infected individuals or bnAbs [
 <xref rid="B72-vaccines-07-00074" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-vaccines-07-00074" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. This evolution was also observed more recently for T/F viruses of subtype C infecting individuals from several sub-Saharan African countries [
 <xref rid="B60-vaccines-07-00074" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] and for T/F viruses of clade CRF02_AG infecting individuals in France [
 <xref rid="B61-vaccines-07-00074" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Through the analysis of 
 <italic>env</italic> sequences, these studies showed that the continued diversification of HIV-1 over time was associated with increasing resistance to NAbs (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="vaccines-07-00074-f004">Figure 4</xref>). Concordant observations in different locations, at different periods of time, and for different genotypes allows us to conclude that there is a drift towards increasing resistance to neutralization of HIV-1 at the population level, which may reflect an adaptation of HIV-1 to the human species. This finding may have major consequences for vaccine development. In addition, the potency of the neutralizing response measured in HIV-1 infected individuals tends to decrease over time [
 <xref rid="B72-vaccines-07-00074" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-vaccines-07-00074" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], possibly due to the evolution of HIV-1 to become less immunogenic, though confounding factors might exist. Still, there is other evidence of HIV-1 adaptation at the population level, both an adaptation to human immune cellular responses [
 <xref rid="B74-vaccines-07-00074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>] and an evolution towards greater virulence [
 <xref rid="B75-vaccines-07-00074" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>,
 <xref rid="B76-vaccines-07-00074" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>,
 <xref rid="B77-vaccines-07-00074" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. 
</p>
