<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Government should take immediate steps to establish an effective active surveillance to ensure early detection of the infection which is crucial for the control of the epidemics if any. Whole country need to be covered under such surveillance, especially in 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> prone areas, halftracks, and the border region. To keep the surveillance in action, a high-power ZIKV surveillance and monitoring unit should be formed with relevant experts under the Ministry of Health and Family Welfare. A surveillance unit needs to be set up at the respective immigration area such as in airport, land, and seaport. The ZIKV specific symptoms showed by overseas visitors and having history of travel in Zika endemic region should be tested by rapid Zika diagnosis kit followed by taking necessary action for further confirmation and quarantine. The unit should also keep close liaison with other organizations, professionals, research institutes, hospitals, and Non-Government Organizations. Institute of Epidemiology, Disease Control and Research could play a vital role in Zika surveillance. Engagement of international organizations such as Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO), WHO, and CDC is also crucial for the surveillance activities for logistics and other supports. Establishment of national Arbovirus reference laboratory for ZIKV and other related virus also need to be established following the WHO’s algorithm for detecting the viruses (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="figure3">Fig. 3</xref>). Veterinarian-physician collaborative research and One Health approach should be conducted to find whether Zika infection is silently circulating in human or domestic animals or non-human primates. Intensive studies of the ZIKV and the possible changes in their genomes/pathogenicity must be reconfirmed, which may reveal genetic and mutational data for updating the fundamentals of the viral biology (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="figure4">Fig. 4</xref>) [
 <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="ref72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>–
 <xref rid="ref74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>].
</p>
