<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Zika virus is a mosquito-borne virus. Control of mosquitoes is therefore the most important step to control the disease. Since Zika, Dengue, and Chikungunya are transmitted by same vector, i.e., 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> spp., the control strategies for mosquitoes are similar [
 <xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Integrated mosquito management (IMM) or integrated vector management (IVM) approach to control mosquitoes are in practice in many countries of the world. Local Government needs to make sure that IMM or IVM is practiced in Bangladesh for the control of mosquitoes. These methods allow reducing the mosquito population and thereby reducing the spread of viruses like Zika, Dengue, and Chikungunya. According to CDC, mosquitoes can be controlled by two main strategies; the professional of local government should apply standard action to destroy the larvae and adult’s mosquitoes followed by the evaluation of effectiveness. In a recent study from International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh, it was found that mosquitoes are increasingly getting resistance against insecticides in Bangladesh (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bdnews24.com/bangladesh/2019/06/27/dhaka-mosquitoes-are-insecticide-resistant-icddrb-study-finds" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://bdnews24.com/bangladesh/2019/06/27/dhaka-mosquitoes-are-insecticide-resistant-icddrb-study-finds</ext-link>). This is very alarming, as evident from recent outbreak of Dengue in Bangladesh, where in many instances, insecticides used in Dhaka city were not found effective against mosquitoes. On the other hand, around 25 mosquitoes species might be carrier of ZIKV [
 <xref rid="ref75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Therefore, it is necessary to reconfirm the vector biology and transmission of ZIKV considering the geographical perspective of Bangladesh. However, more funding need to be allocated for studying insecticide resistance and reconfirmation of vector biology which will be helpful for developing effective insecticides for mosquitoes control (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="figure4">Fig. 4</xref>).
</p>
