<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Among the CHIKV structural proteins, E2 and E1 are envelope proteins present on mature virions [
 <xref rid="pone.0208851.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0208851.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. E2 is known to act as a receptor-binding protein and is exposed on the periphery of the CHIKV particle [
 <xref rid="pone.0208851.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. E2 has high immunogenicity and is a target for current vaccine development [
 <xref rid="pone.0208851.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. However, as a target for antigen detection, E2 presents several challenges. Notably, among the CHIKV structural proteins, E2 shows the highest degree of amino acid variation. A study conducted by Schuffenecker 
 <italic>et al</italic>. comparing CHIKV isolated during the Indian Ocean outbreak with the prototype ECSA-genotype virus (S27 strain) revealed that the protein divergence of IOL from the prototype ECSA stain was 3.3% in the E2 glycoprotein, while divergence was only 0.68% in the E1 protein [
 <xref rid="pone.0208851.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Moreover, these variation rates were even higher when comparing among CHIKV of different genotypes. Our previous sequence comparison among 6 ECSA strains, 5 ECSA-IOL strains, 5 WA strains, and 5 Asian strains of CHIKV revealed variations of 7.7% and 4.3% in E2 and E1, respectively [
 <xref rid="pone.0208851.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. E2 possesses a larger number of B-cell epitopes targeted by human anti-CHIKV neutralizing antibodies than does E1 [
 <xref rid="pone.0208851.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0208851.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], thus increasing the possibility of selection for amino acid changes in the targeted epitopes. The greater antigenicity of CHIKV E2 is consistent with a similar result in SINV. Specifically, SINV E1, a class-II fusion protein, is centrally located and is covered by SINV E2 [
 <xref rid="pone.0208851.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. The dissociation of the SINV E1 from E2 occurs only upon membrane fusion in endosomes, under low pH conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0208851.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].
</p>
