<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A multifunctional C protein consists of three regions: region I (residues 1–80), which functions as a non-specific binding site for viral RNA; region II (residues 81–113), which serves as specific binding site for viral RNA; and region III (residues 114–261), which facilitates binding to the cytoplasmic domain of the E2 protein [
 <xref rid="pone.0208851.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0208851.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Consistent with a previous study by Goh 
 <italic>et al</italic>.,[
 <xref rid="pone.0208851.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] our sequence alignment of C proteins from CHIKVs of various genotypes showed that the C protein is more strongly conserved among genotypes than are envelope proteins. The C protein of the intact CHIKV virion is covered by the envelope protein and therefore is unlikely to be recognized by B-cell receptors. However, putative linear B-cell epitopes have been mapped to amino acid residues on CHIKV C protein regions I and III [
 <xref rid="pone.0208851.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Several studies have reported on the possible application and diagnostic potential of anti-capsid mAbs [
 <xref rid="pone.0208851.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0208851.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. In the present study, anti-CHIKV C protein antibodies were classified into two groups: those showing comparable reactivity among the three CHIKV genotypes (mAbs 24B3 and 26A2) and those with superior reactivity against ECSA compared to CHIKVs of other genotypes (mAbs 32A3, 37C7, and 41G5). Based on the degree of amino acid variation among the CHIKV C proteins of different strains, we hypothesized that the binding epitopes targeted by mAbs 32A3, 37C7, and 41G5 are located in the N-terminal portion (region I or II) of the C protein, regions that showed a higher degree of variation. On the other hand, the highly conserved C-terminal portion (region III) of the C protein is inferred to be recognized by mAbs 24B3 and 26A2. Consistent with this hypothesis, only 26A2 cross-reacted with RRV, a virus that possesses a C protein that shows approximately 72% amino acid identity with that of CHIKV (
 <xref rid="pone.0208851.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0208851.s006">S5 Fig</xref>). Considered together, our results demonstrated the successful generation of a panel of anti-CHIKV C protein mAbs; these clones were able to recognize the different CHIKV genotypes, notably including the ECSA and Asian genotypes that currently are in worldwide circulation. Hence, our anti-CHIKV C mAbs are highly promising tools for use in immunodiagnostic test development.
</p>
