<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fn-group content-type="author-contribution">
 <title>
  <bold>Author contributions</bold>
 </title>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con1">
  <p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Validation, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing - original draft, Project administration, Writing - review and editing.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con2">
  <p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con3">
  <p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Supervision, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing - original draft.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con4">
  <p>Formal analysis, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing - review and editing.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con5">
  <p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Funding acquisition, Investigation, Methodology, Writing - original draft.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con6">
  <p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Funding acquisition, Methodology, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con7">
  <p>Formal analysis, Validation, Investigation, Methodology, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con8">
  <p>Conceptualization, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Methodology, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con9">
  <p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Validation, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con10">
  <p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Methodology, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con11">
  <p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Supervision, Investigation, Methodology.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con12">
  <p>Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con13">
  <p>Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con14">
  <p>Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con15">
  <p>Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con16">
  <p>Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con17">
  <p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con18">
  <p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Investigation, Visualization, Methodology, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con19">
  <p>Conceptualization, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Methodology, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con20">
  <p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con" id="con21">
  <p>Conceptualization, Supervision, Funding acquisition, Validation, Methodology, Writing - original draft, Project administration, Writing - review and editing.</p>
 </fn>
</fn-group>
