<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>By studying RIG-I ubiquitination and signal-transducing activity in murine cells, we have also uncovered commonalities and differences between human and mouse RIG-I regulation. Although Lys172, the critical residue for RIG-I ubiquitination in human 
 <xref rid="ppat.1003059-Gack1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, is not conserved in mouse, we observed a robust ubiquitination of mouse RIG-I 2CARD, suggesting that other lysine residues in the mouse RIG-I CARDs are ubiquitinated. Furthermore, our studies using 
 <italic>TRIM25 −/−</italic> cells indicate that the ubiquitination of mouse RIG-I 2CARD, in contrast to that of human RIG-I 2CARD, is less affected in the absence of TRIM25, indicating that in addition to TRIM25 another ubiquitin E3 ligase mediates RIG-I 2CARD ubiquitination in mouse. The ubiquitin E3 ligase Riplet has been reported to ubiquitinate RIG-I, thereby leading to its optimal activation 
 <xref rid="ppat.1003059-Oshiumi1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1003059-Oshiumi2" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1003059-Gao1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. However, while Riplet has been shown to ubiquitinate Lys849 and Lys851 in the CTD of RIG-I, the role of Riplet for RIG-I CARD ubiquitination has been a subject of debate 
 <xref rid="ppat.1003059-Oshiumi1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1003059-Oshiumi2" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1003059-Gao1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. Our data suggests that, at least in the mouse system, Riplet is unlikely to ubiquitinate the 2CARD, because NS1 was unable to inhibit mouse RIG-I 2CARD ubiquitination. Therefore, in addition to TRIM25 there may be an additional ubiquitin E3 ligase in mice that ubiquitinates the RIG-I N-terminal CARDs, and this E3 ligase is most likely not targeted by NS1. Nevertheless, our studies clearly showed that Riplet plays a crucial role for RIG-I ubiquitination-dependent activation in mouse, most likely by ubiquitinating the C-terminal region of RIG-I. Additional work will be needed to further define the roles and contributions of these ubiquitin E3 ligases for RIG-I activation in mouse.
</p>
