<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Radiological findings from different cohort studies that included COVID-19 patients (Huang 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Zhao 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) were similar to those characterizing lung damage caused by autoimmune and autoinflammatory diseases (Saper 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). This similarity might suggest that at least part of the damage caused by COVID-19 is due to a dysregulated immune response. Moreover, it might explain the efficacy of certain immune modulator drugs in the treatment of severe COVID-19 cases. Since the outset of the current pandemic, several drugs targeting general immune-system function were proposed for their potential role in alleviating symptoms. Corticosteroids were found to exacerbate lung injury in COVID-19 patients, as in the previous epidemics (SARS and MERS), and thus are not recommended (Russell, Millar and Baillie 
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). On the other hand, Tocilizumab (Interleukin-6 Receptor Antagonist) which was noted to have some efficacy in decreasing the symptoms of immune-related toxicity from anti-PD-1 agents in cancer patients including CRS (Horisberger 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Stroud 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>), might have promising results in the treatment of COVID-19. Currently, clinical trials of Tocilizumab (Chinese Clinical Trials Registration number: ChiCTR2000029765) are being conducted in China. Finally HCQ, CQ, IL-1 blockade (anakinra) and JAK2 inhibitors are among the immune modulators under consideration for the management of severe cases of COVID-19 (Ruiz-Irastorza 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Shakoory 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Wu 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>).
</p>
