<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur Heart J Cardiovasc Pharmacother</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur Heart J Cardiovasc Pharmacother</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ehjcvp</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>European Heart Journal &#x02014; Cardiovascular Pharmacotherapy</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2055-6837</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2055-6845</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ehjcvp/pvaa042</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">pvaa042</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Correspondence</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Statin therapy in COVID-19 infection</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9285-2328</contrib-id><name><surname>Castiglione</surname><given-names>Vincenzo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="pvaa042-aff1">p1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="pvaa042-FM1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chiriac&#x000f2;</surname><given-names>Martina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="pvaa042-aff1">p1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="pvaa042-aff2">p2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="pvaa042-FM1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Emdin</surname><given-names>Michele</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="pvaa042-aff1">p1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="pvaa042-aff3">p3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Taddei</surname><given-names>Stefano</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="pvaa042-aff2">p2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vergaro</surname><given-names>Giuseppe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="pvaa042-cor1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="pvaa042-aff1">p1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="pvaa042-aff3">p3</xref><!--<email>vergaro@ftgm.it</email>--></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="pvaa042-aff1"><label>p1</label>
<institution>Institute of Life Science, Scuola Superiore Sant&#x02019;Anna</institution>, Pisa, <country country="IT">Italy</country></aff><aff id="pvaa042-aff2"><label>p2</label>
<institution>Department of Clinical and Experimental Medicine, University of Pisa</institution>, Pisa, <country country="IT">Italy</country></aff><aff id="pvaa042-aff3"><label>p3</label>
<institution>Fondazione Toscana Gabriele Monasterio</institution>, Pisa, <country country="IT">Italy</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="pvaa042-cor1">Corresponding author; Scuola Superiore Sant&#x02019;Anna Piazza Martiri della Libert&#x000e0;, 33, 56127 Pisa, Italy. Tel: +39 050 3153396, Fax: +39 050 3152277, Email: <email>vergaro@ftgm.it</email></corresp><fn id="pvaa042-FM1"><p>Vincenzo Castiglione and Martina Chiriac&#x000f2; contributed equally.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2020-04-29"><day>29</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>29</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><elocation-id>pvaa042</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>Published on behalf of the European Society of Cardiology. All rights reserved. &#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020. For permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license license-type="publisher-standard" xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/journals/pages/open_access/funder_policies/chorus/standard_publication_model"><license-p>This article is published and distributed under the terms of the Oxford University Press, Standard Journals Publication Model (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/journals/pages/open_access/funder_policies/chorus/standard_publication_model">https://academic.oup.com/journals/pages/open_access/funder_policies/chorus/standard_publication_model</ext-link>)</license-p></license><license><license-p>This article is made available via the PMC Open Access Subset for unrestricted re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for the duration of the COVID-19 pandemic or until permissions are revoked in writing. Upon expiration of these permissions, PMC is granted a perpetual license to make this article available via PMC and Europe PMC, consistent with existing copyright protections.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="pvaa042.pdf"/><counts><page-count count="2"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>article-lifecycle</meta-name><meta-value>PAP</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) is the causal agent of the current pandemic of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). SARS-CoV-2 is a positive-sense single-stranded RNA betacoronavirus sharing genetic similarities with the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 1 (SARS-CoV-1) and the Middle East respiratory syndrome-related coronavirus (MERS-CoV).<xref rid="pvaa042-B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> SARS-CoV-2 enters the cells mainly through angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2), and triggers an intense inflammatory host response, sometimes leading to a life-threatening acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS).<xref rid="pvaa042-B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Several randomized controlled trials (RCTs) are investigating the safety and efficacy of various antiviral and immunosuppressive agents. Still, many of these drugs have serious adverse effects, and may not be readily available in some healthcare settings, such as in low-income countries.</p><p>In this paper we support the rationale for the use of statins, a class of drugs with widespread availability and an optimal tolerability profile, as an add-on treatment for COVID-19 patients, on the basis of their known immunomodulatory properties.</p><p>Besides their lipid-lowering activity, statins exert pleiotropic effects on inflammation and oxidative stress, contributing to their beneficial impact on cardiovascular diseases. Statins modulate the immune response at different levels, including immune cell adhesion and migration, antigen presentation, and cytokine production. Moreover, they restore the vascular redox balance by reducing reactive oxygen species and increasing antioxidants, and ameliorate nitric oxide bioavailability, endothelial function, and integrity. Most of these effects depend on statin-mediated inhibition of the production of isoprenoids, which are fundamental constituents of small GTPases (such as Ras, Rho, and Rac), and on consequential down-regulation of redox-sensitive proinflammatory transcriptional factors such as NF-&#x003ba;B.<xref rid="pvaa042-B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref></p><p>Statins have proven to be beneficial as an add-on therapy in patients with different autoimmune inflammatory conditions (e.g. systemic lupus erythematosus, rheumatoid arthritis, multiple sclerosis, and graft-versus-host disease).<xref rid="pvaa042-B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Statins have also been evaluated as an immunomodulatory treatment in various infectious diseases. Although observational studies have reported improved outcomes in patients with community-acquired pneumonia or sepsis receiving statins,<xref rid="pvaa042-B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="pvaa042-B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> most RCTs on inpatient statin treatment in sepsis or ventilator-associated pneumonia failed to demonstrate a beneficial effect.<xref rid="pvaa042-B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> On the other hand, statin therapy appears promising in the context of viral infections. Avian influenza viruses induce an intense host response characterized by a cytokine storm, which can sometimes lead to ARDS.<xref rid="pvaa042-B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> Few large observational studies have reported the effectiveness of statin treatment in reducing influenza-related hospitalizations and deaths.<xref rid="pvaa042-B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> Further, a recently completed RCT (ClinicalTrials.gov number, NCT02056340) showed a significant improvement of symptoms in statin-na&#x000ef;ve patients hospitalized for seasonal influenza receiving atorvastatin 40 mg compared with placebo. An association between outpatient statin use and reduction in disease severity among patients hospitalized during the 2009 H1N1 pandemic has also been demonstrated.<xref rid="pvaa042-B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> Some authors have therefore advocated statin use as an immunomodulatory therapy for viral infections with potential for epidemics and pandemics.<xref rid="pvaa042-B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> Although no RCT has yet investigated this hypothesis, statins [together with angiotensin receptor blockers (ARBs)] were effective in targeting the host response and preventing endothelial barrier damage in patients infected with Ebola virus during the recent Ebola outbreak in West Africa.<xref rid="pvaa042-B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref></p><p>Similar to avian influenza viruses, betacoronaviruses cause severe respiratory illnesses by triggering an intense proinflammatory host response. Some immunomodulatory therapies have indeed proven beneficial in patients with SARS, MERS, and COVID-19; for example, tocilizumab, a humanized monoclonal antibody against the interleukin-6 receptor, was effective as a supportive therapy in selected COVID-19 patients.<xref rid="pvaa042-B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> SARS-CoV-1 interaction with Toll-like receptors on the host cell membrane significantly increases the expression of the <italic>MYD88</italic> gene, whose product activates NF-&#x003ba;B, thereby triggering inflammatory pathways.<xref rid="pvaa042-B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> Notably, inhibition of NF-&#x003ba;B resulted in reduced lung infection and increased survival in a murine model of SARS-CoV-1 infection.<xref rid="pvaa042-B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Experimental models have demonstrated that statins stabilize MYD88 levels after a proinflammatory trigger such as hypoxia.<xref rid="pvaa042-B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> Moreover, in murine cells, atorvastatin 0.1 &#x003bc;M (corresponding to the plasma concentration obtained with a daily dose of &#x0223c;40 mg in humans) significantly attenuated NF-&#x003ba;B activation within 48 h.<xref rid="pvaa042-B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> (<italic>Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pvaa042-F1">1</xref></italic>). Based on this evidence, the use of a statin as an immunomodulatory treatment for COVID-19 patients may deserve consideration.
</p><fig id="pvaa042-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Molecular mechanism of actions and proposed advantages of statins in COVID-19. Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), the causal agent of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), enters the cell through angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2). Once in the cell, SARS-CoV-2 causes ACE2 down-regulation, thus reducing its protective effects on various tissues. Coronaviruses are known to induce a proinflammatory host response via the activation of the Toll-like receptor (TLR)&#x02013;MYD88&#x02013;NF-&#x003ba;B pathway. Statins are available worldwide, and are low-cost, safe drugs with lipid-lowering and immunomodulatory effects. In experimental models, statins inhibit the MYD88<sc>&#x02013;</sc>NF-&#x003ba;B proinflammatory pathway and promote ACE2 up-regulation. Through these mechanisms, statins may prove beneficial in COVID-19 patients. Statins may also counteract hyperlipidaemia caused by some antiviral and immunosuppressive treatments currently used for COVID-19.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pvaa042f1"/></fig><p>Statins also interfere with ACE2 signalling. After initial entry through ACE2, SARS-CoV-2 down-regulates ACE2 expression, possibly facilitating the initial infiltration by innate immunity cells and causing an unopposed angiotensin II accumulation, leading to organ injury.<xref rid="pvaa042-B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Statins, as well as ARBs, are known to experimentally up-regulate <italic>ACE2</italic> via epigenetic modifications.<xref rid="pvaa042-B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> (<italic>Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pvaa042-F1">1</xref></italic>). Since an increase in ACE2 might prove beneficial for COVID-19 patients, RCTs with recombinant human ACE2 or ARBs are currently underway,<xref rid="pvaa042-B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> and there is biological plausibility to investigate statins too.<xref rid="pvaa042-B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref></p><p>Cardioprotective actions of statins should also be taken into consideration in the setting of SARS-CoV-2 infection. Observational studies have found that elderly people with cardiovascular comorbidities are more likely to be infected with SARS-CoV-2 and to develop severe symptoms.<xref rid="pvaa042-B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> In addition, there is evidence of direct cardiovascular involvement in some cases of COVID-19.<xref rid="pvaa042-B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Furthermore, the lipid-lowering action of statins could treat the hyperlipidaemia associated with the use of protease inhibitor-based antiretroviral and immunosuppressive drugs in COVID-19 infection. Statin therapy has proven effective in improving hyperlipidaemia in patients with human immunodeficiency virus receiving protease inhibitor treatment<xref rid="pvaa042-B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> and in patients with rheumatoid arthritis receiving tocilizumab (<italic>Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pvaa042-F1">1</xref></italic>).<xref rid="pvaa042-B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Most statins undergo hepatic metabolism through CYP3A4, and concomitant administration of CYP3A4 inhibitors currently used in COVID-19, such as ritonavir and cobicistat, could increase the risk of muscle and liver toxicity; therefore, starting with a lower dose of statin and monitoring creatine kinase and transaminases would be advisable in these cases.</p><p>In conclusion, statins are low-cost, extensively tested, well-tolerated drugs that are less likely to be affected by a shortage in a health crisis such as the current COVID-19 pandemic, even in low-income countries, where treatment with more expensive drugs may not be implemented. Adjuvant treatment and continuation of pre-existing statin therapy could improve the clinical course of patients with COVID-19, either by their immunomodulatory action or by preventing cardiovascular damage. This hypothesis should warrant consideration for phase III clinical trials.</p><p>
<bold>Conflict of interest:</bold> none declared.</p></body><back><ref-list id="ref1"><title>References</title><ref id="pvaa042-B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Madjid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Safavi-Naeini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vardeny</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Potential effects of coronaviruses on the cardiovascular system: a review</article-title>. <source>JAMA Cardiol</source><year>2020</year>;doi: 10.1001/jamacardio.2020.1286.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pvaa042-B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeiser</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Immune modulatory effects of statins</article-title>. <source>Immunology</source><year>2018</year>;<volume>154</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29392731</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pvaa042-B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fedson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fedson</surname><given-names>DS.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Treating influenza with statins and other immunomodulatory agents</article-title>. <source>Antivir Res</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>417</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>435</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23831494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pvaa042-B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pertzov</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eliakim-Raz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Atamna</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Trestioreanu</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yahav</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leibovici</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Hydroxymethylglutaryl-CoA reductase inhibitors (statins) for the treatment of sepsis in adults&#x02014;a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><year>2019</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>280</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>289</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30472427</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pvaa042-B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fedson</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Opal</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rordam</surname><given-names>OM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Hiding in plain sight: an approach to treating patients with severe COVID-19 infection</article-title>. <source>mBio</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:doi: 10.1128/mBio.00398-20.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pvaa042-B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Totura</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whitmore</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agnihothram</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sch&#x000e4;fer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katze</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heise</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baric</surname><given-names>RS.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Toll-like receptor 3 signaling via TRIF contributes to a protective innate immune response to severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus infection</article-title>. <source>mBio</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e00638</fpage>-<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26015500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pvaa042-B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeDiego</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nieto-Torres</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Regla-Nava</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jimenez-Guardeno</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Delgado</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fett</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Casta&#x000f1;o-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perlman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Enjuanes</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Inhibition of NF-&#x003ba;B-mediated inflammation in severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-infected mice increases survival</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>913</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24198408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pvaa042-B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Atorvastatin attenuates myocardial remodeling induced by chronic intermittent hypoxia in rats: partly involvement of TLR-4/MYD88 pathway</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>446</volume>:<fpage>292</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>297</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24582748</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pvaa042-B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chansrichavala</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chantharaksri</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sritara</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chaiyaroj</surname><given-names>SC.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Atorvastatin attenuates TLR4-mediated NF-kappaB activation in a MyD88-dependent pathway</article-title>. <source>Asian Pac J Allergy</source><year>2009</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pvaa042-B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eckard</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McComsey</surname><given-names>GA.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The role of statins in the setting of HIV infection</article-title>. <source>Curr HIV-AIDS Rep</source><year>2015</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>305</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>312</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>