<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0225">The global research on COVID-19 is accelerating, and the international community has reached a consensus in strengthening scientific collaboration. As of March 8, 2020, at least 1,500 papers on COVID-19 have been published in English or Chinese. In addition to China, the US, Canada, and European countries also carried out scientific research on COVID-19 in the early stages of the pandemic. Regional distribution and related research topics are strongly relevant in the context of the epidemic situation and the need for data acquisition. The US focused on epidemiology, prevention, and control based on the epidemiological data for SARS-CoV-2 in this country, and previous experience of influenza prevention and control during the recent outbreak. European countries and Japan carried out epidemiological studies before the outbreak based on transmission data. Southeast Asian countries and the Middle East focused on epidemiology and control. Researchers around the world launched an unprecedented scale of joint research (26% global and about 18% inter-provincial in China) rapidly in response to WHO appeals; countries have, as a result, reached a consensus on strategic direction and cultivated scientific cooperation.
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>73</sup>
 </xref> China and the US have established cooperative networks with European and Southeast Asian countries, and achieved unprecedented and extensive communication and information sharing in research in the fields of etiology, epidemiology, and clinical studies, leading to research actions being implemented faster than in the SARS and MERS outbreaks. It is worth noting that, due to the limitations of data and clinical samples, the research disparities in different regions will affect the guidance of the global treatment, and more global clinical studies should be explored in the future for more suitable treatment guidance in different countries. For China, researchers should take full advantages of their early research (such as the early clinical samples, and the R&amp;D of a recombinant protein-based vaccine), combined with other regional research advantages (such as the technologies of rapid detection of COVID-19 and nucleic acid vaccines in the US) and, based on the expansion of global clinical samples, promote international joint research.
</p>
