<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although the estimated risk of persistance of viral RNA is almost zero after 24 months, 1 patient from Liberia was still positive after 40 months [
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. In our study, all 223 samples from 158 patients were negative after 40 months. The higher total number of positive patients in the Prevail study from Liberia—30% compared with 10% in our study—could be related to the fact that all samples from the Prevail study were tested within 48 hours with Ebola Xpert and not retrospectively on frozen materials for the early samples. The presence of viral RNA does not mean that the virus is still infectious, but it has to be noted that the patient from the PostEbogui cohort who was still positive at 512 days after ETU discharge has been previously reported to be at the origin of a new cluster of EVD in Guinea and Liberia after the declaration of the end of the outbreak [
 <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The persisting virus was estimated to have been sexually transmitted approximately 470 days after onset of symptoms [
 <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. This patient was 55 years old, corresponding to observations from our and other studies that persistence of viral RNA is longer in older male survivors [
 <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. A previous report suggested that HIV status was associated with presence of viral RNA [
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]; however, HIV prevalence in the PostEbogui cohort is 2%, but all positive patients were HIV negative. Similar to the study in Liberia, we found an association between viral RNA shedding in semen with ocular problems and higher antibody levels [
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. In addition, we also found an association with joint pain. Uveitis was shown to be associated with higher viral load during disease, suggesting a higher risk that the virus could remain present in other immune-privileged compartments, which explains the viral presence in semen and the association with joint pain [
 <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Higher antibody levels could also suggest persistent immune stimulation with minute viral antigens.
</p>
