<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The primary outcome was death because of any cause in the 48 months after ART initiation. To address concerns regarding death under-ascertainment, a survey addressing ascertainment and matching with external mortality registries was distributed. Seventy-five percent of cohorts in Europe reported good or very good death ascertainment, but only 40% conducted cross-checks with mortality registries. Cumulative mortality in the European cohorts did not vary significantly according to self-assessment of mortality ascertainment (data not shown). Death ascertainment was reported to be poor in East and West Africa. To correct mortality estimates for East Africa, we used an inverse-probability-weighted estimator of the mortality rate where weights are constant and equal to the inverse ratio of the patients who could be traced out of all patients who were lost to follow-up [
 <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. For corrections of under-ascertainment in West Africa, we used a modification of the approach by Brinkhof 
 <italic>et al.</italic>[
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], which uses inflation factors to account for mortality under-reporting, under the assumption that mortality under-ascertainment was similar in the two regions [
 <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Death rates based on observed data were estimated for different participant subgroups. These ‘passive’ mortality estimates were then multiplied by a group-specific inflation factor determined as the ratio of the lost-to-follow-up-adjusted death rates over the observed rates estimated within East African cohorts [
 <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. For the Republic of South Africa cohort, civil identification numbers, wherever available, were cross-checked with national population registers prior to data transfer to confirm dates of death. All sites in the Caribbean, Central and South America region, except for Argentina, reported ascertaining deaths with population-based mortality registries. North American cohorts link to a population-based death registry at least annually.
</p>
