<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par7">Typical and atypical clinical features of COVID-19 patients, as well as risk factors with possible impact on COVID-19 outcome, are outlined in several papers of this Topical Collection. Bertolino et al. tried to summarize the evidences on key clinical features to differentiate COVID-19 case from upper respiratory and/or influenza-like illnesses of other aetiology, providing a practical guide for internists [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. According to data collected by Lapostolle et al. among 1487 outpatients diagnosed with COVID-19 in the Greater Paris region, dry cough and fever were the most frequent symptoms reported (more than 90% of cases), in association with general symptoms, such as body aches/myalgia, headache, and asthenia, and a considerable quote of anosmia and ageusia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Nevertheless, the clinical presentation can be sometimes atypical, respiratory symptoms can be less pronounced, and other sites targeted, such as the digestive tract, the cardiovascular system and central nervous system. For instance, a number of neurologic manifestation, from unspecific symptoms such as headache, altered mental status, and anosmia, up to cerebrovascular accidents and Guillain–Barré syndrome have occurred in many patients with Covid-19 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Morjaria et al. described two cases of unusual neurological complications, i.e. bilateral lower limbs weakness, possibly related to cerebrovascular accidents, in critically ill patients with prolonged hospital stays [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Great interest exists on whether patients presenting with atypical symptoms are at increased risk to evolve toward severe forms of COVID-19. Henry et al. revised the available literature about common gastrointestinal symptoms and found that abdominal pain, nausea and vomiting, but not diarrhoea, were significantly associated with an increased odds of severe COVID-19 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Moreover, myocardial injury was often observed in SARS-CoV-2 patients, especially those with severe to critical disease, in need of intensive care treatment. Preliminary data by Violi et al. on a limited sample of patients suggested that patients who show troponin elevation may be at higher risk of mortality [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. As for other predictors of outcome in COVID-19 patients, Sciacqua et al. explored the potential causative factors of poor outcome in elderly people, such as immunosenescence, reduced resilience and the coexistence of multiple comorbidities, and focused on impaired nutritional status and sarcopenia, commonly due to inadequate food and calorie intake and an unmet increased protein demand [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Pantanetti et al. reviewed the pathophysiologic basis related to an excess of disease severity in diabetic patients and suggested a possible use of dipeptidyl peptidase-4 inhibitors as immunomodulatory drugs in COVID-19 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Surprisingly, a systematic review by Farsalinos et al. found that smoking had a protective effect against COVID-19, based on an unexpected low prevalence of current smokers among Chinese patients hospitalized with COVID-19 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Despite confidence issues on the accuracy about data collection methods for reporting smoking status, similar findings have been reported from other countries, allowing to speculate on pharmaceutical nicotine as a potential treatment option in COVID-19 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].
</p>
