<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par9">However, overall management of Covid-19 patients exceeds the administration of antiviral drugs. Immune-modulant drugs and anti-thrombotic prophylaxis are pillars of the treatment of severe forms. Both arterial and venous thrombotic events frequently complicated the course of patients with COVID-19, especially in those critically ill, leading to the definition of Coronavirus-associated coagulopathy (CAC) by the International Society on Thrombosis and Haemostasis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. An interesting Spanish case series of non-ICU hospitalized COVID-19 patients diagnosed with pulmonary embolism, without evidence of concomitant deep–vein thrombosis of the lower limbs, suggested a predominance of small-vessel thrombosis secondary to inflammatory and immune responses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Understanding mechanism underlying CAC is crucial to put in place appropriate therapeutic measures: observed hemostatic alternations—increased 
 <sc>d</sc>-dimer, normal or slightly deranged prothrombin time and within range platelets count—differ from those usually observed during the disseminated intravascular coagulopathy. Bazzan et al. found reduced levels of ADAMTS-13 and higher levels of von Willebrand factor in a cohort of COVID-19 patients, in comparison with healthy controls, and also in fatal COVID-19 cases, when compared to patients with the non-fatal outcome. These alterations, similar to those observed in patients with thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura, may lean more to a thrombotic microangiopathy origin of CAC, rather than a consumption coagulopathy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Moreover, the infusion of hyperimmune plasma from donors recovered from SARS-CoV-2 infection emerged as an attractive option. Perotti et al. presented the COVID-19 PLASMA trial, the first proof-of-concept interventional trial using hyperimmune plasma with a high titre of specific neutralizing antibodies for treating critical patients with COVID-19 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Supportive care includes supplemental oxygen and ventilatory management of patients with respiratory distress. Privitera et al. proposed a flowchart for non-invasive ventilation support in COVID-19 patients, as a first approach in the Emergency Department [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>].
</p>
