<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0085">As SARS-CoV-2 virions are excreted in COVID-19 patients’ faeces, sewage can also be an important point of surveillance for wastewater-based epidemiology. Several groups, notably in Australia, the Netherlands, Sweden, and the USA have already reported detecting traces of SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater [
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Scientists from the Dutch National Institute for Public Health and the Environment analysed wastewater samples from the Amsterdam Schiphol Airport over several weeks and found that, using RT-PCR, they could detect SARS-CoV-2 within four days of cases being confirmed in the country [
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Importantly, detection of SARS-CoV-2 RNA in wastewater does not imply that the virus is viable and able to infect humans. Coronavirus in wastewater is relatively short-lived, with 3-log
 <sub>10</sub> reduction in virus titre reportedly occurring within 2–3 days [
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. However, given the genetic similarity of SARS-CoV-2 to the earlier, widely-studied SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] and the known faecal-oral transmission potential of that virus [
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>], it is possible that a similar transmission pathway exists for SARS-CoV-2. For example, positive SARS-CoV-2 infection of gastrointestinal glandular epithelial cells has been reported, suggesting that infectious SARS-CoV-2 virions are secreted from virus-infected gastrointestinal cells, establishing the potential for faecal-oral transmission [
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The same study also indicated that infectious SARS-CoV-2 had been isolated from faecal samples; although at the time of writing, these data remained unpublished [
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. This contrasts with other research that failed to isolate infectious virus from faecal samples (13 samples taken from four patients) [
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] so clearly more work is needed to explore the potential for faecal-oral SARS-CoV-2 transmission.
</p>
