<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Veterinarians and government actions and decisions relating to the management of HeV followed the typical stages of behaviour change: 
 <italic>pre-contemplation</italic> (behavioural change seen as not needed); 
 <italic>contemplation</italic> (behavioural change under consideration); 
 <italic>preparation</italic> (for behavioural change); 
 <italic>action</italic> (behavioural change implementation); 
 <italic>maintenance</italic> (of behavioural change); 
 <italic>transcendence</italic> (behavioural change becomes the new behavioural norm); and sometimes relapse (reverting to old behaviours) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. The progression through these stages is determined by a number of cognitive variables (Figure 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). In the context of the emergence of HeV, there was at first disbelief that HeV would recur or spread to other areas, and as the government did not recommend any particular changes, veterinary IC behaviours remained unchanged. With recurring HeV outbreaks and additional human infections, there was a slow recognition that changes to veterinary IC were necessary. Some IC changes were made by some veterinarians but these were not always sustained as the required financial and logistic investment could not be justified long-term because of the low frequency of HeV outbreak and the lack of government commitment to a clear HeV management plan. The deaths of two veterinarians in 2008 and 2009 triggered government into finalising their HeV management plan, formulate and widely distribute clear recommendations to private veterinarians and provide more training and field support to equine veterinarians through their emergency response unit. In 2010 all private veterinarians registered in Queensland, received a comprehensive information package from the government. The last three participants to be interviewed for this study had received this package prior to their interview and they were mostly satisfied with this information. Since then there have been no further human infections with HeV even though, in the winter of 2011, there was a marked increase in the number of HeV outbreaks in Queensland and northern New South Wales. Thus, the changes made by the government and the private veterinarians appear to have lowered the risk of human exposure and therefore infection risks for veterinarians and the wider population.
</p>
