<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Aim of this study was to describe the prevalence, morphology, and size of right appendage aneurysm (RAA) in dogs. In this 13‐year single‐centre cross‐sectional study, CT reports of dogs underwent thoracic CT examination for various reasons were reviewed. Patients' characteristics were assessed for likely associations with RAA. Radiographic and echocardiographic studies were also evaluated when available. Continuous data were assessed for normality of distribution with the Shapiro‐Wilk test. Dogs with RAA were compared with dogs without RAA for the variable gender and sexual status using Chi‐Square test. Wilcoxon‐Mann‐Whitney test was used to analyse age and body weight of groups. The body condition score (five points scoring system) was analyzed using the Fischer's exact test. Non‐normally distributed data were reported as median, interquartile range (IQR), and range. For all statistical analyses, the significance level was set to α = 0.05. CT data of dogs with RAA were retrieved from archive and analyzed using various post‐processing techniques. RAA location and shape were recorded. Oblique multiplanar views were used such that the area to be measured was orthogonal to the long axis of the RAA. RAA measurements included the neck, maximum height and width. Additional CT features of cardiac and extracardiac structures were also recorded. RAA was detected in 23/10886 dogs having thoracic CT in the selected period of time (0.21% prevalence). Radiographic and echocardiographic studies were available for 10/23 dogs. A mediastinal mass were visible in 2/10 radiographs. Echocardiographic examination disclosed RAA in 4/10 dogs with pulmonary hypertension. The bodyweights of dogs with RAA were significantly lower than those of the remaining 10 836 dogs without RAA (median 8 kg [IQR 5; range 37.6] and median 16 kg [IQR 23; range 116.9] respectively; 
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.003). Female sex was also significantly associated with RAA (
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.03). Four/23 dogs had also right atrial dilatation. Three different RAA phenotypes were detected: sack‐like in 19/23 dogs, focal lump‐like in 3/23 dogs, and fusiform in 1/23 dog. Results of CT measurements were: mean of the neck 1.48 cm [IQR 1; range 2.6]; mean height 3.06 cm [IQR 1.39; range 4.85], and mean width 1.64 cm [IQR 1; range 3.1]. RAA is an infrequent (0.21%) and often incidental condition that can have different phenotypes. In this study, female sex and smaller size showed an association with RAA. Further case‐control studies are necessary to assess a possible relationship between RAA and pulmonary hypertension.
</p>
