<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We modelled the HFRS epidemics in Hu County (1984–2014) using a discrete-time susceptible-infected-recovered (TSIR) model with age structure [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006198.ref092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. We estimated the seasonality for the HFRS transmission rate by fitting the 30-year-long time series of observed monthly cases using this TSIR model in a Bayesian state-space framework to account for uncertainty in the observation [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006198.ref093" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. New infections were drawn from the pool of susceptible individuals, along with information on births, deaths, and vaccinations. As the natural time scale for the disease is ~1 month [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006198.ref094" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>], we used this as the time interval in our model. The number of people susceptible to disease in month 
 <italic>t</italic>+1 is given as 
 <italic>S</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>t</italic>+1
 </sub> = 
 <italic>B</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>t</italic>
 </sub> + 
 <italic>S</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>t</italic>
 </sub>
 <italic>−D</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>t</italic>
 </sub>−
 <italic>V</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>t</italic>
 </sub>−
 <italic>I</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>t</italic>
 </sub> + λ
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>t</italic>
 </sub>. 
 <italic>B</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>t</italic>
 </sub> and 
 <italic>D</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>t</italic>
 </sub> represent the number of human births and deaths during the time period, respectively. 
 <italic>V</italic> is the number of vaccinated individuals based on medical records, and 
 <italic>R</italic> is the number of immune individuals. 
 <italic>λ</italic> is the proportion of vaccinated people who lost their immunity per month, based on 20 years of surveillance. Susceptible individuals were divided into three different age groups (0–15 yrs., 16–60 yrs., and 61–100 yrs.) according to disease characteristics, and each individual was also kept track of over the study period (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat.1006198.g005">Fig 5A</xref>). The number of people aged 16–60 yrs. accounted for more than 90% of the total cases in the study area, and as the vaccine was only provided to this group (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1006198.s009">S9 Fig</xref>) we assumed that the highest risk of infection was for this age group. Additional information is given in the Supporting Information.
</p>
