<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">As HBV infection is significantly influenced by various of host factors, host factor-targeted antivirals are prospective therapeutic approaches.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>
 </sup> Myrcludex-B, a peptide that mimics the N-terminus of the preS1 in the large surface antigen that is involved in binding to sodium taurocholate cotransporting polypeptide, can block virus entry to hepatocytes and is currently in phase II clinical trials.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>
 </sup> Recently, cyclosporine A, a fungal cyclic polypeptide, and its analogs have been reported to inhibit the virus entry by targeting sodium taurocholate cotransporting polypeptide.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>
 </sup> Such macrocyclic peptide scaffolds often have the advantage of occupying an interface that is required for protein–protein interactions, such as receptor binding and capsid assembly, as described above. Moreover, host enzymes that are essential for virus replication represent promising drug targets. Deoxynojirimycin is an iminosugar α-glucosidase inhibitor and its analogs have shown to reduce the HBV secretion from infected cells.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>
 </sup> Iminosugars have a potential for development as antiviral drugs that disrupt the folding of viral glycoproteins by inhibiting host glucosidase, which is localized to the endoplasmic reticulum.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>
 </sup> Deoxynojirimycin is of plant origin, but this class of compounds is also found in microbial metabolites, such as siastatin B as described above.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup> Although the effects of siastatin B on HBV replication are presently unknown, host glucosidase involved in the antigen and virion secretion might be a suitable target for anti-HBV drug screening for microbial metabolites. Furthermore, several therapeutic vaccines for the treatment of chronic HBV infection are in preclinical and clinical trials. This approach aims to stimulate either specific or nonspecific immune responses against HBV to eliminate the cccDNA pool, while adjuvants may work to enhance vaccination. Previously, bestatin (Ubenimex), an immunomodulator discovered by IMC,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>
 </sup> has been reported to enhance immune responses for HIV vaccination in a murine model,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>
 </sup> although its effect on HBV vaccination is unknown. Compounds with adjuvant activity on HBV vaccination might be present in microbial metabolites.
</p>
