<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">The impact of SARS-COV-2 infection on the brain is associated with excessive physical and psychological stress that stimulates the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis thus further exacerbating neuroinflammatory status
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>
 </sup>. The duration and frequency of exposure to stressors impacts neuroinflammation. In this sense while a response to short and moderate stressors could be beneficial, repeated or extended exposure to strong stressors exacerbates inflammation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>
 </sup>. Exposure to long-lasting stress enhances inflammatory response through the release of several pro-inflammatory factors, which trigger down-stream signalling pathways, including NF-κB-dependent transcription. Contribution of glucocorticoids, associated with stress response, to sustaining and promoting neuroinflammation is complex, going beyond effects deriving from the activation of the signals downstream of their receptors
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>
 </sup>. Microarray experiments demonstrated that glucocorticoids drive expression of specific gene profiles, whereas concurrent co-activation of glucocorticoid receptors and NF-κB-dependent transcription induces a peculiar pattern of gene expression different from the one resulting from separate activation of each signalling pathway
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>
 </sup>. Neuroinflammation is a significant aetiological factor for a large number of neuropsychiatric and neuro-cognitive diseases, including neurodegenerative disorders
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>
 </sup>, depression
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>
 </sup>, psychosis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>
 </sup>, autism
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>
 </sup>, drug abuse
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>
 </sup>, sleep disorders
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>
 </sup> and epilepsy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>
 </sup>. The neuropsychiatric burden of this pandemic is currently unknown, but is likely to be considerable. Based on the results from investigations of recent epidemics by corona respiratory viruses, SARS-COV-1 and MERS-COV, it is possible to assume that a significant percentage of subjects recovering from pneumonia do not fully regain their previous emotional state and cognitive abilities. Indeed, a study of neuropsychiatric consequences of SARS-COV-1 performed at 30–50 months after the infection demonstrated an occurrence of 40% of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD), 36.4% of depression, 15.6% of obsessive convulsive disorder, and an equal incidence for anxiety disorders
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>
 </sup>. Furthermore, a meta-analysis among SARS-COV-1 patients of mixed conditions showed neurocognitive deficits up to 18 months post-discharge
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>
 </sup>, including mild cognitive impairment
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>
 </sup>. Given this evidence the burden of long-term post-SARS-CoV-2 delirium and dementia may be notable, especially for elderly subjects who are more vulnerable to post-infectious neurocognitive sequelae. The average age of the subjects with severe COVID-19 is around 63 years, whereas patients under the age of fifty represent only 26% of all clinical cases. The ageing itself is the major risk factor for cognitive pathologies and neurodegeneration; severe systemic diseases as well as stress are known to provoke or accelerate cognitive decline in elderly. In the aged brain the neurogenesis is dwindling, synaptic plasticity deteriorates, metabolism is reduced and overall brain vulnerability to exogenous insults is increased. Ageing of the human brain is also associated with degeneration and atrophy of microglia and astrocytes which diminishes homoeostatic and neuroprotective support and again increases brain susceptibility to pathology
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>
 </sup>. Infection with SARS-CoV-2 (even in moderate clinical cases) thus promotes cognitive disorders with emergence of delirium, acute psychosis, exacerbation of mild cognitive impairment or with accelerating of dementia associated with various neurodegenerative conditions, including Alzheimer’s disease (AD)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>
 </sup>. Conceptually, neuroinflammation contributes to the pathological development of neurodegeneration and often is considered as a common, even unifying feature of neurodegeneration
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>
 </sup>, while brain infection and ischaemic insults by themselves can trigger neurodegenerative process and instigate dementia
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
