<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This study shows that the lower attack rate of ZIKV in children than in adults will hasten the emergence of a population that will be fully susceptible to infection, especially if immunity is not lifelong. The advantage of our approach is that we used the age-specific attack rates to model the processes of ageing in relation to protective immunity to ZIKV explicitly. Even with lifelong immunity, our model predicts that children aged 0–14 years will become entirely susceptible by 2031 and 15–29 year olds by 2046. In future outbreaks, the attack rate will then be highest amongst 15–29 year olds, including women who will be at risk of ZIKV infection in pregnancy. If immunity wanes, the time until the next ZIKV outbreak will be reduced and, in that case, the distribution of infection risk would be more equal across age groups (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0007978.g004">Fig 4</xref>). Several authors have studied the time to a next ZIKV outbreak, but none studied the effect of the loss of immunity over time in relation to age. Assuming lifelong immunity, our estimates of the time until the risk increases are similar to the 12–20 years before re-emergence estimated for French Polynesia [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007978.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Netto et al. (2017) used an SEIR model to show that in Salvador, Brazil, the effective reproduction number was insufficient to cause a new outbreak during the “subsequent years” [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007978.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Lourenço et al. (2017) showed the same for the whole of Brazil: herd immunity should protect the population from a new outbreak in the coming years [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007978.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Ferguson et al. (2016) concluded that the age distribution of future ZIKV outbreaks will likely differ and that a new large epidemic will be delayed for “at least a decade” [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007978.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].
</p>
