<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The Smithburn live attenuated RVFV vaccine is one of the oldest and widely used vaccines for the control of RVF infections in Egypt. It was isolated in 1944 in Uganda from a mosquito 
 <italic>Eretmapodites</italic> spp. The neurotropic RVFV strain was generated in South Africa between 1953 and 1985 via 102 serial passages in mouse brain, 54 passages in embryonated chicken egg and another 16 passages in mouse brain. In 1958, only 103 serial passages were performed for the RVFV in mouse brain and elicited better protection [
 <xref rid="B59-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Since 1971, this vaccine has been propagated via passages in BHK-21 cells to produce modified live virus vaccine (MLVV) for the vaccination of livestock in susceptible African countries, such as South Africa, Kenya, Saudi Arabia and Egypt [
 <xref rid="B71-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. The same virus was used to produce live-attenuated vaccines in Kenya and Egypt in 1960 and 1994 respectively. In spite of its potency and low cost, the Smithburn vaccine has several disadvantages including residual pathogenicity, abortions, fetal malformations, and reversion to virulence. Therefore, the live attenuated vaccine is prohibited to be used in pregnant animals and restricted to be used in the RVFV free countries [
 <xref rid="B76-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. There is also a possibility of reassortment when the vaccine used during outbreaks, leading to increased diversity of the virus [
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. This vaccine has been reported to cause pathological changes in liver of kids and abortion in pregnant ewes. Therefore the researcher has concluded that it is not safe to be used in Egypt which considered an endemic area [
 <xref rid="B54-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. The Smithburn vaccine provides protection after a single administration and induces long-lasting protective immunity against RVFV.
</p>
