<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>P. mauritianum</italic> is an endemic medicinal plant of the Mascarene Islands, more specifically of the Reunion and Mauritius Islands. The folk use of this plant has been described for the treatment and management of amenorrhea, dysentery and common infectious diseases [
 <xref rid="B29-ijms-20-01860" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-ijms-20-01860" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-ijms-20-01860" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The high amount of polyphenols of this endemic medicinal plant provides a significant antioxidant activity [
 <xref rid="B39-ijms-20-01860" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Our phytochemical analysis of 
 <italic>P. mauritianum</italic> extract, performed with an ultra-high-performance liquid chromatography-diode array detector coupled to mass spectrometry (UHPLC-DAD-MS), confirmed the phenolic-richness composition of this plant, mainly a glycosylated derivate of gallic acid, quercetin and kaempferol (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-20-01860">Figure S3 and Table S1</xref>). Indeed, numerous polyphenol compounds have been described for their anti-flavivirus activities, such as EGCG, which is also efficient against a broad spectrum of enveloped RNA and DNA viruses [
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-20-01860" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-ijms-20-01860" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-ijms-20-01860" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-ijms-20-01860" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-ijms-20-01860" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-ijms-20-01860" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-ijms-20-01860" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], delphinidin [
 <xref rid="B27-ijms-20-01860" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], naringenin [
 <xref rid="B35-ijms-20-01860" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], isoquercitrin [
 <xref rid="B23-ijms-20-01860" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and curcumin [
 <xref rid="B25-ijms-20-01860" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Likewise, we have recently shown that another polyphenol-rich extract from Reunion Island medicinal plant 
 <italic>Aphloia theiformis</italic> inhibits ZIKV and DENV infection [
 <xref rid="B28-ijms-20-01860" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Thus, it would be of great interest to identify the phytochemicals responsible for 
 <italic>P. mauritianum</italic> and 
 <italic>A. theiformis</italic> antiviral activities or whether there is a synergetic effect of several compounds leading to antiviral activity.
</p>
