<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0025">The Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak caused by the Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) was reported for the first time in December 2019, Wuhan, China (
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Khan et al., 2020</xref>). The COVID-19 then rapidly spread from the epicentre globally, and now characterized as a pandemic by the World Health Organization (
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization, 2020</xref>). The high transmissibility of SARS-CoV-2, the lack of specific treatment and vaccines, and the unstoppable spread of infection have recently caused global health emergency, fear, and psychological stress among the public (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Cohen and Kupferschmidt, 2020</xref>). Like SARS-CoV-2, other viruses including Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus (SARS-CoV), Middle East Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus (MERS-CoV), Marburg virus, and Ebola virus, have caused major outbreaks in history. These outbreaks caused large numbers of fatalities, morbidities, and cost billions of dollars, worldwide (
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Allocati et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Fan et al., 2019</xref>). Bats are reported as a natural reservoir for these viruses, especially coronaviruses (CoVs) which constitute approximately, 31% of their virome (
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Allocati et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Afelt et al., 2018</xref>). These viruses are transmitted to humans either directly or 
 <italic>via</italic> intermediate hosts (
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Chan et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Allocati et al., 2016</xref>). Furthermore, higher species diversity (over 1400), longer lifespan (over 30 years), resistance to viral infection, and migration make them a huge reservoir for pathogens and give them higher chances to transmit pathogens to other species in vast areas (
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Allocati et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Frick et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Banerjee et al., 2020</xref>). In 207 bat species, 5717 bat-associated animal viruses have been detected in 77 different countries (
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Allocati et al., 2016</xref>). However, the elusive and nocturnal habits make them difficult to be studied (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Frick et al., 2019</xref>) therefore, there could be more deadly viruses with epidemic and pandemic potentials if other bats species are studied.
</p>
