<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="abstract"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Virus Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Virus Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">vevolu</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Virus Evolution</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2057-1577</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5905443</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ve/vey010.032</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">vey010.032</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Abstract Overview</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading"><subject>22nd International BioInformatics Workshop on Virus Evolution and Molecular Epidemiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A33&#x02002;Respiratory syncytial virus group B evolutionary trends in the attachment (G) glycoprotein in Kilifi, Kenya, 2003&#x02013;2015</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kamau</surname><given-names>Everlyn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vey010.032-AFF1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lewa</surname><given-names>Clement</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vey010.032-AFF1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Medley</surname><given-names>Graham F</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vey010.032-AFF2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cane</surname><given-names>Patricia A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vey010.032-AFF3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>James Nokes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vey010.032-AFF1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vey010.032-AFF4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Agoti</surname><given-names>Charles N</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vey010.032-AFF1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vey010.032-AFF5">5</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="vey010.032-AFF1"><label>1</label>Wellcome Trust Research Programme, Epidemiology and Demography Department, Kenya Medical Research Institute (KEMRI), Kilifi, Kenya</aff><aff id="vey010.032-AFF2"><label>2</label>Department of Global Health and Development, London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, London, UK</aff><aff id="vey010.032-AFF3"><label>3</label>Public Health England, Salisbury, UK</aff><aff id="vey010.032-AFF4"><label>4</label>School of Life Sciences and SBIDER, University of Warwick, Coventry, UK</aff><aff id="vey010.032-AFF5"><label>5</label>Department of Biomedical Sciences, Pwani University, Kilifi, Kenya</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date iso-8601-date="2018-04-17" pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>17</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>4</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><elocation-id>vey010.032</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by-nc" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access publication distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="vey010.032.pdf"/><counts><page-count count="1"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>Respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) attachment (G) protein mediates virus binding to cells and is a target for human neutralising antibodies. Understanding its evolutionary patterns is relevant to design of vaccines or antiviral therapy. RSV group B genotype BA, characterised by a sixty-nucleotide duplication, was first detected in 1999 in Buenos Aires, Argentina, and has since been spread and become the globally dominant RSV B genotype. BA viruses were first detected in Kilifi, coastal Kenya in 2003 and soon achieved high prevalence, replacing all other RSV-B genotypes. We present in detail, evolutionary patterns of the genotype BA G protein from&#x02009;&#x0003e;600 BA viruses obtained during twelve successive RSV epidemics in Kilifi. Phylogenetic analyses revealed extensive diversification of the BA genotype viruses into multiple genetically distinct variants (&#x0223c;58), some of which persisted locally across sequential epidemics while others were re-introductions into the community. The most recent common ancestor dated back to 1990, and the mean evolutionary rate over their G ectodomain region was 6.51&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup> substitutions/site/year (95 per cent CI 5.65&#x02013;7.42&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>). Demographic analysis demonstrated two main phases: an early rapid expansion and subsequent seasonal fluctuations of BA populations. Putative positive selection was detected in six codon sites, all located in the second hyper-variable G protein region. Nucleotide substitutions introducing alternative termination codons were observed resulting in up to five different protein lengths. Two potential N-glycosylation sites were conserved in 89.3 per cent sampled viruses while eight other sites were detected in a small proportion of the viruses. Further, four codons tended to revert to previous states over successive epidemics, an indication of adaptive mechanism for immune evasion. These results provide insights into the local genotype BA viral evolutionary dynamics and highlight the importance of continuous molecular surveillance to inform on changes in proteins that may be important to vaccine design.</p></body></article>