<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="bullet">
 <list-item>
  <p>Change from STATA software (StataCorp, 2015. Release 14.1, which is not an open-source and consequently limits its accessibility) to “EWARS-R”, using the open-access “R” software (which is free and equally compatible with common programming languages).</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>District-specific alarm data analysis rather than use of overall country information,</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>More accurate surveillance information: The run-in data (the first half of the retrospective surveillance data, used to develop and calibrate the prediction model) utilized broader range of weekly records and was defined by all records preceding the year 2009 in Brazil, 2012 in Malaysia and 2014 in Mexico. All data records reported after these cut-off points (years) were used as the evaluation data (i.e. the second half of the retrospective surveillance data, used to validate the derived parameters from the prediction model, and to identify the correct and false outbreak alarms), which facilitates a multiple rounds of cross-validation process.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Reduced duration of the period of the “moving average” (from 13 to 7 weeks): Average (mean) number of dengue cases–within the expected “normal” or seasonal range–were calculated for a fixed window size of three preceding and three succeeding weeks from the point of measure 3+1+3 weeks to generate a smoothed “moving average”. Relatively smaller window size would likely reveal more details about the outbreak indicator.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Extended number of candidate alarm indicators (meteorological, entomological and epidemiological) which now includes: i) Ovitrap-index in Mexico (the proportion of positive ovitraps and the mean number of eggs per block of houses- the only available entomological indicator with weekly reporting) and, ii) Predominant dengue virus serotype in Malaysia (indicating changes of serotype; weekly information on this indicator was previously unavailable in any of the study countries). 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0196811.g001">Fig 1</xref> illustrates the mechanism of calculating the mean of alarms indicators before entering the regression model.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Advanced method of analysis. The second generation EWARS-R has advanced into multiple logistic regression modelling of outbreak probability, allowing one or more alarm indicator(s) per analysis. This has the potential to account for missing or inconsistent records and improve the explanation of the outbreak prediction. Another analytical advancement with potential for model enhancement is the inclusion of the ‘Spline’ function to adjust for likely non-monotonic nature in some variables. A non-monotonic relationship occurs when the number of dengue cases take an inversed direction as the mean alarm indicator continue to increase, during a particular period. For instance, the number of dengue cases increase as the environmental temperature increases but at one point, a decrease in dengue cases is observed due to a decreased vector activity as a result of excessive temperatures.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Use of district-level Excel spreadsheet files (prospective analysis) containing the algorithm and all parametric coefficients needed for calculating the outbreak probability: These coefficients are estimated during the retrospective phase, depending primarily on the sensitivity (i.e. the proportion of correctly predicting an outbreak out of all outbreaks) and PPV (i.e. the proportion of correct alarms out of all alarms) as direct measures for deciding the best calibrated settings (i.e. those with highest sensitivity and PPV). In the Excel spreadsheet file, the prospective information of alarm indicators is being entered to estimate the probability of an ‘alarm signal’ for a forthcoming outbreak—an alarm signal is triggered when the outbreak probability crosses a given alarm threshold. This process is achieved by inserting weekly district-level prospective data of outbreak cases and alarm indicators (see example in 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0196811.g002">Fig 2</xref>). In these excel spreadsheets, displayed parameters (top-left hand corner) and the graph can guide the interpretation of the “alarm signal” field. For instance, as illustrated in 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0196811.g002">Fig 2</xref>, prospective information on “mean temperature” in week 12 shows an “alarm signal” predicting a forthcoming outbreak in the following 2 weeks (prediction distance, lag time) from the current week.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Implementation of an external interface to reduce human error and increase users’ acceptability. The shift from STATA into EWARS-R facilitated the migration from the typical programming-based STATA do-file interface [
   <xref rid="pone.0196811.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] to a more user-friendly interface designed to focus user’s data inputs to specific ‘boxes’ of interest during the process of the program setting and data calibration, see 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0196811.g003">Fig 3</xref>.
  </p>
 </list-item>
</list>
