<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>North-Asia tick-borne spotted fever (NATBSF) is also known as Siberian tick-borne typhus, North Asian tick-borne rickettsiosis, North Asian tick typhus, and North Asia Fever. Its causative agent is 
 <italic>Rickettsia sibirica</italic>, and small rodents are its main source of infection. This tick-borne disease was first described in 1936 in Russia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. Since this type of infection is common in many republics of North Asia, much effort has been invested into the studies of NATBSF [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. An anti-
 <italic>Rickettsia sibirica</italic> antibody was first detected in the serum of humans and animals in Inner Mongolia in 1958 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. The first case was observed in Hulin city, Heilongjiang province in 1962, where the HL-84 strain of 
 <italic>Rickettsia sibirica</italic> was first isolated from a wild rodent, 
 <italic>Microtus fortis</italic>. Later, the 
 <italic>Rickettsia sibirica</italic> JH-74 strain was isolated from 
 <italic>Dermacentor nuttalli</italic> in 1974 in Jinghe county, Xinjiang autonomous region, and the An-84 strain was isolated from a patient in 1984 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. 
 <italic>Dermacentor nuttalli</italic> is the main vector for North-Asia TBSF; however, 
 <italic>Dermacentor marginatus</italic>, 
 <italic>Dermacentor sinicus</italic>, 
 <italic>Derraacentor silvarum</italic> and 
 <italic>Haemaphysalis yeli</italic> can also be vectors for the disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. Its pathogens can be passed through eggs and can survive for two years in ticks. Because methods for diagnosing this disease are not yet standardized, its prevalence in China has yet to be determined; however, cases have been reported in 7 provinces/municipalities of Northern Heilongjiang, Inner Mongolia, Xinjiang, Beijing, Guangdong, Jilin, and Liaoning (Table 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). The natural foci have been reported to exist in most of Northern China (at longitude 90° ~ 135° East and latitude 40° ~ 50° North); serologic clues have also been found in the serum of humans and rodents in parts of Southern China [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>].
</p>
