<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite the fact that veterinary vaccines are widely available [
 <xref rid="B28-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], there are currently no vaccines against EEEV, VEEV, or WEEV licensed for human use. Early research on vaccines against equine encephalitis viruses focused on the development of inactivated viruses through common methods such as heat or formalin [
 <xref rid="B29-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Viruses were propagated in experimentally infected mice, horses, or chick embryos, isolated from infected tissues (brains), and subsequently inactivated [
 <xref rid="B30-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In 1961, the US Army developed a live-attenuated vaccine called TC-83 and, in 1974, a formalin-inactivated vaccine called C-84 [
 <xref rid="B31-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. These vaccines have been used exclusively for laboratory and military personnel at risk for contracting VEEV and to immunize horses. TC-83 was developed by passaging of the virulent Trinidad donkey strain 83 times through guinea pig heart cell cultures [
 <xref rid="B33-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. This serial passage resulted in mutations in the 5′ noncoding region, nsp3, E2, E1, and 3′ noncoding region [
 <xref rid="B34-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The current live-attenuated TC-83 can be transmitted by mosquitos and causes adverse side effects in ~20% of recipients [
 <xref rid="B31-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. TC-83 also has a high rate (~18%) of serological nonresponse [
 <xref rid="B31-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] and (worryingly) has the potential to cause pancreatic disease [
 <xref rid="B36-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and teratogenic effects [
 <xref rid="B37-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. C-84, though associated with lower reactogenicity than TC-83, provides only short-term immunity in animal models and fails to protect against an aerosol challenge in hamsters [
 <xref rid="B38-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. It is therefore used only as a booster for TC-83 non-responders [
 <xref rid="B39-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Furthermore, the incomplete inactivation of a VEEV equine vaccine caused an epidemic from 1969 to 1972, highlighting the potential dangers of live-virus vaccines [
 <xref rid="B40-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. The investigational EEEV vaccine TS-GSD 104 and WEEV vaccine TS-GSD 210 were developed from attenuated strains and formalin-inactivated [
 <xref rid="B41-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Same-day administration of these two investigational vaccines resulted in immune interference in humans [
 <xref rid="B41-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Immune interference was also found when TS-GSD 104, TS-GSD 210, and TC-83 were used sequentially to immunize human volunteers [
 <xref rid="B42-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Thus, the impact of immune interference should be considered when developing multivalent vaccines. From the perspectives of biodefense and costs associated with severe illness, there is an urgent need for the development of an improved vaccine against EEEV, VEEV, and WEEV that is well-tolerated and highly immunogenic [
 <xref rid="B23-vaccines-08-00273" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Here, we review recent progress made towards safe and immunogenic vaccines.
</p>
