<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza HA binds to host cell sialic acid residues (sias) coating the host cell surface 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Springer1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> and mediates viral entry via its receptor binding domain. Human influenza viruses preferentially bind sia α2,6 linkages, while AIV preferentially bind sia α2,3 linkages that are highly expressed in the gastrointestinal tracts of aquatic birds 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Connor1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Ito1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Matrosovich1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Shinya1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Suzuki1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Suzuki2" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Suzuki3" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Suzuki4" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, thus it is thought that sialic acid residues are important barriers in cross-species transmission. Sias are nine-carbon monosaccharides found at the ends of glycan chains. Sias coat many host cell surfaces and secreted proteins 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Angata1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Schauer1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Varki1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Varki2" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. The most common sias found in mammals are N-acetylneuraminic acid (Neu5Ac) and N-glycolylneuraminic acid (Neu5Gc). Sias are transferred to terminal sugars of glycoproteins and glycolipids by sialyltransferases, and can be added to the galactose carbon-6 forming an α2,6 linkage or to galactose carbon-3 forming an α2,3 linkage 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Suzuki3" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Angata1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Varki2" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. The detection of α2,3 or α2,6 linkages can be determined by use of plant lectins that specifically bind to glycolipids and glycoproteins containing sia α2,6 or α2,3 configurations. A lectin from the seed of 
 <italic>Maackia amurensis</italic> tree (MAA) is specific for sia α2,3, while a lectin obtained from the elderberry plant 
 <italic>Sambucus nigra</italic> (SNA) is specific for sia α2,6 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Shibuya1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. Early experiments showed that SNA preferentially bound to the surface of ciliated tracheal epithelial cells indicating the presence of sia α2,6, and MAA bound goblet cells indicating the presence of sia α2,3 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Baum1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. These studies suggested that ciliated cells, but not goblet cells, were a primary target for human H3 influenza infection and were subsequently confirmed by using a fluorescently-labeled H3 virus which primarily attached to ciliated cells 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Couceiro1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. However, later studies using differentiated human tracheal bronchial epithelial cells found that human influenza viruses infect non-ciliated cells expressing sia α2,6, and AIV infect ciliated cells expressing sia α2,3 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Matrosovich2" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. More recent evidence suggests that H5N1 influenza can replicate within 
 <italic>ex vivo</italic> human respiratory epithelial tissues, despite the lack of sia α2,3 staining 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Nicholls1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. Regardless of the predilection of AIV for sia α2,3, a H5N1 AIV (A/Hong Kong/156/1997) outbreak occurred in humans in Hong Kong in 1997 where all eight viral genes were of avian origin. The currently circulating H5N1 AIV strains primarily infect birds and fowl maintaining a sia α2,3 binding preference; however, AIV can acquire mutations changing their HA binding specificity from avian-like, α2,3, to human-like, α2,6 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Connor1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Matrosovich1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Glaser1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>.
</p>
