<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Coronaviruses are responsible for 5–10% of acute respiratory illness while it has been estimated that 2% of the population is deemed as an asymptomatic carrier of these viruses. The first discovered HCoV was IBV that causes respiratory disease in human whereas, HCoV-229E and HCoV-OC43, which cause the common cold in humans [
 <xref rid="B15-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B85-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. They were not considered to be highly pathogenic for humans until the outbreak of SARS in Guangdong state of China in 2002 and 2003. SARS-CoV infected more than 8000 people worldwide and caused 916 deaths (
 <xref rid="ijerph-17-05648-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), representing a mortality rate by around 10% [
 <xref rid="B86-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. Ten years later in 2012, MERS-CoV emerged in Saudi Arabia and infected over 2494 people with 858 deaths, accounting for a mortality rate approximately of 35% [
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B87-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. Starting in China in December 2019, there were reports of patients presenting severe viral pneumonia [
 <xref rid="B15-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B88-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. This public health concern resulted in many unknown pneumonia cases who were admitted to local hospitals [
 <xref rid="B22-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B78-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>] (
 <uri xlink:href="https://www.who.int" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.who.int</uri>). Primary etiologic investigations performed in those patients showed that they were epidemiologically linked to a Huanan wholesale seafood market that also traded live animals and wildlife [
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B90-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. By January 7th, 2020 Chinese authorities announced that a new type of coronavirus was isolated [
 <xref rid="B60-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B91-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. The epicenter of infection was probably linked to a zoonotic pathogen being present in the seafood and exotic animal wholesale market [
 <xref rid="B60-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B91-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. The rapid increasing numbers and rate of fatalities indicated a second mode of transmission, from human-to-human, that allowed viral spreading primarily in other Asian countries such as South Korea and Iran followed by many countries such as Italy, Spain, Germany, France, Brazil and USA [
 <xref rid="B24-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. It is very intriguing to note that the SARS epidemic in southern China in 2002 and the current outbreak of COVID-19 had peaked in mid-February due to exposure to live animals sold in markets. Furthermore, similar to the SARS outbreak, this epidemic has occurred during the Spring Festival in China, as the most famous traditional countrywide festival in China, gathering nearly three billion people from different areas. These favorable conditions caused the wide transmission of this fatal pneumonia and severe difficulties for disease control and prevention of the epidemic [
 <xref rid="B92-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>].
</p>
