<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The main target cells of CoVs include macrophages, endocrine cells, ganglion cells, dendritic cells, and astrocytes. Recognition of cell surface receptors and adhesion to cells is the first step in infection. The S protein is a transmembrane glycoprotein formed by the S1 subunit at the N terminal and the S2 subunit at the C terminal that are the major antigenic sites on the virus. The S1 subunit contains the receptor binding domain allowing the S protein to bind to host cells. The S2 subunit contains HR1 and HR2 domains that are two α-helix peptides. The S1 subunit binds to the receptor, enabling the S2 fusion peptide to be inserted into the cell membrane, while HR1 and HR2 bind to each other to form a hexamer that completes the fusion between the virus outer membrane and the host cell membrane and allows the injection of genetic materials.
 <xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Currently, receptors that have been found to be used by CoVs include APN/CD13,
 <xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> ACE2,
 <xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> and CEACAM1.
 <xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> After virus entry into the host cell, RNA is used as a template for translation of two polyproteins (1a and 1ab) that are encoded by ORF1. The 3C-like protease and the papain-like protease in polyproteins will hydrolyze polyproteins into 15–16 non-structural proteins, including proteases, RNA replicase, RNA helicase, endonuclease and exonuclease. Following this, the virus RNA forms a replication/transcription complex and completes the synthesis of the negative strand subgenomic RNA, transcription of subgenomic mRNA, and replication of virus genomic gRNA.
 <xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> After virus infection of host cells, dendritic cells (DC) will recognize these cells and secrete type I interferons (IFN-α and IFN-β) and inflammatory factors such as IL-1β, IL-6, IL-8, and TNF-α. This will activate downstream signaling pathways and induce natural killer (NK) cells and macrophages to kill or phagocytose infected cells.
 <xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> The chemokine CCL3 recruits and activates neutrophils, while CCL recruits leukocytes to inflammation sites and induces NK cell proliferation and activation.
 <xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> However, the immune evasion mechanisms of CoVs can inhibit signaling pathways related to the secretion of type I interferons and chemokines and can impair the function of DCs, NK cells, and neutrophils, thereby interfering with the body’s antiviral response and causing the body to be unable to generate persistent and effective immunity after infection.
 <xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> In addition, dissemination to neighboring cells is one of the ways by which CoVs evade immune responses.
 <xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>
</p>
