<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The most prominent result of our study was that despite its huge climatic variation sustained influenza epidemics in Australia were often highly synchronized, especially during years that were observed to be associated with antigenically distinct strains. Although we were unable to assess pairwise synchrony by A subtype or B lineage (due to lack of data), we observed that the onset of nationwide epidemics was more synchronized during years in which there was emergence of novel strains or distinct antigenic changes, including 2009 (pandemic A/H1N1), 2012 (a new A/H3N2 variant) and 2014 (another new A/H3N2 variant). However, due to the low level of exact influenza A subtype data we could not assess whether the pairwise synchrony was entirely driven by these subtypes. For example, although 2009 and 2012 were dominated by A/H1N1 and A/H3N2, respectively, more precise subtype data suggested that both A/H1N1 and A/H3N2 viruses were present, with A/H1N1 circulating early in the season and A/H3N2 circulating later in the season [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006780.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Despite the obvious importance of domestic travel in driving the spread of influenza, it is likely that onset synchronicity has been enhanced by the multiple introductions of global influenza viruses into Australia, a process that was clearly apparent in our large-scale phylogeographic analysis. We also believe that this pattern is robust to ascertainment bias. In particular, although the rate of spread during 2009 was much higher compared to other years, the mean week of epidemic onset across all locations was later, at 23 weeks, compared to 21 weeks in 2011 and 2013 (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat.1006780.t001">Table 1</xref>). In addition, that all years studied exhibited greater nationwide synchrony than previously observed in the US [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006780.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] suggests that the pattern is indeed genuine and reflects the intrinsic dynamics of influenza in Australia. This synchronicity occurs despite the diverse array of climate types present across the Australian continent, suggesting that such seasonal epidemic dynamics override considerable climatic variation.
</p>
