<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32">Currently, the World Health Organization (WHO) and Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) do not recommend the routine use of systemic corticosteroids for treatment of viral pneumonia unless indicated for another reason, such as asthma or chronic obstructive pulmonary disease exacerbation, or refractory septic shock [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>]. The Surviving Sepsis Campaign COVID-19 subcommittee recommends against the routine use of systemic corticosteroids in mechanically ventilated adults with COVID-19 and respiratory failure (without ARDS), although this is a weak and poorly substantiated recommendation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>]. However, these recommendations may be amended based on preliminary results from the RECOVERY trial, which showed that dexamethasone reduces mortality among COVID-19 patients with severe respiratory complications [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>]. Low-dose dexamethasone (6 mg once daily, orally or intravenously) for 10 days reduced deaths by one-third in patients on mechanical ventilation [rate ratio (RR) 0.65, 95% CI 0.48–0.88; 
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.0003] and by one-fifth in patients receiving oxygen only (RR 0.80, 95% CI 0.67–0.96; 
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.0021); however, no benefit was reported in patients with milder symptoms (i.e. not requiring respiratory support). Prior to these findings, a multicenter, randomized controlled trial (DEXA-ARDS) studied the effects of intravenous dexamethasone at a dose of 20 mg once daily on days 1–5, followed by 10 mg once daily on days 6–10 in non-COVID-19 patients with moderate-to-severe ARDS receiving lung-protective mechanical ventilation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>]. Compared with those receiving conventional treatment, the addition of dexamethasone to the therapy regimen lead to a reduction in mechanical ventilation duration (between-group difference of 4.8 days, 95% CI 2.57–7.03, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001), and in overall mortality at day 60 (between-group difference –15.3%, 95% CI − 25.9 to − 4.9; 
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.0047). Accordingly, a multicenter, randomized, controlled, open-label trial (DEXA-COVID19) involving mechanically ventilated adult patients with ARDS with confirmed COVID-19 infection has commenced (NCT04325061). Compared with methylprednisolone, dexamethasone has less mineralocorticoid activity and is less likely to cause sodium and fluid retention, a concern in this patient population [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>].
</p>
