<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par37">This article provides an overview of published information on domestic research and the development of coronavirus-related therapeutic agents. The drug-repurposing effort summarized in this article focused primarily on agents currently known to be active against other RNA viruses, including SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV, influenza, HCV, and Ebola, as well as anti-inflammatory drugs. This information provides a strong intellectual groundwork for support of current and future research and development for the discovery and development of therapeutic agents for the treatment of COVID-19 and coronavirus-related diseases. However, there are still no officially approved specific antiviral drugs or vaccines for SARS-CoV-2, and supportive care remains a key to treatment. TCM has accumulated thousands of years of experience in the treatment of pandemic and endemic diseases. Complementary and alternative treatments are still urgently needed for the management of patients with SARS-CoV-2 infection, and experiences in TCM are certainly worth examining. Many antiviral Chinese patent medicines, such as Shuanghuanglian oral solution and others, have been declared to have the effect of heat clearing and detoxifying, which could help clear viral respiratory pathogens and relieve symptoms according to TCM theory. Chinese patent medicine has been used in many historic epidemics, such as the previous two coronavirus outbreaks (SARS-CoV in 2013 and MERS-CoV in 2012) and seasonal epidemics caused by influenza viruses and dengue virus. Fighting against current epidemics also provides an opportunity to test the true value of TCM in treating emerging contagious diseases. It is encouraging that controlled clinical studies to evaluate the efficacy of TCM in the treatment of SARS-CoV were conducted and reported. We believe that specific and efficient antiviral drugs and therapy will arise from these ongoing and developing drugs, especially from the rich tradition of herbal medicines in China.</p>
