<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>FPV (T-705, 
 <bold>3</bold>), a guanine analog approved for influenza treatment in Japan in 2014, can effectively inhibit the RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp) of RNA viruses such as influenza, Ebola, yellow fever, chikungunya, norovirus and enterovirus.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref58">58</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref59">59</xref>
 </sup> FPV is converted into an active phosphoribosylated form (FPV-RTP) in cells that is recognized as a substrate by the viral RNA polymerase, thus inhibiting RNA polymerase activity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref60">60</xref>
 </sup> A recent study conducted by Wang et al. showed that the EC
 <sub>50</sub> of FPV against SARS-CoV-2 in Vero E6 cells was 61.88 μM; the CC
 <sub>50</sub> value was &gt;400 μM; and the SI was &gt;6.46.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>
 </sup> FPV was 100% protective against Ebola virus challenge in mice, although the EC
 <sub>50</sub> in Vero E6 cells was as high as 67 μM.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref61">61</xref>
 </sup> Since late February 2020, two randomized clinical trials were commenced to evaluate the efficacy of FPV in treating COVID-19 patients in China. Cai et al. conducted an open-label controlled study to evaluate FPV’s clinical efficacy for COVID-19. In this study, 35 patients received oral FPV plus IFN-α as an inhaled aerosol, and 45 patients received lopinavir/ritonavir plus IFN-α as an inhaled aerosol. A significantly shorter viral clearance time was observed in the FPV group than in the lopinavir/ritonavir group by day 7. The FPV group also showed significant improvement in chest imaging compared with the lopinavir/ritonavir group, with an improvement rate of 91.4% versus 62.2% at day 4 after treatment. The rate of adverse reactions in the FPV group (11.4%) was significantly smaller compared to the lopinavir/ritonavir group (55.6%).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref62">62</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
