<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Actually, several anti-HIV proteins or peptides with HIV inactivation activity similar to that of 2DLT had already been studied before 2011, but without assessing their virus inactivation effects. The first one was soluble CD4 (sCD4) (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Deen et al., 1988</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B144" ref-type="bibr">Traunecker et al., 1988</xref>). Theoretically, sCD4 could interact with the CD4bs in gp120 on HIV-1 and inactivate the cell-free virions in the absence of host cells because virions would lose their ability to bind with the cellular receptor CD4, making it impossible for them to enter the CD4 T cell for replication. Indeed, 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> studies indicated that sCD4 could inhibit HIV-1 infection with IC50 (half maximal inhibitory concentration) values between 40 and 700 nM (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Daar et al., 1990</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr">Orloff et al., 1993</xref>). The results from phases I–II clinical trials showed that intravenously administered sCD4 effectively reduced viral titers in sera without causing obvious toxicity. However, the half-life of sCD4 is short, leading to viral relapse within a short time after treatment (
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">Kahn et al., 1990</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B131" ref-type="bibr">Schooley et al., 1990</xref>). At low concentrations (&lt;1 μg/ml or 20 nM), sCD4 could not effectively inhibit HIV-1 infection, but rather enhanced the infection of some HIV-1 clinical isolates in host cells, including some CD4- CCR5+ cells. This is because sCD4 binding to CD4bs in gp120 triggers the exposure of CoRbs in gp120 and NHR in gp41, facilitating the interaction between CoRbs in gp120 and the CCR5 coreceptor on the host cell and, hence, fusion between the viral envelope and host cell membrane (
 <xref rid="B140" ref-type="bibr">Sullivan et al., 1998</xref>). Since CD4 is an important immune molecule that exerts its function through interaction with a number of human proteins, 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> application of sCD4, an anti-HIV drug, may cause some adverse effects to the immune system. Therefore, development of sCD4 for clinical use has been discontinued, but the important information from the research on sCD4 has promoted studies of HIV inactivators containing part(s) of CD4 molecule.
</p>
