<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Identifying the roles of reservoir hosts and the vectors of animal disease is a major challenge in epidemiological studies and stable isotopes can provide insights into the ecology of vector-borne diseases. Molecular methods of blood meal typing are sensitive, but can be compromised by rapid digestion of the blood, denaturing of DNA, and mixed blood meals (Gómez-Díaz and Figuerola 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2010</xref>). Stable isotopes represent a complementary technique that can avoid these problems. The isotopic composition of vector tissues is a function of the isotopic signature of each host species on which it fed and also of the relative proportions of each host species assimilated. Hence, once the isotope ratios measured in an arthropod vector are known, inferences regarding its diet and feeding behavior can be made (Hood-Nowotny and Knols 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">2007</xref>). Determination of carbon (δ
 <sup>13</sup>C) and nitrogen (δ
 <sup>15</sup>N) isotope ratios is the most widely used technique for characterizing feeding relationships among vectors/hosts, but the inclusion of other stable isotopes, such as hydrogen, oxygen and sulfur, can make it easier to differentiate between potential hosts in diverse communities. In order to be effective, the determination of discrimination factors requires the development of a library of isotopic signatures of the possible hosts of the vector in the area being studied. The value of SIA in resolving the roles of different hosts and vectors in the ecology of multi-host pathogens has been shown by the studies of Stapp and Salkeld (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR174">2009</xref>) on the host–parasite relationship between mice, prairie dogs, and fleas in the transmission of 
 <italic>Yersinia pestis</italic>. It has been assumed that the mice spread the bacterium among prairie dog colonies by sharing the flea of the prairie dog, 
 <italic>Oropsylla hirsuta</italic>. Stable nitrogen analysis showed that the fleas did not feed on the mice and that they became infected by other methods, such as mechanical transmission or scavenging carcasses. Feeding on vertebrate blood is a critical stage in the transmission of numerous pathogens by ticks, mosquitoes, tsetse flies, midges, and other hematophagous arthropods, but identifying the sources of their blood meals by conventional techniques is only useful for about 36 h after they have fed. In contrast, carbon and nitrogen stable isotope profiles of mosquitoes fed up to 7 days previously could be used to identify successfully the mammal hosts on which the insects had fed (Stapp and Salkeld 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR174">2009</xref>). Proof-of-concept studies have also demonstrated that stable isotope ratios of nitrogen and carbon of host blood are was detected in unfed nymphal 
 <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic> that had developed from larvae fed on that host. SIA of unfed ticks was considered to have potential for determining the physiological age of unfed ticks, identifying the season in which the previous stage had fed, and for identifying the main hosts utilized by ticks (Schmidt et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR163">2011</xref>). Stable isotopes have also been used in determining relationships between the animal host and the vector. For example, the vampire bat, 
 <italic>Desmodus rotundus</italic>, is a significant threat to animals and humans as it is able to transmit pathogens such as the rabies virus, but the host selection preferences are not well understood. The stable carbon isotope signatures of the blood ingested by the bats were used to identify the hosts on which the bats were feeding. Cattle ingest grass and exhibit the C
 <sub>4</sub> metabolic pathway of CO
 <sub>2</sub> fixation, whereas other mammals in the forested areas feed on plants that show the C
 <sub>3</sub> pathway. In an area where both cattle and forest animals were living, the bats preferentially fed on cattle, possibly because they represented an easy source of food since they were herded together and easy prey for the bats (Voigt and Kelm 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR184">2007</xref>). Clearly there is a significant role for the use of stable isotopes in this sort of study, but their use in understanding host–parasite interactions in vector-borne diseases is still largely unexplored.
</p>
