<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F0007" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 7.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Itraconazole treatment restricts progression of IAV infection in mice. Eight-to-ten weeks-old male mice were treated intragastrically with itraconazole (70 mg/kg body weight) diluted in propylene glycol hydroxypropyl-β-cyclodextrine (Itra, solid line). Control animals received the equivalent volume of the solvent (vehicle, dotted line). Mice were infected intranasally with 500 pfu of the IAV H1N1 strain PR8M. (A) Cumulative survival rate and loss of liveweight plotted against days post infection. Mortality also includes mice that were euthanized because of a body weight loss of ≥20%. 
   <italic>n</italic> = 20 mice/group, Mantel-Cox log rank test, 
   <italic>p</italic> = 0.0136 or Mann–Whitney 
   <italic>U</italic>-test. (B) Viral loads in lungs of the individual mice at indicated times post infection. (C) qPCR analysis of 
   <italic>IFNβ</italic> and the ISGs 
   <italic>MX1</italic>and 
   <italic>OASL1</italic> in lung homogenates of non-infected mice treated with either vehicle (control) or itraconazole. Samples were obtained from four individuals per group and were run in triplicates. Expression levels of the genes of interest in the individual samples were normalized to GAPDH and CYCS. 2
   <sup>−ΔΔCt</sup> was used to calculate the drug-induced fold change of relative gene expression compared to control animals. Graphs show difference in the respective genes in individual drug-treated animals relative to control, with the mean fold change ± SEM superimposed. Statistical significance of the differences was evaluated by unpaired student 
   <italic>t-test</italic> on ΔΔCt values. *
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.1, **
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001, ****
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <alternatives>
  <graphic specific-use="web-only" content-type="black-white" xlink:href="TEMI_A_1559709_F0007_OB" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <graphic specific-use="print-only" content-type="black-white" xlink:href="TEMI_A_1559709_F0007_PB" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </alternatives>
</fig>
