<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>According to Brierley et al. (
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>), transmission routes with environmental components (e.g., fecal–oral or food borne transmission) would be associated with higher virulence than direct, contact-based transmission. EnvID analysis shows that distal environmental changes, such as those related to urbanization and climate, need to be considered as they may act through multiple intermediate steps on COVID-19 transmission. As an example, pollution linked either to urbanization and to climate factors may play a role. It is known in fact that a prolonged exposure to air pollution leads to a chronic inflammatory stimulus, even in young and healthy subjects (
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>). For this reason, a contribute of air pollution and particulate cannot be neglected as an environmental factor that may directly or indirectly influence the transmission cycle of SARS-CoV-2. Regarding climate, it has been shown that SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV are quite resistant even at a temperature of 30°C when RH is not exceeding 30%. It has been shown for influenza virus that at low RH, evaporation of water from exhaled bioaerosols would occur rapidly, leading to the formation of droplet nuclei; conversely, at high RH, small respiratory droplets would take on water, increase in size and settle more quickly out of the air (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>). If SARS-CoV-2 will also show similar resistance patterns, as the other CoVs, and its transmission is not impaired at 30°C, this may suggest that contact-based spread may predominate in the tropics where RH is generally high, whereas aerosol transmission may play a larger role in temperate climates. Even if person to person transmission is considered the main transmission pathway, our proposed transmission pattern underlines that human, environment and animal, might all play a role in the potential spread and persistence of SARS-CoV-2 with a different weight in different geographical and social contexts. In particular, environmental contamination and human/animal habitat overlapping cannot be overlooked especially in developing countries. Coronaviruses exist and can maintain their viability in sewage and wastewater, originating from the fecal discharge of infected patients, highlighting the importance of sanitation to protect public health (
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>). In developing countries, where water and sanitation systems are often insufficient or ineffective, it is necessary to consider that SARS-CoV-2 transmission might be amplified through water contamination in cities.
</p>
