<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Identification of cellular receptors has vastly improved our understanding of CDV viral tropism and pathogenesis. Two cellular receptors, the SLAM/CD150, and nectin cell adhesion molecule 4 (nectin-4/PVRL4), involved in the entry of morbillivirus in the cell, and subsequent infection, have been identified for both the vaccine and wild-type CDV strains. Noted, SLAM is reported to be expressed on the surface of activated T-lymphocytes, and B-lymphocytes, macrophages, and dendritic cells, but not in epithelial cells, whereas nectin-4 is known to be expressed on the apical and basolateral surface of polarized epithelial cells, as well as in endothelial cells in the central nervous system (CNS) of dogs [
 <xref rid="B39-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Thus, both SLAM and nectin-4 have been suggested to play crucial roles in the entry, dissemination, and pathogenesis of CDV in vivo (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00339-f002">Figure 2</xref>). After transmission by aerosol, CDV has been shown to cross the respiratory tract to reach immune tissues in the oral cavity via infected SLAM expressing immune cells, most likely macrophages or dendritic cells (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00339-f002">Figure 2</xref>a). Then, infected cells are known to carry the virus to the draining lymph nodes, where the resident activated T-cells and B-cells are infected via SLAM, resulting in the amplification of the virus and the initiation of primary viremia. Subsequently, the virus gets disseminated to secondary lymphoid organs, including the spleen, thymus, lungs, and gastrointestinal tract, followed by a systemic spread through the entire immune circulation system, causing secondary viremia with severe immunosuppression (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00339-f002">Figure 2</xref>b). At this point, CDV infection is thought to occur via the basolateral side of nectin-4 expressing lumen epithelium via the migration of virally-infected T-cells, B-cells, and dendritic cells from the circulation (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00339-f002">Figure 2</xref>c). The hosts would show signs of CD clinical disease, including developing a rash, diarrhea, and conjunctivitis, only after CDV infection of epithelial cells. Then, CDV is known to shed from the epithelium of the respiratory and digestive route via its apical surface (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00339-f002">Figure 2</xref>d). In later stages of infection, CDV would usually cross the blood–brain barrier and reach the CNS, causing neurological symptoms, which might be mediated by nectin-4 or a yet unknown cellular entry receptor in astrocytes [
 <xref rid="B43-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].
</p>
