<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Zika virus (ZIKV) is a recently emerged, mosquito-borne virus belonging to the 
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic> genus isolated initially from a sentinel monkey, at the Zika forest in Uganda in 1947 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. For decades, only sporadic circulation of ZIKV was documented in Africa and South East Asia [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] with two main genotypes; African and Asian genotypes [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Nevertheless, major epidemics were reported in Micronesia in 2007 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], the Pacific region in 2013–2014 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], and Brazil in 2015, the starting point of the unprecedented outbreak affecting several countries and territories in the Americas [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. During the same period, ZIKV transmission was reported in some African countries such as Cabo Verde [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], Guinea Bissau [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], and Angola [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Because of the association of ZIKV with microcephaly [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], Guillain-Barré syndrome [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], and myelitis [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], ZIKV was declared as a Public Health emergency of International concern in 2016 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. ZIKV can be transmitted by sexual intercourse, blood transfusion, and from mother to child (breast milk and in utero) or by physical contacts [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. However, vertebrates including humans are mainly infected through the bite of an infected mosquitoes belonging to the 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> genus. Two main transmission cycles are well documented: (i) a sylvatic cycle between non-human primates and arboreal canopy-dwelling mosquitoes including 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>africanus</italic>, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>furcifer</italic>, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>luteocaphalus</italic>, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>opok</italic>, and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>vittatus</italic> mainly in Africa and (ii) an urban cycle between humans and domestic mosquitoes such as 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Both epidemic vectors, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic>, are well established in Africa where 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> is native [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. While 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> originated from Asia, it was reported for the first time in Central Africa in early 2000 in Cameroon [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and has progressively colonized almost all countries in the region where it tends to supplant the resident species 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Interestingly, the first ZIKV strain isolated from 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> was in Gabon (Central Africa) in mosquitoes collected in urban areas [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], highlighting the potential role of this species as a ZIKV vector in the region. In contrast, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> has never been found naturally infected with ZIKV in the Central African region. However, from a study with blood donors showing that ZIKV is circulating in Cameroon, nearly 5–10% of people from six towns have been exposed to ZIKV infections [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The vector competence of natural 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> populations from Central Africa has remained unclear. It has been demonstrated that the level of vector competence varies according to mosquito populations and ZIKV strains [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0008163.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. To fill this gap, we assessed the ability of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> populations from Central Africa to transmit a ZIKV strain isolated in West Africa.
</p>
