<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the future, it will thus remain critical to administer drugs not only to confirmed or suspect cases, but also to contact individuals as early as possible, in a context where clinical trials or NHP models demonstrated their efficacy. This may meet the request of field teams during the Western African EVD outbreak to propose an early oral treatment to suspected cases, even before their transfer to care centers. In addition, having a drug active even only when administered early may contribute to empower local communities and improve their collaborations with non‐government organizations and local authorities.
 <xref rid="psp412510-bib-0089" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>89</sup>
 </xref> An antiviral strategy may also offer an alternative to a vaccine, or be complementary to it, for exposed people. The promising vesicular stomatitis virus‐based vaccine used in Guinea provided high level protection after a 10‐day delay, but its efficacy in postexposure in both humans and NHPs is less clear.
 <xref rid="psp412510-bib-0090" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>90</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="psp412510-bib-0091" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>91</sup>
 </xref> Interestingly, favipiravir has been used alone or with monoclonal antibodies as postexposure prophylaxis in at least five healthcare workers with percutaneous accidents and suspected EBOV exposures during the West Africa outbreak. None of these individuals developed laboratory or clinical evidence of EBOV infection, but whether any infections were prevented by the use of postexposure prophylaxis is not possible to determine from this small number of uncontrolled cases.
 <xref rid="psp412510-bib-0092" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>92</sup>
 </xref> There remains, more generally, to find drug combinations that could potentiate favipiravir against EBOV. Given the cost of experiments, this will essentially rely on 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> experiments, that can be optimized using modeling, as was done for instance in HCV.
 <xref rid="psp412510-bib-0093" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>93</sup>
 </xref> Importantly, and unlike what was found in mice infected with Lassa virus, it is unlikely that the combination of favipiravir and ribavirin is relevant against EBOV, as no gain in terms of survival or viral replication was found in animals receiving the combination as compared with those receiving favipiravir alone (unpublished results).
</p>
