<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par107">Single B cells can be isolated from either PBMCs or lymphoid tissues using micromanipulation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR198">198</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR199">199</xref>], laser capture microdissection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR200">200</xref>], and fluorescence-activated cell sorting [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR199">199</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR201">201</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR202">202</xref>]. Generally, mononuclear cells are purified from PBMCs or bone marrow by Ficoll-Paque density gradient centrifugation. Based on B cell expression of specific cell surface markers in different stages, isolation of single B cells by fluorescence-activated cell sorting is widely utilized, especially in the identification of rare and discrete B cell subpopulations. Antigen-coated magnetic beads [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR203">203</xref>] and fluorescence-conjugated antigens [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR204">204</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR206">206</xref>] are also often used to select antigen-specific B cells in a process known as antigen baiting. Neutralizing human mAbs against Puumala virus were generated from B cells isolated using antigen-coated magnetic beads [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR207">207</xref>]. Recently, antigen-conjugated fluorescent beads have been used to identify antigen-specific B cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR208">208</xref>]. Fluorescent virus-like particles of rotavirus served as antigen bait for single RV-specific B cells, which had been extracted from healthy rotavirus-infected infants or adult donors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR209">209</xref>]. HIV envelope protein antigens have also been used to isolate antibodies that broadly neutralize HIV-1 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR210">210</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR211">211</xref>]. Moreover, isolation of dengue virus-specific memory B cells was reported [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR212">212</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR213">213</xref>]. Thus, antigen baiting may be applied as a preliminary selection tool to be used on a polyclonal mixture.
</p>
