<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We deem that this study can stimulate an additional investigation on the therapeutic value of mutagenic drugs against flaviviruses and, in particular, for the treatment of persistent flaviviral disease (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>). Mutagenic drugs seem to be especially effective against persistent infections, with major evidences of lethal mutagenesis obtained during treatment of chronically infected hosts, i.e., HCV-infected patients treated with ribavirin, and mice persistently infected with norovirus and treated with favipiravir (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). A tentative explanation for the better efficacy of mutagenic drugs in this context may be linked to potentially larger accumulation of mutations during longer periods of exposure to drugs (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>). A vast range of flavivirus-associated disorders have been connected with persistent infection, including ZIKV (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>). ZIKV infects a broad range of cell types and tissues, including the reproductive tract and the central nervous system (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>). Persistent replication in these tissues has been connected to diverse severe conditions, such as end-organ disease, platelet-related illness, and potentially blinding uveitis (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Persistent ZIKV in the reproductive tissue is possibly responsible for a growing number of cases of sexually transmitted disease, with some studies predicting that this may become a major route of infection in the future (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>). Vaginal mucosa infection has also been related to fetal infection, further highlighting the impact of ZIKV persistence in the genital tract (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>). It is therefore tempting to investigate the potential therapeutic value of lethal mutagenesis in the treatment of persistent infection in the reproductive tract mucosa.
</p>
