<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>According to the Centers for Disease Control (CDC), there are few contraindications against administration to adults of a live attenuated vaccine such as MMR if the recipient is immunocompetent and not pregnant and has not shown previous allergic responses to vaccination (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/vaccines/vpd/mmr/hcp/recommendations.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.cdc.gov/vaccines/vpd/mmr/hcp/recommendations.html</ext-link>). In fact, MMR vaccination is recommended in high-risk adults (i.e., health care workers) and people born before 1957 who did not receive the vaccine as a child. Adults who had received the MMR vaccine in childhood likely still possess antibody titers against the targeted viruses but not the shorter-lived trained innate leukocytes. Hence, at the very least, the MMR vaccine would provide added protection against measles, mumps, and rubella for older adults. But with the added induction of the trained innate cells, the MMR vaccination could provide protection against the worst sequelae of COVID-19. In direct support of this concept, it was recently reported that the milder symptoms seen in the 955 sailors on the U.S.S. 
 <italic>Roosevelt</italic> who tested positive for COVID-19 (only one hospitalization) may have been a consequence of the fact that MMR vaccinations are given to all U.S. Navy recruits (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.globenewswire.com/news-release/2020/05/01/2026166/0/en/MMR-Vaccine-May-Reduce-COVID-19-Hospitalization-Rate-According-to-World-Organization.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.globenewswire.com/news-release/2020/05/01/2026166/0/en/MMR-Vaccine-May-Reduce-COVID-19-Hospitalization-Rate-According-to-World-Organization.html</ext-link>). In addition, epidemiological data suggest a correlation between subjects in geographical locations who routinely receive live attenuated measles-rubella vaccines such as the commonly available MMR vaccine, and reduced COVID-19 death rates (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/341354165_MMR_Vaccine_Appears_to_Confer_Strong_Protection_from_COVID-19_Few_Deaths_from_SARS-CoV-2_in_Highly_Vaccinated_Populations" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/341354165_MMR_Vaccine_Appears_to_Confer_Strong_Protection_from_COVID-19_Few_Deaths_from_SARS-CoV-2_in_Highly_Vaccinated_Populations</ext-link>).
</p>
