<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>GLS-5700, a DNA vaccine encoding for the Zika virus prME genes designed as a consensus based on available Zika virus sequences through December 2015 [
 <xref rid="B43-tropicalmed-04-00104" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], was the first to enter into clinical trials. In pre-clinical studies, vaccinated mice and non-human primates were shown to develop B and T-cell immune responses against the Zika virus envelope and protected against development of neurologic disease and death in immunosuppressed, interferon α, β receptor deficient (IFNAR) mice [
 <xref rid="B43-tropicalmed-04-00104" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Moreover, histologic sections of brain tissue showed that vaccinated mice were without inflammatory infiltrates evident in non-immunized mice [
 <xref rid="B43-tropicalmed-04-00104" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Subsequent studies showed that the vaccine protected against testicular damage, testicular atrophy, spermatozoal damage, and infertility in mice [
 <xref rid="B28-tropicalmed-04-00104" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-tropicalmed-04-00104" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. A Phase I study evaluated GLS-5700 administered via intradermal injection (ID), followed by electroporation (EP) at doses of either 1 or 2 mg per vaccinations followed immediately by electroporation at baseline, 4 weeks and 12 weeks [
 <xref rid="B42-tropicalmed-04-00104" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. There were no serious adverse events (SAE) reported as part of the study, with the most frequent adverse events related to discomfort, pain, or swelling at the injection site. Seroconversion was observed in 83% of individuals after two vaccinations and 100% after three vaccinations with GLS-5700 [
 <xref rid="B42-tropicalmed-04-00104" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Neutralizing antibodies were detected for 62% of participants in a Vero-cell (monkey kidney cell) assay, however, 95% of participants demonstrated the ability to neutralize infection of U87MG neuroblastoma cells [
 <xref rid="B42-tropicalmed-04-00104" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Vaccine responses were maintained through a year of follow-up. There was no difference in responses based on dose level. Notably, passive transfer of immune serum from vaccinated participants was able to protect 92% of IFNAR mice against lethal infection independent of the presence of Vero cell neutralizing antibodies [
 <xref rid="B42-tropicalmed-04-00104" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. GLS-5700 is being evaluated as part of a second double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial (NCT02887482) performed in Puerto Rico. Analysis of the latter study is in progress.
</p>
