<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Aside from the lipids system, polymers have been widely explored for the delivery of different vaccine candidates. Specifically, cationic and ionizable polymers are promising in nucleic acid-based vaccine formulations. Positively charged polymers can condense nucleic acids as nanocomplexes for efficient cellular uptake and endosomal release. In addition, early studies showed that cationic materials tend to induce an inflammatory response.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref90">90</xref>
 </sup> One commonly applied polymer category is polyamines, such as polyethylene imine (PEI) and its derivatives.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref91">91</xref>
 </sup> Chahal 
 <italic>et al</italic>. utilized modified dendrimer for antigen-encoding mRNA replicon complexation to form monodisperse NPs.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref60">60</xref>
 </sup> This delivery system, with self-amplifying mRNA, enabled immunization in mice, which protected them from various virus challenges, including H1N1 influenza, Ebola virus, and the 
 <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> parasite.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref60">60</xref>
 </sup> However, their high molecular weight (MW) and branched polymer structure (needed to allow a massive loading of vaccine therapeutics) also lead to severe cytotoxicity, which limits wider applications.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref92">92</xref>
 </sup> Zhao 
 <italic>et al</italic>. developed a low MW PEI with modifications (stearic acid and 2 kDa PEI conjugates) to form self-assembled micelles for delivering mRNA encoding HIV-1 group-specific antigen (gag).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref62">62</xref>
 </sup> Li 
 <italic>et al</italic>. used 2 kDa PEI conjugated with cyclodextrin for intranasal delivery of HIV antigen-encoding mRNA that was able to stimulate HIV-specific immune response.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref63">63</xref>
 </sup> Cyclodextrin modification provided mucosal permeation and mitigated cytotoxicity by lowering the charge density. Other commonly used polymers include polyester-based, such as poly(lactic-
 <italic>co</italic>-glycolic acid) (PLGA) and poly(lactic acid) (PLA), because of their biocompatibility and biodegradability.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref93">93</xref>
 </sup> Several studies have demonstrated the delivery of protein antigens in PLGA NPs with enhanced immune responses as compared to soluble formulations.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref94">94</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref95">95</xref>
 </sup> In addition, such solid polymer particles can control the kinetics of antigens released from the polymer core based on different biodegradation profiles.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref64">64</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref96">96</xref>
 </sup> However, nonmodified PLGA is generally negatively charged, and as a result, it has a limited cellular uptake efficiency and loading of anionic antigens.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref66">66</xref>
 </sup> Therefore, various coating or modification strategies (such as PEI,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref65">65</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref97">97</xref>
 </sup> chitosan,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref66">66</xref>
 </sup> and poly-
 <sc>l</sc>-lysine (PLL) coatings) have been demonstrated to enable the delivery of vaccines and promote interactions with negatively charged cellular membranes.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref67">67</xref>
 </sup> Notably, the cationic polymeric delivery carrier itself could induce T helper cell responses through TLR-4 dependent IL-12 secretion.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref67">67</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref98">98</xref>
 </sup> Poly(β-amino esters) (PBAE) is also extensively used in delivering plasmids DNA or mRNA vaccines because of its nontoxic and biodegradable nature.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref99">99</xref>
 </sup> Fields 
 <italic>et al</italic>. developed NPs formulations for plasmid DNA delivery by combining PLGA and PBAE to reconcile the drawbacks from each component: the low DNA loading efficiency of PLGA and the cytotoxicity of PBAE.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref68">68</xref>
 </sup> Other polymeric materials have also been explored, such as polysaccharides
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref100">100</xref>
 </sup> and block copolymers.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref101">101</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
