<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Further analysis of NGS data also suggests that IBV may somehow interfere with A549 cell proliferation, which is consistent with our in vitro proliferation data reported in our previous work [
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-12-00383" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Previous studies showed that IAV infection arrested A549 cells at the G0/G1 phase [
 <xref rid="B49-viruses-12-00383" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-viruses-12-00383" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-viruses-12-00383" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], via inhibition of S phase promoting checkpoint proteins. It is assumed that cell cycle arrest can benefit viral replication. For instance, the transcription activity of DNA polymerase II (Pol II), which is required for the transcription of viral proteins, is higher in G0/G1 phase than other phases. The translation of viral proteins requires host-derived cap-dependent translation activity, which is optimal at G0/G1 phase. However, the mechanism of virus mediated host cell cycle arrest is still unclear. One hypothesis is that NS1 of IBV, similar to its counterpart in IAV, down-regulates the expression and activity of the Ras homologue gene family member A (RhoA) kinase [
 <xref rid="B52-viruses-12-00383" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], a GTPase that is critical for G1/S phase transition. Overexpression of IAV NS1 can cause increased expression of both p27 and p21, which as a result down-regulates the expression of cyclin D [
 <xref rid="B52-viruses-12-00383" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. IAV NS1 can also inhibit the catalytic activity of pRb, CDK4, and CDK6, which are important regulators of G1/S check point. In this study, we observed decreased expression of cyclin D2, CDK4, and CDK6, while the expression of p21 was up regulated. These observations are consistent with the above hypothesis, suggesting IBV may use the same mechanism for cell cycle arrest as that reported previously for IAV. Furthermore, the expression of genes functioning in S and M phases are down regulated, implying that IBV infection may slow down cellular processes such as DNA recombination, DNA replication, and chromosome segregation. However, further investigations are required to uncover the mechanisms of these regulations and how these regulations would help IBV to replicate in cells.
</p>
