<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The avian influenza viruses of the subtypes H5 and H7 have the capacity to convert into highly pathogenic avian influenza (HPAI) viruses, which are associated with high mortality rates. Although some specific correlates that lead to the emergence of HPAI viruses have been identified, the underlying mechanism for the predisposition for a low pathogenic avian influenza (LPAI) virus to convert to HPAI virus is unclear. LPAI H9N2 virus strains are widespread, and they are mainly associated with poultry disease, and H9N2 virus infection in humans leads to relatively mild symptoms [
 <xref rid="B11-cells-09-00448" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The H9N2 virus can infect pigs, and these are believed to be the intermediate species in many avian-to-human transmission events. Interestingly an H7N9 virus strain was described in 2013 that was responsible for significant disease severity in humans [
 <xref rid="B12-cells-09-00448" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-cells-09-00448" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], and this virus contained six internal genes that originated from circulating H9N2 viruses [
 <xref rid="B14-cells-09-00448" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-cells-09-00448" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-cells-09-00448" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The H7N9 virus first emerged in China’s Yangtze River Delta in March 2013 [
 <xref rid="B17-cells-09-00448" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], and since the initial detection, there have been five waves of infection that have been associated with increased mortality rates [
 <xref rid="B18-cells-09-00448" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-cells-09-00448" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In human infections, the H7N9 virus showed a bias towards male infection with age older than 50 years old, suggesting that human host factors play a role in biological susceptibility to the virus infections. The last wave of H7N9 virus infection was also associated with the emergence of an HPAI virus variant which was implicated as the causative virus for several human-to-human clusters. The H7N9 seemed to show unusually greater transmissibility, and higher mortality rates with a more severe disease outcome in humans than any other H7 viruses reported to date.
</p>
