<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par70">Life-threatening opportunistic infections or biothreat agents can wreak havoc in individuals with inflammatory conditions if they are treated with available conventional therapies, and this has raised concerns in the management of national security (Tanwar et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2016</xref>). Highest priority opportunistic pathogens like 
 <italic>Salmonella species</italic>, 
 <italic>Brucella abortus</italic>, etc. pose a risk to national security as they can be easily disseminated or transmitted from person to person, which can further result in high mortality rates amongst the vulnerable populations. These pathogens in turn also play an important role in the initiation and perpetuation of such inflammatory conditions (e.g. rheumatoid arthritis and neurological disorders) in susceptible community. However, the use of biologic therapies (corticosteroids, NSAIDS, DMARDS) is also associated with increased risk of infections with intracellular microorganisms like 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> spp., 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, etc. (Thakur et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2016a</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">b</xref> and Tanwar et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2017a</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">b</xref>). Further, the combination therapy of corticosteroids and conventional drugs like anti-inflammatory drugs (naproxen, aspirin, diclofenac) etc. was shown to have antagonistic effects. Nowadays, the management of inflammatory conditions requires aggressive treatment with existing conventional drugs. Due to an increase in the unwanted effects of such therapeutic modalities, alternative therapies, particularly herbal, need to be explored as a curative remedy for the management of such vulnerable condition in terms of ‘worst-case scenario’ (Thakur et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2016a</xref>). With this aim in mind, endeavours were made to identify and develop natural remedies that could be employed in worst-case scenarios (mainly in susceptible population) to modulate the deleterious effects of natural disease outbreaks or deliberate use of biothreat agents. A herbal informatics evidence-based matrix modelling approach was envisaged, and this unique approach utilized the in silico bioprospection for identification of potent herbal leads. The model was developed using PubMed-based dynamic search engines as interactive platform. The priority index algorithms were used as a basis for evaluation of relevance factor of various physiological targets or bioactivity parameters specific to a particular microorganism(s) or inflammatory condition(s) in conferring antibiotic resistance over a period of time (Chakotiya et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR07">2016</xref>; Tanwar et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2017a</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">b</xref>). Similarly, the potential herbals identified the basis of classical bioprospection were subjected to binary, weightage and fuzzy set-based analysis using assigned relevance to each activity parameter as dependent variable. The final optimized matrix provided several potential herbal leads. These identified leads were further carried forward for evaluation of their antimicrobial activity as well as anti-inflammatory potential against a novel standardized ‘vulnerable animal model’ (collagen type II-induced rheumatoid arthritis in combination with opportunistic infections involving multidrug resistant pathogens as worst-case scenario) (Tanwar et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2017a</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">b</xref>). The identified herbal leads (e.g. 
 <italic>Camellia sinensis</italic>, 
 <italic>Berberis aristata</italic>, 
 <italic>etc.</italic>) could be utilized as novel holistic drugs in the future for the management of biothreats posed, particularly in vulnerable populations.
</p>
