<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>With regards to EBOV, DIPs were first described by Calain et al. (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>). In their study, Calain et al. used a serial passage at high multiplicity of infection (MOI) to enhance the probability of defective genome formation. They mapped several of these and found that, when they were co-infected with the low passage virus, cytopathology was tempered. It is difficult to say what role DIPs might play in actual human infection; however, Calain et al. later suggested that it was possible that defective genomes played a role in latent infections possibly observed in cases of EVD where there is recrudescence several months after patients are convalescent and EBOV negative in their bloods (Calain et al., 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). It is unclear why, since DIPs are readily generated in the laboratory, and they temper viral pathology, we are unable to find reports of epidemics and disease in individuals spontaneously resolving because of DIPs. One reason might be that EBOV is known to have the ability to prevent further infection of the cell that it infects (i.e., to prevent super-infection/co-infection). This phenomenon of infection blockade is driven by the Δ-peptide (Radoshitzky et al., 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). In the studies by Calain et al. (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>), DIPs were used at high MOI and simultaneously to the wild-type virus infection. Therefore, coinfection in these studies was significantly more probable. Conversely in epidemics, and in the host, EBOV is a budding virus (Martin et al., 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) and this means exposure of neighboring cells will occur across a greater time period than for a bursting virus. This prevention of super-infection/co-infection is therefore likely to provide a natural defense against parasitisation by DIPs. The existence of a system of infection blockade does not however preclude the possibility that DIPs might be useful as therapies provided one of the following considerations are taken on board: (1) deliver defective genomes prior to EBOV and in a manner that does not preclude super infection (i.e., absence of Δ-peptide), (2) use a route of cellular entry that is independent of EBOV uptake, or (3) be available systemically at high titer.
</p>
