<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This evolution of 
 <italic>TFR1</italic> can be put into contrast with other types of pathogen-driven positive selection of host genes. The human 
 <italic>CCR5</italic> gene encodes a co-receptor for HIV cellular entry. Some humans encode a variant allele of 
 <italic>CCR5</italic>, 
 <italic>CCR5Δ32</italic>, where a 32 base pair deletion gives rise to a defective receptor that is not expressed on the cell surface 
 <xref rid="pbio.1001571-OBrien1" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>. Individuals homozygous for this allele are almost completely resistant to HIV infection, and even heterozygous genotypes afford some protection due to reduced expression of wild-type CCR5. Like the model proposed herein for 
 <italic>TFR1</italic> L212V, 
 <italic>CCR5Δ32</italic> pre-dates HIV and may or may not have had any functional significance before the HIV pandemic. Nonetheless, it has become highly relevant in a world with HIV/AIDS. Like HIV, most simian immunodeficiency virus (SIV) strains also use CCR5 as a co-receptor. In a fascinating case of convergent evolution, some sooty mangabeys and red-capped mangabeys also encode null or defective alleles of 
 <italic>CCR5</italic>
 <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Riddick1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Similarly, the 
 <italic>DARC</italic> gene encodes a chemokine receptor that is used as an entry receptor by some malaria-causing 
 <italic>Plasmodium</italic> species. A cis-regulatory polymorphism that silences 
 <italic>DARC</italic> expression in erythrocytes has arisen independently in human populations from different parts of the world and is highly protective against 
 <italic>Plasmodium vivax</italic> and 
 <italic>Plasmodium knowlesi</italic> infection 
 <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Zimmerman1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Tournamille1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. Similar mutations have arisen in the cis-regulatory region of 
 <italic>DARC</italic> in African baboons, and these are associated with resistance to a malaria-like parasite common in baboon populations 
 <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Tung1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. In all of these cases, it has been speculated that selective pressure exerted by pathogens has driven these hypomorphic receptor alleles to high frequency in the affected human and nonhuman primate populations.
</p>
