<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>These 
 <italic>CCR5</italic> and 
 <italic>DARC</italic> examples represent a more common mode of pathogen-driven positive selection (not recurrent) than the one demonstrated for 
 <italic>TFR1</italic>, and there are several important differences. When receptor genes experience hypomorphic mutations, the predominant evolutionary strategy available to viruses will be to use a new receptor altogether. Indeed, the SIV strains that infect sooty and red-capped mangabeys (SIVsmm and SIVrcm) have both evolved to use alternate co-receptors 
 <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Riddick1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. A few 
 <italic>CCR5Δ32</italic> homozygous humans have also been reported to be infected with HIV, again through mutations that allow the virus to use an alternate co-receptor (CXCR4 in this case). Hypomorphic mutations in receptors are not expected to be “serially replaced” due to arms race dynamics. Rather, viral evolution to use a new receptor ends the arms race with the original receptor gene and starts a new one with the new receptor gene. The 
 <italic>CCR5</italic> and 
 <italic>DARC</italic> examples also involve evolutionary time scales millions of years shorter than what has been demonstrated in the current study; because these hypomorphic alleles are circulating in populations of individuals and are not shared between species, they have arisen relatively recently. Also, because these mutations simply reduce cellular expression of the encoded receptors, they presumably have some negative fitness effect on the host. The TfR1 example that we provide here is unique because solutions to viral entry have been found that appear to lack collateral damage to transferrin binding, and presumably to other host functions as well. Because of this, these mutations become common or fixed in populations where they occur, and are serially replaced as viruses continue to evolve and as rodents continue to speciate.
</p>
