<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0065">Beyond the effects of CCR5/CCR5Δ32 on HIV infection, CCR5Δ32 impacts non-viral infectious diseases (
 <xref rid="bib1520" ref-type="bibr">Ungvári et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib1275" ref-type="bibr">Salnikova et al., 2013</xref>) and inflammation-related conditions (
 <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">Chies and Nardi, 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">Balistreri et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib1060" ref-type="bibr">Muntinghe et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0700" ref-type="bibr">Kaminski et al., 2019a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0810" ref-type="bibr">Kulmann-Leal et al., 2020</xref>). Therefore, both the CCR5 molecule 
 <italic>per se</italic> as well as the CCR5Δ32 variant, through the interference on the interaction of CCR5 with its ligands, may impact CCR5-mediated antiviral cellular activity and inflammatory reactions during host response against pathogens. Indeed, the CCL5−CCR5 axis influences virus-associated immune responses (
 <xref rid="bib1515" ref-type="bibr">Tyner et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0560" ref-type="bibr">Grayson et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0230" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2017</xref>). Although the effects of CCR5Δ32 on CCR5 expression are clear, CCR5 and CCR5Δ32 have varied and even contrasting roles in different diseases. Due to interactions with other genetic variants as well as with environmental factors, the role of CCR5Δ32 may differ even within the same disease, depending on the ethnic group or population assessed (
 <xref rid="bib1200" ref-type="bibr">Rautenbach and Williams, 2020</xref>). Studying the involvement of CCR5 and the effects of CCR5Δ32 on infectious diseases may contribute to the understanding of the genetic factors involved in the susceptibility and progression of multiple viral diseases. Also, these studies can shed light on the use of CCR5 modulators/blockers in a broader perspective, beyond HIV infection. In this context, the aim of this review is to discuss the involvement of CCR5 and the effects of the CCR5Δ32 in human viral infections, covering West Nile virus, Influenza viruses, Human papillomavirus, Hepatitis B virus, Hepatitis C virus, Poliovirus, Dengue virus, Human cytomegalovirus, Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever virus, Enterovirus, Japanese encephalitis virus, and Hantavirus. This review also addresses the impacts of 
 <italic>CCR5</italic> gene editing and the CCR5 modulation on health and viral diseases. Recently, the role of extracellular vesicles has brought complexity to the fields of both immunology and virology. Therefore, this article connects recent findings regarding extracellular vesicles, viruses, and CCR5. In the last part of the review, neglected and emerging topics in “CCR5 research” are briefly discussed, with a focus on Rocio virus, Zika virus, Epstein-Barr virus, and Rhinovirus.
</p>
