<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several studies have described the in vitro anti-HIV activities and cytotoxicity of GRFT (
 <xref rid="marinedrugs-17-00567-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B5-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Mori et al. reported potent, sub-nanomolar antiviral efficacy of both native and recombinant GRFT against laboratory strains and primary isolates of T- and M- tropic HIV-1 [
 <xref rid="B5-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In their publication, they observed that GRFT inhibited soluble gp120 from binding to CD4 receptor-expressing cells [
 <xref rid="B5-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Cell-to-cell fusion and transmission of HIV-1 infection were also blocked by GRFT at similar concentrations [
 <xref rid="B5-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In addition, the coadministration of monosaccharides such as glucose, mannose, and 
 <italic>N</italic>-acetyl glucosamine hindered glycosylation-dependent binding of GRFT to soluble gp120 [
 <xref rid="B5-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In parallel with this observation, Emau et al. also demonstrated that GRFT could block the infectivity of CXCR4- and CCR5-tropic HIV viruses at picomolar concentrations. They also confirmed the long-term stability of GRFT in a cervical/vaginal lavage [
 <xref rid="B27-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. In order to harness the HIV-inactivating power of GRFT, a new peptide called grifonin-1 was designed based on the three carbohydrate-binding amino acid sequences of GRFT. Its sub-micromolar anti-HIV activity was confirmed using an in vitro TZM-bl cell line and p24 gag antigen release assays [
 <xref rid="B24-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In addition to its ability to suppress HIV-1 transmission in CD4+ T-lymphocytes, GRFT also subverted DC-SIGN (dendritic cell-specific intercellular adhesion molecule-3-grabbing nonintegrin)-mediated HIV capture [
 <xref rid="B30-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Mechanistically, a binding competition between GRFT and gp120 for DC-SIGN was proposed as a potential mode of action for GRFT-mediated inhibition of HIV-1 capture by DC-SIGN [
 <xref rid="B21-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Corresponding to this DC-SIGN-dependent antiviral activity, GRFT also potently inhibited giant cell formation between persistently HIV-infected T cells and noninfected CD4+ target T cells. This led to the suppression of HIV transmission, CD4+ T-cell destruction, and ultimately viral replication through the DC-SIGN mediated pathway [
 <xref rid="B33-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. This efficient blockage of the binding of DC-SIGN to immobilized gp120 by GRFT was further confirmed [
 <xref rid="B21-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. This observation was in harmony with the GRFT-mediated expulsion of gp120 from the gp120/DC-SIGN complex [
 <xref rid="B21-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Interestingly, this highly potent inhibition of DC-SIGN-mediated capture and transmission by GRFT was markedly impaired when GRFT was mutated in one of its three carbohydrate-binding sites (D30A, D70A, or D112A) [
 <xref rid="B21-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], further implicating its carbohydrate-binding sites as critical determinants for anti-HIV-1 activity. Regarding its cytotoxicity, two studies demonstrated that the CC
 <sub>50</sub> concentration for GRFT was several hundred nanomolar [
 <xref rid="B5-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], thousands of times higher than its reported antiviral concentrations.
</p>
