<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>No vaccines or specific antiviral treatments are available for viruses transmitted by small mammals and arthropods, with a few exceptions [e.g., 
 <italic>Yellow fever virus</italic> (YFV), Japanese encephalitis virus (JEV), 
 <italic>Tick-borne encephalitis virus</italic> (TBE) and Junin virus (JUNV)], [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005017.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005017.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Therefore, early diagnosis of infection with one of these viruses is of great importance for proper patient management and the rapid implementation of epidemic containment strategies. However, currently available methods for the diagnosis of virus infections are time consuming and expensive, especially when several assays are necessary to identify a virus because only one or a few viruses can be screened per assay using conventional methods. Traditionally, virus isolation has been considered the gold standard for virus diagnosis, but the detection of viral genomic nucleic acids by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) has emerged as an alternative to virus isolation due to its simplicity, rapidity and sensibility. However, PCR does not allow for the simultaneous screening of several virus. High-throughput nucleic acid sequencing methods provide the most in-depth and unbiased information for virus surveillance, but they are very expensive and too time consuming to be used for the routine diagnosis of virus infection. An alternative method for virus surveillance is DNA microarray technology, which enables simultaneous screening of a significantly higher number of viruses than PCR methods and is more economical and faster than high-throughput nucleic acid sequencing methods. Several DNA microarray platforms have been described in the literature for virus detection [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005017.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005017.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Therefore, DNA microarray technology could be an alternative for the rapid identification of viruses, especially when conventional virological methods fail to identify a virus.
</p>
