<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<author-notes>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001">
  <p>
   <bold>Competing Interests: </bold>Competing Interests: C. Schmidbauer (
   <email>schmidbauer.c@gmail.com</email>): received travel support from Gilead, Abbvie and Gebro. R. Schubert (
   <email>raphael.schubert@suchthilfe.at</email>): is employed by Suchthilfe Wien gGmbH and received travel support from Gilead. A. Schütz (
   <email>angelika.schuetz@suchthilfe.at</email>): is employed by Suchthilfe Wien gGmbH and has no conflicts of interest. C. Schwanke (
   <email>cornelia.schwanke@suchthilfe.at</email>): is employed by Suchthilfe Wien gGmbH and has no conflicts of interest. J. Luhn (
   <email>julian.luhn@suchthilfe.at</email>): is employed by Suchthilfe Wien gGmbH and has no conflicts of interest. E. Gutic (
   <email>enisa.gutic@extern.wienkav.at</email>): received travel support from Gilead and Abbvie. R. Pirker (
   <email>roxana.pirker@aon.at</email>): no conflicts of interest. T. Lang (
   <email>tobiaslang1904@gmail.com</email>): no conflicts of interest. T. Reiberger (
   <email>thomas.reiberger@meduniwien.ac.at</email>): received grant support from Abbvie, Boehringer-Ingelheim, Gilead, MSD, Philips Healthcare, Gore; speaking honoraria from Abbvie, Gilead, Gore, Intercept, Roche, MSD; consulting/advisory board fees from Abbvie, Bayer, Boehringer-Ingelheim, Gilead, Intercept, MSD, Siemens; and travel support from Boehringer-Ingelheim, Gilead and Roche. H. Haltmayer (
   <email>hans.haltmayer@suchthilfe.at</email>): is employed by Suchthilfe Wien gGmbH and has no conflicts of interest. M. Gschwantler (
   <email>michael.gschwantler@wienkav.at</email>): received grants from Abbvie, Gilead, MSD; speaking honoraria from Abbvie, Gilead, MSD, Janssen, Roche, Intercept; consulting/advisory board fees from Abbvie, Gilead, MSD, Janssen, Roche, Intercept. Suchthilfe Wien gGmbH represents a governmental non-profit organization financed by the City of Vienna and the Austrian Ministry of Health. Suchthilfe Wien gGmbH did not play a role in the study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript and only provided financial support in the form of authors’ salaries. This does not alter our adherence to PLOS ONE policies on sharing data and materials. Suchthilfe Wien gGmbH provided support in the form of salaries for authors [Raphael Schubert, Angelika Schütz, Cornelia Schwanke, Julian Luhn, Hans Haltmayer], but did not have any additional role in the study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. The specific roles of these authors are articulated in the ‘author contributions’ section.“
  </p>
 </fn>
 <corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: 
  <email>michael.gschwantler@wienkav.at</email>
 </corresp>
</author-notes>
