<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We have surveyed 19159 influenza A virus PB2 sequences available in the Influenza Research Database. Amino acids 601 to 607 were found to be almost absolutely conserved (identical in more than 19100 sequences analysed), regardless of the host species. This indicates that this region of PB2 is involved in an essential polymerase function which is crucial to the virus. Based on our data we propose that amino acids 605 and 606 of PB2 contribute to polymerase function through mediating interaction with NP. From our previous study, basic amino acid at position 627 or 630 is necessary for the interaction [
 <xref rid="pone.0191226.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The low CSP signal of E627 agreed with the previous study, interestingly, we found that PB2 R630 was barely perturbed in NMR chemical shift perturbation experiments by either the full-length NP or the NP 146–185 fragment. Since amino acid R630 is located at a flexible loop in PB2, which may undergo conformational movements in the intermediate exchange regime causing extensive broadening of the NMR signals, we may not observe the HN-N cross peaks of these amino acids in HSQC spectra. As a result, we have not observed the CSP reading of R630 when using full-length NP as ligand. On the other hand, there is a small CSP reading when using an NP 146–185 fragment as ligand, reflecting the change of binding affinity has shifted the interaction to fast exchange regime. The small reading suggested R630 is not involved in binding the proposed region of NP (aa 146–185). These findings are in agreement with the proposal that adaptive mutations at these amino acids affect polymerase-NP interactions indirectly by primarily affecting polymerase activity [
 <xref rid="pone.0191226.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The possibility of the involvement of R630 of PB2 in NP-PB2 interaction cannot be excluded but it is possible that aa 601–607 nearby, which showed a much higher CSP signal, may interact with NP and that interaction was proved by SPR (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0191226.g004">Fig 4</xref>).
</p>
