<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Some studies have discovered rare antibodies specific to the conserved HA stalk in animals and humans with prior exposure to influenza viruses. Some of these antibodies show extremely broad specificity, encompassing both HA groups of IAVs (Ekiert et al., 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) or even both IAVs and IBVs (Dreyfus et al., 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), representing an optimistic prospect of developing a UIV. However, no studies so far have reported a successful vaccine approach that induces such antibodies to a protective level, reflecting considerable difficulty in selectively inducting particular antibodies in the context of vaccination. While antibody-dependent effector mechanisms and T cell immunity have emerged as potential correlates of broad protection against influenza infections (Krammer and Palese, 
 <xref rid="B136" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>), the exact molecular mechanisms of their protective action are not completely understood, and immunopathology by T cell responses still remains a challenge (Peiris et al., 
 <xref rid="B187" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Duan and Thomas, 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Erbelding et al., 
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Moreover, understanding how preexisting immunity (immune imprinting or antigenic sin-like phenomenon) shaped by prior exposure to influenza viruses affects the magnitude, hierarchy, and sustainability of antibody response to vaccination is suggested as critical for designing a UIV in humans (Henry et al., 
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). The involvement of multiple factors in eliciting broad protection and the influence of pre-existing immunity on the subsequent vaccination pose a dilemma on establishing the correlate of cross-protection against heterologous or hetero-subtypic viruses, representing a critical obstacle for the licensure of a UIV by the regulatory authorities.
</p>
