<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An alternative efficient additional strategy to tackle COVID-19 is 
 <italic>in silico</italic> drug repurposing approaches. The main protease M
 <sup>pro</sup>, also called 3CLpro, represents an attractive drug target due to its essential role in the viral life cycle, crucial for viral replication. The pp1a and pp1ab, two overlapping polyproteins, important for viral replication and transcription, are encoded by the SARS-CoV-2 replicase gene [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-03830" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-03830" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The M
 <sup>pro</sup> cleaves large polyprotein 1ab in at least 11 sites. The M
 <sup>pro</sup> is highly conserved across the Coronaviridae family and any mutation here can be disastrous for the virus [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-25-03830" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-03830" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. As one of the best-characterized drug targets among coronaviruses, in the absence of closely related human homologues, the M
 <sup>pro</sup> represents one of the most attractive SARS-CoV-2 drug targets. Since there is no human protease with similar cleavage specificity, the inhibitors are expected to be nontoxic [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-03830" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. SARS-CoV-2 M
 <sup>pro</sup> is active in a dimer form, consisting of two monomers arranged nearly perpendicular to one another [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-03830" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The dimerization is necessary for the M
 <sup>pro</sup> enzymatic activity as the N-finger of each of the two monomers interacts with Glu166 of the other monomer support the correct orientation of the S1 pocket of the substrate binding site. M
 <sup>pro</sup> active site comprises a catalytic dyad that consists of the conserved residues H41 and C145 [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-25-03830" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The available high-resolution experimental structure of the main protease of SARS-CoV-2 was used in the current study as the target for molecular docking-based virtual screening (VS) [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-03830" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].
</p>
