<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Among the many contemporary technologies available, special attention should be paid to rapid lateral flow immunoassay (LFIA), also referred to as immunochromatographic tests. Perhaps they are not so much appreciated in the scientific community as PCR methods or Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA tests), despite the fact that they do find application in diagnostics more and more often. They differ, depending on the type of test, but the basic principle of their action is invariably the same—they make use of the unique property that antibodies possess, that of selective binding to a specific particle or group of similar particles (antigen). LFIAs provide an uncomplicated and relatively inexpensive tool meant for detecting the presence (or absence) of a given component in the examined specimen, such as the presence of a virus in an analyzed blood sample. Examination with the use of those tests is possible for various types of test material—whole human blood, blood plasma, serum, stool, urine, sweat, cerebrospinal fluid, or even tears [
 <xref rid="B9-diagnostics-10-00434" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The test principle is based on an immunological method, using specific antibodies, most often in complex with colloidal gold, where a drop of the examined substance first moves along the nitrocellulose membrane using capillary phenomena. After the sample is absorbed by the membrane, the antigen (should the test prove to be positive) binds to the colloidal gold complex and respective antibodies. Consequently, the effect of that reaction is the formation of a complex, which will be detected by the test. The interpretation of results consists of confirmation or ruling out of the presence of antigens in the examined sample, based on color test strips that appear in the test [
 <xref rid="B21-diagnostics-10-00434" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-diagnostics-10-00434" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The brief comparison of advantages and disadvantages of immunochromatographic tests is presented in 
 <xref rid="diagnostics-10-00434-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>.
</p>
