<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The practice of seasonal influenza surveillance is affected by a lack of a common case definition for influenza-like illness across countries. Moreover, the seasonal influenza epidemics in the various European countries present a high degree of heterogeneity. To improve seasonal influenza surveillance beyond these issues, we propose an unsupervised probabilistic framework based on self-reported symptoms collected daily through a network of participatory web-based influenza surveillance platforms in Europe called Influenzanet. Our approach, which relies on a Non-negative Matrix Factorization of the daily symptoms matrix, is capable of producing an epidemiological signal that does not rely on a specific a priori case definition and that follows the temporal trend of influenza-like illness closely as detected by the traditional sentinel doctors surveillance in each country. The emerging signal successfully captures the ILI incidence trend estimated by the national surveillance data for all the nine countries included in this study. We also demonstrate that the proposed approach can be employed to forecast the forthcoming ILI incidence. Additionally, the proposed approach has the potential to be used to identify other illnesses, as shown here for gastrointestinal syndromes, although additional traditional surveillance data is needed to validate the generalisability of our framework. We can thus conclude that there is great potential in using symptoms directly collected from the general population to inform unsupervised algorithmic approaches aimed at detecting circulating bouts of illnesses without imposing an a priori case definition. The standardized technological and epidemiological framework and the ability to monitor symptoms from the general population, including individuals who do not seek medical assistance, provided by the Influenzanet participatory surveillance platforms, are what enables the application of unsupervised algorithmic approaches such as the one presented in this work. In the next future, we will include data from virologically confirmed influenza cases as ground truth to enhance the specificity of our framework. Regarding the forecasting capabilities of the framework, approaches from existing research on participatory flu surveillance suggest that the integration of real-time official data sources with the crowdsourced digital ones [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006173.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>] [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006173.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>] provide better forecasting performance. In our case, the weekly integration of sufficient traditional surveillance data in the framework could lead to a near-real-time selection of the component that better represents the symptoms in the ILI syndrome circulating among the general population. Finally, the flexibility provided by the participatory surveillance platforms in terms of symptoms that can be collected from the general population enables the possibility to extend the framework to other diseases, provided that traditional surveillance data are available to train the framework.
</p>
