<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <p>We would like to thank the residents of Iquitos for their support and participation in this study and willingness to allow this study to be conducted in their community. We greatly appreciate support of the Loreto Regional Health Department including Drs. Hugo Rodriguez-Ferruci, Christian Carey, Carlos Alvarez, and the Lic. Wilma Casanova Rojas who all facilitated our work in Iquitos. A special thanks to Gloria Talledo for her ongoing support with the preparation of IRB protocols and reports for this project. We appreciate the careful commentary and advice provided by the NAMRU-6 Institutional Review Board and Research Administration Program for the duration of this study. We thank Elvira Zamora and Lucrecia Vizcaino for assistance with insecticide susceptibility bioassays and cone bioassays. Entomological surveys were carried out by Jimmy Maykol Castillo Pizango, Fernando Chota Ruiz, Guillermo Elespuru Hidalgo, Victor Elespuru Hidalgo, Fernando Espinoza Benavides, Rusbel Huinapi Tamani, Guillermo Inapi Huaman, Nestor Jose Nonato Lancha, Federico Reategui Viena, Edson Pilco Mermao, Angel Puertas Lozano, Juan Luiz Sifuentes Rios, Manuel Ruiz Rioja, and Abner Enrique Varzallo Lachi. Jimmy Roberto Espinoza Benavides, Gabriela Vasquez de la Torre and Diana Maritza Bazan Ferrando carried out data entry. Serological surveys were carried out by Junnelhy Mireya Flores Lopez, Juan Flores Michi, Nora Marin Moreno, Geraldine Ocmin Galan, Zenith Maria Pezo Villacorta, Zoila Martha Reategui Chota, Rubiela Nerza Rubio Briceno, Rosana Zenith Tamani Guerrero, Margarita Hoyos Guerra, Olenka, Virginia Fieitas Saavedra, Lauri Dacia Cuespan Camus, Marllory Rubi Ramierez Monsalve, Ysabel Ruiz Berger, and Flora Vargas Ceras. We thank Angelica Espinoza, Roxana Caceda, and Roger Castillo for carrying out the serological testing, Carolina Guevara for supervision of the NMRCD virology laboratory and Juan Perez for data management. Drs. Robert Hontz, Christopher Mores, John Sanders, David Service, Kyle Peterson, Adam Armstrong, Guillermo Pimentel, Zoe Moran, Toane Zuleta and Ms. Roxana Lescano of the U.S. Naval Medical Research Unit No. 6 in Lima, Peru were instrumental in facilitating these studies.</p>
 <sec id="sec012">
  <title>Disclaimer</title>
  <p>The views expressed in this article are those of the author and do not necessarily reflect the official policy or position of the Department of the Navy, Department of Defense, nor the U.S. Government.</p>
 </sec>
</ack>
