<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since the JE vaccine was first introduced in Korea in 1967, the incidence rate has decreased from 12,055 cases (mean annual incidence rate of 6.04/100,000 persons) in 1961–1967 to 3783 cases (mean incidence of 0.67/100,000) in 1968–1983 [
 <xref rid="B6-vaccines-08-00328" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Following the last epidemic in 1982–1983, mandatory vaccination was implemented for all children aged 3–15 years annually until 1994 [
 <xref rid="B7-vaccines-08-00328" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Thereafter, the vaccination schedule has changed two times in 1995 and 2000, and now a revised schedule of a two-dose primary series and three boosters is recommended [
 <xref rid="B5-vaccines-08-00328" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-vaccines-08-00328" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. As a result, JE was nearly eliminated, and only 55 cases (mean incidence of 0.004/100,000) were reported in 1984–2009 [
 <xref rid="B6-vaccines-08-00328" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, JE has reemerged since 2010 (26 cases), and the annual incidences of JE have increased to be highest in 2015 (40 cases) [
 <xref rid="B8-vaccines-08-00328" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. During 2010–2015, 129 JE cases were reported in Korea; the median age of the patients was 53 years, and patients &lt;19 years of age accounted for only 3.1% of cases. These findings indicated that reemerging JE predominantly affected unvaccinated adults &gt;40 years of age, and shifts in age distribution toward older groups might be due to the universal vaccination program. Similar findings were observed in nearby countries. In Japan, following the largest epidemic of approximately 2000 cases in 1965, the annual number of cases has dramatically decreased, and only less than 10 cases have been reported annually since 1992 [
 <xref rid="B9-vaccines-08-00328" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. During the period 1982–2004, 361 JE cases were reported, and most of the patients were 40 years old or older, with a peak in the 60–69 year age group. JE predominantly occurred in unvaccinated populations. In Taiwan, pediatric JE cases have markedly decreased since the vaccination, and a shift in JE cases from young children to adults has also occurred [
 <xref rid="B10-vaccines-08-00328" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-vaccines-08-00328" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].
</p>
