<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To date, at least 23 genotypes of 
 <italic>Pestivirus A</italic> (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>–
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) and six genotypes (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) of 
 <italic>Pestivirus B</italic> have been classified based on sequence comparison analyses and the palindromic nucleotide substitutions (PNS) genotyping method (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). 
 <italic>Pestivirus H</italic>, first isolated from fetal calf serum (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), has spread to different continents, including North America, South America, Europe, and Asia (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>–
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). In China, nine genotypes of 
 <italic>Pestivirus A</italic> (1a,1b, 1c,1d, 1m, 1o, 1p,1q, and 1u) (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>–
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>), two genotypes (2a, 2b) of 
 <italic>Pestivirus B</italic> (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>–
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), and 
 <italic>Pestivirus H</italic> (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>) have been reported. Cattle production by backyard farming is a widespread cattle-keeping pattern in developing countries. In central China, which includes Henan Province, more than 3,720,000 cattle have been raised (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>), and previous data showed that over 20% of cattle were kept in small farms (cattle number &lt;10), including a large number of backyard farms in China (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>), especially in the southern region of Henan Province, where free-range cattle farms are key economic sectors (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). However, the limited biosecurity measures in these farms usually lead to the introduction and spread of exotic or endemic disease (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>–
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). Furthermore, in backyard cattle farms in China, most of the animals graze in the wilderness, and thus come into contact with infected cattle. To our knowledge, information on the epidemiology of pestiviruses in cattle in backyard farms in China is limited. The aim of this study was to investigate the distribution of pestiviruses that are associated with respiratory disease from backyard farms in Henan Province, China.
</p>
