<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Characterization of the DENV E gene informs transmission dynamics, as genotypic variation within serotypes can be a major determinant of epidemics [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007785.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Shift in genotype predominance has been associated with alterations in immunity against infecting virus and mosquito transmission patterns [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007785.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. During our three-year study (2013–2016), we identified the circulation of both the predominant DENV-1 genotype I and DENV-1 genotype IV. This is consistent with earlier studies showing predominant circulation of DENV-1 genotype I in the recent years, shifting from predominance of DENV-1 genotype IV in the earlier years [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007785.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007785.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007785.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. This genotype transition pattern might be associated with the faster replication rate of genotype I compared to genotype IV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007785.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. There was no change for the circulating DENV-2 and DENV-3 genotypes. DENV-2 genotype Cosmopolitan, the only circulating genotype for DENV-2 in Indonesia [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007785.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007785.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007785.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], was observed in our cohort. The Cosmopolitan genotype has a wide geographical distribution, spanning from Asia to Africa [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007785.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. DENV-3 genotype I, which is endemic in Indonesia, Malaysia, the Philippines and the South Pacific Islands [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007785.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], and has been shown to circulate dating back to the 1970s, was the only DENV-3 genotype found in this study. Besides DENV-4 genotype IIa that circulated at all sites, a specimen collected from Bali in 2015 was grouped into DENV-4 genotype I, suggesting the first observation of DENV-4 genotype I in Indonesia. DENV-4 genotype I was identified in the Philippines, Thailand, Malaysia, and Srilanka during 1960s-1980s. The observation of DENV-4 genotype I in Bali marks the introduction or possible reemergence of an old strain. This observation merits deeper investigation of the circulation of DENV-4 as genotype shift is closely related to evolving epidemic characteristics.
</p>
