<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">The VP1 coding region contains many important neutralization epitopes and was demonstrated to help identify different serotypes of EVs
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>. A phylogenetic dendrogram based on the entire VP1 sequences of EV has been used for discrimination of genotypes. This study conducted the entire VP1 sequence-based phylogenetic analyses of 3 predominant serotypes of EV-A71, CV-A16 and CV-A6 isolated from Shaanxi province during 2010–2016. The results showed that the nucleotide and amino acid homologies of Shaanxi EV-A71 strains were 94.2–99.7% and 98.0–100%, respectively, which were highly homologous to the representative strain of C4 sub-genotype in China. According to the nucleotide sequence difference of VP1, EV-A71 can be divided into 7 genotypes (A-G), in which B genotype includes 8 sub-genotypes (B0 to B7), and C genotype includes 6 sub-genotypes (C1 to C6). Since the first strain of EV-A71 virus (genotypes A) was isolated in the United States in 1969
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>
 </sup>, there has been an epidemic of HFMD caused by EV-A71 infection in the world. B1, B2 and C1, C2 sub-genotypes spread in European and American countries and Australia, Japan from 1970s to 1990s
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. After 1997, B3~B5 and C3~C6 sub-genotypes began to appear and spread in Southeast Asia
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>. EV-A71 virus isolated in India in 2001 was classified as genotypes D and G, while genotypes E and F were the main epidemic in Africa
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup>. In the process of continuous evolution of EV-A71 virus, each genotype has different time and regional distribution characteristics. At present, the main epidemic sub-genotypes of EV-A71 in Asia were C2, C4, C5 and B5. B5 and C2 are prevalent in Malaysia and Singapore
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>, C2, C4 and B5 are mainly popular in Japan
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>, and C5 is prevalent in Vietnam
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>. C4 sub-genotype was first isolated in mainland of China in 1998, and this sub-genotype has been prevalent until now. C4 sub-genotype can be divided into two branches: C4a and C4b. The main epidemic strains from 2008 to 2004 belonged to C4b branch, and the C4a branch has the dominant genotype since 2004
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. All of Shaanxi EV-A71 strains formed a gene cluster in the phylogenetic tree, which were located on the C4a branch of C4. Shaanxi EV-A71 strains have the same evolutionary origin as that strains epidemic in mainland of China in recent years. EV-A71 virus has been widely spread in Shaanxi Province.
</p>
