<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Briefly, these drugs can be divided in three groups: the M2 ion channel blockers, the neuraminidase inhibitors (NAIs), and the virus polymerase inhibitors. Amantadine and rimantadine are adamantane derivatives that inhibit viral replication by blocking the proton conductivity of the M2 ion channel preventing delivery of the virus ribonucleoprotein in the cytoplasm (
 <xref rid="ref126" ref-type="bibr">Schnell and Chou, 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">Ison, 2017</xref>). These compounds are specific for influenza A viruses since the M2 protein of influenza B viruses is structurally different (
 <xref rid="ref153" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref116" ref-type="bibr">Pielak and Chou, 2011</xref>). In recent past seasons, surveillance studies reported high levels of resistance (&gt;99%) to adamantanes among circulating influenza A(H3N2) and influenza A(H1N1)pdm09 viruses, and the centers for disease control and prevention (CDC) does not recommend these compounds for antiviral treatment or chemoprophylaxis of currently circulating influenza A viruses (
 <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 2018a</xref>). Development of NAI started in the early 1970s with derivatives of 2-deoxy-2,3-dehydro-N-acetylneuraminic acid (
 <xref rid="ref111" ref-type="bibr">Palese et al., 1970</xref>), although it was not until 1999 that the first NAI was approved for use in humans (
 <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Chaudhuri et al., 2018</xref>). The NAI binds to the neuraminidase of the virus and prevents its cleavage, thus inhibiting the release of new virus particles (
 <xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">Ison, 2017</xref>). NAIs currently approved by the FDA include: oseltamivir, zanamivir, and peramivir. Oseltamivir acid is a pro-drug indicated for oral administration. Once in the gastrointestinal tract, the pro-dug is rapidly cleaved to the active metabolite, oseltamivir carboxylate (
 <xref rid="ref81" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2017</xref>). Due to poor oral bioavailability, zanamivir is approved for inhalation delivery with intravenous administration only available by compassionate use (
 <xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">Ison, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref129" ref-type="bibr">Shaw, 2017</xref>). Peramivir also has poor oral bioavailability; therefore, it has been approved for intravenous administration only. Because the drug reaches high concentrations in plasma and respiratory tissues, it has been approved as a single-dose infusion. One of the inherit problems of these drugs is that, in order to be effective, treatment should start within 48 h post-exposure. Antiviral resistance to oseltamivir, zanamivir, and peramivir is very low in currently circulating influenza virus strains, although this can change because several clusters of oseltamivir resistance have been detected in Japan, Australia, and China (
 <xref rid="ref138" ref-type="bibr">Takashita et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Alame et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref84" ref-type="bibr">Koszalka et al., 2017</xref>). Also known as S-033188, baloxavir marboxil (Xofluza®) is a pro-drug that is hydrolyzed 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> to S-033447, the active form that selectively inhibits cap-dependent endonuclease, preventing the initiation of mRNA synthesis of the influenza virus (
 <xref rid="ref139" ref-type="bibr">Takashita et al., 2018</xref>). This is a potent small molecule that shows activity against several influenza A viruses, including oseltamivir-resistant viruses as well as B viruses (
 <xref rid="ref106" ref-type="bibr">Noshi et al., 2018</xref>). Preclinical studies demonstrated that treated mice infected with influenza virus were protected from clinical signs and mortality even in a delay of treatment approach (treatment started 4 days post-infection). Furthermore, a subtherapeutic dose of baloxavir in combination with oseltamivir also protected mice from infection and mortality (
 <xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">Fukao et al., 2018</xref>). In addition, studies in mice infected with avian influenza viruses such as H5N1 or H7N9 also demonstrated protection after oral administration with baloxavir (
 <xref rid="ref151" ref-type="bibr">Uehara et al., 2016</xref>). A clinical study (NCT02954354) aimed to compare the efficacy of baloxavir with a placebo or oseltamivir in healthy patients infected with influenza demonstrated that the drug was well tolerated and was associated with a significant reduction in viral load compared to the oseltamivir group. Time of alleviation of symptoms was similar to oseltamivir. The currently undergoing clinical program for this drug includes phase 3 clinical trials to determine safety, pharmacokinetics, and efficacy in healthy pediatric participants aged less than 1 year (NCT03653364) or in pediatric patients with influenza-like symptoms (NCT03629184) and a study to assess efficacy and safety of baloxavir in combination with standard-of-care neuraminidase inhibitor in hospitalized participants with severe influenza (NCT03684044). These studies are currently recruiting and expected to be concluded in spring 2020. In Japan, baloxavir has been approved for the treatment of adult and infant patients infected with influenza; while in the US, the drug has just been approved by the FDA for the treatment of acute, uncomplicated influenza in people aged 12 years and older (
 <xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">Food and Drug Administration, 2018</xref>). The emergence of resistant variants to polymerase inhibitors has been observed and it is conferred by an I38T mutation in the PA polymerase (
 <xref rid="ref74" ref-type="bibr">Jones et al., 2018</xref>). In the same study, a novel mutation conferring resistance (E23K) was also observed. Both mutations have been encountered during clinical trials for baloxavir (
 <xref rid="ref63" ref-type="bibr">Hayden et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
