<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>EEEV naturally circulates in an enzootic transmission cycle between its principle vector 
 <italic>Culiseta (Cs.) melanura</italic> and birds (largely passerines) located in freshwater hardwood swamps [
 <xref rid="B64-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B72-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. With respect to North America, this results in regional variations in transmission based on climate and season. In the temperate climates of the Northeastern United States, transmission is seasonal, with detection of viremic birds taking place in the spring (May and June), preceding the detection the virus in mosquitoes, which typically takes place in the mid-summer months. Enzootic circulation of EEEV will persist until the onset of sustained cold weather in November or December [
 <xref rid="B64-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B91-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. However, in the Southeastern regions of the United States, such as Florida, enzootic transmission of EEEV is maintained year-round [
 <xref rid="B64-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B92-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>,
 <xref rid="B93-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. Likewise, MADV in South and Central America is transmitted continuously throughout the year [
 <xref rid="B64-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B91-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. It is important to note that the enzootic cycle of MADV is largely restricted to areas deep within rainforests, which makes full characterization of the enzootic cycle logistically challenging. It is understood, however, that unlike North American EEEV, the primary vector for MADV are 
 <italic>Cx.</italic> (
 <italic>Melanoconion</italic>) mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="B64-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B91-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>].
</p>
