<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0055">The most accepted scientific consensus agrees that the low temperature and the low humidity favor the outbreak, the virus survival and the human-to-human transmission as previously observed in historical epidemic events. However, currently there is no consensus of what climates or weather conditions constitute the lower or higher limit to be considered as key-level factors for pandemics control or spread prediction. In the literature, is common to find several parameters that could be not equivalent for a precise comparison. For instance 1) the chosen response of the epidemics to be monitored i.e. total confirmed cases, suspected cases, mortality, hospital collapse, etc., 2) the chosen time period for evaluation (whole epidemic evolution, weekly, monthly or any arbitrary lapse), and 3) the reference of environmental factors for analysis as indoor or outdoor contexts. The vast majority of the reports are based on either laboratory results -through in situ viral activity observations- or meteorological statistical evidences and mathematical adjusting models. At laboratory conditions, there exist specific protocols at extreme well-defined experimental environments (incubation time, precise room temperature, controlled room humidity, host specimen specification, etc.). Such studies evaluated the effect of “specific controlled environmental conditions” on general infectivity of targeted viruses. Results of such studies normally pointed out precise values of room temperature or humidity as valid limits for virus survival or inactivation (
 <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">Lowen et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">Chan et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">Casanova et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">Doremalen et al., 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">Doremalen et al., 2020</xref>). However, such experimental information cannot fully explain why epidemics are also reached in localities where temperature of humidity are out of the range experimentally observed at laboratory conditions. On the other hand, most of the statistical methods and mathematical models have employed data from different lapses or periods of pandemics. Such information is acquired with more or less detailed and in-depth data according its availability (
 <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">Sajadi Mohammad et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">Keshavarzi, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">Bukhari and Jameel, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">Ma, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">Araujo and Naimi, 2020</xref>). The vast majority of such studies disregard both the origin of the transmission (local or imported) -assuming the total infection cases as the suitable variable to monitor- and the well-differentiated phases of the epidemic -assuming the whole pandemic lapsed as the most valid range for evaluation-. Such studies are not clearly conclusive respect to the environmental effects on epidemic's overall outcomes. Inappropriate focus on the epidemic lapse could release contradictory conclusions as pointed out by 
 <xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">Cai et al. (2007)</xref>. For instance, in this study, the association of temperature with confirmed cases resulted positive with perfect statistical significance (p = 0): as increases temperature, increases the number of infected people as well (see 
 <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). However, this expected result comes from the ordinary seasonal cycles that cross from winter to spring season with a concomitant temperature increase. Therefore, the positive association between temperature and TCPC with statistical significance could be mistakenly interpreted. In contrast, in the present analysis was possible to evaluate the correct negative association between environmental factors and LCPC similar than the high correlation coefficient statistically significant between LPCP and TCPC with the climatic character. Moreover, the LTR, which takes into account the effective number of days when the epidemics is regionally active, showed the highest correlation coefficients in association with the climate variable (see 
 <xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The last results were observed taking in consideration that the principal effect of environmental factors on virus transmission occurred only in the early stage of the epidemics before any imposed contention strategy. Therefore, both the initial lapse of the epidemic and the contagion origin-type are of the most significant highlights here founded useful to assure that the regional climate character in each state did influence the initial transmission of the COVID-19 disease in Mexico. Finally, it is important underline that experimental results under controlled conditions at laboratory scale offer extremely useful information to be employed during confinement phases 2, 3 and beyond. As shown in 
 <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, SARS-CoV-2 is stable at low temperatures (between 5 and 11 °C or generally below 20 °C) and low humidity (generally dry condition) (
 <xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">Doremalen et al., 2020</xref>). Commonly, in tropical and warm-dry climates the indoor environment is artificially adjusted by air-condition apparatus that reduces the temperature and the humidity for comfortable spaces. In the dry cluster analyzed in this study, the LCPC was high in states such BC and BCS likely linked to the intensive use of air-conditioning instrument in agreement with observations previously reported in Singapore and Hong Kong by Chan and cols. (
 <xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">Chan et al., 2011</xref>). The use of air-condition apparatus promotes the most appropriate conditions for survival of the SARS-CoV-2. Therefore it is important avoid the low temperature and low humidity in both indoor hospitals and room-home level spaces during phase 2 and 3 under implemented strict contention strategies. In Mexico, the quarantine obligation in phase 2 and 3 resulted in reduction until up 70% of the mobility in metropolitan areas with &gt;20 million of inhabitants. People stayed at home in a massive extent. Taking into account that the virus infectivity decreases as temperature and humidity increases some public health recommendations could generate massive non-contagion indoor areas. The employment of commercial humidifiers and heaters or even better, natural solar warm and fresh air circulation when possible, could be effective massive sanitary strategies in order to reduce the virus transmission as well as to decelerate the hospital system collapse.
</p>
