<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0005">In December, 2019, a series of human pneumonia cases of unknown cause emerged in Wuhan, Hubei, China. Sequencing analysis from lower respiratory tract samples indicated a novel coronavirus, which was named 2019 novel coronavirus (SARS-Cov-2) that caused clusters of fatal pneumonia with clinical presentation greatly resembling SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>]. COVID-19 started in China but now is present in many different countries with the highest number of cases in US, Italy and Spain among others. To better understand this new global epidemic from the environmental and health perspective I have decided to select the very recent papers published in the scientific literature and to prepare this Opinion Paper for JECE. Air compartment plays a key role in COVID-19 transmissions specially meteorological factors such as weather conditions, temperature, humidity and air pollution PM10, Black Carbon and NOx. But the presence and evolution of COVID-19 virus in other environmental compartment such as water, soils, wastewater and sewage sludge needs attention as well [
 <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Sewage can be used to determine the scale of COVID-19, the so-called Sewage Epidemiology or Waste Based Epidemiology (WBE) approach. In untreated waste water the virus causing COVID-19 (via feces introduced in waste water) can survive from hours to days. First data on COVID-19 in sewage in Europe was reported recently in the Netherlands, by RIVM National Institute for Public Health and the Environment. Patients with COVID-19 in their gastrointestinal tract will thus excrete it in their feces. RIVM has previously used this approach to detect the presence of norovirus, antibiotic-resistant bacteria, the poliovirus and the measles virus in wastewater [
 <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].Few weeks later COVID-19 virus was detected in sewage waters from Australia [
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] and Paris, France [
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Detection of SARS-CoV-2 is generally carried out with nucleic acid–based polymerase chain reaction(PCR) assay, used for confirmation of COVID-19 patients around the globe. PCR has high sensitivity and specificity, requirements for complicated sample handling in the laboratory, skilled personnel, and a long period of data processing and analysis (4–6 h).
</p>
