<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0060">Dengue (DENV serotypes 1–4), Zika (ZIKV), and chikungunya (CHIKV) viruses are transmitted to people primarily by the female 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> mosquito [
 <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. 
 <italic>Ae albopictus</italic> has been implicated as a secondary vector in the transmission of all three arboviruses as well [
 <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. These viruses cause a significant and growing burden of febrile illness in people worldwide. Severe clinical manifestations of dengue fever, although less common, can result in hemorrhage, shock, and death in some cases [
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. CHIKV infections are characterized by fever and severe arthralgias, with increasing evidence of fatal complications [
 <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. ZIKV was designated by the World Health Organization as a Public Health Emergency of International Concern in 2016 after congenital and neurological complications were associated with infections [
 <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Co-infections are common, and differential diagnosis is difficult in the absence of molecular diagnostics (e.g., PCR) due to similar clinical presentation [
 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. No specific therapeutic treatment is available for these arboviruses, and vector control remains the primary public health intervention to prevent and respond to epidemics. A DENV vaccine is available in some countries; however, it is recommended to be used only for seropositive individuals older than nine years [
 <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].
</p>
