<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In 2008, a patient who developed dengue haemorrhagic fever (DHF) in Peninsular Malaysia was found to be infected with a sylvatic DENV-2 strain [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007889.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. A sylvatic DENV-1 virus was also isolated from a patient with dengue fever in the country, and it was suggested that the infection could be due to a rare spillover event as a result of contact with infected forest-dwelling vectors [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007889.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. These findings indicate that in this region, sylvatic DENV is being maintained in a zoonotic cycle, as it has been for the last four decades [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007889.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Furthermore, a sylvatic DENV-2 strain was isolated in West Africa from a man with DHF. This isolate was however found to be from a completely different lineage of the virus detected in Malaysia [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007889.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Thus far, the sylvatic strain of DENV-4 has yet to be reported in humans, with only three known sequences that were successfully isolated in Malaysia [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007889.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. These reports suggest that sylvatic strains of DENV are capable of causing clinical disease in humans and, with the appropriate conditions, may emerge into an urban transmission cycle without requiring significant adaptation to the human host. There exist considerable genetic differences between human and sylvatic DENV strains. However, studies by Vasilakis and colleagues comparing human and sylvatic strains of DENV-2 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007889.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007889.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] and DENV-4 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007889.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] found no significant difference in the replication kinetics of both strains of each serotype, further highlighting the high possibility of re-emergence of sylvatic strains into the human transmission cycle. Despite the growing impact of dengue infections amongst human populations, there remains a lack of information on the presence and distribution of DENV strains in 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitoes in Malaysia. In this study we aimed to investigate the presence and distribution of DENV in urban localities in the Klang Valley, Peninsular Malaysia. We report the presence of all four DENV serotypes, including a sylvatic strain of DENV-4, in field captured 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> mosquitoes.
</p>
