<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Enterovirus 71 (EV71) is one of 19 serotypes within the species 
 <italic>Human Enterovirus A</italic> (HEV-A). EV71 is classified into three genotypes and 11 further subgenotypes: A, B1-B5, and C1-C5 
 <xref rid="pone.0097404-Brown1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Although EV71 infection is often asymptomatic, it can manifest as hand-foot-and-mouth disease (HFMD), severe encephalitis, and polio-like disease 
 <xref rid="pone.0097404-Ooi1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. In Asia, EV71 has been causing extensive epidemics of HFMD and occasional neuroinfection, especially in the last 15 years (reviewed in 
 <xref rid="pone.0097404-Bible1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>). Since 2008, regular epidemics of EV71 infection involving over a million cases have been reported in China 
 <xref rid="pone.0097404-Tan1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. In Europe, large outbreaks of polio-like disease caused by EV71 occurred in Bulgaria in 1975 and in Hungary in 1978. Thereafter, EV71 did not attract major attention until recently, when widespread asymptomatic circulation and detection from isolated neurological cases and minor outbreaks were reported from several European countries 
 <xref rid="pone.0097404-Witso1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0097404-Bible2" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. No major outbreaks have so far occurred in Europe. In Russia, no outbreaks of HFMD or neuroinfection caused by EV71 have been registered before 2013, and no studies of EV71 epidemiology have been carried out. Therefore, the disease profile and epidemiological situation differed strikingly between the adjacent regions of Russia and China during the 2008-2009 epidemic. The threat of EV71 epidemic urged investigation of EV71 circulation in Russia. A retrospective study conducted in Taiwan following the epidemic of 1998 reported low rate of seroconversion against EV71 in infants aged six months to three years prior to the epidemic and implied it as a potential risk factor of the epidemic 
 <xref rid="pone.0097404-Lu1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, and at that time seroepidemiology could be seen as a good measure to predict EV71 epidemics. Here we studied seroepidemiology of EV71 in six regions of Russia and summarized occasional isolations of EV71 over 13 years.
</p>
