<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par73">In 
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic>-infected cells, newly synthesized RNA is translated to generate new viral proteins, as template to generate additional vRNA molecules, as precursor of sfRNA molecules and is encapsidated into new virus particles. How does the virus coordinates these processes remains largely unknown. The process of assembly is considered highly specific because only positive-sense vRNA molecules are incorporated into budding virions. Remarkably, this is a common assumption that requires experimental verification. Whereas the coupling of replication and assembly confers specificity to vRNA (thus, excluding cellular RNA molecules from being incorporated into virus particles), how negative-sense RNA and sfRNA molecules are excluded from the assembly process remains to be determined. We have to consider, however, that the exclusion of sfRNA from virions, which was reported by our group for DENV2-NGC [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], may not be conserved for all flaviviruses. It is likely that dynamic secondary and tertiary structures adopted by the vRNA at different stages of the replication cycle will affect its interaction with viral proteins and cellular RBPs, thus conferring molecular specificity for different processes. Interestingly, we also lack evidence to confirm another widespread assumption about the protein composition of flaviviruses particles, that is, that only C, prM/M and E are present. Given the critical role of NS2A and NS3 during virus assembly that we summarize in this review, it remains a possibility that these viral RBPs are incorporated into virions. Indeed, the interior structure and composition of 
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic> particles remains elusive and, to the best of our knowledge, proteomic analysis of virus preparations are lacking. For the same reason, host proteins have not been associated with 
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic> virions unlike the related HCV particles, which incorporate host apolipoproteins [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR155">155</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR156">156</xref>].
</p>
