<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0135">Unlike type I IFNs which are already widely used in clinic, type III IFNs are not yet approved for any indication. Nevertheless, the unique qualities of type III IFN response—focused, long-lasting, and non-inflammatory—make IFN-λ an attractive intervention strategy in COVID-19. Importantly, IFN-λ administration has been shown to offer effective therapeutic effects without appreciable immunopathology in mice challenged with IAV (
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Davidson et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Galani et al., 2017</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2017</xref>). IFN-λ was as protective as IFN-α when adminsterered prophylactically, and more protective than IFN-β when administered simultaneously with IAV (
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Davidson et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2017</xref>). When administered after the onset of symptoms, IFN-λ2 was protective whereas IFN-α4 exacerbated the disease by promoting pro-inflammatory cytokine secretion and immune cell infiltration (
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Davidson et al., 2016</xref>). Recent study on SARS-CoV-2 shows that knocking out IFNLR1 in human intestinal epithelial cells impairs the ability to control viral replication, even more so than IFNAR1, and that SARS-CoV-2 is sensitive to pre-treatment with either IFN-β or IFN-λ (
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Stanifer et al., 2020</xref>). In a newly developed mouse model of SARS-CoV-2 infection, both prophylactic and therapeutic application of pegylated IFN-λ1 reduced viral replication (
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Dinnon et al., 2020</xref>). Therefore, clinical use of IFN-λ in COVID-19 holds promise, and clinical trials are under way (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04343976" id="intref0020" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04343976</ext-link>, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04331899" id="intref0025" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04331899</ext-link>). For both maximal efficacy and minimal toxicity, we envision an intervention strategy that draws upon the strengths of both type I and III IFN response (
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref> ). Type III IFNs may help to achieve a sustained antiviral state that limits viral spread in the upper airway as well as the lung. Type I IFNs, which are more potent but also more inflammatory, should be restricted to the early phase to facilitate viral clearance and prevent systemic inflammation.
</p>
