<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We have so far considered the possibility of sampling and testing infected and recovered individuals in populations. However, a common practice in zoonotic surveillance is to combine samples from multiple individuals in the stratum of interest in order to save money (e.g., 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1003668-Nasci1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>). Though this pooled sampling does not identify which individual tested positive for the virus, the goal of surveillance is often to identify the presence of the virus instead of a specific infected individual. Pooling sizes must be constrained to prevent the possibility of a positive individual sample being diluted below detectable levels, often determined using experimental dilutions in the laboratory (e.g., 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1003668-Sutherland1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>). To incorporate pooled sampling into our sampling model, we rescaled the probability of a positive detection in a single sample by the number of individuals in a pool, 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003668.e099.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>: the probability of detection in a single 
 <italic>pooled</italic> sample of strata 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003668.e100.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula> at time 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003668.e101.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula> can then be approximated using a linearized binomial expansion:
 <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003668.e102">
  <graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003668.e102.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <label>(13)</label>
 </disp-formula>Approximation (13) works well when 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003668.e103.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>. Our simulations indicate that a 10% approximation error occurs when 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003668.e104.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>, suggesting the approximation is robust for the purpose of early detection. Pooled sampling modifies (10) and (11) to
 <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003668.e105">
  <graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003668.e105.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <label>(14a)</label>
 </disp-formula>
 <disp-formula id="pcbi.1003668.e106">
  <graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1003668.e106.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <label>(14b)</label>
 </disp-formula>Our goal is to determine the resource allocation that will allow us to detect a disease as early as possible. We therefore introduce economic constraints on this sampling process in the next section.
</p>
