<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The segmented genome of IDV encodes for nine proteins [
 <xref rid="B54-jcm-08-00192" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. The longest three segments encode polymerases PB2, PB1, and P3 which are essential in replication and viral mRNA synthesis. The fourth segment encodes the glycoprotein hemagglutinin-esterase fusion (HEF) that shares extreme similarity between IDV and ICV in terms of structural folds and helps in viral entry. Also the IDV-HEF can accommodate diverse extended glycan moieties in its open receptor-binding cavity, thus providing an explanation for the broad cell tropism [
 <xref rid="B60-jcm-08-00192" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. A recent study highlights the role of HEF glycoprotein of IDV in proving exceptional stability to high temperatures and acidity [
 <xref rid="B61-jcm-08-00192" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. The authors revealed that IDV could withstand and retain its infectivity even at higher temperatures of 53 °C for as long as 120 min. Not only this, but the IDV was also observed to lose just 20% of the original infectivity when subjected to a low pH of 3.0 for 30 min as compared to IAV, IBV and ICV that were completely inactive at this low pH. This study demonstrates how IDV has evolved to utilize its proteins for survival in exceptional thermal and acidic conditions [
 <xref rid="B61-jcm-08-00192" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. The fifth segment encodes the nucleoprotein (NP) which constitutes the viral ribonucleoprotein complex [
 <xref rid="B62-jcm-08-00192" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. The sixth segment encodes the matrix proteins DM1 and DM2 that lines the viral membrane from inside and exhibits proton-channel activity respectively [
 <xref rid="B4-jcm-08-00192" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-jcm-08-00192" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-jcm-08-00192" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-jcm-08-00192" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. A recent study conducted on the 
 <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> oocytes, showed that the IDV-M2 protein was functionally similar to the ICV-M2 protein [
 <xref rid="B66-jcm-08-00192" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The last segment seven encodes nonstructural proteins NS1 and NEP that helps in neutralizing the cellular interferon response and mediates the nuclear export of RNPs respectively [
 <xref rid="B67-jcm-08-00192" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. 
</p>
