<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="pcbi.1007561.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007561.t002</object-id>
 <label>Table 2</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Key TasP strategies modeled in this paper.</title>
 </caption>
 <alternatives>
  <graphic id="pcbi.1007561.t002g" xlink:href="pcbi.1007561.t002" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
   <colgroup span="1">
    <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
    <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
   </colgroup>
   <thead>
    <tr>
     <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strategy</th>
     <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th>
    </tr>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Random</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Select diagnosed but virally unsuppressed agents (DUs)
      <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn001">*</xref> at random.
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">“CD4 &lt; 500”</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First select DUs whose CD4 count has ever fallen below 500 cells/μL.
      <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">
       <sup>#</sup>
      </xref> If resources are sufficient to link all selected agents to effective care, select additional agents at random until the treatment limit has been reached.
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">“Under age 25”</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First select DUs under 25. If resources are sufficient to link all selected agents to effective care, select additional DU agents at random until the treatment limit has been reached</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">“Under age 30”</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First select DUs under 25, then those under 30, then at random until the treatment limit has been reached.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">“Under age 35”</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First select DUs under 25, then those under 30, then those under 35, then at random until the treatment limit has been reached.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">“SPVL”</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First select DUs with SPVLs
      <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">
       <sup>#</sup>
      </xref> over 6.0 RNA copies/ml; then those with SPVLs less than 5.5, 5.0, 4.5, and 4.0 RNA copies/ml, respectively; then at random until the treatment limit has been reached.
      <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">
       <sup>&amp;</sup>
      </xref>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">“CD4 &lt; 500, Under 25”</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First select DUs whose CD4 count has ever fallen below 500
      <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">
       <sup>#</sup>
      </xref>. Once all DU agents with CD4 nadirs below 500 are linked to effective care, select agents under age 25. Once all DUs in these two groups have been linked to effective care, select additional DUs at random until the treatment limit has been reached.
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">“Under 25,
      <break/>CD4 &lt; 500”
     </td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First select DUs under age 25, then whose CD4 count has ever fallen below 500.
      <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">
       <sup>#</sup>
      </xref> Once all DUs in these two groups have been linked to effective care, select additional agents at random until the treatment limit has been reached.
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">“Men under 30 &amp; women under 25”</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">First select male DUs under 30, then female DUs under 25, then at random until the treatment limit has been reached.</td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
 </alternatives>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn id="t002fn001">
   <p>* Agents just initiating suppressive therapy are classified as suppressed. Agents dropping out of therapy are assumed to remain suppressed for 30 days.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="t002fn002">
   <p># By targeting agents based on factors that do not change during therapy, we avoid viral load and CD4 oscillations associated with having to wait for CD4 counts to drop (or viral loads to rebound) following a therapy cessation before re-initiating therapy.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="t002fn003">
   <p>&amp; This strategy takes advantage of the fact that viral loads vary widely from person-to-person [
    <xref rid="pcbi.1007561.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>–
    <xref rid="pcbi.1007561.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, 
    <xref rid="pcbi.1007561.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. See technical methods for details.
   </p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
