<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">The first conclusion of this study is that astrocytes are initially more, but in the long term less susceptible to ZIKV infection than the selected mammalian and mosquito cell lines. However, astrocytes are more susceptible to ZIKV infection than neurons, as determined by the percentage of infected cells after infection with the ZIKV. On the other hand, astrocytes production of the virus was comparable to the amount produced in the selected cell lines. Considering that the production of infectious virus particles was much higher in astrocytes and their viability at least as high as in neurons, this indicates that astrocytes can tolerate higher amount of the virus load compared to neurons. The higher susceptibility of human astrocytes versus neurons is in line with the observation that ZIKV strains Cambodia (2010), Brazil (2015), and Puerto Rico (2015) infected more RGCs and astrocytes in cortical tissue slices than post-mitotic neurons in a period from early gestation to around mid-gestation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. Our findings further support this observation by revealing that the infection rate of ZIKV is lower in human neurons than in astrocytes. Our observation of low infection rate in human fetal astrocytes is also in line with data obtained in mice astrocytes and human adult astrocytes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup>. Higher infection rates in astrocytes versus neurons, regardless of the strain, reflect the differences detected in the extent and/or the types of ZIKV entry receptors described in both cell types
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. Namely, astrocytes at mid-gestation abundantly express Axl, a type of TAM entry receptor, while NPCs and neurons poorly express Axl
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. Higher ZIKV uptake into neurons after prolonged hpi in our experiments may indicate that infection further promotes viral entry, which 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> is most likely promoted by astrocytic hyper-production of ZIKV. In line with this conclusion, we observed differences not only in the infection rate between astrocytes and neurons, but also differences in the productive virus release rate for the two cell types. It appears that in neurons, virus production and release were suppressed with prolonged infection. The fact that astrocytes apparently did not suppress virus production and proved to be much more resilient to the higher among of infectious virus particles supports the view that astrocytes are the major producer of ZIKV progeny in the brain. It is to be expected that when astrocytes become infected, massive infection of other CNS cell types will follow. From this perspective, it is of outmost importance to prevent the infection of astrocytes. This was shown to be successful with azithromycin, which reduced the infection, rescued cell viability, and decreased viral production in U87 cell lines and human pluripotent stem cell-derived astrocytes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
