<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Library preparation for the MinION was conducted using Ligation Sequencing 1D (SQK-LSK108/SQK-LSK109, ONT) and Native Barcoding kits (EXP-NBD103/EXP-NBD104/EXP-NBD114, ONT) on FLO-MIN106 (R9.4/R9.4.1, ONT) flowcells according to the manufacturer’s instructions and modifications as per 
 <xref rid="ref-60" ref-type="bibr">Quick 
  <italic>et al.</italic> (2017)
 </xref>. Briefly, DNA prepared in the previous step (PCR amplicon pools for each sample were pooled) was end-repaired and dA-tailed using an UltraII End Prep Reaction Module (E7442, NEB) followed by ligation of barcodes using the NEBNext UltraII Ligation module (E7595, NEB) in a “one-pot” reaction. Following barcode ligation, samples were purified using a SPRI bead cleanup and pooled together into a single tube before ONT adaptor ligation with the NEBNext UltraII Ligation module. Ligated DNA was then cleaned using a SPRI bead clean-up with ABB/SFB (SQK-LSK108/SQK-LSK109, ONT) washes and final library elution in ONT’s elution buffer (SQK-LSK108/SQK-LSK109, ONT). With the latest kit versions, up to 24 native barcodes are available, but multiplexing varied by run according to available samples and barcodes, with multiplexed MinION runs of three to 24 samples conducted. Sequencing libraries were prepared with a negative control (non-template control from cDNA synthesis), which was sequenced as a barcoded sample. Sequencing was performed on a Dell Latitude E5470 laptop (CPU: 6th Generation Intel Core i7-6820HQ [Quad Core, 2.7GHz, 8MB cache]; Memory: 16GB RAM; Storage: 1TB solid state drive) using MinKNOW (version available at the time, v1.7.3 to 18.12.9) with live basecalling turned off. The MinION functions as a “read-until” platform, whereby the length of sequencing runs is determined by the user when sufficient data has been produced (maximum 48h); therefore, this varied between runs. An offline version of MinKNOW provided by ONT was used due to varying internet quality at different locations. To ease the installation and use of bioinformatic pipelines in the field, a lab-on-an-SSD approach was used to ensure a working bioinformatic environment was always available. The lab-on-an-SSD is a bootable USB3 drive containing a linux installation, ONT software and bioinformatic analysis software, available from the ARTIC network resources, that offers a plug-and-play bioinformatic environment for most laptops. SSD image available as an open-source resource here: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/artic-network/fieldbioinformatics/tree/master/lab-on-an-ssd" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/artic-network/fieldbioinformatics/tree/master/lab-on-an-ssd</ext-link>),
</p>
