<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">Most co-evolution studies focused on using homologous sequences of bacterial proteins originating from different species for their analysis, and required the number of sequences
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup> to be anywhere from 100 to 1000. Without highlighting the mathematical details, using a metric of distance between sequences, a concept of effective sequences was introduced
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup> to discount the sequences that are close to one another within the same cluster of sequences and but are further apart from the other clusters. The sequences which are with an identity better than 0.8 were effectively considered to be the same sequence, thus weighing down the total number of sequences. The present analysis is different from the commonly used co-evolution studies in several ways: (i) Sequences are from within the subspace of the same virus, representing polymorphisms, rather than from the hypothetical sample set from all viruses or all proteins. Thus the sequence identities are high and a cutoff of 0.8 was not relevant (ii) Further, weighting of the sequences was not used in our covariance network generation (iii) By choosing increasing homology cut-offs over 0.9 (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">14</xref>), which are still relevant for the virus polymorphisms, the number of effective sequences increases over 100. We thus believe that the size of the sequence data sets used was sufficient, although it might appear to be insufficient based on the standard definitions of number of effective sequences. Further, to eliminate the possibility that the observed patterns in the node degree distribution are an artefact because of the higher number of effective sequences of HIV and avian influenza, the covariance analysis was repeated using randomly selected 200 sequences from the alignment. Even with this significantly reduced number of sequences, the statistical nature of the couplings did not change for HIV and avian influenza. The characteristics of the distribution remained the same for all the viruses as shown in Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">15</xref>.
</p>
