<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>At the end of 2019, pneumonia patients with an unidentified cause were started to be observed in Wuhan, Hubei Province, China.
 <xref rid="jca21806-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> After the genetic analysis of the virus, it was understood that these pneumonia cases were caused by the 2019 Novel Coronavirus (2019‐nCoV).
 <xref rid="jca21806-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>2</sup>
 </xref> On 11 February 2020; the disease was officially named as COVID‐19, by the World Health Organization (WHO).
 <xref rid="jca21806-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> This novel coronavirus was named as SARS‐CoV‐2 by the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses.
 <xref rid="jca21806-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref> It was declared a pandemic by the WHO on 11 March 2020. As of 17 April 2020, in the worldwide, there have been 2 175 130 confirmed cases of COVID‐19, including 145 184 deaths, as reported to WHO.
 <xref rid="jca21806-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> The mortality rate of COVID‐19 is higher than the mortality rate of seasonal influenza in which the mortality rate is reported usually less than 0.1%.
 <xref rid="jca21806-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> Patients with any comorbidity and/or older age are associated with poorer clinical outcomes than younger patients or those without any comorbidity. As the number of comorbidities increases, the clinical outcome gets worse. Smoking, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, diabetes, hypertension, cardiovascular diseases, and malignancy are reported to be the risk factors for severe COVID‐19 and increased mortality.
 <xref rid="jca21806-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref> Although there are clinical trials regarding the development of therapeutics and vaccines, there are currently no licensed vaccines or therapeutics for COVID‐19. Because of the higher mortality rate and the high number of infected cases, it is important to find a treatment in a short time.
</p>
