<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par60">
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic> NS2A is a small (~ 22 KDa), hydrophobic protein generated after processing of the viral polyprotein by an unknown host protease and the viral protease at the NS1-NS2 and NS2A-NS2B boundaries, respectively [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>]. It contains eight segments which have been named 
 <underline>p</underline>redicted 
 <underline>t</underline>rans
 <underline>m</underline>embrane 
 <underline>s</underline>egments (pTMS), although only five of them truly transverse the ER membrane. The N-terminus, pTMS1 and pTMS5 localize to the ER lumen and do not interact with its membrane; pTMS2 is in the ER lumen and interacts peripherally with the ER membrane; pTMS3, 4, 6, 7 and 8 are integral transmembrane domains and a short C-terminus localizes to the cytoplasm [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]. Several reports have mapped NS2A residues that are determinants for viral assembly and egress. It has been shown that the mutation Lys-90-Ser or the triple mutation Arg-22-Ala/Lys-23-Ala/ Arg-24-Ala in YFV NS2A does not affect the accumulation of viral protein or vRNA, but decreases the production of infectious virions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>]. Interestingly, the Lys-90-Ser mutation had no effect on the production of VLPs that lack capsid and vRNA, suggesting that NS2A participates in the incorporation of vRNA into the budding particle [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]. Similarly, an Ile-59-Asn mutation impaired the assembly of KUN WNV. The mutation was associated with the absence of the ER membrane remodelling present in cells transfected with a wild-type infectious RNA replicon. Importantly, a compensatory mutation Thr-149-Pro restored the membrane remodelling and virus production to levels similar to wild-type [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>].
</p>
