<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par62">Several studies have suggested the involvement of NS2A in the transport of vRNA from the replication complexes to the sites of viral assembly, whereby NS2A functions as a viroporin [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>]. Viroporins are hydrophobic proteins that oligomerize at cellular membranes resulting in the formation of an hydrophilic channel that alters membrane permeability, vesicular trafficking and Ca
 <sup>+ 2</sup> homeostasis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>]. Indeed, overexpression of DENV and JEV NS2A in 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> resulted in increased membrane permeability and lysis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>]; however, more recent studies point towards a different mechanism by which NS2A transports newly synthesized vRNA. In their study, Xie and collaborators [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>] showed that NS2A specifically binds to DENV vRNA, with a cytoplasmic loop of NS2A (amino acids 93 to 100) interacting with the last 285 nucleotides of DENV 3′ UTR. Similar findings were reported by the same group for ZIKA NS2A, where the cytoplasmic loop (residues 97 to 104) was shown to interact with the last 333 nucleotides from the 3′ UTR [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]. As no RNA packaging signal has been identified for 
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic> assembly, the authors hypothesize that complex structures located in the 3′ UTR of DENV and ZIKA serve as signals for NS2A to recruit newly synthesized vRNA from the replication complex to the viral assembly site. Because mutations that alter virus assembly do not influence the interaction with DENV or ZIKA 3′ UTR, the authors propose a model in which different molecules of NS2A recruit C-prM-E, NS2B/NS3 and vRNA to the virion assembly site. These molecules are brought together due to oligomerization of NS2A after which processing of the structural proteins occurs yielding free C that binds to vRNA to form the nucleocapsid on the cytoplasmic side. The nucleocapsid is then enveloped by E and prM leading to virion formation and budding into the ER lumen [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]. Although the proposed model is very compelling, it remains to be addressed whether interaction of the vRNA with C will lead to its detachment from NS2A, or whether NS2A is incorporated into the virion. Likewise, 
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic> infection produce large amounts of sfRNA, as these molecules derive from the 3′ UTR from the vRNA, an important question is whether NS2A can bind sfRNA molecules free in the cytoplasm and whether or not these are incorporated into virions.
</p>
