<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although MeV is primary a lymphotropic virus it could also infect the CNS. One of the ways the virus might enter into CNS could be through the hematogenous way by crossing the blood-brain barrier (BBB) [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Since endothelial cells are susceptible to infection in vitro, in vivo and in SSPE cases, their infection at the BBB could also give an opportunity for MeV to reach the CNS [
 <xref rid="B88-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="B178-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">178</xref>]. In addition, lymphocytes are also able to pass the BBB meaning that MeV-infected lymphocytes could carry the virus across the BBB [
 <xref rid="B179-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>,
 <xref rid="B180-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">180</xref>]. However, the specific mechanisms allowing the virus to enter the CNS remain unclear [
 <xref rid="B88-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="B105-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>,
 <xref rid="B181-viruses-11-01017" ref-type="bibr">181</xref>]. The hyperfusogenic phenotype seems to be necessary to allow viral dissemination through neurons even in the absence of known receptor. To date, the early tropism and dissemination of 
 <italic>Paramyxoviridae</italic> within the CNS during early stages of infection remain poorly documented. There are also very few available data on cellular and molecular mechanisms governing CNS invasion. To date, investigations are mainly limited to clinical symptoms, serology, RNA sequencing, and tissue immunostaining. Moreover, most of the studies have been performed with MeV vaccinal strains such as Edmonston B strain or neuro-adapted strains in Hamster, using several wild type or transgenic rodents, or other in vitro models such as primary or immortalized neural cultures. Nowadays, whether these viruses and models perfectly reflect what occurs in human remains questionable, they allow addressing specific questions in obtaining important information regarding the tropism of MeV infection in the brain.
</p>
