<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Therefore, Iran is strategically placed at a remarkable risk zone for these arboviral diseases. In addition, the introduction of exotic vectors into Iran is possible [
 <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Active entomological surveillance of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> was carried out in spring, summer and winter, 2008–2014 in eight provinces [
 <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] following the first dengue case report in Iran in 2008 [
 <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> larvae were collected in the Sistan &amp; Baluchestan province bordering Pakistan in 2009 [
 <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In 2013, 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> adult mosquitoes were also detected in a coastal location neighbouring Chabahar in the same province [
 <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> is regarded as a conspicuously menacing and versatile species that inhabits both temperate and tropical climate regions [
 <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Since this vector has been detected in different parts of Sistan &amp; Baluchestan, there is a possibility of dengue fever and chikungunya fever in southeast Iran. At present, there are just a few studies from Iran on dengue fever in blood donors [
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and on patients who tested negative for Crimean-Congo Haemorrhagic Fever in Sistan &amp; Baluchestan province [
 <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] and there is no report from Iran on dengue fever in patients with rash and fever showing non-specific febrile illness. Between 2017 and 2018, an investigation was cariied out in the Sistan and Baluchistan Province on alleged CHIK patients. Laboratory results from qRT-PCR or ELISA tests performed revealed a quarter (25.1%) of the samples tested positive [
 <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In addition, another study in 2017 depicted the southernmost regions as areas at a high risk of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> establishment [
 <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Hence, this study was implemented with the aim of assessing the serology of chikungunya and dengue fever in suspected patients.
</p>
