<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As previously mentioned, the valleys in fitness landscapes are detrimental regions, corresponding to mutations on nonviable or low-fitness genotypes. In principle, we could use this knowledge to redirect virus evolution towards a more dismal future by increasing the likelihood of acquiring such detrimental mutations. Among substitutions, stop codons are possibly the worst mutation an organism could acquire. This idea was directly tested in our recent work in which two very different RNA viruses, influenza A and Coxsackie B3, were genetically engineered to generate more stop codons after replication occurs. These viruses were re-coded in serine and leucine codons by synonymous mutations that placed them only one mutation away from stop codons. Both engineered viruses generated more stop mutations, in vitro and in vivo, accompanied by significant losses in viral fitness and attenuation in mouse models [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006979.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. These findings were in agreement with previous studies in which the ability of RNA viruses to buffer mutation (known as genetic robustness) was reduced. Importantly, these works show that the same error rate will differently impact a genome depending on the codons it carries, which can lead to distinct amino acid changes. Thus, the position that a virus occupies in genotypic space defines not only its mutational robustness but also its mutant spectrum, the evolutionary trajectories available to it, and ultimately its evolvability [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006979.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The endeavours described are still in their infancy, but the goal to characterize the local sequence and fitness landscape of a virus, to monitor and potentially predict its immediate future, and to evaluate how antiviral approaches might alter these trajectories seems attainable. The further integration of mathematical modelling, bioinformatics, and experimental evolution will booster our response to viral outbreaks.
</p>
