<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>IBV were first identified in the 1940s and, unlike influenza A, they primarily cause disease in humans [
 <xref rid="B7-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Recurrent seasonal epidemics are the consequence of the antigenic drift, ongoing changes in the amino-acid sequences at antigenic sites in the two surface glycoproteins hemagglutinin (HA) and neuraminidase (NA) [
 <xref rid="B8-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. During the early 1980s, evolutionary changes in the HA gene diverged into two phylogenetically and antigenically distinct lineages that are represented by B/Victoria/2/87 (Victoria lineage) and B/Yamagata/16/88 (Yamagata lineage) [
 <xref rid="B9-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Since 2001, both lineages have co-circulated, showing distinct antigenicity and transmission dynamics and often alternating in regional dominance presenting challenges for vaccine strain selection [
 <xref rid="B10-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Importantly, the co-circulation of the two lineages results in a different pattern of evolution of influenza B virus and can explain some of the disparate variability of seasonal outbreaks [
 <xref rid="B11-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Recent reports have highlighted the potential differences in the epidemiology of Victoria and Yamagata lineage viruses, including younger average ages of persons with Victoria virus infection and greater transmissibility. The Victoria lineage is under greater positive selection pressure and, hence, likely to experience greater antigenic drift than the more conserved Yamagata lineage [
 <xref rid="B12-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Annual influenza vaccination is the most effective method for preventing influenza and its associated complications. In general, seasonal vaccines are trivalent, including one influenza B lineage. Despite being only two lineages, the selection of the right influenza B virus strain in the vaccine has been proven very difficult, because the dominant lineage changes over time, as result, the vaccine efficacy decreased when the included vaccine strain did not match the circulating epidemic strain [
 <xref rid="B13-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].
</p>
