<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>First and foremost, complete standardization is likely impossible, because it would place an undue burden on laboratories in more resource-poor settings. One avenue that has been proposed to improve comparisons among vector competence studies is the standardization of reporting methodologies [
 <xref rid="B147-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>] to increase both transparency and reproducibility. While establishing guidelines to encourage better reporting will undoubtedly benefit the field, some experimental standards would also be beneficial. For example, as described above, there is a substantial effect of oral dose (viral titer of the infected host) on the infection of a mosquito, especially in the context of artificial bloodmeals [
 <xref rid="B129-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>,
 <xref rid="B138-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>,
 <xref rid="B140-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>]. Ideally, vector competence assessments would therefore use viral titers that are consistent with viremia titers in humans or other amplification hosts. However, human arboviral pathogens may peak prior to the appearance of symptoms [
 <xref rid="B164-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>,
 <xref rid="B165-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>,
 <xref rid="B166-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">166</xref>], which is complicated by the increasing use of PCR-based rather than infectious assays. Although the direct or indirect feeding of mosquitoes on the blood of infected persons with early diagnosis can mitigate this challenge [
 <xref rid="B135-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>], few research groups have access to this kind of study, which requires substantial community outreach and includes challenges to ethical approval [
 <xref rid="B167-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>]. For viruses with nonhuman amplification hosts, viremia estimates generally come from experimental infections, which are logistically challenging. In the absence of accurate human or other amplifying host viremia data, or human volunteer studies as described above, there is value to be gained from the development and utilization of animal models. In this, ZIKV provides an excellent example of the difficulties associated with models for several human arboviruses that do not replicate efficiently in immunocompetent mice [
 <xref rid="B168-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">168</xref>,
 <xref rid="B169-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">169</xref>,
 <xref rid="B170-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">170</xref>]. Therefore, many of the developed models utilize mice that have had elements of their innate immune response altered (e.g., interferon receptor knockouts, human STAT2 knock-in, etc.) [
 <xref rid="B168-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">168</xref>,
 <xref rid="B171-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">171</xref>,
 <xref rid="B172-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">172</xref>], rendering them even less relevant to natural transmission cycles. Therefore, the use of natural reservoirs as animal models would be ideal. However, in the case of several important arboviruses (YFV, DENV, CHIKV, ZIKV), the natural hosts are nonhuman primates [
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B173-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">173</xref>], which require specialized facilities and expertise, and lack the same breadth of reagents compared to mice [
 <xref rid="B168-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">168</xref>,
 <xref rid="B174-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">174</xref>], not to mention the high costs when compared to murine models.
</p>
