<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although human-mediated long-distance movement was found to be a significant feature of raccoon rabies spread (Smith 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref71">2002</xref>), it was still rare compared to natural dispersal, and stochastic in its occurrence. In contrast, human-mediated dispersal of dog rabies appears more widespread and potentially predictable due to possible links with human activities and migration patterns. The European colonisation of Africa is thought to have led to the introduction and subsequent expansion of canine rabies across the continent (Bourhy 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">2008</xref>; Talbi 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref76">2009</xref>; Lemey 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47">2010</xref>); increasingly frequent records of re-introductions into countries where rabies has been eliminated have been recorded (Zanoni and Breitenmoser, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref87">2003</xref>; Weiss 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref81">2009</xref>; Gautret 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref29">2011</xref>;), and canine rabies has recently emerged on several previously rabies-free islands in Indonesia via fishermen importing incubating dogs (Windiyaningsih 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref84">2004</xref>; Susilawathi 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref73">2012</xref>). Even on smaller scales, phylogeographic patterns frequently imply translocation events that increase the level of mixing between lineages and may obscure patterns of lineage clustering (David 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">2004</xref>; Talbi 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref77">2010</xref>; Hayman 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">2011</xref>).
</p>
