<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although often inferred, it is difficult to quantify the influence of human-mediated movements on the diffusion of RABV. Though translocations may be frequent, the likelihood of establishment and spread is much lower (Smith 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref72">2005</xref>). But, unlike for wild animals, where translocation is risky and often unsuccessful, human-mediated displacement from a dog's original home range confers fewer risks. Dog translocations are therefore likely to be more successful in initiating new disease foci, and with potentially higher consequences, introducing disease into previously disease-free areas. Given that long-distance movements instigated by humans are often in response to social drivers, the genetic structure of dog rabies is expected to reflect variation in cultures and socioeconomic factors. For example, rural workers in Thailand often relocate to urban areas where work is more readily available in the off-growing season, taking their dogs, and sometimes rabies, with them (Denduangboripant 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">2005</xref>). Similarly, the resurgence of canine rabies in KwaZulu-Natal in the 1970s was linked to refugee movements from Mozambique (Swanepoel 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref74">1993</xref>; Cleaveland, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">1998</xref>) and phylogenetic patterns of RABV in parts of northern Tanzania can be tentatively explained by the movement of nomadic Maasai pastoralists with their dogs (Lembo 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">2007</xref>). Counterproductively, dog-owners have been reported to move their dogs to avoid the threat of culling during attempts to control rabies, which may explain more rapid spread of rabies than would be predicted by dog movement alone. Importantly, many of these aspects of human geography are quantifiable, making it possible in principle to generate testable hypotheses about their role in determining rabies phylogeographic structure.
</p>
