<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Note that we incorporate vaccination into this model by removing, deterministically, a proportion of susceptibles to a separate vaccinated class (i.e., they are still counted as part of 
 <italic>N</italic> but otherwise do not interact with the model dynamics). Specifically we remove 21% of the population, based on published vaccination rates and efficacy statistics in Australia [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006377.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006377.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. We chose to do this rather than take vaccination rate as a fitted parameter so as to minimize the number of parameters to be fit. Consequently, we set the prior for initial season susceptibility to be uniformly distributed from 0 to 0.75. We used temperature as the covariate with which to enable seasonal forcing, following the relationship 
 <inline-formula id="pcbi.1006377.e037">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1006377.e037.jpg" id="pcbi.1006377.e037g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M37">
    <mrow>
     <msub>
      <mi>R</mi>
      <mn>0</mn>
     </msub>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <msub>
      <mover accent="true">
       <mi>R</mi>
       <mo>¯</mo>
      </mover>
      <mn>0</mn>
     </msub>
     <mo>+</mo>
     <mi>a</mi>
     <mrow>
      <mo>(</mo>
      <mi>T</mi>
      <mo>-</mo>
      <mover accent="true">
       <mi>T</mi>
       <mo>¯</mo>
      </mover>
      <mo>)</mo>
     </mrow>
    </mrow>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </inline-formula> (with 
 <italic>T</italic> the daily mean temperature and 
 <inline-formula id="pcbi.1006377.e038">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1006377.e038.jpg" id="pcbi.1006377.e038g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M38">
    <mover accent="true">
     <mi>T</mi>
     <mo>¯</mo>
    </mover>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </inline-formula> the mean temperature over the study period). A number of studies have considered a variety of climate covariates and their interaction with influenza transmission both in populations and experimental models (e.g., [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006377.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006377.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]); with indications that relationships with and between climate factors are complex and may vary globally [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006377.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. We noted similar quality model fits when using the specific humidity formulation presented by Shaman 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006377.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], however we chose to use the simplest seasonal link, temperature, as this form produced similar quality fits while requiring fewer parameters and enabling greater ease of interpretation.
</p>
