<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30">In the current situation of rapid spread of the epidemic, and there is no special treatment, effective epidemic prevention measures, to contain the spread of the epidemic is crucial. At present, China’s “sealed” measures, restrictions on residents’ travel and traffic control have played a significant role in controlling the spread of the epidemic. Retrospective studies have found that traffic restrictions have significantly reduced the number of cases outside Hubei [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">108</xref>]. For China, which is celebrating the traditional “Spring Festival”, the traditional way of commemorating has been changed. All live parties have been cancelled, all scenic spots have been closed to tourists and crowds have been avoided by all means. Meanwhile, in an effort to prevent further spread of the virus, the Chinese government paid for the construction of two new hospitals in Wuhan in 10 days to treat the infected, and sent medical teams across the country to provide support. For countries outside China, the monitoring of passing tourists has been increased at airports, ports and other transportation arteries, mainly including temperature detection and symptom screening, to avoid the occurrence of imported cases. At present, China’s epidemic control is relatively stable, and its various measures have been copied by other countries [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">109</xref>]. Although the source and transmission route of SARS-CoV-2 are not clear enough, the main method is still to control the population flow, the early detection of cases, isolation of cases, and isolation of susceptible groups, do a good job of disinfection measures to prevent the further spread of the disease. In addition to significantly limiting the spread of the disease, the closure has also resulted in significant improvements in the city’s air quality [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">110</xref>]. In the event of a global pandemic, unnecessary travel should be avoided. In addition to limiting the movement of people and cutting off potential transmission, it is also important to protect individual residents from travel. In the early stage of the outbreak, due to the shutdown of various enterprises, insufficient production capacity of medical protective equipment such as masks and protective clothing, residents could not buy enough protective equipment, or even buy fake protective equipment, which could not play a protective role. A study of both surgical and cotton masks found that the virus appeared on the outside of the masks and did not completely prevent the virus from spreading, so hands must be disinfected when came into contact with the surface of the masks [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].
</p>
