<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">Need for materials with high thermal, chemical and mechanical properties have led to the development of MSNs. As per IUPAC, mesoporous materials are define as the one having a pore size in the range of 2-50 nm and an ordered arrangement of pores giving an ordered structure to it (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>). Mobil Research and Development Corporation was the first to synthesize mesoporous solids from aluminosilicate gels using liquid crystal template mechanism in the year 1992. They designated it as (Mobil Crystalline Materials or Mobil Composition of Matter) MCM-41. The pore size of the mesoporous materials could be varied and tuned through the choice of surfactants used. MCM-41 is hexagonal with a pore diameter from 2.5 to 6 nm wherein cationic surfactants were used as templates. Various other materials of mesoporous nature have also been synthesized by varying the starting precursors and reaction conditions. These mesoporous materials may vary in their structural arrangement or the pore size. MCM-48 has a cubic arrangement whereas MCM-50 has a lamella-like arrangement (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>). Non-ionic triblock copolymers like alkyl poly(ethylene oxide) (PEO) oligomeric surfactants and poly(alkylene oxide) block copolymers have also been used by University of California, Santa Barbara for synthesized the named Santa Barbara Amorphous materials (SBA). The ratio of ethylene oxide to propylene oxide was varied to achieve the desired symmetry of mesoporous materials (SBA-11 (cubic), SBA-12 (3-d hexagonal), SBA-15 (hexagonal) and SBA-16 (cubic cage-structured) (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>). This is different from MCM in that they possess larger pores of 4.6-30 nm and thicker silica walls. FSM-16, that is, folded sheets of mesoporous materials are another type of mesoporous materials, which are synthesized using quaternary ammonium surfactant as a template and layered polysilicate kanemite (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>). Various other MSNs have been synthesized which vary in their pore symmetry and shape, TUD-1 (Technical Delft University), HMM-33 (Hiroshima Mesoporous Material-33), COK-12 (Centrum Voor Oppervlaktechemie en Katalyse/Centre for Research Chemistry and Catalysis) (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>). The schematic representation of several MSNs structures is shown in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> as well as structural characteristics and applications of some mesoporous materials are listed in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">I</xref>.
</p>
