<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>On September 1984, there was the second epidemic of the disease following a flood. Many patients engaged in post-flood restoration of rice plants. The epidemic spread beyond the areas affected by the previous epidemic to Jeonnam, Jeonbuk, Gyeongbuk, and Chungnam Provinces, with the increasing numbers of deaths. With the efforts of the public health authority and specialists in academia, the disease was finally confirmed as leptospirosis. Briefly, Jungsoon Kim, an epidemiologist in Seoul National University, established a hypothesis based on the findings of the previous studies and described the disease as follows: a systemic infection, no person-to-person transmission, occurrence in association with rice harvesting in fall, having epidemiological setting of wet rice fields with mud, the causative agent to be maintained its lifecycle in carriers, with incidentally infecting humans, and prolonged survival outside of reservoirs, and rodents which were abundant in rice fields in fall, serving as carriers. The differential diagnoses included endemic typhus, scrub typhus, other rickettsioses, Korean hemorrhagic fever, new viral disease, and leptospirosis. Leptospirosis was chosen to be the most likely diagnosis. Furthermore, epidemiological investigations could identify the environmental exposure among residents of Gangwon Province (Wonju, Hongchun, Wonsung, and Hoengsung) and military personnel in Gwangju in Jeonnam Province, supporting of the hypothesis [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Accordingly, the research team in the Korea National Institute of Health (KNIH) successfully isolated 
 <italic>Leptospira</italic> strains from clinical samples (blood, cerebrospinal fluid, and urine) of two patients with the hemorrhagic pneumonitis-like disease in Wonju Presbyterian Hospital, and from wild rats caught in the epidemic areas (Wonju, Hoengsung, Hongchun, and Gwangju). The 
 <italic>Leptospira</italic> isolates were further confirmed for a causative-relationship using guinea pigs according to the four criteria of Koch's postulates [
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In addition, a research team in the Yonsei University also reported the isolation of 
 <italic>Leptospira</italic> strains from two patients in Hongchun Hospital as well as from wild rats caught in Gwangju [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].
</p>
