<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>MAYV has the potential to become a public health issue in the future, although this potential hinges on the virus′ ability to efficiently infect and be transmitted by urban mosquitoes such as 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>, which has to date not been demonstrated in nature [
 <xref rid="B138-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>,
 <xref rid="B229-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">229</xref>]. Indeed, many have predicted MAYV may be the next arbovirus to cause a large epidemic [
 <xref rid="B231-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">231</xref>,
 <xref rid="B248-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">248</xref>,
 <xref rid="B249-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">249</xref>]. However, there are several gaps in knowledge that need to be addressed in order to improve the understanding of this virus and the capacity to predict and prevent MAYV outbreaks [
 <xref rid="B241-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">241</xref>]. It is known the virus is transmitted by 
 <italic>Haemagogus spp</italic>. in the Americas [
 <xref rid="B241-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">241</xref>], but further vector ecology and surveillance studies are essential to analyze the presence of these mosquitoes and other potential vectors and their capacity to introduce MAYV into non-endemic areas. Imported cases in urban centers with the circulation of vector mosquitoes may play a role in potentially spreading the virus into these areas [
 <xref rid="B250-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">250</xref>]. It is also possible that MAYV could adapt to replicate in 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitoes causing large urban outbreaks. MAYV is present in South America [
 <xref rid="B231-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">231</xref>,
 <xref rid="B247-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">247</xref>,
 <xref rid="B251-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">251</xref>,
 <xref rid="B252-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">252</xref>] and it may also be present to a lesser extent in Central [
 <xref rid="B130-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>,
 <xref rid="B253-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">253</xref>] and North America [
 <xref rid="B130-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>,
 <xref rid="B254-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">254</xref>], and it is known to cause small outbreaks in areas close to forests. Adaptation to an anthropophilic mosquito vector could more readily permit sustained urban transmission. Additionally, there is a high antigenic cross-reactivity between MAYV and other viruses of the Semliki forest virus serocomplex [
 <xref rid="B241-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">241</xref>]. This may result in poor accuracy for serological assays and potential enhancement or protection of infection in regions displaying co-circulation of these alphaviruses. The former issue needs to be overcome to improve our capacity to evaluate the circulation of MAYV by serological studies and also accurately diagnose human cases, as these are essential measures to develop a better response to potential MAYV outbreaks. The latter issue has implications regarding disease severity in most of the affected regions and, consequentially, to vaccine development, which is the best prevention method that is still currently unavailable [
 <xref rid="B229-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">229</xref>,
 <xref rid="B255-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">255</xref>]. No vaccine currently exists against MAYF, but experimental work in mice suggests that vaccination with attenuated CHIKV might confer some protection against MAYV infection and disease [
 <xref rid="B256-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">256</xref>].
</p>
