<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0025">Precautions can be taken only when the national bodies responsible for the control of the outbreak acknowledge the significance of this route of transmission and recommend appropriate actions. Currently, this is not the case anywhere in the world. In China, where the outbreak started, the body overseeing the prevention and control of the epidemic (the National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China) has issued a series of prevention and control guidelines. As of 12 March 2020, the guidelines have been updated six times (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nhc.gov.cn/jkj/s3577/202003/4856d5b0458141fa9f376853224d41d7.shtml" id="ir010" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.nhc.gov.cn/jkj/s3577/202003/4856d5b0458141fa9f376853224d41d7.shtml</ext-link>), reflecting some change in the Commission’s perception of the mechanisms of the viral infection spread: from no mention of airborne transmission at all to an admission of the possibility of this route of transmission. However, the guidelines stopped short of accepting that this is in fact happening, and instead stated in the latest version (7 March 2020) that airborne transmission “has not been determined”. In Italy, which has emerged as one of the main hot spots in the world, the distance of 1 m between people is recommended in indoor “red zones”, but there is no mention of longer distance transport (
 <xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">Gazzetta Ufficiale 2020</xref>). The list of examples could go on. The US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (
 <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">CDC Page last reviewed: October 30, 2018</xref>) takes a broader view of viral infection spread, stating that: “
 <italic>Airborne transmission over longer distances, such as from one patient room to another has not been documented and is thought not to occur”</italic>. At the time of writing, the daily increase in the number of cases of COVID-19 in the USA is fast (
 <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">WHO et al., 2020</xref>).
</p>
