<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In two Chinese multicenter surveys, one of which was led by the First Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou Medical University, including 552 hospitals in 31 provinces/provincial municipalities through January 29th, 2020 and the other was led by the First Hospital of Lanzhou University including 7 hospitals, a considerable number of patients with COVID-19 had some abnormalities in liver function tests.
 <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> In particular, 6.2% to 22.2% of patients had increased serum AST levels (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Fig. 2</xref>) and 21.3% to 28.1% of patients had increased serum ALT levels, respectively.
 <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Of the six studies performed in Wuhan, China,
 <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
 <sup>–</sup>
 <xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> only four included data on the proportion of patients with abnormal liver function test results. Specifically, in these four studies, the proportion of infected patients with increased serum AST levels ranged from 24.1% to 36.6% (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Fig. 2</xref>).
 <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> In a survey from Zhejiang Province, China, the proportion of patients with increased serum AST levels was only 16.1%, whereas the proportion of those with increased serum ALT levels was not specified.
 <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> It seems likely that the proportion of infected patients with increased serum AST levels in Wuhan (i.e. the area in which the epidemic of COVID-19 started) is much greater than cases reported outside Wuhan. It is plausible to speculate that there may have been a higher viral load of COVID-19 in exposed patients in Wuhan, where the infection began and was concentrated in a greater proportion of the population.
</p>
