<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0035">The concept of the vaccination game relies on evolutionary game theory (EGT) alongside an epidemiological compartment model. EGT is a powerful framework for modeling the evolution of cooperation in biological and social sciences. It is the prevailing theoretical framework for understanding social and complex epidemic dynamics (
 <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Smith, 1974</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">Tanimoto, 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">Tanimoto, 2019</xref>). Epidemiology with vaccination as a major issue in the study of evolutionary biology has been widely researched in the past few decades (
 <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">Kabir et al., 2019a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">Kabir and Tanimoto, 2019</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">Bauch and Earn, 2004</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">Kuga et al., 2019</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">Fukuda et al., 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">Fukuda and Tanimoto, 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0170" ref-type="bibr">Iwamura and Tanimoto, 2018</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">Kabir et al., 2019b</xref>). More recently, a number of precursors used theoretical models to better understand epidemic dynamics in both local (single epidemic season) and global (repeated seasons) time scales, in order to explore how to control contagious diseases. Among them, notable studies include 
 <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">Kabir and Tanimoto (2019)</xref> for indicating a 
 <italic>meta</italic>-population migration model, 
 <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">Kuga and Tanimoto (2018)</xref> for the imperfectness of vaccines using both a multi-agent simulation and theoretical approach, 
 <xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">Tanaka and Tanimoto (2020)</xref> for presenting a subsidy model, 
 <xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">Kabir et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">Kabir and Tanimoto, 2019</xref> for the vaccination game approach with heterogeneous network and buzz effect, and Alam et al.’s (
 <xref rid="b0205" ref-type="bibr">Kabir et al., 2019c</xref>) vaccination game model for introducing the secondary effect of a vaccine in repeated seasons. Additionally, 
 <xref rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr">Kabir and Tanimoto (2019)</xref> established a mathematical model of SVIR at a local time scale by allowing for the effectiveness of imperfect vaccination, whereas, 
 <xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">Bauch and Bhattacharyya (2012)</xref> and others (
 <xref rid="b0220" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Fu, 2018</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0225" ref-type="bibr">Bauch, 2005</xref>) succeeded in establishing local time evolutionary epidemic models based on the social learning approach. Additionally, 
 <xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr">Kabir and Tanimoto (2019)</xref> studied the theoretical epidemic model by combining both vaccination and a treatment game approach to explain the impact of secondary provisions as a fail-safe effect. Recently, 
 <xref rid="b0235" ref-type="bibr">Arefin et al. (2019)</xref> presented the two-strain with two vaccinations game model by tracking repeated seasons.
</p>
