<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="viruses-10-00200-f006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 6</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Disentangling viral transmission modes: (
   <bold>A</bold>,
   <bold>B</bold>) Simulated data and best model fits for a scenario assuming simultaneous occurrence of both transmission modes given slow diffusion of cell-free virus. Black dots indicate the mean and the 95%-confidence interval of the data obtained from 100 individual simulations runs of the ABM sampled every 24 h. (
   <bold>A</bold>) Lines show the best fits of a model allowing for both transmission modes without (CCF-model, magenta, Equation (
   <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref>)) or with adjusted cell-to-cell transmission dynamics (aCCF-model, green, Equation (
   <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11-viruses-10-00200">11</xref>)) fitted to the number of infected cells; (
   <bold>B</bold>) The observed (black dots) and predicted (solid lines) proportion of cells infected by cell-free (CF) transmission dependent on the best fit shown in panel (
   <bold>A</bold>); (
   <bold>C</bold>) Simulations of a scenario only allowing for CF-transmission with slow viral diffusion (gray) and fast viral diffusion (black). Lines indicate the best fit of the standard model (Equation (
   <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref>) with 
   <inline-formula>
    <math id="mm153">
     <mrow>
      <mrow>
       <msub>
        <mi>β</mi>
        <mi>c</mi>
       </msub>
       <mo>=</mo>
       <mn>0</mn>
      </mrow>
     </mrow>
    </math>
   </inline-formula>) to the data; (
   <bold>D</bold>–
   <bold>F</bold>) Similar scenario as in (
   <bold>A</bold>) with simultaneous occurrence of both transmission modes this time assuming high viral diffusion rates (black, CC/CF trans) and additionally considering a scenario with only CF-transmission (gray, CF trans). Both scenarios are fitted simultaneously. The number of infected cells (
   <bold>D</bold>), as well as the dynamics of the extracellular viral load (
   <bold>E</bold>) are shown. (
   <bold>F</bold>) The observed (black) and predicted proportions of cells infected through CF-transmission in the scenario allowing for both transmission modes. Corresponding parameter estimates for each of the different models are shown in 
   <xref ref-type="table" rid="viruses-10-00200-t003">Table 3</xref>.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="viruses-10-00200-g006" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
