<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In our perspective, the “ideal” nanocarrier for efficient antiviral delivery must take into considerations several key factors namely:
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>Clinical outcome, since patients need safe, effective, targeted, available and affordable therapy, as they are our inspiration;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>From the clinical perspective, the future antiviral candidates should improve the efficacy of the fused/encapsulated drug, reduce the intake frequency and time, restrict adverse side effects and reduce therapy costs;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Design consideration for the nanoplatforms that will allow targeted delivery of the drugs in sustained released manner and improves efficacy, safety and patient convenience; therefore, from a chemist point of view, hybrid nanosystems can gather all the necessary features in terms of composition, shape and size by overcoming limitations of individual systems and offers greater advantages. Starting with the composition, the chosen materials should be biodegradable, biocompatible, and non-toxic, for example polymers are very attractive since they offer the possibility for chemical modifications over the surface or backbone. In addition to these advantages, the second component from the hybrid architecture (in the shape of potential liposomes) should offer besides advanced barrier penetration, higher encapsulation efficiency for the intended drug, which in combination with the polymeric piece will be able to modulate the release kinetics, the stability and prolong drug release. When thinking about the shape, we have in mind targeting capabilities as impact. As we already know, the shape is linked with size and surface charge and density, therefore a complex puzzle that must be solved. The surface charge and density should be carefully chosen during the nanoplatforms design through the surface modification possibility. The ideal candidate here from our perspective is PEG due to its versatility to exhibit various charges, shapes and sizes but also to enhance tolerability, reduce clearance, and lengthen circulation time. The size influences the biodistribution and the uptake rate therefore the “nominee” has to be in the submicron size range, recommended to be under 200 nm.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
