<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Patients diagnosed with chronic pulmonary disease were enrolled to analyze the association between influenza vaccination and the prevention of pneumonia. Our study indicated that patients who received vaccination one year prior to the study had a significantly decreased risk of developing pneumonia. Additionally, patients who received vaccination consecutively for two and three years showed a continuous reduction of their risk of pneumonia. Although the patients who received influenza vaccinations only in the second year did not show any decrease in their risk of developing pneumonia, the data was not statistically significant. Repeated influenza vaccination was demonstrated to be effective for preventing severe and fatal influenza infection in elderly individuals [
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-16-01078" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Our study showed that influenza vaccination can lower the risk of pneumonia in individuals aged ≥ 65. A previous study used health administrative databases to investigate the association between influenza vaccination and the all-cause death of elderly people &gt;65 years. They also concluded that influenza vaccination was associated with reductions in the total hospitalizations for pneumonia and influenza and all-cause mortality during the influenza season [
 <xref rid="B21-ijerph-16-01078" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Moreover, some studies, such as Li et al., confirmed that previous pneumococcal and influenza vaccination in elderly patients reduced the length of hospital stay and reduced the risk of bacteremia [
 <xref rid="B22-ijerph-16-01078" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], which was similar to our study. However, Demirdogen Cetinoglu et al. showed that influenza vaccination did not affect the clinical outcome of hospitalized adult CAP patients. This result may be related to the low influenza vaccination rate in the elderly [
 <xref rid="B23-ijerph-16-01078" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Therefore, further research is needed to analyze this in the future.
</p>
