<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="Tab3">
 <label>Table 3</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Patents on methodologies of different aspects of coronaviruses</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th align="left">Patent no.</th>
    <th align="left">Date</th>
    <th align="left">Basis</th>
    <th align="left">Research/patent title</th>
    <th align="left">Findings</th>
    <th align="left">References</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2016-07-20</td>
    <td align="left">EP3045181A1</td>
    <td align="left">Vaccine</td>
    <td align="left">A novel vaccine against the middle east respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV)</td>
    <td align="left">The invention relates an immunogenic composition comprising the MERS-CoVN nucleocapsid protein and an immunogenic fragment thereof, or a nucleic acid molecule encoding the MERS-CoV N nucleocapsid protein and the immunogenic fragment thereof. Furthermore, the present invention relates to a vector comprising a nucleic acid molecule encoding the MERS-CoV N nucleocapsid protein and an immunogenic fragment thereof, for use as a vaccine as well as a method of inducing a protective immune response against MERS-CoV</td>
    <td align="left">Sutter et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR238">238</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2007-02-15</td>
    <td align="left">JP2007502612A</td>
    <td align="left">Diagnosis, vaccine</td>
    <td align="left">Coronavirus, nucleic acid, protein, and methods for the generation of vaccine, medicaments, and diagnostics</td>
    <td align="left">A new coronavirus, human coronavirus NL63 (HCoV-NL63) is disclosed herein with a tropism that includes humans. Means and methods are provided for diagnosing subjects (previously) infected with the virus. Also offered are among other vaccines, medicaments, nucleic acids, and specific binding members</td>
    <td align="left">Van Der Hoek [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR227">227</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2012-07-05</td>
    <td align="left">ES2384445T3</td>
    <td align="left">Vaccine</td>
    <td align="left">Spike protein of canine respiratory coronavirus (crcv), polymerase, and hemaglutinin/esterase</td>
    <td align="left">A vaccine composition for vaccinating dogs, the composition comprising: a canine respiratory coronavirus (CRCV) containing a Spike (S) protein having a list of amino acid sequence, or a coronaviral S protein having at least 97% amino acid identity with the amino acid sequence, or an immunogenic fragment of Figure 4 of at least 200 amino acids in length, or a nucleic acid encoding said coronaviral S protein or said immunogenic fragment</td>
    <td align="left">Brownlie et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR239">239</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2017-10-12</td>
    <td align="left">WO2017176596A1</td>
    <td align="left">Vaccine</td>
    <td align="left">Multivalent vaccines for rabies virus and coronaviruses</td>
    <td align="left">The present disclosure provides methods and compositions for inducing an immune response that confers dual protection against infections by either or both of a rabies virus and a coronavirus, and which can be used therapeutically for an existing infection with the rabies virus and a coronavirus to treat at least one symptom thereof and to neutralize or clear the infecting agents. In particular, the present disclosure provides a recombinant rabies virus vector comprising a nucleotide sequence encoding at least one coronavirus immunogenic glycoprotein fragment, as well as pharmaceutical compositions comprising the vaccine vectors</td>
    <td align="left">Johnson et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR237">237</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2017-12-28</td>
    <td align="left">WO2017222935A1</td>
    <td align="left">Treatment and control</td>
    <td align="left">Small molecule therapeutic inhibitors against picornaviruses, caliciviruses, and coronaviruses</td>
    <td align="left">Antiviral protease inhibitors are disclosed, along with related antiviral dipeptidyl compounds, macrocyclic derivatives thereof, and methods of using the same to treat or prevent viral infection and disease from coronaviruses, caliciviruses, and picornaviruses</td>
    <td align="left">Chang et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR261">261</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2018-05-22</td>
    <td align="left">S9975885B2</td>
    <td align="left">Treatment and control</td>
    <td align="left">Broad-spectrum non-covalent coronavirus protease inhibitors</td>
    <td align="left">This invention pertains to materials and methods for the treatment of patients with coronavirus infection and the control of zoonotic disease outbreaks using broad-spectrum non-covalent coronavirus protease inhibitors</td>
    <td align="left">Emma et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR231">231</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2017-08-03</td>
    <td align="left">WO2017129975A1</td>
    <td align="left">Vaccine</td>
    <td align="left">Attenuated infectious bronchitis virus</td>
    <td align="left">The present invention provides a live, attenuated coronavirus comprising a mutation in non-structural protein nsp-3 and deletion of accessory proteins 3a and 3b. The coronavirus may be used as a vaccine for treating and preventing disease, such as infectious bronchitis, in a subject</td>
    <td align="left">Bickerton et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR262">262</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2019-12-05</td>
    <td align="left">JP2019206573A</td>
    <td align="left">Immunity boosters</td>
    <td align="left">Immunomodulation methods and compositions</td>
    <td align="left">Methods and compositions for immunomodulation are provided. Cells containing exogenous antigens and uses thereof are produced. The present invention includes, for example, a way of inducing immune tolerance, comprising enucleated hematopoietic cells that express an exogenous antigen to a human subject suffering from or at risk of developing an autoimmune disease, disorder or condition Administering a pharmaceutical composition, wherein the pharmaceutical composition is administered in an amount effective to induce immune tolerance in the subject against the antigen that mediates the autoimmune disease, disorder or condition</td>
    <td align="left">Jordi et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR234">234</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2020-01-02</td>
    <td align="left">US20200002370A1</td>
    <td align="left">Treatment, adjuvants</td>
    <td align="left">Novel compounds</td>
    <td align="left">The invention also relates to the use of said compounds, combinations, compositions and medicaments, in the treatment of diseases in which modulation of STING (Stimulator of Interferon Genes) is beneficial, for example, inflammation, allergic and autoimmune diseases, infectious diseases, cancer, pre-cancerous syndromes and as vaccine adjuvants</td>
    <td align="left">Adams and Lian [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR235">235</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2019-11-14</td>
    <td align="left">US20190343862A1</td>
    <td align="left">Immunomodulators</td>
    <td align="left">Delivery of RNA to trigger multiple immune pathways</td>
    <td align="left">RNA encoding an immunogen is co-delivered to non-immune cells at the site of delivery and also to immune cells, which infiltrate the site of delivery. The responses of these two cell types to the same delivered RNA lead to two different effects, which interact to produce a robust immune response against the immunogen. The non-immune cells translate the RNA and express the immunogen. Infiltrating immune cells respond to the RNA by expressing type I interferons and pro-inflammatory cytokines, which produce a local adjuvant effect that acts on the immunogen-expressing non-immune cells to upregulate major histocompatibility complex expression, thereby increasing presentation of the translated protein to T cells. The effects on the immune and non-immune cells can be achieved by a single delivery of a single RNA, e.g., by a single injection</td>
    <td align="left">Geall et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR263">263</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2018-12-18</td>
    <td align="left">US10154985B2</td>
    <td align="left">Treatment</td>
    <td align="left">Method for treating a glycoprotein-related disease</td>
    <td align="left">A method for treating a glycoprotein-related disease is disclosed, which comprises: administering a first effective amount of phenol red and a second effective amount of an organic arsenic compound to a subject in need thereo</td>
    <td align="left">Lu [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR264">264</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2016-11-24</td>
    <td align="left">US20160339097A1</td>
    <td align="left">Recombinant vaccine proteins</td>
    <td align="left">Coronavirus proteins and antigens</td>
    <td align="left">Disclosed herein are embodiments of a method for collecting, extracting, or eluting proteins and antigens from cells infected with the coronavirus. The coronavirus maybe a porcine coronavirus, such as porcine epidemic diarrhoea virus (PEDV) or porcine delta coronavirus (PDCoV). Also disclosed are embodiments of a composition comprising the coronavirus proteins and antigens, and embodiments of a method of using such a composition. Applications for the composition include, but are not limited to, use in the preparation of antibodies against the proteins and antigens, use as reference markers for coronavirus proteins, and use in an immunogenic composition, such as in a vaccine composition</td>
    <td align="left">Kim [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR265">265</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2017-01-19</td>
    <td align="left">WO2017010835A1</td>
    <td align="left">Drug/treatment</td>
    <td align="left">Use of radotinib for prevention or treatment of viral respiratory disease</td>
    <td align="left">The present invention relates to a new use of a compound of Chemical Formula 1 (radotinib) in the prevention or treatment of viral respiratory disease. According to the present invention, a compound of Chemical Formula 1 or a pharmaceutically acceptable salt thereof can be used for the prevention, alleviation, or treatment of coronavirus infection. Specifically, the present invention can be used as a useful antiviral agent for the prevention or treatment of disease caused by infection of the Middle East respiratory syndrome-coronavirus (MERS-CoV).</td>
    <td align="left">Kim et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR232">232</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2016-06-15</td>
    <td align="left">CN105671209A</td>
    <td align="left">Diagnosis</td>
    <td align="left">Primers, probe, kit, and method for detecting bovine coronavirus</td>
    <td align="left">The invention discloses primers, a probe, a kit and a method for detecting bovine coronavirus. The method comprises the following steps: by using cDNA (complementary deoxyribonucleic acid) obtained by carrying out RNA (ribonucleic acid) reverse transcription on the detected sample as a template, carrying out fluorescent quantitative PCR (polymerase chain reaction) amplification, and comparing the amplification curve CT value. The quantitative PCR primers are designed at the bovine coronavirus conserved gene (N gene), and a probe process is adopted to establish a fluorescent quantitative PCR method. The primers, probe, kit, and method are practical and straightforward to operate, have the advantages of high specificity, high sensitivity, and favourable repetitiveness, and are suitable for the demands for quick and accurate detection of modernized cultivation farms</td>
    <td align="left">Wei et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR229">229</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2016-06-1</td>
    <td align="left">CN105671006A</td>
    <td align="left">Diagnosis and treatment</td>
    <td align="left">High-efficiency ranilla luciferase gene expression recombinant HCoV-OC43 (human coronavirus OC43) virus and application thereof</td>
    <td align="left">The invention discloses a high-efficiency ranilla luciferase gene expression recombinant human coronavirus OC43 virus and application thereof to a screening of antiviral medicines. By an overlap PCR (polymerase chain reaction) method, a ranilla luciferase gene is replaced or inserted into accessory genes (ns2 and ns12.9) to be cloned into human coronavirus OC43 full-length infectious clone pBAC-OC43FL, and four ranilla luciferase gene expression recombinant viruses, including rOC43-ns2DelRluc, rOC43-ns2FusionRluc, rOC43-ns12.9StopRluc, and rOC43-ns12.9FusionRluc, are obtained respectively. The virus rOC43-ns2DelRluc is efficient in ranilla luciferase gene expression and similar to a parent virus HCoV-OC43-WT in the virus growth curve, the inserted reporter gene is stable in a serial passage process, and the virus rOC43-ns2DelRluc can be successfully applied to antiviral medicine screening experiments and has an extensive application prospect in high-throughput screening of anti-coronavirus medicines and host antiviral genes</td>
    <td align="left">Shenliang, [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR228">228</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2016-08-10</td>
    <td align="left">CN105837487A</td>
    <td align="left">Prevention /treatment</td>
    <td align="left">Small-molecule inhibitor against MERS-CoV main protease, and preparation method and application thereof</td>
    <td align="left">The invention provides a small-molecule inhibitor against MERS-CoV main protease. The small-molecule inhibitor is designed on the basis of the crystal structure of the main protease of the novel coronavirus MERS-CoV. The invention also provides a synthetic method for the small-molecule inhibitor and application of the small-molecule inhibitor in the preparation of drugs used for preventing and treating MERS-CoV infections. The small-molecule inhibitor against MERS-CoV main protease can substantially inhibit the activity of the main protease of the MERS coronavirus, has an excellent inhibitory activity to the main protease of coronaviruses like SARS and MHV, and presents good application prospects in preparation of drugs used for preventing or treating coronavirus infection</td>
    <td align="left">Rao et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR266">266</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2016-09-01</td>
    <td align="left">WO2016138160A1</td>
    <td align="left">Recombinant peptides/antibodies treatment</td>
    <td align="left">Middle east respiratory syndrome coronavirus immunogens, antibodies, and their use</td>
    <td align="left">Methods of inducing an immune response in a subject to the Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) are provided. In several embodiments, the immune response is a protective immune response that inhibits or prevents MERS-CoV infection in the subject. Recombinant MERS-CoV polypeptides and nucleic acid molecules encoding the same are also provided. Additionally, neutralizing antibodies that specifically bind to MERS-CoV S protein and antigen-binding fragments thereof are disclosed. The antibodies and antigen-binding fragments are useful, for example, in methods of detecting MERS-CoV S protein in a sample or in a subject, as well as methods of preventing and treating a MERS-CoV infection in a subject</td>
    <td align="left">Graham et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR267">267</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2016-06-01</td>
    <td align="left">CN105624122A</td>
    <td align="left">Mutant virus as a vaccine</td>
    <td align="left">Avian infectious bronchitis virus natural mutant</td>
    <td align="left">The invention relates to the field of virology. It aims to provide an avian infectious bronchitis virus natural mutant, kept in China General Microbiological Culture Collection Center, named infectious bronchitis virus, and collected under CGMCC No. 11491. A genome of this mutant is 27, 541 lbp in length, a complete genome sequence of the mutant is as shown in SEQ ID NO: 1, with structural characteristics of a typical IBV genome coding structure. This mutant having special genes inserted in and provided by the invention can break the immunity protection of vaccines to breed in an organism, this mutant can proliferate in susceptible chickens without causing significant pathogenicity to sensitive chickens, and thus this mutant can serve as the base material for the further study on mutation mechanism of an attenuated vaccine or IBV virus strain</td>
    <td align="left">Liao et al. 2016[
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR268">268</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2017-08-08</td>
    <td align="left">CN107022008A</td>
    <td align="left">Prevention and treatment</td>
    <td align="left">Suppress polypeptide and its application of human coronavirus’s infection broad spectrum</td>
    <td align="left">The invention belongs to the biomedicine field. It is related to the polypeptide for suppressing human coronavirus infection, and in particular, to polypeptide and its application of human coronary virus’s disease can be contained a broad spectrum. The S2 regions based on coronavirus S protein of the invention are more conservative, and features of similar syncretizing mechanisms provide can be to the polypeptide of the infection with broad-spectrum inhibitory action of two or more human coronary virus. The present invention is the results showed obtain “general character” of the human coronavirus, the identical syncretizing mechanism in, i.e., similar HR regions and its mediation, and provide the serial polypeptides of HCoV-EK as the point of penetration, the polypeptide not only has preferable inhibition to some currently a popular human coronaviruses, and equally has an excellent inhibitory activity to the class SARS virus (RsSHC014-CoV or RsW1V1-CoV) for being possible to infect the humankind. The present invention can provide the drug candidate for prevention and treatment for the novel human coronavirus for being still possible to outburst in popular human coronavirus and future at present</td>
    <td align="left">Shibo et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR269">269</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2018-02-13</td>
    <td align="left">US9889194B</td>
    <td align="left">Immunogenic proteins</td>
    <td align="left">Immunogenic composition for MERS coronavirus infection</td>
    <td align="left">Described herein are immunogenic compositions for preventing infection with Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) wherein the immunogenic compositions comprise at least a portion of the MERS-CoV S protein and an immunopotentiator</td>
    <td align="left">Jiang et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR270">270</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2019-11-21</td>
    <td align="left">US20190351049A1</td>
    <td align="left">Spike protein</td>
    <td align="left">Human Antibodies to Middle East Respiratory Syndrome - Coronavirus Spike Protein</td>
    <td align="left">The present invention provides monoclonal antibodies that bind to the Middle East Respiratory Syndrome—Coronavirus (MERS-CoV) spike protein and methods of use. In various embodiments of the invention, the antibodies are fully human antibodies that bind to MERS-CoV spike protein. In some embodiments, the antibodies of the invention are useful for inhibiting or neutralizing MERS-CoV activity, thus providing a means of treating or preventing MERS infection in humans. In some embodiments, the invention provides for a combination of one or more antibodies that bind to the MERS-CoV spike protein for use in treating MERS infection. In certain embodiments, the one or more antibodies bind to distinct non-competing epitopes comprised in the receptor-binding domain of the MERS-CoV spike protein</td>
    <td align="left">Kyratsous et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR271">271</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2019-12-05</td>
    <td align="left">US20190365925A1</td>
    <td align="left">Antigen targets</td>
    <td align="left">AAV vectors targeted to the central nervous syste</td>
    <td align="left">The invention relates to chimeric AAV capsids targeted to the central nervous system, virus vectors comprising the same, and methods of using the vectors to target the central nervous system. The invention further relates to chimeric AAV capsids targeted to oligodendrocytes, virus vectors comprising the same, and methods of using the vectors to target oligodendrocytes</td>
    <td align="left">Gray and McCown, [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR272">272</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2019-09-05</td>
    <td align="left">JP2019146588A</td>
    <td align="left">Vaccine</td>
    <td align="left">Priming of an immune response</td>
    <td align="left">The present invention provides a method for expanding and improving immune response and, at the same time, increasing the speed of response against a pathogenic antigen or a cancer antigen. A two-step prime-boost method whereby the immune system is first primed with a nucleic acid construct comprising an invariant chain or a variant thereof, followed by a booster vaccine using any type of suitable vaccine Administration) to sufficiently stimulate the immune response generated by vaccine administration</td>
    <td align="left">Thomsen et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR273">273</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2019-10-17</td>
    <td align="left">US20190314497A1</td>
    <td align="left">Treatment</td>
    <td align="left">Compositions and methods for treating viral infections through stimulated innate immunity in combination with antiviral compounds</td>
    <td align="left">Embodiments are directed to compositions and methods for treating viral infections</td>
    <td align="left">Dickey et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR274">274</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2019-03-12</td>
    <td align="left">US10226434B2</td>
    <td align="left">Treatment</td>
    <td align="left">Design, synthesis, and methods of use of acyclic fleximer nucleoside analogues having anti-coronavirus activity</td>
    <td align="left">The present invention is directed to compounds, techniques, and compositions for treating or preventing viral infections using nucleosides analogues. Specifically, the present invention provides for the design and synthesis of acyclic fleximer nucleoside analogues, having increased flexibility and ability to alter their conformation structures to provide increased antiviral activity potential with the result of inhibiting several coronaviruses</td>
    <td align="left">Radtke et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR275">275</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2020-02-04</td>
    <td align="left">US10548971B2</td>
    <td align="left">Vaccine</td>
    <td align="left">MERS-CoV vaccine</td>
    <td align="left">Disclosed herein is a vaccine comprising a Middle East Respiratory Syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) antigen. The antigen can be a consensus antigen. The consensus antigen can be a consensus spike antigen. Also disclosed herein is a method of treating a subject in need thereof by administering the vaccine to the topic</td>
    <td align="left">Weineret al. 2020[
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR276">276</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2019-05-08</td>
    <td align="left">Publication of JP6508605B2</td>
    <td align="left">Vaccine</td>
    <td align="left">Modular DNA binding domain and method of use</td>
    <td align="left">The present invention provides a method of selectively recognizing base pairs in a target DNA sequence by a polypeptide, a modified polypeptide that recognizes explicitly one or more base pairs within a target DNA sequence, and a DNA that is modified so that it can be recognized explicitly by the polypeptide, and specific use of polypeptides and DNA in NA targeting and methods of modulating the expression of target genes in cells</td>
    <td align="left">Bonas et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR277">277</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2019-09-10</td>
    <td align="left">US10406229B2</td>
    <td align="left">Vaccine</td>
    <td align="left">Methods and compositions related to inhibition of viral entry</td>
    <td align="left">Disclosed herein are compositions and arrangements for inhibiting viral entry</td>
    <td align="left">Francis et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR278">278</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2018-12-20</td>
    <td align="left">AU2015340134B2</td>
    <td align="left">Antigenic gene identification</td>
    <td align="left">Microfluidic device for detecting target gene, the method for manufacturing same, and method for detecting using same</td>
    <td align="left">The present invention provides a target gene capable of being differentiated by the naked eye by amplifying the target gene to selectively block the fluid path and, specifically, a microfluidic device for detecting pathogen genes, and a detection method using the same. Therefore, the present invention can conveniently identify a single target gene, such as a single pathogen, or at the same time, several target genes, such as several pathogens, without complicated mechanical devices</td>
    <td align="left">Jung et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR279">279</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2018-01-30</td>
    <td align="left">US9878024B2</td>
    <td align="left">Enhanced immune response</td>
    <td align="left">Methods and compositions using Listeria for enhancing immunogenicity by prime-boost</td>
    <td align="left">Provided herein are prime-boost regimens and materials used therein. The prime-boost regimens enhance the immune response to a target antigen. The vaccines used for boost are comprised of recombinant attenuated metabolically active 
     <italic>Listeria</italic> that encodes an expressible antigen that is cross-reactive with the target antigen. In some examples, the immune response is a cellular immune response
    </td>
    <td align="left">Dubensky et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR280">280</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2017-08-0</td>
    <td align="left">US9719107B2</td>
    <td align="left">Recombinant gene and protein expression</td>
    <td align="left">Construction of fully-deleted adenovirus-based gene delivery vectors and uses thereof</td>
    <td align="left">The embodiments disclosed herein relate to the construction of fully-deleted Adenovirus-based gene delivery vectors packaged without helper Adenovirus, and more particularly to their use in gene therapy for gene and protein expression, vaccine development, and immunosuppressive therapy for allogeneic transplantation. In an embodiment, a method for propagating an adenoviral vector includes (a) providing an Adenovirus packaging cell line; (b) transfecting a fully-deleted Adenoviral vector construct into the cell line; and optionally (c) transfecting a packaging construct into the cell line, wherein the fully-deleted Adenoviral vector construct and optionally the packaging construct can transfect the Adenovirus packaging cell line resulting in the encapsidation of a fully-deleted Adenoviral vector independent of helper Adenovirus. In an embodiment, a target cell is transduced with the encapsidated fully-deleted Adenoviral vector for treating a condition, disease, or disorder</td>
    <td align="left">Brennan et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR281">281</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2019-06-04</td>
    <td align="left">US10307439B2</td>
    <td align="left">Drug treatment</td>
    <td align="left">Substituted nucleosides, nucleotides and analogues thereof</td>
    <td align="left">Disclosed herein are nucleosides, nucleotides and nucleotide analogues, methods of synthesizing the same and methods of treating diseases and conditions such as a Coronaviridae virus, a Togaviridae virus, a Hepeviridae virus and a Bunyaviridae virus infection with one or more nucleosides, nucleotides and nucleotide analogue</td>
    <td align="left">Blatt et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR282">282</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2008-05-22</td>
    <td align="left">WO2007062656A3</td>
    <td align="left">Vaccine</td>
    <td align="left">A nucleotide vaccine</td>
    <td align="left">The present invention relates to a vaccine comprising a nucleic acid construct such as a DNA construct, primarily a nucleic acid construct containing sequences encoding invariant chain operatively linked to antigenic protein or peptide encoding sequences. The vaccine stimulates an immune response, especially an immune response in an MHC-I dependent, but CD4+ T-cell independent manner</td>
    <td align="left">Holst et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR283">283</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2018-01-23</td>
    <td align="left">US9872900B</td>
    <td align="left">Vaccine</td>
    <td align="left">Nucleic acid vaccines</td>
    <td align="left">The invention relates to compositions and methods for the preparation, manufacture, and therapeutic use of ribonucleic acid vaccines (NAVs) comprising polynucleotide molecules encoding one or more antigens</td>
    <td align="left">Ciaramella et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR284">284</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2019-05-14</td>
    <td align="left">US10286065B2</td>
    <td align="left">Treatment and immune modulators</td>
    <td align="left">Compositions and methods for treating viral infections through stimulated innate immunity in combination with antiviral compounds</td>
    <td align="left">Embodiments are directed to compositions and methods for treating viral infections</td>
    <td align="left">Dickey et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR285">285</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2019-10-09</td>
    <td align="left">EP3194423B1</td>
    <td align="left">Treatment antiviral</td>
    <td align="left">Method for preparing a vaccine antigen, resulting ina vaccine antigen and uses</td>
    <td align="left">The present invention relates to a method for making a vaccine antigen comprising a membrane protein, as well as a vaccine antigen and a vaccine, and uses thereof</td>
    <td align="left">Rosa-Calatrava et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR286">286</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2018-11-20</td>
    <td align="left">US10130701B2</td>
    <td align="left">Treatment/vaccine</td>
    <td align="left">Coronaviru</td>
    <td align="left">The present invention provides a live, attenuated coronavirus comprising a variant replicase gene encoding polyproteins consisting of a mutation in one or more of non-structural protein(s) (nsp)-10, nsp-14, nsp-15 or nsp-16. The coronavirus may be used as a vaccine for treating and preventing disease, such as infectious bronchitis, in a subject</td>
    <td align="left">Bickerton et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR287">287</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
