<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza A viruses (IAVs) are enveloped, segmented, and negative-sense RNA viruses of the family 
 <italic>Orthomyxoviridae</italic> [
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. IAVs have a broad host range and can infect birds, humans, and other mammals, including swine, canine, feline, and horses, among others [
 <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. IAVs can be classified into different subtypes based on the antigenicity of the two major surface glycoproteins, haemagglutinin (HA) and neuraminidase (NA) [
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Currently, 16 HA (H1–H16) and nine NA (N1–N9) subtypes have been identified in wild aquatic birds [
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], and another two HA and NA subtypes (H17, H18 and N10, N11) have been identified in bats [
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, only three subtypes (H1N1, H2N2, and H3N2) are known to have established sustained human infections and circulate widely in humans. Of these three subtypes, H1N1 and H3N2 are currently responsible for causing seasonal influenza virus epidemics [
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In addition to these three subtypes, many other IAV subtypes have been reported to cross the species barrier to infect humans, including H5N1, H5N6, H7N9, and H7N4 [
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8–11</xref>]. In December 2013, China reported the first human infection with a H10N8 avian influenza virus in Jiangxi Province, with two of the three infections resulting in death [
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], raising concerns regarding the effects of H10N8 influenza viruses on public health. In China, H10N8 influenza viruses were previously isolated from the environment of Dongting Lake in Hunan Province in 2007 [
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and from a duck in a live poultry market (LPM) in Guangdong Province in 2012 [
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], but it was unknown at that time if these strains could infect humans or other mammals. Several studies subsequently confirmed that the human H10N8 influenza virus originated from chickens in LPMs [
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Additionally, a specific antibody for H10N8 influenza virus was detected in sera samples collected from animal workers and feral dogs at LPMs in Guangdong Province before the first H10N8 infection cases were recognized [
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Interspecies transmission of avian influenza viruses to humans and other mammals has been consistently reported in the last two decades. Swine are susceptible to infection with both human and avian influenza viruses. Influenza virus may undergo reassortment to generate novel reassorted viruses in swine [
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]; thus, swine are considered as “mixing vessels” in influenza ecology. Considering this important role, we conducted serological monitoring to detect H10N8 infection in swine herds. Eight serum samples were positive for H10N8 influenza virus based on hemagglutination inhibition (HI) and microneutralization (MN) assays during serological surveys in 2016–2017 in southern China. However, the pathogenicity and transmissibility of H10N8 influenza virus in swine remains unknown. Based on serological evidence, pathogenicity and transmission analyses of H10N8 influenza virus in swine were conducted in this study, which will be helpful for preventing future H10N8 infections and provide new perspectives regarding the transmission of H10N8 influenza virus.
</p>
