<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are currently no specific antiviral agents or vaccines for chikungunya virus.
 <xref rid="rmv1978-bib-0136" ref-type="ref">136</xref> Various in vitro compounds active against chikungunya virus have been reported, including both direct‐acting and host‐targeting antivirals; however, most of these compounds have yet to find their way into in vivo models and clinical trials.
 <xref rid="rmv1978-bib-0137" ref-type="ref">137</xref> Two of the few that have been tested clinically, chloroquine and ribavirin, are already widely used in the treatment of other diseases and have a known safety profile. However, chloroquine was found not to have any benefit for arthritic chikungunya when compared with a nonsteroidal anti‐inflammatory drug in a randomised clinical trial.
 <xref rid="rmv1978-bib-0138" ref-type="ref">138</xref> Ribavirin, on the other hand, had promising results in a small case series of 10 patients with severe arthritis post–chikungunya infection.
 <xref rid="rmv1978-bib-0139" ref-type="ref">139</xref> To the best of our knowledge, no antiviral has been evaluated in the management of chikungunya‐associated neurological disease, which therefore remains the same as that of neurological disease without associated chikungunya infection: for patients with encephalitis, those with a reduced Glasgow coma score (GCS) require assessment by intensive care specialists and may need intubation, ventilatory support, correction of electrolyte abnormalities, management of raised intracranial pressure, and enhancement of cerebral perfusion pressure.
 <xref rid="rmv1978-bib-0140" ref-type="ref">140</xref> In patients with myelitis, corticosteroids are the standard first‐line treatment, despite the lack of trial evidence for their use in this scenario.
 <xref rid="rmv1978-bib-0141" ref-type="ref">141</xref> The management of GBS focuses on immunotherapy with intravenous immunoglobulin or plasma exchange, and ventilatory support if the innervation of respiratory muscles is affected.
 <xref rid="rmv1978-bib-0109" ref-type="ref">109</xref>
</p>
