<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The breadth of the 2015–2017 ZIKV outbreak was unprecedented in the amount of information that became available very quickly. Currently, there are over 5000 publications on “Zika virus” indexed in PubMed, compared to 55 indexed as of 2010. Of these publications, a large number has explored the vector competence of various populations of potential vector mosquitoes to multiple strains of ZIKV using various experimental approaches. Collectively, these efforts are best summarized by the finding that susceptibility to infection, and ability to transmit ZIKV varies widely across disparate geographic strains of several mosquito species, and disparate strains of ZIKV also vary greatly in their ability to be transmitted [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Similar findings have been widely accepted with respect to vector competence of multiple arboviruses [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Despite this typical variability, the principal ZIKV vector, 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti,</italic> has often proved relatively refractory to infection, especially in the context of viral titers representative of human viremias [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. However, drawing overarching conclusions from this vast accumulation of data is difficult, largely due to disparities in the methodologies that have been used to assess vector competence, precluding meta-analyses. To address this problem, there have been various calls for the standardization of techniques, reporting, and methodologies in laboratory arthropod infection studies. As a first step to this end, we examine here the methodologies, techniques, and considerations intrinsic to vector competence analyses, utilizing the body of ZIKV literature as an example, and making comparisons with previously published work on other mosquito-borne arboviruses.
</p>
