<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Viral genetic diversity is important for the survival of the viral population as a whole in the presence of selective pressures favoring mutations that yield beneficial phenotypes. These mutants are expected to survive and act as founders for the next generation. However, high mutation rates are also observed in RNA viruses that infect bacteria and thus do not face an adaptive immune response, suggesting that the high mutation rate of RNA viruses cannot completely be ascribed to a specific life history (Belshaw et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2008</xref>). Similarly, it has been provocatively proposed that HIV-1 variation (a paradigm of viral diversity) is essentially the result of “its lifestyle rather than a perverse predilection for error” (Wain-Hobson 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130">1996</xref>). Although the HIV-1 mutation rate is an order of magnitude lower than that of influenza A virus, the extent of variation encountered during the 5- to 10-year course of a single individual HIV-1 infection is greater than the 1-year global genetic drift of influenza A (Korber et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2001</xref>). This enormous genetic diversification of HIV-1 has inevitably led to a search for links between HIV-1 variation and pathogenesis. It has been suggested that following infection, de novo generation of variants is necessary for the onset of AIDS (Nowak et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">1991</xref>; Nowak and McMichael 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">1995</xref>). Genetic diversity in the HIV-1 envelope from typical patients and infected children has been correlated with disease stages (Ganeshan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">1997</xref>; Shankarappa et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">1999</xref>). HIV-1 can use two chemokine receptors, CCR5 and CXCR4, as coreceptors for viral entry, and uses the CCR5 coreceptor in approximately 90% of primary infections. However, a substantial proportion of individuals develop viruses that use the CXCR4 co-receptor, which is associated with an accelerated T CD4+ cell decline and a more rapid progression to AIDS (Koot et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1993</xref>). Cytotoxic T lymphocytes (CTLs) that kill infected target cells play an important role in the control of HIV-1 during the acute and chronic phases of an HIV-1 infection (Ogg et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">1998</xref>). The most documented CTL-escape mechanism is acquisition of amino acid substitutions within the CTL epitope and/or its flanking regions. These changes reduce the ability of viral peptide to bind to HLA class I molecules, and lead to impaired T-cell receptor recognition, and defective epitope generation (Ogg et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">1998</xref>). A small number of people demonstrate sustained ability to control HIV-1 replication without therapy. Such individuals, referred to as HIV controllers, typically maintain stable CD4+ cell counts, do not develop clinical disease, and are less likely to transmit HIV to others (Deeks and Walker 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2007</xref>). Genome-wide association analysis in a multiethnic cohort of HIV-1 controllers and progressors has demonstrated that the nature of the HLA-viral peptide interaction is the major factor modulating durable control of HIV infection (Pereyra et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">2010</xref>). Viral fitness cost precludes the emergence of variants within the CTL epitopes recognized by controllers’ HLAs, indicating that variation allows evasion of immune surveillance and therefore contributes to pathogenesis (Phillips et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">1991</xref>).
</p>
