<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Remdesivir, lopinavir/ritonavir, CQ, and azithromycin have shown to be effective in inhibiting SARS-CoV-2 replication 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>. However, the efficacy diminishes when symptomatic patients are treated 1 week after the disease's onset. At this point, the patient may have already transitioned from viral expansion to the inflammatory phase leading to a cytokine storm (
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>). For instance, during influenza infection, the viral shedding phase peaks 2–3 days after infection (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>). A meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials of oseltamivir (Tamiflu) indicates that early treatment of the infection accelerated clinical symptom alleviation and reduced the risks of lower respiratory tract complications, suggesting that antiviral drug treatments have to be timed appropriately (
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>). Antiviral drug monotherapy might not be sufficient for severe patients with COVID-19, and supplementation with anti-inflammatory drugs would be necessary as a combination therapy (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>). Sanofi and Regeneron have announced a Phase 2/3 trial of interleukin-6 (IL-6) inhibitor sarilumab (Kevzara) to ameliorate tissue damage in the lung caused by a “cytokine storm” in patients with COVID-19 infection (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clinicalTrials.gov" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">clinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>, NCT 04315298) and Swedish Orphan Biovitrum (SOBI) also started Anakinra (IL-1 receptor antagonist) and Emapalumab (Anti-IFN-γ monoclonal antibody) Phase 2/3 trials to test their efficacy to reduce hyper-inflammation and respiratory distress in patients with COVID-19 infection (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clinicalTrials.gov" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">clinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>, NCT 04324021). Overall, there are more clinical research trials to be made before any of these drugs become available to the public.
</p>
