<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0155">This paper describes the activities undertaken by Working Group 3 on Vaccine Development. The group created a visual process mapping tool to better understand the potentially rate-limiting bottlenecks associated in moving a vaccine candidate from discovery through to development and early Phase clinical trials; then into clinical manufacture and Phase 3 trials. The primary purpose of the tool was to act as a visual aid for early discovery and development scientists, highlighting the major steps required to fully develop any experimental vaccine. The secondary, and crucial purpose of the tool, was to identify any generic bottlenecks that may slow down development. Identifying such strategic limitations may identify corrective actions, that may in turn help to overcome potential delays or setbacks when expediting vaccine development during epidemics. Actions could be taken by policy makers to correct for limitations in regulation, funders to identify limits in scientific knowledge that could be corrected with appropriate investment, and for government and trans-national organisations to consider local and global response. Though the genesis of this tool was considered in the context of epidemic preparedness, the tool itself is sufficiently far-reaching that it can be utilized by the wider vaccine community. Considering the global nature of vaccines, it is important to understand the interdependencies that exist between discovery, development and manufacture. This tool gives scientists vision of the considerations that will need to be made along the development process. In taking a much more holistic approach to vaccine development it is hoped that this can support other international such as the Global Vaccine Action Plan 
 <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, which relies on the continued supply of vaccines to meet immunization targets. Thus, the tool serves multiple users and purposes, and we report on its main findings in this paper.
</p>
