<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Animal models can be validated for a particular disease according to a number of different criteria, which include “face” and “predictive” validity. For face validity there must be similarities in the pathology and clinical symptoms between the animal model and the human disease (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). As discussed above, NiV infection of pigs causes a similar respiratory and neurological syndrome as seen in human infections. Although, disease severity in pigs may be considered lower than in humans. The predictive validity of a model means that clinically effective interventions demonstrate a similar effect in the animal model (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). No clinical trials of NiV vaccine candidates have been reported to compare with vaccine performance in animal models, including the pig. As noted above, the success of the Equivac® HeV vaccine in horses and other animal models was not replicated in swine (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), highlighting a potential issue of predicative validity when comparing NiV vaccines between animal species, which may extend to humans. On the other hand, pigs have been used successfully as models to study many human infectious diseases (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>–
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>), including NiV infection (
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>). There is also a growing appreciation that pigs provide a superior animal model for influenza A virus infection and immunity and should play a more prominent role as a model for human influenza vaccine development (
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>). The success of the pig as an experimental animal model is partly due to their similarities with humans in terms of anatomy, immunology, and physiology, but also due to their manageable behavior and size, and by the general ethical acceptance of using pigs for experimental purposes instead of non-human primates (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>).
</p>
