<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A more pessimistic view is that the reservoir of unknown forest viruses, not presently affecting humans, but potentially transmissible to domestic animals and humans, is immense in Asia, Central and South America, and Africa. More than 500 arboviruses have so far been identified and described, but this is only the tip of the iceberg. From about 1930–1980, the Rockefeller Foundation sponsored a repository for viruses from field-collected arthropods, primarily mosquitoes, that reached more than 4000 isolates of insect-specific viruses or arboviruses, the vast majority of which are undescribed [
 <xref rid="B51-pathogens-09-00265" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], and even this collection is far from complete. Consequently, several non-exclusive scenarios for the emergence of new human viral epidemics are possible:
 <list list-type="simple">
  <list-item>
   <label>(1)</label>
   <p>Via primate-biting bridge vectors such as 
    <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> from forest edges in South America, Africa and Asia, forest 
    <italic>Aedes</italic> of the Albopictus group in South East Asia, 
    <italic>Haemagogus</italic> in South America, 
    <italic>Stegomyia</italic> from forest galleries in Africa. In South America, 
    <italic>Haemagogus</italic> and 
    <italic>Sabethes</italic> are likely to transmit any new potential human viruses among primates and, as displayed by yellow fever, if these viruses are capable of transitioning to transmission in human habitats, it is likely to have already occurred.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(2)</label>
   <p>By misfortune, as happened with the establishment of a sylvan cycle of yellow fever in Central and South America 500 years ago, new viruses may appear in transmission cycles that are heretofore unknown. The increase in trade and travel, and the establishment of invasive species (such as 
    <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>, 
    <italic>Ae. koreicus</italic>, and 
    <italic>Ae. japonicus</italic>, and even 
    <italic>Ae</italic>. 
    <italic>aegypti</italic> in Europe) suggest that this risk should not be overlooked.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(3)</label>
   <p>Via increased human contacts with wild cycles due to deforestation and irrational forest exploitation. These ecological modifications favour the emergence of viruses from forest edges, and then to the human environment.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(4)</label>
   <p>Via zoonotic cycles. For example, many viruses (West Nile, Japanese encephalitis, St Louis encephalitis virus, Murray valley, usutu) which are bird viruses, can be transmitted from birds (or mammals such as pigs) to humans, via vectors taking blood meals from both birds and humans, such as 
    <italic>Cx. tritaeniorhynchus</italic> or 
    <italic>Cx. pipiens</italic>, 
    <italic>Cx. quinquefasciatus.</italic> It is very likely that some of these viruses, presently confined to wild cycles, will emerge in the coming years somewhere in the world, as a result of socio-ecological changes. Their shift from endemic to epidemic will be facilitated by close contact between humans and vertebrate hosts (urban commensal birds or rodents, farm animals).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(5)</label>
   <p>By opening an ecological niche in urbanized areas. It is conceivable that local effective vector control by way of elimination of 
    <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> or 
    <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> would open their ecological niche in some areas, allowing a new species, such as 
    <italic>Ae. malayensis</italic> in South-East Asia, already recognized as a vector of dengue and chikungunya viruses, to begin to colonize even closer to human populations. This scenario has not happened yet. 
    <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> may have replaced 
    <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> or vice versa, but for the moment no third species, with high vectorial capacity, has occupied their niches.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(6)</label>
   <p>Via the evolution of viruses already known, but which have not yet found the conditions for emerging and spreading. Genetic changes in virus strains could lead to better adaptation to new vectors and a better transmissibility, as happened with the chikungunya virus and 
    <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> [
    <xref rid="B52-pathogens-09-00265" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Viruses may also evolve resistance to drugs, when any are used, or human immune defences. Given the short generation time, large population size, and high mutation rate of RNA viruses (like yellow fever, dengue, and most pathogenic arboviruses), virus adaptation to efficient transmission by a human-preferring mosquito is rapid. That is, the virus more readily adapts to the mosquito (and vertebrate host), not the mosquito to the virus [
    <xref rid="B53-pathogens-09-00265" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
