<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">Molecular dating analyses using virus genetic data can be particularly informative due to the rapid rate of evolution of many viral species. By converting genetic differences among sequences into time units, molecular dating provides information on the timing of viral spread or emergence. Most molecular dating approaches are based on maximum-likelihood or Bayesian phylogenetic frameworks 
 <xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, and they usually exploit two strategies: molecular clock calibration using the sampling dates of the viral sequences (tip dating) and/or calibration using information on some internal nodes of the phylogeny. Tip dating is well-suited to study relatively recent events (e.g., epidemics or intra-host evolution), but requires that a temporal signal is present in the dataset (i.e., that the sequences have accumulated a measurable amount of change between sampling times) 
 <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Calibration using internal nodes can in principle allow to dig deeper into the past, but requires some 
 <italic>a priori</italic> knowledge about the virus evolutionary history (e.g., host-virus co-evolution, paleontological information). The widespread use of molecular dating has however revealed that the relationship between genetic divergence and time is complex, as evolutionary rates tend to vary with the time frame of measurement. In particular, high evolutionary rates are observed in the short term, whereas low rates are inferred in long time span studies 
 <xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. This pattern was observed for many viral lineages and is sometimes referred to as the time-dependent rate phenomenon (TDRP) 
 <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Failure to account for the TDRP can potentially lead to erroneous molecular dating results 
 <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>.
</p>
