<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0040">A compound that first showed anti-influenza activity was obtained in the screen of antiviral drugs targeting influenza, and favipiravir was optimized in terms of activity and stability in animals. Dr. Shiraki, K. suggested that the chemical structures of the active compound and its derivatives, including favipiravir, resembled a nucleoside analogue, and the presumed mechanism of action was to inhibit RNA synthesis (
 <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). Three compounds, 5-aminoimidazole-4-carboxamide-1-β-D-ribofuranoside (AICAR), which was biosynthesized de novo from amino acids, ribosyl-favipiravir, and ribavirin, have similar chemical structures, suggesting that favipiravir functions as a purine homologue and inhibits viral RNA synthesis. Therefore, Dr. Shiraki, K. suggested the synthesis of the ribosyl form of favipiravir for its better efficacy, but the ribosylation of favipiravir did not improve its antiviral activity. Addition of 10 × 50% effective concentration for plaque reduction (EC
 <sub>50</sub> = 63.7 μM) of adenine, guanine, adenosine, guanosine, and inosine in the assay medium abolishes the anti-influenza virus activity of favipiravir (
 <xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">Furuta et al., 2005</xref>). Based on these findings, favipiravir is mainly incorporated in the salvage pathways for purine nucleotides through the purine phosphoribosyltransferases (
 <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">Craig 3rd &amp; Eakin, 2000</xref>) and is further phosphorylated to favipiravir-triphosphate as the substrate for viral RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp). The phosphorylation of favipiravir by hypoxanthine guanine phosphoribosyltransferase was confirmed in a subsequent study (
 <xref rid="bb0420" ref-type="bibr">Naesens et al., 2013</xref>). Favipiravir showed anti-influenza virus activity toward all subtypes of seasonal influenza virus strains, including types A, B and C of laboratory strains and clinical isolates, as well as an oseltamivir-resistant virus, with an EC
 <sub>50</sub> ranging from 0.014 to 0.55 μg/mL (
 <xref rid="bb0170" ref-type="bibr">Furuta et al., 2002</xref>). Although the effectiveness against influenza viruses at the cell culture level was confirmed, the use of favipiravir as an anti-influenza drug was confirmed by analyzing its efficacy in animal models of influenza infection, as described below, which led to drug development.
</p>
