<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">Recent advances in sequencing technology have allowed us to identify genetic changes rapidly in influenza genomes, and genome sequencing has become one of the routine procedures in the influenza surveillance program [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Thus, a genome-based vaccine strain selection strategy would be ideal. To develop an effective in silico model to quantify antigenic distances between IAVs solely by using sequences, it is essential that we understand the key structural features determining influenza virus antigenicity. Previous studies have suggested that antigenicity is affected predominantly by changes in the antibody binding sites (i.e., ~ 100 residues) mostly located in the head structure of the HA protein [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Only one or a few of these antigenicity-associated sites change frequently during antigenic drift events [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Mutations at these sites can lead to changes in peptidic epitope structures. Those changes can cause deviations in immunologic responses in serologic assays through modification of biophysical properties of amino acids or modification of glycosylation patterns [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. For H1N1 IAVs, correlation analyses, through linear mixed-effects modeling, between ferret sera–derived hemagglutination inhibition (HI) data and HA protein sequences for A(H1N1)season1977 suggested that a few mutations in HA sequences affected antigenic changes among A(H1N1)season1977 from 1999 to 2009 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. In addition, 
 <italic>N</italic>-linked glycosylation (hereafter referred to as 
 <italic>N</italic>-glycosylation) of HA was considered to be associated with antigenic variations between A(H1N1)pdm09 and A(H1N1)season1977 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Nevertheless, molecular determinants for antigenic changes in H1N1 IAVs are still not fully understood, especially the roles of 
 <italic>N</italic>-glycosylation.
</p>
