<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The candidate gene family that has attracted the most attention in ecological and evolutionary host-pathogen studies, at least in vertebrates, is the major histocompatibility complex (MHC) (
 <xref rid="ref-68" ref-type="bibr">Hughes &amp; Nei, 1988</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Bernatchez &amp; Landry, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-101" ref-type="bibr">Meyer-Lucht &amp; Sommer, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-150" ref-type="bibr">Spurgin &amp; Richardson, 2010</xref>). MHC genes encode cell–surface molecules that play a central role in pathogen recognition as part of the adaptive immune response. T-cells act to destroy infected cells both directly, as cytotoxic T-cells, and indirectly, as T-helper cells which activate other immune cells, but they can only determine what is self or foreign from peptides presented by MHC molecules. The number of MHC gene copies carried by individuals varies widely between, and even within, species (
 <xref rid="ref-77" ref-type="bibr">Kelley, Walter &amp; Trowsdale, 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-89" ref-type="bibr">Lighten et al., 2014</xref>; reviewed in 
 <xref rid="ref-109" ref-type="bibr">O’Connor et al., 2019</xref>). Additionally, the allelic diversity recorded within and between gene copies makes the MHC genes the most polymorphic loci to date (
 <xref rid="ref-127" ref-type="bibr">Reche &amp; Reinherz, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-130" ref-type="bibr">Robinson et al., 2015</xref>). This exceptional polymorphism is believed to be primarily maintained by selection from a wide range of pathogens (
 <xref rid="ref-123" ref-type="bibr">Prugnolle et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-126" ref-type="bibr">Qutob et al., 2011</xref>). Overall, it is clear that MHC genes play a pivotal role in the fight against pathogens and numerous studies have established associations between MHC genotypes and infections with a particular pathogen (
 <xref rid="ref-75" ref-type="bibr">Kaslow et al., 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-101" ref-type="bibr">Meyer-Lucht &amp; Sommer, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-111" ref-type="bibr">Oliver, Telfer &amp; Piertney, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Bolnick &amp; Stutz, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-109" ref-type="bibr">O’Connor et al., 2019</xref>).
</p>
