<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Also known as DAS-181, this is a recombinant sialidase composed of the catalytic domain of a bacterial sialidase (
 <italic>Actinomyces</italic>
 <italic>viscosus</italic>) and the epithelium-anchoring domain of the human protein amphiregulin (
 <xref rid="ref91" ref-type="bibr">Malakhov et al., 2006</xref>). In the human respiratory tract, cell surface sialic acids are the primary receptors for binding and entry of influenza viruses. Fludase works by removing sialic receptors from the airway epithelium, therefore preventing viral entry into cells of the respiratory epithelium (
 <xref rid="ref150" ref-type="bibr">Triana-Baltzer et al., 2011</xref>). Preclinical 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> studies show that fludase is a broad-spectrum anti-influenza antiviral with potent antiviral activity against human and avian influenza viruses with no cellular toxicity (
 <xref rid="ref149" ref-type="bibr">Triana-Baltzer et al., 2009</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref148" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). 
 <italic>In vivo</italic> studies showed that mice can be rescued from influenza infection after treatment with fludase, including after infection with highly pathogenic H5N1 and H7N9 viruses (
 <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Belser et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref92" ref-type="bibr">Marjuki et al., 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref93" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). In a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled phase 2 study conducted to determine the effective dose in healthy adult participants with laboratory-confirmed influenza (NCT01037205), it was observed that treatment with fludase significantly reduces viral load and viral shedding after multiple doses. In addition, no significant adverse effects were observed in the patients that received the treatment (
 <xref rid="ref103" ref-type="bibr">Moss et al., 2012</xref>). In a phase 1 clinical trial (NCT01651494), it was observed that in longer treatments (more than 7 days), patients developed antibodies against the compound leading to a reduced efficacy (
 <xref rid="ref168" ref-type="bibr">Zenilman et al., 2015</xref>).
</p>
