<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One community-based HIV testing strategy with high acceptability among men is HIV self-testing (HIVST) [
 <xref rid="B7-diagnostics-10-00318" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. HIVST is a convenient and discrete alternative to facility-based testing that can overcome men’s barriers to testing, including time and transport costs, stigma, and confidentiality concerns. In a community-based trial in Malawi, HIVST achieved 76% testing coverage among men and was reported as the preferred option for future HIV testing [
 <xref rid="B7-diagnostics-10-00318" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. A particularly promising HIVST delivery strategy is secondary distribution from females to their male partners. In this model, women in antenatal clinics (ANCs) are given an HIVST by a healthcare provider and trained to use the HIVST, interpret results, and deliver it to her male partner. This strategy has been shown to increase HIV testing among men, couples testing, linkage, and mutual disclosure of HIV status [
 <xref rid="B8-diagnostics-10-00318" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-diagnostics-10-00318" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-diagnostics-10-00318" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In addition to increasing HIV testing among men, secondary distribution of HIVST can have health benefits for women regardless of their HIV status. HIV-negative pregnant women are at high-risk of acquiring HIV, partially due to low testing rates among their male partners; HIVST can increase men’s knowledge of their HIV status and facilitate linkage to care, which can reduce transmission to partners. For pregnant women living with HIV (PWLHIV), HIVST distribution can promote couples testing and disclosure, which can increase women’s retention in ART and engagement in PMTCT regimens, improving the health of women and infants [
 <xref rid="B11-diagnostics-10-00318" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Furthermore, testing partners of PWLHIV is a high yield strategy to identify HIV-positive men; studies find HIV positivity of 50%–60% in primary partners of HIV-positive individuals, many of whom are unaware of their status [
 <xref rid="B12-diagnostics-10-00318" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-diagnostics-10-00318" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Male partners of PWLHIV who test HIV-negative will be in HIV sero-discordant partnerships and can benefit from linking to HIV prevention, including pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP). 
</p>
