<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several observations concerning CBSV range expansion can be made using the parameter estimates presented in this work. Firstly, the short retention period (1.6 
 <italic>hours</italic>) is consistent with sub-threshold (i.e. non-epidemic) epidemiology of CBSV since it is associated with a brief whitefly infectious period. The inoculation period is the inverse of the 
 <italic>rate of successful inoculation</italic> (per infected whitefly), which is itself composed of the rate that the virus is introduced into the plant during feeding scaled by the probability that inoculation events lead to plant infection. The long inoculation period (relative to retention period) reported here (48 
 <italic>hours</italic> cf. 1.6 
 <italic>hours</italic>) is another factor in sub-threshold 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub>. It is likely to reflect a low frequency with which inoculation events are successful (i.e., result in plant infection). All of the parameter estimates derived above are consistent with the conclusions of Maruthi 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007724.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], who found that retention period is &lt; 48 
 <italic>hours</italic>, acquisition period is &lt; 1 
 <italic>hour</italic> and CBSV is inoculated in a manner that increases up to 24 
 <italic>hours</italic>. Our findings extend the results of Maruthi 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007724.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] by providing parameter estimates (rather than plausible ranges) that can be used for epidemiological applications such as landscape simulation. As with Maruthi 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007724.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]’s experiment, and in spite of the constraints of a short retention period and a long inoculation period, substantial plant infection does occur in our model of access period assays. In part, this is facilitated by rapid acquisition of the virus when whitefly feed on infected plants (with an acquisition period of 0.55 
 <italic>hours</italic>), and in part this is due to the relatively high density of whitefly used in the experiments.
</p>
