<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>How do our findings relate to epidemics in the field? Our results shed light on a number of critical factors that may be responsible for the transition of CBSV from sub- to super-threshold 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> in sub-Saharan Africa. These factors include 
 <italic>a</italic>): pathogenic adaptation to the cassava host such that the frequency of plant infection following inoculation is increased, 
 <italic>b</italic>): the invasion of novel strains of the 
 <italic>B. tabaci</italic> whitefly having greater affinity for the cassava host, such that insect vectors spend longer periods of time feeding from cassava phloem. CBSV like other RNA viruses, evolves quickly [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007724.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], so that CBSV may have evolved to overcome host defences [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007724.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. A number of 
 <italic>B. tabaci</italic> strains collected from cassava have been shown to vary in host preference and range of diet [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007724.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. This, in turn, suggests that geographic variation in 
 <italic>B. tabaci</italic> strains [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007724.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] is likely to be associated with variation in 
 <italic>B. tabaci</italic> feeding behavior [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007724.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In addition to these possible factors, the increasing abundance of whitefly across Eastern sub-Saharan Africa since the 1990s [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007724.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007724.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007724.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] is certain to have played a key role. Notably the confirmation of re-emergence of CBSD in central Uganda coincided with generally high 
 <italic>B. tabaci</italic> populations in the area [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007724.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Our results also point to the importance of infected cuttings in determining the rate of spread of the epidemic front. The shorter the retention period, the shorter is the distance over which the virus can be effectively carried by insects in airflows to infect the host plant. This then suggests that long distance transmission of CBSV is likely to be dominated by human-mediated movement of infected cuttings rather than by insect movement. However, it should be borne in mind that even for the very briefly retained, non-persistently transmitted potyviruses there is evidence in the literature that some long-distance air-borne dispersal does occur [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007724.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].
</p>
