<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <statement content-type="Example" id="insr12402-mthst-0003">
  <label>Example 3</label>
  <p>We apply the same approach as given in Example 
   <xref rid="insr12402-mthst-0002" ref-type="statement">2</xref> for analysing the daily time series of the COVID‐19 cumulative infectious counts in Michigan during 11 March to 1 May 2020. Details of the data are described in Appendix 
   <xref rid="insr12402-sec-0055" ref-type="sec">A2</xref>, including the 
   <italic>I</italic>(
   <italic>t</italic>) sequence. The already defined 
   <monospace>SIR</monospace> function from Example 
   <xref rid="insr12402-mthst-0001" ref-type="statement">1</xref> is used as the dynamic model, and the already defined 
   <monospace>sse</monospace> function from Example 
   <xref rid="insr12402-mthst-0002" ref-type="statement">2</xref> is used as the loss function. By fixing 
   <italic>γ</italic>=0.2 (i.e. average contagious period of 5 days) the following code computes the solution 
   <math id="nlm-math-19">
    <mover accent="true">
     <mrow>
      <mi>β</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mo>^</mo>
    </mover>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mn>0</mn>
    <mo>.</mo>
    <mn>79</mn>
   </math> using the first 10 observations (11 to 20 March). We then increase the number of observations in the estimation; as shown in Figure 
   <xref rid="insr12402-fig-0008" ref-type="fig">8</xref>, the value of 
   <math id="nlm-math-20">
    <mover accent="true">
     <mrow>
      <mi>β</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mo>^</mo>
    </mover>
   </math> decreases when more data are used. This is noticeably different from Example 
   <xref rid="insr12402-mthst-0002" ref-type="statement">2</xref> where 
   <math id="nlm-math-21">
    <mover accent="true">
     <mrow>
      <mi>β</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mo>^</mo>
    </mover>
   </math> remains constant regardless of the number of observations used. The gradual decrease in our estimate of 
   <italic>β</italic> indicates a potential reduction in the transmission rate over time in Michigan due to the enforcement of statewide social distancing. In other words, the assumption of a constant transmission rate 
   <italic>β</italic> is inappropriate for the Michigan data. This result suggests a need for using a more proper modelling technique, which will be demonstrated in Section 
   <xref rid="insr12402-sec-0031" ref-type="sec">5.5</xref>.
  </p>
 </statement>
 <boxed-text position="anchor" id="insr12402-blkfxd-0003" content-type="graphic" orientation="portrait">
  <graphic xlink:href="INSR-88-462-g018.jpg" position="anchor" id="nlm-graphic-19" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </boxed-text>
</p>
