<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0065">In FP, experimental field trials have been conducted with a strain of 
 <italic>A. polynesiensis</italic> called ‘CP’ strain, which is stably modified with an alternate 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic> type (B supergroup) originated from a closely related mosquito species, 
 <italic>Aedes riversi</italic>. Under semi-field cage conditions on Tahiti (Society Islands), CP males were demonstrated to have a mating competitiveness with wild females that was indistinguishable from that of wild males 
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. An open release trial was performed on Toamaro, an islet of Raiatea (Society Islands), selected for its small size, its high density of 
 <italic>A. polynesiensis</italic> and the absence of inhabitants. Despite only relatively small numbers of CP males being released over 30 weeks (compared with the large wild population size on the islet), a significant decrease in the number of wild females able to produce viable embryos was obtained 
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. Another pilot study started in 2015 on Onetahi, the main islet of Tetiaroa (Society Islands), to evaluate the feasibility and sustainability of releasing incompatible male 
 <italic>A. polynesiensis</italic> on a larger scale. The mass production of 
 <italic>A. polynesiensis</italic> mosquitoes, also modified with B-
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic> from 
 <italic>A. riversi</italic>, enabled the release of more than one million incompatible male mosquitoes on the islet through repeated weekly releases 
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. As early as 6 months after the project began, 
 <italic>A. polynesiensis</italic> mosquitoes were almost eradicated from the islet with a 100-fold drop in the wild population 
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. The successful reduction of 
 <italic>A. polynesiensis</italic> on Onetahi is all the more promising because it lasted over a year after the end of releases with the mosquito population density remaining one-tenth of what it was before the project 
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>.
</p>
