<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are diverse predicaments faced by those with epilepsy, those caring for them as well as those treating them during these trying-and-testing times. Most studies have evinced that epilepsy does not increase the risk of SARS-CoV-2 infection, lest the patient also has associated comorbidities.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r145" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>,
  <xref rid="r146" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>
 </sup> There are however a few exceptions – autoimmune epilepsies, for instance, which make the person more susceptible to infection both due to the disease process itself and as an effect of immunomodulatory therapy for the underlying autoimmune process.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r145" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>,
  <xref rid="r146" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>
 </sup> It is of paramount importance to communicate to patients with epilepsy the consequences of discontinuation of medication. It is essential that they stock up medicines for a few months in advance taking into consideration the effects prolonged periods of lockdowns and empty pharmacy shelves are going to have. Non-compliance with therapy can have dangerous consequences. Additionally, the threshold to administer emergency rescue medications (benzodiazepines via nasal, rectal or buccal route) may be lowered in such crisis situations. The objective is to reduce visits to healthcare facilities as much as possible in order to reduce exposure to infection, prevent acute attacks of seizures/status epilepticus, to minimize visits to the emergency department and to prevent unnecessary utilization of ventilator machines in these times of crises. Caregivers should be instructed to give as much care as possible at home. Introduction of telemedicine practices will mitigate needless visits to the clinics and avoiding crowded places. While it is important to ensure compliance to medication, it should also be kept in mind that most of these antiepileptic drugs interact with many commonly used drugs. Many patients hospitalized with severe COVID-19 require antiepileptic drugs either as prophylaxis or as part of therapy, and it is irrefutable that severe infection is often associated with underlying cardiovascular comorbidities. Certain combinations are not recommended, and certain ones require extra vigilance to prevent adverse effects and avoidable drug interactions. Furthermore, some drugs used for symptomatic therapy like antihistamines are capable of lowering seizure thresholds.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r145" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>
 </sup> For certain conditions like Dravet syndrome, where fever control is crucial to allay seizures, acetaminophen can be used.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r145" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>,
  <xref rid="r146" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>
 </sup> Patients with tuberous sclerosis or autoimmune epilepsy syndromes receiving corticosteroids or everolimus, among others, are potential candidates of a dysregulated immune response because of these drugs make them more susceptible to infections.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r145" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>–
  <xref rid="r147" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>
 </sup> Nevertheless, some studies have shown everolimus to prevent viral infections.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r147" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>,
  <xref rid="r148" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>
 </sup> A major drawback in the treatment of epilepsies and seizures is the limited use of electroencephalography (EEG) and other imaging procedures at present for fear of transmission of infections. The use of video monitoring EEG for the assessment of intractable seizures can be a useful alternative. Given this extraordinary reduction in healthcare facilities and strategies to reduce transmission of SARS-CoV-2, it is prudent to delay diagnostic EEG/non-emergent investigation procedures. Moreover, neurologists may consider postponement of any changes in treatment (such as weaning off or change in therapies, elective epilepsy surgeries, etc.) at present unless dictated by exigent reasons. Key advice on lifestyle issues like need for regular sleep, healthy eating habits and avoidance of alcohol and other recreational drugs must be reinforced on the patients. Anxiety and depression are of frequent occurrence in epilepsy patients, which heighten expectedly during periods of stress and must be appropriately attended to.
</p>
