<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The NorthernMax kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific) was used following the manufacturer´s instructions. RNA was mixed with 3 volumes of formaldehyde loading dye, then incubated 15 min at 65°C and 2 min on ice. Electrophoresis was performed in denaturing 1% agarose gels at 95 V. After electrophoresis, the gel was incubated in alkaline buffer (0.01N NaOH, 3M NaCl) for 20 min and transferred to a Biodyne B nylon membrane (Thermo Fisher Scientific) by downward transfer. RNA was crosslinked to the membrane using the UV stratalinker 2400 auto-crosslink program. The membrane was pre-hybridized for 30 min with ULTRAhyb-oligo Buffer (Thermo Fisher Scientific) at 42°C and hybridized overnight at 42°C with a Biotin-labeled DNA probe to detect ZIKV 3′ UTR (10453–10739 nt). The DNA probe was generated by PCR using 60% of unmodified dTTP and 40% biotin-16-dUTP (Roche). Specific primers (forward: 5′ AGGAGAAGCTGGGAAACCAAGC 3′; reverse: 5′ GATAATACGACTCACTATAGGAAACTCATGGAGTCTCTGGTC 3′) and apt-MR766 3′ UTR plasmid (template) were used to generate the biotin-labeled probe. For 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7</xref> northern blots, RNA was mixed with 2X TBE-Urea loading sample and resolved in 6% acrylamide TBE, 8M Urea gels and transferred to nylon membrane in 0.5% TBE for 3 hr using the XCell II Blot module (Thermo Fisher Scientific). The membrane was crosslinked and hybridized with a DNA probe to detect the ZIKV 3′ UTR DB and SLIII (10528–10807 nt). This probe was generated as above using specific primers (forward: 5′ GATAATACGACTCACTATAGGGCCCCTCAGAGGACACTGAGTCAAAAAA 3′; reverse: 5′ AGAAACCATGGATTTCCCCACACCGGCCGCCGCT 3′). After hybridization, the membranes were washed and incubated for 1 hr at room temperature with IRDYE 800CW streptavidin (LI-COR Biosciences) in Odyssey Blocking Buffer (LI-COR Biosciences) with 1% of SDS. After three washes with TBS containing 0.1% tween, the membrane was scanned using a LI-COR Odyssey instrument. Densitometry was performed using Image Studio Lite Ver 5.0 software.
</p>
