<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several research groups around the world have focused on the search for arbovirus vaccines, primarily against DENV (
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>–
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>). Generally, this type of approach is species-specific and considering the huge variety of known arboviruses, vaccine strategies that seek to prevent transmission seem difficult and remote. This is a long process that requires active participation of public policies and a significant financial investment, which does not occur in most endemic regions (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>–
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>). Several DENV vaccine candidates have been developed over the years, some of which are in the testing phase. The composition of the formulations varies between DNA (monovalent or tetravalent), recombinant adenoviruses, Alfavirus replicons, and chimeric E protein subunits, among others (
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>–
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>). However, only the CYD-TDV vaccine has reached the final stages of testing in humans in different parts of the world (
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>). CYD-TDV (Sanofi-Pasteur) is an attenuated chimeric vaccine containing recombinant fractions from the four serotypes of DENV (tetravalent). The tetravalent attenuated component (TDV) was developed by the Reed Army Research Institute (WRAIR), in collaboration with GlaxoSmithKline Vaccines (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>). Sanofi Pasteur then developed the vaccine including the viral strains PUO-359 (DENV-1), PUO-218 (DENV-2), PaH881/88 (DENV-3), and 1228 (DENV-4) (
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>). After going through the clinical study phases, the vaccine was made commercially available under the name DengVaxia® (CYD-TDV, Sanofi-Pasteur). According to da Costa et al. (
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>), the effectiveness of this vaccine varies around 59%, but more studies are needed to confirm its long-term effectiveness. However, on December 13, 2017, WHO issued a statement warning that DengVaxia® should not be administered to people who have not been previously exposed to DENV due to an increased incidence of childhood cases of severe dengue in vaccinated individuals who had never been infected with the virus. Still, it remains the only arbovirus vaccine available at the moment.
</p>
