<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An interesting approach is the use of 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic> gram-negative bacteria (Order Rickettisiales) discovered by Hertig and Wolbach (
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>) in the reproductive tissues of 
 <italic>Culex pipiens</italic>. It is known that the different strains establish symbiotic relationships with more than 60% of the world's insect species and that they have a great potential to reduce the life span of mosquitoes and block infection by pathogens (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>–
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>). This strategy can be used as a population suppression or as a population replacement approach. The latter uses strains of 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic> that can block arboviruses, especially Flaviviruses (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>) and Alphaviruses (
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>). Several studies on this approach have shown promising results, especially in Australia (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>–
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>). McMeniman et al. (
 <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>) showed that the introduction of the wMelPop-CLA, a 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic> strain, reduced a population of 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic> kept in the laboratory by up to 50%. Moreira et al. (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) demonstrated that the introduction of this strain inhibits the infection of DENV-2 and CHIKV in 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic> and suggested that the blocking strategy, in synergy with the reduction in life span, could be a promising approach to controlling the transmission of arbovirus. Walker et al. (
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>) transfected mosquitoes with the avirulent wMel, another 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic> strain, and showed a more accelerated invasion of 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic> populations when compared to the wMelPop-CLA strain in semi-field conditions. The authors also showed a blockage of DENV-2 transmission by both strains. The use of 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic> as a vector control method provided subsidies for the creation of the “Eliminate Dengue: Our challenge” Project (World Mosquito Program—WMP). The release of mosquitoes in northern Australia (2011) showed that 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic> had already spread throughout the population of 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic> 10 weeks later. The WMP originally aimed to control the transmission of DENV, but today it contributes significantly to the control of other arboviruses in 12 countries, including Brazil. Currently, it is being used in Brazil by the World Mosquito Program (formerly “Eliminate Dengue: Brazil Challenge”) and has shown results worth of attention (
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>). Moreover, the use of this bacteria has also proved to be a promising method of controlling other viruses. Ekwudu et al. (
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>) evaluated the ability of the wAlbB strain to reduce or block the replication of Flavivirus and Alphavirus species in cell cultures and showed that this control strategy is effective against a wide variety of RNA viruses. The cultures in the presence of WNV, ZIKV, Ross River (RRV), Barmah Forest (BFV), and Sindbis virus (SINV) infected with wAlbB showed significantly reduced in viruse load compared to 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-free controls.
</p>
