<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The 
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic> genus is involved in important chapters of both, World and Brazilian epidemiology histories. 
 <italic>Yellow fever virus</italic> (YFV), 
 <italic>Dengue virus</italic> (DENV) and 
 <italic>Zika virus</italic> (ZIKV) were sequentially imported to Brazil and South America. Cases of yellow fever, caused by YFV, were first reported in Brazil in 1685. Thousands of yellow fever cases were noticed until the beginning of the twentieth century, when the 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> mosquitoe was identified as the main vector of the disease. Vector eradication together with vaccination contributed to elimination of yellow fever from Brazilian urban areas (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). In 1981, the first epidemic caused by DENV was confirmed in Brazil (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Since then, many epidemics have reached the country, usually related to the introduction of a new serotype or the change of the dominant serotype in a given region (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Such flavivirus is responsible for approximately 390 million of infections annually by one of its four serotypes (DENV1-4) (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Thus, DENV is considered as the flavivirus of highest epidemiologic relevance of the world. But recently, ZIKV which was a pathogen previously associated with mild infections in Africa and Asia, was associated to microcephaly and 
 <italic>Guillain-Barré</italic> syndrome in the Americas (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). The first cases of ZIKV infection were reported in early 2015, in the Brazilian Northeast. The virus was very quickly spreaded and 141 suspected cases of microcephaly were reported in Northeastern states, in addition to many cases of spontaneous abortions and stillbirths (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). In 2016 yellow fever cases were reported again in Brazil, with a total of 1,127 cases and 331 confirmed deaths until April 2018 (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). There is a number of additional flaviviruses with worldwide epidemiological importance or which are highly pathogenic. Examples are 
 <italic>West Nile virus</italic> (WNV), 
 <italic>Japanese encephalitis virus</italic> (JEV), 
 <italic>Saint Louis encephalitis virus</italic> (SLEV) and 
 <italic>Rocio virus</italic> (ROCV) (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Such pathogens are vector-borne viruses, which are capable of traveling over long distances, carried by both, the human and/or the arthropod hosts. The risk of importing, emergence and epidemics caused by additional flaviviruses is clear in both, Brazil and other tropical regions of the world.
</p>
