<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Following on our previous findings [
 <xref rid="B7-viruses-12-00087" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], we have provided herein a further insight into the mechanism and significance of cortactin degradation during IAV infection. Using the RNA interference screen, we have confirmed the involvement of lysosome and identified the role of a lysosomal protease, cathepsin C in cortactin degradation during IAV infection. However, the role of other cathepsins (A, E, F, L, S, V, and X [
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-12-00087" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-12-00087" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]) not targeted here cannot be ruled out. Furthermore, using the same strategy, we also confirmed the involvement of mainly caspase-3 not caspase-6 or -7, the other two main executioner caspases [
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-12-00087" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], in cortactin degradation. Next, it will be interesting to investigate the link between cathepsin C and caspase-3 in the degradation of cortactin during IAV infection. Cathepsin C, also known as dipeptidyl peptidase I, is one of the first lysosomal proteases to be discovered and is ubiquitously expressed, including in the lungs. It is the main regulator of multiple pro-inflammatory serine proteases, activation of which leads to tissue damage and inflammatory response [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-12-00087" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. One of the cathepsin C-regulated serine proteases, proteinase-3 has been described to cleave and activate caspase-3 [
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-12-00087" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Hence, there is a link between lysosome and apoptosis or cathepsin C and caspase-3 activation, however such link has to be established during IAV infection. Further, several viral proteins contribute to controlling the apoptosis in IAV infected cells [
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-12-00087" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]; it will be interesting to identify the viral protein(s) which is controlling the apoptotic pathway that is leading to cortactin degradation. 
</p>
