<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0035">There have been difficulties in the development of coronavirus vaccines historically. Coronavirus vaccines in animal models that mimic human disease have been immunogenic but generally not shown to effectively prevent acquisition of disease 
 <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. Further, there is a concern that vaccination, as with natural coronaviral infection, may not induce long lived immunity and re-infection may be possible 
 <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. In some ways more concerning has been vaccine associated disease enhancement. Previous use of coronavirus vaccines (SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV) in some animal models raised safety concerns regarding Th2 mediated immunopathology 
 <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. Mice vaccinated with two inactivated whole virus vaccines, a recombinant DNA spike protein vaccine or a virus-like particle vaccine developed lung pathology including eosinophilic infiltration 2 days after being challenged with SARS-CoV which were not seen in the lungs of challenged unvaccinated mice 
 <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. Similar lung immunopathology was observed in several other studies, particularly in aged mice compared to younger mice 
 <xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref> that were challenged following vaccination 
 <xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. Mice immunised with SARS-CoV N protein vaccine developed severe pneumonia or lung eosinophilic infiltrate upon viral challenge, whereas mice immunised with viral replicon particles expressing glycoprotein did not, suggesting that the N protein antigen may be the antigen linked to this immunopathology. Similar enhanced immunopathology has been seen in mice vaccinated with inactivated MERS-CoV vaccine when challenged with live virus 
 <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. Vaccine associated disease enhancement may be more of a concern with certain vaccine types. Enhanced disease caused by viral challenge has been notable following administration of inactivated measles and RSV vaccines 
 <xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0170" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, with the possible mechanisms being a Th2 skewed response resulting from formalin inactivation as well as lack of affinity maturation of the antibodies produced 
 <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>.
</p>
