<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For this review, we set the date for the searches as of February 2020. Only studies published in 2013 or later were included, which reflects the period when DAAs were introduced. Additionally, we only included studies conducted in LMICs (or multisite studies that contained a substantial number of participants from LMICs), published in English, with a sample size greater than 50, and an attrition rate below 20% [
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-17-04951" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. We excluded articles focusing on incarcerated and transplant populations, because the prison environment and transplant protocols yields data that would not be generalizable to the majority of the PWID population. We accepted studies in which participants completed treatment with any interferon-free DAA regimen. Studies whose participants underwent a combination of interferon-free and interferon-containing regimens were included so long as interferon-free treatment regimens comprised over half of the cases. Participants in the studies included persons who injected drugs and who achieved SVR (undetectable HCV RNA) at least 12 weeks following treatment completion. 
 <xref rid="ijerph-17-04951-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows sampling, the rate of reinfection (over 5 cases per 100PY constituted “high”) and recruitment methods in addition to assays used and testing interval. In cases where methodological information was missing, we sent inquiries to authors to provide supplemental data. Such inquiries resulted in one author providing supplementary documents. Reinfection rates were abstracted directly or calculated (the number of reinfections divided by total PY) from data included in the reports. The results obtained from our search were initially screened by abstract and title and are represented by the PRISMA flowchart in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-17-04951-f001">Figure 1</xref>. The full-text review excluded articles that did not meet inclusion criteria (high-income country, interferon containing treatment, no PWID, etc.) or did not include recurrence data. In the case of multiple publications of a single study, we included the study with most up-to-date data. Attrition rates were calculated (dropouts/total) from supplemental information if not provided in the manuscript. Systematic reviews and meta-analyses were included if they contained unpublished data or unpublished studies. 
</p>
