<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8">The distribute pattern COVID-19 other respiratory depends upon the various factor like their basic reproductive number (R
 <sub>0</sub>), nature of the virus, environmental condition, trade/travel with the affected area, population density and social culture. The basic reproductive number (R
 <sub>0</sub>) and nature of the virus are similar for the whole world; therefore the difference of outbreak potential depends on other factors. The WHO data is clearly suggested that colder and humid regions are more affected than warmer and dry regions (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus</ext-link>). In India, initial outbreaks started in the regions, which are directly linked to the affected area via trade/travel. In expert opinion, the number of COVID-19 cases could be more but diagnostic rates of India are very low as compared with other countries. The majority of the confirmed cases were linked to other countries; therefore all tourist visas were suspended and ban the entry from effected parts to reduce the chance of infections (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://mea.gov.in/covid-19-updates.htm" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://mea.gov.in/covid-19-updates.htm</ext-link>). To hamper the virus spread in the community, educational institutions and many other commercial activities have been shut down. To reduce the COVID-19 spread, a 14-hour voluntary public curfew was observed in the whole country at the request of Prime Minister, Modi. The government followed it up with lockdowns in COVID-19 affected parts and major cities. The Prime minister ordered a national lockdown for 21 days on 24 March 2020 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.independent.co.uk" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.independent.co.uk</ext-link>). Some person does not follow the instruction; become the super spreader of COVID-19. A Sikh preacher has a travel history of the infected area (Italy and Germany) attending a Sikh festival in Anandpur Sahib on 7 March. As a result, twenty-seven positive cases of COVID-19 were identified and more than 40,000 people belong to 20 villages of Punjab needed to be quarantined. In another case, more than 2000 people including 281 foreigners attending 
 <italic>Tablighi Jamaat</italic> religious congregation event was organized in Delhi and staying at the mosque since 8 March. About 200 people have shown symptoms, out of which, 24 people were positive for COVID-19 so far. A large number of COVID-19 cases across the country were found to be linked to the event (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.mohfw.gov.in" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.mohfw.gov.in</ext-link>). Michael Ryan, chief executive director of WHO seems to be happy with Indian efforts to control COVID-19. The COVID-19 not only dangerous for our health but the Indian economy is highly affected due to the lockdown. A large segment of the Indian population, lose their livelihood due to shut down of trades, commercial, tourist and other business activities during the lockdown.
</p>
