<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our current serological data are in agreement with our previous report [
 <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] where the estimated seropositivity for cluster ‘1978–1987’ was ~74.6%, followed by cluster ‘1969–1977’ with ~84.6%. A recent publication by Hungarian colleagues has reported 86.2% seropositivity for the 41–45 years old individuals [
 <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], a cluster partially overlapping with the two abovementioned age groups of our classification. The potential gap detected in herd immunity is also supported by the already known insufficiencies during the initial vaccination era [
 <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. These individuals were vaccinated during the early 1970s, when the optimal age of vaccination was not well defined, and the thermolability of the reconstituted vaccine was not fully characterised [
 <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. These relatively high measles seronegativity ratios may have been a consequence of vaccine inefficiency, which seems to be supported by historical data: after the starting of the immunisation campaign in 1969, a decade later, in 1978, the recommended age for vaccination was changed from 10 to 15 months. The 1988–1989 epidemics affected individuals (16–22 years old) who were vaccinated in the early era with a singular measles vaccine. Following the 1988–1989 epidemics, persons born between 1973 and 1977 were revaccinated [
 <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Even though a significant portion of the age groups indicated with ** in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig09">Figure 9</xref> later were re-vaccinated or contracted wild-type measles infection (and thus mounted high IgG antibody response), in this cluster, we found the lowest cumulative anti-measles antibody titres (i.e. high ratio of seronegativity), which suggests the ineffectiveness of the early vaccination system. Additional support for this hypothesis is the high age-specific attack rates during the 1988–1989 outbreak that affected the population with ≥93% vaccine coverage. After the introduction of the trivalent MMR vaccine (1991), we detected a statistically significant improvement in the anti-measles antibody titres (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10">Fig. 10</xref>). The group ‘
 <italic>Vaccinated between 1988–1990</italic>’ has significantly better humoral response compared to the group ‘
 <italic>Vaccinated between 1978–1987</italic>’, reflecting the effectiveness of the trivalent reminder vaccine at age 11.
</p>
