<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>Dengue is becoming a major public health concern in Guangdong (GD) Province of China. The problem was highlighted in 2014 by an unprecedented explosive outbreak, where the number of cases was larger than the total cases in previous 30 years. The present study aimed to clarify the spatial and temporal patterns of this dengue outbreak.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>Based on the district/county-level epidemiological, demographic and geographic data, we first used Moran’s I statistics and Spatial scan method to uncover spatial autocorrelation and clustering of dengue incidence, and then estimated the spatial distributions of mosquito ovitrap index (MOI) by using inverse distance weighting. We finally employed a multivariate time series model to quantitatively decompose dengue cases into endemic, autoregressive and spatiotemporal components.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>The results indicated that dengue incidence was highly spatial-autocorrelated with the inclination of clustering and nonuniformity. About 12 dengue clusters were discovered around Guangzhou and Foshan with significant differences by district/county, where the most likely cluster with the largest relative risk located in central Guangzhou in October. Three significant high-MOI areas were observed around Shaoguan, Qingyuan, Shanwei and Guangzhou. It was further found the districts in Guagnzhou and Foshan were prone to local autoregressive transmission, and most region in southern and central GD exhibited higher endemic components. Moreover, nearly all of districts/counties (especially the urban area) have cases that were infected in adjacent regions.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>The study can help to clarify the heterogeneity and the associations of dengue transmission in space and time, and thus provide useful information for public health authorities to plan dengue control strategies.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
