<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig2">
 <label>Figure 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Comparison of the relative pace of placental and embryonic development in humans and marmosets. The embryonic stages shown encompass those that occurred in the Zika-infected marmoset embryos and reflect critical neurodevelopmental stages. The human blastocyst implants on day 6 post-conception, while in the marmoset implantation occurs on day 12. Marmoset organogenesis is complete by approximately day 80
   <sup>
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>
   </sup>, compared to day 56 (end of the 8
   <sup>th</sup> week) in humans, marking the shift from embryo to fetus. The first appearance of chorionic vessels in the human placenta occurs in week 3
   <sup>
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>
   </sup>; the corresponding period of 20–25 days is when vessels appear in the marmoset placenta
   <sup>
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
   </sup>. Erythroblasts first appear in human chorionic vessels around day 23, 
   <italic>i</italic>.
   <italic>e</italic>. early week 4, the equivalent to marmoset day 36. In this regard, the marmoset may be delayed, because erythroblasts inside chorionic vessels are not reported to occur until days 46–50. In the human, maternal blood supply is not fully established until week 12, but initial entry of maternal blood into the intervillous space occurs as early as mid-week 6. In the marmoset placenta, maternal blood is first apparent on day 45, equivalent to late week 5 in the human placenta. In New World monkeys such as marmosets, placental interdigitation is described as “trabecular” with cytoplasmic bridges instead of “villous” with finger-like appendages. As this minor anatomical difference is not known to be functionally significant, for clarity of comparison the terms “villous” and “intervillous spaces” are used to describe the marmoset placenta.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_25205_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e674" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
