<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Viral virulence is determined by efficient infection, which relies heavily on efficient entry of the viral particles into the host cell and release of its genome for replication. Many cellular receptors, including the most studied scavenger receptor class B member 2 (SCARB2), P-selectin glycoprotein ligand-1 (PSGL1), and cell surface heparan sulfate glycosaminoglycan, have been reported [
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Human SCARB2, a ubiquitously expressed protein that functions in membrane transport, was shown to function as an attachment receptor and an uncoating factor for EV-A71 entry [
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. SCARB2 interacts with the EV-A71 VP1 protein and triggers uncoating of EV-A71 under low pH conditions. The acidic environment causes a pH-dependent conformational alteration of VP1 and dislodges the “pocket factor” from the hydrophobic pocket beneath the canyon region of the virions, permitting initiation of the uncoating process [
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. X-ray structures revealed that the WIN compounds, such as DBPR103 and PR66, replace the natural pocket factor within the hydrophobic pocket, stabilizing the viral particle and preventing virus uncoating [
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12–14</xref>]. Moreover, PSGL1, a pan-selectin ligand, is expressed on leukocytes, platelets, and endothelial cells. Mouse cells overexpressing human PSGL1 are susceptible to EV-A71 [
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. However, unlike SCARB2, PSGL1 may not affect virus uncoating [
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Cell surface heparan sulfate glycosaminoglycan is involved in the entry processes of many viruses [
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. For EV-A71, based on the structural model of the EV-A71 pentamer, the binding site for heparan sulfate is located around the symmetrical five-fold axis containing clustering of the positively charged amino acids, such as VP1-K242 and VP1-K244 [
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Recently, the suramin derivative NF449 and tryptophan dendrimers were shown to interact with the five-fold vertex effectively blocking attachment of EV-A71 to PSGL1 and heparan sulfate [
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Hence, EV-A71 can be classified as PSGL1-binding [
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] and PSGL1-non-binding (non-PB) strains [
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. VP1-145 is located on the virus surface, surrounding the positively charged VP1-K242 and VP1-K244 surrounding the five-fold axis of symmetry. Exposure of the VP1-244K side chain, controlled by VP1-145, is critical for binding of EV-A71 to PSGL1 [
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].
</p>
