<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite the growing epidemics among PWID, the HIV response remains limited in MENA. By 2014, needle and syringe exchange programmes (NSP) were available in nine countries, and OST in five 
 <xref rid="jia225102-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">30</xref>. MENA has the lowest ART coverage globally at a median of 17% in 2015 
 <xref rid="jia225102-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">31</xref>, and could not reach the 2015 mid‐term regional objective of 50% coverage under WHO's initiative to end MENA's HIV treatment crisis 
 <xref rid="jia225102-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">32</xref>. The treatment cascade among PWID seems to suggest an even harsher reality 
 <xref rid="jia225102-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">33</xref>. The striking gap between regional figures and the 90‐90‐90 target is of great concern, especially since the epidemic in this region is strongly driven by injecting drug use. The punitive legal environment, stigma around HIV testing, and fear of discrimination are all challenges that hamper uptake of treatment by PWID 
 <xref rid="jia225102-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">3</xref>. These challenges need to be addressed to scale‐up testing, access to ART, and retention in care. We estimated that increasing ART coverage to the global target of 81% (90% of 90%), would alone avert close to half of incident infections among PWID and their sexual partners. Combining ART scale‐up with harm reduction – including NSP, OST and condom distribution – as part of an optimistic package would avert over 90% and 70% of infections among PWID and their sexual partners respectively (Figure 
 <xref rid="jia225102-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Furthermore studies and considerations – including a discussion dialogue with programme managers, NGOs, affected communities, and other stakeholders – are needed to assess implementation and coverage of these and other interventions, as well as potential barriers and challenges within the MENA context, to reach the desired targets.
</p>
