<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>COVID-19 has been also named SARS (Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome)-Coronavirus (CoV)2 by the Coronavirus Study Group (CSG) of the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses (ICTV). The novel virus is indeed part of the taxonomic Coronaviridae family (subfamily Coronavirinae) [
 <xref rid="B3-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Coronaviruses (CoVs) are positive sense single-stranded RNA viruses. They infect a wide variety of animal species, causing a wide range of symptoms, such as those similar to the common cold to severe/fatal respiratory syndrome [
 <xref rid="B1-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Chinese scientists isolated the virus from biological samples of affected patients during the recent China outbreak and defined its genetic code [
 <xref rid="B4-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]: GenBank Database MN908947.3. Coronaviruses comprise a large family of viruses being classified within the α, β, γ, and δ genera [
 <xref rid="B3-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. CoV2 is a representative betacoronavirus sharing nucleic acid sequence similarity with SARS-CoV and the Middle East Respiratory Syndrome (MERS)-CoV. The crown-like morphology observed in electron microscopy specimens is due to the presence of spike (S) glycoproteins on the viral surface [
 <xref rid="B6-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. These proteins are constituted by an ectodomain with a receptor-binding unit called S1 and a membrane-fusion unit called S2 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-21-05145-f001">Figure 1</xref>). The S1 unit must bind a cell surface receptor through a receptor-binding domain (RBD) to invade host cells. Instead, S2 contributes to fuse the host cellular and viral membranes; thus, the viral nuclei acid can penetrate into the host cells. The Angiotensin Converting Enzyme 2 (ACE2) has been identified as a functional receptor for SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="B7-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-21-05145-f001">Figure 1</xref>).
</p>
