<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par43">HAdV-3 and HAdV-7 have been prevalent throughout the world for decades, and both serotypes frequently play an important role in the etiology of lower respiratory infection in children. In the present study, coinfection with HAdV-3 and HAdV-7 with other respiratory viruses accounted for half of the pediatric cases, but coinfection per se did not result in a difference in clinical manifestation or severe clinical outcomes. These results and the severe respiratory diseases and complications, which we identified with HAdV-7 infection in hospitalized children, were all consistent with previous reports [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Remarkably, we also found a higher rate (19.1%) of toxic encephalopathy associated with HAdV-7 infection. Previous studies in Japan showed that mild encephalitis/encephalopathy with a reversible splenial lesion (MERS) could be triggered by adenovirus infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], which was proposed to be caused by neurotoxins, likely acting as an antigen that induced a strong immune response, leading to a series of symptoms. Recently, silkworm chrysalis ingestion was shown to induce toxic encephalopathy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]; however, our results constitute the first reported case of toxic encephalopathy associated with adenoviral infection. Earlier studies reported that several viruses, including adenoviruses, influenza A virus, parainfluenza virus, and Japanese encephalitis virus, can use the olfactory nerve as a shortcut into the central nervous system, causing infection of nerve cells and induction of immune response [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]; however, the exact mechanisms of such neurotropic infections remain to be elucidated.
</p>
