<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The three films chosen for analysis in this paper—
 <italic>Blindness</italic>, 
 <italic>The Painted Veil</italic> and 
 <italic>Contagion</italic>—each reflects on the capacity of different societies to exhibit levels of distrust during and in anticipation of epidemic disease outbreaks. These elements of distrust can be classified as institutional, where communities lose confidence in the actions and decisions of elites and authorities; social, where communities begin to distrust each other, or more frequently, ‘outsiders’ to these communities; and interpersonal, where individual relationships within families, households, friends and neighbours begin to break down. A recurring feature within these three films is the use of affairs between the main protagonists to demonstrate suspicion and distrust at the very micro-level—an approach that the medium of films and television can perform very well given their focus on individual characters. Another feature recurring within the films is a form of othering—even if it is subconscious rather than a deliberate critique—by exoticising the threat of disease transmission and spread. In 
 <italic>The Painted Veil</italic>, this is turned around in the opposite direction, as the ‘exotic’—the ‘timeless rural Chinese village as the nexus of infection—is ‘saved’ by a selfless Western bacteriologist risking his own life, despite their apparent ‘incapacity’ or ‘unwillingness’ to understand the health risks presented to them. These issues, firmly placed in mainstream cinema, are of obvious relevance to us when we consider (1) the effectiveness of popular culture in presenting public health issues to a broader ‘lay’ audience, and (2) the recent portrayal of the origins and spread of COVID-19 as almost a ‘moral’ issue relating to economic practices and social life in China. It is also important given the feeling recently expressed during this very same outbreak that ordinary lives of citizens, especially the poor and marginalised, often get pushed into the background in favour of ‘macroscopic’ elements of disease management.
 <xref ref-type="other" rid="note34">34</xref>
</p>
