<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Alphaviruses are enveloped, positive sense, single stranded RNA viruses, transmitted to humans and a variety of mammals by insects, often mosquitos. There is currently no available vaccine or treatment for most alphaviruses and this contributes to their rapid spread and to several recent epidemics [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006835.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Causing approximately 5000 cases each year, Ross River virus (RRV) is the most prominent human alphavirus in the South Pacific region, responsible for a debilitating musculoskeletal disease [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006835.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The link between infection and pathogenicity remains unclear. In contrast, Semliki Forest virus (SFV) generally does not cause disease in humans, but is neuropathogenic in mice and has often been used as a model system for the study of alphavirus biology [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006835.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In this study, we apply nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy (NMR) and gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) to analyse the metabolic alterations that accompany cellular infection with SFV and RRV. In SFV infected cells we measured sustained activation of glycolysis and of the pentose phosphate pathway (PPP) towards higher synthesis of new metabolites, and demonstrated that this is dependent on virus-induced activation of PI3K/AKT via a YXXM motif in the viral non-structural protein (nsP) 3. To test whether the presence of this motif is sufficient to predict changes in host metabolism during alphavirus infection, we examined the metabolic profile of cells infected with RRV, an alphavirus carrying the same motif in nsP3, whose metabolic profile has never been characterised. Although infection with RRV also triggers additional mechanisms of metabolic activation, disruption of the YXXM motif causes lower viraemia and reduced pathogenicity 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>, thus demonstrating the importance of AKT activation in viral pathogenesis.
</p>
