<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Aedes</italic> spp. (Diptera: Culicidae) are considered the key vectors of DENV, YFV, CHIKV and ZIKV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006626.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006626.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. At present, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> seems to play a leading role as vector among all of the 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> species, mainly due to its high anthropophily and preference for the urban areas of the tropical regions [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006626.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. However, though generally considered a secondary vector when 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> is present, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic>, the Asian tiger mosquito, demonstrated a key epidemiological role when abundant [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006626.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006626.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Moreover, the species may be responsible of increased risks of epidemics in temperate climate areas [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006626.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], as demonstrated by the DENV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006626.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006626.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] and CHIKV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006626.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] outbreaks occurred in Europe in recent years. In fact, even if less adapted to survive in dry conditions compared to 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic>, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> eggs display a remarkable cold hardiness in the diapausing form [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006626.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] which is highly contributing to the impressive extension of the geographic distribution of the species [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006626.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In addition, a recent mutation in an envelope glycoprotein led to a significant increase in CHIKV infectivity for 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> and enhanced dissemination in mosquito organs and transmission [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006626.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006626.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> was also found susceptible to ZIKV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006626.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006626.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006626.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] even if vector competence can be considered low [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006626.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. At the time of writing, CHIKV outbreaks occurred in Lazio (Rome Province) and Calabria regions [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006626.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] are still recent, with nearly 300 confirmed cases [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006626.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], endorsing the urgency of renewed control approaches.
</p>
