<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The full genome of three H1N1pdm09 isolates from pigs in Nigeria that were analysed in this study were most similar to influenza H1N1pdm09 sequences from human hosts as obtained in GenBank BLAST. This is also supported phylogenetically with the close similarities of A/swine/Nigeria/12VIR4047/2011(H1N1) with A/Nigeria/4280/2011(H1N1), A/Ghana/601/2011(H1N1) and A/Cameroon/EID/07/11/1870/2011(H1N1) which are viral sequences from human. Ghana and Cameroon are neigbouring West African countries with social and economic linkages as well as human/material traffic with Nigeria, hence the potential for transboundary transmission of infectious pathogens. Interestingly, earlier detection of H1N1pdm09 influenza virus in pig was reported in Cameroon [
 <xref rid="CIT0011">11</xref>], but the swine virus is less related to the isolates from pigs in Nigeria unlike the human isolates in the same country (
 <xref rid="F0001a">Figure 1</xref>), this observation suggests different introduction of the pandemic virus into the pig populations in the region (Cameroon, Nigeria and other countries including isolates from Kenya and Togo that were later detected from pigs in Africa). The human isolate of H1N1pdm09 influenza virus (A/Nigeria/4280/2011(H1N1)) detected from nasal swab sample by molecular methods at the CDC Influenza Laboratory in Abuja was sequenced and deposited in GISAID by CDC Atlanta (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://platform.gisaid.org/epi3/frontend#312740" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://platform.gisaid.org/epi3/frontend#312740</ext-link>). That sample was traced to Kano in Northern Nigeria, a major commercial center with direct human and material traffic with Lagos in the southern part of the country where this study was carried out. Similar cases and detection of H1N1pdm09 in human were also reported in Nigeria about the same period (2009 to 2011) suggesting prior circulation of the virus in humans before probable transmission of the virus to pigs [
 <xref rid="CIT0012">12</xref>]. This virus or their progenitors may have circulated either subclinically in human population to have enabled interspecies transmission to pigs that is strongly favoured by prevailing ecological factors and poor biosecurity in the study site where pigs of all ages are mixed together and pig handlers do not have sufficient knowledge and use of personal protective equipment (PPE) [
 <xref rid="CIT0009">9</xref>]. However, this assertion is difficult to prove because there were no sufficient surveillance data on swine influenza or H1N1pdm09 in the country prior to 2009 global outbreaks. Available but limited surveillance data also makes it difficult to trace back the circulation of these viruses in humans and animals within the country.
</p>
