<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Hand-washing, wearing face masks and social distancing (health protective behaviours) increase during epidemics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], and adherence varies with perceived health threats and efficacy beliefs and demographics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Most relevant studies are cross-sectional and of the 26 studies recently reviewed 23 lacked robust theoretical frameworks [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Several theoretical models for understanding health protective behaviours are available, including the cognitively based Theories of Planned Behaviour (TPB) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]/Reasoned Action (TRA) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], Health Belief Model (HBM) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] and Protection Motivation Theory [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Although HBM and TPB among others have been applied in some studies of cognitive interactions with health protective behaviours during RIDs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], these models do not adequately accommodate affect in health behavioural change during RID epidemics/pandemics. Moreover, existing theories have poorly accommodated the spectrum of social influence, exceptions being the TPB/TRA, which include coercive influences from family and friends under “norms”, and Social Learning Theory (SLT) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], which describes observational learning. Neither theoretical position includes both. Some studies have explored combinations of different theories. For example, attempts to predict hand-washing on an intensive care unit by combining SLT and TPB elements found only self-efficacy predicted hand-washing [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], suggesting established theoretical models may be inadequate. Because outbreaks of RIDs are dynamic, embodying significant uncertainty and often, invisible personal threat they differ from non-communicable disease. That the source of threat is not one’s own behaviour but other people argues for social factors to be more influential than existing models of behaviour change allow.
</p>
