<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Homozygous TYLCD susceptible (
 <italic>ty-1</italic>/
 <italic>ty-1</italic>) and heterozygous TYLCD resistant (
 <italic>Ty-1</italic>/
 <italic>ty-1</italic>) tomato quasi-isogenic lines (Monci et al., 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) (kindly provided by M. J. Díez, Universidad Politécnica de Valencia, Spain), 
 <italic>S. nigrum</italic> (IHSM “La Mayora” germplasm bank) and common bean cv Donna (Nunhems, Haelen, The Netherlands) were used as experimental hosts. Plants at the three-leaf growth stage were inoculated with 
 <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> LBA4404 containing infectious clones, and therefore single sequence variants, of isolates [ES:72:97] of the Mld strain of TYLCV (GenBank accession number 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="AF071228" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">AF071228</ext-link>) (García-Andrés et al., 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), [ES:Mur1:92] of the ES strain of TYLCSV (Z25751) (Navas-Castillo et al., 
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>), and [ES:421:99] of TYLCMaV (AF271234) (Noris et al., 
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>). These isolates were derived from infected tomato plants except for TYLCMaV, which was derived from an infected common bean plant. TYLCMaV is the result of a genetic exchange between TYLCV-Mld and TYLCSV-ES, with recombinant genome sequences that share 99% nucleotide identity with that of the parental virus sequences. As depicted in Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> in TYLCMaV, the 3′ half of the IR and the virus sense 
 <italic>V2</italic> and the 
 <italic>CP</italic> ORFs derive from TYLCSV, whereas the remainder 5′ half of the IR and the 
 <italic>Rep, C4, TrAP</italic> and most of 
 <italic>REn</italic> ORFs derive from TYLCV, with the 3′ terminal 40 nucleotides of the 
 <italic>REn</italic> ORF derived from TYLCSV (Monci et al., 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). Viral infectious clones of TYLCSV, TYLCV or TYLCMaV were used to inoculate three plants each of a TYLCD-susceptible tomato, a quasi-isogenic resistant tomato containing the 
 <italic>Ty-1</italic> allele in heterozygosis, common bean and 
 <italic>S. nigrum</italic> (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Liquid cultures of 
 <italic>A. tumefaciens</italic> were adjusted to an OD
 <sub>600</sub> of 1.00 and 20 μl were inoculated to each plant by the stem-puncture method as described elsewhere (Monci et al., 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). After agroinoculation, plants were maintained for 45 days in a growth chamber (26°C during the day and 18°C at night, 70% relative humidity, with a 16 h photoperiod at 250 μmol s
 <sup>−1</sup>m
 <sup>−2</sup> photosynthetically active radiation). Systemic virus infection of agroinoculated plants was confirmed on young non-inoculated leaves by tissue-print hybridization using a mixture of digoxigenin (DIG)-labeled probes specific to TYLCV and TYLCSV (Monci et al., 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) that also recognizes TYLCMaV.
</p>
