<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Kingdom of Saudi Arabia and the neighboring countries faced an extensive ascent in brucellosis incidence during 1991 [
 <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Brucellosis poses serious economic losses because of its effect both on animal production and human health. In the present study, brucellosis was detected in sheep, goats, and camel’s sera by ELISA assay as followed in many studies [
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>–
 <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. All of them stated that ELISA was valid, sensitive, and reliable to diagnose brucellosis infection in domestic ruminants. The overall prevalence rates of brucellosis in this study were 7.7%, 8.8%, and 6.5% in sheep, goats, and camel’s sera, respectively. Al-Sekait [
 <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] reported a higher seroprevalence in sheep (15.3%) and goats (20.1%) in Medina. Nearby in Mecca, the occurrence of brucellosis was 0.5% in sheep, 0.8% in goats, 3.6% in cows, and 2.8% in camels [
 <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Furthermore, Abd El-rahim and Asghar [
 <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] recorded an incidence of 15.6% in sheep and 3.9% in goats in Mecca and Medina. In Alkamil Province of Saudi Arabia, brucellosis prevalence were 5.88% in sheep and 4.87% in goats [
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The serological evidence for Brucella infection in camels was 8% in Riyadh and Al-Kharj cities [
 <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In the present study, brucellosis seroprevalence in the locally bred animals was higher than in imported ones with a highly significant correlation (
 <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.01). Also, it was much higher in females than in males with a highly significant correlation with male animals (
 <italic>p</italic> &gt; 0.01). Higher seroprevalence in females could be attributed to the physiological stresses as pregnancy and suckling which affect their resistance to infection and also the females staying longer due to their reproduction role in the herd. Lower seroprevalence in males could also be attributed to the fact that male sheep and goats are usually provided with adequate feed and water. This disagreed with previous studies in Saudi Arabia, where male and female animals showed no significant difference in brucellosis seroprevalence [
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].
</p>
