<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <title>Acknowledgements</title>
 <p>European Consensus Working Group on Late Presentation for Viral Hepatitis Care: Stanislas Pol, European Association for the Study of the Liver (EASL), Paris; Maria Buti, EASL, Barcelona; Stefan Mauss, EASL, Düsseldorf; Erika Duffell, European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control (ECDC); Stefan Wiktor, Team Lead, Global Hepatitis Programme, World Health Organization (WHO), Geneva; Antons Mozalevskis, WHO Regional Office for Europe, Copenhagen; Irene Veldhuijzen, Public Health Service Rotterdam, the HEPscreen project, Hilje Logtenberg-van der Grient, European Liver Patients Association (ELPA); Nikos Dedes, European AIDS Treatment Group (EATG); Charles Gore, Hepatitis C Trust, World Hepatitis Alliance; Eberhard Schatz, Foundation De Regenboog Groep (FRG) representing Correlation Network, Hepatitis C Initiative; José Gatell, University of Barcelona, European AIDS Clinical Society (EACS); Jeffrey V Lazarus, Copenhagen HIV Programme (CHIP), Rigshospitalet, University of Copenhagen; Jens Lundgren, CHIP, Rigshospitalet, University of Copenhagen, EACS; Dorthe Raben, CHIP, Rigshospitalet, University of Copenhagen; Jürgen Rockstroh, University of Bonn, EACS, Chair of HIV in Europe; Brian West, European AIDS Treatment Group (EATG), Co-chair of HIV in Europe; Jordi Casabona, Centre d'Estudis Epidemiològics sobre les Infeccions de Transmissió Sexual i Sida de Catalunya (CEISCATT), Barcelona; Nikos Dedes, EATG, Greece.</p>
 <sec id="FPar1">
  <title>Funding</title>
  <p>The HIV in Europe initiative has received unrestricted funding from Gilead Sciences, Merck, Tibotec, Pfizer, Schering-Plough, Abbott, Boehringer Ingelheim, Bristol-Myers Squibb, GlaxoSmithKline, and ViiV Healthcare. The operational procedures within the initiative include the following, to maintain the autonomy of the initiative: the Steering Committee is the governing body on which sponsors have no representation; data, records, reports, intellectual property rights and know-how generated as result of the initiative shall be deemed vested in and the property of the Steering Committee, represented by AIDS Fonds Netherlands and CHIP Department of Infectious Diseases, Rigshospitalet. CHIP has received funding from the European Union for the OptTEST project, within the framework of the Second Health Programme (2008–2013), and the Danish National Research Foundation (grant number DNRF126). The funders had no role in the study design, analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar2">
  <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
  <p>Not applicable.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar3">
  <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
  <p>SM, JL, JR made substantial contributions to the conception and design; SM, MB, JL, SP, DR, and JR performed analysis and interpretation; SM, JL, ED, DR, and JR drafted the article; SM, MB, ED, HL, AM, JL, JL, SP, DR, CG, ES, SW, and JR critically revised the manuscript for important intellectual content. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar4">
  <title>Competing interests</title>
  <p>SM has received honoraria for speaking and advisory boards from AbbVie, Bristol-Myers Squibb (BMS), Gilead, Janssen, Merck Sharp and Dohme (MSD), and ViiV Healthcare; SP has received honoraria for speaking and advisory boards from AbbVie, BMS, Gilead, Janssen, and MSD; MB has received honoraria for speaking and advisory boards from AbbVie, Gilead, Janssen, and Merck; JKR has received honoraria for speaking and advisory boards from Abbott, Abbvie, Gilead, Hexal, Janssen, Merck and ViiV; JVL has received speaker fees and/or research grants from AbbVie, Gilead Sciences, and MSD; ES has received grants/research support from AbbVie, and Gilead. All other authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar5">
  <title>Consent for publication</title>
  <p>Not applicable.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar6">
  <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
  <p>Not applicable.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar7">
  <title>Publisher’s Note</title>
  <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
 </sec>
</ack>
