<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">The pathophysiological mechanism of respiratory failure in COVID-19 infection is not clear at present but there is an increasing body of evidence suggesting microthrombosis of the pulmonary vasculature is a key player (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). In COVID-19 pneumonitis, histological changes showed pauci-inflammatory septal capillary injury with significant septal capillary fibrin deposition and neutrophil infiltration of alveolar septa [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Viral cytopathic and classical acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) changes such as diffuse alveolar damage with hyaline membranes or hyperplasia of type II pneumocyte were not prominent. Deposits of terminal complement components C5b-9, C4d, and mannose binding lectin-associated serine protease (MASP) in the microvasculature was noted, suggesting activation of the alternative and lectin-based complement pathways. Another study with lung autopsy findings from ten patients showed predominantly proliferative diffuse alveolar damage, epithelial viral cytopathic effects of small airway epithelium, but minimal lymphocytic infiltration [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. The lung injury observed in this study was secondary to formation of fibrinous thrombi in small pulmonary arteriole, endothelial tumefaction, and megakaryocyte aggregation in pulmonary capillaries, suggesting activation of coagulation cascade with microthrombus formation. The term “microvascular COVID-19 lung vessels obstructive thrombo-inflammatory syndrome (microCLOTS)” has been proposed to describe the thrombo-inflammatory lung pathology [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. The working hypothesis is that in individuals at risk of severe disease, an inflammatory reaction and pulmonary microvascular thrombosis leading to alveolar damage is initiated. Because of the systemic endotheliitis, this thrombo-inflammatory syndrome may progress to involve a microvascular bed of other major organs contributing to multi-organ failure. It is increasingly recognized that in this infection, pulmonary thrombus develops due to a local inflammatory reaction. Platelets interacting with the vascular wall, leukocytes, factor XIIa, Von Willebrand factor and complement leads to an intense thrombo-inflammation, which is a direct consequence of vascular damage associated with viral infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].
</p>
