<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since HCoV-19 emerged recently in the human population, we do not know for certain the origins of this virus and much work remains to be done. There are several websites and servers, such as the 2019 Novel Coronavirus Resource (2019nCoVR: https://bigd.big.ac.cn/ncov/) and GISAID (https://www.gisaid.org/), showing the genomic epidemiology and clustering of HCoV-19 genomes in the human population, and the information there helped scientists to understand mutations in HCoV-19, designing proper diagnostic kits, and tracing ongoing outbreaks across the world. Based on a distorted elucidation and/or improper analysis of the initially released, limited numbers of HCoV-19 genome data, there are several speculations or conspiracy theories that HCoV-19 was artificially generated in the laboratory (
 <xref rid="bAndersen2020" ref-type="bibr">Andersen et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bLiu2020" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2020</xref>), especially the insertion of a poly-basic (furin) cleavage site in the spike protein, which was found for the first time in beta-coronaviruses (
 <xref rid="bAndersen2020" ref-type="bibr">Andersen et al., 2020</xref>). Based on the information and knowledge gained from past SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV epidemics, combined with the successful detection and isolation of SARS-like coronaviruses (Bat-CoV-RaTG13) in bats (
 <italic>R. affinis</italic>) with over 95% similarity to HCoV-19, it can be postulated with a degree of confidence that this novel coronavirus likely also originated from bats (
 <xref rid="bZhou2020a" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2020a</xref>). In addition, the insertion of “PAA” on the cleavage site between S1 and S2 has now been found in a coronavirus genome identified in another bat (
 <italic>R. malaynus</italic>) (
 <xref rid="bZhou2020b" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2020b</xref>). These results further indicate at least two bat species, 
 <italic>R. affinis</italic> and 
 <italic>R. malaynus</italic>, may be the putative natural hosts of HCoV-19, and confirmed that bats are likely the animal reservoir for the SARS-like (
 <xref rid="bShi2008" ref-type="bibr">Shi &amp; Hu, 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bWang2006" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2006</xref>) and HCoV-19-like coronaviruses. So far, there is no conclusive evidence showing that bats can directly transmit the HCoV-19-like coronaviruses to humans. 
</p>
