<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>China's fight against COVID-19: What we have done and what we should do next?</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.28.20046086</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.28.20046086</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Background: On 12 March, the World Health Organization Director-General declared that "the threat of a global pandemic has become a reality", and the disease caused by the novel coronavirus, known as COVID-19, has become a global concern. Chinese efforts in curbing the virus have widely been recognized. Even the WHO has lauded the efforts of the Chinese government and advised the world to learn from China in fighting the disease. Since the outbreak of COVID-19, to curb the spread of the epidemic, the Chinese government has implemented unprecedented prevention interventions at the nationwide level. Currently, the outbreak in Wuhan is changing in a positive direction and has been effectively controlled. However, it is not clear what these measures were and how these measures changed to curb the outbreak of COVID-19 quickly. This study explored the characteristics and identified that China's control strategies have changed the epidemiological curve of rapidly rising new confirmed cases of COVID-19. This study also seeks to expand the experiences and lessons from this outbreak. Methods: We collected public health interventions measures from Jan 20, 2020, to 5 March 2020, and data from COVID-19 daily newly confirmed cases and daily cumulates cases to compare the control effects and changing trends. We performed a retrospective description of these intervention strategies from three stages. Besides, from the perspective of public health, the experiences and lessons exposed by this outbreak were roughly summarized. Results: These non-pharmacology interventions measures adopted by the Chinese government by the instruction and spirit of President Xi Jinping were timely and efficient. Conclusions: The present study was conducted to comprehensively analyze from a social epidemiology context. The results confirmed that these radical interventions taken by the Chinese government were effective, ambitious, and agile. However, we must be aware that the epidemic situation in Wuhan is still challenging. Keywords: China; COVID-19; intervention measures; change features, lessons</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Cheng, S.; Zhao, Y.; Kaminga, A. C.; Zhang, P.; Xu, H.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-30</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>