<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>A deep learning algorithm using CT images to screen for Corona Virus Disease (COVID-19)</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.02.14.20023028</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.02.14.20023028</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Background: To control the spread of Corona Virus Disease (COVID-19), screening large numbers of suspected cases for appropriate quarantine and treatment is a priority. Pathogenic laboratory testing is the diagnostic gold standard but it is time consuming with significant false negative results. Fast and accurate diagnostic methods are urgently needed to combat the disease. Based on COVID-19 radiographical changes in CT images, we aimed to develop a deep learning method that could extract COVID-19's graphical features in order to provide a clinical diagnosis ahead of the pathogenic test, thus saving critical time for disease control. Methods and Findings: We collected 1,065CT images of pathogen-confirmed COVID-19 cases (325 images) along with those previously diagnosed with typical viral pneumonia (740 images). We modified the Inception transfer-learning model to establish the algorithm, followed by internal and external validation. The internal validation achieved a total accuracy of 89.5% with specificity of 0.88 and sensitivity of 0.87. The external testing dataset showed a total accuracy of 79.3% with specificity of 0.83 and sensitivity of 0.67. In addition, in 54 COVID-19 images that first two nucleic acid test results were negative, 46 were predicted as COVID-19 positive by the algorithm, with the accuracy of 85.2%. Conclusion: These results demonstrate the proof-of-principle for using artificial intelligence to extract radiological features for timely and accurate COVID-19 diagnosis.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Wang, S.; Kang, B.; Ma, J.; Zeng, X.; Xiao, M.; Guo, J.; Cai, M.; Yang, J.; Li, Y.; Meng, X.; Xu, B.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-02-17</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>