<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Generalized anxiety disorder, depressive symptoms and sleep quality during COVID-19 epidemic in China: a web-based cross-sectional survey</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.02.19.20025395</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.02.19.20025395</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Background: China has been severely affected by COVID-19 (Corona Virus Disease 2019) since December, 2019. This study aimed to assess the population mental health burden during the epidemic, and to explore the potential influence factors. Methods: Using a web-based cross-sectional survey, we collected data from 7,236 self-selected volunteers assessed with demographic information, COVID-19 related knowledge, Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 (GAD-7), Center for Epidemiology Scale for Depression (CES-D), and Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI). Logistic regressions were used to identify influence factors associated with mental health problem. Results: Of the total sample analyzed, the overall prevalence of GAD, depressive symptoms, and sleep quality were 35.1%, 20.1%, and 18.2%, respectively. Young people reported a higher prevalence of GAD and depressive symptoms than older people (P&lt;0.001). Compared with other occupational group, healthcare workers have the highest rate of poor sleep quality (P&lt;0.001). Multivariate logistic regression showed that age (&lt; 35 years) and times to focus on the COVID-19 ([&amp;ge;] 3 hours per day) were associated with GAD, and healthcare workers were associated with poor sleep quality. Conclusions: Our study identified a major mental health burden of the public during COVID-19 epidemic in China. Young people, people who spent too much time on the epidemic, and healthcare workers were at high risk for mental illness. Continuous surveillance and monitoring of the psychological consequences for outbreaks should become routine as part of preparedness efforts worldwide.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Huang, Y.; Zhao, N.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-02-23</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>