<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Longitudinal analysis of laboratory findings during the process of recovery for patients with COVID-19</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.04.04.20053280</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.04.04.20053280</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Objective To explore longitudinal change patterns of key laboratory tests in patients with COVID-19, and to identify independent prognostic factors by examining the associations between laboratory findings and outcomes of patients. Methods The multicenter study prospectively included 59 patients with COVID-19 treated at Jilin province from January 21, 2020 to May 5, 2020. Laboratory tests were included haematological, biochemical, and immunological tests. Results Laboratory findings, the characteristics of epidemiological and demographic data were extracted from electronic medical records. Eosinopenia was shown in 52.6% cases at onset, and the average value of eosinophil continued to significantly increase thereafter. Lymphopenia was found in 40.4% cases at onset, and the average value of lymphocyte was slowly elevated after day 5. Thrombocytopenia was shown in 12.3% cases at onset, and the average value of mean platelet volume was decreased sharply after day 7. The values of aspartate aminotransferase, lactate dehydrogenase, creatine kinase, creatinine kinase-muscle/brain activity, and cardiac troponin I, serum cardiac markers, were beyond the upper limit of RI from 6.1% to 30.6% at onset. The abnormity of liver function tests, kidney function tests, electrolytes was 2.0%~59.2%, 2.0%~4.1%, 6.0%~30.0%, respectively. Eosinophil, platelet and carbondioxide combining power were selected as the prognostic factors. Conclusions The haematological, biochemical, and immunological tests were found significant abnormity at onset and longitudinal change patterns in the patients with COVID-19. Age, Eosinophil, PLT and CO2 may used to predict the recovery probability. Risk stratification and management could be improved for the patients with COVID-19 according to temporal trajectories of laboratory tests.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Tian, S.; Zhu, X.; Sun, X.; Wang, J.; Zhou, Q.; Wang, C.; Chen, L.; Xu, J.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-04-07</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>