<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Insights into The Codon Usage Bias of 13 Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) Isolates from Different Geo-locations</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.04.01.019463</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://biorxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.04.01.019463</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) is the causative agent of Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) which is an infectious disease that spread throughout the world and was declared as a pandemic by the World Health Organization (WHO). In the present study, we analyzed genome-wide codon usage patterns in 13 SARS-CoV-2 isolates from different geo-locations (countries) by utilizing different CUB measurements. Nucleotide and di-nucleotide compositions displayed bias toward A/U content in all codon positions and CpU-ended codons preference, respectively. Relative Synonymous Codon Usage (RSCU) analysis revealed 8 common putative preferred codons among all the 13 isolates. Interestingly, all of the latter codons are A/U-ended (U-ended: 7, A-ended: 1). Cluster analysis (based on RSCU values) was performed and showed comparable results to the phylogenetic analysis (based on their whole genome sequences) indicating that the CUB pattern may reflect the evolutionary relationship between the tested isolates. To investigate the force (mutation and/or selection) influencing the pattern of CUB in SARS-CoV-2 coding sequences, we employed the following; (i). Effective number of codons (ENc), (ii). ENc-GC3 plot, (iii). Neutrality plot, and (iv) Codon adaptation index (CAI). According to their results, natural selection and/or other factors (not investigated in this study) may be the dominant force driving SARS-CoV-2 CUB. It is also worth mentioning that, by using the most expressed genes in human lung tissues as a reference set, some viral genes such as Nucleocapsid phosphoprotein, ORF7a protein, and surface glycoprotein had high CAI values which may indicate for selection force acting on their codon usage, as they play important roles in viral assembly and may help viruses avoid the host immune system. The outcome of our study may help in understanding the underlying factors involved in the evolution of SARS-CoV-2 viruses, and the interactions with their host. Also, it may aid in vaccine design strategies.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Anwar, A. M.; Khodary, S. M.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-04-02</rel_date>
    <rel_site>biorxiv</rel_site>
</item>