<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Ocular manifestations and clinical characteristics of 534 cases of COVID-19 in China: A cross-sectional study</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.12.20034678</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.12.20034678</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Objective: The novel coronavirus disease (COVID-19) was first reported in Wuhan, China in December 2019 and is now pandemic all over the world. Previous study has reported several COVID-19 cases with conjunctivitis. However, the complete profiling of COVID-19 related ocular symptoms and diseases are still missing. We aim to investigate the ocular manifestations and clinical characteristics of COVID-19 patients. Methods: A total of five hundred and thirty-four patients were recruited at Mobile Cabin Hospital and Tongji Hospital. We collected information on demographic characteristics, exposure history, ocular symptoms, systemic concomitant symptoms, eye drop medication, eye protections, radiologic findings, and SARS-CoV-2 detection in nasopharyngeal swabs by RT-PCR from questionnaires and electronic medical records. Results: The median age of patients was 40 and 50 years at Mobile Cabin Hospital and Tongji Hospital, respectively. Of 534 COVID-19 patients, 25 patients (4.68%) presented with conjunctival congestion and 3 patients had conjunctival congestion as the initial symptom. The average duration of conjunctival congestion was 4.9 {+/-} 2.6 days (mean [SD]), ranging from 2 to 10 days. Dry eye (112, 20.97%), blurred vision (68, 12.73%), and foreign body sensation (63, 11.80%) ranked as the top three COVID-19 related ocular symptoms. Notably, a total of 332 COVID-19 patients (62%) had a hand-eye contact history. We also found that some COVID-19 patients had a history of eye disease, including conjunctivitis (33, 6.18%), dry eye (24, 4.49%), keratitis (14, 2.62%), cataract (9, 1.69%), and diabetic retinopathy (5, 0.94%). In consistent with previous studies, the most common clinical symptoms were fever, cough, and fatigue. Patients, 60.5% in Mobile Cabin Hospital and 67.5% in Tongji Hospital, respectively were confirmed with positive SARS-CoV-2 detection. Conclusions: Conjunctival congestion was one of the COVID-19 related ocular symptoms, which may have clinical diagnostic significance. It is essential to provide eye-care equipment and strengthen education on eye protection, as dirty hand-eye contact might be a high risk factor of COVID-19. Further detailed and comprehensive ophthalmological guidance is needed for COVID-19 control.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Chen, L.; Deng, C.; Chen, X.; Zhang, X.; Chen, B.; Yu, H.; Qin, Y.; Xiao, K.; Zhang, H.; Sun, X.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-16</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>