<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Clinical and radiographic features of cardiac injury in patients with 2019 novel coronavirus pneumonia</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.02.24.20027052</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.02.24.20027052</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Objective: To investigate the correlation between clinical characteristics and cardiac injury of COVID-2019 pneumonia. Methods: In this retrospective, single-center study, 41 consecutive corona virus disease 2019 (COVID-2019) patients (including 2 deaths) of COVID-2019 in Beijing Youan Hospital, China Jan 21 to Feb 03, 2020, were involved in this study. The high risk factors of cardiac injury in different COVID-2019 patients were analyzed. Computed tomographic (CT) imaging of epicardial adipose tissue (EAT) has been used to demonstrate the cardiac inflammation of COVID-2019. ResultsOf the 41 COVID-2019 patients, 2 (4.88%), 32 (78.05%), 4 (9.75%) and 3 (7.32%) patients were clinically diagnosed as light, mild, severe and critical cases, according to the 6th guidance issued by the National Health Commission of China. 10 (24.4%) patients had underlying complications, such as hypertension, CAD, type 2 diabetes mellites and tumor. The peak value of TnI in critical patients is 40-fold more than normal value. 2 patients in the critical group had the onset of atrial fibrillation, and the peak heart rates reached up to 160 bpm. CT scan showed low EAT density in severe and critical patients. Conclusion: Our results indicated that cardiac injury of COVID-2019 was rare in light and mild patients, while common in severe and critical patients. Therefore, the monitoring of the heart functions of COVID-2019 patients and applying potential interventions for those with abnormal cardiac injury related characteristics, is vital to prevent the fatality.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Hui, H.; Zhang, Y.; Yang, X.; Wang, X.; He, B.; Li, L.; Li, H.; Tian, J.; Chen, Y.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-02-27</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>