<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Epidemiological Characteristics of COVID-19: A Systemic Review and Meta-Analysis</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.04.01.20050138</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.04.01.20050138</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Background: Our understanding of the corona virus disease 2019 (COVID-19) continues to evolve. However, there are many unknowns about its epidemiology. Purpose: To synthesize the number of deaths from confirmed COVID-19 cases, incubation period, as well as time from onset of COVID-19 symptoms to first medical visit, ICU admission, recovery and death of COVID-19. Data Sources: MEDLINE, Embase, and Google Scholar from December 01, 2019 through to March 11, 2020 without language restrictions as well as bibliographies of relevant articles. Study Selection: Quantitative studies that recruited people living with or died due to COVID-19. Data Extraction: Two independent reviewers extracted the data. Conflicts were resolved through discussion with a senior author. Data Synthesis: Out of 1675 non-duplicate studies identified, 57 were included. Pooled mean incubation period was 5.84 (99% CI: 4.83, 6.85) days. Pooled mean number of days from the onset of COVID-19 symptoms to first clinical visit was 4.82 (95% CI: 3.48, 6.15), ICU admission was 10.48 (95% CI: 9.80, 11.16), recovery was 17.76 (95% CI: 12.64, 22.87), and until death was 15.93 (95% CI: 13.07, 18.79). Pooled probability of COVID-19-related death was 0.02 (95% CI: 0.02, 0.03). Limitations: Studies are observational and findings are mainly based on studies that recruited patient from clinics and hospitals and so may be biased toward more severe cases. Conclusion: We found that the incubation period and lag between the onset of symptoms and diagnosis of COVID-19 is longer than other respiratory viral infections including MERS and SARS; however, the current policy of 14 days of mandatory quarantine for everyone might be too conservative. Longer quarantine periods might be more justified for extreme cases.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Khalili, M.; Karamouzian, M.; Nasiri, N.; Javadi, S.; Mirzazadeh, A.; Sharifi, H.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-04-06</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>