<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Epidemiological and clinical characteristics of SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV: a system review</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.02.20.20025601</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.02.20.20025601</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Importance: In 2002-2003, a severe pulmonary infectious disease occurred in Guangdong, China. The disease was caused by SARS-CoV, 17 years apart, also happen in China, and SARS-CoV-2, this epidemic has posed a significant hazard to people health both China and the whole world. Objective: Summarized the latest epidemiological changes, clinical manifestations, auxiliary examination and pathological characteristics of COVID-19. Evidence Review: PubMed database were searched from 2019 to 2020 using the index terms novel coronavirus or COVID-19 or 2019-nCoV or SARS-CoV-2 and synonyms. Articles that reported clinical characteristics, laboratory results, imageological diagnosis and pathologic condition were included and were retrospectively reviewed for these cases. This paper adopts the method of descriptive statistics. Results: 34 COVID-19-related articles were eligible for this systematic review;Four of the articles were related to pathology. We found that Fever (86.0%), cough (63.9%) and Malaise/Fatigue (34.7%) were the most common symptoms in COVID-19. But in general, the clinical symptoms and signs of COVID-19 were not obvious. Compared with SARS, COVID-19 was transmitted in a more diverse way. The mortality rates of COVID-19 were 2.5%, and the overall infection rate of healthcare worker of COVID-19 was 3.9%. We also found that the pathological features of COVID-19 have greatly similar with SARS, which manifested as ARDS. But the latest pathological examination of COVID-19 revealed the obvious mucinous secretions in the lungs. Interpretation: The clinical and pathological characteristics of SARS and COVID-19 in China are very similar, but also difference. The latest finds of pathological examination on COVID-19 may upend existing treatment schemes, so the early recognition of disease by healthcare worker is very important.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>yaqian, m.; Lin, W.; Wen, J.; Chen, G.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-02-25</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>