<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Strategies for vaccine design for corona virus using Immunoinformatics techniques</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.02.27.967422</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://biorxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.02.27.967422</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>The cutting-edge technology vaccinomics is the combination of two topics immunogenetics and immunogenomics with the knowledge of systems biology and immune profiling for designing vaccine against infectious disease. In our present study, an epitope-based peptide vaccine against nonstructural protein 4 of beta coronavirus, using a combination of B cell and T cell epitope predictions, followed by molecular docking methods are performed. Here, protein sequences of homologous nonstructural protein 4 of beta coronavirus are collected and conserved regions present in them are investigated via phylogenetic study to determine the most immunogenic part of protein. From the identified region of the target protein, the peptide sequence IRNTTNPSAR from the region ranging from 38-47 and the sequence PTDTYTSVYLGKFRG from the positions of 76-90 are considered as the most potential B cell and T cell epitopes respectively. Furthermore, this predicted T cell epitopes PTDTYTSVY and PTDTYTSVYLGKFRG interacted with MHC allelic proteins HLA-A*01:01 and HLA-DRB5*01:01 respectively with the low IC50 values. These epitopes are perfectly fitted into the epitope binding grooves of alpha helix of MHC I molecule and MHC II molecule with binding energy scores -725.0 Kcal/mole and -786.0 Kcal/mole respectively, showing stability in MHC molecules binding. This MHC restricted epitope PTDTYTSVY also showed a good conservancy of 50.16% in world population coverage. This MHC I HLA-A*01:01 allele is present among 58.87% of Chinese population also. Therefore, the epitopes IRNTTNPSAR and PTDTYTSVYLGKFRG may be considered as potential peptides for peptide-based vaccine for coronavirus after further experimental study.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Basu, A.; Sarkar, A.; Maulik, U.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-02</rel_date>
    <rel_site>biorxiv</rel_site>
</item>