<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Radiographic Findings and other Predictors in Adults with Covid-19</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.23.20041673</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.23.20041673</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>As of March 20, 2020, there were 234,073 confirmed cases of coronavirus disease 2019 (Covid-19) and 9,840 deaths worldwide. Older age and elevated d-dimer are reported risk factors for Covid-19. However, whether early radiographic change is a predictor of fatality remains unknown. We retrospectively reviewed records of all laboratory-confirmed patients admitted to a quarantine unit at Tongji Hospital, a large regional hospital in Wuhan, China, between January 31 and March 5, 2020. The Tongji Hospital ethics committee approved this study. A total of 128 patients were admitted. 102 patients were confirmed to have severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infection using RNA detection. As of March 20, 82 confirmed patients were discharged, 15 died, and 5 remained hospitalized. The median age was 57 years (range, 27 - 85), 59 (58%) were male, and 44 (43%) patients had a comorbidity. The most common symptoms were fever, cough, and dyspnea. When compared with survivors, non-survivors were older and more likely to have lymphopenia, elevated lactate dehydrogenase (LDH), elevated d-dimer, and increased hypersensitive troponin I. In a multivariate regression model that included these predictors, older age and elevated LDH were independent risk factors for fatality. Twenty-one survivors and 11 non-survivors had CT scans within the first week. We used severity score to quantify the extent of lung opacification as described in the Supplementary Appendix. The total severity score and number of involved lung lobes within the first week were significantly greater in non-survivors compared to survivors . Using univariate logistic regression analysis, higher total severity score ([&amp;ge;]15) (odds ratio 53, 95% CI 3-369; p = 0.003), and more involved lung lobes (5 involved lobes) (9, 2-53; p = 0.016) in CT images within the first week were significantly associated with fatality. Moreover, in this subset of patients with CT data within the first week, higher total severity score was the only independent risk factor in a multivariate analysis incorporated the predictors discussed above (older age, lymphocytopenia, elevated LDH, elevated d-dimer, and increased troponin I). For survivors with serial CT scans performed over four weeks, total severity score peaked in the second week. This report suggests that the extent of lung lesions in early CT images is a potential predictor of poor outcome of Covid-19. This will help clinicians to identify the patients with poor prognosis at early stage.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Li, K.; Chen, D.; Chen, S.; Feng, Y.; Chang, C.; Wang, Z.; Wang, N.; Zhen, G.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-27</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>