<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Triaging patients in the outbreak of the 2019 novel coronavirus</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.13.20035212</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.13.20035212</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>In the end of 2019, the epidemic of a new coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) occurred in Wuhan and spread rapidly. Changsha, a city located south to the epicenter, was soon impacted. To control the transmission of the coronavirus and avoid nosocomial infection, triage procedures based on epidemiology were implemented in a local hospital of the city. This retrospective study analyzed the data collected during the triage period and found that COVID-19 patients were enriched seven folds into the Section A designated for rapid detection and quarantine. On the other side, roughly triple amounts of visits were received at the Section B for patients without obvious epidemiological history. Eight COVID-19 cases were spotted out of 247 suspected patients. More than 50% of the suspected patients were submitted to multiple rounds of nucleic acid analysis for SARS-CoV-2 infection. Of the 239 patients who were diagnosed as negative of the virus infection,188 were successfully revisited and none was reported as a COVID-19 case. Of the eight COVID-19 patients, three were confirmed only after multiple rounds of nucleic acid analysis. Besides comorbidities, delayed sharing of epidemiological history added another layer of complexity to the diagnosis in practice. While SARS-CoV-2 epidemic is being alerted in many countries, our report will be helpful to other colleagues in rapid identification of COVID-19 cases and controlling the transmission of the disease.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Huang, G.; Zeng, W.; Wang, W.; Song, Y.; Mo, X.; Li, J.; Wu, P.; Wang, R.; Zhou, F.; Wu, J.; Yi, B.; Xiong, Z.; Zhou, L.; Wang, F.; Tian, Y.; Hu, W.; Xu, X.; Zhai, R.; Yuan, K.; Li, X.; Qiu, X.; Qiu, J.; Wang, A.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-16</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>