<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Comparative genomic analysis revealed specific mutation pattern between human coronavirus SARS-CoV-2 and Bat-SARSr-CoV RaTG13</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.02.27.969006</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://biorxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.02.27.969006</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>The novel coronavirus SARS-CoV-2 (2019-nCoV) is a member of the family coronaviridae and contains a single-stranded RNA genome with positive-polarity. To reveal the evolution mechanism of SARS-CoV-2 genome, we performed comprehensive genomic analysis with newly sequenced SARS-CoV-2 strains and 20 closely related coronavirus strains. Among 98 nucleotide mutations at 93 sites of the genome among different SARS-CoV-2 strains, 58 of them caused amino acid change, indicating a result of neutral evolution. However, the ratio of nucleotide substitutions to amino acid substitutions of spike gene (9.07) between SARS-CoV-2 WIV04 and Bat-SARSr-CoV RaTG13 was extensively higher than those from comparisons between other coronaviruses (range 1.29 - 4.81). The elevated synonymous mutations between SARS-CoV-2 and RaTG13, suggesting they underwent stronger purifying selection. Moreover, their nucleotide substitutions are enriched with T:C transition, which is consistent with the mutation signature caused by deactivity of RNA 3-to-5 exoribonuclease (ExoN). The codon usage was similar between SARS-CoV-2 and other strains in beta-coronavirus lineage B, suggesting it had small impact on the mutation pattern. In comparison of SARS-CoV-2 WIV04 with Bat-SARSr-CoV RaTG13, the ratios of non-synonymous to synonymous substitution rates (dN/dS) was the lowest among all performed comparisons, reconfirming the evolution of SARS-CoV-2 under stringent selective pressure. Moreover, some sites of spike protein might be subjected to positive selection. Therefore, our results will help understanding the evolutionary mechanisms contribute to viral pathogenicity and its adaptation with hosts.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Lv, L.; Li, G.; Chen, J.; Liang, X.; Li, Y.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-02</rel_date>
    <rel_site>biorxiv</rel_site>
</item>