<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>The landscape of lung bronchoalveolar immune cells in COVID-19 revealed by single-cell RNA sequencing</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.02.23.20026690</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.02.23.20026690</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>The novel coronavirus SARS-CoV-2, etiological agent of recently named Coronavirus infected disease (COVID-19) by WHO, has caused more than 2, 000 deaths worldwide since its emergency in Wuhan City, Hubei province, China, in December, 2019. The symptoms of COVID-19 varied from modest, mild to acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), and the latter of which is generally associated with deregulated immune cytokine production; however, we currently know little as to the interplay between the extent of clinical symptoms and the compositions of lung immune microenvironment. Here, we comprehensively characterized the lung immune microenvironment with the bronchoalveolar lavage fluid (BALF) from 3 severe and 3 mild COVID-19 patients and 8 previously reported healthy lung controls through single-cell RNA sequence (scRNA-seq) combined with TCR-seq. Our data shows that monocyte-derived FCN1+ macrophages, whereas notFABP4+ alveolar macrophages that represent a predominant macrophage subset in BALF from patients with mild diseases, overwhelm in the severely damaged lungs from patients with ARDS. These cells are highly inflammatory and enormous chemokine producers implicated in cytokine storm. Furthermore, the formation of tissue resident, highly expanded clonal CD8+ T cells in the lung microenvironment of mild symptom patients suggests a robust adaptive immune response connected to a better control of COVID-19. This study first reported the cellular atlas of lung bronchoalveolar immune microenvironment in COVID-19 patients at the single-cell resolution, and unveiled the potential immune mechanisms underlying disease progression and protection in COVID-19.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Liao, M.; Liu, Y.; Yuan, J.; Wen, Y.; Xu, G.; Zhao, J.; Chen, L.; Li, J.; Wang, X.; Wang, F.; Liu, L.; Zhang, S.; Zhang, Z.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-02-26</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>