<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Clinical features and outcomes of 197 adult discharged patients with COIVD-19 in Yichang, Hubei</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.26.20041426</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.26.20041426</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Purpose To investigate the epidemiology and clinical features of discharged adult patients with COVID-19 in Yichang. Method The retrospective study recruited 197 cases of COVID-19 discharged from Yichang Central People's Hospital and Yichang Third People's Hospital from Jan 17 to Feb 26, 2020. All cases were confirmed by real-time RT-PCR or chest computer tomography (CT).The survivors were followed up until March 4,2020. Clinical data, including demographic characteristic, presentation, exposure history, laboratory examination, radiology and prognosis were enrolled and analyzed by SPSS 19.0 software. Results There were 197 adult discharged patients with COVID-19 in this study. Statistical analysis indicated that the average age was 55.94 years, and female patients were 50.3%. Those patients mainly resided in urban with exposure history in 2 weeks. Fever, cough and weakness were the common symptoms. Leucocytes were mainly normal or decreased in 185 patents, both lymphocytes and eosinophils reduced, the ratios were 56.9% and 50.3%, respectively. On the contrary, lactate dehydrogenases raised in 65 patients. C-reactive protein elevated in the most of patients. The sensitivity of RT-PCR was 63.5%. Chest CT indicated that bilateral patchy shadows were the most common imaging manifestations.169 patients recovered and transferred to a designated hospital for observation, and the others turned worst and died of acute respiratory failure. Conclusion COIVD-19 infection have become a life-threaten public health problem, the sensitivity of RT-PCR was limited. Chest CT scan was recommended for the suspected patients. Moreover, lymphocytopenia and eosinophils declining without leukocytes increasing may be considered as a useful evidence for the diagnosis.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Zhou, F.; Yu, X.; Tong, X.; Zhang, R.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-30</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>