<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Prevalence and Factors Associated with Depression and Anxiety of Hospitalized Patients with COVID-19</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.24.20043075</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.24.20043075</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Objective: The 2019 coronavirus disease (COVID-19) epidemic has raised international concern. Mental health is becoming an issue that cannot be ignored in our fight against it. This study aimed to explore the prevalence and factors linked to anxiety and depression in hospitalized patients with COVID-19. Methods: A total of 144 patients diagnosed with COVID-19 were included in this study. We assessed depression and anxiety symptoms using the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS), and social support using the Perceived Social Support Scale (PSSS) among patients at admission. Multivariate linear regression analyses were performed to identify factors associated with symptoms of anxiety and depression. Results: Of the 144 participants, 34.72% and 28.47% patients with COVID-19 had symptoms of anxiety or depression, respectively. The bivariate correlations showed that less social support was correlated with more anxious (r=-0.196, p&lt;0.05) and depressive (r=-0.360p&lt;0.05) symptoms among patients with COVID-19. The multiple linear regression analysis showed that gender ({beta}=1.446, p=0.034), age ({beta}=0.074, p=0.003), oxygen saturation ({beta} =-2.140, p=0.049), and social support ({beta} =-1.545, p=0.017) were associated with anxiety for COVID-19 patients. Moreover, age ({beta}=0.084, p=0.001), family infection with SARS-CoV-2 ({beta} =1.515, p=0.027) and social support ({beta} =-2.236, p&lt;0.001) were the factors associated with depression. Conclusion: Hospitalized patients with COVID-19 presented features of anxiety and depression. Mental concern and appropriate intervention are essential parts of clinical care for those who are at risk.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Dong, Y.; Su, T.; Jiao, P.; Kong, X.; Zheng, K.; Tang, M.; Kong, F.; Zhou, J.; Diao, L.; Wu, S.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-30</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>