<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Cryptic transmission of SARS-CoV-2 in Washington State</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.04.02.20051417</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.04.02.20051417</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Following its emergence in Wuhan, China, in late November or early December 2019, the SARS-CoV-2 virus has rapidly spread throughout the world. On March 11, 2020, the World Health Organization declared Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) a pandemic. Genome sequencing of SARS-CoV-2 strains allows for the reconstruction of transmission history connecting these infections. Here, we analyze 346 SARS-CoV-2 genomes from samples collected between 20 February and 15 March 2020 from infected patients in Washington State, USA. We found that the large majority of SARS-CoV-2 infections sampled during this time frame appeared to have derived from a single introduction event into the state in late January or early February 2020 and subsequent local spread, strongly suggesting cryptic spread of COVID-19 during the months of January and February 2020, before active community surveillance was implemented. We estimate a common ancestor of this outbreak clade as occurring between 18 January and 9 February 2020. From genomic data, we estimate an exponential doubling between 2.4 and 5.1 days. These results highlight the need for large-scale community surveillance for SARS-CoV-2 introductions and spread and the power of pathogen genomics to inform epidemiological understanding.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Bedford, T.; Greninger, A. L.; Roychoudhury, P.; Starita, L. M.; Famulare, M.; Huang, M.-L.; Nalla, A.; Pepper, G.; Reinhardt, A.; Xie, H.; Shrestha, L.; Nguyen, T. N.; Adler, A.; Brandstetter, E.; Cho, S.; Giroux, D.; Han, P. D.; Fay, K.; Frazar, C. D.; Ilcisin, M.; Lacombe, K.; Lee, J.; Kiavand, A.; Richardson, M.; Sibley, T. R.; Truong, M.; Wolf, C. R.; Nickerson, D. A.; Rieder, M. J.; Englund, J. A.; the Seattle Flu Study Investigators,  ; Hadfield, J.; Hodcroft, E. B.; Huddleston, J.; Moncla, L. H.; Müller, N. F.; Neher, R. A.; Deng, X.; Gu, W.; Federman, S.; Chiu, C.; Duchin, J.; Gautom</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-04-06</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>