<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Correlation Analysis Between Disease Severity and Inflammation-related Parameters in Patients with COVID-19 Pneumonia</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.02.25.20025643</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.02.25.20025643</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Aim: The new coronavirus pneumonia (COVID-19) outbreaking at the end of 2019 is highly contagious. Crude mortality rate reached 49% in critical patients. Inflammation matters on disease progression. This study analyzed blood inflammation indicators among mild, severe and critical patients, helping to identify severe or critical patients early. Methods: In this cross-sectional study, 100 patients were included and divided to mild, severe or critical groups. Correlation of peripheral blood inflammation-related indicators with disease criticality was analyzed. Cut-off values for critically ill patients were speculated through the ROC curve. ResultsSignificantly, disease severity were associated with age (R=-0.564, P&lt;0.001), interleukin-2 receptor (IL2R) (R=-0.534, P&lt;0.001), interleukin-6 (IL-6) (R=-0.535, P&lt;0.001), interleukin-8 (IL-8) (R=-0.308, P&lt;0.001), interleukin-10 (IL-10) (R=-0.422, P&lt;0.001), tumor necrosis factor  (TNF) (R=-0.322, P&lt;0.001), C-reactive protein (CRP) (R=-0.604, P&lt;0.001), ferroprotein (R=-0.508, P&lt;0.001), procalcitonin (R=-0.650, P&lt;0.001), white cell counts (WBC) (R=-0.54, P&lt;0.001), lymphocyte counts (LC) (R=-0.56, P&lt;0.001), neutrophil count (NC) (R=-0.585, P&lt;0.001) and eosinophil counts (EC) (R=-0.299, P=0.01). ConclusionWith following parameters such as age &gt;67.5 years, IL2R &gt;793.5U/mL, CRP &gt;30.7ng/mL, ferroprotein &gt;2252g/L, WBC&gt;9.5*10^9/L or NC &gt;7.305*10^9/L, the progress of COVID-19 to critical stage should be closely observed and possibly prevented. Inflammation is closely related to severity of COVID-19, and IL-6, TNF and IL-8 might be promising therapeutic targets.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Gong, J.; Dong, H.; Xia, S. Q.; Huang, Y. Z.; Wang, D.; Zhao, Y.; Liu, W.; Tu, S.; Zhang, M.; Wang, Q.; Lu, F.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-02-27</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>