<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Anxiety, worry and perceived stress in the world due to the COVID-19 pandemic, March 2020. Preliminary results.</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.04.03.20043992</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.04.03.20043992</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Introduction: Since the beginning of the outbreak in China, ending 2019, the Novel Coronavirus (COVID-19) has spread subsequently to the rest of the world causing an on-going pandemic. The World Health Organisation (WHO) declared COVID-19: a public health emergency of international concern. Having into consideration the lockdown and quarantine situation, we decided to do evaluate the current emotional state on the general population with a web-based survey in English and in Spanish, which was considered a useful and fast method that could help us determine how people perceived stress and worry due to the COVID-19. Methods: The survey included a 22 items, gathering information in 3 sections: Sociodemographic data, the Perceived Stress Scale (PSS-10) by Cohen and additional queries that assessed the current worry and change of behaviours due to this pandemic. Results: The survey received 891 respondents from 25 countries, from March 17 to 23rd, 2020. The mean age of the respondents was 43.8 (14.2) years old, and more than two thirds were women. 12.8% were health personnel.The mean of the PSS-10 score was 17.4 (6.4). Significantly higher scores were observed among women, youth, students, and among those who expressed concern and those who perceived increased susceptibility to the COVID-19. In contrast, no significant differences were observed between the health professionals and the general population. A good correlation was observed between mean relative volume (RSV) of the las 14 days and the number of cases reported (rho = 0.68, p &lt;0.001) and deaths (rho = 0.51, p &lt;0.001). Discussion: With these results we describe an increase of affective symptoms due to the COVID-19. This pandemic is raising the anxiety levels. The findings of our study show the affective and cognitive alterations people are going through. This survey is the first attempt to measure the psychological consequences this pandemic is having, in order to be able to later be able to provide the support to confront this global issue, addressing the mental health care that will be needed.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Limcaoco, R. S. G.; Mateos, E. M.; Fernandez, J. M.; Roncero, C.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-04-06</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>