<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Mechanical Ventilator Milano (MVM):A Novel Mechanical Ventilator Designed for Mass Scale Production in response to the COVID-19 Pandemics</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.24.20042234</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.24.20042234</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>We present here the design of the Mechanical Ventilator Milano (MVM), a novel mechan- ical ventilator designed for mass scale production in response to the COVID-19 pandemics, to compensate for the dramatic shortage of such ventilators in many countries. This venti- lator is an electro-mechanical equivalent of the old, reliable Manley Ventilator. Our design is optimized to permit large sale production in short time and at a limited cost, relying on off-the-shelf components, readily available worldwide from hardware suppliers. Operation of the MVM requires only a source of compressed oxygen (or compressed medical air) and electrical power. The MVM control and monitoring unit can be connected and networked via WiFi so that no additional electrical connections are necessary other than the connection to the electrical power. At this stage the MVM is not a certified medical device. Construction of the first proto- types is starting with a team of engineers, scientists and computing experts. The purpose of this paper is to disseminate the conceptual design of the MVM broadly and to solicit feed- back from the scientific and medical community to speed the process of review, improvement and possible implementation.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Cristiano, G.; Bonivento, W.; Caravati, M.; Razeti, M.; DeCecco, S.; Fiorillo, G.; Gabriele, F.; Tartaglia, R.; Razeto, A.; Sablone, D.; Scapparone, E.; Testera, G.; Rescigno, M.; Franco, D.; Kochanek, I.; Kendziora, C.; Pordes, S. H.; Wang, H.; Ianni, A.; McDonald, A.; Molinari Tosatti, L.; Dinon, T.; Malosio, M.; Minuzzo, D.; Zardoni, A.; Prini, A.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-27</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>