<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>The level of plasma C-reactive protein is closely related to the liver injury in patients with COVID-19</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.02.28.20028514</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.02.28.20028514</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Aims: Corona virus disease 2019 (COVID-19) has rapidly become the most severe public health issue all over the world. Despite respiratory symptoms, hepatic injury has also been observed in clinical settings. This study aimed to investigate the risk factors involved with hepatic injury in the patients with COVID-19. Methods: A total of 85 hospitalized patients who were diagnosed with COVID-19 in Beijing Youan Hospital were retrospectively analyzed. According to liver function, they were divided into ALT normal group (n=52) and ALT elevation group (n=33). Clinical features and laboratory data were compared between the two groups. The independent risk factors for liver injury were analyzed. Results: There were 33 patients with hepatic injury in our study, accounting for 38.8% (33/85). The patients in ALT elevation group were older than those in ALT normal group. The levels of lactic acid, CRP, myoglobin, and neutrophils were significantly higher in ALT elevation group. The lymphocytes and albumin were significantly lower in ALT elevation group. The proportion of severe and critical patients in ALT elevation group was significantly higher. Multivariate logistic regression analysis showed CRP [&amp;ge;]20 mg/L and lymphocyte count&lt; 1.1*10^9/L were independently related to hepatic injury. Conclusions: Lymphopenia and CRP may serve as the risk factors related to hepatic injury in patients with COVID-19, which might be related to inflammatory cytokine storm in liver injury. Early detection and timely treatment of hepatic injury in patients with COVID-19 are necessary.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Li, L.; Li, S.; Xu, M.; Zheng, S.; Duan, Z.; Chen, Y.; Li, J.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-03</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>