<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Single-cell RNA Analysis on ACE2 Expression Provides Insight into SARS-CoV-2 Blood Entry and Heart Injury</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.31.20047621</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.31.20047621</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>COVID-19 is a global pandemic with high infectivity and pathogenicity, accounting for tens of thousands of deaths worldwide. Recent studies have found that the pathogen of COVID-19, SARS-CoV-2, shares the same cell receptor Angiotensin converting enzyme II (ACE2) with SARS-CoV. The pathological investigation of COVID-19 death showed that the lung had the characteristics of pulmonary fibrosis. However, how SARS-CoV-2 spreads from the lungs to other organs has not yet been determined. Here, we performed an unbiased evaluation of cell-type specific expression of ACE2 in healthy and fibrotic lungs, as well as in normal and failed adult human hearts, using published single-cell RNA-seq data. We found that ACE2 expression in fibrotic lungs mainly locates in arterial vascular cells, which might provide the route for bloodstream spreading of SARS-CoV-2. The failed human hearts have a higher percentage of ACE2-expressing cardiomyocytes, and SARS-CoV-2 might attack cardiomyocytes through the bloodstream in patients with heart failure. Moreover, ACE2 was highly expressed in cells infected by RSV or MERS-CoV and in mice treated by LPS. Our findings indicate that patients with pulmonary fibrosis, heart failure, and virus infection have a higher risk and are more susceptible to SARS-CoV-2 infection. SARS-CoV-2 might attack other organs by getting into the bloodstream. This work provides new insights into SARS-CoV-2 blood entry and heart injury and might propose a therapeutic strategy to prevent patients from developing severe complications.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Guo, J.; Wei, X.; Li, Q.; Li, L.; Yang, Z.; Shi, Y.; Qin, Y.; Zhang, X.; Wang, X.; Zhi, X.; Meng, D.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-04-04</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>