<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Correlation between hypophosphatemia and the severity of Corona Virus Disease 2019 patients</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.27.20040816</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.27.20040816</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Objective: Retrospectively analyze the clinical data of Corona Virus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) patients and explore the value of serum phosphorus level in evaluating the severity and prognosis of the disease. Methods: COVID-19 patients transferred from the first emergency ward of Taiyuan fourth people's Hospital from February 8 to March 3, 2020 were selected. The information of general conditions, clinical manifestations, laboratory indexes, nucleic acid detection and treatment were collected. The changes of blood phosphorus level and absolute value of lymphocytes in ordinary and severe/critical patients were recorded and compared. Results: A total of 32 patients with COVID-19 were collected, including 12 cases of common type and 20 cases of severe/critical type. Before treatment, the serum phosphorus levels of the two groups were significantly lower than the normal level, and the serum phosphorus levels of the severe/critical patients were lower than those of the common type patients (t = 2.767, P &lt; 0.010). After treatment, the serum phosphorus levels of the two groups reached normal, and there was no significant difference between the two groups (t = 0.231, P &gt; 0.819). The level of lymphocytes in severe/critical patients was lower than that in normal patients (t = 4.636, P &lt; 0.001) before treatment. After treatment, the absolute value of lymphocytes in the two groups reached normal, and there was no significant difference between the two groups (t=1.208, P=0.237). There was a positive correlation between lymphocytes and serum phosphorus, and the correlation coefficient was 0.479. Conclusion: hypophosphatemia is related to the severity of COVID-19, and strengthening the monitoring of serum phosphorus level of COVID-19's severe/critical patients and correcting hypophosphatemia in time are of significance to improve the prognosis.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Xue, X.; Ma, J.; Zhao, Y.; Zhao, A.; Liu, X.; Guo, W.; Yan, F.; Wang, Z.; Guo, Y.; Fan, M.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-30</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>