<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Study on SARS-COV-2 transmission and the effects of control measures in China</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.02.16.20023770</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.02.16.20023770</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Objective To reconstruct the transmission trajectory of SARS-COV-2 and analyze the effects of control measures in China. Methods Python 3.7.1 was used to write a SEIR class to model the epidemic procedure and a back propagation class to estimate the initial true infected number. The epidemic area in China was divided into three parts, Wuhan city, Hubei province (except Wuhan) and China (except Hubei) based on the different transmission pattern. A limitation factor for the medical resource was imposed to model the infected but not quarantined. Credible data source from Baidu Qianxi were used to assess the number of infected cases migrated from Wuhan to other areas. Results Basic reproduction number, R0, was 3.6 in the very early stage. The true infected number was 4508 in our model in Wuhan before January 22, 2020. By January 22 2020, it was estimated that 1764 infected cases migrated from Wuhan to other cities in Hubei province. Effective reproductive number, R, gradually decreased from 3.6 (Wuhan, stage 1), 3.4 (Hubei except Wuhan, stage 1) and 3.3 (China except Hubei, stage 1) to 0.67 (Wuhan, stage 4), 0.83 (Hubei except Wuhan, stage 2) and 0.63 (China except Hubei, stage 2), respectively. Especially after January 23, 2020 when Wuhan City was closed, the infected number showed a turning point in Wuhan. By early April, there would be 42073, 21342 and 13384 infected cases in Wuhan, Hubei (except Wuhan) and China (except Hubei) respectively, and there would be 2179, 633 and 107 death in Wuhan, Hubei (except Wuhan) and China (except Hubei) respectively. Conclusion A series of control measures in China have effectively prevented the spread of COVID-19, and the epidemic will end in early April.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Zhang, B.; Zhou, H.; Zhou, F.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-02-18</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>