<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Early, low-dose and short-term application of corticosteroid treatment in patients with severe COVID-19 pneumonia: single-center experience from Wuhan, China</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.06.20032342</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.06.20032342</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Background: Severe patients with 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) pneumonia progressed rapidly to acute respiratory failure. We aimed to evaluate the definite efficacy and safety of corticosteroid in the treatment of severe COVID-19 pneumonia. Methods: Forty-six hospitalized patients with severe COVID-19 pneumonia hospitalized at Wuhan Union Hospital from January 20 to February 25, 2020, were retrospectively reviewed. The patients were divided into two groups based on whether they received corticosteroid treatment. The clinical symptoms and chest computed tomography(CT) results were compared. Results: A total of 26 patients received intravenous administration of methylprednisolone with a dosage of 1-2mg/kg/d for 5-7 days, while the remaining patients not. There was no significant difference in age, sex, comorbidities, clinical or laboratory parameters between the two groups on admission. The average number of days for body temperature back to the normal range was significantly shorter in patients with administration of methylprednisolone when compared to those without administration of methylprednisolone (2.06 {+/-} 0.28 vs. 5.29 {+/-} 0.70, P=0.010). The patients with administration of methylprednisolone had a faster improvement of SpO2, while patients without administration of methylprednisolone had a significantly longer interval of using supplemental oxygen therapy (8.2days[IQR 7.0-10.3] vs. 13.5days(IQR 10.3-16); P&lt;0.001). In terms of chest CT, the absorption degree of the focus was significantly better in patients with administration of methylprednisolone. Conclusion: Our data indicate that in patients with severe COVID-19 pneumonia, early, low-dose and short-term application of corticosteroid was associated with a faster improvement of clinical symptoms and absorption of lung focus.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Wang, Y.; Jiang, W.; He, Q.; Wang, C.; Wang, B.; Zhou, P.; Dong, N.; Tong, Q.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-12</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>