<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Epidemiological and clinical features of 2019-nCoV acute respiratory disease cases in Chongqing municipality, China: a retrospective, descriptive, multiple-center study</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.01.20029397</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.01.20029397</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>BackgroundIn January 19, 2020, first case of 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) pneumonia (COVID-19) was confirmed in Chongqing municipality, China. MethodsIn this retrospective, descriptive, multiple-center study, total of 267 patients with COVID-19 confirmed by real-time RT-PCR in Chongqing from Jan 19 to Feb 16, 2020 were recruited. Epidemiological, demographic, clinical, radiological characteristics, laboratory examinations, and treatment regimens were collected on admission. Clinical outcomes were followed up until Feb 16, 2020. Results267 laboratory-confirmed COVID-19 patients admitted to 3 designated-hospitals in Chongqing provincial municipality from January 19 to February 16, 2020 were enrolled and categorized on admission. 217 (81.27%) and 50 (18.73%) patients were categorized into non-severe and severe subgroups, respectively. The median age of patients was 48.0 years (IQR, 35.0-65.0), with 129 (48.3%) of the patients were more than 50 years of age. 149 (55.8%) patients were men. Severe patients were significantly older (median age, 71.5 years [IQR, 65.8-77.0] vs 43.0 years [IQR, 32.5-57.0]) and more likely to be male (110 [50.7%] vs 39 [78.0%]) and have coexisting disorders (15 [30.0%] vs 26 [12.0%]). 41 (15.4%) patients had a recent travel to Hubei province, and 139 (52.1%) patients had a history of contact with patients from Hubei. On admission, the most common symptoms of COVID-19 were fever 225(84.3%), fatigue (208 [77.9%]), dry cough (189 [70.8%]), myalgia or arthralgia (136 [50.9%]). Severe patients were more likely to present dyspnea (17 [34.0%] vs 26 [12.0%]) and confusion (10 [20.0%] vs 15 [6.9%]). Rales (32 [12.0%]) and wheezes (20 [7.5%]) are not common noted for COVID-19 patients, especially for the non-severe (11 [5.1%], 10 [4.6%]). 118 (44.2%). Most severe patients demonstrated more laboratory abnormalities. 231 (86.5%), 61 (22.8%) patients had lymphopenia, leukopenia and thrombocytopenia, respectively. CD4+T cell counts decrease was observed in 77.1 % of cases, especially in the severe patients (45, 100%). 53.1% patients had decreased CD+3 T cell counts, count of CD8+T cells was lower than the normal range in part of patients (34.4%). More severe patients had lower level of CD4+ T cells and CD+3 T cells (45 [100.0%] vs 29[56.9%], 31 [68.9%] vs 20 [39.2%]). Most patients had normal level of IL-2, IL-4, TNF- and INF-{gamma}, while high level of IL-6 and IL-17A was common in COVID-19 patients (47 [70.1%], 35 [52.2%]). Level of IL-6, IL-17A and TNF- was remarkably elevated in severe patients (32 [84.2%] vs 15 [51.7%], 25 [65.8%] vs 10 [34.5%], 17 [44.7%] vs 5 [17.2%]). All patients received antiviral therapy (267, 100%). A portion of severe patients (38, 76.0%) received systemic corticosteroid therapy. Invasive mechanical ventilation in prone position, non-invasive mechanical ventilation, high-flow nasal cannula oxygen therapy was adopted only in severe patients with respiratory failure (5[10.0%], 35[70.0%], 12[24.0%]). Traditional Chinese medicine was adopted to most of severe patients (43,86.0%). Conclusion:Our study firstly demonstrated the regional disparity of COVID-19 in Chongqing municipality and further thoroughly compared the differences between severe and non-severe patients. The 28-day mortality of COVID-19 patients from 3 designed hospitals of Chongqing is 1.5%, lower than that of Hubei province and mainland China including Hubei province. However, the 28-mortality of severe patients was relatively high, with much higher when complications occurred. Notably, the 28-mortality of critically severe patients complicated with severe ARDS is considerably as high as 44.4%. Therefore, early diagnosis and intensive care of critically severe COVID-19 cases, especially those combined with ARDS, will be considerably essential to reduce mortality.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Qi, D.; Yan, X.; Tang, X.; Peng, J.; Yu, Q.; Feng, L.; Yuan, G.; Zhang, A.; Chen, Y.; Yuan, J.; Huang, X.; Zhang, X.; Hu, P.; Song, Y.; Qian, C.; Sun, Q.; Wang, D.; Tong, J.; Xiang, J.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-03</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>