<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>An Evaluation of the Vulnerable Physician Workforce in the United States During the Coronavirus Disease-19 Pandemic</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.26.20044263</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.26.20044263</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Background: The coronavirus disease-19 (COVID-19) pandemic threatens to overwhelm the healthcare resources of the country, but also poses a personal hazard to healthcare workers, including physicians. To address the potential impact of excluding physicians with a high risk of adverse outcomes based on age, we evaluated the current patterns of age of licensed physicians across the United States. Methods: We compiled information from the 2018 database of actively licensed physicians in the Federation of State Medical Boards (FSMB) across the US. Both at a national- and the state-level, we assessed the number and proportion of physicians who would be at an elevated risk due to age over 60 years. Results: Of the 985,026 licensed physicians in the US, 235857 or 23.9% were aged 25-40 years, 447052 or 45.4% are 40-60 years, 191794 or 19.5% were 60-70 years, and 106121 or 10.8% were 70 years or older. Age was not reported in 4202 or 0.4% of physicians. Overall, 297915 or 30.2% of physicians were 60 years of age or older, 246167 (25.0%) 65 years and older, and 106121 (10.8%) 70 years or older. States in the US reported that a median 5470 licensed physicians (interquartile range [IQR], 2394 to 10108) were 60 years of age or older. Notably, states of North Dakota (n=1180) and Vermont (n = 1215) had the lowest and California (n=50786) and New York (n=31582) the highest number of physicians over the age of 60 years (Figure 1). Across states, the median proportion of physicians aged 60 years and older was 28.9% (IQR, 27.2%, 31.4%), and ranged between 25.9% for Nebraska to 32.6% for New Mexico (Figure 2). Discussion: Older physicians represent a large proportion of the US physician workforce, particularly in states with the worst COVID-19 outbreak. Therefore, their exclusion from patient care will be impractical. Optimizing care practices by limiting direct patient contact of physicians vulnerable to adverse outcomes from COVID-19, potentially by expanding their participation in telehealth may be a strategy to protect them.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Khera, R.; Dhingra, L. S.; Jain, S.; Krumholz, H.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-30</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>