<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Association of Cardiovascular Manifestations with In-hospital Outcomes in Patients with COVID-19: A Hospital Staff Data</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.02.29.20029348</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.02.29.20029348</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Background: The outbreaks of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) caused by the novel severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) remain a huge threat to the public health worldwide. Clinical data is limited up to now regarding the risk factors in favor of severe conversion of non-severe case with COVID-19. Aims: This study analyzed a hospital staff data to figure out general clinical features of COVID-19 in terms of the association of cardiovascular manifestations (CVMs) with in-hospital outcomes of COVID-19 cases. Methods: Retrospective, single-center case series of 41 consecutive hospitalized health staff with confirmed COVID-19 were collected at the Central Hospital of Wuhan in Wuhan, China, from January 15 to January 24, 2020. Epidemiological, demographic, clinical, laboratory, radiological, treatment data and in-hospital adverse events were collected and analyzed. Final date of follow-up was March 3, 2020. A comparative study was applied between cases with CVMs and those without CVMs. Results: Of all, clinicians and clinical nurses accounted for 80.5%, while 87.8% of all had history of patient contact. The population was presented with a mean age of 39.1 +- 9.2 and less comorbidities than community population. The three most frequent symptoms of COVID-19 cases analyzed were fever (82.9%), myalgia or fatigue (80.5%) and cough (63.4%). While, the three most frequent initial symptoms were myalgia or fatigue (80.5%), fever (73.2%) and cough (41.5%). There were 95.1% cases featured as non-severe course of disease according to the official standard in China. Patients with CVMs and those without CVMs accounted for 58.5% and 41.5%, respectively. Compared with cases without CVMs, patients with CVMs were presented with lower baseline lymphocyte count (0.99 +- 0.43 and 1.55 +- 0.61, P&lt;0.001), more who had at least once positive nucleic acid detection of throat swab during admission (50.0% and 11.8%, P=0.011), and more received oxygen support (79.2% and 23.5%, P&lt;0.001). The rate of in-hospital adverse events was significantly higher in patients with CVMs group (75.0% and 23.5%, P=0.001). Multivariable logistic regression model indicated that, coexisting with CVMs in COVID-19 patients was not independently associated with in-hospital adverse events. Conclusions: Most of hospital staff with COVID-19 had history of patient contact, featured non-severe course of disease. Cases with CVMs suffered from more in-hospital adverse events than those without CVMs. But concomitant CVMs were not independently associated with in-hospital adverse events in COVID-19 patients.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Liu, R.; Ming, X.; Zhu, H.; Song, L.; Gao, Z.; Gao, L.; Jia, S.; Zhang, C.; Xu, O.; Zhou, J.; Yuan, J.; Zhang, J.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-03</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>