<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Comparative study of the lymphocyte change between COVID-19 and non-COVID-19 pneumonia cases suggesting uncontrolled inflammation might not be the main reason of tissue injury</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.02.19.20024885</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.02.19.20024885</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Background: The corona virus disease 2019 (COVID-19) shows unusually high transmission rate and unique clinical characteristics, with key pathological mechanism remaining unclear. Here, we analysed the laboratory data based on clinical samples from COVID-19 patients, in parallel comparison with non-COVID-19 pneumonia cases, in an attempt to elucidate the key pathological features of COVID-19 during its infection of the human body. Methods: We analysed biochemical indices and lymphocyte subpopulation in COVID-19 patients, and compare these data from non-COVID-19 pneumonia cases. Correlation analysis was performed between leukocyte subgroups count and biochemical indexes in COVID-19 patients. Results: The study enrolled 110 patients, comprising 88 COVID-19 patients and 22 non-COVID-19 pneumonia cases. We observed significant differences, including abnormal biochemical indices (CRP, LDH, AST, eGFR, and sodium ion concentration) and reduced lymphocyte subsets count, between the COVID-19 patients and non-COVID-19-caused pneumonia cases. Correlation analysis indicates that the count for lymphocyte subsets-but not that for neutrophils and monocytes-exhibits a significant negative correlation with biochemical indices relating to organ injury, in the COVID-19 infected patients. Conclusions: The study indicates significantly different clinical features between 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV)-caused and non-2019-nCoV-caused pneumonia, especially in terms of lymphocytopenia and organ injury. Notably, correlation analysis demonstrates that tissue damage in COVID-19 patients is attributed to virus infection itself rather than uncontrolled inflammatory responses ("cytokine storm"). These findings provide new insights for developing efficient therapeutic strategies against COVID-19 infection.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Zheng, Y.; Huang, Z.; Ying, G.; Zhang, X.; Ye, W.; Hu, Z.; Hu, C.; Wei, H.; Zeng, Y.; Chi, Y.; Cheng, C.; Lin, F.; Lu, H.; Xiao, L.; Song, Y.; Wang, C.; Yi, Y.; Dong, L.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-02-23</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>