<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>scRNA-seq reveals ACE2 and TMPRSS2 expression in TROP2+ Liver Progenitor Cells: Implications in COVID-19 associated Liver Dysfunction</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.23.002832</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://biorxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.23.002832</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>The recent pandemic of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) is caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). COVID-19 was first reported in China (December 2019) and now prevalent in [~]170 countries across the globe. Entry of SARS-CoV-2 into mammalian cells require the binding of viral Spike (S) proteins to the ACE2 (angiotensin converting enzyme 2) receptor. Once entered the S protein is primed by a specialised serine protease, TMPRSS2 (Transmembrane Serine Protease 2) in the host cell. Importantly, beside respiratory symptoms, consistent with other common respiratory virus infection when patients become viraemic, a significant number of COVID-19 patients also develop liver comorbidities. We explored if specific target cell-type in the mammalian liver, could be implicated in disease pathophysiology other than the general deleterious response to cytokine storms. Here we employed single-cell RNA-seq (scRNA-seq) to survey the human liver and identified potentially implicated liver cell-type for viral ingress. We report the co-expression of ACE2 and TMPRSS2 in a TROP2+ liver progenitor population. Importantly, we fail to detect the expression of ACE2 in hepatocyte or any other liver (immune and stromal) cell types. These results indicated that in COVID-19 associated liver dysfunction and cell death, viral infection of TROP2+ progenitors in liver may significantly impaired liver regeneration and could lead to pathology.

Highlights- EPCAM+ Liver progenitors co-express ACE2 and TMPRSS2
- ACE2 and TMPRSS2 expression is highest in TROP2high progenitors
- ACE2 and TMPRSS2 cells express cholangiocyte biased fate markers
- ACE2 and TMPRSS2 positive cells are absent in human fetal liver</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Seow, J. J. W.; Pai, R.; Mishra, A.; Shepherdson, E.; Lim, T. K. H.; Goh, B. K. P.; Chan, J. K.; Chow, P. K.; Ginhoux, F.; DasGupta, R.; Sharma, A.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-25</rel_date>
    <rel_site>biorxiv</rel_site>
</item>