<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Factors associated with prolonged viral shedding and impact of Lopinavir/Ritonavir treatment in patients with SARS-CoV-2 infection</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.22.20040832</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.22.20040832</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Background: The duration of viral shedding is central to guide decisions around isolation precautions and antiviral treatment. However, studies about risk factors associated with prolonged SARS-CoV-2 shedding and the potential impact of Lopinavir/Ritonavir (LPV/r) treatment remain scarce. Methods: In this retrospective study, data were collected from all SARS-CoV-2 infected patients who were admitted to isolation wards and had RT-PCR conversion at the NO.3 People's hospital of Hubei province between 31 January and 09 March 2020. We compared clinical features and SARS-CoV-2 RNA shedding between patients with LPV/r treatment and those without. Logistic regression analysis was employed to evaluate risk factors associated with prolonged viral shedding. Results: Of 120 patients, the median age was 52 years, 54 (45%) were male and 78 (65%) received LPV/r treatment. The median duration of SARS-CoV-2 RNA detection from symptom onset was 23 days (IQR, 18-32 days). Older age (odd ratio [OR] 1.03, 95% confidence interval [CI] 1.00-1.05, p=0.03) and lack of LPV/r treatment (OR 2.42, 95% CI 1.10-5.36, p=0.029) were independent risk factors for prolonged SARS-CoV-2 RNA shedding in multivariate logistic regression analysis. The median duration of viral shedding was shorter in the LPV/r treatment group (n=78) than that in no LPV/r treatment group (n=42) (median, 22 days vs. 28.5 days, p=0.02). Only earlier administration of LPV/r treatment ([&amp;le;]10 days from symptom onset) could shorten the duration of viral shedding. Conclusions: Older age and lack of LPV/r treatment were independently associated with prolonged SARS-CoV-2 RNA shedding in patients with COVID-19. Earlier administration of LPV/r treatment could shorten viral shedding.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Yan, D.; Liu, X.-y.; Zhu, Y.-n.; Huang, L.; Dan, B.-t.; Zhang, G.-j.; Gao, Y.-h.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-27</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>