<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Impact of self-imposed prevention measures and short-term government intervention on mitigating and delaying a COVID-19 epidemic</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.12.20034827</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.12.20034827</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Background: With new cases of COVID-19 surging around the world, many countries have to prepare for moving beyond the containment phase. Prediction of the effectiveness of non-case-based interventions for mitigating, delaying or preventing the epidemic is urgent, especially for countries affected by the ongoing seasonal influenza activity. Methods: We developed a transmission model to evaluate the impact of self-imposed prevention measures (handwashing, mask-wearing, and social distancing) due to the spread of COVID-19 awareness and of short-term government-imposed social distancing on the peak number of diagnoses, attack rate and time until the peak number of diagnoses. Findings: For fast awareness spread in the population, self-imposed measures can significantly reduce the attack rate, diminish and postpone the peak number of diagnoses. A large epidemic can be prevented if the efficacy of these measures exceeds 50%. For slow awareness spread, self-imposed measures reduce the peak number of diagnoses and attack rate but do not affect the timing of the peak. Early implementation of short-term government interventions can only delay the peak (by at most 7 months for a 3-month intervention). Interpretation: Handwashing, mask-wearing and social distancing as a reaction to information dissemination about COVID-19 can be effective strategies to mitigate and delay the epidemic. We stress the importance of rapidly spreading awareness on the use of these self-imposed prevention measures in the population. Early-initiated short-term government-imposed social distancing can buy time for healthcare systems to prepare for an increasing COVID-19 burden. Keywords: SARS-CoV-2, COVID-19, mathematical model, prevention measures, mitigation, epidemic control, disease awareness, social distancing, handwashing, mask-wearing</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Teslya, A.; Pham, T. M.; Godijk, N. E.; Kretzschmar, M. E.; Bootsma, M. C. J.; Rozhnova, G.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-16</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>