<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Demand for hospitalization services for COVID-19 patients in Brazil</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.30.20047662</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.30.20047662</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>COVID-19 is now a pandemic and many of the affected countries face severe shortages of hospital resources. In Brazil, the first case was reported on February 26. As the number of cases grows in the country, there is a concern that the health system may become overwhelmed, resulting in shortages of hospital beds, intensive care unit beds, and mechanical ventilators. The timing of shortage is likely to vary geographically depending on the observed onset and pace of transmission observed, on the availability of resources, and on the actions implemented. Here we consider the daily number of cases reported in municipalities in Brazil to simulate twelve alternative scenarios of the likely timing of shortage, based on parameters consistently reported for China and Italy, on rates of hospital occupancy for other health conditions observed in Brazil in 2019, and on assumptions of allocation of patients in public and private facilities. Results show that hospital services could start to experience shortages of hospital beds, ICU beds, and ventilators in early April, the most critical situation observed for ICU beds. Increasing the allocation of beds for COVID-19 (in lieu of other conditions) or temporarily placing all resources under the administration of the state delays the anticipated start of shortages by a week. This suggests that solutions adopted by the Brazilian government must aim at expanding the available capacity (e.g., makeshift hospitals), and not simply prioritizing the allocation of available resources to COVID-19.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Castro, M. C.; Resende de Carvalho, L.; Chin, T.; Kahn, R.; Franca, G. V. A.; Macario, E. M.; de Oliveira, W. K.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-04-01</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>