<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Toilets dominate environmental detection of SARS-CoV-2 virus in a hospital</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.04.03.20052175</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.04.03.20052175</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Background: Respiratory and faecal aerosols play a suspected role in transmitting the SARS-CoV-2 virus. We performed extensive environmental sampling in a dedicated hospital building for Covid-19 patients in both toilet and non-toilet environments, and analysed the associated environmental factors. Methods: We collected data of the Covid-19 patients. 107 surface samples, 46 air samples, two exhaled condensate samples, and two expired air samples were collected were collected within and beyond the four three-bed isolation rooms. We reviewed the environmental design of the building and the cleaning routines. We conducted field measurement of airflow and CO2 concentrations. Findings: The 107 surface samples comprised 37 from toilets, 34 from other surfaces in isolation rooms (ventilated at 30-60 L/s), and 36 from other surfaces outside isolation rooms in the hospital. Four of these samples were positive, namely two ward door-handles, one bathroom toilet-seat cover and one bathroom door-handle; and three were weakly positive, namely one bathroom toilet seat, one bathroom washbasin tap lever and one bathroom ceiling-exhaust louvre. One of the 46 air samples was weakly positive, and this was a corridor air sample. The two exhaled condensate samples and the two expired air samples were negative. Interpretation: The faecal-derived aerosols in patients' toilets contained most of the detected SARS-CoV-2 virus in the hospital, highlighting the importance of surface and hand hygiene for intervention.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Ding, Z.; Qian, H.; Xu, B.; Huang, Y.; Miao, T.; Yen, H.-L.; Xiao, S.; Cui, L.; Wu, X.; Shao, W.; Song, Y.; Sha, L.; Zhou, L.; Xu, Y.; Zhu, B.; Li, Y.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-04-07</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>