<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Long-Term Persistence of IgG Antibodies in SARS-CoV Infected Healthcare Workers</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.02.12.20021386</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.02.12.20021386</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>BACKGROUND: The ongoing worldwide outbreak of the 2019-nCoV is markedly similar to the severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) outbreak 17 years ago. During the 2002-2003 SARS outbreak, healthcare workers formed a special population of patients. Although virus-specific IgG play important roles in virus neutralization and prevention against future infection, limited information is available regarding the long term persistence of IgG after infection with SARS-like coronavirus. METHODS: A long-term prospective cohort study followed 34 SARS-CoV-infected healthcare workers from a hospital with clustered infected cases during the 2002-2003 SARS outbreak in Guangzhou, China, with a 13-year follow-up. Serum samples were collected annually from 2003-2015. Twenty SARS-CoV-infected and 40 non-infected healthcare workers were enrolled in 2015, and their serum samples were collected. All sera were tested for IgG antibodies with ELISA using whole virus and a recombinant nucleocapsid protein of SARS-CoV, as a diagnostic antigen. RESULTS: Anti SARS-CoV IgG was found to persist for up to 12 years. IgG titers typically peaked in 2004, declining rapidly from 2004-2006, and then continued to decline at a slower rate. IgG titers in SARS-CoV-infected healthcare workers remained at a significantly high level until 2015. Patients treated with corticosteroids at the time of infection were found to have lower IgG titers than those without. CONCLUSIONS: IgG antibodies against SARS-CoV can persist for at least 12 years. The presence of SARS-CoV IgG might provide protection against SARS-CoV and other betacoronavirus. This study provides valuable information regarding humoral immune responses against SARS-CoV and the 2019-nCoV.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Guo, X.; Guo, Z.; Duan, C.; chen, Z.; Wang, G.; Lu, Y.; Li, M.; Lu, J.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-02-14</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>