<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Epidemiological identification of a novel infectious disease in real time: Analysis of the atypical pneumonia outbreak in Wuhan, China, 2019-20</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.01.26.20018887</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.01.26.20018887</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Objective: Virological tests indicate that a novel coronavirus is the most likely explanation for the 2019-20 pneumonia outbreak in Wuhan, China. We demonstrate that non-virological descriptive characteristics could have determined that the outbreak is caused by a novel pathogen in advance of virological testing. Methods: Characteristics of the ongoing outbreak were collected in real time from two medical social media sites. These were compared against characteristics of ten existing pathogens that can induce atypical pneumonia. The probability that the current outbreak is due to "Disease X" (i.e., previously unknown etiology) as opposed to one of the known pathogens was inferred, and this estimate was updated as the outbreak continued. Results: The probability that Disease X is driving the outbreak was assessed as over 32% on 31 December 2019, one week before virus identification. After some specific pathogens were ruled out by laboratory tests on 5 Jan 2020, the inferred probability of Disease X was over 59%. Conclusions: We showed quantitatively that the emerging outbreak of atypical pneumonia cases is consistent with causation by a novel pathogen. The proposed approach, that uses only routinely-observed non-virological data, can aid ongoing risk assessments even before virological test results become available. Keywords: Epidemic; Causation; Bayes' theorem; Diagnosis; Prediction; Statistical model</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Jung, S.-m.; Kinoshita, R.; Hayashi, K.; Linton, N. M.; Yang, Y.; Akhmetzhanov, A. R.; Nishiura, H.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-01-28</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>