<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Early chest computed tomography to diagnose COVID-19 from suspected patients: A multicenter retrospective study</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.24.20042432</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.24.20042432</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Objective: The purpose of this study is to distinguish the imaging features of COVID-19 with other chest infectious diseases and evaluate diagnostic value of chest CT for suspected patients. Methods: Adult suspected patients aged &gt;18 years within 14 days who underwent chest CT scan and reverse-transcription polymerase-chain-reaction (RT-PCR) tests were enrolled. The enrolled patients were confirmed and grouped according to results of RT-PCR tests. The data of basic demographics, single chest CT features, and combined chest CT features were analyzed for confirmed and non-confirmed groups. Results: A total of 130 patients were enrolled with 54 cases positive and 76 cases negative. The typical CT imaging features of positive group were ground glass opacity (GGO), crazy-paving pattern and air bronchogram. The lesions were mostly distributed bilaterally, close to the lower lungs or the pleura. When features combined, GGO with bilateral pulmonary distribution and GGO with pleural distribution were more common, of which were 31 cases (57.4%) and 30 cases (55.6%) respectively. The combinations were almost presented statistically significant (P&lt;0.05) except for the combination of GGO with consolidation. Most combinations presented relatively low sensitivity but extremely high specificity. The average specificity of these combinations is around 90%. Conclusions: The combinations of GGO could be useful in the identification and differential diagnosis of COVID-19, which alerts clinicians to isolate patients for treatment promptly and repeat RT-PCR tests until incubation ends.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Miao, C.; Jin, M.; Miao, L.; Yang, X.; Huang, P.; Xiong, H.; Huang, P.; Zhao, Q.; Du, J.; Hong, J.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-26</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>