<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Clinical Characteristics of Patients with Severe Pneumonia Caused by the 2019 Novel Coronavirus in Wuhan, China</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.02.20029306</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.02.20029306</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Abstract Background: A new virus broke out in Wuhan, Hubei, China, and was later named 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV). The clinical characteristics of severe pneumonia caused by 2019-nCoV are still not clear. Objectives: The aim of this study was to explore the clinical characteristics and risk factors of the severe pneumonia caused by the 2019-nCoV in Wuhan, China. Method: The study included patients hospitalized at the central hospital of Wuhan who had been diagnosed with a pneumonia caused by the novel coronavirus. Clinical features, chronic co-morbidities, demographic data, laboratory examinations, and chest computed tomography (CT) scans were reviewed through electronic medical records. SPSS was used for data analysis to explore the clinical characteristics and risk factors of the patients with the severe pneumonia. Results: A total of 110 patients diagnosed with 2019 novel coronavirus pneumonia were included in the study, including 38 with severe pneumonia and 72 with non-severe pneumonia. Statistical analysis showed that advanced age, an increase of D-dimer, and a decrease of lymphocytes were characteristics of the patients with severe pneumonia. Moreover, in the early stage of the disease, chest CT scans of patients with the severe pneumonia showed the illness can progress rapidly. Conclusions: Advanced age, lymphocyte decline, and D-dimer elevation are important characteristics of patients with severe pneumonia. Clinicians should focus on these characteristics to identify high-risk patients at an early stage.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Wang, Y.; Zhou, Y.; Yang, Z.; Xia, D.; Geng, S.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-03</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>