<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Role of Chloroquine and Hydroxychloroquine in the Treatment of COVID-19 Infection- A Systematic Literature Review</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.24.20042366</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.24.20042366</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Background: Coronavirus pandemic is currently a global public health emergency. At present, no pharmacological treatment is known to treat this condition, and there is a need to review the available treatments. Objective: While there have been studies to describe the role of chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine in various viral conditions, there is limited information about the use of them in COVID-19. This systematic review aims to summarize the available evidence regarding the role of chloroquine in treating coronavirus infection. Methods: The preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses (PRISMA) guidelines were used for this review. A literature search was performed using PUBMED &amp; Google Scholar to find articles about the role of CQ in COVID-19 patients. Results: We included 19 publications (Five published articles, three letters/correspondence, one commentary, five pre-proofs of accepted articles, one abstract of yet to be published article, and four were pre-prints (not yet peer-reviewed) articles) in this systematic review. All the articles mentioned about the role of chloroquine and /or hydroxychloroquine in limiting the infection with SARS-CoV-2 (the virus causing COVID-19). Conclusions: There is theoretical, experimental, preclinical and clinical evidence of the effectiveness of chloroquine in patients affected with COVID-19. There is adequate evidence of drug safety from the long-time clinical use of chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine in other indications. More data from ongoing and future trials will add more insight into the role of chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine in COVID-19 infection.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Kapoor, K. M.; Kapoor, A.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-30</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>