<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Estimating the risk on outbreak spreading of 2019-nCoV in China using transportation data</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.02.01.20019984</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.02.01.20019984</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>A novel corona virus (2019-nCoV) was identified in Wuhan, China and has been causing an unprecedented outbreak in China. The spread of this novel virus can eventually become an international emergency. During the early outbreak phase in Wuhan, one of the most important public health tasks is to prevent the spread of the virus to other cities. Therefore, full-scale border control measures to prevent the spread of virus have been discussed in many nearby countries. At the same time, lockdown in Wuhan cityu (border control from leaving out) has been imposed. The challenge is that many people have traveled from Wuhan to other cities before the border control. Thus, it is difficult to forecast the number of imported cases at different cities and estimate their risk on outbreak emergence. Here, we have developed a mathematical framework incorporating city-to-city connections to calculate the number of imported cases of the novel virus from an outbreak source, and the cumulative number of secondary cases generated by the imported cases. We used this number to estimate the arrival time of outbreak emergence using air travel frequency data from Wuhan to other cities, collected from the International Air Transport Association database. In addition, a meta-population compartmental model was built based on a classical SIR approach to simulate outbreaks at different cities. We consider the scenarios under three basic reproductive number settings using the best knowledge of the current findings, from high (2.92), mild (1.68), to a much lower numbers (1.4). The mean arrival time of outbreak spreading has been determined. Under the high , the critical time is 17.9 days after December 31, 2019 for outbreak spreading. Under the low , the critical time is between day 26.2 to day 35 after December 31, 2019. To make an extra 30 days gain, under the low (1.4), the control measures have to reduce 87% of the connections between the source and target cities. Under the higher (2.92), the effect on reducing the chance of outbreak emergence is generally low until the border control measure was enhanced to reduce more than 95% of the connections.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Yuan, H.-Y.; Hossain, M. P.; Tsegaye, M. M.; Zhu, X.; Jia, P.; Wen, T.-H.; Pfeiffer, D.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-02-04</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>