<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Association between Clinical, Laboratory and CT Characteristics and RT-PCR Results in the Follow-up of COVID-19 patients</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.19.20038315</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.19.20038315</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Abstract Background: Since December 2019, more than 100,000 coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) patients have been confirmed globally based on positive viral nucleic acids with real-time reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR). However, the association between clinical, laboratory and CT characteristics and RT-PCR results is still unclear. We sought to examine this association in detail, especially in recovered patients. Methods: We analysed data from 52 confirmed patients who had been discharged with COVID-19. The clinical, laboratory, and radiological data were dynamically recorded and compared with the admission and follow-up RT-PCR results. Results: In this cohort, 52 admitted COVID-19 patients who had confirmed positive RT-PCR results were discharged after 2 rounds of consecutively negative RT-PCR results. Compared with admission levels, CRP levels (median 4.93 mg/L [IQR: 1.78-10.20]) decreased significantly (p&lt;0.001). and lymphocyte counts (median 1.50x109/L [IQR: 1.11-1.88]) increased obviously after obtaining negative RT-PCR results (p&lt;0.001). Additionally, substantially improved inflammatory exudation was observed on chest CT except for 2 progressed patients. At the two-week follow-up after discharge, 7 patients had re-positive RT-PCR results, including the abovementioned 2 progressed patients. Among the 7 patients, new GGO was demonstrated in 2 patients. There were no significant differences in CPR levels or lymphocyte counts when comparing the negative and re-positive PCT results (all p &gt;0.05). Conclusion: Heterogeneity between CT features and RT-PCR results was found in COVID-19, especially in some recovered patients with negative RT-PCR results. Our study highlights that both RT-PCR and chest CT should be considered as the key determinants for the diagnosis and management of COVID-19 patients.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Fu, H.; Xu, H.; Zhang, N.; Xu, H.; Li, Z.; Chen, H.; Xu, R.; Sun, R.; Wen, L.; Xie, L.; Liu, H.; Zhang, K.; Fu, C.; Hou, K.; Yang, Z.; Yang, M.; Guo, Y.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-23</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>