<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Highly accurate and sensitive diagnostic detection of SARS-CoV-2 by digital PCR</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.14.20036129</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.14.20036129</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>BACKGROUND: The outbreak of COVID-19 caused by a novel Coronavirus (termed SARS-CoV-2) has spread to over 140 countries around the world. Currently, reverse transcription quantitative qPCR (RT-qPCR) is used as the gold standard for diagnostics of SARS-CoV-2. However, the positive rate of RT-qPCR assay of pharyngeal swab samples are reported to vary from 30~60%. More accurate and sensitive methods are urgently needed to support the quality assurance of the RT-qPCR or as an alternative diagnostic approach. METHODSWe established a reverse transcription digital PCR (RT-dPCR) protocol to detect SARS-CoV-2 on 194 clinical pharyngeal swab samples, including 103 suspected patients, 75 close contacts and 16 supposed convalescents. RESULTS: The limit of blanks (LoBs) of the RT-dPCR assays were ~1.6, ~1.6 and ~0.8 copies/reaction for ORF 1ab, N and E genes, respectively. The limit of detection (LoD) was 2 copies/reaction. For the 103 fever suspected patients, the sensitivity of SARS-CoV-2 detection was significantly improved from 28.2% by RT-qPCR to 87.4% by RT-dPCR. For close contacts, the suspect rate was greatly decreased from 21% down to 1%. The overall sensitivity, specificity and diagnostic accuracy of RT-dPCR were 90%, 100% and 93 %, respectively. In addition, quantification of the viral load for convalescents by RT-dPCR showed that a longer observation period was needed in the hospital for elderly patients. CONCLUSION: RT-dPCR could be a confirmatory method for suspected patients diagnosed by RT-qPCR. Furthermore, RT-dPCR was more sensitive and suitable for low viral load specimens from the both patients under isolation and those under observation who may not be exhibiting clinical symptoms.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>dong, l.; Zhou, J.; Niu, C.; Wang, Q.; Pan, Y.; Wang, X.; zhang, Y.; yang, J.; Liu, M.; zhao, Y.; peng, T.; xie, J.; gao, y.; wang, D.; zhao, y.; Dai, X.; fang, x.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-18</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>