<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>The infection evidence of SARS-COV-2 in ocular surface： a single-center cross-sectional study</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.02.26.20027938</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.02.26.20027938</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Purpose: The aim of this study was to identify whether SARS-COV-2 infected in ocular surface. Methods: Cross-sectional study of patients presenting for who received a COVID-19 diagnosis, from December 30, 2019 to February 7, 2020, at Tongji hospital, Tongji medical college, Huazhong University of Science and Technology. Demographics, temperature was recorded, blood routine test (Rt), chest Computed Tomography (CT) were took intermittently, and SARS-COV-2 real-time reverse-transcriptase-polymerase-chain-reaction (RT-PCR) assay were arranged for the nasopharyngeal and conjunctival swab samples. Results: A total of 102 patients (48 Male [50%] and 54 Female [50%]) with clinical symptoms, Rt, and chest Computed Tomography (CT) abnormalities were identified with a clinical diagnosis of COVID-19. Patients had a mean [SD] gestational age of 57.63 [14.90] years. Of a total of 102 patients identified, 72 patients (36 men [50%] and 36 women [50%]; mean [SD] age, 58.68 [14.81] years) confirmed by laboratory diagnosis with SARS-COV-2 RT-PCR assay. Only two patients (2.78%) with conjunctivitis was identified from 72 patients with a laboratory confirmed COVID-19. However, SARS-COV-2 RNA fragments was found in ocular discharges by SARS-COV-2 RT-PCR only in one patient with conjunctivitis. Conclusions: Although we suspect the incidence of SARS-COV-2 infection through the ocular surface is extremely low, the nosocomial infection of SARS-CoV-2 through the eyes after occupational exposure is a potential route. The inefficient diagnostic method and the sampling time lag may contribute to the lower positive rate of conjunctival swab samples of SARS-COV-2. Therefore, to lower the SARS-COV-2 nosocomial infection, the protective goggles should be wore in all the health care workers.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Sun, X.; Zhang, X.; Chen, X.; Chen, L.; Deng, C.; Zou, X.; Liu, W.; Yu, H.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-02-26</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>