<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Ultra-High-Resolution CT Follow-Up in Patients with Imported Early-Stage Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) Related Pneumonia</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.31.20048256</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.31.20048256</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Background: An ongoing outbreak of mystery pneumonia in Wuhan was caused by coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). The infectious disease has spread globally and become a major threat to public health. Purpose: We aim to investigate the ultra-high-resolution CT (UHR-CT) findings of imported COVID-19 related pneumonia from the initial diagnosis to early-phase follow-up. Methods: This retrospective study included confirmed cases with early-stage COVID-19 related pneumonia imported from the epicenter. Initial and early-phase follow-up UHR-CT scans (within 5 days) were reviewed for characterizing the radiological findings. The normalized total volumes of ground-glass opacities (GGOs) and consolidations were calculated and compared during the radiological follow-up by artificial-intelligence-based methods. Results: Eleven patients (3 males and 8 females, aged 32-74 years) with confirmed COVID-19 were evaluated. Subpleural GGOs with inter/intralobular septal thickening were typical imaging findings. Other diagnostic CT features included distinct margins (8/11, 73%), pleural retraction or thickening (7/11, 64%), intralesional vasodilatation (6/11, 55%). Normalized volumes of pulmonary GGOs (p=0.003) and consolidations (p=0.003) significantly increased during the CT follow-up. Conclusions: The abnormalities of GGOs with peripleural distribution, consolidated areas, septal thickening, pleural involvement and intralesional vasodilatation on UHR-CT indicate the diagnosis of COVID-19. COVID-19 cases could manifest significantly progressed GGOs and consolidations with increased volume during the early-phase CT follow-up.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Lin, Y.; Lv, S.; Wang, J.; Kang, J.; Zhang, Y.; Feng, Z.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-04-06</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>