<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Optimization of Microbiological Laboratory Detection Strategy for Patients in A Designated Hospital Treating Novel Coronavirus Pneumonia in Anhui Province</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.21.20039065</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.21.20039065</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Novel coronavirus pneumonia (NCP) is an emerging, highly contagious community acquired pneumonia (CAP) caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). Highly efficient and accurate microbiological laboratory assay is essential to confirm the SARS-CoV-2 infection, rule out other pathogens that can cause CAP, and monitor secondary infections. Here, we enrolled and provide microbiological analysis for 129 suspected and 52 transferred confirmed NCP patients hospitalized in the First Affiliated Hospital of University of Science and Technology of China (USTC) from Jan 21 to Feb 29, 2020. By analyzing the dual swab samples (sputum and pharyngeal) from 129 suspected patients with realtime RT-PCR, we confirmed 33 SARS-CoV-2 infections, with two co-infection cases with adenovirus or rhinovirus. We also used multiplex PCR to detect 13 common respiratory tract pathogens in 96 non-NCP patients, and found that 30 patients (31.25%) were infected with at least one respiratory tract pathogen that may cause CAP. Further, we performed bacterial and fungal cultures as well as fungal serologic tests and found that there is no secondary bacterial/fungal infections in confirmed NCP patients. Our studies suggest that, during the epidemic of NCP in Anhui province, there was a certain proportion of infection and co-infection of other common pathogens of CAP, and the secondary bacterial and fungal infection is not detectable in NCP patients. In comparison with SARS-CoV-2 detection alone, this optimized strategy combining multiple pathogen detection for identification of NCP and other CAP patients as well as cultures and serologic tests for confirmed patients increases the diagnosis efficiency and facilitates the personalized medication.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Chang, W.; Shi, Y.; Qi, Y.; Liu, J.; Liu, T.; Chen, Z.; Zhang, W.; Wang, M.; Liu, D.; Yin, M.; Xu, J.; Yang, Y.; Zhu, X.; Ge, J.; Zhu, S.; Gao, Y.; Ma, X.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-23</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>