<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Restoration of leukomonocyte counts is associated with viral clearance in COVID-19 hospitalized patients</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.03.20030437</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.03.20030437</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Background: Viral clearance is one important indicator for the recovery of SARS-CoV-2 infected patients. Suboptimal T and B cell responses can delay viral clearance in MERS and SARS patients. The role of leukomonocytes in viral clearance of COVID-19 patients is not yet well defined.Methods: From January 26 to February 28, 2020, an observational study was launched at Zhongnan Hospital of Wuhan University, Wuhan, China. We enrolled 25 laboratory-confirmed COVID-19 patients, whose throat-swab specimens were tested positive for SARS-CoV-2 infection by qRT-PCR. We comprehensively analyzed clinical records, counts of lymphocyte subsets including CD3+, CD4+, CD8+ T cells, B cells and NK cells in the patients who successfully cleared SARS-CoV-2, and compared to those that failed to, after a standardized treatment of 8-14 days. Findings: In 25 enrolled COVID-19 patients, lymphopeniawas a common feature. After the treatment, 14 patients were tested negative for SARS-CoV-2. The patients that cleared the infection had restored the numbers of CD3+, CD4+, CD8+ T cellsand B cells as compared to the still viral RNA positive patients, while the recovered patients had a higher count of leukomonocytes. Conclusions: By comparison of leukomonocytes counts in COVID-19 patients at different stages of the disease, we found that CD3+, CD4+, CD8+ T cells and B cells appear to play important roles in viral clearance. The restoration of leukomonocytes counts from peripheral blood can be used as prognosis for the recovery of an COVID-19 infection. We propose that restoration of leukomonocytes counts can be added to the COVID-19 diagnostic guidanceas a criterion for releasing and discharging patients.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Chen, X.; Ling, J.; Mo, P.; Zhang, Y.; Jiang, Q.; Ma, Z.; Cao, Q.; Hu, W.; Zou, S.; Chen, L.; Yao, L.; Luo, M.; Chen, T.; Deng, L.; Liang, K.; Song, S.; Yang, R.; Zheng, R.; Gao, S.; Gui, X.; Ke, H.; Hou, W.; Lundkvist, A.; Xiong, Y.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-06</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>