<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Bibliometric Analysis of Global Scientific Research on SARSCoV-2 (COVID-19)</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.19.20038752</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.19.20038752</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Background and Aim: Since late 2019, an unknown-origin pneumonia outbreak detected in Wuhan city, Hubei Province, China. We aimed to build a model to qualitatively and quantitatively assess publications of research of COVID-19 from 2019 to 2020. Materials and Methods: Data were obtained from the Web of Science (WOS), PubMed, and Scopus Core Collection on March 02, 2020, and updated on March 10. We conducted a qualitative and quantitative analysis of publication outputs, journals, authors, institutions, countries, cited references, keywords, and terms according to bibliometric methods using VOS viewer c software packages. Results: Initially, we identified 227 papers, of which after an exclusion process, 92 studies were selected for statistical analyses. China accounted for the highest proportion of published research (44 papers, 40.48%), followed by the United States (21 papers, 19.32%), and Canada (7 papers, 6.44%). Adjusted by gross domestic product (GDP), ranked first, with 0.003 articles per billion GDP. In total, the top 10 journals published 47 articles, which accounted for 51.08% of all publications in this Feld. A total of 6 studies (05.52%) were supported by National Natural Science Foundation of China. Chinese Academy of Sciences ranked second 2, 2.76%). Conclusion: Bibliometric and visualized mapping may quantitatively monitor research performance in science and present predictions. The subject of this study was the fast growing publication on COVID-19. Most studies are published in journals with very high impact factors (IFs) and other journals are more interested in this type of research.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Rafiei Nasab, F.; rahim, F.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-23</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>