<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Public perspectives on social distancing and other protective measures in Europe: a cross-sectional survey study during the COVID-19 pandemic</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.04.02.20049676</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.04.02.20049676</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Objectives: The extent to which people implement government-issued protective measures is critical in preventing further spread of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) caused by coronavirus SARS-CoV-2. Our study aimed to evaluate the public belief in the effectiveness of protective measures, the reported implementation of these measures in daily life, and to identify communication channels used to acquire relevant information on COVID-19 in European countries. Design: A cross-sectional online survey available in multiple languages was disseminated on social media starting March 19th, 2020. After five days, we computed descriptive statistics for countries with more than 500 respondents. Each day, we compiled and categorized community containment measures enacted in each country by stringency (stage I-IV). Response collection continued for one week to explore possible dynamics as containment strategies intensified. Participants: In total, 9,796 adults responded, of whom 8,611 resided in the Netherlands (stage III), 604 in Germany (stage III), and 581 in Italy (stage IV). An additional 1,365 respondents completed the survey in the following week. Results: Participants indicated support for governmental measures related to avoiding social gatherings, selective closure of public places, and hand hygiene and respiratory measures (range for all measures: 95.0%-99.7%). Respondents from the Netherlands were less likely to consider a complete social lockdown effective (59.2%), compared to respondents in Germany (76.6%) or Italy (87.2%). Italian residents did not only apply enforced social distancing measures more frequently (range: 90.2%-99.3%, German and Dutch residents: 67.5%-97.0%), but also self-initiated hygienic and social distancing behaviors (range: 36.3%-96.6%, German and Dutch residents: 28.3%-95.7%). Respondents largely reported being sufficiently informed about the COVID-19 outbreak and about behaviors to avoid infection (range across countries: 90.2%-91.1%). Information channels most commonly reported included television (range: 53.0%-82.0%), newspapers (range: 31.0%-63.0%), official health websites (range: 39.0%-54.1%), and social media (range: 40.0%-55.8%). We observed no major changes in answers over time. Conclusions: In European countries, the degree of public belief in the effectiveness of protective measures was high and residents reported to be sufficiently informed by various communication channels. In March 2020, implementation of enacted and self-initiated measures differed between countries and were highest among Italian respondents, who were subjected to the most elaborate measures of social lockdown and greatest COVID-19 burden in Europe.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Meier, K.; Glatz, T.; Guijt, M. C.; Piccininni, M.; van der Meulen, M.; Atmar, K.; Jolink, A.-T. C.; Kurth, T.; Rohmann, J. L.; Zamanipoor Najafabadi, A. H.; on behalf of the COVID-19 Survey Study group,  </rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-04-06</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>