<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Evaluation of recombinant nucleocapsid and spike proteins for serological diagnosis of novel coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19)</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.17.20036954</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.17.20036954</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Background: The colloidal gold immunochromatography assay (GICA) is a rapid diagnostic tool for novel coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) infections. However, with significant numbers of false negatives, improvements to GICA are needed. Methods: Six recombinant HCoV-19 nucleocapsid and spike proteins were prepared and evaluated. The optimal proteins were employed to develop a sandwich-format GICA strip to detect total antibodies (IgM and IgG) against HCoV-19. GICA performance was assessed with comparison of viral RNA detection. Results: Recombinant HCoV-19 proteins were obtained, including three prokaryotically expressed rN, rN1, rN2 nucleocapsid proteins, and three eukaryotically expressed rS1, rS-RBD, rS-RBD-mFc spike proteins. The recombinant proteins with the highest ELISA titers (rS1 and rS-RBD-mFc) against coronavirus-specific IgM and IgG were chosen for GICA development. The GICA has a sensitivity and specificity of 86.89% (106/122) and 99.39% (656/660), respectively. Furthermore, 65.63% (21/32) of the clinically confirmed but RT-PCR negative samples were GICA positive. Conclusions: The eukaryotically-expressed spike proteins (rS1and rS-RBD-mFc) are more suitable than the prokaryotically expressed nucleocapsid proteins for HCoV-19 serological diagnosis. The GICA sandwich used to detect total antibodies is a powerful complement to the current standard RNA-based tests.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Zhang, P.; Gao, Q.; Wang, T.; Ke, Y.; Mo, F.; Jia, R.; Liu, W.; Liu, L.; Zheng, S.; Liu, Y.; Li, L.; Wang, Y.; Xu, L.; Hao, K.; Yang, R.; Li, S.; Lin, C.; Zhao, Y.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-20</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>