<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Urinalysis, but not blood biochemistry, detects the early renal-impairment in patients with COVID-19</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.04.03.20051722</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.04.03.20051722</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Background: In December 2019, a novel coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) caused infectious disease, termed COVID-19, outbroke in Wuhan, China. COVID-19 patients manifested as lung injury with complications in other organs, such as liver, heart, gastrointestinal tract, especially for severe cases. However, whether COVID-19 causes significant acute kidney injury (AKI) remained controversial. Methods: We retrospectively analyzed the clinical characteristics, urine and blood routine tests and other laboratory parameters of hospitalized COVID-19 patients in Wuhan Union Hospital. Findings: 178 patients, admitted to Wuhan Union hospital from February 02 to February 29, 2020, were included in this study. No patient (0 [0%]) presented increased serum creatinine (Scr), and 5 (2.8%) patients showed increased blood urea nitrogen (BUN), indicating few cases with kidney dysfunction. However, for patients (83) with no history of kidney disease who received routine urine test upon hospitalization, 45 (54.2%) patients displayed abnormality in urinalysis, such as proteinuria, hematuria and leukocyturia, while none of the patients was recorded to have acute kidney injury (AKI) throughout the study. Meanwhile, the patients with abnormal urinalysis usually had worse disease progression reflecting by laboratory parameters presentations, including markers of liver injury, inflammation, and coagulation. Conclusion: Many patients manifested by abnormal urinalysis on admission, including proteinuria or hematuria. Our results revealed that urinalysis is better in unveiling potential kidney impairment of COVID-19 patients than blood chemistry test and urinalysis could be used to reflect and predict the disease severity. We therefore recommend pay more attention in urinalysis and kidney impairment in COVID-19 patients.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>zhou, H.; Zhang, Z.; Fan, H.; Li, J.; Li, M.; Dong, Y.; Guo, W.; Lin, L.; Kang, Z.; Yu, T.; Tian, C.; Gui, Y.; Qin, R.; Wang, H.; Luo, S.; Hu, D.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-04-06</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>