<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Simulating the infected population and spread trend of 2019-nCov under different policy by EIR model</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.02.10.20021519</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.02.10.20021519</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Chinese government has taken strong measures in response to the epidemic of new coronavirus (2019-nCoV) from Jan.23, 2020. The number of confirmed infected individuals are still increasing rapidly. Estimating the accurate infected population and the future trend of epidemic spreading under control measures is significant and urgent. There have been reports external icon of spread from an infected patient with no symptoms to a close contact, which means the incubation individuals may has the possibility of infectiousness. However, the traditional transmission model, Susceptible-Exposed-Infectious-Recovered (SEIR) model, assumes that the exposed individual is being infected but without infectiousness. Thus, the estimating infected populations based on SEIR model from the existing literatures seems too far more than the official reported data. Here, we inferred that the epidemic could be spread by exposed (incubation) individuals. Then, we provide a new Exposed-identified-Recovered (EIR) model, and simulated the epidemic spreading processes from free propagation phase to extremely control phase. Then, we estimate of the size of the epidemic and forecast the future development of the epidemics under strong prevention interventions. According to the spread characters of 2019-nCov, we construct a novel EIR compartment system dynamics model. This model integrates two phases of the epidemic spreading: before intervention and after intervention. We assume that 2019-nCov is firstly spread without intervention then the government started to take strong quarantine measures. Use the latest reported official data, we estimate the basic parameters of the model and the basic reproduction number of 2019-nCov. Then, based on this model, we simulate the future spread of the epidemics. Both the infected population and the spreading trend of 2019-nCov under different prevention policy scenarios are estimated. The epidemic spreading trends under different quarantine rate and action starting date of prevention policy are simulated and compared.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Xiong, H.; Yan, H.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-02-12</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>