<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Estimation of instant case fatality rate of COVID-19 in Wuhan and Hubei based on daily case notification data</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.11.20034215</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.11.20034215</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Background The outbreak of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) initially appeared and has most rapidly spread in Wuhan, China. The case fatality rate is the most direct indicator to assess the hazards of an infectious disease. We aimed to estimate the instant fatality rate and cure rate of COVID-19 in Wuhan City and its affiliated Hubei Province. Methods We collected the daily case notification data of COVID-19 from Dec 8, 2019 to Mar 10, 2020 in Wuhan City and Hubei Province officially announced by the Chinese authority. The numbers of daily confirmed/deaths/cured cases and the numbers of daily cumulative confirmed/deaths/cured cases were obtained. The death time and cure time of COVID-19 patients were calculated based on the dates of diagnosis, death and discharge of individual cases. Then the estimated diagnosis dates of deaths and cured cases were obtained on the basis of the median death or medium cure time, respectively. Finally, the instant fatality rate of COVID-19 was calculated according to the numbers of deaths and cured cases on the same estimated diagnosis dates. Results From Jan 1, 2020 to Feb 22, 2020 in Wuhan City, the instant case fatality rate of COVID-19 was 3.4%19.5% and the instant cured rate was 80.0%96.6%. The average fatality rate reached 11.4% while the average cure rate was 88.6%. During the same period in Hubei Province, the instant case fatality rate was 3.8%16.6% and the instant cured rate was 83.4%96.6%. The average fatality rate and the average cure rate were 9.2% and 91.8%, respectively. Conclusions The fatality rate and cure rate of COVID-19 in Wuhan City and Hubei Province were underestimated. Wuhan showed higher fatality rate and cure rate than the whole Hubei Province did.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Cao, L.; Huang, T.-t.; Zhang, J.-x.; Qin, Q.; Liu, S.-y.; Xue, H.-m.; Gong, Y.-x.; Ning, C.-h.; Shen, X.-t.; Yang, J.-x.; Mi, Y.-n.; Xiao, X.; Cao, Y.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-13</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>