<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Knowledge and Beliefs towards Universal Safety Precautions to flatten the curve during Novel Coronavirus Disease (nCOVID-19) Pandemic among general Public in India: Explorations from a National Perspective</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.31.20047126</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.31.20047126</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>Background: The novel Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) is being considered as the most serious health threat that the world has never witnessed in the recent times and significantly affecting the daily routine of mankind by emerging as a global pandemic. Yet, as there is no treatment nor a vaccine that was approved so far, universal safety precautions (USPs) and mitigating strategies are the only way to deal with this emergency crisis. However, knowledge and beliefs towards USPs among the general public in countries such as India with a large population are lacking. Methods: A prospective, cross-sectional, web-based online survey was conducted among the general public in India during March 2020. A 20-items self-administered survey questionnaire was developed and randomly distributed among the public using google document forms through social media networks. Descriptive statistics were used in representing the study characteristics, and the Chi-square test was used in assessing the associations among the study variables with a p-value of &lt; 0.05 was considered as statistically significant. Results: Of 1287 participants, 1117 have given their consent of willingness and completed the questionnaire with a response rate of 86.8%. The mean age of the study participants was 28.8 {+/-} 10.9 years, where the majority of them belong to the age category &lt;25 years, and sex was equally distributed. Based upon the socio-demographic information, the majority were post-graduates (32.9%), professional job holders (45%) and belonged to the upper-middle (40%) economic class. Overall, the knowledge and beliefs towards USPs and mitigating strategies among participants varied between moderate to high, with statistically significant associations with their socio-demographic characteristics. Conclusions: Although the knowledge and beliefs of the general public in India towards USPs are encouraging, there is a need for long-term educational interventions as the dynamics and severity of COVID-19 have been changing day-by-day rapidly. The findings of this study could guide the public health authorities in making and implementing decisions to combat this pandemic. Keywords: Coronavirus, COVID-19, outbreak, Pandemic, universal precautions, SARS-CoV-2.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Gudi, S. K.; Undela, K.; Venkataraman, R.; Mateti, U. V.; Chhabra, M.; Nyamagoud, S.; Tiwari, K. K.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-04-03</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>