<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>Immune Cell Profiling of COVID-19 Patients in the Recovery Stage by Single-Cell Sequencing</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.23.20039362</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://medrxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.23.20039362</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>COVID-19 caused by SARS-CoV-2 has recently affected over 200,000 people and killed more than 8000. Immune system dysregulation such as lymphopenia and inflammatory cytokine storm has been observed in COVID-19 patients, but it remains unclear for the change of key immune cell subsets and their states during COVID-19. Here, we applied single-cell technology to comprehensively characterize transcriptional changes of peripheral blood mononuclear cells in ten patients recovered from COVID-19. Compared with healthy control, COVID-19 induced a unique signature of immune cells in humans, especially in the early recovery stage (ERS). In ERS patients, T cells were decreased remarkably, while monocytes were increased. A detailed analysis of monocytes showed that there was an increased ratio of classical CD14++ monocytes with highly inflammatory genes expression, as well as a greater abundance of CD14++IL1B+ monocytes. For nature killer (NK) cells and T cells, CD4+ T cells were significantly decreased and expressed high level of inflammatory markers, while NK cells were increased. In addition, T cells were highly expanded clone, especially in CD4+ T memory cells and CD8+ T cells. Among B cells, plasma cells were increased remarkably, and naive B cells were reduced. Our study also identified several novel B cell receptor (BCR) changes (such as IGHV1-8 and IGHV3-7), and confirmed isotypes (IGKV3-11 and IGHV3-21) previously used for virus vaccine development. The strongest pairing frequencies, IGHV3-23+IGHJ4, indicated a monoclonal state associated with SARS-CoV-2 specificity. Furthermore, integrated analysis predicated that IL-1B and M-CSF may be novel candidate target gene for inflammatory storm, and TNFSF13, IL-18 and IL-4 may be benefit for the recovery of COVID-19 patients. Our study provides the first evidence of inflammatory immune signature in early recovery stage, suggesting that the COVID-19 patients are still vulnerable after hospital discharge. Our identification of novel BCR signaling may lead to the development of vaccine and antibodies for the treatment of COVID-19.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Wen, W.; Su, W.; Tang, H.; Le, W.; Zhang, X.; Zheng, Y.; Liu, X.; Xie, L.; Li, J.; Ye, J.; Cui, X.; Miao, Y.; Wang, D.; Dong, J.; Xiao, C.-L.; Chen, W.; Wang, H.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-27</rel_date>
    <rel_site>medrxiv</rel_site>
</item>