<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<item>
    <rel_title>A data-driven drug repositioning framework discovered a potential therapeutic agent targeting COVID-19</rel_title>
    <rel_doi>10.1101/2020.03.11.986836</rel_doi>
    <rel_link>http://biorxiv.org/cgi/content/short/2020.03.11.986836</rel_link>
    <rel_abs>The global spread of SARS-CoV-2 requires an urgent need to find effective therapeutics for the treatment of COVID-19. We developed a data-driven drug repositioning framework, which applies both machine learning and statistical analysis approaches to systematically integrate and mine large-scale knowledge graph, literature and transcriptome data to discover the potential drug candidates against SARS-CoV-2. The retrospective study using the past SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV data demonstrated that our machine learning based method can successfully predict effective drug candidates against a specific coronavirus. Our in silico screening followed by wet-lab validation indicated that a poly-ADP-ribose polymerase 1 (PARP1) inhibitor, CVL218, currently in Phase I clinical trial, may be repurposed to treat COVID-19. Our in vitro assays revealed that CVL218 can exhibit effective inhibitory activity against SARS-CoV-2 replication without obvious cytopathic effect. In addition, we showed that CVL218 is able to suppress the CpG-induced IL-6 production in peripheral blood mononuclear cells, suggesting that it may also have anti-inflammatory effect that is highly relevant to the prevention immunopathology induced by SARS-CoV-2 infection. Further pharmacokinetic and toxicokinetic evaluation in rats and monkeys showed a high concentration of CVL218 in lung and observed no apparent signs of toxicity, indicating the appealing potential of this drug for the treatment of the pneumonia caused by SARS-CoV-2 infection. Moreover, molecular docking simulation suggested that CVL218 may bind to the N-terminal domain of nucleocapsid (N) protein of SARS-CoV-2, providing a possible model to explain its antiviral action. We also proposed several possible mechanisms to explain the antiviral activities of PARP1 inhibitors against SARS-CoV-2, based on the data present in this study and previous evidences reported in the literature. In summary, the PARP1 inhibitor CVL218 discovered by our data-driven drug repositioning framework can serve as a potential therapeutic agent for the treatment of COVID-19.</rel_abs>
    <rel_authors>Ge, Y.; Tian, T.; Huang, S.; Wan, F.; Li, J.; Li, S.; Yang, H.; Hong, L.; Wu, N.; Yuan, E.; Cheng, L.; Lei, Y.; Shu, H.; Feng, X.; Jiang, Z.; Chi, Y.; Guo, X.; Cui, L.; Xiao, L.; Li, Z.; Yang, C.; Miao, Z.; Tang, H.; Chen, L.; Zeng, H.; Zhao, D.; Zhu, F.; Shen, X.; Zeng, J.</rel_authors>
    <rel_date>2020-03-12</rel_date>
    <rel_site>biorxiv</rel_site>
</item>