<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is generally accepted that influenza A virus infection in epithelial cells is productive leading to the release of a great number of progeny viruses from these cells. There is, however, a controversy whether human DCs and Mɸs can efficiently produce infectious influenza A viruses. Bender and coworkers showed that a seasonal H1N1 influenza A virus infection in human DCs is abortive (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Tate et al. (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>) and Ioannidis et al. (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) obtained very similar results in mouse Mɸ and DC model systems with both seasonal H1N1 and H3N2 influenza A viruses. On the other hand, the study by Yu et al. (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) indicates that the HPAI H5N1 virus can replicate productively in human alveolar Mɸs but the infection with seasonal H1N1 virus was abortive. Also, several other studies show that an infection in monocyte-derived Mɸs with seasonal H3N2 or HPAI H5N1 viruses seems to be productive (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). In conclusion, it seems that a H1N1 type influenza A virus infection is likely abortive and, consistent with our results, HPAI H5N1 virus infection is productive (Figures 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>A,B) in human immune cells. Nonetheless, there are inconsistent results on the productivity of seasonal H3N2 influenza A virus infection in human cells. In our analyses, a H3N2 influenza A virus as well as the LPAI human isolate of H7N9 virus appeared to cause abortive infection in human moDCs (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>B). Instead, H3N2 and H7N9 virus infections seemed to be productive in Mɸs (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>A). However, the productivity of these viruses was clearly lower when compared with that of the HPAI H5N1 virus. We used another way, namely analyzing the relative amount of virus-specific RNA from cell culture supernatants, to indirectly quantitate the amount of secreted influenza virus into cell culture supernatant. Based on this analysis, there was a good correlation between the amount of infectious virus and the viral RNA levels in the supernatants of H3N2, H5N1, and H7N9-infected Mɸs and moDCs (Figures 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>C,D). A technical detail may, however, confound the results since in moDC infections the input virus was not washed away. It may be that, since in the plaque assay of the supernatant samples the background is relative high and H3N2 or H7N9 infections are only weakly productive, we are unable to clearly see an increase in the virus titers. The productivity of influenza virus infections in human DCs and Mɸs have remained poorly investigated and thus our result is a significant addition to the present knowledge.
</p>
