<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For each tree in the posterior distribution, we consider the ancestral virus at the root to start spreading from the mid-point of our available samples (average of longitudes and latitudes). We recursively visit all branches from root to tip, each time simulating a number of successive infections, which jointly encompass the entire time length for each branch. Each time interval 
 <italic>t</italic> (in days) between successive infections follows:
 <disp-formula>
  <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1001166.e001.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <label>(1)</label>
 </disp-formula>where 
 <italic>a</italic> is a random incubation time, 
 <italic>b</italic> is the random period of infectiousness, and 
 <italic>f</italic> is a random fraction drawn from a uniform[0,1] distribution. Following the results of the comprehensive study by Hampson et al. 
 <xref rid="ppat.1001166-Hampson2" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, we consider
 <disp-formula>
  <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1001166.e002.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <label>(2)</label>
 </disp-formula>and
 <disp-formula>
  <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1001166.e003.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <label>(3)</label>
 </disp-formula>Each new infection is moved a random distance 
 <italic>d</italic> (in m) away from its source case; the distribution for 
 <italic>d</italic> follows a previously described spatial infection kernel 
 <xref rid="ppat.1001166-Hampson2" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>:
 <disp-formula>
  <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1001166.e004.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <label>(4)</label>
 </disp-formula>In the spatial simulation process, we assume that each new distance takes a random direction in continuous space, but we also explore subsequent infections consistently taking the same direction. To achieve a realistic distribution in the relevant geographic area, we prohibit new infections to invade water areas. The tree heights used for simulation for Algeria and Morocco were 33 (23–46) years and 28 (18–39) years respectively (as estimated from the country-specific data), whereas the tree lengths encompassed 623 (490–789) years and 532 (367–706) years respectively.
</p>
