<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par39">The co-circulation of the four serotypes of DENV has been previously reported in the country [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], and our results are consistent with those reports because we found the circulation of serotypes − 1, − 2, and − 3, although with a higher prevalence of DENV-2 (90.9%). However, the analysis of the sequenced samples demonstrated that the DENV-2 Asian/American genotype predominated, which is consistent with reports in recent years in the northern region of Colombia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Genotype V was identified for DENV-1, which is also representative of most of the strains of this serotype isolated in Colombia and generally in the Americas [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. Finally, genotype III was found in the DENV-3 strains, which has been the predominant genotype in Colombia since its introduction in 2002 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. In the case of the samples positive for CHIKV, sequencing revealed the presence of the Asian strain, the same strain that has been previously reported in Colombia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. Finally, although no sequencing of the samples positive for ZIKV was performed because the real-time PCR primers amplify a specific region of the Asian/Caribbean strain [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], we can presume that these samples belong to this lineage, which is the same that has been previously reported in the country [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. Subsequent phylogenetic analyses are necessary to understand the molecular epidemiology of DENV, as well as of CHIKV and ZIKV. In other studies, ongoing, we are evaluating the molecular epidemiology (by sequencing) of those positive samples to identify the evolution level and adaptation of those virus strains in the region.
</p>
