<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2848574</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20376191</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">09-PONE-RA-14022R1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009936</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Evolutionary Biology/Animal Behavior</subject><subject>Evolutionary Biology/Evolutionary Ecology</subject><subject>Evolutionary Biology/Sexual Behavior</subject><subject>Microbiology/Immunity to Infections</subject><subject>Microbiology/Microbial Evolution and Genomics</subject><subject>Virology/Emerging Viral Diseases</subject><subject>Virology/Immunodeficiency Viruses</subject><subject>Virology/Viral Replication and Gene Regulation</subject><subject>Virology/Virus Evolution and Symbiosis</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases/HIV Infection and AIDS</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases/Sexually Transmitted Diseases</subject><subject>Public Health and Epidemiology/Epidemiology</subject><subject>Public Health and Epidemiology/Infectious Diseases</subject><subject>Evolutionary Biology/Human Evolution</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>High GUD Incidence in the Early 20<sup>th</sup> Century Created a Particularly Permissive Time Window for the Origin and Initial Spread of Epidemic HIV Strains</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">GUD and HIV Emergence</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Sousa</surname><given-names>Jo&#x000e3;o Dinis</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>&#x0002a;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>Viktor</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lemey</surname><given-names>Philippe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vandamme</surname><given-names>Anne-Mieke</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Laboratory for Clinical and Evolutionary Virology, Rega Institute for Medical Research, Katholieke Universiteit Leuven, Leuven, Belgium</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Institute of Biology, E&#x000f6;tv&#x000f6;s Lor&#x000e1;nd University, Budapest, Hungary</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Centro de Mal&#x000e1;ria e Outras Doen&#x000e7;as Tropicais, Instituto de Higiene e Medicina Tropical, Universidade Nova de Lisboa, Lisboa, Portugal</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>Darren P.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Institute of Infectious Disease and Molecular Medicine, South Africa</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>joao.sousa@rega.kuleuven.be</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: JDdS VM PL AMV. Performed the experiments: VM PL. Analyzed the data: JDdS VM PL AMV. Wrote the paper: JDdS VM PL AMV.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2010</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>4</month><year>2010</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e9936</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>11</month><year>2009</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>3</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Sousa et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2010</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The processes that permitted a few SIV strains to emerge epidemically as HIV groups remain elusive. Paradigmatic theories propose factors that may have facilitated adaptation to the human host (e.g., unsafe injections), none of which provide a coherent explanation for the timing, geographical origin, and scarcity of epidemic HIV strains. Our updated molecular clock analyses established relatively narrow time intervals (roughly 1880&#x02013;1940) for major SIV transfers to humans. Factors that could favor HIV emergence in this time frame may have been genital ulcer disease (GUD), resulting in high HIV-1 transmissibility (4&#x02013;43&#x00025;), largely exceeding parenteral transmissibility; lack of male circumcision increasing male HIV infection risk; and gender-skewed city growth increasing sexual promiscuity. We surveyed colonial medical literature reporting incidences of GUD for the relevant regions, concentrating on cities, suffering less reporting biases than rural areas. Coinciding in time with the origin of the major HIV groups, colonial cities showed intense GUD outbreaks with incidences 1.5&#x02013;2.5 orders of magnitude higher than in mid 20<sup>th</sup> century. We surveyed ethnographic literature, and concluded that male circumcision frequencies were lower in early 20<sup>th</sup> century than nowadays, with low rates correlating spatially with the emergence of HIV groups. We developed computer simulations to model the early spread of HIV-1 group M in Kinshasa before, during and after the estimated origin of the virus, using parameters derived from the colonial literature. These confirmed that the early 20<sup>th</sup> century was particularly permissive for the emergence of HIV by heterosexual transmission. The strongest potential facilitating factor was high GUD levels. Remarkably, the direct effects of city population size and circumcision frequency seemed relatively small. Our results suggest that intense GUD in promiscuous urban communities was the main factor driving HIV emergence. Low circumcision rates may have played a role, probably by their indirect effects on GUD.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Independent simian immunodeficiency virus (SIV) transfers to humans have established twelve different known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) groups <xref rid="pone.0009936-VanHeuverswyn1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Plantier1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Pandemic HIV-1 group M, and group N descend from SIVcpz endemic in West Central African chimpanzees <xref rid="pone.0009936-VanHeuverswyn1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Chitnis1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, while the closest relatives of HIV-1 groups O and P are SIVs infecting western lowland gorillas (SIVgor) in the same region <xref rid="pone.0009936-VanHeuverswyn1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Plantier1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Clifford1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. All known HIV-2 groups (A&#x02013;H) descend from SIVsmm endemic in sooty mangabeys <xref rid="pone.0009936-Marx1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Santiago1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, which inhabit a strip of forested coast in West Africa <xref rid="pone.0009936-Santiago1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Groves1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hooper1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>.</p><p>Only four of these twelve strains generated successful epidemics in humans: HIV-1 groups M and O, and HIV-2 groups A and B. The pandemic group M strain clusters most closely with SIVcpz endemic in wild chimpanzees from the southeast corner of Cameroon <xref rid="pone.0009936-Keele1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. There is compelling evidence, both from serology and AIDS cases, that HIV-1 infections were initially restricted to the Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hooper1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Rmy1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. The geographical origin of the simian ancestor of HIV-1 group O is still unknown, but its human epicenter was Cameroon, a country to which it remains largely restricted <xref rid="pone.0009936-QuionesMateu1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. Both HIV-2 groups A and B cluster more closely with SIVsmm from sooty mangabeys living in the forests of southwestern C&#x000f4;te d'Ivoire <xref rid="pone.0009936-Santiago1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Both groups spread abundantly in this country, and have spread only recently to Guinea, Sierra Leone, and Liberia, while group A was able to spread to Guinea-Bissau early in its epidemic history <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hooper1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-DeCock1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. This suggests that C&#x000f4;te d'Ivoire was the main early epicenter of these HIV-2 groups. Of the four main groups, HIV-1 group O is the most confined; it currently infects only tens of thousands of people, mainly in Cameroon and Nigeria <xref rid="pone.0009936-QuionesMateu1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Peeters1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Ayouba1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. HIV-1 group N is much rarer and restricted to Cameroon <xref rid="pone.0009936-Yamaguchi2" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref> and the remaining HIV groups have been found in just one patient <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hahn1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Marx1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Yamaguchi1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Plantier1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, including the recently identified HIV-1 group P strain <xref rid="pone.0009936-Plantier1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s001">Figure S1</xref> for an illustration of HIV biogeography.</p><p>Transmission of simian retroviruses to humans is not exceptional. Simian foamy viruses (SFV) have frequently been transmitted to humans exposed to bushmeat, apparently without further spread <xref rid="pone.0009936-Wolfe1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref> and the epidemic human T-cell lymphotropic viruses (HTLV) arose from their simian counterparts (STLV) through contacts over thousands of years. It is generally accepted that SFV, STLV, as well as SIV, entered the human population through bushmeat handling. Although such events are common today <xref rid="pone.0009936-Wolfe1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Salemi1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, and therefore assumed to also have been common in the recent and distant past, they seldom result in a virus with epidemic potential. Despite progress in identifying SIVs closely related to HIV groups <xref rid="pone.0009936-VanHeuverswyn1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Hahn1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Santiago1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <italic>how</italic> and <italic>why</italic> only some of the transmitted SIV strains established epidemics is subject of ardent debate <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hahn1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Chitnis1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Gisselquist1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Ppin1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>.</p><p>The estimated times of cross-species transmission to humans of the different HTLV-1 subtypes span between less than 3,000 and up to about 50,000 years ago <xref rid="pone.0009936-VanDooren1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Salemi2" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, while HTLV-2 was transferred to humans between 60,000 and 400,000 years ago <xref rid="pone.0009936-Salemi1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-VanDooren1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Salemi2" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. In contrast, all main epidemic HIV groups started to spread in humans only recently, and nearly simultaneously, in the early 20<sup>th</sup> century <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lemey1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Salemi3" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Wertheim1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. This fact prompted the search for factors driving HIV emergence, which can be attributed to phenomena new in the 20<sup>th</sup> century. As one of many speculative theories, a hypothesis involving SIV-contaminated polio vaccines has been extensively debated <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hooper1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, but decisively refuted by many lines of scientific evidence <xref rid="pone.0009936-Keele1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Hahn1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lemey1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Salemi3" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Wertheim1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. Another hypothesis proposes that unsterile injections serially transmitted SIV from a bushmeat handler to other humans in a chain of acutely infected people, improving its adaptation to the new host <xref rid="pone.0009936-Marx1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Gisselquist1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Ppin1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. Also hunting intensification <xref rid="pone.0009936-Chitnis1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, social changes, urbanization, and/or increased human mobility <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hahn1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref> have been invoked as explanations for HIV emergence.</p><p>It is conceivable that host or circumstantial factors currently increasing the transmissibility of HIV were also involved in its origin and initial spread. This notion is implicit in the theories that proposed unsterile injections as the driving factor <xref rid="pone.0009936-Marx1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Gisselquist1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Ppin1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. Standard per-reuse transmissibility of unsterile intravenous injections is considerably higher than standard per-act sexual transmissibility (0.6&#x02013;1.6&#x00025; vs. 0.05&#x02013;0.1&#x00025;) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Gisselquist2" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hayes1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. However, the involvement of genital ulcer disease (GUD) dramatically raises the latter. GUD-assisted per-act transmissibilities for HIV-1 were estimated at: 1) man to woman with GUD: 7.4&#x00025; (95&#x00025; CI 3.8&#x02013;15.7&#x00025;) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hayes1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>; 2) woman with GUD to man: 16&#x00025; (95&#x00025; CI 6&#x02013;32&#x00025;) in a cohort in which two thirds of the men were circumcised; the measured per-act transmissibility was 4&#x00025; for the circumcised men, and 43&#x00025; for the uncircumcised <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hayes1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Cameron1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. Although the per-exposure risk for men with GUD has not been measured, evidence from observational studies also suggest a very high HIV transmission risk <xref rid="pone.0009936-Fleming1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Freeman1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. The effect of GUD infections is also very strong at the population level: more than half of new HIV infections in Africa might be attributed to GUD facilitated transmission <xref rid="pone.0009936-White1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. However, to our knowledge no study has investigated the role of GUD prevalence in the origin, initial spread and adaptation of HIV. Another host factor linked with HIV transmissibility is circumcision. For heterosexual men, per-act risk of HIV-1 acquisition is about 6&#x02013;11 times higher if they are uncircumcised <xref rid="pone.0009936-Cameron1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Baeten1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, although more moderate odds ratios have been estimated over longer periods. For uncircumcised men exposed to GUD-suffering sex workers, the measured per-act risk was 43&#x00025; <xref rid="pone.0009936-Cameron1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. Second to transfusions, this is the highest HIV transmissibility ever measured.</p><p>Here, we aimed to identify which factors could have favored SIV adaptation to humans and facilitated its emergence and spread as HIV. First, we investigated the timing of the splits between HIV-1 groups M and O, and HIV-2 groups A and B and their respective closest SIV lineage, either by reviewing the literature or by using phylogenetic methods to narrow down the missing links. Having established a likely time interval of cross species transmission, we then reviewed colonial medical, and demographic literature, including original archival sources, to investigate how the proposed risk factors, including GUD incidence, city growth, health systems, gender distribution, and commercial sex work (CSW), varied in time and space, across the relevant African regions. Additionally we reviewed ethnographic literature on male circumcision per ethnic group, and assessed whether its geographical distribution, in early 20<sup>th</sup> century, overlapped with the putative epicenters for the HIV groups. Finally, we developed computer simulations based on detailed population, sociological and medical data found in our literature and archival searches to identify the key factors that might have facilitated the emergence of HIV-1 group M. Since spatial and temporal coincidence have previously been considered as evidence for factors involved in the emergence of a pathogen <xref rid="pone.0009936-Frank1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, including drafting hypotheses on the origins of HIV <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hahn1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Chitnis1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hooper1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Gisselquist1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Ppin1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, we here invoke such coincidences to support our hypothesis on the origin of the HIV groups.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Estimating divergence times between HIV-1 groups M/O and their simian ancestors</title><p>We obtained divergence dates between epidemic HIVs and their closest simian relatives including recently discovered simian strains <xref rid="pone.0009936-VanHeuverswyn1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Keele1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, through literature survey <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lemey1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Salemi3" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Wertheim1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref> or by estimating new dates. We infer divergence dates using Bayesian relaxed clock analysis <xref rid="pone.0009936-Drummond1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref> for two separate data sets representing HIV-1 group M/SIVcpz and HIV-1 groupO/SIVgor/SIVcpz respectively.</p><p>The combined results are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009936-t001">Table 1</xref>. In general, epidemic HIV crossed to humans after the 18<sup>th</sup> century (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009936-t001">Table 1</xref>). The interspecies transmission of each HIV group occurred between the split with the closest SIV lineage and the time to the most recent common ancestor (MRCA; TMRCA) of the group, probably closer to the latter.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0009936-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009936.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>TMRCA estimates for HIV groups and their divergence from the most closely related SIV strains.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0009936-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0009936.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calculation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dating estimates</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">References</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>HIV-1 group M</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group TMRCA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1920 (1902&#x02013;39)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref> 1937 (1925&#x02013;49)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salemi et al. (2000) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Salemi3" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group TMRCA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1931 (1915&#x02013;41)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Korber et al. (2000) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Korber1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group TMRCA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1921 (1908&#x02013;33)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">b</xref> 1902 (1873&#x02013;1922)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">b</xref> 1908 (1884&#x02013;1924)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Worobey et al. (2008) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Worobey1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Split from closest SIV</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1853 (1799&#x02013;1904)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wertheim &#x00026; Worobey (2009) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Wertheim1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Split from closest SIV</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1876 (1847&#x02013;1907)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>HIV-1 group O</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group TMRCA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1920 (1890&#x02013;1940)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lemey et al. (2004) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lemey2" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group TMRCA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1905 (1866&#x02013;1938)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wertheim &#x00026; Worobey (2009) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Wertheim1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Split from closest SIV</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1741 (1606&#x02013;1870)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>HIV-1 group N</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group TMRCA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1963 (1948&#x02013;77)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wertheim &#x00026; Worobey (2009) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Wertheim1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>HIV-2 group A</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group TMRCA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1940 (1924&#x02013;56)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lemey et al. (2003) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lemey1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group TMRCA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1932 (1906&#x02013;55)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wertheim &#x00026; Worobey (2009) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Wertheim1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Split from closest SIV</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1889 (1856&#x02013;1922)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lemey et al. (2003) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lemey1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>HIV-2 group A</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group TMRCA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1945 (1931&#x02013;59)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lemey et al. (2003) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lemey1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group TMRCA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1935 (1907&#x02013;61)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wertheim &#x00026; Worobey (2009) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Wertheim1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Split from closest SIV</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1889 (1856&#x02013;1922)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lemey et al. (2003) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lemey1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Mean estimates and 95&#x00025; credible/confidence intervals for group TMRCAs were obtained from previous studies, whereas divergence times from the closest SIVs were estimated in this study, and taken from <xref rid="pone.0009936-Wertheim1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>
<sup><bold>a</bold></sup>the two estimates correspond to different genes used.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>
<sup><bold>b</bold></sup>The three estimates correspond to different coalescent tree priors used.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>The early 20<sup>th</sup> century constituted a preferential time window for HIV emergence</title><p>The five HIV groups represented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009936-t001">Table 1</xref> are the ones for which an ongoing epidemic is demonstrated; all the others have only been found in a single person <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hahn1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Marx1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Yamaguchi1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Plantier1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Of these five, four (HIV-1 groups M and O, and HIV-2 groups A and B) have been able to spread at an epidemic level and are currently infecting at least tens of thousands of people, and likely adapted to humans and started to spread in early 20<sup>th</sup> century, whereas HIV-1 group N may have started to spread in mid century (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009936-t001">Table 1</xref>). Thus, the early 20<sup>th</sup> century seems to have constituted a particularly permissive time window for SIV zoonoses with clear epidemic consequences; for example, both epidemiological evidence and population size studies indicate that HIV-1 group M as well as HIV-2 group A spread epidemically at rates nearly equivalent to a tenfold increase in each decade <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lemey1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hooper1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Yusim1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>.</p><p>The narrow time interval in which the four major HIV groups emerged, contrasting with the origins of HTLVs <xref rid="pone.0009936-Salemi1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-VanDooren1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Salemi2" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, suggests that driving factors specific to early 20<sup>th</sup> century have assisted HIV emergence in our species. The prevailing theories would predict more HIV groups emerging after 1950 than before. Injection intensity was much higher in mid 20<sup>th</sup> century than before <xref rid="pone.0009936-Marx1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Urbanization and traffic have also intensified since mid century <xref rid="pone.0009936-Chitnis1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Thomas1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>; for example, among the rural Ngbaka-Mabo people of Lobaye, in southwest Central African Republic (CAR), hunting practice was common, and by 1957, the majority of men, many of them hunters/bushmeat handlers, had already migrated to one or more large Central African cities (e.g., Bangui, Brazzaville) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Thomas1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>; other rural peoples also migrated to cities abundantly, albeit not necessarily to the same extent as the Ngbaka-Mabo. The mid century also likely generated increased human exposures to SIV, and particularly SIVcpz, because the main wild chimpanzee population collapse, partly due to intensified hunting, happened between 1946 and 1980 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Oates1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Teleki1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>.</p><p>To understand why only the early 20<sup>th</sup> century generated all epidemic HIVs, we aimed to reveal the full spectrum of factors that might have had the potential to increase SIV/HIV transmissibility and adaptation in the established critical time interval. In order to be consistent with a causal relationship, the factor or factors responsible should coincide both spatially and temporally with the origin of the epidemic <xref rid="pone.0009936-Frank1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, and thus should have peaked in early 20<sup>th</sup> century in the geographic areas coinciding more or less with the ranges of the relevant SIV-carrying primates.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>The origin of epidemic HIVs coincided with the peak of GUD epidemics</title><p>We reviewed colonial medicine articles, reports, and reviews, for the countries of chimpanzee and sooty mangabey ranges, searching for information about sexually transmitted diseases (STDs), GUDs, and diseases requiring intensive injection treatments (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>, section GUD incidences survey). We found that the most commonly reported GUDs were syphilis, chancroid (<italic>chancrelle</italic>, <italic>chancre mou</italic>), and to a lesser extent, lymphogranuloma venereum (LGV) (<italic>bubon v&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;rien</italic>).</p><p>Primary and secondary syphilis (PSS) last a total of about five months, with exudative genital ulcers being present 30&#x00025; of the time in either stage. This is followed by latent and tertiary stages, with no genital ulceration, and no infectiousness <xref rid="pone.0009936-Garnett1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Oxman1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. As an epidemic progresses, a decreasing fraction of all syphilis infections are PSS; the latent and tertiary stages predominate <xref rid="pone.0009936-Garnett1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Croix1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. Chancroid's single chancre lasts ten weeks on average <xref rid="pone.0009936-Steen1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. Syphilis' and chancroid's high per-contact infectiousness <xref rid="pone.0009936-Garnett1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Oxman1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Steen1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref> promotes rapid spread and high frequency of genital ulcers in local sexually promiscuous settings (e.g., PSS may attain frequencies of 20&#x02013;60&#x00025; during initial invasion <xref rid="pone.0009936-Garnett1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>). These conditions, particularly if occurring in populations with many uncircumcised men, constitute a favorable setting for SIV adaptation to humans through serial sexual transmission during acute infection.</p><p>In the relevant regions, the early 20<sup>th</sup> century witnessed very high GUD incidences especially in fast growing cities and socially changed semi-rural areas. This trend started around 1885, when European powers decidedly rushed to control the interior. Many sources explicitly state that syphilis was absent from nearly all forested areas where chimpanzees, gorillas, and sooty mangabeys live, up to 1885 <xref rid="pone.0009936-RetelLaurentin1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Kermorgant1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>, although it was present before in seaports with European presence <xref rid="pone.0009936-Headrick1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Patterson1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Phillips1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>, and in savannah-forest interface regions connected with Arab states <xref rid="pone.0009936-RetelLaurentin1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. Yaws (<italic>Treponema pallidum pertenue</italic>) has a longstanding and high prevalence in these forests <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Headrick1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, and exhibits cross-immunity with syphilis (<italic>Treponema pallidum pallidum</italic>) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Headrick1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. However, this is not the explanation of why syphilis did not generate epidemics there during centuries. Indeed, these populations <italic>did</italic> experience epidemic syphilis, when they were recruited to cities, and when social disruption due to colonial practices entered deep in the yaws-riddled forests (e.g., in the networks of posts in the Ogoou&#x000e9; (Gabon) and Sangha (French Congo) riversides, in the &#x000c9;quateur province (Belgian Congo), and in southern Cameroon <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Kermorgant1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Georgelin1" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Letonturier1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>). Recent simulations show that syphilis epidemics are very dependent on highly promiscuous minorities <xref rid="pone.0009936-Oxman1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. Chancroid is also very dependent on CSWs for its spread <xref rid="pone.0009936-Steen1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Goeman1" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>. Since our review of colonial medical and ethnographic papers reveals that no CSWs with levels of sexual promiscuity comparable to those operating in the West existed in forested equatorial areas before organized colonialism (excepting in the coast and in the savannah-forest interface regions frequented by Arab traders) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Phillips1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-VanWing1" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Schwab1" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>, we assume that it was this absence of CSWs that was keeping syphilis, chancroid, and the other STDs at bay.</p><p>In the period 1890&#x02013;1920, colonization produced generalized social disruption, sex work flourished, and syphilis (and to a lesser extent chancroid and LGV) invaded all these areas <xref rid="pone.0009936-RetelLaurentin1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Headrick1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Kermorgant1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Georgelin1" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>. Except for tertiary and purely serological diagnoses, colonial doctors of this period were not mistaking yaws for syphilis. Most yaws cases are presented in children <xref rid="pone.0009936-Headrick1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>; unlike syphilis, yaws is not venereal, seldom affects mucosa, and does not cause primary chancres <xref rid="pone.0009936-Mouchet1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Meheus1" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>. In addition, syphilis appeared correlated in time and space with other STDs and with presumed sexual promiscuity in a community (e.g, syphilis was frequent in the colonial posts, and absent in the still undisturbed villages around, and its incidence raised in the posts upon arrival of ships, caravans and military contingents <xref rid="pone.0009936-RetelLaurentin1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Headrick1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Kermorgant1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Heim1" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>).</p><p>A common ironical pun was &#x0201c;<italic>Nous leur avons apport&#x000e9; la syphilization</italic>&#x0201d; (&#x0201c;We have brought them syphilization&#x0201d;). GUD invasion accompanied the social disruption that resulted from colonial development of each region <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Croix1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-RetelLaurentin1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Headrick1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. We hypothesize that this promoted sexual transmission of several zoonotic SIVs. Among these zoonotic strains, those arriving to cities, not only could rapidly generate a larger hub of infected people but also, being placed at a major traffic node, would have had more long-term epidemic possibilities. Cities started to grow fast, and riverine traffic intensified only after 1920 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lahmeyer1" ref-type="bibr">[65]</xref>.</p><p>In Kinshasa (then Leopoldville), capital of the DRC (then Belgian Congo), GUD was much more intense in its early growth period, and then declined steadily after the mid 1930s (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g001">Figure 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s007">Text S1</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0009936-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009936.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Annual incidences of several GUDs (in &#x00025;) in Kinshasa.</title><p>Declines of 1.5&#x02013;2.5 orders of magnitude happened between the 1920s and the 1950s. (Data compilation in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s007">Text S1</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0009936.g001"/></fig><p>Starting to grow fast in 1919, the Kinshasa population tripled to about 47,000 by 1929 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, accompanied by increasing river and railway traffic. Commercial sex work became widespread, not least because of the extremely male-biased (4&#x02236;1) sex-ratio <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. Of 6,000 women living in the eastern part of the city in 1928, only 1,724 were married, 1,600 lived in &#x0201c;illegitimate relationships of more or less duration&#x0201d;, and the remaining (45&#x00025; of the female population) were presumed to &#x0201c;live mainly on prostitution&#x0201d; <xref rid="pone.0009936-Comissaire1" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref>; we must stress that only some of these would be pure CSWs; colonial authorities commonly used this derogatory categorization whenever they suspected that women were having multiple sexual partners. By this time, PSS and other GUDs had very high incidences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Before 1919, reports suggest that GUD incidences were probably higher <xref rid="pone.0009936-Mouchet2" ref-type="bibr">[67]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Service3" ref-type="bibr">[69]</xref>, but archival sources are very incomplete for this period. In 1930&#x02013;32, large surveys covering most women from the city showed that about 5&#x00025; had active genital ulcers at the moment of the visit <xref rid="pone.0009936-Croix1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>.</p><p>By 1928, there was a decided colonial response to these medical conditions. Mass surveys, movement restrictions, monitoring of sex workers and treatment of venereal diseases were initiated and were broadened further in scope and technically improved after 1932 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Croix1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. Surveillance and treatments were successful, and after the mid 1930s, GUD incidences declined. During this period, the proportion of syphilis cases representing PSS also declined, from being the majority in the twenties, to only 1&#x02013;9&#x00025; in 1949&#x02013;58 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Croix1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Bruaux1" ref-type="bibr">[70]</xref>, in agreement with epidemiological simulations <xref rid="pone.0009936-Garnett1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. With penicillin adding up to old arsenic, bismuth, and sulfonamide treatments after 1947, incident ulcerative syphilis, chancroid, and LGV became residual. PSS cases declined to 40&#x02013;60 per year in 1949&#x02013;51, and to 10&#x02013;25 in 1954&#x02013;58, these representing incidences of about 1.5&#x02013;2.5 orders of magnitude lower than those of the period 1919&#x02013;35 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Croix1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Bruaux1" ref-type="bibr">[70]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g001">Figure 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s007">Text S1</xref>).</p><p>Similar trends were observed in other African cities <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service4" ref-type="bibr">[71]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Service7" ref-type="bibr">[75]</xref>, although their timings were not exactly in concordance with those of Kinshasa. For example, in Douala, Cameroon, syphilis represented 13.5&#x00025; of morbidity in 1923 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Letonturier1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref> and only 0.20&#x02013;0.91&#x00025; in the period 1935&#x02013;39 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service4" ref-type="bibr">[71]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-LeGall1" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>, an amelioration attributed to intensive surveys and treatments <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service5" ref-type="bibr">[72]</xref>. In Brazzaville, syphilis represented 3.0&#x02013;7.6&#x00025; of morbidity in the period 1930&#x02013;34 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service6" ref-type="bibr">[74]</xref>, and only 0.33&#x02013;1.11&#x00025; in the period 1953&#x02013;57 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service7" ref-type="bibr">[75]</xref>. In the same city, the proportion PSS/syphilis also declined from 84&#x02013;92&#x00025; in 1933&#x02013;34 to 8&#x02013;34&#x00025; in 1953&#x02013;57 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service6" ref-type="bibr">[74]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service7" ref-type="bibr">[75]</xref>. After 1945, GUD incidences became extremely low in urban settings <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Croix1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Bruaux1" ref-type="bibr">[70]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service5" ref-type="bibr">[72]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-LeGall1" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service7" ref-type="bibr">[75]</xref>.</p><p>Although we cannot exclude reporting biases concerning GUDs (or any other diseases) in colonial reports, these biases are likely to be less of an issue for cases detected in the major cities from the 1920s onwards, when health systems became better established. For this reason, we attempt to quantify GUD incidences only for cities, and from 1919 onward, despite having reviewed many other reports beyond these bounds.</p><p>Genital herpes (caused by the herpes simplex viruses (HSV), most often by HSV-2) plays a major role in HIV transmission nowadays, but its slow monotonic spread made it to be an important cause of genital ulcers in Africa only after the mid eighties <xref rid="pone.0009936-OFarrell1" ref-type="bibr">[76]</xref>. Accordingly, HSV-2 seroprevalence in Kinshasa, in 1959, was 21&#x00025; (and 6&#x00025; in rural Congo), and it took 26 years to attain 60&#x00025; <xref rid="pone.0009936-OFarrell1" ref-type="bibr">[76]</xref>.</p><p>In summary, the period 1945&#x02013;80 is characterized by a low intensity of the four main GUDs in major cities: PSS, chancroid, and LGV became rarer due to the better health systems, and penicillin use; PSS became a small fraction of treated syphilis cases; and genital herpes prevalence was still low. The incidences of the three former GUDs in cities showed peaks up to the mid thirties, when the cities were still small (10,000&#x02013;50,000 inhabitants), sex ratios were very male-biased, and health systems were incipient.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>City growth does not match in time and in space with the origin of epidemic HIV clades</title><p>City growth is a factor to be considered when investigating the emergence of epidemic HIV because a fast growing city potentially receives more SIV-infected migrants per unit time, and can spread the virus among more inhabitants. We examined the curves of population growth of the major Central and West African cities that lie within or near the chimpanzee, gorilla, or sooty mangabey ranges, and that received immigrants from within these ranges (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Periods of fast growth span all over the century; growth rates in mid 20<sup>th</sup> century were among the highest, and involved much higher absolute number of migrant arrivals.</p><fig id="pone-0009936-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009936.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>The growth of the most relevant Central African (A) and West African (B) cities.</title><p>Plotted the evolution of the population of the most relevant cities at or near: (A) chimpanzee and gorilla ranges in Central Africa; (B) sooty mangabey range in West Africa. The supporting references are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s008">Text S2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0009936.g002"/></fig><p>As <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g002">Figure 2A</xref> shows, up to the early thirties, Kinshasa and Douala where clearly the largest cities in the chimpanzee and gorilla ranges. Kinshasa is the recognized early epicenter of HIV-1 group M <xref rid="pone.0009936-Keele1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Worobey1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Vidal1" ref-type="bibr">[77]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Vidal2" ref-type="bibr">[78]</xref>, and Douala was, in early 20<sup>th</sup> century, by far the largest city of Cameroon, which is most likely the country where the early epicenter of HIV-1 group O developed <xref rid="pone.0009936-QuionesMateu1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Peeters1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Ayouba1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. The two cities were experiencing high GUD incidences at the time of the TMRCAs of these HIV groups <xref rid="pone.0009936-Croix1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Letonturier1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s007">Text S1</xref>). Thus, at the same time, two different epidemic HIV clades emerged in Central Africa in the early 20<sup>th</sup> century.</p><p>Both HIV-2 groups A and B originated most likely in C&#x000f4;te d'Ivoire <xref rid="pone.0009936-Santiago1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Urban development was tardy in this colony; the capital Abidjan only grew fast and surpassed 10,000 inhabitants after 1932 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g002">Figure 2B</xref>). GUD levels were high throughout the thirties <xref rid="pone.0009936-DomergueCloarec1" ref-type="bibr">[79]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service8" ref-type="bibr">[80]</xref>. It is thus consistent with our hypothesis that the estimates of both HIV-2 groups' TMRCAs fall in this timeframe, a few decades later than HIV-1 groups M and O <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lemey1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Wertheim1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. However, Freetown was already of considerable size before Abidjan, Conakry grew strongly after 1933 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g002">Figure 2B</xref>), to our knowledge these cities did not differ much from Ivorian cities in their GUD levels, and no epidemic HIV-2 seems to have emerged in them. This motivated us to investigate other factors that may explain why HIV groups emerged only in particular cities.</p><p>City growth is not restricted in time with the emergence of HIV groups. Cities continued to grow, well after the origin of the epidemic HIVs. While there is some spatial coincidence in Central Africa between city size and origin of HIV-1 groups, this is not the case for West Africa and the origin of the HIV-2 groups.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Male circumcision patterns in Central and West Africa show some correlation with HIV emergence</title><p>Male circumcision reduces the risk of HIV acquisition in men <xref rid="pone.0009936-Cameron1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Baeten1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Weiss1" ref-type="bibr">[81]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Williams1" ref-type="bibr">[82]</xref>, and HIV/AIDS prevalence correlates inversely with the level of male circumcision in Africa <xref rid="pone.0009936-Bongaarts1" ref-type="bibr">[83]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Wendell1" ref-type="bibr">[86]</xref>. Recent randomised trials of male circumcision demonstrated a marked reduction in male susceptibility to HIV infection <xref rid="pone.0009936-Bailey1" ref-type="bibr">[87]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Gray1" ref-type="bibr">[88]</xref>. We hypothesized that circumcision levels in cities might also have influenced the chances of HIV emergence from zoonotic SIV transmissions.</p><p>We studied the geographical distribution of circumcision patterns in Central and West Africa both today and at the time of the HIV groups' TMRCAs, to evaluate if it correlated spatially and in time with HIV emergence. We reviewed all the Demographic and Health Surveys (DHS) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Macro1" ref-type="bibr">[89]</xref>, pertaining to the relevant countries, and additional studies <xref rid="pone.0009936-Ppin2" ref-type="bibr">[90]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Bangna1" ref-type="bibr">[91]</xref>, which reported circumcision levels. We found that circumcision is nowadays nearly universal in the countries of the chimpanzee and sooty mangabey ranges, except for Rwanda, Burundi, Uganda, and Tanzania (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s002">Table S1</xref>).</p><p>This near universality contrasts with what can be inferred from Murdock's Ethnographic Atlas <xref rid="pone.0009936-Murdock1" ref-type="bibr">[92]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Gray2" ref-type="bibr">[93]</xref>. Also due to other inconsistencies in this Atlas, we decided to gather primary ethnographic papers, putting more focus on the period of HIV emergence (1900&#x02013;1940) (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>, section circumcision study). Our survey extensively expanded upon currently available circumcision information for the relevant ethnic groups <xref rid="pone.0009936-Gordon1" ref-type="bibr">[94]</xref>, and permits a detailed study of the geographical distribution of male circumcision during colonial times in the areas of chimpanzees and sooty mangabeys (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s003">Table S2</xref>).</p><p>We found that, in the early 20<sup>th</sup> century, circumcision patterns in Central and West Africa exhibited much stronger regional differences than nowadays. Peoples of the Adamawa-Ubangi linguistic cluster (occupying most CAR and northern DRC), and many Bantu peoples of the Orientale and &#x000c9;quateur provinces of DRC, adopted it in late 19<sup>th</sup>&#x02013;early 20<sup>th</sup> century <xref rid="pone.0009936-Friedrichs1" ref-type="bibr">[95]</xref>. In Rwanda and Burundi, circumcision was not practiced, a pattern that persists today <xref rid="pone.0009936-Friedrichs1" ref-type="bibr">[95]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Frobenius1" ref-type="bibr">[96]</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s008">Text S2</xref>). In West Africa, most ethnic groups were circumcised, with some exceptions (e.g., the Akan peoples from eastern C&#x000f4;te d'Ivoire and Ghana, and many Gur peoples from northeastern C&#x000f4;te d'Ivoire, Burkina-Faso, and Ghana) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s008">Text S2</xref>).</p><p>For the main cities of the relevant areas, we collected demographic surveys at several points in time which discriminated the urban population by ethnic group. To each ethnic group present in a city, at a given time, we assigned a &#x0201c;circumcision class&#x0201d; (e.g., generalized at puberty, absent, etc), based on the information provided in ethnographic sources, and we calculated upper and lower estimates of frequency of circumcision in male adults (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref>, section Circumcision prevalence survey, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s008">Text S2</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s010">Dataset S1</xref>). This permitted us to calculate, for each city, and at a given time, the distribution of its male population by the defined circumcision classes, and lower and upper estimates of circumcision frequency. The results are displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g003">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g004">4</xref>.</p><fig id="pone-0009936-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009936.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Male circumcision patterns in Central African (A) and West African (B) cities.</title><p>The charts show, for each city, and at the referred time, the proportional distribution of the male population by &#x0201c;circumcision classes&#x0201d; which are directly derived from the ethnographic literature and do not depend on additional assumptions. Each bar is based on either: i) a published census or survey partitioning by ethnicity; ii) assumption of the same ethnic distribution as in a neighboring time point for which there is a census or survey; iii) published numbers for some ethnic groups, and estimates for some relevant others. The proportions of red and orange in each bar indicate the proportions of the population belonging to groups which, respectively had not adopted circumcision by the time of the data point (red), or had adopted it, or started to generalize it from a situation in which it is described as far from general in the ethnographic literature, less than 15 years before the time of the data point (orange). So, higher proportions of red and orange (and, to a lesser extent, pink) mean lower circumcision frequencies. See supporting information in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s008">Text S2</xref>, and supporting calculations in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s010">Dataset S1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0009936.g003"/></fig><fig id="pone-0009936-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009936.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Estimates of male circumcision frequencies in Central African (A) and West African (B) cities.</title><p>The charts show, for each city, and at the referred time, the upper and lower estimates of male circumcision frequency. The cities and times of estimates are the same that appear in the bars of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g003">Figure 3</xref>. Each estimate is based on either: i) a published census or survey partitioning by ethnicity (filled squares); ii) assumption of the same ethnic distribution as in a neighboring time point for which there is a census or survey (shallow squares); iii) published numbers for some ethnic groups, and estimates for some relevant others (lozenges); iv) present time estimates for each city are assumed to be similar to the national prevalences measured by the DHS, because the latter are above 95&#x00025; for nearly all relevant countries, and this, considering the current high levels of ethnic mixing seen in African major cities, leaves little room for a major city to differ from the national average. Except for the situation iv) above, circumcision frequencies are estimated based on the ethnographic information about the circumcision practices of each group, according to an algorithm described in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s008">Text S2</xref>, and the supporting calculations are implemented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s010">Dataset S1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0009936.g004"/></fig><p>Among the three Central African cities which were clearly outstanding in size before the 1930s (Kinshasa, Douala, and Brazzaville (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g002">Figure 2A</xref>)) the first two (the proposed epicenters of HIV-1 groups M and O) had lower circumcision rates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g003">Figures 3A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g004">4A</xref>). During the period 1910&#x02013;35, Libreville, Bangui, and Yaound&#x000e9; may have had lower circumcision rates than after World War II, but we could not ascertain this by lack of adequate tables of ethnic composition. We did not include Rwandese and Burundian cities in our study, because they were very small up to mid 20<sup>th</sup> century <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lahmeyer1" ref-type="bibr">[65]</xref>, and the cattle raising tradition of these countries makes bushmeat practice uncommon <xref rid="pone.0009936-Gray2" ref-type="bibr">[93]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Gourou1" ref-type="bibr">[97]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Frazer1" ref-type="bibr">[98]</xref>.</p><p>Among the four West African cities that clearly stood out in size before World War II (Abidjan, Freetown, Monrovia, and Conakry (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g002">Figure 2B</xref>)) the first had a much lower circumcision rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g003">Figures 3B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g004">4B</xref>). Both HIV-2 epidemic groups (A and B) appear to have originated in C&#x000f4;te d'Ivoire <xref rid="pone.0009936-Santiago1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, as well as the dead-end/rare infections of groups G and H <xref rid="pone.0009936-Yamaguchi1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Santiago1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Therefore, the match between lack of circumcision in cities and HIV emergence appears to be stronger for HIV-2 than for HIV-1. Although C&#x000f4;te d'Ivoire contains only about 5&#x00025; of the sooty mangabey range <xref rid="pone.0009936-Santiago1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hooper1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, it is the country of origin of half of the identified HIV-2 strains, and Ivorian cities, such as Abidjan and Bouak&#x000e9;, had much lower circumcision rates up to World War II than the other West African cities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g003">Figures 3B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g004">4B</xref>). Our findings of significant differences between the cities are robust and independent of the assumptions we introduced to estimate circumcision rates (expressed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g004">Figure 4</xref>); they are clearly demonstrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g003">Figure 3</xref> (which does not work with circumcision rate estimates).</p><p>To further substantiate these observations, we gathered tables of surgical operations discriminating circumcisions to treat phimosis and paraphimosis in major cities <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service4" ref-type="bibr">[71]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service6" ref-type="bibr">[74]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Broden1" ref-type="bibr">[99]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Service13" ref-type="bibr">[106]</xref>. Ethnic groups performing universal circumcision almost always did it either at puberty with rituals, or in early childhood without rituals (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s008">Text S2</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s010">Dataset S1</xref>); in the first case, we assume parents would wait for puberty to circumcise the boy within the tribal rituals, even if he had phimosis; in the second case, a boy could have phimosis only during the first years of life. Therefore, ethnic groups performing universal circumcision should contribute little to the statistics of circumcisions for phimosis made in the colonial health system. These statistics should include mainly males from groups not performing universal circumcision. Therefore, we assume that high numbers of such recorded operations in a city reflect a relatively high proportion of uncircumcised adults living there. We display the results in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009936-t002">Table 2</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0009936-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009936.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Incidences of phimosis and paraphimosis in several African cities.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0009936-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0009936.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">City/division</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Years</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"># of cases</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annual incid.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Refs.</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belgian Congo</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kinshasa</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1907, 1910&#x02013;12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.685&#x00025;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pone.0009936-Broden1" ref-type="bibr">[99]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Hpital1" ref-type="bibr">[102]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belgian Congo</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kinshasa</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1926</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.357&#x00025;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pone.0009936-Staub1" ref-type="bibr">[103]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Belgian Congo</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kinshasa, Matadi, Boma<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1930&#x02013;31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.395&#x00025;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pone.0009936-Service11" ref-type="bibr">[104]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">French Congo</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazzaville</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1930&#x02013;34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.265&#x00025;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pone.0009936-Service6" ref-type="bibr">[74]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cameroon</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Douala/Wouri<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1932, 1935</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">313</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.635&#x00025;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pone.0009936-Service4" ref-type="bibr">[71]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mali</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bamako</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1937</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045&#x00025;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pone.0009936-Service12" ref-type="bibr">[105]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senegal</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saint Louis</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1937</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040&#x00025;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="pone.0009936-Service13" ref-type="bibr">[106]</xref>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>Presented the joint annual incidences of phimosis and paraphimosis in the males of several African cities, as reported in the medical references listed in the last column. Demographic data for each city is in <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lahmeyer1" ref-type="bibr">[65]</xref> and in the references listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s008">Text S2</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label/><p>
<sup><bold>a</bold></sup>The incidence is calculated over the joint adult male population of the three cities; about 3/5 of the operations were in Kinshasa.</p></fn><fn id="nt106"><label/><p>
<sup><bold>b</bold></sup>Most people from Wouri division were in Douala city <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service4" ref-type="bibr">[71]</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The low incidences of phimosis in Mali and Senegal are explained by the Islamic practice of circumcision in childhood. The phimosis data support the findings of our ethnographic study that circumcision was far from general in Central Africa in 1910&#x02013;35, and of lower rates in Kinshasa and Douala than in Brazzaville (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g003">Figures 3A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g004">4A</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s008">Text S2</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s010">Dataset S1</xref>). <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009936-t002">Table 2</xref> presents all the phimosis statistics we found that <italic>referred to a city</italic>; in addition to these, we collected many dozens of other phimosis statistics <italic>at the country level</italic>. They tend to corroborate the between country differences in circumcision levels that we obtained through the ethnographic approach (data not shown).</p><p>In our ethnographic study, we seized the opportunity to survey not only patterns of male circumcision, but also patterns of primate hunting. We present the results of this survey in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s004">Table S3</xref>. Hunting of chimpanzees and gorillas was very widespread among the ethnic groups of Central Africa, as was the hunting of monkeys in Central and West Africa (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s004">Table S3</xref>). Furthermore, SIVcpz and SIVsmm have a very wide geographical presence across the range of their primate hosts <xref rid="pone.0009936-Keele1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Santiago1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Santiago2" ref-type="bibr">[107]</xref>. Therefore, differences in hunting practices are unlikely to be the major factor explaining why HIV strains emerged only in some countries.</p><p>In conclusion, male circumcision rates in Central and West Africa were generally lower, and showed more pronounced regional differences in early 20<sup>th</sup> century than nowadays. Low circumcision levels in cities also appear to match early HIV epicenters and this is more evident for HIV-2 in West Africa than for HIV-1 in Central Africa.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Simulating the early spread of HIV in Kinshasa</title><p>Finally, we used computer simulations to verify that the time window for the emergence of epidemic/pandemic HIV strains indeed offered uniquely favorable conditions for the heterosexual spread of the virus. Because the window of opportunity may have involved simultaneous changes in several factors (population size, sex ratio, sexual promiscuity, GUD and circumcision prevalence), we also wanted to evaluate the individual contribution of each factor to successful epidemic emergence.</p><p>We focused on the origin of HIV-1 group M in Kinshasa for which we were able to collect the most complete historical data. Our simulations were parameterized to follow the recorded population size and structure of Kinshasa at several relevant time points, partly based on the availability of detailed population and medical records (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009936-t003">Table 3</xref>). The years 1919 and 1929 were chosen from the time interval estimated for the origin of HIV-1 group M <xref rid="pone.0009936-Salemi3" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Worobey1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>; both time points were characterized by rampant GUD epidemics, highly male-biased sex ratio and lower levels of circumcision than today. The year 1958 was chosen as a time point beyond the window defined by our phylogenetic dating study; although the city population had considerably expanded, GUD infections were generally under control and circumcision was almost universal. Finally, we have explored a &#x0201c;pre-colonial village&#x0201d; scenario to reflect a large settlement in the region before colonization, characterized by a healthy population structure and the absence of GUD infections and sex work.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0009936-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009936.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Scenario-specific parameters of the simulations.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0009936-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0009936.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-colonial village</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kinshasa 1919</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kinshasa 1929</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kinshasa 1958</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of women</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,265</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,081</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69,159</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of men</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,798</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31,817</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93,064</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of married couples</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">450</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">947</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,923</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48,411</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00025; of women &#x0201c;<italic>femmes libres</italic>&#x0201d;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00025; of men circumcised</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genital ulcer frequency (&#x00025;) in:</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Commercial sex workers (CSWs)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Femmes libres</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other women</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt107"><label/><p>The parameters are based on archival historical data and colonial medicine articles (<xref rid="pone.0009936-Croix1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Comissaire1" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Bruaux1" ref-type="bibr">[70]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service11" ref-type="bibr">[104]</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s007">Text S1</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s008">Text S2</xref>).</p></fn><fn id="nt108"><label/><p>
<sup><bold>a</bold></sup>A genital ulcer frequency of 5&#x00025; in <italic>femmes libres</italic> in 1929 is supported by two different venereal control surveys made in 1930 and 1932, involving 953 and 1,202 women (mostly <italic>femmes libres</italic>) respectively, which showed this frequency to be 4.7&#x00025; in 1930 and 4.6&#x00025; in 1932 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Croix1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. The venereal situation was probably even worse in the decade preceding 1929&#x02013;32 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Croix1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service11" ref-type="bibr">[104]</xref>, and reports from the years around 1910 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Mouchet2" ref-type="bibr">[67]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Service3" ref-type="bibr">[69]</xref> suggest incidences higher than in the period 1929&#x02013;32 (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s007">Text S1</xref>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Our simulations followed the early spread of the epidemic from the first zoonotic SIV infection over a dynamic network of sexual contacts, which was parameterized according to recent surveys <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lagarde1" ref-type="bibr">[108]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Buv2" ref-type="bibr">[114]</xref> (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009936-t004">Table 4</xref>). Transmission parameters were modeled after current HIV data, adopting the estimated relative effects of modifiers (e.g. GUD infection) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hayes1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Cameron1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Baeten1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Weiss1" ref-type="bibr">[81]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Williams1" ref-type="bibr">[82]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hollingsworth1" ref-type="bibr">[115]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Powers1" ref-type="bibr">[116]</xref>, but assuming a lower baseline transmission probability for ancestral HIV. The modifier effects of GUD infections and circumcision were implemented in the transmission process. We also assumed that transmission of these early strains (not yet adapted to humans) was limited to acute infection, as has been observed for recent cross-species SIV transmissions <xref rid="pone.0009936-Kalish1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. The network of contacts was parameterized according to recent studies <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lagarde1" ref-type="bibr">[108]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Buv2" ref-type="bibr">[114]</xref>, with the sexual promiscuity of &#x0201c;<italic>femmes libres</italic>&#x0201d; (an expression used by colonial writers to refer to unmarried/unmated women to whom a high rate of sexual partner change was attributed <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hooper1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Croix1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Bruaux1" ref-type="bibr">[70]</xref>) adjusted according to the sex ratio (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Materials and Methods</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009936-t004">Table 4</xref> for all scenario-independent parameters). We provide the code of our simulations in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s009">Text S3</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0009936-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009936.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Scenario-independent parameters of the simulations.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0009936-t004-4" xlink:href="pone.0009936.t004"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter (notation)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Default value/Formula [references]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other values tested [references]</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>Network parameters</italic></bold>
<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of non-spousal partners per year<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single women (N<sub>SW</sub>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lagarde1" ref-type="bibr">[108]</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Married women (N<sub>MW</sub>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 (estimated from data in <xref rid="pone.0009936-Ferry1" ref-type="bibr">[109]</xref>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single men (N<sub>SM</sub>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lagarde1" ref-type="bibr">[108]</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt111">c</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of short links<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">b</xref> (weeks) (D)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 (in <xref rid="pone.0009936-Ferry1" ref-type="bibr">[109]</xref> as reported by women)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt111">c</xref> (in <xref rid="pone.0009936-Ferry1" ref-type="bibr">[109]</xref> as reported by men)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of sex acts per week<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stable (spousal) link</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Buv1" ref-type="bibr">[110]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Wawer1" ref-type="bibr">[111]</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short link</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24 (estimated from data in <xref rid="pone.0009936-Ferry1" ref-type="bibr">[109]</xref>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt112">d</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CSW visits per man per year<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt110">b</xref> (C)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Ferry1" ref-type="bibr">[109]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Morison1" ref-type="bibr">[112]</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt113">e</xref>, 8<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt114">f</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex acts per CSW per year (S<sub>C</sub>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">600 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Kreiss1" ref-type="bibr">[113]</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt113">e</xref> (estimated from data in <xref rid="pone.0009936-Ferry1" ref-type="bibr">[109]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Buv2" ref-type="bibr">[114]</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>Derived parameters</italic></bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probability of short link breakup per week (p<sub>b</sub>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/D</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probability of short link formation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single women</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N<sub>SW</sub>/(D&#x0002b;52)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Married women</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N<sub>SM</sub>/(D&#x0002b;52)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single men (p<sub>f,SM</sub>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N<sub>SM</sub>/(D&#x0002b;52)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Married men<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt115">g</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p<sub>f,SM</sub>&#x02013;p<sub>b</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of CSW</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(Number of men)&#x0002a;C/S<sub>C</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probability of CSW visit per man per week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C/52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>HIV parameters</italic></bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of acute infection (weeks)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hollingsworth1" ref-type="bibr">[115]</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transmission multiplier for acute infection</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4, 26 (estimate for modern HIV-1 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hollingsworth1" ref-type="bibr">[115]</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum per-act transmission probability</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43 (equal to highest observed heterosexual rate <xref rid="pone.0009936-Cameron1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Per-act transmission probabilities<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt116">h</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02642;&#x02192;&#x02640; and &#x02640;&#x02192;&#x02642;(C)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Powers1" ref-type="bibr">[116]</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02640;&#x02192;&#x02642;(NC)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0025 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Weiss1" ref-type="bibr">[81]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Williams1" ref-type="bibr">[82]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Powers1" ref-type="bibr">[116]</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Cameron1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Baeten1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Powers1" ref-type="bibr">[116]</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02642;&#x02192;&#x02640;(GU)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hayes1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02642;(GU)&#x02192;&#x02640; and &#x02640;(GU) &#x02192;&#x02642;(C)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Cameron1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02640; (GU) &#x02192;&#x02642;(NC)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Cameron1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02640; &#x02192;&#x02642;(GU)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02642;(GU)&#x02192;&#x02640;(GU) and &#x02640;(GU)&#x02192;&#x02642;(GU)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>GUD parameters</italic></bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of GU episodes (weeks)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Garnett1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Oxman1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Steen1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt109"><label/><p>
<sup><bold>a</bold></sup>The studies in <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lagarde1" ref-type="bibr">[108]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Buv1" ref-type="bibr">[110]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Morison1" ref-type="bibr">[112]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Buv2" ref-type="bibr">[114]</xref> surveyed several African cities: we used the estimates provided for Yaound&#x000e9;, which was the location nearest to Kinshasa.</p></fn><fn id="nt110"><label/><p>
<sup><bold>b</bold></sup>These parameters determined means for random distributions, rather than fixed values.</p></fn><fn id="nt111"><label/><p>
<sup><bold>c</bold></sup>Both combinations of 3 partners per year with 52-week short links and 4.5 partners per year with 26-week short links yielded a concurrency index around 1.5, consistent with <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lagarde1" ref-type="bibr">[108]</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="nt112"><label/><p>
<sup><bold>d</bold></sup>Employing the same value as for stable links.</p></fn><fn id="nt113"><label/><p>
<sup><bold>e</bold></sup>The line between CSWs and <italic>femmes libres</italic> is blurred. We therefore ran also simulations without professional CSWs, and with CSWs with intermediate sexual promiscuity.</p></fn><fn id="nt114"><label/><p>
<sup><bold>f</bold></sup>There were 14 CSWs per 1,000 men in Yaound&#x000e9; according to <xref rid="pone.0009936-Buv2" ref-type="bibr">[114]</xref>. With 600 acts per CSW per year, this would yield about 8 CSW visits per man per year.</p></fn><fn id="nt115"><label/><p>
<sup><bold>g</bold></sup>This formula implies the same number of concurrent links (including the spousal link) but fewer annual partners for married compared with single men.</p></fn><fn id="nt116"><label/><p>
<sup><bold>h</bold></sup>(GU) indicates a partner with an active genital ulcer; (C) indicates a circumcised man; (NC) indicates a non-circumcised man.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>We defined several markers to characterize the efficiency of epidemic spread in the simulations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g005">Figure 5</xref>). Per simulation, we determined the total number of infections (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g005">Figure 5A</xref>) and the duration of an epidemic (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g005">Figure 5B</xref>), which characterize the extent of the first outbreak of infections and the ability of the virus to persist in the population even in its initial ill-adapted form (with reduced transmission efficiency compared with modern HIV). Long-term establishment (epidemic emergence) of HIV probably also depended on rapid initial adaptation to the new human host species. The capacity for this adaptation is also determined partly by the total number of human hosts and the duration of the epidemic (the age of the oldest lineage). However, an additional important determinant of adaptation is the length of the longest transmission chain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g005">Figure 5C</xref>), i.e. the number of &#x0201c;serial passages&#x0201d; in human hosts.</p><fig id="pone-0009936-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009936.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Comparison of early spread of HIV in simulated historical scenarios.</title><p>The graphs depict frequency distributions of the total number of infections per simulation (A), the duration of the epidemic (B) and the longest chain of transmission (C) from 1,000 simulations of Kinshasa in 1919 (red dots and bars), 1929 (blue dots and bars) and 1958 (green dots and bars), and a pre-colonial village (black dots and bars). The duration of an epidemic was defined as the time until the resolution of the last acute infection: its lower bound was defined by the length of acute infection in patient zero (12 weeks), its upper bound by the length of the simulations (52 weeks). The longest transmission chain was defined as the number of individuals in the longest chain of subsequent transmissions in each simulation. All frequencies (number of observations) are plotted on a log scale.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0009936.g005"/></fig><p>In all three quantifiers of epidemic emergence, the performance of the historical scenarios followed the same pattern: Kinshasa 1919&#x0003e; Kinshasa 1929&#x0226b; Kinshasa 1958&#x0226b; pre-colonial village (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g005">Figure 5</xref>). E.g. compared with the 1958 scenario, the 1929 scenario had 5-fold, the 1919 scenario 11-fold higher chance to generate at least 100 infections (6, 30 and 68 times out of 1,000 simulations); the pre-colonial village scenario never generated more than two infections. The probability of the ill-adapted virus to persist until the end of the simulated year was also dramatically higher for the 1919 and 1929 scenarios compared with the pre- and post-origin scenarios (73 and 37 vs. 5 and 0 times out of 1,000 simulations), as was the probability of generating a transmission chain of at least length five (81 and 49 vs. 10 and 0 times out of 1,000 simulations; see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s005">Table S4</xref> for more detailed simulation outcomes). We thus found that the scenarios dated around the origin of HIV-1 group M (1919 and 1929) were indeed much more permissive for the heterosexual spread of emergent HIV compared with scenarios dated either before or after the estimated origin. This result proved to be robust with respect to varying a number of parameters in the model (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s005">Table S4</xref>). Note also that even in the most permissive scenarios, the initial zoonotic infection was a dead end in more than 50&#x00025; of the simulation runs. Furthermore, the more permissive 1919 and 1929 scenarios yielded a bimodal distribution of outcomes indicating the effect of early stochastic events: after the first few transmissions, the epidemics that happened to reach the highly connected core of the sexual network can spread extensively; those that fail to do so, are likely to die out quickly.</p><p>While the resistance of the pre-colonial village to HIV emergence is not surprising, the dramatic decrease in permissiveness between 1929 and 1958, in spite of continued explosive population growth, demands further explanation. Furthermore, the 1919 scenario proved to be consistently more permissive than the 1929 scenario, in spite of considerable population growth over the decade. To identify the key factor(s) behind the observed differences, we explored systematically the effect of removing or reducing several factors that have been implicated in the emergence of HIV. Based on the most permissive 1919 scenario, we tested 10-fold reduced population size, balanced sex ratio (with 90&#x00025; of the sexually active population in stable relationship), absence of GUD infections and universal circumcision. The removal of GUD infections proved to have by far the most dramatic effect (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g006">Figure 6</xref>). Remarkably, both a strongly reduced population size (&#x0223c;1,200 sexually active individuals) and universal circumcision had a much weaker effect on the spread of ill-adapted HIV in the simulations. We also explored all combinations of these mitigating factors and found a consistently dominant effect of GUD prevalence (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s006">Table S5</xref>). We thus conclude that the period around the estimated origin of HIV-1 group M was uniquely permissive for the emergence of the virus by heterosexual transmission, and that the unprecedented GUD epidemics of the time were the main contributor to this high permissiveness.</p><fig id="pone-0009936-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009936.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>The effect of selected factors on the simulated early spread of HIV for Kinshasa 1919.</title><p>The graphs depict frequency distributions of the total number of infections (A), the duration of the epidemic (B) and the longest chain of transmission (C) from 1,000 simulations of Kinshasa with default parameters (black dots and bars), 10-fold reduced population size (red dots and bars), balanced sex ratio (blue dots and bars), no GUD (green dots and bars) and universal circumcision (gray dots and bars). The duration of an epidemic was defined as the time until the resolution of the last acute infection: its lower bound was defined by the length of acute infection in patient zero (12 weeks), its upper bound by the length of the simulations (52 weeks). The longest transmission chain was defined as the number of individuals in the longest chain of subsequent transmissions in each simulation. All frequencies (number of observations) are plotted on a log scale.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0009936.g006"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>We present multiple lines of evidence favorable to the hypothesis of rampant GUD epidemics having played a key role in the origin of the major HIV strains.</p><p>In agreement with earlier studies our molecular dating confirmed that all major epidemic HIV lineages were transmitted to our species in a narrow time frame. We dated the divergence of the HIV-1 groups M and O from their closest related SIVs using a different, but complementary approach compared to Wertheim and Worobey (2009) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Wertheim1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. Whereas Wertheim and Worobey (2009) aimed at estimating the TMRCA of SIV in chimpanzees and sooty mangabeys <xref rid="pone.0009936-Wertheim1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, we focused on obtaining an upper bound on the cross-species transmission from the chimpanzee species. To this purpose, we focused on separate <italic>pol</italic> data sets for HIV-1 group M/SIVcpz and HIV-1 group O/SIVgor/SIVcpz. Because the relatively conserved <italic>pol</italic> gene does not contain sufficient temporal signal (which may explain the relatively low rate and old TMRCAs of Wertheim and Worobey (2009) for a similar <italic>pol</italic> data set), we calibrated the phylogenies using the group M and group O TMRCAs respectively. Therefore, we essentially extrapolated on the rate of HIV-1 evolution, but also Wertheim and Worobey (2009) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Wertheim1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref> noted that the SIVcpz sequences could not be used on their own for meaningful date estimates. We obtained a relatively narrow timeframe for the interspecies transmissions, defined, for each HIV group, by the period between the split from the closest SIV and the intragroup TMRCA. Moreover, interspecies transmission and possible adaptation to humans probably happened close to the latter date, which would restrict the timeframe even further.</p><p>Thus, we looked for factors to explain why emergence of HIV is temporally and spatially restricted to the era and areas observed. Our review of the co-factors of sexual transmission indicated GUD as paramount and lack of male circumcision of secondary importance. GUD provides a portal of entry and attracts cells carrying CCR5, the co-receptor most used by HIVs and SIVs upon sexual transmission. In addition, GUD and especially syphilis induces a potent inflammatory response, and tumor-necrosis-factor (TNF)-&#x003b1; production <xref rid="pone.0009936-LaFond1" ref-type="bibr">[117]</xref>, which is a major enhancer of HIV replication <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lawn1" ref-type="bibr">[118]</xref>. Genital ulceration and inflammation in humans contributes strongly to the odds of acquisition of more than one HIV-1 viral variant <xref rid="pone.0009936-Haaland1" ref-type="bibr">[119]</xref>; and transmission of multiple viral variants was shown to contribute to adaptation to a different host species in experimental infection of chimpanzees with HIV-1 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Novembre1" ref-type="bibr">[120]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Novembre2" ref-type="bibr">[121]</xref> and rhesus macaques with SIVsmm <xref rid="pone.0009936-Demma1" ref-type="bibr">[122]</xref>. These processes suggest that GUD may contribute to SIV adaptation in ways beyond increased transmissibility.</p><p>Most theories for the origin of HIVs depend on a specific mechanism to facilitate the first few serial transmissions of the virus in humans, and largely limit the problem to initial adaptation <xref rid="pone.0009936-Marx1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Chitnis1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hooper1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Gisselquist1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. However, the emergence of an epidemic might also have depended on the conditions for large scale spread in the general population by the conventional route, i.e. by heterosexual transmission. Without favorable conditions for further spread, even a virus that passed initial adaptation might quickly go extinct. While we cannot exclude that the initial adaptation of HIVs depended on specific transmission routes (e.g. parenteral transmission), we investigated the possibility that epidemic emergence may have depended on large population centers riddled with sexual promiscuity and GUD. Bearing in mind that few cities in Central and West Africa were well developed during the peak GUD period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g002">Figure 2</xref>), our hypothesis may explain why few well-adapted strains emerged; and it may not be coincidence that exactly two HIV-1 groups emerged in Central Africa, at a time when two cities (Kinshasa and Douala) stood out in the region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g002">Figure 2A</xref>). Therefore we focused on the co-factors sexual promiscuity, GUD, and lack of circumcision in cities. Our review of the colonial medical literature established that GUD, particularly syphilis, chancroid, and LGV, peaked in the relevant cities, in the period 1910&#x02013;35, with incidences 1.5&#x02013;2.5 orders of magnitude higher than in mid 20<sup>th</sup> century, coinciding in time with the narrow timeframe of the emergence of epidemic HIV groups.</p><p>Our computer simulations of detailed historical scenarios for Kinshasa confirmed that the period around the origin of HIV-1 group M in the city was uniquely permissive for the emergence of an epidemic by heterosexual transmission. While exact probabilities of HIV emergence cannot be computed (e.g. we have no information on the initial infectivity of a novel zoonotic HIV), our semi-quantitative approach could robustly predict an increased relative probability associated with this time period. Furthermore, our simulations suggested that the peak in GUD prevalence was the most important contributor to chains of transmission of ill-adapted HIV. A related important result of the simulations is the inability of zoonotic HIV to generate epidemics in the pre-colonial village scenario (characterized by the absence of GUD and CSWs), which explains the long standing absence of HIV epidemics in the pre-colonial environments. According to these results, the window of high permissivity for epidemic HIV emergence was open by the spread of GUD infections due to the organized colonization of the relevant African areas, and probably closed by the aggressive treatment campaigns against GUDs from the mid thirties. Therefore, we predict that newly emerging HIV groups will have a less dramatic spread if GUD remains under control. Remarkably, the direct effect of population size and circumcision proved to be relatively small, although their effect is recognized and they may have acted indirectly.</p><p>In the simulations, the probabilities for sexual link formation and breakup were the same for all individuals of a class (e.g. single men, married women, etc). For the sake of simplicity, we did not implement a &#x0201c;small world network&#x0201d; <xref rid="pone.0009936-Liljeros1" ref-type="bibr">[123]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Sloot1" ref-type="bibr">[124]</xref>. However, the role of highly-connected &#x0201c;hubs&#x0201d; was explored by adding highly promiscuous CSWs with various settings to the simulations. Furthermore, increasing the proportion of highly-connected individuals in the population by employing a power-law distribution for the number of partners would only have enhanced heterosexual transmission even further.</p><p>Simulation models have been used before to estimate the contribution of sexually transmitted infections/GUDs to the current heterosexual spread of HIV <xref rid="pone.0009936-White1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Orroth1" ref-type="bibr">[125]</xref>. However, our study is the first to attempt a semi-quantitative assessment of the role of GUDs in the origin of the epidemics. Our model was tailored to focus on the early spread of HIV, which allowed for a simplified model structure.</p><p>We hypothesized that differences in male circumcision levels between cities may help to explain why HIV zoonotic strains emerged only in particular countries. Our extensive survey revealed circumcision patterns that were historically low in the putative centers of HIV emergence (Kinshasa, Douala, and Abidjan). Our simulations showed only a moderate direct effect of circumcision in the probability of generating long chains of transmission. However, lack of circumcision also favors GUD transmission <xref rid="pone.0009936-Steen1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Morris1" ref-type="bibr">[126]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Weiss2" ref-type="bibr">[127]</xref>, and low circumcision levels might have correlated with high GUD incidence. The prevalence of circumcision might thus have affected HIV emergence indirectly through its effect on GUD incidence. Lack of circumcision may have been more important for HIV-2 emergence, because epidemic HIV-2 groups emerged <italic>only</italic> in C&#x000f4;te d'Ivoire, a country which cities had <italic>much lower</italic> circumcision rates than the others of the region in the critical period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g003">Figure 3B</xref>).</p><p>Independently of the regional differences encountered, our finding of a very widespread trend of adoptions of circumcision, in early 20<sup>th</sup> century, by ethnic groups previously not practicing it, and the resulting temporal increase of circumcision rates in most relevant countries, is a solid result. It explains, as far as we know for the first time, the discrepancy between modern levels of circumcision, as showed by the Demographic and Health Surveys (DHS) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Macro1" ref-type="bibr">[89]</xref>, and the levels inferred from the Ethnographic Atlas <xref rid="pone.0009936-Murdock1" ref-type="bibr">[92]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Gray2" ref-type="bibr">[93]</xref>.</p><p>Independent of whether lack of circumcision was important to HIV adaptation, its geographical distribution may have determined to a large extent, which secondary foci developed in the decades after early emergence. Our finding of a relatively low circumcision rate in Guinea-Bissau may reinvigorate the debate about why this country became an early important focus of HIV-2 group A. In this regard it is important to note that some of the earliest transnational jumps of pandemic HIV-1 happened to countries where circumcision is uncommon: Haiti <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hempstone1" ref-type="bibr">[128]</xref>, Rwanda, Burundi, Zambia <xref rid="pone.0009936-Bongaarts1" ref-type="bibr">[83]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Wendell1" ref-type="bibr">[86]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Macro1" ref-type="bibr">[89]</xref>, and Thailand <xref rid="pone.0009936-Halperin1" ref-type="bibr">[85]</xref>.</p><p>Our simulations suggest that city size <italic>per se</italic> was not an important factor for initial HIV transmission. Therefore, we cannot rule out that the first transmissions (and possible initial adaptation of the virus) occurred in smaller settlements such as Bangui, Yaound&#x000e9;, Kribi or Brazzaville. However, the larger size of Kinshasa and Douala in that period may have been important for, at least, three reasons. First, a larger city attracts more immigrants per unit time, and hence potentially more SIV infections. Second, their larger size reflected early industrialization associated with start-up infrastructure projects (fluvial and sea harbors, railways), and this led to hasty recruitment of young male labor force, and thus to a extremely male-biased sex ratio, favoring commercial sex work and GUD. In the 1920s and 1930s, industry, public works, and business in general, were more advanced in Kinshasa and Douala than in the other Central African cities. Accordingly, sex work was &#x0201c;by far more flourishing&#x0201d; in Kinshasa than in Brazzaville <xref rid="pone.0009936-Gondola1" ref-type="bibr">[129]</xref>. Douala was also a major center of sex work and GUD <xref rid="pone.0009936-Letonturier1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Service4" ref-type="bibr">[71]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Schler1" ref-type="bibr">[130]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Diziain1" ref-type="bibr">[131]</xref>. In West Africa, sex work was widespread in Abidjan <xref rid="pone.0009936-DomergueCloarec1" ref-type="bibr">[79]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Rouch1" ref-type="bibr">[132]</xref>, whereas it only &#x0201c;existed on a small scale&#x0201d; in Monrovia <xref rid="pone.0009936-Fraenkel1" ref-type="bibr">[133]</xref>. Thus, high GUD prevalence might have depended indirectly on population size.</p><p>Third, while initial bursts of SIV spread, and resulting adaptation, might have happened in small settlements, further spread of the epidemic was probably centered on cities with large populations. Large cities were at the center of star-like traffic networks, connecting them to nearby settlements, and allowing for quick transfer of the virus from a local initial outbreak. Furthermore, outbreaks in small settlements might quickly become self-limiting by exhausting the supply of susceptible individuals, and sustained epidemics probably depended on the early transmission of the virus to a large center with fast replenishment of susceptible individuals to maintain the epidemic. Thus, major, well-connected centers, such as Kinshasa and Douala (which were better served by railway and fluvial connections, and had far more traffic than the other cities), may have acted as an &#x0201c;attractor&#x0201d; and a &#x0201c;hub&#x0201d; for HIV epidemics. Although these ideas were not explicitly modeled in this study, they may help to understand why exactly two HIV-1 strains evolved and spread considerably in Central Africa, and perhaps may give clues on the origin of the subtypes.</p><p>Our proposal that Kinshasa, Douala, and Abidjan constituted the initial hubs of the epidemic HIV groups can also explain the following historical facts: 1) the presence of already diversified HIV-1 group M in Kinshasa in 1959&#x02013;60, as evidenced by two seropositive samples (a subtype B/D and a subtype A) in only a few hundred stored blood and tissue samples available for screening <xref rid="pone.0009936-Worobey1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Nahmias1" ref-type="bibr">[134]</xref>; 2) the serologically confirmed evidence that HIV-1 group O was present in Douala's communities of sex workers by 1962 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hooper1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>; 3) the widespread presence of HIV-2 in separated locations in C&#x000f4;te d'Ivoire and in Guinea-Bissau (a country 1,000 km away) in the early sixties <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hooper1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>; this fact is better understood assuming that HIV-2 had expanded in the previous decades in a major, internationally connected, Ivorian city.</p><p>Our hypothesis satisfies both temporal and spatial coincidence between the factors which we invoke and the emergence of a pathogen. Such coincidence has previously been considered evidence that the factors are causally implicated <xref rid="pone.0009936-Frank1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, including by authors drafting hypotheses on the origins of HIV <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hahn1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Chitnis1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hooper1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Gisselquist1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Ppin1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. It also offers a conceptual simplicity because it proposes as causal factors for SIV adaptation to humans and initial spread the very same factors that most promote the continued spread of HIV nowadays: promiscuous sex, particularly involving sex workers, GUD, and possibly lack of circumcision. However, we are aware that the evidence we provide does not rule out the possibility of other processes having contributed to HIV emergence and/or adaptation. For example, parenteral transmission might also have contributed to the initial adaptation and/or initial spread of HIV (as seems to have been the case for SIVmac <xref rid="pone.0009936-Apetrei1" ref-type="bibr">[135]</xref>), or to further epidemic expansion. What we claim is that this is not necessary to explain the spatial and temporal patterns of HIV emergence, while high GUD incidence seems to have been the key determinant.</p><p>In this study, we narrowed down the origin of the epidemic HIV clades (HIV-1 groups M and O, HIV-2 groups A and B) to the first half of the 20<sup>th</sup> century, using phylogenetic molecular clock calculations. Our colonial archival literature survey shows that GUD epidemics peaked in cities in their early phases of development, providing a better coincidence with this narrow time frame than the driving factors proposed by other theories. Ethnographic literature illustrates that circumcision frequencies were historically considerably lower, and spatially more variable, than they are currently; in particular for HIV-2, low circumcision prevalence in cities indeed showed a geographical match with emerging HIV epicenters. Through epidemiological modeling we could simulate that early ill-adapted HIV could generate long chains of transmission only during a period of high GUD intensity. The effects of circumcision and city size were more likely indirect, through their capacity to enhance GUD intensity and allowing the initial hub of infections to potentially reach a threshold, and to spawn secondary foci. We conclude that intense GUD in nascent cities was probably the main factor that permitted zoonotic SIV to emerge as epidemic HIV, possibly in association with low circumcision rates.</p><p>We hope our hypothesis will increase awareness of the dangers posed by GUD in promoting transfer of SIV, STLV, and possibly other sexually transmitted viruses, to our species. These observations recommend close monitoring and treatment of GUD in Africa, and raise concern over the currently high prevalence of HSV-2 associated genital ulcers. We also underscore the importance of male circumcision in the prevention of novel HIV strain emergence.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Phylogenetic dating</title><p>SIVcpz&#x02013;HIV-1 group M and SIVgor&#x02013;HIV-1 group O divergence dates were estimated using a Bayesian relaxed clock analysis implemented in BEAST <xref rid="pone.0009936-Drummond1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. For SIVcpz&#x02013;HIV-1 group M, we analyzed the partial <italic>pol</italic> gene sequences (nucleotide 3887 to 4775 according to the HXB2 numbering) recently obtained from chimpanzees <xref rid="pone.0009936-Keele1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, three additional SIVcpz lineages (X52154, AY169968 and AF382828), and HIV-1 group M sequences previously analyzed by Lemey et al. (2005) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lemey3" ref-type="bibr">[136]</xref>. For SIVgor&#x02013;HIV-1 group O, we analyzed partial <italic>pol</italic> gene sequences (nucleotide 4230 to 4775 according to the HXB2 numbering) from three SIVgor <xref rid="pone.0009936-VanHeuverswyn1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, two SIVcpz (U42720 and X52154), and HIV-1 group O sequences previously analyzed by Lemey et al. (2004) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lemey2" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. We applied a general time reversible model with gamma-distributed rate variation among sites combined with an uncorrelated lognormal relaxed clock model and a piecewise constant population size model <xref rid="pone.0009936-Drummond1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. These conserved gene regions in the HIV genome are less subject to substitution saturation, but contain poor temporal signal <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lemey2" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. Therefore, we used a normal prior distribution on the TMRCA for both HIV-1 group M (1931&#x000b1;8 years) and HIV-1 group O (1915&#x000b1;17 years), based on published dates and their uncertainty <xref rid="pone.0009936-Korber1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Lemey2" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, to calibrate the molecular clock. Posterior distributions were obtained using Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) analysys and MCMC runs were investigated using Tracer (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/tracer/">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/tracer/</ext-link> ).</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>GUD incidences survey</title><p>We compiled STD and GUD incidence data for all the countries at or near the ranges of chimpanzees and sooty mangabeys through a survey of the relevant literature, of the period 1890&#x02013;1960, from the following sources:</p><p>1) Official colonial reports about health, or containing sections about health, and covering also demographic issues. A) For the Belgian Congo, collected in the Afrika Archief, Federale Overheidsdients&#x02013;Buitenlandse Zaken, Buitenlandse Handel en Ontwikkelingssamenwerking (FO-BZBHO) (Ministry of Foreign Affairs), Brussels; B) For French Equatorial Africa (AEF), and French West Africa (AOF), collected in the Centre des Archives d'Outre-Mer (CAOM), Aix-en-Provence (France), and in the Institut de M&#x000e9;decine Tropicale du Service de Sant&#x000e9; des Arm&#x000e9;es (IMTSSA), Marseille (France).</p><p>2) We complemented this information with articles in the main colonial and tropical medicine journals (Ann M&#x000e9;d Pharm Coloniales, Ann Hyg M&#x000e9;d Coloniales, Ann Soc Belge M&#x000e9;d Trop, Bull Soc Pathol Exotique, West African Med J, and others), and with books on the subject.</p><p>We did a complete survey of the GUD incidences in Kinshasa: supporting data and methods are described in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s007">Text S1</xref>.</p><p>We obtained the relevant demographic data about the relevant cities from articles, books, and archival reports (references in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s008">Text S2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Circumcision prevalence survey</title><p>We obtained circumcision information on ethnic groups from the Revised Ethnographic Atlas (Gray (1999) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Gray2" ref-type="bibr">[93]</xref>, which is based on Murdock (1967) <xref rid="pone.0009936-Murdock1" ref-type="bibr">[92]</xref>). We considered all relevant ethnic groups in the Ethnologue database <xref rid="pone.0009936-Gordon1" ref-type="bibr">[94]</xref>. We collected primary ethnographic articles and books to complement the circumcision information provided by the Atlas, thus covering all important ethnic groups, and almost all groups with more than 20,000 people, of the areas at or near chimpanzee and sooty mangabey ranges. Most observations were from the period 1880&#x02013;1940 (both those on which the Atlas is based, and those of our ethnographic collection). For each ethnic group, we gathered information on male circumcision practice, including generality, approximate time of adoption (if adopted recently), associated initiations and rituals if any, and age of circumcision. We collected demographic surveys specifying ethnic group composition of Central and West African cities, at several points in time. We generated lower and upper estimates of circumcision frequency in urban male adults of each ethnic group, based on the method explained in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s008">Text S2</xref> and implemented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s010">Dataset S1</xref>. We then computed the distribution of adults in cities by circumcision classes displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g003">Figure 3</xref>, and the estimates of circumcision frequencies displayed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0009936-g004">Figure 4</xref>. The full tables of ethnic composition, and the supporting references of this study are in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s008">Text S2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s010">Dataset S1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Simulation study</title><p>We developed a stochastic, individual-based simulation model to track the initial spread of HIV over a dynamic network of sexual contacts. The model distinguished married and single men and women, &#x0201c;<italic>femmes libres</italic>&#x0201d; and commercial sex workers (CSW). During the timeframe of the simulations (one year), the population was assumed to be constant (no birth, death or migration). The sexual network consisted of stable (spousal) links, short-term links and male visits to CSWs. Stable links were fixed throughout a simulation; short-term links were allowed to form and break up at each time step, and involved both married and single men and women, and <italic>femmes libres</italic>. Network parameters for married and single men and women were set according to modern studies from Yaound&#x000e9; (the closest available survey location) (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009936-t004">Table 4</xref> and references therein). <italic>Femmes libres</italic> were assigned with replacement to the remaining &#x0201c;open&#x0201d; short links of men: their sexual promiscuity was thus governed by the sex ratio (the shortage of short links by single and married women compared with short links of men) in each scenario. The number of CSWs was also automatically set in each scenario to match the demand for CSW visits.</p><p>Simulations had a time step of one week. All runs were preceded by an initialization phase restricted to link formation and breakup until the sexual network settled to a steady state. The initial HIV infection was then introduced into a single male to reflect the most likely source of a bushmeat hunter, and the spread of the virus was followed for a year. At each time step, sexual contacts were generated randomly over stable and short links; CSW visits involved a single sexual contact. HIV transmission was restricted to acute infection; its probability per contact was modified by GUD and circumcision status. Transmission rates were scaled according to estimates on modern HIV (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0009936-t004">Table 4</xref>), assuming multiplicative modifier effects and bounded from above by a maximum allowed rate. The basic acute transmission rate of early HIV was per default assumed to be lower than that of modern HIV, but higher than modern rates of chronic transmission. Circumcision status in men was fixed for the duration of the simulations. GUD dynamics was not modeled explicitly: healed genital ulcers were replaced randomly from the appropriate class of individuals. The age of GUD episodes and HIV infections was updated at the end of each time step. Chronic HIV infection was per default not transmissible, but protected against repeated acute infection. Population figures were set to reflect historical scenarios as described in the main text. Simulations were implemented in the R software package <xref rid="pone.0009936-R1" ref-type="bibr">[137]</xref>. All code is provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s009">Text S3</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0009936.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>The biogeography of epidemic HIV strains in Central Africa (A), and West Africa (B). The ranges of the primates that were the source of SIVs that gave rise to HIV strains are indicated (based on <xref rid="pone.0009936-Keele1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Clifford1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Hooper1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>). The circles mark the locations where SIVs most closely matching HIV-1 group M <xref rid="pone.0009936-Keele1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref> and HIV-2 groups A and B <xref rid="pone.0009936-Santiago1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref> were found. Compelling evidence suggests that the countries indicated in red were the most likely epicenters of particular HIV groups <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hooper1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0009936-Peeters1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Vidal1" ref-type="bibr">[77]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0009936-Vidal2" ref-type="bibr">[78]</xref>. The references cited in this legend are listed in the main article.</p><p>(8.73 MB TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0009936.s001.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0009936.s002"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>Modern levels of male circumcision in relevant countries of Central and West Africa.</p><p>(0.02 MB PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0009936.s002.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0009936.s003"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p>The coverage of male circumcision information attained by our ethnographic survey.</p><p>(0.02 MB PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0009936.s003.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0009936.s004"><label>Table S3</label><caption><p>Killing and consumption of apes/monkeys in Central and West Africa.</p><p>(0.06 MB PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0009936.s004.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0009936.s005"><label>Table S4</label><caption><p>Summary of the simulations outcomes for the four historical scenarios.</p><p>(0.04 MB XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0009936.s005.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0009936.s006"><label>Table S5</label><caption><p>Summary of simulation outcomes for combinatorial variants of the Kinshasa 1919 scenario.</p><p>(0.05 MB XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0009936.s006.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0009936.s007"><label>Text S1</label><caption><p>GUD incidences in Leopoldville/Kinshasa.</p><p>(0.14 MB PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0009936.s007.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0009936.s008"><label>Text S2</label><caption><p>Circumcision prevalences in Central and West Africa.</p><p>(0.12 MB PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0009936.s008.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0009936.s009"><label>Text S3</label><caption><p>Source code of the simulations.</p><p>(0.03 MB ZIP)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0009936.s009.zip"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0009936.s010"><label>Dataset S1</label><caption><p>Circumcision classes and frequencies in Central and West African cities.</p><p>(0.67 MB XLS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0009936.s010.xls"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are grateful to Prof Emeritus Jozef Vandepitte (Katholieke Universiteit Leuven, Belgium), to Prof Emeritus Stefaan Pattyn, (Tropical Institute of Medicine, Antwerp, Belgium), to Father Honor&#x000e9; Vinck and Prof Motingea Mangulu (Aequatoria, Belgium, and Democratic Republic of Congo), and to Prof Tamara Giles-Vernick (Univ of Minnesotta), for enlightening discussions. We thank Prof Charles Becker (Centre National de Recherche Scientifique, France), for guidance over the use of French colonial archives, Prof Barry Hewlett (Univ of Vancouver, Canada) for having provided us his original ethnographic dataset. We thank Drs Pierre Dandoy and Rafael Storme (Afrika Archief, Federale Overheidsdients&#x02013;Buitenlandse Zaken, Buitenlandse Handel en Ontwikkelingssamenwerking (FO-BZBHO), Brussels), Dr Evelyne Camara (Centre des Archives d'Outre-Mer (CAOM), Aix-en-Provence, France), and Dr Aline Pueyo (Institut de M&#x000e9;decine Tropicale du Service de Sant&#x000e9; des Arm&#x000e9;es (IMTSSA), Marseille, France), for their attention and help to our research in their respective Archives.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>P.L. was supported by a postdoctoral fellowship from the Fonds voor Wetenschappelijk Onderzoek (FWO; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fwo.be">http://www.fwo.be</ext-link>) Flanders, and FWO grant G.0513.06. V.M. was supported by the Hungarian Scientific Research Fund (Orszagos Tudomanyos Kutatasi Alap (OTKA); <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.otka.hu">http://www.otka.hu</ext-link>) grant NF72791. Both P.L. and V.M. were also supported by the European Commission Virolab Project (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.virolab.org">http://www.virolab.org</ext-link>) grant 027446. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0009936-VanHeuverswyn1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Heuverswyn</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Neel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Keele</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>SIV infection in wild gorillas.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>444</volume>
<fpage>164</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17093443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Keele1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keele</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Heuverswyn</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Takehisa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Chimpanzee Reservoirs of Pandemic and Nonpandemic HIV-1.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>313</volume>
<fpage>523</fpage>
<lpage>526</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16728595</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Hahn1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>De Cock</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>AIDS as a zoonosis: scientific and public health implications.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>287</volume>
<fpage>607</fpage>
<lpage>614</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10649986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Marx1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marx</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alcabes</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Drucker</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Serial human passage of simian immunodeficiency virus by unsterile injections and the emergence of epidemic human immunodeficiency virus in Africa.</article-title>
<source>Phil Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source>
<volume>356</volume>
<fpage>911</fpage>
<lpage>920</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11405938</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Chitnis1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chitnis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawls</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Origin of HIV-1 in colonial French Equatorial Africa?</article-title>
<source>AIDS Res Hum Retroviruses</source>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>5</fpage>
<lpage>8</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10628811</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Lemey1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pybus</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Saksena</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Salemi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Tracing the origin and history of the HIV-2 epidemic.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>100</volume>
<fpage>6588</fpage>
<lpage>6592</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12743376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Yamaguchi1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Devare</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Identification of a new HIV-2 subtype based on phylogenetic analysis of full-length genomic sequence.</article-title>
<source>AIDS Res Hum Retroviruses</source>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>925</fpage>
<lpage>930</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10875618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Damond1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Damond</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Worobey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Campa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Farfara</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Colin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Identification of a highly divergent HIV type 2 and proposal for a change in HIV type 2 classification.</article-title>
<source>AIDS Res Hum Retroviruses</source>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>666</fpage>
<lpage>672</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15242544</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Santiago1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santiago</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Range</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Keele</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Simian Immunodeficiency Virus Infection in Free-Ranging Sooty Mangabeys <italic>(Cercocebus atys aty</italic>s) from the Tai Forest, C&#x000f4;te d'Ivoire: Implications for the Origin of Epidemic Human Immunodeficiency Virus Type 2.</article-title>
<source>J Virol</source>
<volume>79</volume>
<fpage>12515</fpage>
<lpage>12527</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16160179</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Plantier1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plantier</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Leoz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickerson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>De Oliveira</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cordonnier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>A new human immunodeficiency virus derived from gorillas.</article-title>
<source>Nat Med</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>871</fpage>
<lpage>872</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19648927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Clifford1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clifford</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Anthony</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bawe-Johnson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abernethy</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tutin</surname><given-names>CEG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Mitochondrial DNA phylogeography of western lowland gorillas (<italic>Gorilla gorilla gorilla</italic>).</article-title>
<source>Mol Ecol</source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>1551</fpage>
<lpage>1565</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15140097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Groves1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Groves</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1978</year>
<article-title>Phylogenetic and Population Systematics of the Mangabeys (Primates: Cercopithecoidea).</article-title>
<source>Primates</source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>34</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Hooper1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hooper</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>The River: a Journey to the Source of HIV and AIDS.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Little, Brown, and Company</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Rmy1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>R&#x000e9;my</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1993</year>
<article-title>Image geographique de l'infection &#x000e0; VIH-1 en Afrique Centrale: des descontinuit&#x000e9;s remarquables.</article-title>
<source>Ann Soc Belg M&#x000e9;d Trop</source>
<volume>73</volume>
<fpage>127</fpage>
<lpage>142</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-QuionesMateu1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qui&#x000f1;ones-Mateu</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Arts</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Role of Human Immunodeficiency Virus Type 1 Group O in the AIDS Pandemic.</article-title>
<source>AIDS Rev</source>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>190</fpage>
<lpage>202</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-DeCock1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Cock</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brun-V&#x000e9;zinet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Soro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>HIV-1 and HIV-2 infections and AIDS in West Africa.</article-title>
<source>AIDS</source>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>Suppl 1</issue>
<fpage>S21</fpage>
<lpage>28</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Peeters1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peeters</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gueye</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mboup</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bibollet-Ruche</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekaza</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Geographical distribution of HIV-1 group O viruses in Africa.</article-title>
<source>AIDS</source>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>493</fpage>
<lpage>498</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9084797</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Ayouba1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ayouba</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Maucl&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>PMV</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mfoupouendoun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>HIV-1 Group O Infection in Cameroon, 1986&#x02013;1998.</article-title>
<source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>466</fpage>
<lpage>467</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11384531</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Yamaguchi2"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Coffey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vallari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngansop</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mbanya</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Identification of HIV Type 1 Group N Infections in a Husband and Wife in Cameroon: Viral Genome Sequences Provide Evidence for Horizontal Transmission.</article-title>
<source>AIDS Res Hum Retroviruses</source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>83</fpage>
<lpage>92</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16438650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Wolfe1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Switzer</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhullar</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanmugam</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Naturally acquired simian retrovirus infections in central African hunters.</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>
<volume>363</volume>
<fpage>932</fpage>
<lpage>937</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15043960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Kalish1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalish</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Ndongmo</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>McNicholl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Central African Hunters Exposed to Simian Immunodeficiency Virus.</article-title>
<source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>1928</fpage>
<lpage>1930</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16485481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Salemi1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salemi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Dooren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandamme</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Origin and Evolution of Human and Simian T-Cell Lymphotropic Viruses.</article-title>
<source>AIDS Rev</source>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>131</fpage>
<lpage>139</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Gisselquist1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gisselquist</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Emergence of HIV type 1 epidemic in the twentieth century: comparing hypotheses to evidence.</article-title>
<source>AIDS Res Hum Retroviruses</source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>1071</fpage>
<lpage>1078</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14709242</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Ppin1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;pin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Labb&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Noble goals, unforeseen consequences: control of tropical diseases in colonial Central Africa and the iatrogenic transmission of blood-borne viruses.</article-title>
<source>Trop Med Int Health</source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>10</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18578806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-VanDooren1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Dooren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Salemi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandamme</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Dating the Origin of the African Human T-Cell Lymphotropic Virus Type-I (HTLV-I) Subtypes.</article-title>
<source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>661</fpage>
<lpage>671</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11264418</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Salemi2"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salemi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Desmyter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandamme</surname><given-names>A-M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Tempo and mode of human and simian T-lymphotropic virus (HTLV/STLV) evolution revealed by analyses of full-genome sequences.</article-title>
<source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>374</fpage>
<lpage>386</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10723738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Salemi3"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salemi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Strimmer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Delaporte</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Dating the radiation of HIV-1 group M in 1930s using a new method to uncover clock-like molecular evolution.</article-title>
<source>FASEB J print</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>276</fpage>
<lpage>278</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Korber1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korber</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Muldoon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Theiler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Timing the ancestor of the HIV-1 pandemic strains.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>288</volume>
<fpage>1789</fpage>
<lpage>1796</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10846155</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Worobey1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Worobey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gemmel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Teuwen</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Haselkorn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunstman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Direct evidence of extensive diversity of HIV-1 in Kinshasa by 1960.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>455</volume>
<fpage>661</fpage>
<lpage>665</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18833279</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Lemey2"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pybus</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>The molecular population genetics of HIV-1 group O.</article-title>
<source>Genetics</source>
<volume>167</volume>
<fpage>1059</fpage>
<lpage>1068</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15280223</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Wertheim1"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wertheim</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Worobey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Dating the Age of the SIV Lineages That Gave Rise to HIV-1 and HIV-2.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>e1000377</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19412344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Gisselquist2"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gisselquist</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Upham</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Potterat</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Efficiency of Human Immunodeficiency Virus Transmission Through Injections and Other Medical Procedures: Evidence, Estimates, and Unfinished Business.</article-title>
<source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>944</fpage>
<lpage>952</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16941321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Hayes1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Plummer</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>The cofactor effect of genital ulcers on the per-exposure risk of HIV transmission in sub-Saharan Africa.</article-title>
<source>J Trop Med Hyg</source>
<volume>98</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>8</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Cameron1"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Simonsen</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Costa</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ronald</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Maitha</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1989</year>
<article-title>Female to male transmission of human immunodeficiency virus type 1: risk factors for seroconversion in men.</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>
<volume>2(8660)</volume>
<fpage>403</fpage>
<lpage>407</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2569597</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Fleming1"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wasserheit</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>From epidemiological synergy to public health policy and practice: the contribution of other sexually transmitted diseases to sexual transmission of HIV infection.</article-title>
<source>Sex Transm Infect</source>
<volume>75</volume>
<fpage>3</fpage>
<lpage>17</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10448335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Freeman1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Glynn</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Whithworth</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Herpes simplex virus 2 infection increases HIV acquisition in men and women: systematic review and meta-analysis of longitudinal studies.</article-title>
<source>AIDS</source>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>73</fpage>
<lpage>83</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16327322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-White1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Orroth</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Glynn</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Treating curable sexually transmitted infections to prevent HIV in Africa: still an effective control strategy?</article-title>
<source>J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</source>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>346</fpage>
<lpage>353</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18176323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Baeten1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baeten</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavreys</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rakwar</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandaliya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Female-to-male infectivity of HIV-1 among circumcised and uncircumcised Kenyan men.</article-title>
<source>J Infect Dis</source>
<volume>191</volume>
<fpage>546</fpage>
<lpage>553</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15655778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Frank1"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Strickland</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavanchy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Arthur</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>The role of parenteral antischistosomal therapy in the spread of hepatitis C virus in Egypt.</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>
<volume>355</volume>
<fpage>887</fpage>
<lpage>891</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10752705</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Drummond1"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SYW</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Relaxed phylogenetics and dating with confidence.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Biol</source>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>e88</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16683862</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Yusim1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yusim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Peeters</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pybus</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Delaporte</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Using human immunodeficiency virus type 1 sequences to infer historical features of the acquired immune deficiency syndrome epidemic and human immunodeficiency virus evolution.</article-title>
<source>Phil Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source>
<volume>356</volume>
<fpage>855</fpage>
<lpage>866</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11405933</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Thomas1"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>JMC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1963</year>
<article-title>Les Ngbaka de la Lobaye: le d&#x000e9;peuplement rural chez une population foresti&#x000e8;re de la R&#x000e9;publique Centrafricaine.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Mouton</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Oates1"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oates</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>African Primates: Status Survey and Conservation Action Plan, Revised Edition.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>Gland, Switzerland</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>IUCN/SSC Primate Specialist Group</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Teleki1"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teleki</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1989</year>
<article-title>Population status of wild chimpanzees <italic>(Pan troglodytes)</italic> and threats to survival.</article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Heltne</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquardt</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Understanding Chimpanzees</source>
<publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Harvard Univ Press</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Garnett1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garnett</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Aral</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoyle</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Cates</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>The natural history of syphilis: implications for the transmission dynamics and control of infection.</article-title>
<source>Sex Transm Dis</source>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>185</fpage>
<lpage>200</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9101629</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Oxman1"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oxman</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Smolkowski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Noell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Mathematical modeling of epidemic syphilis transmission. Implications for syphilis control programs.</article-title>
<source>Sex Transm Dis</source>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>30</fpage>
<lpage>39</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8801640</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Service1"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Service de l'Hygi&#x000e8;ne Publique</collab>
<year>1933&#x02013;58</year>
<article-title>Rapport sur l'hygi&#x000e8;ne publique au Congo Belge pendant l'ann&#x000e9;e [1933 through 1958].</article-title>
<publisher-loc>Leopoldville, Belgian Congo</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Service de l'Hygi&#x000e8;ne Publique</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Croix1"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Croix Rouge du Congo</collab>
<year>1928&#x02013;54</year>
<article-title>Rapport annuel [1928 through 1954].</article-title>
<publisher-loc>Brussels</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Croix Rouge de Belgique</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Steen1"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Eradicating chancroid.</article-title>
<source>Bull World Health Organ</source>
<volume>79</volume>
<fpage>818</fpage>
<lpage>826</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11584729</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-RetelLaurentin1"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Retel-Laurentin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1979</year>
<article-title>Un Pays &#x000e0; la D&#x000e9;rive: une Societ&#x000e9; en R&#x000e9;gression D&#x000e9;mographique: les Nzakara de l'Est Centrafricain.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Jean-Pierre Delarge</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Harms1"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harms</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1981</year>
<article-title>River of Wealth, River of Sorrow: the Central Zaire Basin in the Era of the Slave and Ivory Trade, 1500&#x02013;1891.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>New Haven</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Yale Univ Press</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Headrick1"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Headrick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Colonialism, Health and Illness in French Equatorial Africa, 1885&#x02013;1935.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>Atlanta</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>African Studies Associated Press</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Mouchet1"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mouchet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1926</year>
<article-title>Yaws and syphilis among natives of the Belgian Congo.</article-title>
<source>Kenya Med J</source>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>242</fpage>
<lpage>245</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Kermorgant1"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kermorgant</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1903</year>
<article-title>Aper&#x000e7;u sur les maladies v&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;riennes dans les colonies fran&#x000e7;aises.</article-title>
<source>Ann Hyg M&#x000e9;d Colon</source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>428</fpage>
<lpage>460</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Patterson1"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1975</year>
<article-title>The vanishing Mpongwe: European contact and demographic change in the Gabon river.</article-title>
<source>J Afr Hist</source>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>217</fpage>
<lpage>238</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Phillips1"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Heterogeneous Imperialism and the Regulation of Sexuality in British West Africa.</article-title>
<source>J Hist Sexuality</source>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>291</fpage>
<lpage>315</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Georgelin1"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Georgelin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1920</year>
<article-title>Notes m&#x000e9;dicales sur le Gabon: les facteurs de d&#x000e9;population.</article-title>
<source>Ann M&#x000e9;d Pharm Colon</source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>58</fpage>
<lpage>64</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Heim1"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heim</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1913</year>
<article-title>Die Syphilis in den deutschen Schutzgebieten.</article-title>
<source>Arch Dermatol Res</source>
<volume>118</volume>
<fpage>165</fpage>
<lpage>198</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Letonturier1"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Letonturier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1924</year>
<article-title>Rapport sur le fonctionnement du service de sant&#x000e9; au Cameroun pendant l'ann&#x000e9;e 1923.</article-title>
<source>Ann M&#x000e9;d Pharm Colon</source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>396</fpage>
<lpage>408</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Goeman1"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goeman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Meheus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Piot</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Sexually Transmitted Diseases.</article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Janssens</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kivits</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vuylsteke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Health in Central Africa since 1885: past, present, and future</source>
<publisher-loc>Brussels</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Koning Boudewijnstichting</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-VanWing1"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Wing</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1938</year>
<article-title>&#x000c9;tudes Bakongo: Sociologie, Religion et Magie.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>Brussels</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Van Campenhout</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Trezenem1"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trezenem</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1936</year>
<article-title>Notes ethnographiques sur les tribus Fan du Moyen-Ogoou&#x000e9;.</article-title>
<source>J Soc Africanistes</source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>65</fpage>
<lpage>93</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Schwab1"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1947</year>
<article-title>Tribes of the Liberian hinterland: Report of the Peabody Museum expedition to Liberia.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Peabody Museum of American Archaeology and Ethnology</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Meheus1"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meheus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Yaws.</article-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Janssens</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kivits</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vuylsteke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Health in Central Africa since 1885: past, present, and future</source>
<publisher-loc>Brussels</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Koning Boudewijnstichting</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Lahmeyer1"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lahmeyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Population Statistics: historical demography of all countries, their divisions and towns.</article-title>
<comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.populstat.info">http://www.populstat.info</ext-link>. Accessed 2009 Aug 22</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Comissaire1"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>Comissaire du District Urbain de Leopoldville</collab>
<year>1928</year>
<article-title>Rapport sur le r&#x000e9;censement de la population indig&#x000e8;ne.</article-title>
<comment>Afrika Archief (FO-BZBHO, Brussels), Inventory A39, Box RA/AIMO 119</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Mouchet2"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mouchet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1913</year>
<article-title>Le traitement du Pian et de la Syphilis par le Salvarsan dans la pratique indig&#x000e8;ne.</article-title>
<source>Bull Soc Pathol Exot Fil</source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>14</fpage>
<lpage>19</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Service2"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>Service M&#x000e9;dical</collab>
<year>1911</year>
<article-title>R&#x000e9;sultats des examens m&#x000e9;dicaux mensuels pour les mois de Janvier et F&#x000e9;vrier 1911.</article-title>
<comment>Leopoldville, Belgian Congo. Afrika Archief (FO-BZBHO, Brussels), Inventory A11, Box 841</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Service3"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>Service M&#x000e9;dical</collab>
<year>1911</year>
<article-title>Note explicative du relev&#x000e9; statistique des visites m&#x000e9;dicales mensuelles (Mars&#x02013;Avril-Mai 1911).</article-title>
<comment>Leopoldville, Belgian Congo. Afrika Archief (FO-BZBHO, Brussels), Inventory A11, Box 841</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Bruaux1"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruaux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerf</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebrun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1957</year>
<article-title>La lutte contre les affections v&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;riennes &#x000e0; L&#x000e9;opoldville.</article-title>
<source>Ann Soc Belg M&#x000e9;d Trop</source>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>801</fpage>
<lpage>813</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Service4"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>Service de Sant&#x000e9;</collab>
<year>1935</year>
<article-title>Rapport du Service de Sant&#x000e9;, Division du Wouri, Territoire du Cameroun.</article-title>
<comment>Douala, Cameroon: Service de Sant&#x000e9;. IMTSSA, Box 481</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Service5"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>Service de Sant&#x000e9;</collab>
<year>1939</year>
<article-title>Rapport Annuel du Service de Sant&#x000e9;, Territoire du Cameroun.</article-title>
<comment>Yaound&#x000e9;, Cameroon: Service de Sant&#x000e9;. IMTSSA, Box 107</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-LeGall1"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le Gall</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1941</year>
<article-title>Rapport du Minist&#x000e8;re des Colonies sur les maladies pestilentielles et les maladies end&#x000e9;mo-&#x000e9;pid&#x000e9;miques dans l'Empire Colonial Fran&#x000e7;ais au cours de l'ann&#x000e9;e 1939.</article-title>
<source>M&#x000e9;d Trop</source>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>575</fpage>
<lpage>954</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Service6"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>Service de Sant&#x000e9;</collab>
<year>1930</year>
<article-title>Rapport annuel du Chef du Service de Sant&#x000e9;, Colonie du Moyen-Congo, Afrique &#x000c9;quatoriale Fran&#x000e7;aise [1930 through 1934].</article-title>
<comment>Brazzaville, AEF: Service de Sant&#x000e9;. IMTSSA, Box 117</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Service7"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>Service de Sant&#x000e9;</collab>
<year>1952</year>
<article-title>Rapport Annuel, H&#x000f4;pital G&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;ral de Brazzaville, Afrique &#x000c9;quatoriale Fran&#x000e7;aise [1952 through 1957].</article-title>
<comment>Brazzaville, AEF: Service de Sant&#x000e9;. IMTSSA, Box 120</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-OFarrell1"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Farrell</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Increasing prevalence of genital herpes in developing countries: implications for heterosexual HIV transmission and STI control programmes.</article-title>
<source>Sex Transm Infect</source>
<volume>75</volume>
<fpage>377</fpage>
<lpage>384</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10754939</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Vidal1"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Peeters</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulanga-Kabeya</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nzilambi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Unprecedented Degree of Human Immunodeficiency Virus Type 1 (HIV-1) Group M Genetic Diversity in the Democratic Republic of Congo Suggests that the HIV-1 Pandemic Originated in Central Africa.</article-title>
<source>J Virol</source>
<volume>74</volume>
<fpage>10498</fpage>
<lpage>10507</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11044094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Vidal2"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulanga</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazepeo</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mwamba</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tchimpaka</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Distribution of HIV-1 Variants in the Democratic Republic of Congo Suggests Increase of Subtype C in Kinshasa Between 1997 and 2002.</article-title>
<source>J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr</source>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>456</fpage>
<lpage>462</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16280702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-DomergueCloarec1"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Domergue-Cloarec</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1986</year>
<article-title>La Sant&#x000e9; en C&#x000f4;te d'Ivoire, 1905&#x02013;1958.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>Toulouse</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Association des Publications Univ Toulouse-Le Mirail</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Service8"><label>80</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>Service de Sant&#x000e9;</collab>
<year>1937</year>
<article-title>Rapport annuel m&#x000e9;dical, Colonie de la C&#x000f4;te d'Ivoire.</article-title>
<comment>Abidjan, C&#x000f4;te d'Ivoire: Service de Sant&#x000e9;. CAOM, Series 14 Mi, Reference 2G37</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Weiss1"><label>81</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Quigley</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Male circumcision and risk of HIV infection in sub-Saharan Africa: a systematic review and meta-analysis.</article-title>
<source>AIDS</source>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>2361</fpage>
<lpage>2370</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11089625</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Williams1"><label>82</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd-Smith</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouws</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hankins</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Getz</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>The Potential Impact of Male Circumcision on HIV in Sub-Saharan Africa.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Med</source>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>e262</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16822094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Bongaarts1"><label>83</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bongaarts</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Reining</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Way</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Conant</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1989</year>
<article-title>The relationship between male circumcision and HIV infection in African populations.</article-title>
<source>AIDS</source>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>373</fpage>
<lpage>377</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2502151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Moses1"><label>84</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moses</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagelkerke</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ronald</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ndinya-Achola</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1990</year>
<article-title>Geographical patterns of male circumcision practices in Africa: association with HIV seroprevalence.</article-title>
<source>Int J Epidemiol</source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>693</fpage>
<lpage>697</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2262266</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Halperin1"><label>85</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halperin</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Male circumcision and HIV infection: 10 years and counting.</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>
<volume>354</volume>
<fpage>1813</fpage>
<lpage>1815</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10577659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Wendell1"><label>86</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wendell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Werker</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Male Circumcision and the Impact of AIDS in Africa.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>Cambridge MA</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Harvard University Department of Economics</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Bailey1"><label>87</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Moses</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Agot</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Maclean</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Male circumcision for HIV prevention in young men in Kisumu, Kenya: a randomised controlled trial.</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>
<volume>369</volume>
<fpage>643</fpage>
<lpage>656</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17321310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Gray1"><label>88</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kigozi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Serwadda</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Makumbi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Watya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Male circumcision for HIV prevention in men in Rakai, Uganda: a randomised trial.</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>
<volume>369</volume>
<fpage>657</fpage>
<lpage>666</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17321311</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Macro1"><label>89</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Macro International</collab>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Demographic and Health Surveys.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>Calverton</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Macro International</publisher-name>
<comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.measuredhs.com">http://www.measuredhs.com</ext-link>. Accessed 2010 Feb 25</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Ppin2"><label>90</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;pin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Plamondon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaudet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Labb&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Parenteral transmission during excision and treatment of tuberculosis and trypanosomiasis may be responsible for the HIV-2 epidemic in Guinea-Bissau.</article-title>
<source>AIDS</source>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>1303</fpage>
<lpage>1311</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16816560</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Bangna1"><label>91</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bangna</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Caracter&#x000ed;sticas S&#x000f3;cio-Comportamentais Relacionadas ao Risco de Transmiss&#x000e3;o do HIV em Escolares de 15 a 24 anos, na Guin&#x000e9;-Bissau.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>Rio de Janeiro</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Oswaldo Cruz, Escola Nacional de Sa&#x000fa;de P&#x000fa;blica S&#x000e9;rgio Arouca</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Murdock1"><label>92</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murdock</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1967</year>
<article-title>Ethnographic Atlas.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>Pittsburgh</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Univ of Pittsburgh Press</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Gray2"><label>93</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Ethnographic Atlas Revised by World Cultures.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>York College, CUNY</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Gordon1"><label>94</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>RGJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Ethnologue: Languages of the World, Fifteenth edition.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>Dallas</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>SIL International</publisher-name>
<comment>Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ethnologue.com">http://www.ethnologue.com</ext-link>. Accessed 2009 Sep 10</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Friedrichs1"><label>95</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Friedrichs</surname><given-names>A (Herzogs zu Mecklenbourg)</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1924</year>
<article-title>Wissenschaftliche Ergebnisse der Deutschen Zentral-Afrika Expedition 1907&#x02013;1908.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>Leipzig</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Klinkhardt &#x00026; Biermann</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Frobenius1"><label>96</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frobenius</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Von Wilm</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1929</year>
<article-title>Atlas Africanus: Belege zur Morphologie der afrikanischen Kulturen.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>M&#x000fc;nchen</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>C H Beck</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Gourou1"><label>97</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gourou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1953</year>
<article-title>La densit&#x000e9; de la population au Ruanda-Urundi: Esquisse d'une &#x000e9;tude g&#x000e9;ographique.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>Brussels</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Koninklijk Belgisch Koloniaal Instituut</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Frazer1"><label>98</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frazer</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1938</year>
<article-title>Native races of Africa and Madagascar.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Percy Lund Humphries &#x00026; Co</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Broden1"><label>99</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Broden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodhain</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1908</year>
<article-title>Rapport sur les travaux fais au Laboratoire de la Societ&#x000e9; Belge d'&#x000c9;tudes Coloniales, &#x000e0; l'H&#x000f4;pital des Noirs et au Lazaret pour Trypanosomi&#x000e9;s &#x000e0; Leopoldville (Congo Belge).</article-title>
<publisher-loc>Brussels</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Hayez</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Service9"><label>100</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>Service d'Hygi&#x000e8;ne Publique</collab>
<year>1910</year>
<article-title>Rapport sur l'hygi&#x000e8;ne publique au Congo Belge. Boma, Belgian Congo: Service d'Hygi&#x000e8;ne Publique.</article-title>
<comment>Afrika Archief (FO-BZBHO, Brussels), Inventory A39, Box 80</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Service10"><label>101</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>Service M&#x000e9;dical</collab>
<year>1911</year>
<article-title>Rapport du Service M&#x000e9;dical du District du Moyen-Congo.</article-title>
<comment>Leopoldville, Belgian Congo: Service M&#x000e9;dical. Afrika Archief (FO-BZBHO, Brussels), Series GG, Folder GG 16807</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Hpital1"><label>102</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>H&#x000f4;pital des Noirs</collab>
<year>1913</year>
<article-title>Rapport sur le fonctionnement de l'H&#x000f4;pital des Noirs pendant l'ann&#x000e9;e 1912.</article-title>
<comment>Leopoldville, Belgian Congo: Service M&#x000e9;dical. Afrika Archief (FO-BZBHO, Brussels), Inventory A39, Box 80</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Staub1"><label>103</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Staub</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1926</year>
<article-title>Rapport r&#x000e9;sumant des observations concernant le service de chirurgie &#x000e0; L&#x000e9;opoldville de juillet 1925 &#x000e0; juillet 1926; statistique des op&#x000e9;rations chirurgicales pratiqu&#x000e9;es pendant ce temps [dissertation].</article-title>
<comment>Instituut voor Tropische Geneeskunde, Antwerp, Examen ITG/B-47</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Service11"><label>104</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>Service M&#x000e9;dical</collab>
<year>1930</year>
<article-title>Rapport Annuel, Service M&#x000e9;dical, Province du Congo-Kasai [1930 through 1931].</article-title>
<comment>Leopoldville, Belgian Congo: Service M&#x000e9;dical. Afrika Archief (FO-BZBHO, Brussels), Inventory A39, Box 88</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Service12"><label>105</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>Service de Sant&#x000e9;</collab>
<year>1937</year>
<article-title>Rapport annuel m&#x000e9;dical, Colonie du Soudan Fran&#x000e7;ais.</article-title>
<comment>Bamako, French Sudan/Mali: Service de Sant&#x000e9;. CAOM, Series 14 Mi, Reference 2G37</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Service13"><label>106</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>Service de Sant&#x000e9;</collab>
<year>1937</year>
<article-title>Rapport annuel m&#x000e9;dical, Colonie du S&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;gal.</article-title>
<comment>Dakar, Senegal: Service de Sant&#x000e9;. CAOM, Series 14 Mi, Reference 2G37</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Santiago2"><label>107</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santiago</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukasik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamenya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bibollet-Ruche</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Foci of Endemic Simian Immunodeficiency Virus Infection in Wild-Living Eastern Chimpanzees (<italic>Pan troglodytes schweinfurthii</italic>).</article-title>
<source>J Virol</source>
<volume>77</volume>
<fpage>7545</fpage>
<lpage>7562</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12805455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Lagarde1"><label>108</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lagarde</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Auvert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Carael</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Laourou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferry</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Concurrent sexual partnerships and HIV prevalence in five urban communities of sub-Saharan Africa.</article-title>
<source>AIDS</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>877</fpage>
<lpage>884</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11399960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Ferry1"><label>109</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferry</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Carael</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Buv&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Auvert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Laourou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Comparison of key parameters of sexual behaviour in four African urban populations with different levels of HIV infection.</article-title>
<source>AIDS</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>Suppl 4</issue>
<fpage>S41</fpage>
<lpage>50</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Buv1"><label>110</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buv&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagarde</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Carael</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutenberg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferry</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Interpreting sexual behaviour data: validity issues in the multicentre study on factors determining the differential spread of HIV in four African cities.</article-title>
<source>AIDS</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>Suppl 4</issue>
<fpage>S117</fpage>
<lpage>126</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Wawer1"><label>111</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wawer</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sewankambo</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Serwadda</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Rates of HIV-1 transmission per coital act, by stage of HIV-1 infection, in Rakai, Uganda.</article-title>
<source>J Infect Dis</source>
<volume>191</volume>
<fpage>1403</fpage>
<lpage>1409</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15809897</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Morison1"><label>112</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morison</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Buv&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carael</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abega</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Commercial sex and the spread of HIV in four cities in sub-Saharan Africa.</article-title>
<source>AIDS</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>Suppl 4</issue>
<fpage>S61</fpage>
<lpage>69</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11686467</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Kreiss1"><label>113</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kreiss</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Koech</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Plummer</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lightfoote</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1986</year>
<article-title>AIDS virus infection in Nairobi prostitutes. Spread of the epidemic to East Africa.</article-title>
<source>N Engl J Med</source>
<volume>314</volume>
<fpage>414</fpage>
<lpage>418</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3484804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Buv2"><label>114</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buv&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carael</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Auvert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferry</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Multicentre study on factors determining differences in rate of spread of HIV in sub-Saharan Africa: methods and prevalence of HIV infection.</article-title>
<source>AIDS</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>Suppl 4</issue>
<fpage>S5</fpage>
<lpage>14</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Hollingsworth1"><label>115</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hollingsworth</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>HIV-1 transmission, by stage of infection.</article-title>
<source>J Infect Dis</source>
<volume>198</volume>
<fpage>687</fpage>
<lpage>693</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18662132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Powers1"><label>116</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pettifor</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Rethinking the heterosexual infectivity of HIV-1: a systematic review and meta-analysis.</article-title>
<source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>553</fpage>
<lpage>563</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18684670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-LaFond1"><label>117</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>LaFond</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukehart</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Biological Basis for Syphilis.</article-title>
<source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>29</fpage>
<lpage>49</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16418521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Lawn1"><label>118</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lawn</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Butera</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Folks</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Contribution of immune activation to the pathogenesis and transmission of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 infection.</article-title>
<source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>753</fpage>
<lpage>777</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11585784</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Haaland1"><label>119</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haaland</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Salazar-Gonzalez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tichacek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Inflammatory Genital Infections Mitigate a Severe Genetic Bottleneck in Heterosexual Transmission of Subtype A and C HIV-1.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Path</source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>e1000274</fpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Novembre1"><label>120</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Novembre</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Saucier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Klumpp</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Neil</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Development of AIDS in a Chimpanzee Infected with Human Immunodeficiency Virus Type 1.</article-title>
<source>J Virol</source>
<volume>71</volume>
<fpage>4086</fpage>
<lpage>4091</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9094687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Novembre2"><label>121</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Novembre</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosayro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nidtha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Neil</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Rapid CD4<sup>&#x0002b;</sup> T-Cell Loss Induced by Human Immunodeficiency Virus Type 1<sub>NC</sub> in Uninfected and Previously Infected Chimpanzees.</article-title>
<source>J Virol</source>
<volume>75</volume>
<fpage>1533</fpage>
<lpage>1539</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11152525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Demma1"><label>122</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demma</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Logsdon</surname><given-names>JM</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Vanderford</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Feinberg</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Staprans</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>SIVsm Quasispecies Adaptation to a New Simian Host.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Path</source>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>e3</fpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Liljeros1"><label>123</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liljeros</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Edling</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Amaral</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Aberg</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>The web of human sexual contacts.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>411</volume>
<fpage>907</fpage>
<lpage>908</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11418846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Sloot1"><label>124</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sloot</surname><given-names>PMA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Boukhanovsky</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Vijver</surname><given-names>DAMC</given-names></name><name><surname>Boucher</surname><given-names>CAB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Stochastic simulation of HIV population dynamics through complex network modelling.</article-title>
<source>Int J Comput Math</source>
<volume>85</volume>
<fpage>1175</fpage>
<lpage>1187</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Orroth1"><label>125</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orroth</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Korenromp</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Changalucha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Empirical observations underestimate the proportion of human immunodeficiency virus infections attributable to sexually transmitted diseases in the Mwanza and Rakai sexually transmitted disease treatment trials: Simulation results.</article-title>
<source>Sex Transm Dis</source>
<volume>33</volume>
<fpage>536</fpage>
<lpage>544</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16778738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Morris1"><label>126</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Why circumcision is a biomedical imperative for the 21(st) century.</article-title>
<source>BioEssays</source>
<volume>29</volume>
<fpage>1147</fpage>
<lpage>1158</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17935209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Weiss2"><label>127</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Munabi</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Male circumcision and risk of syphilis, chancroid, and genital herpes: a systematic review and meta-analysis.</article-title>
<source>Sex Transm Infect</source>
<volume>82</volume>
<fpage>101</fpage>
<lpage>110</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16581731</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Hempstone1"><label>128</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hempstone</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Diop-Sidibe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahanda</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Laurendent</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Heerey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>HIV/AIDS in Haiti: A Literature Review.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>USAID/Health Communication Partnership</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Gondola1"><label>129</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gondola</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Villes Miroirs: Migrations et identit&#x000e9;s urbaines &#x000e0; Kinshasa et Brazzaville, 1930&#x02013;1970.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>L'Harmattan</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Schler1"><label>130</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Ambiguous spaces: the struggle over African identities and urban communities in colonial Douala, 1914&#x02013;45.</article-title>
<source>J Afr Hist</source>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>51</fpage>
<lpage>72</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Diziain1"><label>131</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diziain</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cambon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1956</year>
<article-title>&#x000c9;tude sur la population du quartier New-Bell &#x000e0; Douala.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>Yaound&#x000e9;, Cameroon</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Institut des Recherches Scientifiques du Cameroun</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Rouch1"><label>132</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rouch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernus</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1957</year>
<article-title>Note sur les prostitu&#x000e9;es &#x0201c;Toutou&#x0201d; de Treichville et d'Adjam&#x000e9;.</article-title>
<source>&#x000c9;tudes &#x000c9;burn&#x000e9;ennes</source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>231</fpage>
<lpage>242</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Fraenkel1"><label>133</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fraenkel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1964</year>
<article-title>Tribe and Class in Monrovia.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Oxford Univ Press</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Nahmias1"><label>134</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nahmias</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kodsi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1986</year>
<article-title>Evidence for human infection with an HTLV III/LAV-like virus in Central Africa, 1959.</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>
<volume>1(ii)</volume>
<fpage>1279</fpage>
<lpage>1280</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2872424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Apetrei1"><label>135</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Apetrei</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerche</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandrea</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gormus</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Silvestri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Kuru experiments triggered the emergence of pathogenic SIV<sub>mac</sub>.</article-title>
<source>AIDS</source>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>317</fpage>
<lpage>321</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16439864</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-Lemey3"><label>136</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Dooren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandamme</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Evolutionary dynamics of human retroviruses investigated through full-genome scanning.</article-title>
<source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
<volume>22</volume>
<fpage>942</fpage>
<lpage>951</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15635055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0009936-R1"><label>137</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>R Development Core Team</collab>
<year>2009</year>
<comment>R: A language and environment for statistical computing. Vienna: R Foundation for Statistical Computing. ISBN 3-900051-07-0. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org">http://www.R-project.org</ext-link></comment>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>