<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P3">Initially, tailored Cre recombinases were proposed to excise the integrated proviral DNA from the cellular genome through recombination at the HIV long terminal repeat (LTR)that is present at both the 5′ and 3′ proviral DNA end (
 <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1b</xref>) [
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>–
 <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The proviral DNA can also be targeted and disrupted by designer endonucleases that cleave-specific sequences in the viral DNA, such as zinc finger nucleases (ZFN), transcription activator-like effector nucleases (TALEN) and homing endonucleases [
 <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–
 <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. More recently, CRISPR–Cas9 has become a very popular endonuclease to attack HIV DNA. This tool is derived from the CRISPR–Cas system that detects and cleaves nucleic acids from invading viruses and plasmids in bacteria and archaea [
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>–
 <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The CRISPR-associated endonuclease Cas9 of 
 <italic>Streptococcus pyogenes</italic> (spCas9) was developed into a genome editing tool that cleaves double-stranded (ds) DNA in eukaryotic cells. Sequence specificity is mediated by a 20 nucleotide (nt) sequence in the guide RNA (gRNA) that directs Cas9 to a complementary DNA target (
 <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). Only complementary sequences flanked by a protospacer adjacent motif (PAM; NGG for spCas9) can be cleaved [
 <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–
 <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The dsDNA breaks resulting from Cas9 cleavage are repaired by cellular DNA repair mechanisms. These mechanisms include classical non-homologous end-joining (NHEJ), which ligates the DNA ends with frequent introduction of insertions or deletions (indels), and microhomology-mediated end-joining (MMEJ), in which short matching sequences present at the DNA ends anneal, eventually resulting in deletion of intervening nucleotides [
 <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].
</p>
