<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In principle, mathematical models can be embedded in broader frameworks for scientific investigation based on hypothesis generation and experimental falsification or validation. It is almost 50 years since Platt (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b61">1964</xref>) laid out the principles of strong inference and advocated an iterative process of formulating multiple alternative hypotheses, generating testable predictions, gathering experimental evidence and then revisiting the hypotheses in view of the evidence. Along the same lines, mechanistic models should evolve with the experimental evidence generated through the scientific process. Various textbooks, such as Hilborn &amp; Mangel's (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">1997</xref>) Ecological Detective, have greatly contributed to promoting model integration in population ecology. This iterative process has been put into practice in ecology in various contexts, notably experimental planktonic prey–predator systems, where the systematic use of mathematical models has helped ascertain and quantify the respective roles of diverse factors, including resource availability (Fussmann 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">2000</xref>) and genetic composition (Becks 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">2010</xref>), in the generation of complex trophic dynamics. Extending such approaches to natural populations poses many challenges, but there are examples of iterative implementation of observations, theory and experiments in field settings. Many of these have aimed to determine the drivers of population cycles, following a tradition set by Volterra (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b75">1926</xref>), and have encompassed a broad range of ecological factors and interactions: from the iconic Canadian lynx-hare predator–prey system (Krebs 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">2001</xref>) to the Soay sheep population of St Kilda island (Coulson 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">2001</xref>), and from the British red grouse and its parasites (Hudson 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">1998</xref>) to the California red scale (a pest of citrus trees) and its parasitoid (Murdoch 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b55">2006</xref>). However, the common thread to all these examples is that only after long time series (several years if not decades) of data had been collected did theoretical questions appear, leading ultimately to a cycle of mathematical models and experimental validation. Ecologists have generally failed to harness the power of mechanistic models for study design and data integration during early phases of field studies, which can limit the power of data analysis and inference at later stages.
</p>
