<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In particular, Egypt has experienced incursion of LPAI H9N2 viruses of the G1-like clade in late 2010 (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Monne et al., 2012</xref>). Since then, LPAIV H9N2 has established endemic status among the Egyptian poultry population, causing serious economic problems to the poultry industry. In addition, the co-circulation with other endemic highly pathogenic AIVs (HPAIVs) of subtypes H5N1 and H5N8, has also been reported in wide parts of the Egyptian poultry population (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Arafa et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Kim, 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Samy and Naguib, 2018</xref>). In 2014, a reassortant LPAIV H9N2 was reported in pigeon containing five internal gene segments (PB2, PB1, PA, NP, and NS) form Eurasian AIV subtypes (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Kandeil et al., 2017</xref>). The same genotype was found in backyard chickens in three Egyptian governorates in 2015 (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Samir et al., 2019</xref>). Recently a new genotype was described similar to the reassortant H9N2 but inherited its NP gene segment from the Egyptian 2010 H9N2 viruses (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Kandeil et al., 2019</xref>). It is also noteworthy that the continuous spread and circulation of LPAIV H9N2 in the Egyptian poultry population has been linked LPAIV H9N2 cases in humans and pigs (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization [WHO], 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Gomaa et al., 2018</xref>). In January 2015, three human cases of LPAI H9N2 following exposure to infected poultry was recorded indicating the zoonotic potential of these viruses (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization [WHO], 2016</xref>). Importantly, this ranks Egypt as the third country, after China and Bangladesh, reporting H9N2 infections in humans. The vast majority of the Egyptian H9N2 viruses encoded amino acid residues H183 and L226 (H3 numbering), the same feature as a vast majority of viruses in the G1-like lineage, which are described to correlate with a shift in affinity of the HA from the “avian” alpha 2–3 toward the “human-like” alpha 2–6 sialic acid linkage (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Matrosovich et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Naguib et al., 2017</xref>). LPAIVs H9N2 in Egypt form the majority of group B, G1 lineage along with viruses from Saudi Arabia, United Arab Emirates, Jordon, Israel, and Bangladesh (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Kayali et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Naguib et al., 2015</xref>). Phylogenetically, the Egyptian LPAIVs H9N2 have been described to be diversified further into three groups clustered within G1-B lineage based on their HA gene segment (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Kandeil et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Naguib et al., 2017</xref>). It is generally acknowledged that waterfowl migration and poultry trade play an important role in the spread of AIVs (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Peacock et al., 2019</xref>). However, the geographic diffusion of H9N2 globally and into and within Egypt is not fully understood. In particular, the probability of backward transmission of Egyptian H9N2 viruses to the rest of the world is still unclear.
</p>
