<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0595">Three mechanisms of increased viral replication have been proposed that would allow for higher viral replication in the human host, leading to higher pathogenicity through more robust infection of target cells and resultant exacerbated cytokine cascade: (1) More pathogenic DENV strains replicate more productively in human cells and thereby replicate to higher titers (
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Cologna and Rico-Hesse, 2003</xref>); (2) more pathogenic DENV strains may evade host adaptive, cross-reactive immune responses (
 <xref rid="bib181" ref-type="bibr">Kochel et al., 2002</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib231" ref-type="bibr">Mongkolsapaya et al., 2006</xref>); or (3) antibody-mediated infection may increase viral replication through infection of more target cells (
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Balsitis et al., 2010</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Boonnak et al., 2008</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib355" ref-type="bibr">Zellweger et al., 2010</xref>) or increased viral output from infected cells. Also inappropriate cross-reactive adaptive immune response during sequential DENV infection may lead to the more severe immunopathogenesis, that is, characteristic of DHF/DSS. Changes in viral proteins that interact with the host may impact viral virulence. Such interactions include the interaction of NS1 with the host complement pathway (
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Avirutnan et al., 2006</xref>), potential immune recognition of NS1 bound to endothelial cells of the vascular system (
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Avirutnan et al., 2007</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 1997</xref>), or cleavage during maturation of NS4B that appears to induce immunomediators from monocytes that increase endothelial cell permeability (
 <xref rid="bib174" ref-type="bibr">Kelley et al., 2012</xref>). Finally, differences in the breadth of diversity of circulating DENV genomes during acute infection (“intrahost diversity”) have been hypothesized to play a role in determining disease outcome (
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Descloux et al., 2009</xref>).
</p>
