<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are several limitations to this study. First, it is unknown to what degree individuals in the cohort had undiagnosed syphilis infection(s). As this is an observational cohort, information on syphilis screening cannot be obtained. However, given current screening guidelines, the authors are hopeful that syphilis has been detected in the majority of individuals in this cohort.[
 <xref rid="pone.0226614.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] If syphilis screening is not as high as current guidelines recommend, syphilis rates could be higher than the rates observed in this study. Second, only the first syphilis diagnosis per individual within the study timeframe was included in this study. Therefore, any syphilis diagnosis prior to study start, or subsequent to the individual’s initial syphilis diagnosis, was not accounted for (N = 36). Individuals with repeat syphilis infection may have a differing level of risk. Further analyses should examine repeat syphilis and/or additional STI diagnoses in this cohort. Third, the defined cohort of MSM was based on HIV transmission risk, which does not indicate current sexual risk, and also omits individuals who did not disclose sexual risk at time of HIV diagnosis. Fourth, virally suppressed was categorized as an HIV viral load &lt;200 copies/mL rather than &lt;1,500 copies/mL, which research indicates is the threshold of HIV-RNA needed to sexually transmit HIV.[
 <xref rid="pone.0226614.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0226614.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] This categorization may have resulted in fewer individuals being classified as suppressed than the less conservative measures would assume. Supplemental analyses conducted to mirror analytics presented in Tables 
 <xref rid="pone.0226614.t001" ref-type="table">1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="pone.0226614.t003" ref-type="table">3</xref> (Table A in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0226614.s001">S1 File</xref>, and Table B in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0226614.s001">S1 File</xref>) show the results did not significantly differ when increasing the viral load cutoff from &lt;200 copies/mL to &lt;1,500 copies/mL. Therefore, any bias introduced is thought to be minute. Additionally, residence was based on an individual’s last known address which may not reflect one’s current address. Based on previous research in NYS, it is known that in- and out-migration to the jurisdiction occurs frequently, and that an absence of an HIV-related laboratory test might not be reflective of being not in HIV care, but rather having moved to another jurisdiction or receiving care from an organization that is not subject to state reporting laws.[
 <xref rid="pone.0226614.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0226614.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] This limitation would most impact the group of individuals who were without HIV-related laboratory tests for the duration of the follow-up period who were classified as never in care. However, as per NYSDOH practice, individuals diagnosed with AIDS and have had no HIV-related laboratory tests reported to the NYSDOH for five years, or individuals diagnosed with HIV (stage 1 and 2) and have had no HIV-related laboratory tests reported for eight years, are not considered to be in NYS, and are therefore were not included this analysis. Lastly, syphilis staging might be incorrect when a patient’s serologic history could not be confirmed. However, this is true for all jurisdictions and therefore would not preclude comparing the results from this analysis to other previously conducted analyses in other jurisdictions.
</p>
