<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our study addresses only the clinical development period of drug development; it omits the time and resources needed to discover and bring a candidate molecule through laboratory and initial animal studies, and does not consider activities postapproval, including marketing, phase IV studies, evidence reviews and the generation of guidance to clinicians and health services.
 <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
 <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Several commentators have described models of the translation pathway providing consistent definitions for different stages of the process and allowing comparison between studies and evaluation of efforts to reduce unwarranted delays. Trochim 
 <italic>et al</italic>
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> proposed a ‘process marker’ model that recognises translational research as a continuous process that may be ‘bidirectional, variable, (and) complex’ with observable milestones along a generalised pathway allowing measurement of time elapsed between them. Recognising that the process marker model may be more appropriate to technology driven developments, Hanney 
 <italic>et al</italic>
 <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> have proposed a generalisable model for all healthcare innovation, suggesting a matrix of four different ‘tracks’ in the innovation process, building from discovery research, through human research and research review, to clinical and health service/public policy development and finally clinical practice. This recognises the overlapping nature of research translation activities, and allows for the initiation of different tracks at different times despite relevant research still occurring in ‘earlier’ tracks. Our study considers the ‘Clinical Trials System’ element of the translational research continuum described by Trochim 
 <italic>et al</italic>
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> and overlapping elements of tracks 2 and 3 in Hanney 
 <italic>et al</italic>'s
 <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> description of the innovation process. Taken together, these help identify drivers of the trends seen. In this way, the increasing demands of regulators that have led to increasing complexity of clinical trial programmes are highly relevant to the increase in clinical trial periods we have observed. This has been recognised by policymakers, who have agreed revisions to the 2001 EU Clinical Trials Directive (effective from 2004), widely seen as having a negative impact on translational research, increasing administrative burdens and waiting periods
 <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21–24</xref> and introduced a range of initiatives in the USA and Europe to provide a more rapid pathway to approval for innovative drugs that address serious conditions, urgent public health needs or specific patient groups.
 <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>
 <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
</p>
