<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We first systematize the searching behavior of aphids, focusing initially on the attractiveness of plants to aphids searching for a feeding site during feeding dispersal; see glossary of specialist terms (Box 1) and biological schematic (Fig. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A). Virus transmission (acquisition and then inoculation) is associated with alighting and probing of plant epidermal cells (Powell 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>, Krenz et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Acquisition requires probing of an infected plant, with subsequent rejection required for NPT virus, which is only very briefly retained on the vector, to be transported to a healthy plant (blue arrow, Fig. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A). Inoculation is associated with subsequent alighting and probing on a healthy plant (green arrow, Fig. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A). A Markov chain for feeding dispersals of aphids (Fig. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B) represents all possible transitions between plant probing states (i.e., probe 
 <italic>S</italic> vs. probe 
 <italic>I</italic>) ending in aphid acceptance of a probed plant (which corresponds to the settled state of phloem feeding). Within these representations of feeding dispersals VMPP of plant attractiveness have the effect of biasing alighting towards (or away) from infected plants and can be represented by the parameter ν (Fig. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A, B). Plant acceptability VMPP alters the probability of acceptance of probed infected plants and can be represented by the parameter ε (Fig. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A, B). We define a spectrum of attract–repel for plant attractiveness VMPP (ν &lt; 1 for repel; ν &gt; 1 for attract) and a spectrum of deter–retain for plant acceptability VMPP (ε &lt; 1 for deter; ε &gt; 1 for retain), see set of VMPP combinations (Table 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>).
</p>
