<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ACE2 is a transcellular protein predominantly expressed in the heart, vasculature, kidney, lung, brain, intestine, and testis and is usually located at the apical side of cells attached to basal membrane (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Fig. 1</xref>) (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). In the heart, ACE2 is widely expressed in all cardiac cell types, including endothelial cells, smooth muscle cells in the myocardial vasculature and in cardiac myocytes (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). ACE2 has 400-fold affinity to angiotensin II (ANG II), as compared with the classic ACE, and it converts ANG II to angiotensin-(1–7) [Ang-(1–7)] (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). The latter short peptide exerts vasodilatory, natriuretic/diuretic, anti-inflammatory, and antifibrotic effects via Mas receptor (MasR). Noteworthy, both clinical (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>) and experimental (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) heart failure is characterized by upregulation of cardiac ACE2 and enhanced Ang-(1–7) generation, which may represent a cardioprotective compensatory response aimed at reducing or preventing cardiac remodeling (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F0001">Fig. 1</xref>). In agreement with this notion, targeted overexpression of cardiac ACE2 by applying local injection of lenti-viral vector in Sprague-Dawley normotensive rats significantly attenuated cardiac hypertrophy and myocardial fibrosis induced by prolonged ANG II administration (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Similarly, overexpression of ACE2 in cardiac tissues of spontaneously hypertensive rats decreased cardiac remodeling in as was evident by reduced left ventricular wall thickness and perivascular fibrosis (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), probably via reduction of collagen production (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Collectively, these animal studies highlight a cardioprotective role for the ACE2–Ang-(
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>)–MasR axis.
</p>
