<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">Acute pancreatitis is a well-known complication of viral hepatitis, but the mechanism whereby it causes cell injury remains unclear
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>
 </sup>. HEV-induced necrotising pancreatitis has recently been reported, excluding other causes of acute pancreatitis, such as gallstones, alcohol, drugs, trauma, hypercalcemia, and hypertriglyceridemia
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. Unlike the case for other hepatitis viruses, such as HAV, HBV, and HCV, the presence of HEV in the pancreas is unknown
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. To date, HEV inducing necrotising pancreatitis has been genotyped in only one patient, and was identified as HEV gt1
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>. It is not known whether HEV gt1 has high tropism for the pancreas or whether it causes pancreatitis due to genetic susceptibility of the patient. The pancreas, which we focused on in our study, exhibited extensive histological changes, an abundance of HEV, and the development of necroptosis. Therefore, it may be said that this study elucidated the mechanism underlying the pancreatic injury associated with HEV infection and identified that such pancreatitis can be caused by HEV gt3 and is not limited to strains of HEV gt1. In previous studies, RIP3 expression did not match TUNEL staining, as it did in this study
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>. However, staining with propidium iodide, an indicator of cell viability based on membrane permeability, indicated strong co-localisation. Necroptosis is also termed programmed cell necrosis because it has characteristics similar to those of necrosis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, the indicator of cell death is more likely to be related to necrosis than to apoptosis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>. Necroptosis can be triggered by various stimuli, the most-studied stimulus being TNF signalling
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup>. When TNF-α binds to TNF receptor 1 (TNFR1), TNFR1-associated death domain protein binds to the intracellular domain of TNFR1. Subsequently, Fas-associated protein with death domain and caspase 8 are recruited to form the death-inducing signalling complex, which causes apoptosis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>. Inhibition of caspase activity during the course of this process alternatively activates RIP3, following which RIP3 signalling phosphorylates and oligomerises MLKL downstream, resulting in necroptosis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>. Further research is required to reveal the mechanism underlying caspase inhibition by HEV. Necroptosis is a recently discovered cell death pathway that is assuming importance as a topic in the field of inflammatory diseases, including acute pancreatitis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>. Recent studies have identified necrotising pancreatitis as a major determinant of mortality associated with HEV infection
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. This study suggests a link between necroptosis and necrotising pancreatitis caused by HEV. The presence of HEV in the pancreas sharply decreased after 21 dpi, which was in line with the pattern of faecal shedding. This suggests that pancreatic infection may be responsible for faecal shedding of HEV.
</p>
