<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">HEV is a hepatotropic virus and thus, the primary site of HEV replication is the liver. However, the path by which HEV reaches the liver remains unclear. Because inducing oral HEV infection in animal models poses difficulties, most studies focus on symptoms that develop after HEV reaches the liver
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. In some previous studies, the HEV antigen was observed in infiltrating inflammatory cells and Kupffer cells, whereas in other studies, it was observed in the cytoplasm of hepatocytes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>. In our study, HEV was continuously detected in lymphoid tissues and PBMCs, from the early stages of infection until the end of the experiment. It was rarely present in hepatocytes at 7 dpi, but multiplied in hepatocytes following liver infiltration by HEV-infected immune cells, presumably, T cells or NK cells. It was found that infected immune cells delivered HEV to hepatocytes via cell-to-cell transmission. In HEV-infected patients, NK/NKT cells showed a significant decrease in degranulation activity directly related to cytotoxicity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. Based on this finding, it was postulated that HEV is transmitted via impaired immunological synapses generated between infected T/NK/NKT cells and hepatocytes. However, further research is required to verify this. The liver showed no signs of cell death in the form of either apoptosis or necroptosis. Although the TUNEL assay detects only the late stages of apoptosis that follow extensive DNA fragmentation, and not the early stages of apoptosis, no satisfactory signals were detected in the liver throughout the experiment
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup>. Compared with that in the pancreas, RIP3 expression was stronger in the cytoplasm of hepatocytes, although it was substantially lower in the nucleus. RIP3 is a nuclear-cytoplasmic shuttling protein that is phosphorylated in the nucleus, and nuclear export of phosphorylated RIP3 to the cytoplasm induces necrosome formation, leading to necroptosis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, necroptosis of hepatocytes is not induced by insufficient nuclear–cytoplasmic export. There are several possible reasons why necroptosis does not occur in the liver. One possibility is associated with the strain and virulence of the virus. HEV gt3 used in this study may be a low-pathogenic strain as it was isolated from the faeces of pigs that did not exhibit significant clinical symptoms. In a previous study in which rabbits were inoculated with genotype 1 or 4, ALT levels increased only in rabbits inoculated with genotype 4
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>. Similarly, in chimpanzees inoculated with genotype 1, 3, or 4, only chimpanzees inoculated with genotype 4 displayed elevated ALT
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>. A second possibility relates to the dose of HEV used. Clinical and immunological progression of HEV in humans and animal models is known to be dose-dependent
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>. In this study, the amount of HEV in the liver was less than that in the pancreas and was insufficient to induce necroptosis, which may be associated with the dose–response pattern of HEV infection. This possible explanation requires verification in high-dose, long-term studies using various HEV strains.
</p>
