<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <title>Acknowledgements</title>
 <p>We acknowledge the Texas Department of State Health Services (DSHS) for providing historic arbovirus county importation data, and MUG Kraemer and A Perkins for providing Texas mosquito abundance data and technical guidance. We also thank M Johansson and M Meltzer of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) and Dr. John Hellerstedt, commissioner of the Texas DSHS, for critical conversations regarding the modeling framework and its application to Texas and national ZIKV planning efforts. We finally acknowledge the Texas Advanced Computing Center (TACC) at The University of Texas at Austin for providing High performance computing resources that have contributed to the research results reported within this paper. URL: 
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tacc.utexas.edu" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.tacc.utexas.edu</ext-link>.
 </p>
 <sec id="FPar1">
  <title>Funding</title>
  <p>LAC, SEB, LAM, and APG were supported by a National Institute of General Medical Sciences MIDAS grant to LAM and APG (U01GM087719), and APG received additional NIGMS support (U01GM105627). SJF, KL, and LAM were funded through a grant from the Defense Threat Reduction Agency to LAM (HDTRA-14-C-0114). SEB was additionally supported by the International Clinics on Infectious Disease Dynamics and Data (ICI3D) program, which is funded by a NIGMS grant (R25GM102149). NBD and XC were partially supported by a contract with the Texas Department of State Health Services (2015–047259-001). The funders did not contribute to the design, of the study, analysis, or interpretation of data.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar2">
  <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
  <p>The datasets generated and analyzed during the current study are available in the Additional files 
   <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref> and 
   <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: supplemental materials and the R package, rtZIKVrisk, which can be accessed here: 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/sjfox/rtZIKVrisk" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/sjfox/rtZIKVrisk</ext-link>. There was no individualized patient or medical data used in our study, and all ZIKV case data is publicly available.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar3">
  <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
  <p>ND, APG, LAM, LAC, SEB, and SJF developed the conceptual modeling framework and study design. LAC, SJF, and XC collected the data used in the analysis. LAC, KL, and SJF reviewed relevant literature. XC and ND developed and completed the Texas importation risk analysis. LAM, LAC, and SJF interpreted all results. LAC and SJF performed the analyses, created the figures, and wrote the first draft. All authors contributed to the presentation of the results, and the writing and approval of the final manuscript.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar4">
  <title>Competing interests</title>
  <p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar5">
  <title>Consent for publication</title>
  <p>Not applicable.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar6">
  <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
  <p>Not applicable.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar7">
  <title>Publisher’s Note</title>
  <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
 </sec>
</ack>
