<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We also detected An(g)FVs only in mosquito populations from the Lake Baringo region, despite the more than seven times greater sample size of 
 <italic>An</italic>. 
 <italic>gambiae</italic> tested from the malaria endemic Lake Victoria region. While it is curious that this ISFV was only detected in malaria mosquitoes from regions with relatively low malaria transmission rates [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>], they have been previously identified in 
 <italic>An</italic>. 
 <italic>gambiae</italic> and 
 <italic>Anopheles squamosus</italic> mosquitoes from malaria endemic North-Eastern Province [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], and Coastal and Western Provinces of Kenya (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0006949.g003">Fig 3</xref>). Other closely related Anopheles flaviviruses (AnFVs) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0006949.g003">Fig 3</xref>) have since been reported in anopheline mosquitoes from Australia [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>], Liberia and Senegal [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>], and Turkey [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0006949.g003">Fig 3</xref>). Furthermore, transcriptionally active 
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic>-derived endogenous viral elements have been identified in 
 <italic>Anopheles minimus</italic> and 
 <italic>Anopheles sinensis</italic> genomes via 
 <italic>in silico</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> analyses [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>], which suggests a historical presence of ISFVs in anopheline mosquitoes. Though ISFVs may have important implications in the transmission of medically important arboviruses [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>], the study of AnFVs has been limited by their inability to replicate in standard 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> cell line cultures, or even in cell lines of heterologous 
 <italic>Anopheles</italic> species [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Appropriate 
 <italic>Anopheles</italic> cell line cultures for the 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> replication of the AnFVs will have to be established to further study their role in co-infection with other arboviruses, and possibly malaria parasites [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].
</p>
