<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The H++ server [
 <xref rid="B47-ijms-21-03099" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] was used to protonate the SARS-CoV-2 (PDB IDs: 6lu7, and 6y2e) and SARS-CoV main proteases’ structures (PDB IDs: 2amq, and 1q2w) using standard parameters at pH 7.4. The missing 4-amino-acids-long loop of the 1q2w model was added using the corresponding loop of the 6lu7 model, and the quality of the loop refinement was confirmed by comparison with 2h2z structure of SARS-CoV (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-21-03099">Figure S8</xref>). Additionally, 4 and 3 Na
 <sup>+</sup> ions were added to the SARS-CoV-2 and the SARS-CoV, respectively. Water molecules were placed using the combination of 3D-RISM [
 <xref rid="B48-ijms-21-03099" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] and the Placevent algorithm [
 <xref rid="B49-ijms-21-03099" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The AMBER 18 LEaP [
 <xref rid="B50-ijms-21-03099" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] was used to immerse models in a truncated octahedral box with 12 Å radius of TIP3P water molecules and prepare the systems for simulation using the ff14SB force field. PMEMD CUDA package of AMBER 18 software [
 <xref rid="B50-ijms-21-03099" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] was used to run a total of 2 μs (10 replicas of 50 ns for each system) simulations of both SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV Mpros systems using apo structures and structure with co-crystalised N3 inhibitor (removed before starting the simulations) to provide more starting points for simulations. To improve conformation sampling, the starting geometry for each system was kept but the initial vectors were randomly assigned. The minimisation procedure consisted of 2000 steps, involving 1000 steepest descent steps followed by 1000 steps of conjugate gradient energy minimisation, with decreasing constraints on the protein backbone (500, 125, and 25 kcal × mol
 <sup>−1</sup> × Å
 <sup>−2</sup>) and a final minimisation with no constraints of conjugate gradient energy minimization. Next, gradual heating was performed from 0 K to 300 K over 20 ps using a Langevin thermostat with a collision frequency of 1.0 ps
 <sup>−1</sup> in periodic boundary conditions with constant volume. Equilibration stage was run using the periodic boundary conditions with constant pressure for 1 ns with 1 fs step using Langevin dynamics with a frequency collision of 1 ps
 <sup>−1</sup> to maintain temperature. Production stage was run for 50 ns with a 2 fs time step using Langevin dynamics with a collision frequency of 1 ps
 <sup>−1</sup> to maintain constant temperature. Long-range electrostatic interactions were modelled using the particle mesh Ewald method with a non-bonded cut-off of 10 Å and the SHAKE algorithm. The coordinates were saved at an interval of 1 ps. The number of added water molecules is shown in 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijms-21-03099">Table S4</xref>.
</p>
