<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="chapter-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><front><?noissn?><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Hunter's Tropical Medicine and Emerging Infectious Diseases</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Hunter's Tropical Medicine and Emerging Infectious Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7151808</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">B978-0-323-55512-8.00036-3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-323-55512-8.00036-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Viral Febrile Illnesses and Emerging Pathogens</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0010"><name><surname>Endy</surname><given-names>Timothy P.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>Edward T.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, FACP, FIDSA, FASTMH, FAAM</degrees></contrib><aff>Professor of Medicine, Professor of Immunology and Infectious Diseases, Harvard University</aff><aff>Director, Global Infectious Diseases, Division of Infectious Diseases, Massachusetts General Hospital, Boston, MA, USA</aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>David R.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, DTM &#x00026; H, FRCP, FFTM (RCPS Glasg), FASTMH</degrees></contrib><aff>Professor of Medical Sciences, Director of Global Public Health, Frank H. Netter MD School of Medicine, Quinnipiac University, Hamden, CT, USA</aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>Tom</given-names></name><degrees>BA, BM, BCh, FRCP, DCH, DTM &#x00026; H, PhD</degrees></contrib><aff>Professor of Neurological Science, Walton Centre NHS, Foundation Trust, Director, National Institute for Health Research Health, Protection Research Unit in Emerging and Zoonotic Infections, Institute of Infection and Global Health, University of Liverpool, Liverpool, UK</aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Aronson</surname><given-names>Naomi E.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><aff>Professor of Medicine, Director, Infectious Diseases Division, Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences, Bethesda, MD, USA</aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Endy</surname><given-names>Timothy P.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, MPH, FACP, FIDSA, FASTMH</degrees></contrib><aff>Professor and Chair, Microbiology and Immunology, State University of New York Upstate, Medical University, Syracuse, NY, USA</aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>350</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2020 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Elsevier Inc.</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="ab0010"><p>Emerging or emerged diseases and viral pathogens are responsible historically and currently for large epidemics, global pandemics, and significant morbidity and mortality. Our civilization will continue to face the emergence of new pathogens and viruses: viruses will continue to evolve and adapt to new environments at a high rate; our population continues to grow through birth rate, land development, and migration; climate change will continue to increase the vector burden and spread and change the migratory pattern of animals; and our societal mobility will continue to increase through rapid transportation. The clinical evaluation of the febrile patient with a potential emerging viral pathogen involves documenting the likelihood for an infection by a detailed travel history, calculation of an incubation time by exposure, and an understanding of the disease progression though the clinical illness, which drives the differential diagnosis and the type of diagnostics ordered. Ultimately, the proper identification and diagnosis of a patient with a viral febrile illness due to an emerging pathogen will elicit the appropriate precautions to protect health care providers and communities, deliver appropriate therapeutic interventions, and initiate a targeted public health response.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="objectives"><title>Key Features</title><p id="p0010">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010"><list-item id="u0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0015">The majority of emerging diseases are caused by viruses, with many that are transmitted by insect vectors or are zoonotic.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0020">RNA viruses in particular have high mutation rates and can evolve rapidly in new and changing environments. This, in combination with societal factors, climate change, and rapid travel, has increased the number of epidemics from emerging pathogens in the last several decades.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0025">Understanding the travel history, incubation time of potential viruses, and the clinical presentation by illness day is essential in making the right diagnosis and identifying the infecting virus.</p></list-item></list>
</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwd0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>virus</kwd><kwd>fever</kwd><kwd>emerging disease</kwd><kwd>clinical course</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0010"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0030">
<italic>Emerging diseases and/or pathogens</italic> is a term used frequently when describing new or spreading infections in the human population. It is a term used to describe the emergence of previously unrecognized pathogens that produce human disease or recognized pathogens expanding in different ways through the population.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Emerging diseases have historically been responsible for civilization-altering events. Bubonic plague during the 14th century was responsible for the death of 60% of the European population.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> The Spanish flu pandemic in 1918 resulted in the death of 50 to 100 million worldwide; the rinderpest epidemic in livestock in Eastern Africa during the 19th century resulted in the starvation of 75% of the Massai population; and potato blight produced the Irish potato famine, reducing the Irish population by 25%.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> Our generation has had dramatic experiences in the last decade with emerging or reemerging pathogens that rapidly spread and result in death or illness in large segments of the population, to include many of the pathogens mentioned in this section and outlined in this book, such as Ebola and Zika viruses. For the clinician, the challenge is to distinguish a viral febrile illness caused by an endemic pathogen from one that is &#x0201c;emerging&#x0201d; and has the potential for human-to-human spread, requiring isolation and, if available, targeted therapy. The scenario is common: a patient presents to the emergency room, usually on a weekend, with fever and a constellation of symptoms and a recent history of travel overseas. The fear is this Ebola, Lassa fever, or another unknown contagious pathogen, and are the clinician and the staff at risk? In this section the epidemiology, clinical features, and evaluation of the patient with a potential viral febrile illness from an emerging pathogen are discussed.</p></sec><sec id="s0015"><title>Epidemiology</title><p id="p0035">We are humbled by a 2011 editorial entitled &#x0201c;Microbiology by Numbers,&#x0201d; which estimates that &#x0201c;if all the 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>31</sup> viruses on earth were laid end to end, they would stretch for 100 million light years!&#x0201d;<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> Additionally in this editorial, it is estimated that there are approximately 1400 known species of human pathogens which includes viruses, bacteria, fungi, and parasites and represents 1% of the total number of microbial species on the earth.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> Approximately 50% of the human pathogens have an origin in the animal species.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> The potential of the remaining 99% of microbial species to adapt and transform into potential human pathogens is daunting and emphasizes the challenges we face in recognizing and predicting the next epidemic. <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 36.1</xref>
lists the reported outbreaks by year as reported by the World Health Organization.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> Conclusions that we can draw from this table are that the majority of the reported outbreaks of diseases in the world are caused by viruses, the majority of these viruses are RNA viruses, most have an animal reservoir in their life cycle, and the majority of outbreaks affect developing countries and potential &#x0201c;hot spots&#x0201d; for emerging pathogens. Jones et&#x0202f;al. analyzed 335 emerging infectious disease events between 1940 and 2004.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Emerging disease events were found to have risen significantly over time, with the peak number of events occurring in the 1980s corresponding to the HIV pandemic. Emerging disease events were predominantly zoonotic (60.3%), originated from wildlife (71.8%), and are increasing over time. Factors that determine the emergence of these viruses include (1) high mutation rate and adaptation of the RNA viruses; (2) human intimacy (cross-species transmission) and movement of animal species due to land development and migration from political conflicts; (3) increase in urbanization; (4) climate change with increase and spread of potential insect vectors and changes in migratory patterns of birds; and (5) societal mobility through air travel.<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0010"><label>TABLE 36.1</label><caption><p>Reported Disease Outbreaks by Year</p></caption><alt-text id="atte0075">TABLE 36.1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Year</th><th align="left">Outbreaks by Pathogen</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">2017</td><td align="left">Marburg virus, plague, MERS-CoV, dengue fever, influenza (H7N9), chikungunya, yellow fever, cholera, hepatitis E, meningococcus, hepatitis A, Zika virus.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2016</td><td align="left">Poliovirus, MERS-CoV, dengue fever, avian influenza (H7N9, H5N6), Rift Valley fever, monkeypox, chikungunya, enterohemorrhagic <italic>E. coli,</italic> yellow fever, Lassa fever, salmonellosis, Zika virus, Elizabethkingia, oropouche.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2015</td><td align="left">Poliovirus, MERS-CoV, cholera, avian influenza (H7N9), chikungunya, plague, Lassa fever, Zika virus, measles, meningococcus, typhoid fever, Ebola.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2014</td><td align="left">Ebola, avian influenza (H7N9, H5N6), West Nile virus, plague, Marburg, polio, MERS-CoV, chikungunya, enterovirus D68, cholera, yellow fever.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2013</td><td align="left">MERS-CoV, avian influenza (H7N9), yellow fever, polio, cholera, meningococcus, novel coronavirus.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2012</td><td align="left">Yellow fever, novel coronavirus, Ebola, Marburg, Rift Valley fever, dengue fever, cholera, hantavirus pulmonary syndrome, enterovirus 71, meningococcus.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2011</td><td align="left">Yellow fever, polio, cholera, enterohemorrhagic <italic>E. coli,</italic> Ebola, measles, avian influenza (H5N1).</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2010</td><td align="left">Avian influenza (H5N1), cholera, polio, yellow fever, plague, pandemic influenza (H1N1), Rift Valley fever.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2009</td><td align="left">Pandemic influenza (H1N1), avian influenza (H5N1), yellow fever, dengue fever, swine influenza (A/H1N1), polio, cholera, Ebola.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2008</td><td align="left">Cholera, Ebola, yellow fever, avian influenza (H5N1), Marburg, polio, enterovirus, Rift Valley fever.</td></tr></tbody></table><attrib>Source: Disease outbreaks by year: World Health Organization; [Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/csr/don/archive/year/en/" id="iw0010">http://www.who.int/csr/don/archive/year/en/</ext-link>.]</attrib></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0020"><title>Clinical Features</title><p id="p0040">Emerging viral pathogens can, in general, present in one of the following clinical categories: (1) generalized febrile illness producing a &#x0201c;viral syndrome,&#x0201d; (2) fever with meningitis/encephalitis, (3) fever with joint pain, (4) hemorrhagic fever, and (5) birth defects. Due to human host and viral diversity, many viruses can produce illness across the spectrum of these clinical categories. For example, dengue virus as a first infection can result in a sub-clinical infection or a febrile illness that results in a self-limited fever, myalgia, bone pain, and transient laboratory abnormalities. On second infection, dengue virus in a minority of patients can produce a severe hemorrhagic disease. Chikungunya and Ross River viruses can produce a generalized febrile illness but also severe joint pains that can persist for months. Japanese encephalitis, West Nile, and the equine encephalitis viruses are classic viruses that produce a meningo-encephalitis in 1% of the persons infected. Yellow fever and the filoviruses (Ebola and Marburg) are examples of severe hemorrhagic fever viruses. The recent Zika virus outbreak and birth defects associated with infection in pregnant women have broadened our clinical categories to include those that produce birth defects. All viruses produce a constellation of signs and symptoms early in infection that are clinically the same. After infection, an incubation period of normally between 1 and 14 days can occur, with some exceptions. For example, Ebola has been reported to occur 21 days after exposure.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> The first onset of symptoms heralds the host immune response with fever followed by generalized symptoms of headache, muscle aches, joint pains, nausea, vomiting, and diarrhea. Early laboratory abnormalities that would indicate a viral infection include leukopenia, anemia, and thrombocytopenia. Electrolyte and renal function abnormalities can be common if the patient is volume depleted. As the disease progresses, clinical manifestations will be become more specific for the clinical syndrome and provide clues on the potential virus, such as the onset of headache, neck stiffness, and altered sensorium in the case of encephalitis; severe joint pains; or bleeding internally or externally with blood loss or hemoconcentration, with plasma leakage with the hemorrhagic fevers. Specific manifestations such as diuresis, volume loss, and renal dysfunction can be an indicator for viruses that produce hemorrhagic fever with renal syndrome such as the Hantaviruses or Lassa fever. Rash is common to all the viral illnesses and in general indicates a shift in the host immune response from a cell-mediated to a humoral immune response with a rise in antibodies. It is important for the clinician to understand that viremia occurs several days before the onset of clinical illness and through the duration of early clinical symptoms. Pathogens that are spread by insect vectors, the respiratory route, blood-borne contact, or sexually can occur before the onset of clinical symptoms, and thus infect others who come in contact by that route. Contact tracing from the index patient should include the days of viremia before the onset of symptoms.</p></sec><sec id="s0025"><title>Patient Evaluation, Diagnosis, and Differential Diagnosis</title><p id="p0045">Understanding the incubation time of viral pathogens is the first important step in evaluating the febrile patient. A travel history in an area of an outbreak or potential hot spot for an emerging disease should be within the incubation period of these pathogens (1&#x02013;21 days). For example, a febrile patient in your clinic or emergency room who had traveled overseas 3 months before fever would be unlikely to have a viral infection, and potential other etiologies such as non-falciparum malaria or a parasitic infection should be considered. An extensive travel history and exposures while traveling will help to determine the risk for the patient to acquire a local infection. An important question often not asked is &#x0201c;who else is sick in your travel party, and have you been in contact with anyone acutely ill?&#x0201d; This can often be an important clue on the risk of acquiring an infection. If the patient is within the incubation period and at risk for a viral illness, determining the clinical illness day is important when obtaining the history. Our studies in hospitalized patients with dengue infection, for example, illustrate the importance for the clinician to approach the viral febrile illness and differential of potential viruses by determining the patient's clinical illness day and their clinical manifestation.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>
<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 36.1</xref>
demonstrates an idealized patient with a viral febrile illness. In this example, after an incubation period of 3 days, the first day of viremia occurs. Viremia will continue, with the onset of fever heralding the first day of clinical illness. In general, the first 3 to 5 days of clinical illness of most viral infections will be a generalized febrile illness with no clinical signs or symptoms that will distinguish the illness to a specific viral pathogen, denoted here as a <italic>viral syndrome.</italic> Headache, myalgia, nausea, diarrhea, and respiratory symptoms will be common during the viral syndrome stage. Influenza, dengue, chikungunya, Ebola, or Lassa fever will all be indistinguishable from each other in the early clinical illness. By day 5 of the clinical illness day, day 9 post-infection, the manifestations will become more specific and hemorrhagic manifestations and coagulopathy will occur, along with plasma leakage and encephalitis. As the host response increases with antibody levels rising and cytokines peaking, the manifestations of a specific viral illness will become apparent as cellular damage occurs.<fig id="f0010"><label>Fig. 36.1</label><caption><p>Clinical course by illness day and diagnostic methods.</p></caption><alt-text id="atte0010">Fig. 36.1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="f036-001-9780323555128"/></fig></p><p id="p0050">The diagnosis and diagnostic methods used to identify the viral pathogens are also dependent on the clinical illness day. <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 36.1</xref> demonstrates the time-dependent diagnostic test that can be performed during the clinical course of the patient. In this example, viremia will start before fever and last until 6 days of clinical illness and before the onset of viral-specific IgM and IgG antibodies. During viremia, diagnostic tests should be focused on detecting the virus, whether by viral isolation, molecular techniques, or antigen detection. Viremia starts to resolve with the onset of the host response and corresponding rise in viral-specific IgM and IgG. Antibodies will continue to rise during the convalescent period, and IgG will last several years or more. Once antibodies start to rise, the diagnostics are focused on their detection, with a variety of methods that can be used, including enzyme-linked immunoassays, hemagglutination inhibition, plaque reduction neutralization, and rapid tests.</p></sec><sec id="s0030"><title>Treatment and Control</title><p id="p0055">Treatment and control are virus specific, emphasizing the need for early recognition and ordering the appropriate diagnostics. Many of the viruses that are responsible for febrile illnesses and are considered emerging or emerged have no available treatment or vaccine. Reading through the specific viruses and chapters in this book will give the reader valuable information on potential treatments. For vector-borne or zoonotic viruses, control will be specific and include both aerial and larvicidal spraying for mosquito-borne viruses, personal protection practices for both mosquitoes and ticks, and animal control for zoonotic-borne viruses. Contact practices and/or isolation may be appropriate for viruses that can be transmitted human to human, such as the respiratory viruses, Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever, and the filoviruses Marburg and Ebola.</p></sec><sec id="sc0015"><sec-meta><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0015"><name><surname>Libraty</surname><given-names>Daniel H.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group></sec-meta><label>36.1</label><title>Dengue and Dengue Hemorrhagic Fever</title><sec id="s0035"><sec id="s0040"><title>Abstract</title><p id="p0060">Dengue is the most common and significant arboviral disease throughout the world. It is caused by infection with any one of four dengue virus serotypes (DENVs 1&#x02013;4). The clinical manifestations of a DENV infection can range from an inapparent or mild febrile illness, to the more symptomatic and well-described dengue fever, to the most severe and sometimes fatal form of illness, dengue hemorrhagic fever/dengue shock syndrome (severe dengue). The distinguishing characteristic of severe dengue is a vascular leakage syndrome that develops around the time of defervescence. The relative risk for developing severe dengue is increased in individuals with sequential heterologous DENV infections. Patients with dengue, or suspected dengue, who manifest pre-defined warning signs require close monitoring and supportive care during the critical phase of illness. The case-fatality rate for severe dengue is &#x0003c;1% with early recognition and appropriate supportive care and management.</p></sec><sec id="s0045"><title>Keywords</title><p id="p0065">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0015"><list-item id="u0025"><p id="p0070">dengue</p></list-item><list-item id="u0030"><p id="p0075">flavivirus</p></list-item><list-item id="u0035"><p id="p0080">arboviral</p></list-item><list-item id="u0040"><p id="p0085">dengue fever</p></list-item><list-item id="u0045"><p id="p0090">dengue hemorrhagic fever</p></list-item><list-item id="u0050"><p id="p0095">dengue shock syndrome</p></list-item><list-item id="u0055"><p id="p0100">severe dengue</p></list-item><list-item id="u0060"><p id="p0105">
<italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>
</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0050"><title>Key Features</title><p id="p0110">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0020"><list-item id="u0065"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0115">Dengue is the most common and significant arboviral disease throughout the world. It is caused by infection with any one of the four dengue virus serotypes (DENVs 1&#x02013;4).</p></list-item><list-item id="u0070"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0120">The clinical manifestations of a DENV infection can range from an inapparent or mild febrile illness, to the more symptomatic and well-described dengue fever (DF), to the most severe, and sometimes fatal, form of illness, dengue hemorrhagic fever (DHF) (severe dengue).</p></list-item><list-item id="u0075"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0125">The distinguishing characteristic of DHF/severe dengue is a vascular leakage syndrome that develops around the time of defervescence. The relative risk for developing DHF/severe dengue is increased with sequential heterologous DENV infections.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0080"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0130">Patients with dengue, or suspected dengue, who manifest pre-defined &#x0201c;warning signs&#x0201d; require close monitoring and supportive care during the critical phase of illness.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0085"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0135">The case-fatality rate for severe dengue is &#x0003c;1% with early recognition and appropriate supportive care and management.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="s0055"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0140">Dengue is the most prevalent and widespread human arboviral disease in the 21st century. It is caused by infection with any one of four dengue viruses (DENVs 1&#x02013;4), single-stranded RNA viruses that belong to the genus <italic>Flavivirus,</italic> family Flaviviridae. The DENVs are transmitted to humans through the bite of infected urban and peri-urban mosquitoes (female <italic>Aedes [Stegomyia] aegypti</italic> and <italic>Aedes [Stegomyia] albopictus</italic>). Outbreaks of dengue-like illnesses were recognized and recorded in the 17th and 18th centuries, and perhaps even earlier.<xref rid="bib1.1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> There has been a dramatic increase in the incidence and global spread of dengue over the past 50 years.<xref rid="bib1.2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib1.3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0060"><title>Epidemiology</title><p id="p0145">The areas at risk for dengue essentially correspond to the global distribution of <italic>A. aegypti</italic> mosquitoes (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 36.1.1</xref>
). In the Asian tropics, all four DENV serotypes co-circulate, creating a large region of hyper-endemicity. Dengue outbreaks occur with predictable seasonality and periodicity. The majority of dengue cases are seen during the rainy season in a given year. Through a complex interplay of population immunity, vector biology, and environmental conditions, a shift in the dominant circulating DENV serotype typically occurs every 4 to 6 years. The shift in the dominant circulating DENV serotype often leads to waves of large-scale epidemic dengue activity.<xref rid="bib1.4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> Historically, the Americas were characterized by isolated and interspersed dengue outbreaks of a single infecting serotype. Over the past several decades, Asian genotype DENV strains have spread throughout the Americas accompanied by increased co-circulation of multiple DENV serotypes.<xref rid="bib1.5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> As such, the dengue disease and transmission patterns in the Americas are shifting toward the Asian hyper-endemic patterns. The global burden of symptomatic dengue is on the order of 100 million cases/year.<xref rid="bib1.6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>
<fig id="f0015"><label>Fig. 36.1.1</label><caption><p>Distribution of countries or areas at risk of dengue transmission, worldwide, 2008.</p></caption><alt-text id="atte0015">Fig. 36.1.1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="f036001-001-9780323555128"/><attrib>(Redrawn with permission from WHO map. Public Health Information and Geographic Information Systems [GIS], WHO).</attrib></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0065"><title>Natural History, Pathogenesis, and Pathology</title><p id="p0150">The human dengue cycle is maintained by DENV transmission back and forth between mosquito vectors and viremic individuals. After the bite of a DENV-infected mosquito, there is local viral replication in Langerhans cells and cutaneous dendritic cells and spread to regional lymph nodes. Thereafter, the virus rapidly disseminates, leading to viremia. The likely DENV factories are tissue macrophages, dendritic cells, and adipocytes. The incubation period between a mosquito bite and symptom onset is 3 to 10 days. Viremia generally lasts for 4 to 5 days, and the disappearance of viremia correlates with fever resolution.<xref rid="bib1.5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib1.7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
</p><p id="p0155">The most severe and sometimes fatal form of dengue is dengue hemorrhagic fever/dengue shock syndrome (DHF/DSS) (severe dengue). The distinguishing characteristic of DHF/DSS is a transient and rapid increase in vascular permeability. The plasma leakage syndrome is most often characterized by hemoconcentration and transudate accumulation across serosal surfaces (i.e., pleural effusions and ascites). In its extreme form (DSS), hypovolemic shock ensues.<xref rid="bib1.8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="bib1.9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> The plasma leakage syndrome of DHF/DSS develops rapidly at the time of defervescence and clearance of viremia, and is transient (hours to days). Primary infection with a DENV serotype produces long-term protective immunity against re-infection with the homologous serotype (homotypic immunity), but only short-term protective immunity against heterologous serotypes (heterotypic immunity).<xref rid="bib1.10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib1.11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> The relative risk of developing DHF/DSS (severe dengue) is increased 15- to 100-fold with sequential heterologous DENV infections (secondary DENV infection) compared with primary DENV infections.<xref rid="bib1.3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> Most individuals with secondary DENV infections do not develop severe dengue. Primary DENV infections in infants &#x0003c;12 months old also appear more likely to lead to DHF/DSS (severe dengue) than primary DENV infections in children or adults.<xref rid="bib1.12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p0160">Numerous risk factors have been identified for the development of severe dengue. They can be divided into three general steps, and multiple risk factor combinations can take place to produce the three steps. The first step includes factors that can increase the dengue viral load. These include antibody-dependent enhancement of viral infection,<xref rid="bib1.3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> impairment of CD8+ T-cell and natural killer cell anti-viral immune responses,<xref rid="bib1.13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> adiposity,<xref rid="bib1.14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> virus genetics/serotype differences, and host genetics. The second step includes factors that can promote anti-DENV pro-inflammatory immune responses. These include cross-reactive anti-DENV T-cell responses,<xref rid="bib1.15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> anti-DENV IgG/DENV immune complexes, adiposity,<xref rid="bib1.14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> and host genetics. The final step includes factors that tip the balance in favor of permeability-inducing conditions in the serosal cavities. Several pro-inflammatory cytokines/mediators can promote endothelial paracellular permeability, and virus-induced type I interferon signaling can augment the endothelial barrier function. Each of the three steps described here is necessary, but not sufficient by itself, to produce severe dengue.</p></sec><sec id="s0070"><title>Clinical Features</title><p id="p0165">The most likely outcome of a primary or secondary DENV infection is either asymptomatic infection or a mild undifferentiated febrile illness. The mild febrile illness is often characterized by non-specific constitutional symptoms. This is particularly true in children, whereas DENV infections may be more likely to present as classic DF in adults.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p0170">Classic DF begins with the abrupt onset of fever, retro-orbital headache, backache, and severe myalgias (&#x0201c;breakbone fever&#x0201d;).<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib1.16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> The febrile illness typically lasts for 5 to 7 days and can be accompanied by anorexia, nausea/vomiting, and prolonged asthenia. There is accompanying leukopenia, thrombocytopenia, and often mild hepatic transaminase elevation. Petechiae may develop spontaneously, but, most commonly, can be elicited in a positive tourniquet test.<xref rid="bib1.17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> Clinically significant bleeding is much less common, but can occasionally be severe or life threatening. Toward the end of the febrile period, the classic rash of dengue may appear (Herman's rash). It is a confluent, erythematous, macular rash over the extremities with scattered, well-circumscribed areas of sparing. The appearance of this rash is pathognomonic for a DENV infection.</p><p id="p0175">DHF/DSS is the dengue clinical syndrome whose distinguishing feature is abrupt plasma leakage from the intravascular to the extravascular space. The World Health Organization (WHO) case definition for DHF/DSS incorporates three additional clinical criteria beyond DF and has established a grading scale of I to IV for DHF severity (<xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 36.1.1</xref>
).<xref rid="bib1.16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> Despite the moniker &#x0201c;hemorrhagic fever,&#x0201d; most often the hemorrhagic manifestations may only be a positive tourniquet test or spontaneous skin or mucosal petechiae. Severe coagulopathy is nearly always seen in the context of profound shock and multi-organ failure. Recent WHO guidelines have moved away from the DHF case definition and, instead, proposed a new case definition termed <italic>severe dengue</italic> (see <xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 36.1.1</xref>).<xref rid="bib1.18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> Whether defined as DHF/DSS or severe dengue, the majority of serious morbidity and mortality caused by DENV infections is due to a vascular leakage syndrome with hypotension and shock. Clinically significant hemorrhage can sometimes occur in the absence of vascular leakage, particularly in adults. Other uncommon complications of DENV infections include hepatic necrosis, encephalopathy/encephalitis, and chorioretinitis. Unlike Zika virus infection, DENV infection during pregnancy has not been associated with congenital malformations.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0015"><label>TABLE 36.1.1</label><caption><p>Case Definitions for Dengue Hemorrhagic Fever/Dengue Shock Syndrome, Severe Dengue, and the Warning Signs for Severe Dengue</p></caption><alt-text id="atte0080">TABLE 36.1.1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Case Definition for Dengue Hemorrhagic Fever (DHF) and DHF Severity Classification</th><th align="left">Case Definition for Severe Dengue</th><th align="left">Warning Signs for Severe Dengue</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Signs/symptoms of dengue fever and:<break/><list list-type="simple" id="olist0025"><list-item id="o0090"><label>1.</label><p id="p0180">thrombocytopenia (platelet count &#x0003c;100,000/mm<sup>3</sup>), and</p></list-item><list-item id="o0095"><label>2.</label><p id="p0185">evidence of plasma leakage (hematocrit rise &#x02265;20% from baseline, pleural effusion, or ascites), and</p></list-item><list-item id="o0100"><label>3.</label><p id="p0190">hemorrhagic manifestation<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0030"><list-item id="u0105"><p id="p0195">DHF grade I = criteria 1 + 2 + positive tourniquet test</p></list-item><list-item id="u0110"><p id="p0200">DHF grade II = criteria 1 + 2 + spontaneous bleeding</p></list-item><list-item id="u0115"><p id="p0205">DHF grade III = DHF grade I/II criteria + circulatory failure (hypotension, weak pulse)</p></list-item><list-item id="u0120"><p id="p0210">DHF grade IV = DHF grade I/II criteria + profound shock</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item></list></td><td align="left">Probable or laboratory-confirmed dengue and:<break/><list list-type="simple" id="olist0035"><list-item id="o0125"><label>1.</label><p id="p0215">severe plasma leakage (shock or fluid accumulation with respiratory distress), or</p></list-item><list-item id="o0130"><label>2.</label><p id="p0220">severe hemorrhage (as evaluated by clinician), or</p></list-item><list-item id="o0135"><label>3.</label><p id="p0225">severe organ impairment:<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0040"><list-item id="u0140"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0230">liver: AST or ALT &#x02265;1000&#x0202f;U/mL</p></list-item><list-item id="u0145"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0235">central nervous system: impaired consciousness</p></list-item><list-item id="u0150"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0240">heart and other organs</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item></list></td><td align="left"><list list-type="simple" id="ulist0045"><list-item id="u0155"><p id="p0245">Abdominal pain or tenderness</p></list-item><list-item id="u0160"><p id="p0250">Persistent vomiting</p></list-item><list-item id="u0165"><p id="p0255">Clinical fluid accumulation</p></list-item><list-item id="u0170"><p id="p0260">Mucosal bleed</p></list-item><list-item id="u0175"><p id="p0265">Lethargy, restlessness</p></list-item><list-item id="u0180"><p id="p0270">Liver enlargement &#x0003e;2&#x0202f;cm</p></list-item><list-item id="u0185"><p id="p0275">Increase in hematocrit concurrent with rapid decrease in platelet count</p></list-item></list></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic>ALT,</italic> Alanine aminotransferase; <italic>AST,</italic> aspartate transaminase.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0075"><title>Patient Evaluation, Diagnosis, and Differential Diagnosis</title><p id="p0280">Dengue should be considered in all individuals in endemic regions, particularly children, who present with an abrupt-onset febrile illness of &#x0003c;10 to 14 days&#x02019; duration during the DENV transmission season. The initial clinical findings in DENV infections are fairly non-specific and can be difficult to distinguish from other common febrile illnesses in the tropics. The differential diagnosis for dengue-like illnesses includes typhoid fever, leptospirosis, rickettsial infections, or malaria. In the appropriate clinical setting, measles, influenza, chikungunya, or Zika virus infections are also possibilities. Early in the febrile course, the suspicion for a DENV infection can be heightened by the presence of leukopenia, thrombocytopenia, mild aspartate aminotransferase elevation, and a positive tourniquet test or spontaneous petechiae. The positive predictive value for combinations of these early clinical findings has generally been good when dengue is highly prevalent (i.e., during the rainy season).<xref rid="bib1.17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib1.19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
</p><p id="p0285">The critical phase of any DENV infection is the 24 to 48 hours surrounding defervescence&#x02014;generally around days 5 to 7 of the febrile illness in a secondary DENV infection. This is the time period when plasma leakage will take place in patients developing DHF/DSS. A challenge in patients with dengue, or suspected dengue, is to identify those at risk for severe disease before the critical phase is reached. A group of warning signs and symptoms have been identified in DENV-infected patients that often presage the deterioration to DHF/DSS (severe dengue) (see <xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 36.1.1</xref>).<xref rid="bib1.18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> These patients require close monitoring and supportive care during the critical phase of illness.</p><p id="p0290">Laboratory diagnosis remains the most reliable way to identify a DENV infection. Reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) can detect viral RNA in the blood for up to 5 to 7 days after the onset of fever in primary infections and 3 to 4 days in secondary infections. However, DENV RT-PCR is not routinely available in most clinical settings. Viremia can also be detected by antigen-detection assays that measure circulating levels of a DENV non-structural protein, NS1. The timeline for detectable circulating soluble NS1 lags viral RNA RT-PCR detection by 1 to 2 days. The most widely used serologic assay for dengue is IgM/IgG enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA). A single positive dengue IgM or high-titer IgG can only provide a presumptive diagnosis of dengue. Definitive serologic diagnosis requires paired acute and convalescent sera. Anti-DENV IgM antibody levels do not generally become positive until the fifth or sixth day of illness and can be affected by other flavivirus infections (e.g., Japanese encephalitis virus, Zika virus). Therefore the diagnostic sensitivity and specificity of anti-DENV IgM ELISA assays often depend on the timing of the blood sample, co-circulating flaviviruses in the region, and the manufacturer.</p></sec><sec id="s0080"><title>Treatment</title><p id="p0295">No specific anti-viral therapies are available for dengue. The vast majority of uncomplicated dengue can be managed on an outpatient basis with rest, oral rehydration solution, and analgesia/antipyretics. The use of aspirin or non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) should be avoided, as they can exacerbate platelet dysfunction and mucosal bleeding. Patients and the parents of affected children should be notified of the warning signs and symptoms that should prompt an immediate return to medical attention.</p><p id="p0300">In-hospital management should be arranged for patients with the pre-defined warning signs, early evidence of plasma leakage (including narrow pulse pressure), bleeding or severe hematologic abnormalities, co-morbid conditions, or those with unreliable access to outpatient follow-up care. For hospitalized patients without frank hypotension or shock, the key aspect of supportive therapy is judicious intravascular volume replacement as the critical phase is entered. This is accomplished by the careful administration of intravenous isotonic crystalloid solutions (e.g., 0.9% saline, Ringer's lactate, Hartmann's solution) with frequent re-assessment of intravascular volume status and urine output. The overly aggressive use of intravenous fluids or the failure to adequately monitor therapy can lead to serious complications of fluid overload during the critical phase of illness. Treatment guidelines are shown in <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 36.1.2</xref>
.<fig id="f0020"><label>Fig. 36.1.2</label><caption><p>Treatment guidelines for dengue and dengue hemorrhagic fever.</p></caption><alt-text id="atte0020">Fig. 36.1.2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="f036001-002a-9780323555128"/><graphic xlink:href="f036001-002b-9780323555128"/></fig></p><p id="p0305">Prophylactic platelet transfusions have not proven to be useful in dengue and should be avoided. Platelet transfusions can be considered in patients with thrombocytopenia and clinically significant hemorrhage. Intramuscular injections, multiple large-bore intravenous lines, and diagnostic or prophylactic placement of nasogastric tubes should be avoided, except as needed in the most severe cases. If possible, complicated or unusual severe dengue cases should be transferred to experienced referral centers in the area. The case-fatality rate for severe dengue is &#x0003c;1% with early recognition and appropriate supportive care and management.</p></sec><sec id="s0085"><title>Prevention</title><p id="p0310">Dengue prevention can be approached by strategies to minimize human&#x02013;vector contact and control mosquito-vector populations. Functioning screens and insecticide-treated bed nets for daytime sleeping (e.g., in infants) can reduce mosquito-vector contact indoors. Personal measures that afford some protection against the daytime biting habits of female <italic>A. aegypti</italic> include wearing clothing that minimizes skin exposure and appropriate use of repellants on exposed skin or clothing. Effective repellants should contain N,N-diethyl-3-methylbenzamide (DEET), 3-(N-acetyl-N-butyl)-aminopropionic acid ethyl ester (IR3535), or 1-piperidinecarboxylic acid, 2-(2-hydroxyethyl)-1-methylpropylester (icaridin).<xref rid="bib1.18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> At the public health level, a sustained and integrated vector-control strategy is generally needed to consistently reduce <italic>A. aegypti</italic> population densities. <italic>A. aegypti</italic> mosquitoes proliferate in many peri-domestic water-containing habitats. These include purposely filled man-made containers (e.g., water storage barrels, flowerpots/vases), rain-filled objects (e.g., used tires), and natural habitats (e.g., tree holes).</p><p id="p0315">Dengue vaccine development has moved forward with encouraging advances. Given the potential for increased disease severity upon sequential infection with heterologous DENV serotypes, a general consensus has been that effective vaccination strategies will require simultaneous immunization to the four DENV serotypes (tetravalent vaccines). A chimeric live-attenuated viral vaccine, where the DENVs 1 to 4 envelope proteins have been engineered onto a yellow fever (YF)&#x02013;17D vaccine backbone, is licensed in several countries. However, if this vaccine is administered to truly dengue-na&#x000ef;ve individuals, it appears to be able to enhance the subsequent disease severity with a natural DENV infection. Another tetravalent live-attenuated dengue vaccine (attenuated by a deletion in the DENV2 3&#x02019; untranslated region [UTR]) is in phase III clinical trials. Other dengue vaccine products that are in pre-clinical or early clinical phases include an adjuvanted recombinant envelope protein vaccine, an adjuvanted inactivated virus vaccine, and a plasmid DNA vaccine. The combination of effective dengue vaccination with vector-control strategies will open up the possibility of severely halting, or even eradicating, DENV transmission in many endemic regions.</p></sec><ref-list id="bb0015"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1.1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vasilakis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The history and evolution of human dengue emergence</article-title><source>Adv Virus Res</source><volume>72</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19081488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib1.2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kyle</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global spread and persistence of dengue</article-title><source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source><volume>62</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18429680</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib1.3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halstead</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dengue</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>370</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>1644</fpage><lpage>1652</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17993365</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib1.4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Irizarry</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Travelling waves in the occurrence of dengue haemorrhagic fever in Thailand</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>427</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>37</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib1.5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rigau-Perez</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gubler</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dengue and dengue haemorrhagic fever</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>352</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>971</fpage><lpage>977</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9752834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib1.6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhatt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gething</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The global distribution and burden of dengue</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>496</volume><issue>7446</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>504</fpage><lpage>507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23563266</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib1.7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halstead</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathogenesis of dengue: challenges to molecular biology</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>239</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>476</fpage><lpage>481</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib1.8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sr0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nimmannitya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Dengue hemorrhagic fever: diagnosis and management</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Gubler</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuno</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><source>Dengue and dengue hemorrhagic fever</source><year>1997</year><publisher-name>CAB International</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib1.9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wills</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Oragui</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dung</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Size and charge characteristics of the protein leak in dengue shock syndrome</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><volume>190</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>810</fpage><lpage>818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15272410</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib1.10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sabin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Research on dengue during World War II</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source><volume>1</volume><year>1952</year><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14903434</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib1.11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halstead</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathogenesis of dengue: challenges to molecular biology</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>239</volume><year>1988</year><fpage>476</fpage><lpage>481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3277268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib1.12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halstead</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Myint</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dengue hemorrhagic fever in infants: research opportunities ignored</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><volume>8</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>1474</fpage><lpage>1479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12498666</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib1.13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beltran</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez-Verges</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NK cells during dengue disease and their recognition of dengue virus-infected cells</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><volume>5</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>192</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24829565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib1.14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Libraty</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pattern of adipose tissue accumulation during early infancy provides an environment for the development of dengue hemorrhagic fever</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><volume>9</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>e0004267</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26636570</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib1.15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rothman</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dengue: defining protective versus pathologic immunity</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><volume>113</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>946</fpage><lpage>951</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15057297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib1.16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sr0135"><source>Dengue haemorrhagic fever: diagnosis, treatment, prevention and control</source><edition>2nd ed</edition><year>1997</year><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib1.17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalayanarooj</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Nimmannitya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early clinical and laboratory indicators of acute dengue illness</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><volume>176</volume><year>1997</year><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9237695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib1.18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sr0145"><source>World Health Organization. Dengue: guidelines for diagnosis, treatment, prevention and control&#x02014;new edition</source><year>2009</year><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib1.19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Potts</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothman</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical and laboratory features that distinguish dengue from other febrile illnesses in endemic populations</article-title><source>Trop Med Int Health</source><volume>13</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>1328</fpage><lpage>1340</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18803612</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></sec><sec id="sc0020"><sec-meta><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0020"><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>Ann M.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group></sec-meta><label>36.2</label><title>Chikungunya Fever</title><sec id="s0090"><sec id="s0095"><title>Abstract</title><p id="p0320">Chikungunya fever is a re-emerging arboviral disease characterized by the abrupt onset of fever with severe arthralgia followed by constitutional symptoms and rash lasting for approximately 1 week. The disease is nearly always self-limited, but some patients may have joint pain that persists for weeks or months. There is no specific treatment, and supportive care is indicated during the acute symptoms. It is transmitted by the bite of infected <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and <italic>A. albopictus</italic> mosquitoes. There is no commercially available vaccine; therefore preventive efforts focus on the avoidance of mosquito bites and mosquito vector control.</p></sec><sec id="s0100"><title>Keywords</title><p id="p0325">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0050"><list-item id="u0190"><p id="p0330">chikungunya</p></list-item><list-item id="u0195"><p id="p0335">alphavirus</p></list-item><list-item id="u0200"><p id="p0340">arthralgia</p></list-item><list-item id="u0205"><p id="p0345">joint pain</p></list-item><list-item id="u0210"><p id="p0350">rash</p></list-item><list-item id="u0215"><p id="p0355">
<italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0220"><p id="p0360">
<italic>Aedes albopictus</italic>
</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0105"><title>Key Features</title><p id="p0365">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0055"><list-item id="u0225"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0370">Chikungunya fever is a significant arboviral disease with nearly global distribution. Infection is characterized by the abrupt onset of high fever with severe arthralgia and rash.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0230"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0375">The disease is nearly always self-limiting and rarely fatal but may result in long-term arthralgia affecting quality of life.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0235"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0380">There is no specific treatment, and supportive care consists of treatment for the fever and pain. No vaccine yet exists, but both vaccines and therapeutic options are under development.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0240"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0385">The virus is transmitted in urban settings by infected <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and <italic>A. albopictus</italic> mosquitoes. Endemic maintenance of the virus is by forest-dwelling <italic>Aedes</italic> species mosquitoes.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="s0110"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0390">Chikungunya (CHIK) fever is an arboviral disease that is characterized by the rapid onset of high fever, rash, and severe joint pain (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 36.2.1</xref>
). Its name is derived from the Makonde word meaning &#x0201c;that which bends up&#x0201d; in reference to the stooped posture that develops as a result of the arthritic symptoms of the disease. The disease is nearly always self-limiting.<xref rid="bib2.1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> The causative agent, chikungunya virus (CHIKV), is a single-stranded, positive-sense RNA virus belonging to the family Togaviridae<italic>,</italic> genus <italic>Alphavirus.</italic> Molecular characterization has demonstrated three distinct genotypes (West African, Central/East African, and Asian) that historically were geographically limited to Africa and Asia.<xref rid="bib2.2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Recent spread has made the pathogen a nearly global concern (<xref rid="f0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 36.2.2</xref>
). A zoonotic cycle is known to exist in Africa involving a range of vertebrate hosts, including non-human primates, and forest-dwelling <italic>Aedes (Stegomyia)</italic> mosquitoes. The virus is transmitted to humans primarily by <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and <italic>A. albopictus</italic> mosquitoes.<fig id="f0025"><label>Fig. 36.2.1</label><caption><p>(A) Inability to stand or walk without support due to involvement of joints in a chikungunya case (stooped posture). Maculopapular rash on lower extremities (B) and upper extremities (C) in cases of chikungunya fever.</p></caption><alt-text id="atte0025">Fig. 36.2.1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="f036002-001a-9780323555128"/><graphic xlink:href="f036002-001b-9780323555128"/><graphic xlink:href="f036002-001c-9780323555128"/></fig><fig id="f0030"><label>Fig. 36.2.2</label><caption><p>Global distribution of autochthonous CHIKV (as of 2016).</p></caption><alt-text id="atte0030">Fig. 36.2.2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="f036002-002-9780323555128"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0115"><title>Epidemiology</title><p id="p0395">The first recorded epidemic occurred in Tanzania in 1952&#x02013;1953. In Asia, CHIKV was first detected in Bangkok, Thailand, in 1958. In India, well-documented outbreaks occurred in 1963 and 1964 in Calcutta and southern India, respectively. Thereafter, a small outbreak of CHIK was reported from the Sholapur district, Maharashtra, in 1973.<xref rid="bib2.3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> Cases of CHIK continued to be reported in Africa and Southeast Asia, although no additional major outbreaks were reported for nearly three decades. The virus emerged in East Africa (Kenya) and the islands of the Indian Ocean, including Comoros, La Reunion, Mayotte, Mauritius, and Seychelles, beginning in 2004.<xref rid="bib2.4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib2.5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib2.6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> CHIKV then re-emerged in India in December 2005. The 2005&#x02013;2006 outbreak in India involved approximately 1.35 million suspected cases in 12 states. The attack rate reached up to 45% due to the lack of herd immunity, a large susceptible population, and the ability of certain strains containing an alanine to valine mutation in the E1 gene to more efficiently infect the secondary vector, <italic>A. albopictus</italic>.<xref rid="bib2.3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p0400">Imported cases of CHIKV infection were reported from Europe and North and South America in returning travelers from areas with high incidence rates.<xref rid="bib2.7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> In 2013 the virus emerged in the Caribbean island of St. Martin and quickly spread throughout the Caribbean and Latin America. In the first year alone in the Americas, an estimated &#x0003e;1 million cases occurred in over 40 countries (<xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 36.2.3</xref>
). Although massive outbreaks have subsided, the virus continues to circulate on a nearly global scale.<fig id="f0035"><label>Fig. 36.2.3</label><caption><p>Number of countries in the Americas with local chikungunya transmission and number of cases, 2014&#x02013;2015.</p></caption><alt-text id="atte0035">Fig. 36.2.3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="f036002-003-9780323555128"/><attrib>(From Petersen LR, Powers AM. Chikungunya: epidemiology. F1000Research 2016;5:82.)</attrib></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0120"><title>Pathogenesis</title><p id="p0405">After the bite of an infected mosquito, the virus replicates in fibroblasts and epithelial cells leading to a viremia that can reach up to 8 log<sub>10</sub>/mL. The skin, joints, and muscles are the primary affected organs, whereas the nervous system, heart, and liver are less frequently involved. Macrophage appear to be susceptible to infection during the viremic phase. Mouse models have shown that type 1 interferon response appears to be associated with control of infection.<xref rid="bib2.8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0125"><title>Clinical Features</title><p id="p0410">CHIK is an acute infection of abrupt onset, heralded by high fever and severe arthralgia, followed by other constitutional symptoms and rash (typically maculopapular) lasting for a period of 1 to 7 days. The incubation period is usually 3 to 7 days, with a range of 2 to 12 days. Fever rises abruptly, often reaching 39&#x000b0;C to 40&#x000b0;C. This acute phase lasts a few days to 2 weeks.<xref rid="bib2.9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> In some cases, the temperature may remit for 1 to 2 days after a gap of 4 to 10 days, resulting in a &#x0201c;saddle back&#x0201d; fever curve that is characteristic of arthropod-borne virus infections.</p><p id="p0415">The arthralgias are polyarticular, symmetric, and predominantly affect the small joints of the hands, wrists, ankles, and feet (see <xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 36.2.1</xref>) with lesser involvement of larger joints. During the acute phase, joint pain can be incapacitating. Patients with milder articular manifestations are usually symptom free within a few weeks, but more severe cases require months or years to resolve entirely.<xref rid="bib2.10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> One study indicated that one third of patients had chronic joint symptoms that persisted for at least 9 months.<xref rid="bib2.11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> Cutaneous manifestations are typical with many patients. This is usually a maculopapular rash, but bullous lesions can occur in infants. The trunk and limbs are most commonly involved, but the face, palms, and soles may also show lesions. During the acute phase, some patients will have headache, but it is not usually severe, and retro-orbital pain, commonly found in dengue infections, rarely occurs. Conjunctival redness is present in some cases. Pregnant women can pass the virus to their infant, most commonly during the intrapartum phase. The Reunion South Hospital Group observed 84 pregnant women who had laboratory-confirmed CHIK infection. In 88% of these women (all involving infections relatively distant from delivery), the newborns appeared asymptomatic. Conversely, 10 newborns developed disease soon after birth (4 with meningoencephalitis and 3 with intravascular coagulation) and required intensive care support.<xref rid="bib2.12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> Severe cases of CHIK, including neurologic complications, myocarditis, or nephritis, can occur, most commonly in the elderly, newborns, and immunocompromised individuals.<xref rid="bib2.13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="bib2.14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> CHIK outbreaks typically result in several hundred or thousands of cases, but deaths are rarely encountered.</p></sec><sec id="s0130"><title>Diagnosis</title><p id="p0420">Symptoms of CHIKV infection can be clinically indistinguishable from dengue fever. Other causes in the differential diagnosis of CHIK include malaria, O'nyong nyong, Sindbis, Ross River, West Nile, and Zika virus infections.<xref rid="bib2.9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib2.15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib2.16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
</p><p id="p0425">The clinical laboratory findings in CHIK are not remarkable. A few patients may present with leukopenia with relative lymphocytosis; however, most patients will have normal blood counts. The platelet count may be moderately depressed. The erythrocyte sedimentation rate and C-reactive protein levels are typically elevated in acute cases.<xref rid="bib2.15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> A definitive diagnosis can only be made by laboratory testing, but CHIK should be suspected when epidemic disease occurs with the characteristic triad of fever, rash, and arthralgia.</p><p id="p0430">Virus-specific IgM antibodies typically can be detected by 5 to 7 days of illness using enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA). Because viremia is so high and persists for several days post-illness onset, blood samples for virus isolation and reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) should be collected within the first 5 days of illness when viremia is detectable. Frequently, diagnosis can be definitively confirmed by virus isolation or molecular techniques such as RT-PCR, for which a wide range of tests now exist.<xref rid="bib2.17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0135"><title>Treatment</title><p id="p0435">There is no specific treatment for CHIK. The illness is usually self-limiting and resolves with time. Supportive care with rest is indicated during the acute joint symptoms. Movement and mild exercise may decrease stiffness and arthralgia, but heavy exercise may exacerbate rheumatic symptoms. Aspirin and other non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) are recommended for chronic pain. A number of therapeutic options are in development, as are several vaccine candidates.<xref rid="bib2.18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p0440">Because no vaccine or specific medication is yet available against CHIKV infection, vector control is very important in controlling or preventing transmission. Elimination of breeding sites or source reduction is an important control approach. <italic>A. aegypti</italic> is typically a container-habitat species (<xref rid="f0040" ref-type="fig">Fig. 36.2.4</xref>
) and breeds primarily in artificial containers and receptacles. Therefore all water tanks, cisterns, barrels, trash containers, etc., need to be covered tightly with a lid. Old tires, tin cans, buckets, drums, bottles, etc., should be removed, as mosquitoes may breed in these containers if they accumulate water. In ornamental garden water tanks, larvivorous fish (e.g<italic>.</italic>, gambusia, guppy) can be introduced. In case water containers cannot be emptied on a daily or weekly basis, larvicidal treatments can be applied.<xref rid="bib2.19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref>
<fig id="f0040"><label>Fig. 36.2.4</label><caption><p><italic>Aedes</italic> larvae in water-storing containers.</p></caption><alt-text id="atte0040">Fig. 36.2.4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="f036002-004-9780323555128"/></fig></p><p id="p0445">Both primary vectors, <italic>A. aegypti</italic> and <italic>A. albopictus,</italic> are principally daytime biters. Insect repellant containing <italic>N,N</italic>-diethyl-m-toluamide (DEET) or another registered active ingredient should be applied on exposed skin (<xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 36.2.1</xref>
). People should be advised to wear long sleeves and pants and have secure screens on windows and doors to keep mosquitoes out. Insecticide-treated bed net use during daytime resting can help prevent mosquito bites. Infected persons should be protected from further mosquito exposure (staying indoors and/or under a mosquito net during the first few days of illness) so that they cannot contribute to the transmission cycle.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0020"><label>TABLE 36.2.1</label><caption><p>Environmental Protection Agency&#x02013;Registered Insect Repellents</p></caption><alt-text id="atte0085">TABLE 36.2.1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Active Ingredient</th><th align="left">Other Names</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">DEET</td><td align="left"><italic>N,N</italic>-diethyl-m-toluamide</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Picaridin</td><td align="left">Known as KBR 3023 and icaridin outside the US</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">IR3535</td><td align="left">3-[N-butyl-N-acetyl]-aminopropionic acid</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Oil of lemon eucalyptus (OLE)</td><td align="left">Para-menthane-diol (PMD), p-menthane-3,8-diol</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">2-undecanone</td><td align="left">Methyl nonyl ketone</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Higher percentages of active ingredient provide longer protection. The EPA's search tool is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.epa.gov/insect-repellents/find-insect-repellent-right-you" id="iw0020">www.epa.gov/insect-repellents/find-insect-repellent-right-you</ext-link>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><ref-list id="bb0020"><title>References</title><ref id="bib2.1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chikungunya: epidemiology</article-title><source>F1000Res</source><volume>5</volume><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2.2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0160"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brault</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tesh</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Re-emergence of chikungunya and O'nyong-nyong viruses: evidence for distinct geographical lineages and distant evolutionary relationships</article-title><source>J Gen Virol</source><volume>81</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10644846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2.3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chhabra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mittal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chikungunya fever: a re-emerging viral infection</article-title><source>Indian J Med Microbiol</source><volume>26</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18227590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2.4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0170"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sergon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Njuguna</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seroprevalence of chikungunya virus (CHIKV) infection on Lamu Island, Kenya, October 2004</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source><volume>78</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18256441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2.5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0175"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sergon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yahaya</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seroprevalence of chikungunya virus infection on Grande Comore Island, Union of the Comoros, 2005</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source><volume>76</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>1189</fpage><lpage>1193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17556634</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2.6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0180"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pialoux</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gauzere</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaureguiberry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Strobel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chikungunya, an epidemic arbovirosis</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><volume>7</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17448935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2.7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0185"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Staples</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Notes from the field: chikungunya virus spreads in the Americas - Caribbean and South America, 2013-2014</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><volume>63</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>500</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24898168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2.8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0190"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burt</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Miner</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chikungunya virus: an update on the biology and pathogenesis of this emerging pathogen</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><volume>17</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>e107</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28159534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2.9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0195"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Staples</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Breiman</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chikungunya fever: an epidemiological review of a re-emerging infectious disease</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><volume>49</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>942</fpage><lpage>948</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19663604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2.10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0200"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Aalst</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelen</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Goorhuis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term sequelae of chikungunya virus disease: a systematic review</article-title><source>Travel Med Infect Dis</source><volume>15</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28163198</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2.11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0205"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeana</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Heredia</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-chikungunya rheumatic disorders in travelers after return from the Caribbean</article-title><source>Travel Med Infect Dis</source><volume>14</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26872414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2.12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0210"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robillard</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Boumahni</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerardin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vertical maternal fetal transmission of the chikungunya virus. Ten cases among 84 pregnant women</article-title><source>Presse Med</source><volume>35</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>785</fpage><lpage>788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16710146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2.13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0215"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vu</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jungkind</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelle</surname><given-names>Desiree L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chikungunya virus</article-title><source>Clin Lab Med</source><volume>37</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28457355</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2.14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0220"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brizzi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurologic manifestation of chikungunya virus</article-title><source>Curr Infect Dis Rep</source><volume>19</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>6</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28233188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2.15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sr0225"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>PAHO</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Preparedness and response for chikungunya virus: introduction in the Americas</chapter-title><year>2011</year><publisher-name>Pan American Health Organization (PAHO)</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://new.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_content&#x00026;view=article&#x00026;id=6464%3Apaho%2C-cdc-publish-guide-on-preparing-for-chikungunya-virus-introduction-in-the-Americas&#x00026;catid=740%3Anews-press-%20releases&#x00026;Itemid=1926&#x00026;lang=en" id="iw0025">http://new.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_content&#x00026;view=article&#x00026;id=6464%3Apaho%2C-cdc-publish-guide-on-preparing-for-chikungunya-virus-introduction-in-the-Americas&#x00026;catid=740%3Anews-press- releases&#x00026;Itemid=1926&#x00026;lang=en</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2.16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0230"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chikungunya</article-title><source>Clin Lab Med</source><volume>30</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20513548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2.17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0235"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sam</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kummerer</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Updates on chikungunya epidemiology, clinical disease, and diagnostics</article-title><source>Vector Borne Zoonotic Dis</source><volume>15</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25897809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2.18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0240"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vaccine and therapeutic options to control chikungunya virus</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>e00104</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><comment>pii:</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29237708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2.19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0245"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diallo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dia</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Diallo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perspectives and challenges in entomological risk assessment and vector control of chikungunya</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><volume>214</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>S459</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27920174</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></sec><sec id="sc0025"><sec-meta><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0025"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Lin H.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0030"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Mary E.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group></sec-meta><label>36.3</label><title>Zika</title><sec id="s0140"><sec id="s0145"><title>Abstract</title><p id="p0450">Zika virus is a Flavivirus identified in 1947 transmitted by <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitoes. It remained obscure until Zika outbreaks erupted in Yap in 2007, French Polynesia in 2013 to 2014, Brazil since 2013, and the Americas thereafter. Outbreaks have occurred in Asia and Africa, and importations by travelers are well documented. Zika virus infection causes typically mild symptoms (or is asymptomatic), such as rash, fever, conjunctivitis, and myalgias, but has been associated with Guillain&#x02013;Barr&#x000e9; syndrome and other complications. Infection during pregnancy can lead to severe microcephaly and other birth defects. The symptoms of Zika resemble those of dengue and chikungunya virus infections, and Zika testing has limitations in terms of availability, sensitivity, and specificity. Sexual transmission is of concern, with potentially prolonged viral shedding in semen. Transfusion-related transmission has also occurred. Prevention of Zika virus infection rests on avoidance of vector mosquitoes and sexual contact with infected persons, especially important during pregnancy to reduce the occurrence of congenital infection.</p></sec><sec id="s0150"><title>Keywords</title><p id="p0455">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0060"><list-item id="u0245"><p id="p0460">Zika</p></list-item><list-item id="u0250"><p id="p0465">congenital Zika syndrome</p></list-item><list-item id="u0255"><p id="p0470">microcephaly</p></list-item><list-item id="u0260"><p id="p0475">flavivirus</p></list-item><list-item id="u0265"><p id="p0480">arbovirus</p></list-item><list-item id="u0270"><p id="p0485">Guillain&#x02013;Barr&#x000e9; syndrome</p></list-item><list-item id="u0275"><p id="p0490">travel</p></list-item><list-item id="u0280"><p id="p0495">in utero infection</p></list-item><list-item id="u0285"><p id="p0500">pregnancy</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0155"><title>Key Features</title><p id="p0505">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0065"><list-item id="u0290"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0510">Zika virus, a flavivirus, has re-emerged with intense outbreaks in the Americas since 2013.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0295"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0515">It is transmitted by <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitoes, primarily the species <italic>Aedes aegypti,</italic> but sexual transmission and transfusion-related transmission have also occurred.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0300"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0520">It is often a mild or asymptomatic illness, but infections can manifest with rash, fever, conjunctivitis, and myalgias; severe manifestations have occurred and include Guillain&#x02013;Barr&#x000e9; syndrome (GBS). In utero transmission has led to microcephaly and other severe birth defects.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0305"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0525">There is no anti-viral agent to treat Zika virus infection; supportive care is indicated.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0310"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0530">There is no effective vaccine yet; prevention relies on avoidance of vector mosquitoes and sexual contact with infected persons, which are particularly important for pregnant women and persons who are planning conception.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="s0160"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0535">Zika virus, a single-stranded RNA virus of the Flaviviridae family, genus <italic>Flavivirus,</italic> originally isolated in Africa, gained worldwide attention in 2015 and 2016 when massive outbreaks in Brazil were followed by a marked increase in infants born with severe microcephaly and congenital abnormalities. The virus subsequently spread throughout the Americas. Intense research activities have answered key questions about Zika virus, its spread, and control, but gaps in knowledge remain.</p></sec><sec id="s0165"><title>Epidemiology</title><p id="p0540">Zika virus, first isolated from a sentinel rhesus monkey in the Zika forest in Uganda in 1947, was found in the same area in 1948 in <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitoes. The first human infection was identified in the 1950s. In subsequent decades it was identified sporadically in animals and in mild human infections in Africa and Asia. In 2007 Zika virus caused a large outbreak on Yap Island (western Pacific), initially thought to be caused by dengue virus; the virus was estimated to infect 70% of the population.<xref rid="bib3.1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> It subsequently caused a major outbreak in French Polynesia in 2013 to 2014.<xref rid="bib3.2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Zika virus was first associated with recognized outbreaks in Brazil in 2015, but recent analyses using sequencing, molecular mapping, and modeling suggest Zika reached the Americas as early as 2013, with cryptic transmission before the disease was detected.<xref rid="bib3.3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> From northeast Brazil the virus spread to the Caribbean, Central America, and throughout South America (except Chile and Uruguay where local vector transmission has not been documented); many countries in Asia and Africa have also documented transmission<xref rid="bib3.6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> (<xref rid="f0045" ref-type="fig">Fig. 36.3.1</xref>
). Local vector transmission in the continental United States has occurred in Florida and Texas (226 cases as of December 2017; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/zika" id="iw0035">https://www.cdc.gov/zika</ext-link>). A 2016 outbreak in Singapore (455 cases confirmed) shows the potential for outbreaks in many tropical and sub-tropical regions where competent mosquito vectors are present and ecoclimatic conditions are favorable.<xref rid="bib3.7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref>
<fig id="f0045"><label>Fig. 36.3.1</label><caption><p>Recent status of Zika virus transmission.</p></caption><alt-text id="atte0045">Fig. 36.3.1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="f036003-001-9780323555128"/><attrib>(From European Center for Disease Control and Prevention: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ecdc.europa.eu/en/publications-data/current-zika-transmission-worldwide" id="iw0030">https://ecdc.europa.eu/en/publications-data/current-zika-transmission-worldwide</ext-link>.)</attrib></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0170"><title>Transmission</title><p id="p0545">Infection is spread primarily via infected female mosquitoes, with <italic>A. aegypti</italic> being the primary vector in the Americas. <italic>A. albopictus,</italic> which can survive in more temperate areas, can also transmit Zika virus. These mosquito vectors infest most sub-tropical and tropical regions globally, including urban areas (areas with a total population of about 3.6 billion people). Seasonality of transmission is linked to local temperature and rainfall patterns. The same mosquitoes can also transmit dengue and chikungunya (and co-transmission can occur). In the past 10 years, Zika transmission has been reported from at least 84 countries.<xref rid="bib3.6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> Zika virus can be transmitted vertically in <italic>A. aegypti</italic> mosquitoes. The transmission cycle in the Americas has been person&#x02013;mosquito&#x02013;person. It is not known whether the virus will become established in an animal reservoir host in the Americas, as occurs in Africa, where the virus infected animal hosts and occasionally spilled over into the human population&#x02014;at least in the past.<xref rid="bib3.8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> The growth of urban areas infested with <italic>A. aegypti</italic> provides a suitable environment for transmission.</p><p id="p0550">Of the 5413 Zika virus disease cases (excluding congenital cases) reported in the United States for January 2015 to December 6, 2017, 95% were travel related and 99% were vector borne. Of the 51 cases that were not vector borne, 94% were attributed to sexual transmission, 1 due to laboratory transmission, and 1 unknown route (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/zika" id="iw0040">https://www.cdc.gov/zika</ext-link>).</p><p id="p0555">Virus can be found in blood, urine, saliva, semen, and vaginal or cervical secretions. Sexual transmission can occur during or after symptomatic or asymptomatic infection from male to female, male to male, and female to male (possibly via oral sex).<xref rid="bib3.9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> Virus is found in vaginal secretions, and viral RNA has been documented in semen up to 188 days after infection and infectious virus up to 69 days. In a longitudinal assessment of Zika virus RNA in body fluids, 95% of men had cleared the virus from semen after about 3 months.<xref rid="bib3.10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> In areas infested with competent vectors, it is difficult to assess what percentage is vector borne and how much infection is sexually transmitted. Zika virus particles and RNA have been found in breast milk, but transmission via breastfeeding has not been documented to date. Virus persists longer in whole blood than in plasma, which may be relevant for diagnosis and in testing blood or tissue donations for transfusion/transplantation. Transmission via platelet transfusion was reported from Brazil,<xref rid="bib3.11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> and RNA Zika&#x02013;positive asymptomatic donors were identified in Florida and Texas in the United States.<xref rid="bib3.12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> Screening of blood donors in Puerto Rico during an outbreak on the island found 1.1% viremic.<xref rid="bib3.13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0175"><title>Pathogenesis and Pathology</title><p id="p0560">Perinatal transmission of Zika virus was reported to occur in the French Polynesia outbreak in 2013 to 2014, but the association between Zika virus and microcephaly was not recognized until the observations had been made in Brazil and a retrospective study was done in 2016 based on serologic and surveillance data.<xref rid="bib3.14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> Zika virus can infect the placenta, reach the developing fetus, and can target neural precursors. Maternal infection disrupts fetal central nervous system development and causes intrauterine growth retardation and fetal loss. Infection is associated with cortical malformations and intra-cranial calcifications. The congenital malformations include ventriculomegaly, dystrophic calcifications, severe cortical neuronal depletion, decreased brain weight, congenital contractures, marked early hypertonia with symptoms of extrapyramidal involvement, and ocular and hearing problems.<xref rid="bib3.15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> Pathologists also identified pulmonary hypoplasia and pathologic changes consistent with viral infection of multiple organs, including liver and kidneys.<xref rid="bib3.17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> Ongoing follow-up will reveal the extent of other developmental problems.</p><p id="p0565">Based on data from the U.S. territories (2464 live-born infants from completed pregnancies with laboratory evidence of possible Zika virus infection), about 5% had Zika-associated birth defects. The likelihood varied by trimester and was highest during the first trimester (8%, 5%, and 4%, respectively, for first, second, and third trimesters).<xref rid="bib3.18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0180"><title>Clinical Features</title><p id="p0570">Zika virus seroprevalence studies in Yap and French Polynesia estimated that asymptomatic infections ranged from 29% to 80%.<xref rid="bib3.1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Clinical syndromes among residents from outbreak areas such as Yap, French Polynesia, Brazil, and Puerto Rico and returned infected travelers appeared to be alike<xref rid="bib3.1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> (<xref rid="t0025" ref-type="table">Table 36.3.1</xref>
). The most frequently reported symptoms were rash (74%&#x02013;100%), fever, arthritis and/or arthralgia, myalgia, conjunctivitis, and fatigue. The most common finding, rash, was usually described as maculopapular.<xref rid="bib3.1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Pruritus was reported from Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, and travelers evaluated in the GeoSentinel Surveillance Network, but not from other series.<xref rid="bib3.1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Fatigue was frequently reported from French Polynesia and Brazil (78% and 73%, respectively)<xref rid="bib3.2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> but possibly not solicited or recorded in some other series. Proportions with retro-orbital pain or edema/swelling were variable. Presenting symptoms among children infected postnatally resembled those in adults, mainly with rash, fever, conjunctivitis, and arthralgia.<xref rid="bib3.7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0025"><label>TABLE 36.3.1</label><caption><p>Comparison of Proportions of Symptoms in Samples of Zika-Infected Persons</p></caption><alt-text id="atte0090">TABLE 36.3.1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Yap<xref rid="bib3.1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref></th><th align="left">French Polynesia<xref rid="bib3.2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref></th><th align="left">Brazil<xref rid="bib3.20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref></th><th align="left">Puerto Rico<xref rid="bib3.21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref></th><th align="left">U.S. Travelers<xref rid="bib3.22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref></th><th align="left">GeoSentinel Travelers<xref rid="bib3.23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref></th><th colspan="2" align="center">Singapore<xref rid="bib3.7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref></th><th align="left"><bold>U.S. Pediatric Travelers</bold><xref rid="bib3.24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Sample size, N</td><td align="left">31</td><td align="left">297</td><td align="left">119</td><td align="left">683</td><td align="left">115</td><td align="left">91</td><td align="left">149 adults</td><td align="left">14 children</td><td align="left">158</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rash</td><td align="left">90</td><td align="left">93</td><td align="left">97</td><td align="left">74</td><td align="left">98</td><td align="left">88</td><td align="left">93</td><td align="left">100</td><td align="left">82</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fever/sweats</td><td align="left">65</td><td align="left">72</td><td align="left">36</td><td align="left">63</td><td align="left">82</td><td align="left">76</td><td align="left">79</td><td align="left">93</td><td align="left">55</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Arthralgia</td><td align="left">65</td><td align="left">65</td><td align="left">63</td><td align="left">63</td><td align="left">66</td><td align="left">72</td><td align="left">23</td><td align="left">14</td><td align="left">28</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Headache</td><td align="left">45</td><td align="left">46</td><td align="left">66</td><td align="left">63</td><td align="left">57</td><td align="left">61</td><td align="left">23</td><td align="left">21</td><td align="left">+</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Myalgia</td><td align="left">48</td><td align="left">65</td><td align="left">61</td><td align="left">68</td><td align="left">55</td><td align="left">60</td><td align="left">42</td><td align="left">29</td><td align="left">+</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fatigue</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">78</td><td align="left">73</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">47</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Conjunctivitis</td><td align="left">55</td><td align="left">64</td><td align="left">56</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">37</td><td align="left">40</td><td align="left">23</td><td align="left">29</td><td align="left">29</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pruritus</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">79</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">23</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Retro-orbital pain</td><td align="left">39</td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">45</td><td align="left">51</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">+</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Edema/swelling</td><td align="left">19</td><td align="left">47</td><td align="left">29</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td colspan="10"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Gastrointestinal (nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, or abdominal pain)</td><td align="left">+</td><td align="left">+</td><td align="left">+</td><td align="left">+</td><td align="left">+</td><td align="left">+</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">&#x02212;</td><td align="left">+</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>&#x02212; = Not reported specifically; + = reported.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0575">Rarely, some severe complications in adults have been attributed to Zika virus infection, particularly neurologic disorders (GBS, myelitis, demyelinating polyneuropathy, meningoencephalitis), autoimmune disorder, and immune-mediated thrombocytopenia.<xref rid="bib3.23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> GBS occurred in about 1/4000 Zika infections in studies from French Polynesia and Brazil, at least six times that of the global baseline incidence; males had higher risk.<xref rid="bib3.25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Patients with Zika-associated GBS or encephalitis have died (6%), and 51% have chronic pain.<xref rid="bib3.27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> As described earlier, congenital Zika syndrome resulting from infection during pregnancy is associated with devastating abnormalities in the newborn and has the most significant impact.</p></sec><sec id="s0185"><title>Patient Evaluation, Diagnosis, and Differential Diagnosis</title><p id="p0580">During acute infection with Zika virus, laboratory findings may reveal leukopenia, lymphopenia, thrombocytopenia, and less frequently, leukocytosis. C-reactive protein may be mildly elevated, as well as transaminases.</p><p id="p0585">Recommendations for confirmatory Zika virus testing vary among countries and have evolved over the course of its rapid spread in the Americas. In the United States testing has been constrained by availability of diagnostic tests and laboratory capability. The guidelines consider the pregnancy status of the patient or partner, exposure history, and symptoms, with strongest focus on pregnant women<xref rid="bib3.28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> (<xref rid="f0050" ref-type="fig">Fig. 36.3.2</xref>
).<fig-group id="f0050"><label>Fig. 36.3.2</label><alt-text id="atte0050">Fig. 36.3.2</alt-text><fig id="f9000"><caption><p>Testing recommendations and interpretation of results for symptomatic persons with possible Zika virus exposure. (A) Pregnant women.</p></caption><alt-text id="atte0055">Unlabelled image</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="f036003-002a-9780323555128"/><attrib>(From Oduyebo T, Polen KD, Walke HT, et al. Update: interim guidance for health care providers caring for pregnant women with possible Zika virus exposure &#x02013; United States (including U.S. territories), July 2017. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2017;28;66(29):781&#x02013;93.)</attrib></fig><fig id="f9005"><caption><p>Testing recommendations and interpretation of results for symptomatic persons with possible Zika virus exposure. (B) Non-pregnant women.</p></caption><alt-text id="atte0060">Unlabelled image</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="f036003-002b-9780323555128"/><attrib>(From CDC. Guidance for US laboratories testing for Zika virus infection, July 24, 2017. Available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/zika/laboratories/lab-guidance.html" id="iw0045">https://www.cdc.gov/zika/laboratories/lab-guidance.html</ext-link>.)</attrib></fig></fig-group></p><p id="p0590">Definitive Zika diagnosis can be made by detection of viral RNA during acute infection by reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) or other nucleic acid tests (NATs). RNA appears to be detectable longer in whole blood and urine samples compared with serum samples. These molecular tests can be performed on serum, whole blood, or urine up to 2 weeks after symptom onset; in pregnant women, NATs may be performed up to 12 weeks after symptom onset or exposure<xref rid="bib3.28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="bib3.29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> (see <xref rid="f0050" ref-type="fig">Fig. 36.3.2</xref>).</p><p id="p0595">Detection of Zika IgM by IgM-capture enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (MAC-ELISA) followed by confirmation with plaque reduction neutralization test (PRNT) can also establish the diagnosis. Zika IgM may be reactive when performed 2 to 12 weeks after exposure, but can persist longer. Unfortunately, Zika serology cross-reacts with other flaviviruses, and PRNT, which is needed to differentiate among the flaviviruses, is labor intensive, time consuming, and challenging to interpret. Unlike dengue and chikungunya, where IgG is available to assess past infection and immunity, Zika IgG is not available in the United States.</p><p id="p0600">There are no Food and Drug Administration (FDA)&#x02013;licensed diagnostic tests for the diagnosis of Zika virus infection, but several diagnostic tests are available under Emergency Use Authorization. The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) and state laboratories perform testing with PCR or IgM, and the CDC performs PRNT. In October 2017, the FDA approved the first Zika test for screening blood donations.</p><p id="p0605">The main differential diagnoses for Zika virus infection are other viruses transmitted by <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitoes, especially dengue (also a flavivirus) and chikungunya (an alphavirus). Because Zika, dengue, and chikungunya cause similar symptoms and each may have important consequences, distinguishing between the three arboviruses by molecular test or serology followed by PRNT is desirable. Other diagnoses that may resemble Zika virus infections include rubeola, rubella, parvovirus, West Nile virus, and many other viruses, as well as leptospirosis, rickettsiosis, and malaria.</p></sec><sec id="s0190"><title>Treatment and Prevention</title><p id="p0610">Treatment for the typical uncomplicated Zika virus infection aims to provide symptomatic relief. There is no known specific medication targeting Zika virus. However, research is underway to assess the effect of some existing drugs on Zika virus. Preliminary investigations have identified some candidate drugs: emricasan, niclosamide, sofosbuvir, chloroquine, azithromycin, and bovine lactoferrin.<xref rid="bib3.9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> Further evaluation is needed regarding their potential activity against Zika virus.</p><p id="p0615">Currently there is no vaccine to prevent Zika virus infection but multiple candidate vaccines are under development and testing. Therefore avoidance of mosquito bites and sexual transmission is fundamental in prevention. The impact of Zika virus infection is most consequential during pregnancy; thus preventing infection in pregnant women is crucial. The key messages for pregnant women, their partners, and persons planning conception include the following: avoid travel to areas with active Zika virus transmission, take measures to avoid mosquito bites, and practice safe sex to reduce risk from sexual transmission. In areas with active Zika virus transmission, vector control measures are essential. Updated epidemiology and testing recommendations on the CDC website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/zika" id="iw0050">www.cdc.gov/zika</ext-link>) are valuable in guiding clinical practice.</p></sec><ref-list id="bb0025"><title>References</title><ref id="bib3.1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0250"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zika virus outbreak on Yap Island, Federated States of Micronesia</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>360</volume><issue>24</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>2536</fpage><lpage>2543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19516034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0255"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Musso</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gubler</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zika virus</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source><volume>29</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>524</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27029595</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0260"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faria</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Quick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Claro</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Establishment and cryptic transmission of Zika virus in Brazil and the Americas</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>546</volume><issue>7658</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>406</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28538727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0265"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Worobey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology: molecular mapping of Zika spread</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>546</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>355</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28538722</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0270"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chinazzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spread of Zika virus in the Americas</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>114</volume><issue>22</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>E4334</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28442561</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sr0275"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>WHO</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Situation Report: Zika virus, microcephaly, Guillain-Barre syndrome</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/emergencies/zika-virus/situation-report/10-march-2017/en/" id="iw0055">http://www.who.int/emergencies/zika-virus/situation-report/10-march-2017/en/</ext-link><year>2017</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0280"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>The Singapore Study Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Outbreak of Zika virus infection in Singapore: an epidemiological, entomological, virological, and clinical analysis</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><volume>17</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>813</fpage><lpage>821</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28527892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0285"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Althouse</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasilakis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sall</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential for Zika virus to establish a sylvatic transmission cycle in the Americas</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><volume>10</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>e0005055</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27977671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0290"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Jean</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology, prevention, and potential future treatments of sexually transmitted Zika virus infection</article-title><source>Curr Infect Dis Rep</source><volume>19</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>16</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28281082</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0295"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paz-Bailey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Persistence of Zika virus in body fluids &#x02013; final report</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>379</volume><issue>13</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>1234</fpage><lpage>1243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28195756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0300"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Motta</surname><given-names>IJF</given-names></name><name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cordeiro da Silva</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for transmission of Zika virus by platelet transfusion</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>375</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1101</fpage><lpage>1103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27532622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0305"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galel</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First Zika-positive donations in the continental United States</article-title><source>Transfusion</source><volume>57</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>762</fpage><lpage>769</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28164310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0310"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuehnert</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Basavaraju</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Moseley</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening of blood donations for Zika virus infection &#x02013; Puerto Rico, April 3-June 11, 2016</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><volume>65</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>627</fpage><lpage>628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27337368</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0315"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cauchemez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Besnard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bompard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between Zika virus and microcephaly in French Polynesia, 2013-15: a retrospective study</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>387</volume><issue>10033</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>2125</fpage><lpage>2132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26993883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0320"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Honein</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>US Zika pregnancy registry collaboration. Birth defects among fetuses and infants of US women with evidence of possible Zika virus infection during pregnancy</article-title><source>JAMA</source><volume>317</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27960197</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0325"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Staples</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobyns</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterizing the pattern of anomalies in congenital Zika syndrome for pediatric clinicians</article-title><source>JAMA Pediatr</source><volume>171</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>288</fpage><lpage>295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27812690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0330"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>AQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavalcante</surname><given-names>DIM</given-names></name><name><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postmortem findings for 7 neotates with congenital Zika virus infection</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><volume>23</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>1164</fpage><lpage>1167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28459414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0335"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shapiro-Mendoza</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Galang</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pregnancy outcomes after maternal Zika virus infection during pregnancy- U.S. territories, January 1, 2016-April 25, 2017</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><volume>66</volume><issue>23</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>615</fpage><lpage>621</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28617773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0340"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aubry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Teissier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Huart</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zika virus seroprevalence, French Polynesia, 2014&#x02013;2015</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><volume>23</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>672</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0345"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brasil</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvet</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Siqueira</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zika virus outbreak in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil: clinical characterization, epidemiological and virological aspects</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>e0004636</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27070912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0350"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dirlikov</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryff</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres-Aponte</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Update: ongoing Zika virus transmission, Puerto Rico, November 1, 2015 &#x02013; April 14, 2016</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><volume>65</volume><issue>17</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27149205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0355"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hennessey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Travel-associated Zika virus disease cases among U.S. Residents - United States, January 2015-February 2016</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><volume>65</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>286</fpage><lpage>289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27023833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0360"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbre</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GeoSentinel surveillance network. travel-associated Zika virus disease acquired in the Americas through February 2016: a geosentinel analysis</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><volume>166</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27893080</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0365"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dziuban</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characteristics of children aged &#x0003c;18 years with Zika virus disease acquired postnatally - U.S. States, January 2015-July 2016</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><volume>65</volume><issue>39</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1082</fpage><lpage>1085</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27711041</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0370"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao-Lormeau</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mons</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Guillain-Barr&#x000e9; syndrome outbreak associated with Zika virus infection in French Polynesia: a case-control study</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>387</volume><issue>10027</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1531</fpage><lpage>1539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26948433</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0375"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parra</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lizarazo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jim&#x000e9;nez-Arango</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Guillain-Barr&#x000e9; syndrome associated with Zika virus infection in Colombia</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>375</volume><issue>16</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1513</fpage><lpage>1523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27705091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0380"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Da Silva</surname><given-names>IRF</given-names></name><name><surname>Frontera</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bispo de Filippis</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurologic complications associated with the Zika virus in Brazilian adults</article-title><source>JAMA Neurol</source><volume>74</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>1190</fpage><lpage>1198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28806453</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0385"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oduyebo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Polen</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Walke</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Update: interim guidance for health care providers caring for pregnant women with possible Zika virus exposure - United States (including U.S. territories), July 2017</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><volume>66</volume><issue>29</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>781</fpage><lpage>793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28749921</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3.29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sr0390"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>CDC</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Guidance for US Laboratories Testing for Zika Virus Infection</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/zika/laboratories/lab-guidance.html" id="iw0060">https://www.cdc.gov/zika/laboratories/lab-guidance.html</ext-link><year>2017</year></element-citation></ref></ref-list></sec><sec id="sc0030"><sec-meta><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0035"><name><surname>Deye</surname><given-names>Gregory</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0040"><name><surname>Koren</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group></sec-meta><label>36.4</label><title>O'nyong Nyong Fever</title><sec id="s0195"><sec id="s0200"><title>Abstract</title><p id="p0620">O'nyong nyong fever (ONN) is an arboviral disease caused by an alphavirus of the Semliki Forest complex. Clinical disease has primarily been described in large sporadic outbreaks in sub-Saharan Africa focused primarily in Uganda, Kenya, and Tanzania. ONN is transmitted by mosquitoes of the genus <italic>Anopheles</italic> and has no known vertebrate reservoir. Clinical disease is characterized by fever and arthralgia. Conjunctival suffusions and cervical lymphadenopathy have also been described in about half of the cases. Diagnosis can be made with amplification of virus using molecular amplification during viremia or by demonstration of seroconversion. Treatment is supportive, with non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) providing some potential benefit.</p></sec><sec id="s0205"><title>Keywords</title><p id="p0625">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0070"><list-item id="u0315"><p id="p0630">O'nyong nyong</p></list-item><list-item id="u0320"><p id="p0635">arbovirus</p></list-item><list-item id="u0325"><p id="p0640">alphavirus</p></list-item><list-item id="u0330"><p id="p0645">conjunctival suffusion</p></list-item><list-item id="u0335"><p id="p0650">arthralgia</p></list-item><list-item id="u0340"><p id="p0655">Kenya</p></list-item><list-item id="u0345"><p id="p0660">Uganda</p></list-item><list-item id="u0350"><p id="p0665">Tanzania</p></list-item><list-item id="u0355"><p id="p0670">
<italic>Anopheles</italic>
</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0210"><title>Key Features</title><p id="p0675">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0075"><list-item id="u0360"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0680">Alphavirus transmitted by anopheline mosquitoes in sub-Saharan Africa.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0365"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0685">Typically reported in large epidemics with high attack rates.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0370"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0690">Fever and severe symmetric arthralgias are nearly universal. Pruritic maculopapular rash is common.</p></list-item><list-item id="o9000"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p9000">Lymphadenitis (especially posterior cervical) is common but not universal.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0375"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0695">Diagnosis is by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) in the first 3 days or by serology.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0380"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0700">Treatment is supportive, with acute symptoms resolving in 5 to 7 days.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="s9000"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p9005">O'nyong nyong fever (ONN) is an arboviral disease caused by an alphavirus of the Semliki Forest complex and closely related to chikungunya virus (CHIKV) (<xref rid="f0055" ref-type="fig">Fig. 36.4.1</xref>
). Like other members of this complex, O'nyong nyong virus (ONNV) causes a febrile arthralgic illness. It is unique among alphaviruses in its adaptation to <italic>Anopheles</italic> mosquito vectors, which are primarily responsible for its transmission.<fig id="f0055"><label>Fig. 36.4.1</label><caption><p>Alphavirus phylogenetic tree.</p></caption><alt-text id="atte0065">Fig. 36.4.1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="f036004-001-9780323555128"/><attrib>(From Bessaud M, Peyrefitte CN, Pastorino BA, et&#x0202f;al. O'nyong-nyong virus, Chad. Emerg Infect Dis 2006;12:1248.)</attrib></fig></p><p id="p9010">The disease was first recognized in 1959 when an epidemic began in northwestern Uganda. By the end of the epidemic in 1962, it had involved 2 million people in a bandlike distribution across Uganda, Kenya, and Tanzania. Investigation of this epidemic led to the discovery of the novel virus, which was named after an Acholi term meaning &#x0201c;the joint breaker.&#x0201d;<xref rid="bib4.1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0220"><title>Epidemiology</title><p id="p0715">ONN has largely been described as occurring in epidemics in sub-Saharan Africa. After the end of the initial epidemic in 1962, no clinical cases were recognized until a subsequent epidemic occurred in Uganda in 1996 to 1997 resulting in several hundred cases. However, sporadic cases have been reported from several regions in sub-Saharan Africa outside of recognized epidemics.<xref rid="bib4.2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib4.3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4.4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Furthermore, a recent serosurvey from coastal Kenya demonstrated 13% prevalence of ONNV antibody presence despite no reported recent outbreaks in the region.<xref rid="bib4.5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> An illness with clinical features very similar to ONN has been described in Nigeria with the causative agent originally named <italic>Igbo Ora virus.</italic> Subsequent studies have shown that Igbo Ora is actually a strain of ONNV.<xref rid="bib4.3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> The genetic similarities of Igbo Ora and the 1996 to 1997 ONNV to the 1959 ONNV, together with serosurveys from Kenya, Cameroon, and West Africa, suggest at least some level of unrecognized endemic transmission occurs during interepidemic periods.</p><p id="p0720">During recognized epidemics, rates of infection have been very high in some areas; up to 68% in some affected villages.<xref rid="bib4.6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p0725">The virus is principally transmitted by <italic>Anopheles funestus</italic> and <italic>A. gambiae,</italic> both of which also serve as important vectors of malaria. No vertebrate reservoir has been identified. Risk factors for infection are likely to be related to risk of mosquito exposure and are likely to be similar to risk factors associated with malaria.</p></sec><sec id="s0225"><title>Clinical Features</title><p id="p0730">The ratio of symptomatic to inapparent infections is roughly 2&#x02009;:&#x02009;1.<xref rid="bib4.6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> The incubation period is estimated to be 8 days.<xref rid="bib4.7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Clinical symptoms typically begin with sudden onset of fever and joint pains.<xref rid="bib4.8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> Joint involvement is generally symmetric, involving knees (90%), ankles (83%), elbows (75%), wrists (75%), or fingers (63%). Joint pain lasts for an average of 6 days, although durations as long as 90 days have been reported. Arthralgia was sufficiently severe to lead to immobilization in 78% of cases for an average of 4 days.<xref rid="bib4.8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> Headache and rash are also very commonly reported in clinical cases. The rash is described as maculopapular and descending in progression from head to trunk to extremities. It typically lasts for 4 to 7 days.<xref rid="bib4.7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p0735">Lymphadenopathy has also been commonly described and occurs most often in the cervical region but also in inguinal and axillary areas in some cases. This has been suggested as a distinguishing factor in ONN, but it notably only appears to occur in 40% to 50% of cases.<xref rid="bib4.7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib4.8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Conjunctival suffusions have also been reported in approximately half of cases.</p><p id="p0740">A mild neutropenia has been reported during the acute phase of the illness.<xref rid="bib4.7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> In both the 1959 to 1962 epidemic and the 1996 to 1997 epidemic, there were no reported fatalities, despite a total of more than 2 million cases.</p></sec><sec id="s0230"><title>Patient Evaluation, Diagnosis, and Differential Diagnosis</title><p id="p0745">Clinical features such as lymphadenopathy, fever, and arthralgia are important characteristic features but are not sufficiently specific to exclude other similar arbovirus infections such as chikungunya.<xref rid="bib4.8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> Careful history and physical examination should be directed at excluding other illnesses, as well as finding supportive features such as rash. Virus can be detected in whole blood by molecular amplification (polymerase chain reaction [PCR]), with greatest sensitivity during the first 3 days after the onset of illness. Serology can help to establish the diagnosis, which can be made by the detection of specific IgM or by paired acute and convalescent sera showing development of specific IgG. IgM typically appears during the second week of illness and persists for about 2 months, but can be as long as 6 months in some cases.<xref rid="bib4.8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> IgG titers begin to rise by day 21 and are long-lasting.<xref rid="bib4.2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p0750">Care must be taken in the interpretation of serologic results because of a well-known, one-way cross-reactivity with CHIKV (i.e., patients previously infected with chikungunya will develop cross-reactive antibodies against ONNV, but antibodies generated by ONNV infection will not reliably cross-react with chikungunya virus).<xref rid="bib4.9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0235"><title>Treatment and Control</title><p id="p0755">The illness is self-limited, but therapy with non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) may benefit joint symptoms. Preventive measures against exposure to malaria vectors&#x02014;for example, insecticide-treated bed nets and indoor residual insecticides&#x02014;should also be effective in controlling epidemic ONN. Additionally, vaccine efforts aimed at prevention of chikungunya may provide protection against ONNV infection due to production of cross-reactive antibodies.<xref rid="bib4.10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>
</p></sec><ref-list id="bb0030"><title>References</title><ref id="bib4.1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="or0010">O&#x02019;nyong-nyong. Lancet 1962;279(7225):363&#x02013;4.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4.2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0395"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bessaud</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Peyrefitte</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Pastorino</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>O'nyong-nyong virus, Chad</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><volume>12</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>1248</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16965706</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4.3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0400"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brault</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tesh</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Re-emergence of chikungunya and O'nyong-nyong viruses: evidence for distinct geographical lineages and distant evolutionary relationships</article-title><source>J Gen Virol</source><volume>81</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10644846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4.4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0405"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tappe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapaun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Emmerich</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>O'nyong-nyong virus infection imported to Europe from Kenya by a traveler</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><volume>20</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>1766</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25271361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4.5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0410"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>LaBeaud</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Banda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Brichard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High rates of O'nyong nyong and chikungunya virus transmission in coastal Kenya</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><volume>9</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>e0003436</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25658762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4.6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0415"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rwaguma</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawamata</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>O'nyong-nyong fever in south-central Uganda, 1996&#x02013;1997: description of the epidemic and results of a household-based seroprevalence survey</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><volume>180</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>1436</fpage><lpage>1443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10515801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4.7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0420"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shore</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>O'nyong-nyong fever: an epidemic virus disease in east Africa: III. Some clinical and epidemiological observations in the northern province of Uganda</article-title><source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source><volume>55</volume><year>1961</year><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>373</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4.8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0425"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kiwanuka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rwaguma</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>O'nyong-nyong fever in south-central Uganda, 1996&#x02014;1997: clinical features and validation of a clinical case definition for surveillance purposes</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><volume>29</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>1243</fpage><lpage>1250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10524970</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4.9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0430"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blackburn</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Besselaar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antigenic relationship between chikungunya virus strains and O'nyong nyong virus using monoclonal antibodies</article-title><source>Res Virol</source><volume>146</volume><year>1995</year><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7754238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4.10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0435"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Partidos</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Paykel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Weger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cross-protective immunity against O'nyong-nyong virus afforded by a novel recombinant chikungunya vaccine</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><volume>30</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>4638</fpage><lpage>4643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22583812</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></sec><sec id="sc0035"><sec-meta><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0045"><name><surname>Harley</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0050"><name><surname>Suhrbier</surname><given-names>Andreas</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group></sec-meta><label>36.5</label><title>Ross River Virus Disease</title><sec id="s0240"><sec id="s0245"><title>Abstract</title><p id="p0760">Ross River virus is an Australian mosquito-borne alphavirus that is the causative agent of Ross River virus disease, previously known as <italic>epidemic polyarthritis.</italic> The disease typically presents as a peripheral symmetric polyarthralgia or polyarthritis, accompanied during the acute phase by fever, rash, and/or myalgia. Arthritic symptoms can last for 3 to 6 months, generally with no long-term sequelae. Diagnosis is usually undertaken by IgM serology using a commercially available kit. Differential diagnoses include other arthritogenic alphaviruses and other infectious or autoimmune arthritides. Disease symptoms are usually treated with paracetamol or non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs.</p></sec><sec id="s0250"><title>Keywords</title><p id="p0765">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0080"><list-item id="u0385"><p id="p0770">Ross River virus</p></list-item><list-item id="u0390"><p id="p0775">Ross River fever</p></list-item><list-item id="u0395"><p id="p0780">epidemic polyarthritis</p></list-item><list-item id="u0400"><p id="p0785">Australia</p></list-item><list-item id="u0405"><p id="p0790">alphavirus</p></list-item><list-item id="u0410"><p id="p0795">arbovirus</p></list-item><list-item id="u0415"><p id="p0800">mosquito</p></list-item><list-item id="u0420"><p id="p0805">viral arthritis</p></list-item><list-item id="u0425"><p id="p0810">arthritis</p></list-item><list-item id="u0430"><p id="p0815">arthralgia</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0255"><title>Key Features</title><p id="p0820">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0085"><list-item id="u0435"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0825">Synonyms include epidemic polyarthritis and Ross River fever.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0440"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0830">Endemic and epidemic transmission in Australia and Papua New Guinea, with a mean of 4600 cases per annum in Australia (2000&#x02013;2015).</p></list-item><list-item id="u0445"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0835">Notable clinical features include peripheral symmetric polyarthralgia or polyarthritis, predominantly involving joints of the appendicular skeleton. The disease usually progressively resolves within 3 to 6 months.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0450"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0840">Diagnosis is usually made by pathology services using commercially available IgM/IgG enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA).</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="s0260"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0845">Ross River virus (RRV) is a mosquito-borne virus that causes several thousand human cases per year in Australia, with polyarthralgia or polyarthritis being the predominant clinical feature. This single-stranded, positive-sense RNA virus (11.8&#x0202f;kb genome) belongs to the genus <italic>Alphavirus</italic> and the family Togaviridae<italic>.</italic> The virus was first isolated from <italic>Aedes vigilax</italic> mosquitoes trapped beside the Ross River in Queensland (<xref rid="f0060" ref-type="fig">Fig. 36.5.1</xref>
) in 1959.<xref rid="bib5.1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> After a series of outbreaks, the disease was originally called <italic>epidemic polyarthritis</italic>.<xref rid="bib5.2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<fig id="f0060"><label>Fig. 36.5.1</label><caption><p>The figure shows the course of the 1979&#x02013;1980 epidemic in the Pacific islands <italic>(arrows)</italic>; the blue shaded areas show where RRV is endemic. The range of incidence rates per 100,000 per annum and the mean percentage of total Australian cases (for 2010&#x02013;2015) are given for each state or territory of Australia.</p></caption><alt-text id="atte0070">Fig. 36.5.1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="f036005-001-9780323555128"/><attrib>(Data were obtained from the Communicable Diseases Network Australia. Available via: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www9.health.gov.au/cda/source/cda-index.cfm" id="iw0065">http://www9.health.gov.au/cda/source/cda-index.cfm</ext-link>.)</attrib></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0265"><title>Epidemiology</title><p id="p0850">RRV disease is notifiable to public health authorities in Australia and is the most common arboviral disease in Australia. There has been a mean of 4600 (range 1451&#x02013;9554) reported cases per year (2000&#x02013;2015), equating to a mean national incidence of 21.3 (range 7.4&#x02013;40.2) per 100,000 per annum in the same period (data available via <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www9.health.gov.au/cda/source/rpt_4.cfm" id="iw0070">http://www9.health.gov.au/cda/source/rpt_4.cfm</ext-link>). Disease typically occurs in adults between 25 and 39 years old, with no clear predominance in males or females. Symptomatic infections are rare in children.<xref rid="bib5.1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p0855">RRV is endemic in Australia and Papua New Guinea. Most cases occur in northern Australia during the wet season (usually December&#x02013;February) when mosquito numbers are high. In 1979&#x02013;1980, RRV caused a large epidemic in the South Pacific (see <xref rid="f0060" ref-type="fig">Fig. 36.5.1</xref>) where the virus may still be circulating.</p></sec><sec id="s0270"><title>Natural History, Pathogenesis, and Pathology</title><p id="p0860">RRV is transmitted in enzootic cycles with macropods (kangaroos and wallabies) as the natural vertebrate hosts. The virus is transmitted to humans from other vertebrates (and humans during epidemics) by mosquitoes, principally <italic>A. vigilax, A. camptorhynchus,</italic> and <italic>Culex annulorostris</italic>.<xref rid="bib5.1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Enzootic transmission, complex ecology involving multiple hosts and vectors, and different modes of transmission in different biogeographic areas make the disease difficult to model and predict and hence hinder disease control.<xref rid="bib5.3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p0865">Rheumatic disease is believed to arise from adaptive and innate immune responses directed at RRV antigens and RNA persisting in affected tissues. These responses produce arthritogenic pro-inflammatory mediators.<xref rid="bib5.4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib5.5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Joint effusions predominantly contain mononuclear cells, and RRV RNA has been detected in synovial fluids by polymerase chain reaction (PCR). However, joint aspirations and PCR have limited value for diagnosis.<xref rid="bib5.6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> RRV infections can be sub-clinical, with the asymptomatic-to-symptomatic ratio between 1.2&#x02009;:&#x02009;1 and 3.0&#x02009;:&#x02009;1.<xref rid="bib5.1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p0870">Virus-specific antibodies, probably neutralizing antibodies, are believed to be the principal protective adaptive immune response to RRV.<xref rid="bib5.7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Naturally acquired immunity appears to be lifelong, with no reports of re-infection.</p></sec><sec id="s0275"><title>Clinical Features</title><p id="p0875">The incubation period for RRV is usually 7 to 9 days, with a range of 3 to 21 days.<xref rid="bib5.1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Acute disease typically involves polyarthralgia or polyarthritis (80%&#x02013;100% of patients), fever (20%&#x02013;60%), rash (40%&#x02013;60%, usually maculopapular), and/or myalgia (40%&#x02013;80%).<xref rid="bib5.1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="bib5.2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib5.4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> The joints most commonly affected are multiple peripheral small joints and the knees, usually with a symmetric pattern (<xref rid="t0030" ref-type="table">Table 36.5.1</xref>
). Effusions are often present but are usually small.<xref rid="bib5.2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Other symptoms include fatigue (&#x0003e;50%), headache, photophobia, and lymphadenopathy.<xref rid="bib5.1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="bib5.2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib5.4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> RRV encephalitis cases have been reported; however, causal links to the virus are unsupported.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0030"><label>TABLE 36.5.1</label><caption><p>Joint Involvement in Ross River Virus Disease.</p></caption><alt-text id="atte0095">TABLE 36.5.1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Joint</th><th align="left">Percentage With Involvement</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Wrist</td><td align="left">36&#x02013;100</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Knee</td><td align="left">39&#x02013;100</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ankle</td><td align="left">50&#x02013;97</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Interphalangeal (fingers)</td><td align="left">50&#x02013;81</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Elbow</td><td align="left">17&#x02013;71</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cervical spine</td><td align="left">12&#x02013;70</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Shoulder</td><td align="left">38&#x02013;62</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Interphalangeal (thumb)</td><td align="left">53&#x02013;58</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Thoracolumbar spine</td><td align="left">36&#x02013;56</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Tarsus</td><td align="left">36&#x02013;49</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Interphalangeal (toes)</td><td align="left">47</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x0201c;Hand,&#x0201d; including metacarpophalangeal joints</td><td align="left">45</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hip</td><td align="left">4&#x02013;27</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Temporomandibular joint</td><td align="left">10&#x02013;15</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>The percentage of patients who have arthritis/arthralgia in the indicated joint(s) is shown, with the range reflecting the data obtained from several studies.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><attrib>Data from Harley D, Sleigh A, Ritchie S. Ross River virus transmission, infection, and disease: a cross-disciplinary review. Clin Microbiol Rev 2001;14:909&#x02013;32, and papers cited therein.</attrib></table-wrap></p><p id="p0880">A popular misconception is that RRV disease symptoms persist for years. However, prospective studies using validated questionnaires illustrated that in patients with RRV disease (and no other diagnoses), symptoms usually progressively resolve over 3 to 6 months with no long-term sequelae.<xref rid="bib5.8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="bib5.9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0280"><title>Patient Evaluation, Diagnosis, and Differential Diagnosis</title><p id="p0885">A detailed history is helpful, especially with regard to residence, domestic and international travel, and season. Rapid onset of arthritic symptoms is usual, with pain on movement, tenderness, and slight swelling (which can be hard to detect) the most common signs. Tenderness, swelling, heat, redness, and intolerance to movement or pressure can be extreme. The rash is usually maculopapular, occurs within a few days after the onset of symptoms, and resolves within 5 to 10 days.<xref rid="bib5.4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> Rash distribution varies considerably, with the trunk and limbs most affected. The face is less affected and, rarely, the rash may be confined to palms, soles, and/or digital webs. Lymphadenopathy is frequently present, if sought. Aside from fatigue, constitutional symptoms usually resolve within a week.<xref rid="bib5.1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="bib5.2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib5.4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
</p><p id="p0890">Diagnosis is usually made by a primary-care physician aided by a commercial serodiagnostic enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA)-based test (widely available in Australia). Two serologic tests at least 10 to 14 days apart are recommended. Peripheral blood counts are usually normal except for a possible slight neutrophilia. An elevated erythrocyte sedimentation rate can occur, but decreases within a few weeks. Serum C-reactive protein levels are rarely elevated. If erosive changes are seen in x-rays, alternative diagnoses should be sought.<xref rid="bib5.2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib5.8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
</p><p id="p0895">The differential diagnoses at initial disease presentation include related Old World alphaviruses (e.g., chikungunya, Barmah Forest, or Sindbis virus<xref rid="bib5.4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>), dengue, and Epstein&#x02013;Barr virus. Other viral arthritides may also be considered, for example, rubella or parvovirus B19.<xref rid="bib5.2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib5.5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Drug reactions, autoimmune arthritides (e.g., rheumatoid arthritis), and other infectious arthritides may also be among the differential diagnoses. Persistent distinct monoarticular arthritis is inconsistent with RRV disease.<xref rid="bib5.2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p0900">In patients diagnosed with RRV disease but in whom symptoms last longer than 3 to 6 months, other differential diagnoses should be actively sought. In a survey of RRV disease patients, about half the patients reported disease lasting longer than 6 months. However, in nearly all these patients, other rheumatic conditions (primarily autoimmune) or depression were subsequently diagnosed.<xref rid="bib5.8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> There is no evidence that RRV disease predisposes to other rheumatic diseases,<xref rid="bib5.8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> but it may contribute to post-infective depression or fatigue.<xref rid="bib5.10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0285"><title>Prevention and Treatment</title><p id="p0905">Preventing mosquito bites prevents RRV infection. Insect repellants containing DEET are recommended (except for infants &#x0003c;2 months). Insect screens; bed nets; and long-sleeved, loose-fitting, light-colored clothes are also protective.</p><p id="p0910">RRV disease is generally treated with paracetamol or non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), with many patients being satisfied with this treatment.<xref rid="bib5.8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="bib5.9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Anecdotal evidence suggests different NSAIDs may need to be tried.<xref rid="bib5.2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Standard risks and contraindications for NSAID use in patients with conditions including asthma, peptic ulcer, cardiovascular and renal disease should be considered. Aspirin is used by some patients (but is not recommended for chikungunya<xref rid="bib5.4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>). Steroids are not generally recommended.<xref rid="bib5.11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> Although a vaccine has been tested in phase III human trials,<xref rid="bib5.7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> this is not commercially available.</p></sec><ref-list id="bb0035"><title>References</title><ref id="bib5.1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0440"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sleigh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ross River virus transmission, infection, and disease: a cross-disciplinary review</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source><volume>14</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2001</year><fpage>909</fpage><lpage>932</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11585790</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5.2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sr0445"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Epidemic polyarthritis handbook</chapter-title><year>1989</year><publisher-name>Department of Community Services and Health</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Canberra, Australia</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5.3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0450"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Claflin</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ross River virus: many vectors and unusual hosts make for an unpredictable pathogen</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><volume>11</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>e1005070</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26335937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5.4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0455"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suhrbier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaffar-Bandjee</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasque</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arthritogenic alphaviruses-an overview</article-title><source>Nat Rev Rheumatol</source><volume>8</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>420</fpage><lpage>429</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22565316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5.5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0460"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suhrbier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahalingam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The immunobiology of viral arthritides</article-title><source>Pharmacol Ther</source><volume>124</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19788897</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5.6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0465"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Denholm</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Spelman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ross River virus</article-title><source>Aust Fam Physician</source><volume>38</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>586</fpage><lpage>589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19893779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5.7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0470"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wressnigg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Velden</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Portsmouth</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An inactivated Ross River virus vaccine is well tolerated and immunogenic in an adult population in a randomized phase 3 trial</article-title><source>Clin Vaccine Immunol</source><volume>22</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25540268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5.8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0475"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mylonas</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Carthew</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural history of Ross River virus-induced epidemic polyarthritis</article-title><source>Med J Aust</source><volume>177</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>356</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12358577</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5.9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0480"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bossingham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Purdie</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ross River virus disease in tropical Queensland: evolution of rheumatic manifestations in an inception cohort followed for six months</article-title><source>Med J Aust</source><volume>177</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>352</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12358576</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5.10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0485"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galbraith</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peripheral blood gene expression in postinfective fatigue syndrome following from three different triggering infections</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><volume>204</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>1632</fpage><lpage>1640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21964398</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5.11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0490"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mylonas</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Harley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Purdie</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Corticosteroid therapy in an alphaviral arthritis</article-title><source>J Clin Rheumatol</source><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>326</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17043541</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></sec><sec id="sc0040"><sec-meta><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0055"><name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>Marcio R.T.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0060"><name><surname>Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>Pedro F.C.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group></sec-meta><label>36.6</label><title>Oropouche Virus</title><sec id="s0290"><sec id="s0295"><title>Abstract</title><p id="p0915">Oropouche fever is the native most prevalent arboviral disease in the Americas and is caused by Oropouche fever virus (OROV) (<italic>Orthobunyavirus</italic> genus in the Peribunyaviridae family). OROV has four recognized genotypes (I, II, III, and IV) causing the same disease, which is characterized by acute febrile onset accompanied by headache, photophobia, muscle and joint pains, and in limited cases, meningitis. OROV is widely distributed in northern South America and is transmitted in urban settings by the midge <italic>Culicoides paraensis</italic>. The diagnosis is performed by virus isolation into cell culture or mice of suspected blood of acute-phase patients, by reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) and real-time PCR, and by serologically through detection of specific IgM antibodies. Conventional serologic tests can also give a positive result, but need two serum samples (acute and convalescent phases) with an interval of at least 1 week. There are no specific drugs for treatment of Oropouche fever patients, but fever, headache, and muscle/joint pains are often treated with common analgesics such as aspirin and acetaminophen. No vaccine against OROV is available, and only personal protection measures can avoid the anthropophilic vector bites.</p></sec><sec id="s0300"><title>Keywords</title><p id="p0920">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0090"><list-item id="u0455"><p id="p0925">Oropouche virus</p></list-item><list-item id="u0460"><p id="p0930">Peribunyviridae</p></list-item><list-item id="u0465"><p id="p0935">
<italic>Orthobunyavirus</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0470"><p id="p0940">Oropouche fever</p></list-item><list-item id="u0475"><p id="p0945">febrile illness</p></list-item><list-item id="u0480"><p id="p0950">
<italic>Culicoides paraensis</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0485"><p id="p0955">aseptic meningitis</p></list-item><list-item id="u0490"><p id="p0960">IgM ELISA</p></list-item><list-item id="u0495"><p id="p0965">molecular biology</p></list-item><list-item id="u0500"><p id="p0970">genotypes</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0305"><title>Key Features</title><p id="p0975">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0095"><list-item id="u0505"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0980">The most prevalent arboviral disease in South America, after dengue and chikungunya fever viruses.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0510"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0985">More than 30 epidemics reported in the last three decades in the Brazilian Amazon region, Peru, Panama, and Trinidad and Tobago, with an estimated occurrence of over 500,000 infections.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0515"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0990">Clinical picture caused by Oropouche fever virus is an acute febrile disease with headache, chills, myalgia, nausea/vomiting, retro-ocular pain, and dizziness.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0520"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0995">Some patients develop aseptic meningitis, and virus can be recovered from blood but also from cerebrospinal fluid.</p></list-item><list-item id="o9005"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p9015">Four genotypes of Oropouche fever virus (I, II, III, and IV) are recognized.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0525"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p1000">Urban cycle is responsible for outbreaks and transmission, and is transmitted by the midge <italic>Culicoides paraensis</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0530"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p1005">Diagnosing of Oropouche fever virus is by IgM enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) virus isolation and molecular biology techniques, mainly reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) and real-time PCR, and nucleotide sequencing.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0535"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p1010">There is no vaccine available to prevent Oropouche fever virus, and personal protection is recommended during epidemics.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="s0310"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p1015">Oropouche virus (OROV), a member of the <italic>Orthobunyavirus</italic> genus in the Peribunyaviridae family, is the causative agent of Oropouche fever.<xref rid="bib6.1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="bib6.2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> The first case of Oropouche fever was described in 1955, when the virus was isolated from the blood sample of a febrile patient in the West Indies and from a pool of <italic>Coquillettidia venezuel&#x000ad;ensis</italic> mosquitoes. A large epidemic was recorded in the 1960s in Bel&#x000e9;m, Brazil, involving an estimated 11,000 people.<xref rid="bib6.1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Over the past five decades, it is estimated that more than half a million people have been infected by the virus in the tropical areas of South and Central America, mainly in the Amazon region of Brazil and Peru.<xref rid="bib6.3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib6.4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0315"><title>Epidemiology</title><p id="p1020">OROV has been found in Brazil, Panama, Peru, and Trinidad and Tobago, and is basically maintained by two different life cycles. One occurs in urban areas of tropical cities in the Amazon basin and involves humans as the vertebrate hosts, with <italic>Culicoides paraensis</italic> midges as the major arthropod vector. Transmission in general occurs outdoor in the daytime, especially during sunrise and sunset. The other described life cycle is sylvatic and not well understood and is based on serologic prevalence involving wild mammals (especially sloths and monkeys) and birds as the potential vertebrate hosts. The arthropod vector in the sylvatic life cycle is unknown, but may include <italic>C. paraensis</italic>.<xref rid="bib6.1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="bib6.2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
</p><p id="p1025">Many outbreaks of Oropouche fever have been characterized by epidemics spreading in numerous villages within one geographic area and over a short period; these episodes essentially occur in new colonized areas and in the suburbs of large Amazonian urban centers. The spread of the virus is probably a consequence of the circulation of viremic people in localities where the transmitting vector can be found and where there is a large concentration of susceptible individuals.<xref rid="bib6.4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0320"><title>Natural History, Pathogenesis, and Pathology</title><p id="p1030">Oropouche fever is a self-limiting, febrile illness with no fatalities recorded. Using molecular typing methods, four different OROV genotypes have been described in the Americas.<xref rid="bib6.3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib6.4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib6.5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Little is known about the pathogenesis of the Oropouche fever in humans&#x02014;most of the information on pathogenesis has been obtained in experimental studies on golden hamsters. As in humans, the viremic period in these animals is brief and reaches titers high enough to easily infect <italic>C. paraensis</italic> midges.<xref rid="bib6.2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> In lethal infections in hamsters, intense encephalitis is observed with a prominent hepatitis, the probable mechanism of animal deaths.<xref rid="bib6.1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0325"><title>Clinical Features</title><p id="p1035">Clinically, Oropouche fever is characterized by the sudden onset of high fever, headache, myalgia, arthralgia, anorexia, dizziness, chills, and photophobia. Some patients present with a morbilliform exanthem that resembles rubella or dengue. Nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, conjunctiva congestion, epigastric and retro-ocular pain, and other constitutional symptoms are also common.<xref rid="bib6.1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Some patients may display a picture of aseptic meningitis, and others temporary encephalitis. A recrudescence of mild symptoms several days after waning of the initial febrile episode is commonly seen (biphasic illness). Recovery is complete in all individuals without apparent sequelae, even in the most severe cases. There are no reports of proven lethality caused by Oropouche fever.<xref rid="bib6.2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0330"><title>Patient Evaluation, Diagnosis, and Differential Diagnosis</title><p id="p1040">The differential diagnosis includes other causes of febrile illness, particularly dengue fever, chikungunya fever, and malaria. Blood samples collected during the acute phase of illness (up to 5 days after the onset of the symptoms) can be used for virus detection methods. The most commonly applied molecular method is reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR),<xref rid="bib6.3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib6.4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib6.5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> and recently a real-time PCR showed excellent results.<xref rid="bib6.6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> Virus isolation can be attempted in newborn mice or hamsters (1&#x02013;3 days), or in Vero or C6/36 cell cultures. For viral identification, suspensions prepared from brains of mice or supernatants of infected Vero or C6/36 cells are used as antigens in complement fixation or immunofluorescence assays with OROV hyper-immune serum. More recently the molecular approaches have been used for genotyping and identification of isolates.<xref rid="bib6.3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib6.4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib6.5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib6.6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> For specific identification of OROV, neutralization and hemagglutination inhibition tests can be also performed.<xref rid="bib6.2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0335"><title>Treatment and Prevention</title><p id="p1045">Treatment is supportive, common analgesics should be used to relieve the headache and muscle and joint pains, in particular to treat retrobulbar pain that in general is severe. No vaccine is available to prevent Oropouche fever; only personal control measures are recommended, including use of repellents.</p></sec><ref-list id="bb0040"><title>References</title><ref id="bib6.1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0495"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name><surname>Travassos da Rosa</surname><given-names>APA</given-names></name><name><surname>Travasssos da Rosa</surname><given-names>JFS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oropouche virus. I. A review of clinical, epidemiological and ecological findings</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source><volume>30</volume><year>1981</year><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6782898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6.2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sr0500"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name><surname>Travassos da Rosa</surname><given-names>APA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>PFC</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Oropouche fever</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Feigin</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><source>Textbook of pediatric infectious diseases</source><edition>5th ed</edition><year>2004</year><publisher-name>Saunders</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc><fpage>2418</fpage><lpage>2423</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6.3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0505"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>MRT</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Medeiros</surname><given-names>DBA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A febre do Oropouche: uma revis&#x000e3;o dos aspectos epidemiol&#x000f3;gicos e moleculares na Amaz&#x000f4;nia Brasileira</article-title><source>Cad Sa&#x000fa;de Colet</source><volume>15</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><comment>in Portuguese</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6.4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0510"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Azevedo</surname><given-names>RSS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>MRT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oropouche fever epidemic in Northern Brazil: epidemiology and molecular characterization of isolates</article-title><source>J Clin Virol</source><volume>44</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19117799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6.5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0515"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saeed</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>MRT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nucleotide sequences and phylogeny of the nucleocapsid gene of Oropouche virus</article-title><source>J Gen Virol</source><volume>81</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>743</fpage><lpage>748</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10675412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6.6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0520"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naveca</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Nascimento</surname><given-names>VAD</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiplexed reverse transcription real-time polymerase chain reaction for simultaneous detection of Mayaro, Oropouche, and Oropouche-like viruses</article-title><source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source><volume>112</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>510</fpage><lpage>513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28591313</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></sec><sec id="sc0045"><sec-meta><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0065"><name><surname>Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>Pedro F.C.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0070"><name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>Marcio R.T.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group></sec-meta><label>36.7</label><title>Mayaro Virus</title><sec id="s0340"><sec id="s0345"><title>Abstract</title><p id="p1050">Mayaro fever is an arboviral disease characterized by an acute onset with fever, headache, muscle and joint pains, and pruriginous skin rash. The causal agent is the Mayaro virus (MAYV) that is a member of the <italic>Alphavirus</italic> genus of the Togaviridae family. Three MAYV genotypes have been identified. MAYV belongs to the Semliki Forest complex group, together with other viruses such as chikungunya, O'nyong-nyong, Ross River, and Bharmah Forest, among others, that cause fever, skin rash, and arthralgia. In northern South America, MAYV is widely recognized, and the prevalence is increasing within communities with close contact with forested areas. MAYV is mainly transmitted by <italic>Haemagogus</italic> spp., especially <italic>H. janthinomys,</italic> to non-human primates, and humans are tangentially infected when intruding on the natural ecosystem where the virus is endemic. The arthralgias are severe and last several months. There is no specific treatment, nor vaccines to prevent Mayaro fever; non-hormonal analgesics should be used to combat arthralgias.</p></sec><sec id="s0350"><title>Keywords</title><p id="p1055">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0100"><list-item id="u0540"><p id="p1060">Mayaro virus</p></list-item><list-item id="u0545"><p id="p1065">Togaviridae</p></list-item><list-item id="u0550"><p id="p1070">alphavirus</p></list-item><list-item id="u0555"><p id="p1075">rash febrile illness</p></list-item><list-item id="u0560"><p id="p1080">arthralgia</p></list-item><list-item id="u0565"><p id="p1085">IgM ELISA</p></list-item><list-item id="u0570"><p id="p1090">molecular biology</p></list-item><list-item id="u0575"><p id="p1095">real-time PCR</p></list-item><list-item id="u0580"><p id="p1100">genotypes</p></list-item><list-item id="u0585"><p id="p1105">
<italic>Haemagogus</italic>
</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0355"><title>Key Features</title><p id="p1110">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0105"><list-item id="u0590"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p1115">Mayaro fever virus is an alphavirus responsible for sporadic cases and several outbreaks of illness with fever, arthralgia, and rash in northern South America.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0595"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p1120">Some infected patients develop severe arthralgia during the defervescence period that can last up to a year.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0600"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p1125">Three Mayaro fever virus genotypes are recognized.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0605"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p1130">Mayaro fever virus is transmitted by <italic>Haemagogus</italic> mosquitoes, particularly <italic>H. janthinomys.</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0610"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p1135">The main vertebrate hosts are non-human primates.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0615"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p1140">In the Brazilian Amazon, the specific antibody rate ranges from 5% to 60%; it is higher among closed communities (South American Indians) in the forests.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="s0360"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p1145">Mayaro virus (MAYV) is a single-stranded, positive-sense, arthropod-borne RNA virus in the family Togaviridae, genus <italic>Alphavirus.</italic> Typically, it causes Mayaro fever, an acute fever illness, accompanied by intense arthralgia and a rash syndrome.<xref rid="bib7.1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Mayaro virus causes sporadic cases or small outbreaks in forest workers, but has caused a few larger epidemics, particularly in Brazil and nearby South American countries, especially in people living in communities near or inside the forest. The original isolation of Mayaro virus occurred in Trinidad and Tobago in 1954 from the blood of febrile patients. Two major epidemics were described in the Brazilian Amazon region<xref rid="bib7.2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>; smaller epidemics have been recognized since then in other parts of Brazil and in Santa Cruz, Bolivia.<xref rid="bib7.3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib7.4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Mayaro virus is maintained in nature in a cycle involving mammals, birds, and hematophagous arthropods. New World non-human primates and marmosets have been implicated as natural hosts.<xref rid="bib7.5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> The virus has been isolated several times from <italic>Haemagogus</italic> spp. mosquitoes, mainly from <italic>H. janthinomys</italic> species, which is considered the primary potential vector. There are three distinct genotypes of the virus. In addition, a unique strain of Mayaro virus has been recovered from <italic>Coquillettidia venezuelensis</italic> in Trinidad, two others from <italic>Sabethes</italic> spp., and one from <italic>Culex</italic> spp., which can represent spillover of the virus from the hosts.</p></sec><sec id="s0365"><title>Epidemiology</title><p id="p1150">Mayaro virus has been isolated from patient residents in tropical areas of Central and South America, mainly in Brazil, Trinidad and Tobago, Bolivia, Surinam, and Haiti. The virus has also been isolated in French Guiana, Colombia, Panama, and Peru. Detection of antibodies to the virus has been also demonstrated in certain populations of these countries, as well as in Guyana, Colombia, and Peru.<xref rid="bib7.2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Most cases occur in forest workers, who are typically adult males. In the Brazilian Amazon, the specific antibody rate ranges from 5% to 60%; it is higher among closed communities (South American Indians).</p><p id="p1155">Only a few major Mayaro fever epidemics have been reported in the Americas: two in Brazil, one in Bolivia, and one in Peru.<xref rid="bib7.2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib7.6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Between 1955 and 1991, epidemics of Mayaro fever were restricted to Brazil, beginning in the municipality of Guam&#x000e1;, Par&#x000e1; state (1955), and spreading toward other localities in the S&#x000e3;o Miguel do Par&#x000e1; state, such as Belterra (1978), Concei&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o do Araguaia (1981), Itaruma in Goias state, the central region of Brazil (1981), Benevides, Par&#x000e1; state (1991), and Peixe, Tocantins state (1991). In the following years, the agent reached other Peruvian Amazon counties (Tumbes, Aucayacu, and Huanuco in 1995).<xref rid="bib7.6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> In 2008 the virus re-emerged in Par&#x000e1; state causing an outbreak in the municipality of Santa B&#x000e1;rbara, Par&#x000e1; state, 50&#x0202f;km from Bel&#x000e9;m in northern Brazil,<xref rid="bib7.4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> and in 2014 to 2016 small outbreaks were also reported in central Brazil in the states of Mato Grosso and Goi&#x000e1;s, where this agent is considered an emerging virus.</p></sec><sec id="s0370"><title>Natural History, Pathogenesis, and Pathology</title><p id="p1160">Little is known about the pathogenesis of Mayaro fever in humans, as the virus has not been associated with deaths. Thus no material is available for histopathologic examination.<xref rid="bib7.1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> The data regarding its pathogenesis are a result of experimental in vitro studies using Vero cell cultures. These have indicated intense cytopathic effects and cell death, with casein kinase 2 (CK2) having an important role during the Mayaro virus infection cycle.<xref rid="bib7.7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0375"><title>Clinical Features</title><p id="p1165">Mayaro fever is clinically characterized as an acute febrile illness, generally accompanied by headache, myalgia, rash, chills, and photophobia. Dizziness, eye pain, nausea, and vomiting are less frequently reported. Arthralgia, predominantly affecting the wrists, fingers, ankles, and toes, as well as a cutaneous rash, are also commonly observed on the trunk and extremities.<xref rid="bib7.2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib7.3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Occasionally, there may also be painful joint swelling that can persist. In some patients, arthralgia lasts up to a year. An aspect to consider is the possibility of co-circulation of MAYV and chikungunya virus (CHIKV) in a same area, because both viruses are members of the Semliki Forest group in the <italic>Alphavirus</italic> genus, and a high cross-reactivity is present in serologic tests even on IgM-ELISA (enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay). Thus the molecular biology approaches are more indicated to confirm MAYV and/or CHIKV infection; indeed, the real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) is the gold standard diagnostic test to make a confirmation of infection by both viruses.</p></sec><sec id="s0380"><title>Patient Evaluation, Diagnosis, and Differential Diagnosis</title><p id="p1170">Leukopenia is a common finding in unspecific laboratory tests within the first week of illness, and a white cell count of about 2500/mm<sup>3</sup> is commonly observed; platelet counts and liver function tests are usually normal. The differential diagnosis includes other causes of fever, arthralgia, and rash, particularly dengue, Oropouche, chikungunya, and Zika fever viruses. The laboratory diagnosis of Mayaro fever either depends on virus isolation attempts or serologic diagnostic and molecular methods for genome detection. For virus isolation, biologic samples (serum or blood) obtained from viremic patients (up to 5 days after the onset of the symptoms) are used for inoculation in newborn mice or in Vero cells. Suspensions prepared from brains of mice or supernatants of infected cells are used as antigens in either complement fixation tests or an immunofluorescence assay against hyperimmune sera of different arboviruses circulating in the region. Specific identification of Mayaro virus is carried out using neutralization and hemagglutination inhibition tests<xref rid="bib7.1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> and by reverse transcription (RT)&#x02013;PCR,<xref rid="bib7.3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib7.4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> as well as by real-time PCR, that has showed excellent results.<xref rid="bib7.8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0385"><title>Treatment and Prevention</title><p id="p1175">Treatment is supportive. Some patients require hospitalization, but no deaths have been reported. In theory, personal protection against mosquito bites (insect repellent and long sleeves and trousers) should be protective, but this is not practical for most forest workers. Bed nets and window screens are of little benefit because <italic>Haemagogus</italic> mosquitoes are day biters. In addition, no vaccine is available to prevent Mayaro fever.</p></sec><ref-list id="bb0045"><title>References</title><ref id="bib7.1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sr0525"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name><surname>LeDuc</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Mayaro virus disease</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Monath</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group><series>The arboviruses&#x02014;epidemiology and ecology</series><volume>vol. III</volume><year>1986</year><publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Boca Raton</publisher-loc><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>150</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7.2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0530"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Travassos da Rosa</surname><given-names>JFS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An outbreak of Mayaro virus disease in Belterra, Brazil. I. clinical and virological findings</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source><volume>30</volume><year>1981</year><fpage>674</fpage><lpage>681</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6266263</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7.3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0535"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic relationships among Mayaro and Una viruses suggest distinct patterns of transmission</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source><volume>75</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>469</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16968922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7.4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0540"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azevedo</surname><given-names>RSS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>MRT</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>EPV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mayaro fever virus outbreak, Santa Barbara, Par&#x000e1; State, Brazilian Amazon</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><volume>15</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>1830</fpage><lpage>1832</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19891877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7.5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sr0545"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabezas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Arthropod-borne viral diseases in Peru</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Travassos da Rosa</surname><given-names>APA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>PFC</given-names></name><name><surname>Travassos da Rosa</surname><given-names>JFS</given-names></name></person-group><source>An overview of arbovirology in Brazil and neighbouring countries</source><year>1998</year><publisher-name>Instituto Evandro Chagas</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Belem</publisher-loc><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>218</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7.6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sr0550"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woodall</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Virus research in Amz&#x000f4;nia</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Lent</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><series>Atas simp&#x000f3;sio biota Amaz&#x000f4;nica</series><volume>vol. 6</volume><year>1967</year><publisher-name>Conselho Nacional de Pesquisas</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Rio de Janeiro</publisher-loc><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>63</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7.7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0555"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barroso</surname><given-names>MMS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva-Neto</surname><given-names>MAC</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Poian</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mayaro virus infection cycle relies on casein kinase 2 activity</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><volume>5</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>1334</fpage><lpage>1339</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7.8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0560"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naveca</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Nascimento</surname><given-names>VAD</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiplexed reverse transcription real-time polymerase chain reaction for simultaneous detection of Mayaro, Oropouche, and Oropouche-like viruses</article-title><source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source><volume>112</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>510</fpage><lpage>513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28591313</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></sec><sec id="sc0050"><sec-meta><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0075"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Keun Hwa</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0080"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Sung-Han</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0085"><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>In-Kyu</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group></sec-meta><label>36.8</label><title>Pathogenic Phleboviruses: Severe Fever With Thrombocytopenia Syndrome, Heartland Virus Disease, and Sandfly Fever</title><sec id="s0390"><sec id="s0395"><title>Abstract</title><p id="p1180">Phleboviruses cause human diseases, including severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome (SFTS), Heartland virus disease, and sandfly fever. SFTS virus is transmitted by <italic>Haemaphysalis longicornis</italic> ticks, causing hundreds of cases in China, Japan, and Korea annually. SFTS can lead to multi-organ failure and death. Heartland virus is thought to be transmitted by the Lone Star tick, and has been identified in a handful of cases in the United States. Sandfly fever viruses are transmitted by <italic>Phlebotomus</italic> sandflies in the Mediterranean, Middle East, and South Asia. Sandfly fever is usually a self-limited febrile illness; however, Toscana virus causes central nervous system disease.</p></sec><sec id="s0400"><title>Keywords</title><p id="p1185">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0110"><list-item id="u0620"><p id="p1190">
<italic>Phlebovirus</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item id="u0625"><p id="p1195">severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome (SFTS)</p></list-item><list-item id="u0630"><p id="p1200">Heartland virus</p></list-item><list-item id="u0635"><p id="p1205">sandfly fever</p></list-item><list-item id="u0640"><p id="p1210">epidemiology</p></list-item><list-item id="u0645"><p id="p1215">pathogenesis</p></list-item><list-item id="u0650"><p id="p1220">clinical presentation</p></list-item><list-item id="u0655"><p id="p1225">treatment</p></list-item><list-item id="u0660"><p id="p1230">sandfly</p></list-item><list-item id="u0665"><p id="p1235">tick</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0405"><title>Key Features</title><p id="p1240">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0115"><list-item id="u0670"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p1245">Phleboviruses belong to a genus of arboviruses that can cause human diseases, including Rift Valley fever, sandfly fever, and the more recently emerged severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome (SFTS) and Heartland virus disease.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0675"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p1250">SFTS virus (SFTSV) is transmitted by the <italic>Haemaphysalis longicornis</italic> tick, and is endemic in central and eastern China, Japan,and South Korea, with hundreds of cases occurring annually.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0680"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p1255">SFTS presents as a non-specific febrile illness that can progress to multi-organ failure with up to 12% to 30% mortality.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0685"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p1260">Heartland virus disease has occurred in a small number of older men in the Midwestern United States with a history of tick exposure.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0690"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p1265">Heartland virus is thought to be transmitted by the Lone Star tick, and fatal infections have occurred with multi-organ dissemination.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0695"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p1270">Sandfly fever viruses are transmitted by <italic>Phlebotomus</italic> sandflies, endemic to the Mediterranean region, Middle East, and South Asia.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0700"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p1275">Sandfly fever viruses usually cause self-limited febrile illness; however, Toscana virus is unique by primarily causing central nervous system disease.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="s0410"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p1280">The genus <italic>Phlebovirus,</italic> within the family Phenuiviridae (formerly Bunyaviridae) of the order Bunyavirales, contains viruses that cause human diseases, including Rift Valley fever, sandfly fever, and the more recently emerged severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome (SFTS) and Heartland virus (HRTV) disease.<xref rid="bib8.1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Phleboviruses are enveloped, negative-sense, single-stranded RNA viruses with a tri-segment genome (large [L], medium [M], and small [S]), containing over 70 viruses grouped into 10 species.<xref rid="bib8.2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> This chapter will briefly summarize SFTS virus (SFTSV), HRTV, and the sandfly fever viruses.</p></sec><sec id="s0415"><title>Severe Fever With Thrombocytopenia Syndrome</title><p id="p1285">
<italic><bold>Epidemiology:</bold></italic> SFTSV was first isolated from a patient in central China in 2009 and reported in 2011.<xref rid="bib8.3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> Since then, hundreds of SFTS cases have been reported in central and eastern China where the disease is endemic. SFTS was first reported in Japan and South Korea in 2013. Retrospective studies have subsequently documented SFTS cases in Japan in 2005, rural areas of central China in spring 2006, and South Korea in 2010.<xref rid="bib8.3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Transmission occurs through tick vectors, mainly <italic>Haemaphysalis longicornis,</italic> with animals such as goats, cattle, sheep, yak, donkeys, pigs, cats, deer, rats, mice, hedgehogs, weasels, brushtail possums, chickens, and some birds thought to serve as animal reservoirs. Migratory birds can act as carriers for <italic>H. longicornis</italic>&#x02013;borne SFTSV and may be important in long-distance dissemination.<xref rid="bib8.3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> SFTS occurs mainly during the spring and summer months when tick density is highest in endemic areas and human contact with infected ticks from animals is most likely. High-risk groups include farmers, ranchers, forest workers, and others who live in rural, hilly, wooded areas. Person-to-person transmission through direct contact with blood or bloody secretions has been reported.<xref rid="bib8.7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> SFTSV is phylogenetically separated into two clades, Chinese and Japanese, with viruses usually (though not always) consistent with their geographic origin. Korean strains fall within the Japanese clade.<xref rid="bib8.9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p1290">
<italic><bold>Pathogenesis:</bold></italic> SFTSV infection generally has four overlapping stages: incubation, febrile illness, multi-organ involvement, and convalescence (all four stages may not occur in milder infections). The incubation period is generally 5 to 14 days, and can be affected by viral dose and route of infection. Viremia peaks during the febrile illness stage at about 7 to 10 days after fever onset, and high viremia may be associated with poor outcomes.<xref rid="bib8.10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Very high viremia can occur, accompanied by uncontrolled systemic inflammatory response. During the multi-organ involvement stage, viremia gradually falls in survivors, but remains high in fatal cases. Viral components have been detected in the liver, spleen, lymph nodes, and bone marrow.<xref rid="bib8.12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> The marked thrombocytopenia typical of SFTS has been proposed to be due to splenic macrophage clearance of circulating virus-bound platelets.<xref rid="bib8.13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p1295">
<italic><bold>Clinical features:</bold></italic> SFTS presents as a non-specific febrile illness with sudden onset of fever lasting for 5 to 11 days, headache, fatigue, malaise, muscle and joint pain, nausea/vomiting, and diarrhea, accompanied by thrombocytopenia and leukopenia, which occur in almost all patients, and abnormal liver function tests. Multi-organ involvement can occur about 5 days after illness onset, lasting for 7 to 14 days, with progressive failure in fatal cases or a self-limited course in survivors. Progressive organ failure can be rapid, first in the liver and heart, then the lungs and kidneys. About one fifth of patients can have central nervous system (CNS) manifestations, including apathy, seizures, muscle tremors, and/or coma. Death can occur in 12% to 30% of cases, with the average time between illness onset and death being 9 days.<xref rid="bib8.12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> Poor outcomes are more likely in patients with advanced age, decreased consciousness, underlying disease, bleeding tendencies, elevated lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) and creatine kinase, prolonged activated partial prothrombin times, and elevated C-reactive protein during the disease course.<xref rid="bib8.15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> The convalescence period in survivors begins about 11 to 19 days after illness onset.</p><p id="p1300">
<italic><bold>Diagnosis:</bold></italic> SFTS should be considered in patients presenting with fever, thrombocytopenia, and leukopenia between spring and fall, with a history of exposure to ticks or relevant animals in endemic areas of China, Japan, and South Korea. Laboratory diagnosis consists of reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) (if available) during the first week of illness, or virus-specific IgM/IgG enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) after the first week.<xref rid="bib8.12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> Because the clinical presentation is non-specific, the differential diagnosis is broad and may include scrub typhus, rickettsial infections, anaplasmosis, leptospirosis, Q fever, dengue fever (where endemic), and other etiologies.</p><p id="p1305">
<italic><bold>Treatment and prevention:</bold></italic> No specific therapy has been proven to improve outcomes in SFTS. Treatment is supportive, consisting of early diagnosis and management of complications such as bacterial and fungal infections.<xref rid="bib8.12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> Ribavirin has been shown to have in vitro antiviral activity against SFTSV.<xref rid="bib8.18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> However, clinical benefit has not been demonstrated by ribavirin alone, perhaps due to sub-optimal doses and/or late timing of intervention.<xref rid="bib8.19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> Plasma exchange has been proposed to have some benefit when administered early.<xref rid="bib8.20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> Ribavirin and plasma exchange in combination has been used in some SFTS patients who have recovered.<xref rid="bib8.21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> Plasma exchange followed by convalescent serum therapy has been used to successfully treat a case of SFTS encephalopathy.<xref rid="bib8.14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> All of these therapies need to be confirmed with further studies. No vaccine is available for SFTS, and prevention consists of avoidance of tick bites. Health care providers should adhere to strict contact and droplet precautions due to the risk of environmental contamination and person-to-person transmission, especially when treating critically ill patients.<xref rid="bib8.22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0420"><title>Heartland Virus Disease</title><p id="p1310">
<italic><bold>Epidemiology:</bold></italic> HRTV was first isolated from two patients from Missouri in 2009.<xref rid="bib8.23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> A handful of cases have been documented since then, mainly in older men from the Midwestern United States with a history of tick bite exposure during the summer months. Transmission is thought to occur through the Lone Star tick (<italic>Amblyomma americanum</italic>).<xref rid="bib8.24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> No animal reservoir has yet been confirmed, although neutralizing antibodies have been detected in a variety of animals, including horses, deer, raccoons, and coyotes.<xref rid="bib8.27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
</p><p id="p1315">
<italic><bold>Pathogenesis:</bold></italic> The pathogenesis of HRTV is not well understood, given the low number of cases. HRTV has been detected in the brain (thalamus), liver, gallbladder, pancreas, heart, lung, large and small bowel, kidney, and testes, in addition to bone marrow, lymph node, and splenic tissue.<xref rid="bib8.29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p1320">
<italic><bold>Clinical features:</bold></italic> HRTV disease presents with fever, fatigue, headache, cough, joint and muscle pain, nausea, and diarrhea, with leukopenia and thrombocytopenia. Patients can have confusion with short-term memory loss lasting up to several months. Death has occurred in at least two confirmed cases with wide dissemination of virus and multi-organ failure.<xref rid="bib8.29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
</p><p id="p1325">
<italic><bold>Diagnosis:</bold></italic> HRTV disease should be considered in older men from the Midwestern United States with non-specific febrile illness and a history of tick bite exposure. Laboratory diagnosis can be performed at specialized laboratories using RT-PCR, IgM/IgG ELISA, and neutralization assays.<xref rid="bib8.31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> Differential diagnosis may include ehrlichiosis, anaplasmosis, West Nile virus infection, rickettsial infection, leptospirosis, and other etiologies.</p><p id="p1330">
<italic><bold>Treatment and prevention:</bold></italic> No specific therapy is available, and clinical management is supportive.</p></sec><sec id="s0425"><title>Sandfly Fever</title><p id="p1335">
<italic><bold>Epidemiology:</bold></italic> Sandfly fever is caused by viruses within the sandfly fever Naples virus (SFNV) species, including sandfly fever Sicilian virus (SFSV), sandfly fever Turkey virus (SFTV), and Toscana virus.<xref rid="bib8.2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Toscana virus is unique among sandfly-transmitted phleboviruses in that it primarily causes CNS disease.<xref rid="bib8.34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> The sandfly fever viruses are found in subtropical regions of southern Europe, North Africa, Eastern Mediterranean, Iraq, Iran, Pakistan, Afghanistan, and India, and can affect the local population as well as travelers and military personnel deployed to these areas.<xref rid="bib8.9002" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref> Sandfly fever viruses are transmitted by sandflies of the <italic>Phlebotomus</italic> genus in a human&#x02013;vector&#x02013;human cycle, especially during the warm season (e.g., April to October in the Mediterranean).<xref rid="bib8.32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> The role of animal reservoirs is unclear at present. Only adult female sandflies bite humans and readily pass through mosquito bed nets. Novel sandfly fever viruses continue to be identified and may be responsible for more human disease than previously thought.<xref rid="bib8.33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p1340">
<italic><bold>Pathogenesis:</bold></italic> The incubation period of sandfly fever viruses is usually a few days up to 2 weeks. The duration of viremia is typically less than 1 week. The viral load in cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) is usually low.<xref rid="bib8.32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.36" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.37" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>
</p><p id="p1345">
<italic><bold>Clinical features:</bold></italic> Most sandfly fever virus infections are thought to be subclinical as suggested by high seroprevalence rates in endemic regions, but with relatively few clinical cases.<xref rid="bib8.38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref> Symptomatic infections are typically self-limited with fever, headache, muscle and joint pain, fatigue, and abdominal pain. Facial flushing and rapid heart rate can sometimes occur. However, Toscana virus can cause encephalitis, meningitis, and peripheral neuropathy.<xref rid="bib8.35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.36" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> In most Toscana virus&#x02013;infected patients, fever, headache, nausea, and vomiting with nuchal rigidity occur, and depressed consciousness can be present in about 10% of cases. CSF shows mild pleocytosis with elevated protein and glucose levels, although protein and glucose may be normal.<xref rid="bib8.36" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.39" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.40" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> In addition to Toscana virus, SFTV can cause severe disease, including rarely CNS infections.<xref rid="bib8.33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.41" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.42" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>
</p><p id="p1350">
<italic><bold>Diagnosis:</bold></italic> Laboratory diagnosis is performed at specialized laboratories. RT-PCR can be performed for direct detection. Serologic testing can be done by IgM/IgG ELISA, with neutralization assays performed for confirmation. Viral isolation from blood or CSF can be done using mammalian cell lines.<xref rid="bib8.42" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.43" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="bib8.44" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>
</p><p id="p1355">
<italic><bold>Treatment and prevention:</bold></italic> No specific therapy is available, and clinical management is supportive. Prevention consists of sandfly control measures and avoidance of sandfly bites.</p></sec><ref-list id="bb0050"><title>References</title><ref id="bib8.1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sr0565"><article-title>International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses. Virus Taxonomy: The Classification and Nomenclature of Viruses; the Online (10th) Report of the ICTV</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://talk.ictvonline.org/ictv-reports/ictv_online_report/" id="iw0125">https://talk.ictvonline.org/ictv-reports/ictv_online_report/</ext-link><year>2017</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0570"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emerging phleboviruses</article-title><source>Curr Opin Virol</source><volume>5</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24607799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0575"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fever with thrombocytopenia associated with a novel Bunyavirus in China</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>364</volume><issue>16</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>1523</fpage><lpage>1532</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21410387</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0585"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The first identification and retrospective study of severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome in Japan</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><volume>209</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>816</fpage><lpage>827</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24231186</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr9000"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome virus infection, South Korea, 2010</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><volume>24</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>2103</fpage><lpage>2105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30334706</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0590"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Heo</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic analysis of severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome virus in South Korea and migratory bird routes between China, South Korea, and Japan</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source><volume>93</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>468</fpage><lpage>474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26033016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0595"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nosocomial transmission of severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome in Korea</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><volume>60</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1681</fpage><lpage>1683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25694652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0600"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Heo</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Family cluster analysis of severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome virus infection in Korea</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source><volume>95</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1351</fpage><lpage>1357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27928083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0605"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimojima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukushi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic and geographic relationships of severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome virus in China, South Korea, and Japan</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><volume>212</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>889</fpage><lpage>898</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25762790</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0610"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamic changes of laboratory parameters and peripheral blood lymphocyte subsets in severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome patients</article-title><source>Int J Infect Dis</source><volume>58</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28249810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0615"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hemorrhagic fever caused by a novel Bunyavirus in China: pathogenesis and correlates of fatal outcome</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><volume>54</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>527</fpage><lpage>533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22144540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0620"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome, an emerging tick-borne zoonosis</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><volume>14</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>763</fpage><lpage>772</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24837566</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0625"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathogenesis of emerging severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome virus in C57/BL6 mouse model</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><volume>109</volume><issue>25</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>10053</fpage><lpage>10058</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22665769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0630"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of plasma therapy for severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome encephalopathy</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><volume>22</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1306</fpage><lpage>1308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27315224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0635"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>QB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Case-fatality ratio and effectiveness of ribavirin therapy among hospitalized patients in China who had severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><volume>57</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>1292</fpage><lpage>1299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23965284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0640"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome in South Korea, 2013-2015</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><volume>10</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>e0005264</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28033338</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0645"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome, an emerging tick-borne zoonosis</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><volume>14</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>763</fpage><lpage>772</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24837566</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0650"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro antiviral activity of ribavirin against severe fever with thrombocytopenia virus</article-title><source>Korean J Intern Med</source><volume>32</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27899013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0655"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>QB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Case-fatality ratio and effectiveness of ribavirin therapy among hospitalized patients with severe fever with thrombocytopneia syndrome</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><volume>57</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>1292</fpage><lpage>1299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23965284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0660"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of early plasma exchange on survival in patients with severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome: a multicenter study</article-title><source>Yonsei Med J</source><volume>58</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>867</fpage><lpage>871</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28541003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0665"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two treatment cases of severe fever and thrombocytopenia syndrome with oral ribavirin and plasma exchange</article-title><source>Infect Chemother</source><volume>49</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28271646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0670"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extensive severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome virus contamination in surrounding environment in patient rooms</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><volume>24</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>911</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29355730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0675"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McMullan</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Folk</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new phlebovirus associated with severe febrile illness in Missouri</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>367</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>834</fpage><lpage>841</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22931317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0680"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Godsey</surname><given-names>MS</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First detection of Heartland virus (Bunyaviridae: phlebovirus) from field collected arthropods</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source><volume>89</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23878186</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0685"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Godsey</surname><given-names>MS</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Burkhalter</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transmission of Heartland virus (Bunyaviridae: phlebovirus) by experimentally infected Amblyomma americanum (Acari: Ixodidae)</article-title><source>J Med Entomol</source><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0690"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Godsey</surname><given-names>MS</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Panella</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surveillance for Heartland virus (Bunyaviridae: phlebovirus) in Missouri during 2013: first detection of virus in adults of Amblyomma americanum (Acari: Ixodidae)</article-title><source>J Med Entomol</source><volume>53</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27032416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0695"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bosco-Lauth</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Panella</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Root</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serological investigation of Heartland virus (Bunyaviridae: phlebovirus) exposure in wild and domestic animals adjacent to human case sites in Missouri 2012-2013</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source><volume>92</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1163</fpage><lpage>1167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25870419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0700"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riemersma</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Komar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heartland virus neutralizing antibodies in vertebrate wildlife, United States, 2009-2014</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><volume>21</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1830</fpage><lpage>1833</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26401988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0705"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fill</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Compton</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel clinical and pathologic findings in a Heartland virus-associated death</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><volume>64</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>510</fpage><lpage>512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27927857</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0710"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muehlenbachs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fata</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heartland virus-associated death in Tennessee</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><volume>59</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>845</fpage><lpage>850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24917656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0715"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pastula</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Turabelidze</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Notes from the field: Heartland virus disease - United States, 2012-2013</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><volume>63</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>270</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24670929</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0720"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alkan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bichaud</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>de Lamballerie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sandfly-borne phleboviruses of Eurasia and Africa: epidemiology, genetic diversity, geographic range, control measures</article-title><source>Antiviral Res</source><volume>100</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23872312</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0725"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ergunay</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayhan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Charrel</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel and emergent sandfly-borne phleboviruses in Asia Minor: a systematic review</article-title><source>Rev Med Virol</source><volume>27</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2017</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0730"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charrel</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bichaud</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>de Lamballerie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emergence of Toscana virus in the Mediterranean area</article-title><source>World J Virol</source><volume>1</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24175218</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0735"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Varani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelsomino</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartoletti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Meningitis caused by Toscana virus is associated with strong antiviral response in the CNS and altered frequency of blood antigen-presenting cells</article-title><source>Viruses</source><volume>7</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>5831</fpage><lpage>5843</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26569288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.9002"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr9005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Downs</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Flood</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sandfly fever in Afghanistan &#x02013; a sometimes overlooked disease of military importance: a case series and review of the literature</article-title><source>US Army Med Dep J</source><issue>3&#x02013;17</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>66</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.36"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0740"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dupouey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bichaud</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ninove</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toscana virus infections: a case series from France</article-title><source>J Infect</source><volume>68</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>290</fpage><lpage>295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24247068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.37"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0745"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ergunay</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sayiner</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Litzba</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multicentre evaluation of central nervous system infections due to flavi and phleboviruses in Turkey</article-title><source>J Infect</source><volume>65</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22705706</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.38"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0750"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Lamballerie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Tolou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of Toscana virus antibodies in volunteer blood donors and patients with central nervous system infections in southeastern France</article-title><source>Vector Borne Zoonotic Dis</source><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17627448</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.39"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0755"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bichaud</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Izri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>de Lamballerie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First detection of Toscana virus in Corsica, France</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><volume>20</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>O101</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23992202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.40"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0760"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alkan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Allal-Ikhlef</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Alwassouf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Virus isolation, genetic characterization and seroprevalence of Toscana virus in Algeria</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><volume>21</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1040.e1</fpage><lpage>1040.e9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.41"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0765"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ergunay</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ismayilova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Colpak</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A case of central nervous system infection due to a novel sandfly fever virus (SFV) variant: sandfly fever Turkey virus (SFTV)</article-title><source>J Clin Virol</source><volume>54</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22336084</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.42"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0770"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kocak Tufan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Weidmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulut</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical and laboratory findings of a sandfly fever Turkey virus outbreak in Ankara</article-title><source>J Infect</source><volume>63</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21824495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.43"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0775"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perez-Ruiz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Collao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro-Mar&#x000ed;</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reverse transcription, real-time PCR assay for detection of Toscana virus</article-title><source>J Clin Virol</source><volume>39</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17584525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8.44"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0780"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weidmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez-Seco</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sall</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid detection of important human pathogenic phleboviruses</article-title><source>J Clin Virol</source><volume>41</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>138</fpage><lpage>142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18006376</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></sec><sec id="sc0055"><sec-meta><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0090"><name><surname>Deye</surname><given-names>Gregory</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0095"><name><surname>Koren</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group></sec-meta><label>36.9</label><title>Sindbis Fever</title><sec id="s0430"><sec id="s0435"><title>Abstract</title><p id="p1360">Sindbis virus (SINV) is an alphavirus within the Western equine encephalitis virus complex. The virus is transmitted primarily by mosquitoes of the genus <italic>Culex,</italic> typically among multiple avian species, but occasional human infections and human outbreaks do occur. The virus is widely distributed, with reports of virus circulation in Asia, Africa, Europe, the Middle East, and Australia. Most infections in humans are asymptomatic, but infection may result in symptoms of fever, arthralgia, and rash along with fatigue, myalgias, and headache in some cases. Diagnosis is typically made with confirmation of seroconversion. There are no specific therapies for symptomatic cases, but treatment with non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) may be helpful.</p></sec><sec id="s0440"><title>Keywords</title><p id="p1365">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0120"><list-item id="u0705"><p id="p1370">Sindbis</p></list-item><list-item id="u0710"><p id="p1375">Culex</p></list-item><list-item id="u0715"><p id="p1380">arbovirus</p></list-item><list-item id="u0720"><p id="p1385">arthralgia</p></list-item><list-item id="u0725"><p id="p1390">fever</p></list-item><list-item id="u0730"><p id="p1395">rash</p></list-item><list-item id="u0735"><p id="p1400">Ockelbo disease</p></list-item><list-item id="u0740"><p id="p1405">Karelian fever</p></list-item><list-item id="u0745"><p id="p1410">Pogosta disease</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0445"><title>Key Features</title><p id="p1415">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0125"><list-item id="u0750"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p1420">Self-limited febrile illness with rash and polyarthropathy.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0755"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p1425">Arthritis may persist for longer than 12 months.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0760"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p1430">Broad geographic range.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="s0450"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p1435">Sindbis virus (SINV) is an alphavirus within the Western equine encephalitis virus complex. Like other alphaviruses, it has a single-stranded, positive-sense genome contained within a small, enveloped virion. The virus was first isolated in 1952 from <italic>Culex univittatus</italic> mosquitoes trapped in the Sindbis district of Egypt.<xref rid="bib9.1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> It was first isolated from human whole blood from a febrile patient in Uganda in 1961.<xref rid="bib9.2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> The first major recognized outbreak occurred in South Africa in 1974 causing hundreds of cases. During the 1980s a disease characterized by rash and arthritis was described in Sweden, Russia, and Finland and named <italic>Ockelbo disease, Karelian fever</italic>, and <italic>Pogosta disease,</italic> respectively. Subsequent analysis has shown all of these clinical syndromes to be caused by SINV.<xref rid="bib9.3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> Six genotypes have been described spread across four continents.<xref rid="bib9.2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0455"><title>Epidemiology</title><p id="p1440">The virus is transmitted primarily from <italic>Culex</italic> species of mosquitoes to multiple avian species, which serve as amplifying hosts and perpetuate the cycle of transmission. However, <italic>Aedes cinereus</italic> and <italic>A. communis</italic> are capable carriers and may function as bridging vectors from infected birds to humans.<xref rid="bib9.4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p1445">Outbreaks of clinical cases due to SINV infection have primarily been reported from South Africa and Scandinavia. However, reports of seropositive individuals have been reported from Australia, several countries in South and Southeast Asia, the Middle East, Central Europe, and several other countries across multiple geographic regions of Africa.<xref rid="bib9.2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p1450">In South Africa and Finland, disease incidence tends to be clustered in discrete outbreaks occurring on a background of sporadic endemic cases.<xref rid="bib9.5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib9.6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> The seasonality of cases mirrors changes in local <italic>Culex</italic> mosquito populations. Overall incidence has been noted to be steadily rising in Finland from 0.4 cases per 100,000 in 1982 to 1987 to 2.0 cases per 100,000 in 2010 to 2012.<xref rid="bib9.2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p1455">Seroprevalence rates vary significantly between various endemic regions, with some of the highest rates reported in areas of Finland (17%)<xref rid="bib9.7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> and South Africa (18%).<xref rid="bib9.6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p1460">Sindbis fever outbreaks have notably been reported in conjunction with outbreaks of West Nile virus infection as they share the same <italic>Culex</italic> mosquito vectors.<xref rid="bib9.8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0460"><title>Clinical Features</title><p id="p1465">The majority of infections result in asymptomatic or sub-clinical infection, with only approximately 6% of cases manifesting clinical symptoms.<xref rid="bib9.5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p1470">The incubation period is estimated to be 8 to 9 days.<xref rid="bib9.9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> The most common symptoms reported by patients are rash and arthralgia, both of which occur in more than 90% of cases. The rash typically appears on the trunk and limbs first, as macules and progressing to papules, with all lesions usually in the same stage of development.<xref rid="bib9.2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Distribution may include all four extremities, including palms and soles; the face is usually spared. The rash may persist for more than 5 days.</p><p id="p1475">Arthropathy is often symmetric and may occur with or without effusion. The joints most commonly involved include ankles, knees, fingers, and wrists, with less frequent involvement of hips, shoulders, neck, and back.<xref rid="bib9.9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p1480">Other symptoms often reported include fever, fatigue, myalgias, and headache, which are reported in approximately half of symptomatic cases.</p><p id="p1485">Joint symptoms can persist 3 years or longer, and may cause a significant degree of disability.<xref rid="bib9.10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> The presence of the HLADRB1*01 allele has been significantly associated with the manifestation of clinical disease and with a higher rate of chronic joint pain.<xref rid="bib9.11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0465"><title>Patient Evaluation, Diagnosis, and Differential Diagnosis</title><p id="p1490">Differential diagnosis should include consideration of chikungunya or Ross River virus infection based on geographic location. Other important considerations include parvovirus B19, varicella, or measles, along with non-infectious rheumatic conditions.</p><p id="p1495">Reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) usually is ineffective for diagnosis because viremia is low level and transient.<xref rid="bib9.2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Diagnosis is typically based on serologic confirmation.<xref rid="bib9.3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> Elevation of specific IgM is typically detectable within 1 week of symptom onset and persists for up to 6 months. IgG is generally elevated 8 to 9 days after symptom onset and is persistent.<xref rid="bib9.9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>
</p></sec><sec id="s0470"><title>Treatment</title><p id="p1500">There are no specific therapies. Symptomatic therapy with non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) and rest may provide some relief, although effectiveness may vary in individuals. Preventive measures include avoidance of the bites of <italic>Culex</italic> mosquitoes.</p></sec><ref-list id="bb0055"><title>References</title><ref id="bib9.1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0785"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurlbut</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Work</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sindbis virus: a newly recognized arthropod transmitted virus</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source><volume>4</volume><issue>5</issue><year>1955</year><fpage>844</fpage><lpage>862</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13259009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9.2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0790"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adouchief</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sane</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sindbis virus as a human pathogen&#x02014;epidemiology, clinical picture and pathogenesis</article-title><source>Rev Med Virol</source><volume>26</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26990827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9.3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0795"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manni</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurkela</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaheri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vapalahti</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnostics of Pogosta disease: antigenic properties and evaluation of Sindbis virus IgM and IgG enzyme immunoassays</article-title><source>Vector Borne Zoonotic Dis</source><volume>8</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18380591</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9.4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0800"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundstr&#x000d6;M</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Niklasson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transmission of Ockelbo virus by Aedes cinereus, Ae. communis, and Ae. excrucians (Diptera: Culicidae) collected in an enzootic area in central Sweden</article-title><source>J Med Entomol</source><volume>27</volume><issue>3</issue><year>1990</year><fpage>266</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2159073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9.5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0805"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brummer-Korvenkontio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vapalahti</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuusisto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of Sindbis virus infections in Finland 1981&#x02013;96: possible factors explaining a peculiar disease pattern</article-title><source>Epidemiol Infect</source><volume>129</volume><issue>02</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12403109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9.6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0810"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Storm</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Weyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Markotter</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human cases of Sindbis fever in South Africa, 2006-2010</article-title><source>Epidemiol Infect</source><volume>142</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>234</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23611492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9.7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0815"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laine</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vainionp&#x000e4;&#x000e4;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Oksi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The prevalence of antibodies against Sindbis-related (Pogosta) virus in different parts of Finland</article-title><source>Rheumatology</source><volume>42</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>632</fpage><lpage>636</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12709538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9.8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0820"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McIntosh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jupp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dos Santos</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Meenehan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemics of West Nile and Sindbis viruses in South Africa with Culex (Culex) univittatus theobald as vector</article-title><source>S Afr J Sci</source><volume>72</volume><issue>10</issue><year>1976</year><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>300</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9.9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0825"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurkela</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Manni</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Myllynen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical and laboratory manifestations of Sindbis virus infection: prospective study, Finland, 2002&#x02013;2003</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><volume>191</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>1820</fpage><lpage>1829</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15871114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9.10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0830"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurkela</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Helve</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaheri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vapalahti</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arthritis and arthralgia three years after Sindbis virus infection: clinical follow-up of a cohort of 49 patients</article-title><source>Scand J Infect Dis</source><volume>40</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17852949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9.11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0835"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sane</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurkela</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lokki</surname><given-names>M-L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical Sindbis alphavirus infection is associated with HLA-DRB1* 01 allele and production of autoantibodies</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><volume>55</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>358</fpage><lpage>363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22523259</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bb0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Developing an integrated epidemiologic approach to emerging infectious diseases</article-title><source>Epidemiol Rev</source><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1996</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8877326</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benedictow</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morbidity in historical plague epidemics</article-title><source>Popul Stud (Camb)</source><volume>41</volume><issue>3</issue><year>1987</year><fpage>401</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11612345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindahl</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Grace</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The consequences of human actions on risks for infectious diseases: a review</article-title><source>Infect Ecol Epidemiol</source><volume>5</volume><year>2015</year><comment>30048</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0025"><article-title>Microbiology by numbers</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><volume>9</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>628</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21961177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emerging virus diseases: can we ever expect the unexpected?</article-title><source>Emerg Microbes Infect</source><volume>1</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>e46</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26038413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sr0035"><article-title>World Health Organization. Disease oubreaks by year</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/csr/don/archive/year/en/" id="iw0015">http://www.who.int/csr/don/archive/year/en/</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global trends in emerging infectious diseases</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>451</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>990</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18288193</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woolhouse</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Haydon</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Antia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emerging pathogens: the epidemiology and evolution of species jumps</article-title><source>Trends Ecol Evol (Amst)</source><volume>20</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>238</fpage><lpage>244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16701375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Council of the World Federation of Societies of Intensive and Critical Care Medicine. Ebola virus disease: report from the task force on tropical diseases by the world federation of societies of intensive and critical care medicine</article-title><source>J Crit Care</source><volume>43</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>352</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29128378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sr0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Libraty</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Endy</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Houng</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differing influences of virus burden and immune activation on disease severity in secondary dengue-3 virus infections</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><volume>185</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>1213</fpage><lpage>1221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12001037</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>