<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For planning public health measures, basic transmission data for the novel coronavirus are essential. The first 425 confirmed cases from Wuhan provided data for a first epidemiological analysis (Li 
 <italic>et al.</italic>, 
 <xref rid="mbt213557-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">2020a</xref>), but it should be kept in mind that the virus might evolve during the epidemic and change its properties. Over the three early phases of the infection (&lt; Jan1, Jan1‐11, Jan 12‐22), no change in average age was seen (56–61 years); no cases &lt; 15 years of age were observed. Male dominance among the patients disappeared, and the degree of ‘wet’ market exposure in the patients dropped over time. In addition, patient contact with persons showing respiratory symptoms was reported in fewer than 30% of the cases. These scientists calculated a mean incubation period of 5.2 days displaying a long tail (95th percentile: 12.5 days). Comparisons of index cases and secondary cases in five clusters yielded a ‘serial interval’ of 7 days. From onset of illness to a medical visit, and then to hospital admission, 5 and 12 days elapsed respectively. The Wuhan epidemic showed a doubling time of 7 days. From the cluster analysis, a basic reproduction number of 2.2 was estimated, i.e. each case led on average to 2.2 new infections. Another report investigated a case of a family from Shenzhen visiting relatives in Wuhan (Chan 
 <italic>et al.</italic>, 
 <xref rid="mbt213557-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). One Wuhan relative had developed fever, cough and dyspnoea four days before the arrival of family members from Shenzhen. Four further relatives developed respiratory symptoms which led to hospitalization in two. From the six Shenzhen family visitors, the four adults developed symptoms (fever, cough, weakness and diarrhoea) during the 5 days of their Wuhan visit, while two children remained unaffected. Notably, a family member who remained in Shenzhen contracted the disease four days after the return of the visitors from Wuhan to Shenzhen. The data are evidence for efficient human‐to‐human virus transmission. The virus was detected in most nasopharyngeal and half of the throat swabs, a single serum sample, but no urine or stool sample of this family cluster. Of importance for easy sampling and virus diagnostics, 90% of hospitalized patients from Hongkong were positive for PCR virus detection in self‐collected saliva (Te 
 <italic>et al.</italic>, 
 <xref rid="mbt213557-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). The viral load ranged from 10
 <sup>3</sup> to 10
 <sup>8</sup> viral copies per ml saliva and decreased over the duration of hospitalization, but in one patient, it was still detectable 11 days after hospitalization. Another study extended the epidemiological analysis to 88 infected patients living outside of Wuhan, but who had a recent travel history to Wuhan (Backer 
 <italic>et al.</italic>, 
 <xref rid="mbt213557-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). This cohort allowed an estimation of the mean incubation period to 6.4 days. Upper estimates range up to 11 days, which is important to determine the appropriate duration of quarantine.
</p>
