<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In a humid atmosphere, the transformation of microdroplets and aerosols to solid residues are slowed down, thereby increasing the chance of precipitation of larger microdroplets. Yet smaller microdroplets and aerosols may suspend longer and keep their virulence, although the formation of solid residues are less‐likely in a humid environment. In hot and dry climate, fast evaporation of water from microdroplets and aerosols accelerates the generation of solid residues. This will aid that viruses suspend for several hours, however as mentioned above, the stability of enveloped viruses are lower in higher temperature and deactivated quickly.
 <sup>[</sup>
 <xref rid="adbi202000105-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>]</sup> This may explain why Middle East Respiratory Syndrome (MERS) that is caused by a similar enveloped virus and spread from camel to humans in hot and dry climate of middle eastern countries, never got the opportunity to became more widespread. Thus, the most favorable climate for effective spreading of enveloped viruses, is cold and dry weather, when not only sneezing and coughing but also normal breathing from asymptomatic people, creates a condense mist or virus‐laden aerosols suitable for creating virus‐laden solid residues. At the same time, cold temperature could keep the virus viable for several days (
 <bold>Figure</bold>
 <xref rid="adbi202000105-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>1</bold>
 </xref>). Although, yet to prove for SARS‐CoV‐2, the discussed criteria expected to hold true as prior studies hinted both temperature and humidity could aid both spreading and viability of enveloped viruses. Therefore, society should be especially prepared in cold and dry climate by employing suitable protective measure, e.g., face masks, as under these conditions asymptomatic people most likely create small enough virus‐laden solid residues that remain viable and suspended for several hours, and might travel with air flow. However, this does not mean viral transfection is less‐likely in warmer climates where indoor public places with cold and dry atmosphere (e.g., under AC operation) are suitable places to get infected, even if the outside temperature and humidity is not optimal for transfection. Particularly, in my opinion nearby cold‐shelves and freezers of groceries with limited ventilation and high human traffic are considered as high‐risk zone. Therefore, further protective measure, e.g., installation of laminar flow ventilation is recommended to improve the customer safety and reduce the chance of viral transfection.
</p>
