<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <title>Abstract</title>
 <sec id="s0100">
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>Respiratory virus–laden particles are commonly detected in the exhaled breath of symptomatic patients or in air sampled from healthcare settings. However, the temporal relationship of detecting virus-laden particles at nonhealthcare locations vs surveillance data obtained by conventional means has not been fully assessed.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s0101">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>From October 2016 to June 2018, air was sampled weekly from a university campus in Hong Kong. Viral genomes were detected and quantified by real-time reverse-transcription polymerase chain reaction. Logistic regression models were fitted to examine the adjusted odds ratios (aORs) of ecological and environmental factors associated with the detection of virus-laden airborne particles.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s0102">
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>Influenza A (16.9% [117/694]) and influenza B (4.5% [31/694]) viruses were detected at higher frequencies in air than rhinovirus (2.2% [6/270]), respiratory syncytial virus (0.4% [1/270]), or human coronaviruses (0% [0/270]). Multivariate analyses showed that increased crowdedness (aOR, 2.3 [95% confidence interval {CI}, 1.5–3.8]; 
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) and higher indoor temperature (aOR, 1.2 [95% CI, 1.1–1.3]; 
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001) were associated with detection of influenza airborne particles, but absolute humidity was not (aOR, 0.9 [95% CI, .7–1.1]; 
   <italic>P</italic> = .213). Higher copies of influenza viral genome were detected from airborne particles &gt;4 μm in spring and &lt;1 μm in autumn. Influenza A(H3N2) and influenza B viruses that caused epidemics during the study period were detected in air prior to observing increased influenza activities in the community.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s0103">
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>Air sampling as a surveillance tool for monitoring influenza activity at public locations may provide early detection signals on influenza viruses that circulate in the community.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
