<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is understandable that people living in quarantine, isolation, or at risk of an infectious disease outbreak are likely to experience psychosocial stress and adverse health outcomes, which may provoke their interest in learning more about the disease. However, such situations require assurance complemented by a flow of correct information. This need has been acknowledged by the World Health Organization, which has partnered with several social media platforms and seven major tech companies—namely, Facebook, Google, LinkedIn, Microsoft, Reddit, Twitter, and YouTube—that agreed to stamp out fraud and misinformation, and to promote critical updates from healthcare agencies [
 <xref rid="b7-jpmph-53-3-171" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Despite these agreements, rumors are still rampant on all these platforms, a problem that necessitates several multipronged interventions to address. First, frontline healthcare providers should be equipped with the most recent research findings and accurate information, which can be used for direct caregiving and communicated to at-risk patients or populations. Doing so may also facilitate more robust patient-provider communication and result in better health outcomes. Previously, the integration of information technology successfully improved patient care in managing mass casualty incidents, yielding several positive outcomes in the form of optimization of resources, extension of care, and improved health outcomes of patients [
 <xref rid="b8-jpmph-53-3-171" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Secondly, mass media, community organizations, support groups, and civil society may play critical roles in disseminating accurate information. To achieve this, it is necessary to build strategic partnerships at local and global levels, connecting offline and online resources in a coordinated manner so that validated information is communicated across platforms. Third, all hoaxes and rumors should be removed from all online platforms, and only scientifically sound information should be allowed to improve awareness among the general population. Advanced technologies like natural language processing or text-mining approaches may be helpful in detecting online content that has no scientific basis. The latest data-mining algorithms are successfully detecting the unique characteristics of all kinds of fake news and removing them from their respective platforms [
 <xref rid="b2-jpmph-53-3-171" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Twitter, Reddit, and Amazon have already implemented these methods to remove fake accounts or product reviews. Application of the same principles to remove all rumors and hoaxes regarding this pandemic is therefore evidently feasible, despite its unique challenges. Therefore, social media and other online providers should adopt such measures to identify and eliminate potentially harmful misinformation and rumors. Fourth, online portals and personnel involved with the production and propagation of such misinformation should be brought to justice. Local and national regulatory authorities and law enforcement agencies should be made aware of these challenges in order for them to address these issues comprehensively in their respective contexts. In this regard, the governments of many countries have arrested individuals involved with the spread of such rumors [
 <xref rid="b9-jpmph-53-3-171" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. However, before enforcing any of these laws worldwide, authorities should conduct a proper investigation and ensure the legal rights of the accused. Fifth, common platforms should be launched to provide precautionary information in both online and offline media at a large scale. Successful strategies for mass media campaigns from the last few epidemics should be identified and implemented. These messages should be culturally tailored and translated to several languages to increase outreach. For example, media coverage of the recent severe acute respiratory syndrome, H1N1 influenza, Middle East respiratory syndrome, Ebola, and H7N9 influenza epidemics had a significant effect on reducing the total spread of these pathogens by promoting healthy behaviors [
 <xref rid="b10-jpmph-53-3-171" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Factual information regarding COVID-19 can also be expected to have similar results. Sixth, telemedicine should be used to provide evidence-based care and informational services should be made available for people with limited access to care, such as people in rural areas, the elderly, and those who are simply stuck at home due to lockdown. This will both decrease the risk of hospital-acquired infections and also reduce the utilization of resources such as ventilators and personal protective equipment for doctors. Lastly, transparency, good information governance, and leadership across communities and institutions should be promoted to remove misleading information related to COVID-19, which is essential for the greater good of populations experiencing the health and psychosocial burdens of this pandemic.
</p>
