<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Viral sovereignty is the concept that virus samples isolated from within the territorial boundaries of a nation state are the sovereign property of that state. The history of viral sovereignty as a concept in international law is always told in the classic three-act narrative structure: the setup, the confrontation, and the resolution. The first act plays out across the latter half of the twentieth century, with the development of the World Health Organisation’s (WHO) global network of more than 100 influenza laboratories. The system that became known as the Global Influenza Surveillance Network (GISN)
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn1">1</xref> and now known as the Global Influenza Surveillance and Response System (GISRS), depended on the open sharing of influenza viruses from around the world to monitor the spread of seasonal influenza and detect the emergence of novel pandemic strains. The second act is the confrontation, set in 2007 when the Indonesian Health Minister refused to share H5N1 influenza viruses with the GISN, troubled by the fact that the WHO was giving their virus strains to pharmaceutical companies who used them to develop vaccines that were unaffordable to Indonesia and other lower and middle-income countries (LMICs).
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn2">2</xref> The Indonesians cited an environmental conservation treaty as the legal basis for claiming sovereignty over the viruses isolated within their territorial borders. This is the time at which the notion of viral sovereignty first entered the public discourse.
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn3">3</xref> The standoff between Indonesia and the WHO split global opinion along the old North-South political divide: developed countries were indignant at such a “morally reprehensible” move on Indonesia’s part,
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn4">4</xref> and developing countries were largely sympathetic to Indonesia’s claim.
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn5">5</xref> The third and final act is neatly wrapped up by 2011 with the adoption of the WHO’s 
 <italic>Pandemic Influenza Preparedness Framework</italic> (PIP Framework). Indonesia was apparently placated and access to influenza viruses with pandemic potential was secured by this “innovative” and “enforceable” international agreement.
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn6">6</xref> Viral sovereignty as a concept in law was seen as nothing but a blip on the international radar; a problem both created and resolved in less than five years.
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn7">7</xref>
</p>
