<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par69">Chemical insecticides remain the cornerstone of arbovirus vector control. In the medium term, there are no globally applicable alternatives. As a consequence, preserving the susceptibility to conventional insecticides should be the priority to all stakeholders and policy makers involved in vector borne disease control [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par70">When applied at high coverage, chemical-based interventions do have entomological impact, although epidemiological assessments of efficacy are rare [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Consequently, prioritisation of vector control strategies is difficult. The development of a “Global Fund” for ABVs would help to build in-country capacity to implement, monitor and evaluate interventions in order to generate the evidence require for decision making.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par71">Currently, it is hard to discriminate between vector control failures caused by sub-optimal use or by insecticide resistance. Regionally relevant trials, conducted against well-characterized IR mosquito populations, should be conducted to make an informed choice of intervention.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par72">Insecticide resistance is not binary, but rather continuous trait and lower levels of resistance may, temporarily, overcome by increased application rates. Accurate assessment of the phenotype and early detection of mutations that confer resistance can help to adjust vector control policies before operational consequences or intervention failures occur.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par73">Few operational teams or national authorities have the capacities to monitor insecticide resistance in routine. However, research institutions can provide support to local authorities by training public health officers, share laboratories, provide the expertise to design trials, and evaluate vector control interventions [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par74">All public health authorities tend to use single products until they fail. Unfortunately, the pipeline of new public health insecticides is very narrow, which means that older products cannot be removed and replaced with new ones when resistance is detected in a target mosquito population. WIN advocates for promoting routine substitutions/rotations between chemical classes that proved to be effective against the target species and/or deployment of non-chemical strategies [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], even at higher immediate cost in order to preserve susceptibility over the long term.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par75">WIN can help defining operational best practice, norms and guidance for IRM and develop Standard Operating Practices for monitoring and evaluation of IRM strategies.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par76">WIN can advocate for funding for training courses and regionally relevant trials as well as for the development of regulatory framework to promote the concept of susceptibility in vector control programmes.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
