<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In clinics, medical imaging tools are indispensable and form an essential component of viral diagnosis, as well as for monitoring viral progression [
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. They have also been used for follow-up in outpatient settings for coronavirus-related pulmonary disorders. Just like both SARS and MERS, pulmonary complications in COVID-19 patients have been observed. Learning from the well-documented SARS and MERS studies, CT imaging results in the acute and chronic periods of COVID-19 are invariant, but not always present [
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>–
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. Evidence is found in previous studies on SARS and MERS. The glass opacities observed are not always found in COVID-19 patients. Crucially, preliminary imaging discoveries indicate that COVID-19 yields nonspecific results as well [
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>–
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. Radiologists are presently striving to any characteristics specific to COVID-19, although present medical information remains limited. Given the precarious situation, there is a pressing need for alternative, complementary diagnostics. CT is one example. COVID-19 patients often develop “ground glass” lung opacities [
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. As such, a CT imaging scan can readily identify lung abnormalities in human subjects, thereby enabling early treatment against COVID-19. CT has demonstrated some common imaging characteristics in COVID-19 patients. These features include bilateral, multifocal, ground glass opacities, with a peripheral distribution (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7(a)</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. Crucially, more than half of 90 patients under study presented multilobar involvement and lesions more prominently in the lower lobes of their lungs. Given its feasibility and ease of use, CT has become an essential tool for the 2019-nCoV infection diagnosis. From a radiological perspective, the advantages of using CT imaging could expedite the rate of diagnosis. It also supports the current shortage and heavily reliant on technical know-how during RT-PCR testings. Nonetheless, one limitation is that it should be cautiously utilized as a diagnostic approach because there are no proven, evidence-based clinical benefits of using CT. It could also cause false securities if results are negative. Other limitations include requirements of relatively high-dose CT scans and long-term, continuous usage, which can altogether be logistically challenging and deplete additional medical resources.
</p>
