<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par103">Suitable combination therapies reduce the likelihood of drug resistance, suppress viral replication, lower toxicity levels, and provide synergistic effects (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Achieving high potency intensities, combinatorial treatments were employed especially in RNA viruses which mutate at higher rate than DNA viruses. However, care must be taken in order to avoid unwanted contraindications. Although there is no clinically approved antiviral drug or vaccine available to be used against COVID-19, few therapeutic combinations have been evaluated to cope with this viral outbreak. Some patients were clinically recovered after the administration of remdesivir combined with chloroquine (CQ) or IFN-β due to the significant blockade of the SARS-CoV-2 replication [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>]. In Saudi Arabia, a clinical trial discovered that a combination of lopinavir/ritonavir and IFN-β1b was shown to be effective among MERS-CoV-infected patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. It is also hypothesized that the combination of lopinavir/ritonavir and arbidol will deliver enhanced efficacy against SARS-CoV-2 for a synergistic effect is predictable [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. A higher potency of antiviral therapy was achieved after the fusion of ribavirin and IFN with immunomodulating agents such as intravenous N-acetylcysteine [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>]. Few synergistic combinations resulting from a network-based analysis include sirolimus and dactinomycin, an approved RNA synthesis inhibitor, target HCoV-associated host protein subnetwork by “complementary exposure” pattern, resulting in potential combination regimens for treatment of HCoVs. To successfully inhibit MERS-CoV replication, kinase inhibitors were combined with other host-targeting molecules such as peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor alpha (PPAR-α) agonists [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. In a retrospective analysis, ribavirin was tested in combination with corticosteroids, immunoglobulins, and/or antibiotics for SARS-CoV; no efficacy and high fatality rates were shown. Since ribavirin treatment did not improve patient outcome health, Canada stopped permitting the use of ribavirin. Additional studies tested the activity of ribavirin jointly with lopinavir against SARS-CoV. Compared to the control groups, confirmed SARS-CoV cases undergo a milder disease progression with no consequences. In another retrospective analysis, patients were treated with oral ribavirin and SC pegylated IFN-α2a for 2 weeks. At day 14 after confirmed diagnosis of MERS, survival was increased in the tested group (70%) compared to the control (29%). In an additional case study, an elderly patient who was infected with MERS in Jeddah was treated with oral lopinavir/ritonavir, pegylated IFN, and ribavirin. Viral RNA was detected in feces, serum, and respiratory secretions’ samples after 2 days for initiating the therapy and up to 2 weeks. An ongoing randomized clinical trial in Saudi Arabia is evaluating treatment of MERS patients with IFN-β1b conjointly with lopinavir/ritonavir due to the latter’s high efficacy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Among clinical treatments studied for treating SARS-CoV, combinations of steroid with either alfacon-1, a recombinant consensus IFN-α, or protease inhibitors and ribavirin were found to improve patients’ health [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. Patients with COVID-19 are being recruited in randomized trials to evaluate the efficacy of favipiravir plus IFN-α and favipiravir plus baloxavir marboxil (an approved influenza inhibitor targeting the cap-dependent endonuclease). The synergism between a pegylated-IFN and a nucleoside compound against COVID-19 is still ambiguous [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. In spite of drug repurposing and the use of targeted antiviral therapies (CQ, remdesivir, rapamycin, ribavirin), epigenetic drugs such as BRD4 inhibitors, DNMT1 inhibitors, and HDAC inhibitors have been demonstrated to potentially inhibit SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]. Novel broad spectrum replication inhibitors such as remdesivir or GS-5734 (Gilead Sciences, in phase I clinical trial), and immunomodulators along with direct-acting antiviral agents that are in development could make an efficient amalgamation for treating HCoVs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Knowing that the core treatment for eradicating HCoVs is controlling replication and immune response, offering drug therapies that target both pathways could be the best approach. Some epigenetic therapies have a dual action; resveratrol decreased the expression of NP protein in addition to SIRT-1 activation which counteracts viral replication and hyperinflammation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. The anti-viral and anti-inflammatory effects of CQ may play a crucial role in prevention and treatment of COVID-19 as it operated at entry and post-entry phases of SARS-CoV-2 infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>]. Generally, CQ blocks viral infection by elevating endosomal pH necessary for entry, replication, and maturation. For MERS-CoV and SARS-CoV, CQ interfered with cellular proteases and glycosylation of ACE2, respectively [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>]. Along with CQ’s antiviral effect, CQ decreases the production of pro-inflammatory indicators and cytokines reducing cytokine storm destruction [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>]. Merging antiviral drugs with epigenetic therapies targeting hyperinflammation is considered as an alternative. Antivirals (remdesivir, ribavirin, favipiravir, and galidesivir) could be combined with DNMTi (decitabine, azacitidine) or HDACi (vorinostat, belinostat, panobinostat, TSA). However, further preclinical experiments and clinical trials are required to validate the clinical benefits of these combined candidates. Epidemiological studies showed that the majority of severe SARS-CoV-2 cases were elderly patients with comorbid conditions whereas children cases have been rarely reported [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>] suggesting the use of anti-aging drugs targeting epigenetics (resveratrol), other anti-aging drugs (CQ, rapamycin, and doxycycline) and senolytics (azithromycin and quercetin) which could decrease substantial morbidity and mortality [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>]. Several anti-aging therapeutics exists as FDA-approved drugs with acceptable safety profile proposing their use in COVID-19 prevention [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>].
</p>
