<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A few studies have also evaluated the relevance of pro‐resolution molecules and pathways in the context of viral infections of the lung, especially influenza. In an elegant study, Morita et al. (
 <xref rid="bph15164-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>) found that another endogenous mediator of resolution, the lipid protectin D1 (PD1), was suppressed during severe influenza, and PD1 levels inversely correlated with the pathogenicity of H5N1 viruses (Morita et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15164-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). PD1 treatment improved the survival and pulmonary injury following severe influenza in mice and markedly attenuated influenza virus replication via the RNA export machinery. This is consistent with an earlier finding showing that a strain of H5N1 (VN/1203) was more pathogenic in mice than H1N1 (1918 pandemic virus), in part due to early and sustained up‐regulation of the components of pro‐inflammatory molecules along with inhibition of lipoxin‐mediated anti‐inflammatory responses (Cilloniz et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15164-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). The influenza A virus (IAV) H1N1 (strain PR8) enhanced its replication and propagation through the use of the ANXA1/FPR2 axis (Ampomah, Moraes, Lukman, &amp; Lim, 
 <xref rid="bph15164-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Arora et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15164-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). Indeed, the latter study clearly shows that regulation of ANXA1 and FPR2 expression during IAV infection may be a viral strategy to enhance its infectivity. However, administration of ANXA1 to mice, prior to infection, with the same strain of IAV, significantly attenuated pulmonary injury induced by the infection, with significantly improved survival, impaired viral replication in the respiratory tract, and less severe lung damage. These effects were associated with expansion of alveolar macrophages in ANXA1 pretreated animals (Schloer et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15164-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>).
</p>
