<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A previous influenza infection is known to increase the risk to a subsequent pulmonary bacterial infection, such as that caused by 
 <styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">S. pneumoniae</styled-content>. Indeed, post‐influenza bacterial infections seem to account for a significant number of deaths following annual flu epidemics. In a model of pulmonary co‐infection with influenza H3N2 (strain A/HKx31) and 
 <styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">S. pneumoniae</styled-content>, Wang et al. (
 <xref rid="bph15164-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) showed that administration of exogenous resolvin AT‐RvD1, facilitated more rapid clearance of pneumococci in the lungs, while concurrently reducing the severity of pneumonia by limiting excessive leukocyte chemotaxis from the infected bronchioles to distal areas of the lungs (Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15164-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). More recently, we showed that perturbation of the gut microbiota during IAV infection favoured respiratory bacterial superinfection with 
 <styled-content style="fixed-case" toggle="no">S. pneumoniae</styled-content>. In mechanistic terms, reduced production of the predominant short chain fatty acid, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/LigandDisplayForward?tab=biology%26ligandId=1058" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">acetate</ext-link>, appeared to account for the facilitating effects of influenza infection. Indeed, treatment with acetate reduced bacterial loads, lung pathology, and improved survival rates of double‐infected mice (Sencio et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15164-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). It is clear that the overall effects of mediators of resolution in the context of pulmonary infection is enhancement of anti‐bacterial and anti‐viral defences and inhibition of inflammatory responses, without interfering with the ability of the host to deal with the infection. A note of caution must be given here. At least one study has shown that resolution of inflammation can trigger a prolonged phase of localized immunosuppression which could predispose the host to secondary infections (Newson et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15164-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>).
</p>
