<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The possibility of using mediators of resolution to treat inflammation has led to the concept of “resolution pharmacology,” based on correcting and “pushing the resolution back on track” as a new strategy for the treatment of complicated and often chronic, inflammatory diseases, such as rheumatoid arthritis (Perretti, Leroy, Bland, &amp; Montero‐Melendez, 
 <xref rid="bph15164-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). There have also been a few studies evaluating the role and effects of mediators of resolution of inflammation in the context of bacterial, viral, and fungal infection. Overall, most studies have suggested that the mediators of resolution tend to decrease inflammatory responses during infection and provide normal or greater ability of the host to deal with infection. For example, in the context of infection with the protozoan parasite 
 <italic>Leishmania brasiliensis</italic>, the pro‐resolution peptide, annexin A1 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/LigandDisplayForward?ligandId=1031" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">ANXA1</ext-link>), was actively expressed during infection and its absence was associated with more intense inflammatory responses and delayed ability to resolve the lesion (Oliveira et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15164-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Similarly, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/FamilyDisplayForward?familyId=23" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">FPR2/ALX</ext-link>, the receptor for ANXA1, lipoxin A4 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/LigandDisplayForward?ligandId=1034" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">LXA
  <sub>4</sub>
 </ext-link>), and resolvin D1 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/LigandDisplayForward?ligandId=3934" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">RvD1</ext-link>), played non‐redundant roles in sepsis with exacerbated disease severity in the absence of the receptor (Gobbetti et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15164-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Below, we review the effects of the mediators of resolution in the context of experimental models simulating inflammation and infection in the lungs.
</p>
