<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Rabies has been present within the dog population of Ghana for decades 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001001-Belcher1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001001-Alonge1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Previously, control methods including dog vaccination and stray dog removal have been intermittent and not sustained. Unfortunately, as in several other developing African countries, rabies diagnostics within the Ghanaian veterinary services remains limited to non-
 <italic>Lyssavirus</italic> species specific staining techniques, including the Sellers' stain and fluorescent antibody test (FAT) 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001001-Dean1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Currently, only individual owners vaccinate their dogs for their (owner and dog) protection. Between 1970 and 1974, an average of 72 cases of canine rabies were reported annually throughout the country 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001001-Belcher1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Between 1977 and 1981 this number increased to over 100 cases annually, with an incidence of human rabies cases rising to 27 in 1981 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001001-Alonge1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Since 1981 there have been no further published reports of rabies in Ghana, and rabies viruses from the country have not been included in phylogenetic analyses of rabies in Africa 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001001-Talbi1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001001-Lemey1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. The virus is believed to cause disease in approximately 0–60% of those patients that are exposed depending on route of exposure 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001001-Cleaveland1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. Despite this, 123 clinically-confirmed human cases were recorded by public health officials between 2000 and 2004 (unpublished results). Moreover, ‘suspect’ human rabies cases are rarely confirmed using a laboratory-based diagnosis, relying solely on a clinical diagnosis 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001001-Mallewa1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>.
</p>
