<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pone-0093659-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093659.g004</object-id>
 <label>Figure 4</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Phylogenetic analysis of BDV sequences obtained from bicolored white-toothed shrews.</title>
  <p>A. 1824(P), C. 1110 bp nucleic acid sequences within the gene coding for p40 (N) of 14 BDVs obtained from naturally infected bicolored white-toothed shrews from Germany determined in this study (red diamonds), three Swiss 
   <xref rid="pone.0093659-Hilbe1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, 
   <xref rid="pone.0093659-Puorger1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref> (blue circles) and one Bavarian 
   <xref rid="pone.0093659-Bourg1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref> (purple triangle) 
   <italic>Crocidura leucodon</italic>-derived BDVs, and other representative BDVs mainly from spill-over hosts, which succumbed to BD. Evolutionary analyses were conducted in MEGA5 
   <xref rid="pone.0093659-Tamura1" ref-type="bibr">[72]</xref>. For tree 4A (unrooted tree, 63 nucleotide sequences) the Neighbor-Joining method was used. For trees 4B (76 nucleotide sequences, outgroup BDV He/80, oldest available BDV sequence of the region where BDV was first reported) and 4C (69 nucleotide sequences, outgroup BDV No/98, most distant mammalian BDV known so far originating from a location far away from the BDV endemic regions) the Maximum Likelihood method was performed. The percentage of replicates in the bootstrap test (1000 replicates) is shown next to the branches. Values less than 70% are hidden. Cluster 1: Southwest Germany and Southern Rhine valley group, 1A. Baden-Wurttemberg and Bavaria west of Augsburg (Swabia) as well as central Bavaria around Munich, Germany, 1B. Graubuenden and Sankt Gallen, Switzerland, The Principality of Liechtenstein, and Austria (south of Lake Constance); Cluster 2: South German group (major parts of Bavaria), 3. Southern Saxony-Anhalt and Saxony (mainly along and between rivers Saale and Elbe south of Magdeburg); Cluster 4: Central German group: Lower Saxony, northern Saxony-Anhalt, Thuringia and bordering Saxony-Anhalt (mainly west of the river Saale), northern parts of Bavaria, Germany. BW, Baden-Wurttemberg; HE, Hesse; LS, Lower Saxony; SA, Saxony-Anhalt; SX, Saxony; TH, Thuringia (Germany); GB, Graubuenden; SG, Sankt Gallen (Switzerland); L, Liechtenstein (The Principality of Liechtenstein).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pone.0093659.g004" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
