<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The first polysaccharide capsular antigen conjugated to a protein (PCV) was PCV7 (4, 6B, 9V, 14, 18C, 19F, 23F), which was introduced in the United States in 2000 for use in infants. Its introduction in Europe followed in 2001. With the development of PCVs, a new era in the prevention of infections due to 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> has begun [
 <xref rid="B67-vaccines-07-00168" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. However, despite being able to significantly reduce pneumococcal disease incidence, the first PCV, the heptavalent preparation (PCV7), quickly exhibited limitations. It was protected against 7 pneumococcal serotypes, considerably fewer than the total number of infective pneumococcal serotypes that circulate [
 <xref rid="B67-vaccines-07-00168" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Moreover, the composition of PCV7 was based on serotypes that most commonly caused invasive pneumococcal disease (IPD) in the USA [
 <xref rid="B67-vaccines-07-00168" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. However, other serotypes isolated more frequently in other countries meant PCV7 could be less effective than expected in some geographic areas. To address these limitations, a few vaccines effective against an increased number of pneumococcal serotypes were developed. Among them, those with 10 and 13 serotypes were licensed for use in humans. Both contained, together with the serotypes already present in PCV7, serotypes 1, 5, and 7F [
 <xref rid="B68-vaccines-07-00168" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-vaccines-07-00168" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]; in PCV13 serotypes 3, 6A and 19A were added [
 <xref rid="B68-vaccines-07-00168" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-vaccines-07-00168" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. A great number of studies have shown that both vaccines are immunogenic, safe, well tolerated and very effective because their contribution reduces the risk of pneumococcal diseases in vaccinated children and, increases herd immunity, for the unimmunized [
 <xref rid="B68-vaccines-07-00168" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-vaccines-07-00168" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>].
</p>
