<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to small molecules, monoclonal antibodies are an exciting class of medication, given their success in the treatment of Ebola virus.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>
 </sup> Antibodies are a natural part of humoral immunity and can be engineered to block specific ligands or receptors vital for viral function. These therapies generally need to be delivered intravenously to be successful. In the Ebola virus studies, for example, patients required one to three infusion sessions, depending on the antibody. A human monoclonal antibody was developed against SARS-CoV-1 and was demonstrated to be effective in a ferret model.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>
 </sup> Researchers have screened monoclonal antibodies designed against SARS-CoV-1 and have discovered cross-reactivity of at least one of the antibodies against SARS-CoV-2.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>
 </sup> Systems designs for the controlled extended release of antibodies may be advantageous over multiple infusion sessions for clinical practice. Nanoporous scaffolds coated with allylamine-based polymer were capable of releasing rituximab, a monoclonal antibody against B cells, for up to 30 days.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>
 </sup> Similarly, an alginate-based drug delivery system was able to deliver a human immunoglobulin G1 (IgG1) monoclonal antibody in a rat model for at least 28 days with a single dose of the system.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>
 </sup> In addition to the possibility of reducing administration to single dosing by extended release, there has also been development of ingestible injection systems to deliver biomacromolecules through autoinjection during gastric transit. These allowed for insulin delivery in a porcine model and may facilitate oral delivery of medications previously only efficacious in intravenous form.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
