<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0010">In late April 2020, alarming news emerged from Europe that a group of children with evidence of recent SARS-CoV-2 infection had developed a severe illness, manifesting fever, hypotension requiring inotropic support, severe abdominal pain, and myocardial dysfunction with marked elevation in cardiac damage markers. This syndrome has been named Pediatric Multisystem Inflammatory Syndrome in Europe, and Multisystem Inflammatory Syndrome in Children (MIS-C) by the U.S. Centers for Disease Control (CDC). As case series began to be reported, the similarities in the clinical features among the cases were striking, as were the frequent additional laboratory features of lymphopenia, thrombocytopenia, and cytokine storm with marked elevation in serum inflammatory markers including interleukin-6 (IL-6 )(1-6,
 <xref rid="bib6a" ref-type="bibr">6A</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib6b" ref-type="bibr">6B</xref>). Most of these children recovered, although infrequently patients have required extracorporeal membrane oxygenation, with a fatal outcome from complications of this therapy reported rarely (3,
 <xref rid="bib6a" ref-type="bibr">6A</xref>). Patients were managed in different ways, often with corticosteroid therapy, intravenous gammaglobulin, and, less often, anti-cytokine therapies, and the vast majority appeared to require intensive care therapy only for a matter of days, regardless of the management strategy (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib6a" ref-type="bibr">6A</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib6b" ref-type="bibr">6B</xref>). Some patients had one or more clinical features that can be observed in many illnesses of childhood including Kawasaki disease, such as conjunctival injection, oral erythema, and rash. Classic KD diagnostic criteria were rarely present. Moreover, the median age of the cases was 9-10 years in the largest series reported to date (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), which is in marked contrast to KD, which occurs predominately in children 
 <underline>&lt;</underline>5 years of age and with a peak incidence at ∼10 months of age (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Asian children have the highest attack rates of KD, whereas the highest rates of MIS-C have been in children of African descent (
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). These marked epidemiologic differences make it clear that the two conditions are not the same.
</p>
