<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0020">It is problematic that some similar clinical features of MIS-C and incomplete KD can lead to diagnostic uncertainty in individual patients. This scenario reminds me of my clinical experience in the late 1980s and early 1990s in Chicago when we were experiencing a different viral epidemic, due to measles. During that time, it was startling to see how closely the clinical features of KD resembled those of measles. Our approach at that time to differentiate the conditions was to perform a measles IgM antibody test, run daily in our hospital during the epidemic, and if the test was negative, treat the patient for KD. Measles is one of the few infectious diseases that virtually always is symptomatic, so a positive test result confirmed the diagnosis. The present COVID-19 epidemic does not offer such a straightforward solution to the diagnostic dilemma. Not only is there no diagnostic test for KD at present, but asymptomatic or mildly symptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection is prevalent enough in children in many areas of the U.S. and abroad at the present time that even a positive RT-PCR or serologic test for SARS-CoV-2 antibody does not necessarily mean that a child’s presenting illness is related to SARS-CoV-2. With routine RT-PCR screening of hospitalized patients, we find occasional positive results in children admitted with fractures, for routine surgical procedures, and with a variety of other clinical problems not related to SARS-CoV-2 infection. In addition, antibody positivity is very likely to be increasing over time in the population. Understandably, diagnostic confusion can result, and incorrect diagnoses may be assigned. To add to this confusion, some patients with MIS-C are reported to have developed mild coronary artery dilation (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) or rarely, aneurysms (
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). That mild transient coronary artery dilation can develop as a result of cytokine storm with high IL-6 levels has been demonstrated in systemic onset juvenile idiopathic arthritis (
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), and mild transient coronary dilation could be the result of a similar cytokine storm in MIS-C. Persistent coronary artery aneurysms and their complications, however, have previously only been attributed to KD in pediatric patients. Because of the clinical similarities in the two conditions, it is possible that patients reported as having MIS-C with persisting aneurysms actually had KD. Fortunately, patients with KD and MIS-C both improve with intravenous gammaglobulin and corticosteroid therapy, although the efficacy of any therapy for MIS-C is evolving and is as yet is unproven. If SARS-CoV-2 can result in persisting coronary artery aneurysms, it would be noteworthy, as it would be the first virus proved to do so.
</p>
