<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The 
 <italic>Morbillivirus</italic> genus comprises well known pathogens of terrestrial mammals including measles virus (MV) a pathogen of humans and primates, rinderpest virus (RPV) and peste des petits ruminants (PPRV) both pathogens of ungulates and CDV a pathogen of carnivores [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. A recently identified virus in cats has been proposed as a new morbillivirus of domestic felines, feline morbillivirus (FmoPV) [
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Although this virus has the same gene organization as morbilliviruses, its pathological and molecular biological features are quite different from those of the conventional morbilliviruses. Among marine mammals, cetaceans (whales, dolphins and porpoises) may be infected by the recently recognized cetacean morbillivirus (CeMV) in which a number of strains are now recognized globally including dolphin morbillivirus (DMV), porpoise morbillivirus (PMV) and pilot whale morbillivirus (PWMV) [
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Although not a subject of this review, CDV from terrestrial hosts has caused epidemics among land-locked Baikal seals and Caspian seals (
 <italic>P. caspica</italic>) since the late 1980s [
 <xref rid="B1-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The morbillivirus genome is comprised of a non-segmented, negative-sense, single stranded RNA that varies from 15,500 to 16,050 nucleotides in length and contains six transcription units that encode six structural proteins: nucleocapsid (N), phosphoprotein (P), matrix (M) protein, fusion (F) glycoprotein, hemagglutinin (H) glycoprotein, and the major component of the RNA-dependent RNA polymerase, the large (L) protein. Two non-structural proteins (C and V) sometimes termed virulence factors that interfere with the innate immune response and affect infectivity, are also expressed in infected cells. Preliminary genetic characterization of PDV isolates from the 1988 epidemic using cDNA probes confirmed its membership in the 
 <italic>Morbillivirus</italic> genus as a novel species [
 <xref rid="B5-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Phylogenies of morbilli and paramyxoviruses based on partial [
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], and more recently, complete gene sequences [
 <xref rid="B36-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] consistently place all PDV strains as a monophyletic sister clade to CDV across all genes. Recent evidence points to bats as a potential source of significant paramyxovirus diversity, with some taxa clustering with the CDV/PDV group [
 <xref rid="B37-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Host jumping appears to be relatively common in the 
 <italic>Paramyxovirinae</italic>, and morbilli-like viruses are found in diverse mammals [
 <xref rid="B38-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Final confirmation of the unique identity of PDV was achieved with full genome sequencing using a 1988 isolate in Vero cells expressing the canine receptor CD150 [
 <xref rid="B39-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The genome was 15,696 nucleotides in length with the typical six non-overlapping morbillivirus genes in the order N-P/V/C-M-F-H-L [
 <xref rid="B39-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Like all other morbilliviruses it obeys the rule of six [
 <xref rid="B40-viruses-06-05093" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].
</p>
