<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Progress has been made by identifying several compounds that aid in the treatment of viral infections and besides the treatment of humans, these are used by farmers to protect their flocks [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. However, concerns arose about the increasing incidence of resistance to antiviral drugs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Several causes have been suggested including the inappropriate use of antiviral drugs in the treatment of humans during the outbreaks of avian influenza and severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Furthermore, it has been shown that oseltamivir carboxylate (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) is not removed or degraded in normal sewage water treatment and thus enters the environment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Waterfowl are then in a position to ingest the active oseltamivir carboxylate. This could drive the selection of resistant avian influenza A strains in the gut. Especially in countries (e.g. Southeast Asia) where waterfowl and humans come in close contact, this could lead to the spread of other strains incorporating the resistance genes and change of host [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Finally, amantadine, oseltamivir and arbidol (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) are allegedly being administered to poultry and other livestock in China, Southeast Asia and Russia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. To prevent excessive use of antiviral drugs the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) prohibited the non-consistent use of two types of antiviral drugs in chickens, turkeys and ducks: the amantadines, including amantadine and rimantadine, and the neuramidase inhibitors, including zanamivir and oseltamivir (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].
</p>
