<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Arboviruses (Arbo = ARthropod-BOrne) are a diverse group of viruses that are transmitted by arthropod vectors, most commonly by insects such as mosquitoes and blood-feeding flies, or arachnids such as ticks. With the exception of African swine fever virus, a DNA virus, all arboviruses are RNA viruses and belong to one of six viral families: 
 <italic>Bunyaviridae</italic> (e.g., Rift Valley fever virus), 
 <italic>Reoviridae</italic> (e.g., Bluetongue virus), 
 <italic>Orthomyxoviridae</italic> (e.g., Bourbon virus), 
 <italic>Rhabdoviridae</italic> (e.g., vesicular stomatitis virus), 
 <italic>Togaviridae</italic> (e.g., equine encephalitis and chikungunya viruses), or 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic> (e.g., tick-borne encephalitis, dengue, Japanese encephalitis, West Nile, Zika, and yellow fever viruses) (Hanley and Weaver, 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Flaviviruses pose a major human threat, and the world's population is at risk of infection with several flaviviruses: In the United States, West Nile virus (WNV) is the leading cause of arbovirus infections (Lindsey et al., 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) and caused over 2,000 confirmed cases in 2017 (ArboNET, 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Zika virus (ZIKV), while previously considered a minimal threat to human health, is now present in over 30 countries (Tham et al., 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Additionally, over 40% of the world's population is at risk for dengue virus (DENV) infection (Jindal et al., 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). All of these flaviviruses can cause severe complications in human patients: two-thirds of West Nile virus cases are classified as neuroinvasive, Zika virus is associated with Guillain-Barré syndrome and microcephaly, and dengue virus causes hemorrhagic fever in 500,000 patients annually. There are no post-exposure therapeutics available for any flavivirus and no approved vaccines other than for yellow fever and Japanese encephalitis viruses, indicating an unmet need in medicine. Moreover, diabetic individuals are at a higher risk for contracting West Nile virus disease (Nash et al., 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). Flavivirus infection is only expected to increase, due to climate change affecting the geographical ranges of the mosquito vectors (Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Kraemer et al., 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Thus, it is imperative that current research investigates the both the immune response to and pathogenesis of these arboviral infections. The purpose of this research topic is to provide a platform for the dissemination of high-quality primary research articles, comprehensive reviews, and opinions that explore the host responses to arboviral infections. Serendipitously, each of the five review articles published in our research topic nicely introduces one of the five primary research articles, and our topic includes an opinion article that discusses flaviviral vaccine development, which suitably ties together the research topic.
</p>
