<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0007">CRS is a potentially life-threatening, non–antigen-specific toxicity that has been described following use of bispecific antibodies such as blinatumomab, chimeric antigen receptor (CAR)-T cell therapy and other immune therapies including but not limited to anti-thymocyte globulin (ATG) rituximab, alemtuzumab and nivolumab. CRS is one of the two most common treatment-related adverse events observed after CAR-T cell therapy; as such, identification, grading and treatment of this complication has been well described in recent years [
 <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. To harmonize the definitions and grading systems for CRS and neurotoxicity, consensus recommendations were recently implemented by the American Society for Transplantation and Cellular Therapy 
 <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref> (
 <xref rid="tbl0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The clinical manifestations of CRS have variable timing and can range from mild to life-threatening. The onset of CRS may be within hours after therapeutic antibody therapy and resolve within days. In contrast, the typical course of CRS after CAR-T infusion, is 1 to 14 days (median, 2–3 days), and resolution is expected within a few days to weeks. CRS manifests with fever, tachycardia, hypotension, respiratory distress or hypoxemia and is associated with elevated circulating levels of several cytokines including IL-6 and interferon-γ 
 <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. In general, the degree of cytokine activation correlates with the severity of the clinical picture. Other laboratory findings are variable and reflect systemic inflammation. sHLH/macrophage activation syndrome (MAS) is a syndrome of excessive inflammation and tissue destruction with overlapping features of CRS. In adults, sHLH is most commonly triggered by viral infections. sHLH is characterized by T-cell-mediated inflammation, fulminant cytokine storm, ferritin elevation and multi-organ failure. The HLH diagnostic criteria is based on the HLH Study Group of the Histiocyte Society 2004 description of the combination of five of the following eight characteristics (
 <xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> ): fever, splenomegaly, cytopenias, hypertriglyceridemia, hypofibrinogenemia, high ferritin, hemophagocytosis, low/absent NK-cell activity and high soluble IL-2 receptor. CRS and sHLH/MAS have many features in common, as each reflects the activation of the reticuloendothelial system initiated by T-cell-mediated inflammation. In the CAR-T literature, most patients with moderate to severe CRS meet criteria for HLH/MAS with or without organomegaly, lymphadenopathy or evident hemophagocytosis. Patients may meet some of the criteria for HLH/MAS after CAR-T-cell infusion, but this may also reflect CRS 
 <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Importantly, the clinical and cytokine profile suggestive of HLH/MAS resolve with CRS resolution; therefore, primary amelioration of CRS with targeted cytokine biologics may be sufficient without using specific HLH pharmacotherapies 
 <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. A retrospective study of COVID-19 patients found that elevated serum ferritin and IL-6 correlated with increased mortality 
 <xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>.
</p>
