<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21">We recently showed that the 
 <italic>w</italic>AlbB strain was able to block CHIKV infection in 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> C6/36 cell lines relative to uninfected cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. This is in line with observations in all studies using cellular models [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>], suggesting that viral inhibition is common in such simplified systems, possibly due in part to the proximity of the interacting partners. Thus, cellular models could represent interesting systems to decipher the mechanisms involved in the tripartite interactions between 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic>, arboviruses and host cells. Both naturally and artificially 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-infected 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> cell lines have shown changes in the expression of several genes involved in structural, metabolic and stress functions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. On the other hand CHIKV was reported to activate cellular functions necessary for infection and persistence [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. However, no molecular mechanism for the interplay between 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic> and CHIKV in 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> has been proposed to date. Therefore, in this study we used proteome profiling of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> C6/36 cell lines to discover how 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-infected cells reacted when challenged with CHIKV. Two-dimensional electrophoresis (2DE) followed by nano liquid chromatography and coupled with tandem mass spectrometry (nanoLC-MS/MS) showed differentially expressed proteins likely belonging to diverse processes of glycolysis, protein metabolism, protein modification and amino acid metabolism. Overall, the innovative proteomic approach used in this descriptive work provided potential candidates involved in the tripartite interaction between mosquito-CHIKV-
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic>. Future investigation will focus on the functional studies to validate the more promising candidates implicated in cellular processes that mediated the interplay between microbes.
</p>
