<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21">In this research, we identified a new BLV genotype, G11, by the maximum likelihood algorithm method. In fact, the neighbor-joining method was also performed to conduct the phylogenetic analysis and cluster the G11 isolates into a unique branch (data not shown). The amino acid alignment presented more information about the new G11 isolates. In the ND2/ZB, when aligned with those of G1-G10, we identified a particular motif in our two G11 isolates (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). We observed that the clustered variation sites T-X-D-X-R-XXXX-A (T131/D133/R135/A140) together were unique in G11 and absent in the GenBank-recorded G1-G10 BLV env sequences (Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1). The precise factors that led to this unique motif in G11 were unclear. Regardless, this motif was located in the ND2 domain and thus was possibly related to the host humoral immune responses in vivo. This motif indeed defined the genotypical features of the new G11. A recent report indicated that several residues of gp51 were under positive selection, including residues 48, 74, 82, 133, 142, and 291 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>], which could be correlated with viral immune escape in vivo. However, in our present study, only the variation site of residue 133 was monitored, which was located within the G11 T-X-D (133)-X-R-XXXX-A motif. Considering these characteristics of G11, we thus aimed to test the G11 Env infectivity. Unfortunately, we failed to acquire the G11 full-length env gene, which blocked us from further confirming its infection capacity. G11 isolates E101/E102 and G6 isolates E110/E112/E119 were derived from the same farm but diverged into two genotypes. By aligning E101 and E110 amino acid sequences, as shown in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, we could readily identify a variation in the four residues in the G11 ND2/ZB and one residue in the G6 E-epitope region. Theoretically, a recombination potential exists between the differential G6 and G11 isolates, for both genotypical isolates coexisted on one farm. However, we still have not identified isolates that inherit the variation sites of both G6 and G11 together. Provided that recombination between G6 and G11 occurs, such an event may give rise to new BLV genotypes or subgenotypes, which is an interesting issue for further study.
</p>
