<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8">As countries enact policies to slow the spread of COVID-19, unintended consequences for health systems have been observed, particularly for vulnerable populations including people living with HIV. In Kenya, barriers across the HIV care cascade have impacted aPS provision and general HIV services. Reductions in clinic volume can result in fewer individuals diagnosed with HIV. This is concerning since identification of index clients through clinic-based testing is the backbone of successful aPS programs as indexes provide information used to trace HIV-exposed partners. In addition, community-based HIV testing strategies have increased testing coverage, particularly among men and those without regular healthcare access.[
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] As aPS staff are no longer conducing field tracing and community-based HIV testing, numbers of male partners tested will likely further decline, leading to poorer clinical outcomes and increased transmission. Additionally, reductions in counseling provision could impact initiation and retention on ART. Potential interventions include offering HIVST to indexes to give to their partners, or providing HIVST kits directly to partners who are reluctant to visit the clinic. In accordance with national guidelines, many clinics have started HIV self-test (HIVST) distribution, focusing on partners of pregnant/breastfeeding women, key populations, along with some targeted clinic-based HIVST to reduce patient waiting time. However, HIV testing outcomes and linkage to care following HIVST has been difficult to document, as is common with HIVST strategies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] . Further, providing transport reimbursements for clinic visits may increase the number of partners reached with testing. As more COVID-19 cases are confirmed in Kenya, health services disruptions will likely become more severe. Continuing to assess the pandemic’s impact on health services is crucial to informing strategies to reduce service disruption and maintain the progress made thus far in controlling the HIV epidemic.
</p>
