<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Neuroimmunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Neuroimmunol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Neuroimmunology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0165-5728</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1872-8421</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier B.V.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7305747</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S0165-5728(20)30333-7</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jneuroim.2020.577294</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">577294</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Guillain-Barr&#x000e9; syndrome in a patient infected with SARS-CoV-2, a case report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name><surname>Farzi</surname><given-names>Mohammad Amin</given-names></name><email>farzi.neuro@gmail.com</email><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cr0005" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0010"><name><surname>Ayromlou</surname><given-names>Hormoz</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0015"><name><surname>Jahanbakhsh</surname><given-names>Naser</given-names></name><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0020"><name><surname>Bavil</surname><given-names>Parisa Hadavi</given-names></name><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0025"><name><surname>Janzadeh</surname><given-names>Abdolali</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0030"><name><surname>Shayan</surname><given-names>Farid Karkon</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><aff id="af0005"><label>a</label>Tabriz University of Medical Sciences, Iran</aff><aff id="af0010"><label>b</label>Urmia University of Medical Sciences, Iran</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cr0005"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author at: Tabriz University of Medical Sciences, 5166614756 Tabriz, Iran. <email>farzi.neuro@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>346</volume><fpage>577294</fpage><lpage>577294</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>12</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Elsevier B.V.</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="ab0005"><sec><title>Background</title><p>The COVID-19 is a novel condition affecting all the world, so every manifestation of disease should be reported. Neurologic manifestations of the disease are increasingly identified and this will help clinician to improve their diagnostic and therapeutic skills in dealing with COVID-19 patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Case</title><p>In this article we report a 41-year-old male that developed ascending paresthesia and paralysis following infection with SARS-CoV-2 virus. Electrodiagnostic evaluation in patient revealed demyelinating type polyneuropathy and patient diagnosed as Guillain-Barr&#x000e9; syndrome (AIDP type) and treated with IVIG which resulted in favorable response.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Considering this report and other reports that are mentioned in our short review, there is probably causal relationship between COVID-19 and development of Guillain-Barr&#x000e9; syndrome.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="ab0010"><title>Graphical abstract</title><p><fig id="f0010" position="anchor"><alt-text id="al0015">Unlabelled Image</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="ga1_lrg"/></fig></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="ab0015"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="l0005"><list-item id="li0005"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0005">The COVID-19 affects both peripheral and central nervous system</p></list-item><list-item id="li7005"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p7005">Probably there is causal relationship between Guillain-Barr&#x000e9; syndrome and SARS-CoV-2 infection</p></list-item><list-item id="li6005"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p6005">Both demyelinating and axonal type Guillain-Barr&#x000e9; syndrome can occur in association with SARS-CoV-2 infection</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><kwd-group id="ks0005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd><kwd>Guillain-Barr&#x000e9; syndrome</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">The outbreak of novel coronavirus infection emerged on 2019 December in Wuhan, China and soon spread to involve all the world.</p><p id="p0015">Now the health care systems worldwide are facing with pandemic of severe acute respiratory coronavirus 2 (SARS-COV-2) and its associated disease, named coronavirus disease 19 (COVID-19). The identified symptoms of infection first thought to be confined to the respiratory system, but as the time passed extrarespiratory manifestations became increasingly identified.</p><p id="p0020">At first it seemed that the COVED-19 spares the nervous system and neurologic complications were among the manifestations later to be identified. Now we know that both central and peripheral nervous system may be affected by COVID-19(<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">Baig, 2020</xref>)(<xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">Mao et al., 2020</xref>). Involvement of central nervous system based on report by Helms et al. ranges from encephalopathy with agitation and confusion, and corticospinal tract signs to ischemic stroke(<xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">Helms et al., 2020</xref>). Peripheral nervous system is also affected by COVID-19, and several cases of acute polyneuropathy had recently reported.</p><p id="p0025">Here, the authors report the case of an acute and severe peripheral polyneuropathy associated with SARS-COV-2 infection.</p></sec><sec id="s0010"><label>2</label><title>Case presentation</title><p id="p0030">On April 15 (As of this date, 76,389 patients with COVID- 19 have been identified in Iran, of which 4777 deaths have been occurred by the virus, and according to statistics, Iran ranks sixth in the number of deaths due to COVID- 19) a 41-year-old male was referred to emergency department for acute onset of cough, dyspnea, and fever. Regarding symptom profile and chest CT scan findings (obtained same day) of multiple ground glass opacities and consolidations, typical of COVID-19 pneumonia (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
) the patient diagnosed as COVID-19 and was admitted to hospital. At the time of admission, the patient was febrile with an oral temperature of 39&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, the blood pressure was 110/70&#x000a0;mmHg, the pulse was 110 beats per minute and the respiratory rate was 22 breaths per minute. O<sub>2</sub> saturation was 88% on room air. His medical history included type 2 diabetes mellitus under treatment with metformin and gliclazide. Laboratory data revealed lymphopenia (WBC:5.9&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>9</sup>/L, PMN:85%, Lymphocyte:15%), elevated levels of C-reactive protein (CRP: ++) and erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR:69&#x000a0;mm/h), glucose (280&#x000a0;mg/dL) and HbA1c (8.7%).<fig id="f0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Chest CT scan revealed a peripheral ground-glass opacity.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0005">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p><p id="p0035">The patient underwent treatment with antiviral agent lopinavir/ritonavir and hydroxychloroquine. Reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) assays of nasopharyngeal sample was positive for SARS-CoV-2.</p><p id="p0040">Ten days after onset of pneumonia the patient experienced paresthesia in feet which later days progressed to involve more proximal parts and mild weakness added, but these symptoms unnoticed until patient discharged 14&#x000a0;days after the onset of COVID-19 symptoms, following improvement of respiratory symptoms (probably because of attributing these complaints by treating physician to diabetic neuropathy).</p><p id="p0045">Seven days after onset of neurologic symptom regarding worsening of paresthesia and weakness the patient was referred for neurologic evaluation. In the first look at neurology office the patient was unable to stand and walk without assistance. The neurologic examination revealed normal mental status and speech. Motor examination showed absent muscle stretch reflexes in lower extremities and diminished reflexes in upper extremities. There was symmetric limb weakness (Medical Research Council score 4/5 at upper limbs and 3/5 at lower limbs), and symmetric and severe stocking-and-glove hypesthesia and reduced vibration and position sense at all 4 limbs (more pronounced at lower limbs). There was no cranial nerve deficit. Plantar responses were flexor. The patients complained of pain and an aching discomfort in the muscles, mainly those of the shoulder, hips, thighs, and back. There was no dyspnea, and cough if present was occasional. Electromyography and nerve conduction studies showed absence of right tibial and both peroneal nerves compound muscle action potentials (CMAP). F waves were unobtainable at lower limbs. Left tibial, Right and left median, and ulnar nerves distal latencies were markedly prolonged and velocities and amplitudes (with spatial and temporal dispersion) were decreased. All sensory nerve action potentials (SNAP) latencies were prolonged and amplitudes decreased (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table.1</xref>
).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Nerve conduction study parameters.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0010">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Nerve</th><th>SNAP Onset Latency(ms)</th><th>SNAP Peak Latency(ms)</th><th>SCV (m/s)</th><th>SNAP Amplitude (&#x003bc;V)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Right Sural</td><td>3.6</td><td>4.4</td><td>38.89</td><td>6.24</td></tr><tr><td>Left Sural</td><td>3.5</td><td>4.5</td><td>36.01</td><td>5.21</td></tr><tr><td>Right Median</td><td>3.83</td><td>5.5</td><td>36.6</td><td>4.48</td></tr><tr><td>Left Median</td><td>3.28</td><td>4.8</td><td>42.75</td><td>10.19</td></tr><tr><td>Right Ulnar</td><td>3.5</td><td>4.53</td><td>42.1</td><td>5.34</td></tr><tr><td>Left Ulnar</td><td>3.4</td><td>4.65</td><td>42.28</td><td>5.21</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="5">&#x02028;&#x02028;<hr/></th></tr><tr><th>Nerve</th><th>CMAP Distal Latency(ms)</th><th>CMAP Amplitude(mV)</th><th>Velocity(m/s)</th><th>F wave latency(ms)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Right Tibial</td><td>NR</td><td>NR</td><td>NR</td><td>NR</td></tr><tr><td>Left Tibial</td><td>12.43</td><td>0.1</td><td>31</td><td>NR</td></tr><tr><td>Right Peronal</td><td>NR</td><td>NR</td><td>NR</td><td>NR</td></tr><tr><td>Left Peronal</td><td>NR</td><td>NR</td><td>NR</td><td>NR</td></tr><tr><td>Right median</td><td>8.93</td><td>2.91<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>41</td><td>38</td></tr><tr><td>Left median</td><td>7.13</td><td>1.64<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>40</td><td>36</td></tr><tr><td>Right ulnar</td><td>7.14</td><td>4.2<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>41</td><td>35</td></tr><tr><td>Left ulnar</td><td>6.18</td><td>3.1<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>37</td><td>36</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Abbreviations: SNAP: sensory nerve action potential; CMAP: compound muscle action potential; NR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;no response; SCV: sensory conduction velocity.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf0005"><label>a</label><p id="np0005">Spatial and temporal dispersion.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0050">On needle EMG examination, no spontaneous activity was seen. Motor unit action potential (MUAP) morphology was normal, but with reduced recruitment in weak muscles including tibialis anterior, vastus lateralis, and iliacus.</p><p id="p0055">These findings were consistent with demyelination pattern polyneuropathy, so the patient diagnosed as Guillain-Barr&#x000e9; syndrome (GBS) associated with COVID-19, and at the same day admitted in hospital and treatment with IV immunoglobulins (0.4&#x000a0;g/kg per day for 5 consecutive days) was initiated. There was a favorable response to IVIG so the patient was able to stand and walk a short distance without assistance in day 3 of therapy. On discharge patient was ambulate but with some residual weakness in lower extremities, so was referred for rehabilitation clinic.</p><p id="p0060">Personal protective equipment was used during first examination and subsequent visits.</p></sec><sec id="s0015"><label>3</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0065">Guillain&#x02013;Barr&#x000e9; syndrome is considered an autoimmune process that affects peripheral nerves, and commonly manifests as demyelinating neuropathy with ascending paresthesia and weakness. Though the exact etiology and pathophysiology have poorly been identified, the syndrome is commonly preceded by a respiratory or gastrointestinal infection.</p><p id="p0070">Although various microbial agents and antecedent events including various viral illnesses in adults and children have been associated with Guillain&#x02013;Barr&#x000e9; syndrome, <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic>, Epstein&#x02013;Barr virus, cytomegalovirus, and Zika virus are among the most reported agents. There have been reports of an association between Guillain&#x02013;Barr&#x000e9; syndrome and <italic>Coronaviridae</italic> family viruses. For instance, during 2012 outbreak of Middle East respiratory syndrome (MERS) caused by MERS coronavirus (CoV) that shares many similar features with SARS-COV-2 a few cases of Guillain&#x02013;Barr&#x000e9; syndrome associated with infection had been reported(<xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p id="p0075">The occurrence of autoimmune polyneuropathy in patients with aforementioned viral and bacterial infections indicates that these agents have the potential of autoimmune response induction. In the case of <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> for instance molecular mimicry between GM1 gangliosides expressed on nerve fibers and lipooligosaccharides present on bacteria may account for their association with GBS.</p><p id="p0080">The same pathophysiology has been proposed for <italic>Haemophilus influenzae, Cytomegalovirus,</italic> and <italic>Mycoplasma pneumoniae</italic>(<xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">Koga, 2018</xref>)<italic>.</italic>
</p><p id="p0085">Considering these facts and based on prior knowledge of dealing with other viral epidemics we expected increasing number of reports on involvement of peripheral nervous system especially peripheral neuropathy in the era of COVID-19 pandemics.</p><p id="p0090">The first case of Guillain-Barr&#x000e9; syndrome associated with SARS-CoV-2 infection in the literature has probably been reported by Zhao et al. who reported the GBS as presenting syndrome in a 61&#x000a0;years old woman which later diagnosed as Covid-19(<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2020</xref>). Following this case other cases have been reported.</p><p id="p0095">Remarkable fact in some reports including reports by Aberti(<xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">Alberti et al., 2020</xref>) and Sedaghat(<xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">Sedaghat and Karimi, 2020</xref>) and in our case is that these cases share a common comorbidity, the diabetes.</p><p id="p0100">The interval of 10&#x000a0;days between the onset of viral illness respiratory symptoms and the first manifestations of Guillain&#x02013;Barr&#x000e9; syndrome in our case, is similar to cases reported by Galan(<xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">Gal&#x000e1;n et al., 2020</xref>) and Virani(<xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">Virani et al., 2020</xref>). This interval was 5&#x02013;10&#x000a0;days in case series by Toscano that is quiet the same as occurs during or after other infections(<xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">Toscano et al., 2020</xref>). Considering the temporal association, we hypothesize that there is causal relationship between GBS and SARS-CoV-2 infection, but there is no evidence of direct invasion of nerves or nerve roots by virus, as the CSF was negative for SARS-CoV-2 in patient reported by Alberti(<xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">Alberti et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p id="p0105">COVID-19 associated neuropathies are not confined to peripheral nerves as cranial nerve involvement as Miller Fisher syndrome have been reported(<xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">Guti&#x000e9;rrez-Ortiz et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p id="p0110">The important clinical point about this patient is ignorance of patient's compliant in COVID-19 isolation ward. The treating physicians of patients affected with COVID-19 should be aware of neurological complications of infection, and pay attention to every single symptom and sing in patients; because the disease is a novel condition and not every feature of it identified.</p><p id="p0115">We described this case as GBS but it should be kept in mind that our follow up period is short and acute-onset chronic inflammatory demyelinating polyneuropathy (A-CIDP) that accounts for 18% of CIDP cases(<xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">Bunschoten et al., 2019</xref>) should be in consideration as a differential diagnosis.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bi0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bb0005"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alberti</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beretta</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Piatti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karantzoulis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Piatti</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santoro</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vigan&#x000f2;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giovannelli</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirro</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montisano</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Appollonio</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrarese</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Guillain-Barr&#x000e9; syndrome related to COVID-19 infection</article-title><source>Neurol. Neuroimmunol. Neuroinflamm.</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/NXI.0000000000000741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0010"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baig</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurological manifestations in COVID-19 caused by SARS-CoV-2</article-title><source>CNS Neurosci. Ther.</source><volume>26</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cns.13372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32266761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0015"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bunschoten</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van den Bergh</surname><given-names>P.Y.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornblath</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Doorn</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Progress in diagnosis and treatment of chronic inflammatory demyelinating polyradiculoneuropathy</article-title><source>Lancet Neurol.</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(19)30144-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0020"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gal&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>del Saz Saucedo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Postigo</surname><given-names>F.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paniagua</surname><given-names>E.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Guillain-Barr&#x000e9; syndrome associated with SARS-CoV-2 infection TT - S&#x000ed;ndrome de Guillain-Barr&#x000e9; asociado a infecci&#x000f3;n por SARS-CoV-2</article-title><source>Neurol</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nrleng.2020.04.006</pub-id><comment>(English Ed.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0025"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez-Ortiz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000e9;ndez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigo-Rey</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>San Pedro-Murillo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bermejo-Guerrero</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordo-Ma&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Arag&#x000f3;n-G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benito-Le&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Miller fisher syndrome and polyneuritis cranialis in COVID-19</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.0000000000009619</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0030"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Helms</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merdji</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clere-Jehl</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schenck</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kummerlen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Collange</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulay</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fafi-Kremer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohana</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anheim</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meziani</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurologic features in severe SARS-CoV-2 infection</article-title><source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMc2008597</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0035"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heo</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>J.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurological complications during treatment of Middle East respiratory syndrome</article-title><source>J. Clin. Neurol.</source><volume>13</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3988/jcn.2017.13.3.227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28748673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0040"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koga</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimental approach in research of Guillain&#x02013;Barr&#x000e9; syndrome: a range of pathogeneses mediated by molecular mimicry</article-title><source>Clin. Exp. Neuroimmunol.</source><volume>9</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cen3.12457</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0045"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurologic manifestations of hospitalized patients with coronavirus disease 2019 in Wuhan, China</article-title><source>JAMA Neurol.</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaneurol.2020.1127</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0050"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sedaghat</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Guillain Barre syndrome associated with COVID-19 infection: a case report</article-title><source>J. Clin. Neurosci.</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jocn.2020.04.062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0055"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toscano</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmerini</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravaglia</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Invernizzi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuzzoni</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Franciotta</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldanti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daturi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Postorino</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavallini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Micieli</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Guillain&#x02013;Barr&#x000e9; syndrome associated with SARS-CoV-2</article-title><source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/nejmc2009191</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0060"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Virani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabold</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elrufay</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheema</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balaan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhanot</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Guillain-Barr&#x000e9; syndrome associated with SARS-CoV-2 infection</article-title><source>IDCases</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.idcr.2020.e00771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0065"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Guillain-Barre syndrome associated with SARS-CoV-2 infection: causality or coincidence?</article-title><source>Lancet Neurol.</source><volume>19</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(20)30109-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32246917</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>