<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par395">The cells in the brain identified to contain HIV-1 are:
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par396">Microglia</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par397">Macrophages</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par398">Multinucleated giant cells</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par399">Astrocytes (possibly)</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par400">Endothelial cells (possibly)</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par401">Oligodendrocytes (possibly)</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <title>Mechanisms of Brain Lesions</title>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par402">The development of brain lesions due to opportunistic infections and lymphomas might be explained by the lack of a competent immunologic defense system.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par403">One might assume that the changes described in Sect. 
    <xref rid="Sec14" ref-type="sec">26.5.8</xref> might result by direct infection with HIV-1.
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par404">However, it has been shown that neither neurons, nor astrocytes nor endothelial cells are infected with HIV-1.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par405">Thus, these changes more probably result from indirect toxic factors that are produced either by infected multinucleated giant cells or by activated microglia.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par406">Neuronal dropout occurs in brain regions
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par407">That are free from any neuropathological changes.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par408">Neuronal damage in AIDS was, at least, partly due to apoptosis.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par409">No correlation was found between the presence and severity of neuronal loss or of neuronal apoptosis and a history of cognitive disorders.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par410">No correlation between the presence of HIV-1 proteins and neuronal loss.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par411">The reactive astrogliosis was not correlated with the loss of nerve cells, indicating that this reaction pattern is rather a response to toxic factors secreted into the brain tissue.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par412">The number of activated microglia/macrophages is significantly increased in all brain regions. This activation of microglia is not correlated with the presence of HIV-1 antigen in the brain tissue. Activated microglia/macrophages, rather than MGCs, most probably secrete toxic factors.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par413">The neurotoxicity associated with HIV-1 infection is mediated, in part, through
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par414">cytokines</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par415">arachidonic acid metabolites</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par416">produced during cell-to-cell interactions between HIV-1-infected brain macrophages and astrocytes</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par417">Pathobiological events underlying the neurodegenerative processes in HIV-1-associated dementia are believed to begin with productive infection of monocytes/macrophages by HIV-1.
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par418">Peripheral activation causes the differentiation of macrophages to produce a variety of immune products that lead to the upregulation of adhesion molecules on brain microvascular endothelial cells and the expression of adhesins on the monocyte-macrophage cell surface.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par419">After penetration of the BBB, the differentiated brain macrophages and microglia can be vehicles for viral dissemination throughout the brain and focal reservoirs for productive HIV-1 replication.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par420">The neurotoxic events in the brain are caused by neurotoxins produced by these cells which are primed by HIV-1 and secondarily activated by factors such as immune stimuli or by T-cells trafficking through the nervous system.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par421">The primed and immune-activated brain macrophages/microglia secrete a variety of factors which affect neural and glial function and eventually lead to CNS inflammation.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par422">A pro-inflammatory cytokine response from blood-derived monocytes/macrophages, microglia, and astrocytes is amplified and leads finally to neurodegeneration.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par423">Immune neurotoxic factors may contribute to the breakdown of the BBB and affect the generation of chemokines, leading to transendothelial migration of monocytes into the brain perpetuating the inflammatory cascade.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par424">As a result of the neurotoxic activities of activated macrophages/microglia, astrocytes may suppress or increasemacrophages/microglia secretory functions and toxicity, depending on the astrocytic functional status.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par425">Cytolytic T-lymphocytes serve to eliminate infected cells, but are lost in late-stage HIV-1 disease, allowing the virus-induced, neurodegenerative response to continue unabated.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par426">Other factors include:
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par427">viral proteins</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par428">CA
       <sup>2+</sup> channels
      </p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par429">NMDA receptors</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par430">chemokines and cytokines</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par431">Expression of developmental proteins (Malik and Eugenin 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">2016</xref>):
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par432">Dickkopf homolog 1 (DKK1): upregulated</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par433">Rho-associated, coiled-coil containing protein kinase 2 (ROCK2)—upregulated</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par434">Low density lipoprotein receptor-related protein-associated protein 1 (LRPAP1)—upregulated</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par435">Low density lipoprotein receptor-related protein 5-like (LRP5L)—downregulated</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par436">Low density lipoprotein-related protein 12 (LRP12)—upregulated</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par437">Low density lipoprotein receptor-related protein 8, apolipoprotein e receptor (LRP8)—downregulated</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par438">Catenin (cadherin-associated protein), alpha-like 1 (CTNNAL1)—upregulated</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par439">Catenin, beta-like 1 (CTNNBL1)—downregulated</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par440">Catenin (cadherin-associated protein), delta 1 (CTNND1)—downregulated</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par441">Catenin (cadherin-associated protein), alpha-like 1 (CTNNAL1)—upregulated</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par442">Glycogen synthase kinase 3 beta (GSK3B)—downregulated</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par443">Wingless-type MMTV integration site family, member 10A (WNT10A)—downregulated</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par444">For more details, see (Zayyad and Spudich 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR158">2015</xref>; Singh 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR126">2016</xref>; Ru and Tang 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115">2017</xref>; Rao et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">2014</xref>; Malik and Eugenin 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">2016</xref>; Lamers et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">2016</xref>; Joseph et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2016</xref>; Chen et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2014</xref>; Carroll and Brew 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2017</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
