<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?OLF?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Clin Exp Hepatol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Clin Exp Hepatol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Clinical and Experimental Hepatology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0973-6883</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2213-3453</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Indian National Association for Study of the Liver. Published by Elsevier B.V.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7286271</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S0973-6883(20)30090-6</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jceh.2020.06.003</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>COVID-19 vaccines: A race against time in the middle of death and devastation!</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Khuroo</surname><given-names>Mohammad Sultan</given-names></name><degrees>MD, DM, FRCP (Edin), FACP, Master American College of Physicians (MACP, Emeritus)</degrees><role>Prof. Former Director, Professor and Head, Former Consultant and Head, Director</role><email>khuroo@yahoo.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Khuroo</surname><given-names>Mohammad</given-names></name><degrees>HSC (CBSE)</degrees><email>mkhuroo2003@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref><xref rid="fn2" ref-type="fn">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Khuroo</surname><given-names>Mehnaaz S.</given-names></name><degrees>MD (Pathology)</degrees><role>Prof.</role><email>mkhuroo@yahoo.com</email><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref><xref rid="fn3" ref-type="fn">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Sofi</surname><given-names>Ahmad A.</given-names></name><degrees>HSC (State Board of Education, J&#x00026;K)</degrees><email>ahmadsofi03@yahoo.com</email><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">6</xref><xref rid="fn4" ref-type="fn">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Khuroo</surname><given-names>Naira S.</given-names></name><degrees>Dr.</degrees><degrees>MBBS</degrees><role>Consultant Radiologist/Sonologist</role><email>naira_sultan@yahoo.com</email><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">7</xref><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">8</xref><xref rid="fn5" ref-type="fn">5</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Gastroenterology, Chairman Dept., Medicine, Sher-I-Kashmir Institute of Medical Sciences, Soura, Srinagar, Kashmir, India</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Gastroenterology and Liver Transplantation, King Faisal Specialist Hospital and Research Centre, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Digestive Diseases Centre, Dr. Khuroo&#x02019;s Medical Clinic, Srinagar, J&#x00026;K(UT), India</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Indian School Al-Ghubrah, Muscat, Oman</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Pathology, Government Medical College, Srinagar, Kashmir, J&#x00026;K (UT), India 190010</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label>Burn Hall School, Srinagar, J&#x00026;K (UT), India, 190010</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label>Fellowship Medical Imaging &#x00026; Radiology, KFSH&#x00026;RC, Riyadh, KSA</aff><aff id="aff8"><label>8</label>Digestive Diseases Centre, Dr. Khuroo&#x02019;s Medical Clinic, Sector 1, SK Colony, Qamarwari, Srinagar, Kashmir, J&#x00026;K (UT), India 190010</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label><bold>Corresponding author</bold>. Digestive Diseases Centre, Dr. Khuroo&#x02019;s Medical Clinic, Sector 1, SK Colony, Qamarwari, Srinagar, Kashmir, J&#x00026;K, India 190010. Tel.: +91 9906591044 <email>khuroo@yahoo.com</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p id="ntpara0010">Website: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.drkhuroo.com/" id="intref0010">www.drkhuroo.com</ext-link>, Facebook: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.facebook.com/mohammad.khuroo" id="intref0015">www.facebook.com/mohammad.khuroo</ext-link>; Twitter: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://twitter.com/Mohammad%20Khuroo%20mskhuroo" id="intref0020">Mohammad Khuroo @mskhuroo</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>2</label><p id="ntpara0015">Tel.: +968 93730786.</p></fn><fn id="fn3"><label>3</label><p id="ntpara0020">Tel.: +91 9906680006.</p></fn><fn id="fn4"><label>4</label><p id="ntpara0025">Tel.: +91 7889770991.</p></fn><fn id="fn5"><label>5</label><p id="ntpara0030">Tel.: +91 9906633966.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>2</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Indian National Association for Study of the Liver. Published by Elsevier B.V.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p>The COVID-19 has turned in to a global human tragedy and economic devastation. Governments have implemented lockdown measures, blocked international travel, and enforced other public containment measures to mitigate the virus morbidity and mortality. As of today, no drug has the power to fight the infection and bring normalcy to the utter chaos. This leaves us with only one choice namely an effective and safe vaccine that shall be manufactured as soon as possible and available to all countries and populations affected by the pandemic at an affordable price. There has been an unprecedented fast track path taken in Research &#x00026; Development (R&#x00026;D) by the World community for developing an effective and safe vaccine. Platform technology has been exploited to develop candidate vaccines in a matter of days to weeks and as of now, 108 such vaccines are available. Six of these vaccines have entered clinical trials. As clinical trials are &#x02018;rate-limiting&#x02019; and &#x02018;time-consuming&#x02019;, many innovative methods are in practice for a fast track. These include parallel phase I-II trials and obtaining efficacy data from phase IIb trials. Human &#x02018;challenge experiments&#x02019; to confirm efficacy in humans is under serious consideration. The availability of the COVID-19 vaccine has become a race against time in the middle of death and devastation. There is an atmosphere of tremendous hype around the COVID-19 vaccine and developers are using every moment to make claims, which remain unverified. However, concerns are raised about a rush to deploy a COVID-19 vaccine. Applying &#x02018;Quick fix&#x02019; and &#x02018;short cuts&#x02019; can lead to errors with disastrous consequences.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd><kwd>Coronavirus</kwd><kwd>Vaccine</kwd><kwd>Platform technology Clinical trials</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Authors Declaration</title><p id="p0010">None of the authors has any conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Contributions</title><p id="p0015">All authors have contributed to this manuscript equally and the final draft has been read and accepted by all authors.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Credit author statement</title><p id="p0020">Mohammad Khuroo: Conceptualization, Reviewing and Editing; Mohammad Khuroo and Ahmad Sofi: Data collection, software, schematic diagrams; Mehnaaz Khuroo: Writing and first draft; Naira Khuroo: Supervision, reviewing and editing.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Human and animal experiments</title><p id="p0025">No human or animal experiments were done for the study.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title><bold>Financial support</bold></title><p id="p0030">The work was financially supported by Dr. Khuroo&#x02019;s Medical Trust, a non-profit organization that supports academic activities and helps poor and needy for treatment.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0035">The coronavirus infection which originated from Wuhan, China in December 2019 has turned in to a global catastrophe (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). The virus has been designated as Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome-Coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) and the disease caused by the agent as Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). World Health Organization (WHO) pronounced the disease as a pandemic on March 11, 2020 (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). As of May 4<sup>th,</sup> 2020, the infection has spread to 212 countries and territories around the World and 2 international conveyances, with over 3.5 million cases and around two hundred fifty-thousand deaths (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). The disease on average affects over 33,000 individuals with over 1300 deaths daily. The world community has responded to the challenge of death and devastation with resilience and determination (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Governments have implemented lockdown measures, blocked international travel, and enforced other public containment measures to mitigate the virus morbidity and mortality (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). There has been a major understanding of the disease as well as the pathogen and these data have been generated and widely publicized in a matter of days and weeks rather than years and decades, an unprecedented occurrence in the history of medicine (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>Coronavirus Family</title><p id="p0040">SARS-CoV-2 belongs to a family of zoonotic viruses known as <italic>Coronavirus</italic>, genus <italic>Betacononavirus</italic> and is closely related to two other viruses namely Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus (SARS-CoV) and the Middle East Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus (MERS-CoV) (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). All three are bat viruses and cross over to cause human infection through an intermediate host (civets for SARS-CoV, camels for MERS-CoV, and possibly pangolins for SARS-CoV-2) (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Coronaviruses are enveloped viruses, around 125 nm in diameter, with a positive-sense single-stranded RNA genome of around 30kb and a nucleocapsid of helical symmetry. This is wrapped in an icosahedral protein shell. The surface has multiple club-shaped spikes, which creates the appearance of solar corona on EM. The viral envelope consists of a lipid bilayer, in which the membrane (M), envelope (E) and spike (S) structural proteins are anchored. All the coronaviruses use Angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) receptors as a cellular entry receptor, however, the propensity of SARS-CoV-2 to attach to these receptors is much higher, giving it high infectivity (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>Need for Coronavirus Vaccine</title><p id="p0045">There has been an intensive search for an effective drug against the virus or the resultant disease and has not led to any breakthrough agents. Few drugs namely hydroxychloroquine and Remdesivir have been advocated as desperate measures to fight COVID-19 based on a few preliminary, contradictory, and inconclusive studies (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). What we need is a drug that is at least 95% effective to stop the pandemic. These and other drugs may save lives but are nowhere near that power to bring normalcy in the utter chaos caused by the pandemic (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). This leaves us with only one choice namely an effective and safe vaccine that shall be manufactured as soon as possible and available to all countries and populations affected by the pandemic at an affordable price (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). A vaccine has the power to generate herd immunity in the communities, which will reduce the incidence of disease, block transmission, and reduce the social and economic burden of the disease. Very high immunization coverage can effectively fight the pandemic, prevent secondary waves of infection, and control the seasonal endemic infection outbursts. Eventually, the disease can be eradicated as has happened in many other diseases that have had even with higher potential than COVID-19 to cause pandemics namely smallpox, poliomyelitis, etc (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><title>Vaccine Immunology</title><sec id="sec9.1"><title>Adaptive Immune Response</title><p id="p0050">A vaccine is medical preparations ranging from intact organisms (attenuated live, or inactivated) to genetically engineered parts of the organisms (antigenic) that induce both arms of the adaptive immune system and stimulate a sufficient number of memory T cells and B lymphocytes (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Vaccines should contain antigens necessary to mount the specific response without causing disease. Once challenged with the pathogen, memory cells yield effector T cells and antibody-producing B cells and fight the infection. The antibodies have to be the neutralizing type which binds to the virus and block infection (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). The virus coated with neutralizing antibodies either cannot interact with the receptor or may be unable to uncoat of the genome. Most currently licensed vaccines to induce neutralizing antibody responses capable of mediating long-term protection against lytic viruses such as influenza and smallpox (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). The T cell-based responses that recognize and kill infected cells do also fight the infection (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Following antigen processing in dendritic cells, the small peptides are displayed at the cell surface at the groove of major histocompatibility complex (<italic>MHC</italic>) class I and class II molecules. Cytotoxic T cells (CD8 +) recognize MHC class I-peptide complexes and differentiate into cytotoxic effector cells capable of killing infected cells or pathogens. Helper T cells (CD4 +) recognize MHC class II-peptide complexes and differentiate in effector cells that produce preferentially T helper Th1 or Th2 cytokines (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>
). T helper cells 1 (Th1) support CD8 + T-cell differentiation, which is in contrast inhibited by T helper cells 2 (Th2) like cytokines. Vaccines against chronic pathogens namely <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>, malaria, HCV, HIV, etc more often require cell-mediated immune responses to control the infection (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>).<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig 1</label><caption><p>Schematic drawing of 8 platform strategies used for the development of COVID-19 vaccines and the pathway each one follows to induce T cell and B cell immune response. The strategies include Live attenuated vaccine (<bold>LA)</bold>, Inactivated vaccine (<bold>IA</bold>), DNA vaccine (<bold>DNA</bold>), RNA vaccine (<bold>RNA</bold>), viral vector replicating vaccine (<bold>VVR</bold>), viral vector non-replicating (<bold>VVNR</bold>), Virus-like particles (<bold>VLP</bold>) and subunit vaccine (<bold>Subunit</bold>). CV=Coronavirus, APC=Antigen processing cell.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Fig 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec9.2"><title>Vaccine-Preventable Diseases</title><p id="p0055">The success of a vaccine against a pathogen is a complex issue and depends upon the biology of the virus and the type of immune response elicited by the body against the organism. While vaccines have been successful against several pathogens including 14 major infectious diseases (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>), not all infectious diseases are vaccine-preventable (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). The development of vaccines against HIV and HCV have proved challenging. These viruses have an extreme genetic heterogeneity including the hypervariable regions (target for neutralizing antibodies) and the mutation contribute to immune escape (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). The mutations lead to a mixture of genomes in the patient over time and from patient to patient. Also, antibodies mounted against such viral infections are predominantly non-neutralizing. Neutralizing antibodies are often either absent or weak to fight the pathogen or neutralize only a narrow range of circulating viral strains and only appear in a subgroup of patients who either recover or are &#x02018;elite controller&#x02019; (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Another aspect to be considered is whether the virus can be grown in cell culture and transmitted to small animals for experimentation. Since HCV has been discovered by molecular cloning in 1989, its propagation in cell culture has been difficult which hampers the ability of investigators to experiment with various antigenic components of the virus (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec9.3"><title>COVID-19 Vaccine immunology</title><p id="p0060">To develop a safe and effective vaccine against COVID-19, we need to consider several things about the SARS-CoV-2 and the immune response against the natural infection and the vaccine.</p><sec id="sec9.3.1"><title>Mutations</title><p id="p0065">Does SARS-CoV-2 mutate, how fast and will mutations cause a phenomenon of immune escape as is seen in HIV and HCV (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). SARS-CoV-2 has shown mutations as is true to every RNA virus. However, the mutations are slow, mild and mutants show nearly similar sequences as in the parent strain. Dorp et al (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>) studied genomic diversity of SARS-CoV-2 and recorded 198 filtered recurrent mutations, however, most of the mutations were either neutral or even deleterious and of no clinical significance in vaccine immunity. Ahmad et al (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>) found no mutations in 120 available SARS-CoV-2 sequences and identified a set of B cell and T cell epitopes derived from the spike (S) and nucleoprotein(N) proteins that map identically to SARS-CoV-2 proteins. These findings provide a screened set of epitopes that can help guide experimental efforts towards the development of vaccines against SARS-CoV-2.</p></sec><sec id="sec9.3.2"><title>COVID-19 Immune Response</title><p id="p0070">What type of immune response occurs in natural COVID-19 and after vaccination and are antibodies neutralizing in nature? SARS-CoV-2 infection evokes a robust adaptive immune response of both T cell and B cell type arms (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Furthermore, both IgM and IgG antibodies appear around the 10<sup>th</sup> day of infection and most patients seroconvert within 3 weeks. The antibodies are raised against internal nucleoprotein (N) and spike protein (S) of the virion and have neutralizing activity (<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). Now that several candidate vaccines are in the clinical trial, investigators shall study the strength and nature of immune response against the vaccine antigen (mostly spike protein).</p></sec><sec id="sec9.3.3"><title>COVID-19 Re-infections</title><p id="p0075">Are people who recover from COVID-19 infection protected from a second or a third infection? Should re-infections occur it would imply that immune response against SARS-CoV-2 is not protective, making possibilities of a successful vaccine difficult. There were scary reports from South Korea about patients thought to have recovered from COVID-19 had tested positive again (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). An intense debate started about re-activation or re-infections of the virus. Soon these reports were put to rest and the positive sample were found to be residual dead fragments of the virus, not the virus, which had re-activated or re-infected (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). After these reports, two groups of investigators have shown that SARS-CoV-2 antibodies are protective. Bao et al showed that 2 monkeys who recovered from SARS-CoV-2 infection were protected from re-infection on the challenge during convalescence (<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). Gao et al administered candidate vaccine <italic>PiCoVacc</italic> Sinovac Biotech to mice, rats, and non-human primates. The antibodies raised against the vaccine in animals showed neutralizing ability against SARS-CoV-2 strains. Three immunizations of two doses (3&#x003bc;g or 6&#x003bc;g per dose) gave partial or complete protection in macaques against SARS-CoV-2 (<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). These data are exciting and if reproducible in humans confirm that vaccines against COVID-19 shall be protective.</p></sec><sec id="sec9.3.4"><title>Duration of immunity</title><p id="p0080">For the COVID-19 vaccination program to succeed, the antibody response mounted against the virus/vaccine must be long-lasting. As of today, it is not possible to address this question as the virus has been in the community only for the last few months. However, we can take leads from data generated about the duration of immunity against 2 other coronaviruses namely SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Both these viruses, which are closely related to SARS-CoV-2 induce a robust T cell and B cell immune response which is long-lasting. Many candidate vaccines against both these viruses had gone through successful clinical trials and are safe and immunogenic (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec9.3.5"><title>Antibody-Dependent Enhancement (ADE)</title><p id="p0085">The greatest fear among vaccine developers is to create a vaccine that does not protect from infection but causes disease exacerbation, increased morbidity, and mortality (<xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Some vaccines can mount Antibody-Dependent Enhancement (ADE), which negates the basic purpose of vaccination (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). This response is mediated by the type of non-neutralizing antibodies mounted against infection or vaccination. The immune response to such vaccines is subverted, leading to exacerbated illness. This could be due to Fc receptor- or complement bearing cells-mediated mechanisms. The Fc-region of the antibody binds to FC&#x003b3;R on the immune cells, which subverts the immune response by reducing T<sub>H</sub>1 cytokines (IL2, TNF-a, and IFN-g) and skews T<sub>H</sub>2 cytokines (IL-10, IL-6, PGE-2, and INF-a) and inhibits STAT pathway leading to increased viral replication (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>
). ADE is of clinical significance in several viral infections including influenza, RSV, SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV, Dengue virus, Zika virus, and West Nile virus. Considering ADE is a major impediment to vaccine development, efforts to identify highly selected epitopes have been done to avoid the production of antibodies responsible for disease enhancement.<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig 2</label><caption><p>Schematic drawing depicting FC&#x003b3; receptor (FC&#x003b3;R) mediated Antibody-Mediated Enhancement (ADE). This response is mediated by the type of non-neutralizing antibodies mounted against infection or vaccination. The immune response to such vaccines is subverted, leading to exacerbated illness. The Fc-region of the antibody binds to FC&#x003b3;R on the immune cells, which subverts the immune response by reducing T<sub>H</sub>1 cytokines (IL2, TNF-a, and IFN-&#x003b3;) and skews T<sub>H</sub>2 cytokines (IL-10, IL-6, PGE-2, and INF-&#x003ac;) and inhibits STAT pathway leading to increased viral replication. <bold>STAT-A</bold>= Signal Transducer and Activator of Transcription protein-A, <bold>IRF</bold>= Interferon Regulatory Factor, <bold>INOS</bold>= Inducible Nitric Oxide Synthase.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig></p><p id="p0090">ADE has been reported in animals during vaccination trials with SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Vaccine candidates against coronaviruses based on full-length Spike protein induce non-neutralizing antibodies, lack of protection of animals against a viral challenge, and severe disease enhancement presenting as enhanced hepatitis, increased morbidity, and stronger inflammatory response (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). As of today, there are no reports of ADE with the use of COVID-19 candidate vaccines in non-human primates and humans (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). However, it is an early period in the development of these vaccines and as the matter is of major importance in the success of such a vaccine, we need to be vigilant. ADE following COVID-19 vaccination if reported can be prevented by shielding non-neutralizing epitopes of S protein by glycosylation or selecting critical neutralizing epitopes of the S antigen to elicit a more robust protective immunity.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec10"><title>Developing a Covid-19 Vaccine</title><sec id="sec10.1"><title>Stages of Vaccine Development</title><p id="p0095">Every new Vaccine follows a stringent protocol in R&#x00026;D which has to be meticulously followed and completed before it is licensed to be marketed (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>
). Regulatory authorities namely WHO, U.S. Food and Drug Administration (USFDA), the European Medicines Agency (EMA), and national authorities of many countries have issued guidelines relevant to the clinical evaluation of vaccines (<xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). The guidelines for vaccine development are more stringent than those meant for drug development. The reason for this is obvious, the vaccines are for global use, have enormous potential for production and marketing, and are given to healthy populations including children, elderly and pregnant mothers. The vaccine development follows a unique stepwise pattern and is broadly divided into Exploratory, Preclinical, Clinical, and Post-marketing stages. The clinical-stage is divided into 3 phases, namely phases I, II, and III. There are 2 regulatory permissions needed namely &#x02018;Clinical Trial Authorization&#x02019; before the clinical stage to allow &#x02018;First-in-human&#x02019; testing and &#x02018;Biologic Licence Application/Approval&#x02019; for the marketing of the vaccine after successful clinical trials (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
).<fig id="fig3"><label>Fig 3</label><caption><p>Schematic drawing showing steps in vaccine development. The vaccine development follows a unique stepwise pattern and is broadly divided into Exploratory, Preclinical, Clinical, and Post-marketing stages. The clinical-stage is divided into 3 phases, namely phases I, II, and III. There are 2 regulatory permissions needed namely &#x02018;Clinical Trial Authorization&#x02019; before the clinical stage to allow &#x02018;First-in-human&#x02019; testing and marketing of the vaccine after successful clinical trials.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3_lrg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The Vaccine Development Stages and the Process.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Phase</th><th>Aim</th><th>Features</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Exploratory</td><td><bold><italic>Develop a vaccine.</italic></bold></td><td>Research intensive phase.<break/>Identify synthetic or natural antigen.<break/>Develop a vaccine (natural or synthetic).<break/>Time: 2-5 years. <sup>&#x003bc;</sup><break/>The success rate to proceed is 40%. <sup>&#x003b4;</sup><break/>Causes of failure based on the nature of the pathogen.</td></tr><tr><td>Preclinical</td><td><bold><italic>The vaccine is safe and immunogenic.</italic></bold><break/><bold><italic>Evaluate the starting dose for human studies.</italic></bold></td><td>Subjects: Vaccine is studied in Cell culture &#x00026; animals.<break/>Design: toxicity and antibody response, challenge studies.<break/>Time: &#x0003c;1 year.<break/>The success to proceed is 33%. <sup>&#x003b4;</sup><break/>Causes of a failure-vaccine toxic or ineffective immune response, underfunding.</td></tr><tr><td>Clinical Trial Authorization</td><td><bold><italic>Allow human experiments (Application for IND)</italic></bold></td><td>The basis for authorization-Manufacturing steps &#x00026; analytical methods for vaccine &#x00026; placebo production,<break/>Availability and stability of vaccine &#x00026; placebo during clinical studies.<break/>Time: within 30 days.</td></tr><tr><td>Phase I<sup>&#x003b1;</sup></td><td><bold><italic>First-in-human testing. Vaccine safety and immune response.</italic></bold></td><td>Subjects: Healthy volunteers (20 -100).<break/>Site: vicinity of the tertiary care for close observation.<break/>Design: Escalation study to avoid severe adverse effects (SAE).<break/>Monitor: Health outcomes (clinical and laboratory) and antibody production<break/>Time: a few mon.<break/>Success rate to proceed 66 %. <sup>&#x003b4;</sup><break/>Caution: Follow strict go/no-go criteria based on safety and immunity data</td></tr><tr><td>Phase II<sup>&#x003b1;</sup><sup>&#x020ac;</sup></td><td><bold><italic>Vaccine safety, immunity/partial efficacy.</italic></bold><break/><bold><italic>Dose-response, schedule &#x00026; method of delivery</italic></bold></td><td>Subjects: Healthy volunteers (hundreds), may include a diverse set of humans.<break/>Site: Community-based (university, colleges, schools, etc).<break/>Study design: studied against a placebo, adjuvant, or established vaccine.<break/>Dose: Test vaccine in different schedules and a diverse set of humans.<break/>Monitor: Health outcomes (clinical and laboratory) and antibody response<break/>Partial efficacy data can be procured under circumstances.<break/>Time: 2yr.<break/>Success rate to proceed 30 %. <sup>&#x003b4;</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Phase III<sup>&#x003b1;</sup></td><td><bold><italic>Vaccine efficacy and safety</italic></bold><sup><bold><italic>&#x02260;</italic></bold></sup></td><td>Subjects: Target population (thousands).<break/>Site: Field conditions similar to future vaccine use.<break/>Design: vaccine randomized vis-a-vis a placebo, adjuvant, or an established vaccine.<break/>Monitor: Vaccine Efficacy and SAE.<break/>Time: many years.<break/>Success rate to proceed 70 %. <sup>&#x003b4;</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Biologic License Application</td><td><bold><italic>Marketing of vaccine</italic></bold><sup><bold><italic>&#x000a3;</italic></bold></sup></td><td>The basis for approval-The vaccine is safe and effective in humans (Efficacy &#x0003e;95%).<break/>Capacity to produce in bulk for market demand.<break/>Affordable cost to a susceptible population.</td></tr><tr><td>Phase IV</td><td><bold><italic>Postmarketting surveillance</italic></bold></td><td>Spontaneous reporting (Adverse Events Reporting System).<break/>Monitor: data collected by the end-users.</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tspara0015"><p>&#x02260;=Vaccine Efficacy (VE)=(Iu-Iv/Iu) x100= (1-Iv/Iu) x100= (1-RR) X100 %. (Iv=incidence in vaccine group, Iu=incidence in unvaccinated group, RR=relative risk).</p></fn><fn id="tspara0020"><p>&#x003bc;=Platform Technology has shortened time for vaccine production from years to days.</p></fn><fn id="tspara0025"><p>&#x003b1;=Clinical trials are rate-limiting in vaccine marketing.</p></fn><fn id="tspara0030"><p>&#x020ac;=Human challenge studies can be done in phase IIa in certain diseases where the challenge is ethical.</p></fn><fn id="tspara0035"><p>&#x020ac;=Phase IIb studies can provide data on efficacy in regions with a high prevalence of the disease in the community.</p></fn><fn id="tspara0040"><p>&#x000a3;=The cost of developing a vaccine from research and discovery to product registration is around US$ 1 Billion.</p></fn><fn id="tspara0045"><p>This figure includes vaccines that are abandoned during the development process.</p></fn><fn id="tspara0050"><p>&#x003b4;=The overall success rate for vaccine development is around 15%.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><sec id="sec10.1.1"><title>A race against time</title><p id="p0100">Given the above several facts about vaccine development are glaring. Vaccine development from the exploratory stage to marketing is a lengthy process and generally takes between 5 to 10 years. For the COVID-19 vaccine, this period is being substantially compressed by the use of modern platform technology to develop the candidate vaccine (pre-clinical stage) and fast authorization by regulatory agencies for clinical trials. It took Moderna Inc. (American biotechnology company based in Cambridge, Massachusetts) only 42 days from sequence analysis of the virus to create a new generation vaccine (mRNA-1273) at the Company&#x02019;s cGMP facility. This would have normally taken more than 2 years period without platform technology to develop such a vaccine. However, clinical trials &#x02018;that follow a unique protocol are &#x02018;rate-limiting&#x02019; and &#x02018;time-consuming&#x02019;. Here also, to respond to the pandemic, the investigators are exploring innovative methods of data collection. Many developers are running clinical trials in parallel (phase I-II) to shorten the time for approval. Some have started collecting data on efficacy from phase II itself (IIb). There is an intense debate on whether challenge studies are ethical in COVID-19, assessing the risk to a healthy volunteer (<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). If allowed and done, efficacy data on the COVID-19 vaccine shall be available in a matter of weeks rather than years. However, it will be dangerous to grant authorization without proof that the COVID-19 vaccine is immunogenic, effective, and safe.</p></sec><sec id="sec10.1.2"><title>Success Rate</title><p id="p0105">The second item which needs consideration is the success rate of vaccine development from clinical trial authorization to Licence. Typically, this rate was &#x0003c;10% during the period 2000-2010. A 2016 study showed that around 20% of vaccine clinical trials make up from phase I to license (<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). Of the 37 vaccines developed for the Ebola virus, only one was licensed based on efficacy and safety in the phase II trial. In the COVID-19 vaccine landscape, investigators have introduced a few new generation vaccines based on nucleic acid technology. Such vaccine technology is not in clinical practice against any infectious disease and experts believe the success rate of such a vaccine to get licensed is not more than 5% (<xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec10.1.3"><title>Costs</title><p id="p0110">It has also to be considered that vaccine development is a high cost and high-risk involvement (<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). Apart from competition between other major vaccine manufacturers, the cost of developing a single new vaccine against an infectious disease exceeds US $I billion. The figure includes vaccines that are abandoned during the development process. Here, given impending human catastrophe and global devastation, several Governmental and non-Governmental agencies have supported institutions with sufficient funds. The Coalition for Epidemic Preparedness Innovations (CEPI) is a foundation that takes donations from public, private, philanthropic, and civil society organizations, to finance independent research projects to develop vaccines against emerging infectious diseases. In March 2020, CEPI announced the US $ 2 billion to accelerate the development of the COVID-19 vaccine (<xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). Similarly, the US Government has agreed to pay $ 483 million to Moderna Inc. to develop the COVID-19 vaccine (<xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>). The Canadian Government has initiated a CA $ 1.3 billion innovation fund for vaccine research and development through 2022 (<xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec10.2"><title>Platform Technology-A gamechanger</title><p id="p0115">The technology behind the development of vaccines in Research and Development (R&#x00026;D) has seen a transformation in the recent past. Over the year&#x02019;s candidate vaccines were made through traditional methods of biotechnology. Because of this making of a prototype vaccine took between 2 to 5 years and was limited to a few types of vaccines. It needed the availability of cutting-edge research facilities to work with the infectious agent and was possible only in few laboratories over the globe (<xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). Recently platform technology has been employed in developing candidate vaccines (<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>). Platform technology offers several advantages in the development of vaccines which include automation, speed, ability to develop several prototype vaccines from the single system, cost-effectiveness, and developing among other complex mRNA vaccines with ease. It is believed that the mRNA-based vaccine developed by platform technology appears particularly promising in terms of ease of manufacture, adaptability to various targets, and biological delivery (<xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>). As candidate vaccines can be developed in a matter of days rather than years, the platform technology has been termed as a single game-changer in the fight against epidemics or pandemics caused by new agents (<xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>, <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>, <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>).</p><sec id="sec10.2.1"><title>COVID-19 Vaccine Platform Technologies</title><p id="p0120">Researches are trialing several designs to develop candidate vaccines against COVID-19. Overall, 8 types of designs, under 4 broad groups have been tried to develop candidate COVID-19 vaccines (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
). Each vaccine design has a subtle structure, advantages, and disadvantages in immunogenicity, safety, ease of use, and effectiveness (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>) (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>) (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Various types of vaccines categorized by the antigen used in the preparation.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Vaccine</th><th>Structure</th><th>Comments</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3">Virus Vaccines</td></tr><tr><td>Attenuated</td><td>Virus is weakened by passing through animal or human cells, until genome mutates and unable to cause disease</td><td>Inexpensive, rapid production<break/>Live vaccine, small chance of disease, replicates<break/>Needs cold chain<break/>Induces strong long-lasting T-cell &#x00026; B-cell immune response<break/>Good for attaining herd immunity in the community<break/>Vaccine in use: BCG, Smallpox, MMR, Chickenpox, Rotavirus, Yellow fever, Polio (OPV)</td></tr><tr><td>Inactivated</td><td>Virus inactivated with formaldehyde or heat</td><td>Non-infectious, cannot cause disease.<break/>Can be freeze dried, no cold chain needed<break/>Needs adjuvant for immune response<break/>Can cause T<sub>H</sub>2cell skewed response (ADE)<break/>Vaccines in use: Polio (IPV), HAV, Rabies. Hepatitis A, rabies, Flu.<break/>Candidate COVID-19 vaccine: PiCoVacc (Sinovac Biotech)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Nucleic Acid Vaccines</td></tr><tr><td>DNA Vaccine</td><td>Gene encoding antigenic components (Spike protein)</td><td>Safe, cannot cause disease.<break/>Yet unproven in practice.<break/>Can cause T<sub>H</sub>2 cell skewed response (ADE) when used alone.<break/>Highly immunogenic, generate high titre neutralizing antibodies when given with inactivated vaccine.<break/>Electroporation device needed for delivery<break/>Candidate COVID-19 vaccine: INO-4800 (Inovio Pharma, CEPI, Korean Institute of Health, International Vaccine Institute)</td></tr><tr><td>RNA Vaccine</td><td>mRNA vaccine for spike protein, with a lipid coat</td><td>Safe, cannot cause disease,<break/>Can cause T<sub>H</sub>2 cell skewed response,<break/>Yet unproven in practice<break/>Candidate COVID-19 vaccine: mRNA-1273 (Moderna/NIAID). BNT162 (a1, b1, b2, c2) (BioNTehc/Fosun Pharma/Pfizer)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Viral Vector Vaccines</td></tr><tr><td>Replicating</td><td>An unrelated virus like measles or Adenovirus is genetically engineered to encode the gene of interest</td><td>Safe,<break/>Induces strong T-cell and B-cell response,<break/>Vaccines in use: Hepatitis B, pertussis, pneumonia caused by <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic>, HPV, Hib (<italic>Haemophilus influenza</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td>Non-replicating</td><td>An unrelated virus like measles or Adenovirus (with inactive gene) is genetically engineered to encode the gene of interest</td><td>Safe,<break/>Need booster shots to induce long term immunity,<break/>No vaccine licensed yet Candidate COVID vaccine: Ad5-nCoV (CanSino Biological Inc./Beijing Institute of Biotechnology). ChAdOx1-nCoV-19 (University of Oxford)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Protein Based Vaccines</td></tr><tr><td>Subunit</td><td>Antigenic components (spike protein) are generated in vitro and harvested for vaccine</td><td>Safe,<break/>Need multiple dosing and adjuvants</td></tr><tr><td>Virus-like Particles</td><td>Empty virus shells with no genetic material</td><td>Safe,<break/>Strong immune response,<break/>Difficult to manufacture</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The Candidate COVID-19 Vaccines in Clinical Evaluation.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Name of Vaccine (Developer)</th><th>Candidate Vaccine (Platform)</th><th>Location</th><th>Current stage (participants)</th><th>Trial Quality</th><th>Status (completion date)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2">Ad5-nCoV <bold>(CanSino Biological Inc./Beijing Institute of Biotechnology</bold>)</td><td rowspan="2">Recombinant Adenovirus Type 5 Vector (Non-replicating Viral Vector)</td><td rowspan="2">China</td><td>Phase II (500)</td><td>Safety &#x00026; Immune response; Randomized double-blind placebo controlled</td><td>Recruiting (Jan 2021).</td></tr><tr><td>Phase I (108)</td><td>Safety; 3 different doses</td><td>Completed.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">mRNA-1273 <bold>(Moderna/NIAID)</bold></td><td rowspan="2">Lipid nanoparticle-encapsulated mRNA (RNA)</td><td rowspan="2">USA</td><td>Phase II (IND submission)</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>Phase I (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>)</td><td>Safety &#x00026; immune response; 3 arms (dose 25, 100, 250 mcg)</td><td>Recruiting (June 2021).</td></tr><tr><td>PiCoVacc <bold>(Sinovac Biotech)</bold></td><td>Inactivated SARS-CoV + Alum (Inactivated)</td><td>China</td><td>Phase I-II (144)</td><td>Randomized double-blind single centre placebo-controlled</td><td>Recruiting (Dec 2020)</td></tr><tr><td>ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 <bold>(University of Oxford)</bold></td><td>Adenovirus vector (Non-replicating Viral Vector)</td><td>UK</td><td>Phase I-II (510)</td><td>Single blinded randomized placebo controlled multicentre&#x02019; safety and efficacy.</td><td>Recruiting (May 2021)</td></tr><tr><td>BNT162 (a1, b1, b2, c2)<break/><bold>(BioNTehc/Fosun Pharma/Pfizer)</bold></td><td>Lipid nanoparticle-encapsulated -mRNA (RNA)</td><td>Germany</td><td>Phase I-II (196)</td><td>Safety &#x00026; immune response; Four vaccines, dose-escalation, parallel cohort</td><td>Recruiting (May 2021)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">INO-4800 <bold>(Inovio Pharmaceuticals, CEPI, Korean Institute of Health, International Vaccine Institute)</bold></td><td rowspan="2">DNA Plasmid Vaccine with electroporation (DNA)</td><td rowspan="2">USA, South Korea</td><td>Planning Phase II-III trials.</td><td>Safety and efficacy trial</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>Phase I-II (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>)</td><td>Phase I in South Korea in parallel with Phase I in the USA, completed phase I using 2 doses spaced 4 weeks apart.</td><td>Results June 2020</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0125">Live attenuated vaccine is developed by the process in which the live virus is passed through animal or human cells until genome mutates and is unable to cause disease. The weekend virus replicates like a natural infection and causes strong T cell and B cell immune response, which is long-lasting. Such vaccines are good to attain herd immunity in the population and block transmission of disease. However, there is a small chance of reversion of mutation to virulence and the occurrence of disease. Besides, such vaccines need a cold chain for distribution to the community. Examples of such vaccines are BCG, smallpox, MMR (Measles, Mumps &#x00026; Rubella), Rotavirus, Poliomyelitis (OPV), etc. Inactivated vaccines are treated with formaldehyde or heat and as the virus is killed such vaccines are safe and cannot cause disease. However, such vaccines do not replicate, cause a suboptimum immune response, and need repeated dosing and adjuvants to enhance immunity. Antibody-Dependant enhancement has been reported in such vaccines and to avoid this, we need to maintain the structure of epitopes on the surface antigen during inactivation. Examples of such vaccines include Poliomyelitis (IPV), HAV, Rabies, etc.</p><p id="p0130">Nucleic acid vaccines are the new generation vaccines, made available by modern technology. A DNA vaccine is made by inserting DNA encoding the antigen from the pathogen into plasmid DNA. RNA vaccines employ lipid-coated mRNA of the SARS-CoV-2 which expresses Spike protein. The expressed proteins are presented BY MHC class I to CD+ 8 T cells and inducing a strong T cell response. These vaccines are safe, easy to manufacture by the platform technology, and maybe gamechanger in the future of vaccines. As of today, there are no nucleic acid vaccines in clinical practice.</p><p id="p0135">Recombinant vector virus vaccines are producing through recombinant DNA technology. This involves inserting the DNA encoding an antigen from the pathogen into bacteria or virus vectors, expressing the antigen in these cells, and then purifying it from them (<xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>). During vaccination, the vector replicates and along with it the encoded DNA is expressed and processed, giving robust T cell and B cell immune response. Vectors may be bacteria like <italic>E. coli</italic> or viruses like Adenovirus or poxvirus. Classical examples of vector vaccines are HBV, HPV, Whooping cough, Hib, and Meningococcus.</p><p id="p0140">Subunit vaccines composed of purified antigen peptides of viruses like Spike protein of SARS-CoV-2 and are safe to use. Such an antigen is directly presented to MCH class II and often does not generate a robust cytotoxic T cell response (MHC class I dependant). Thus, such vaccines need repeated dosing and adjuvants to enhance immunity. Virus-like particles are made from empty virus particles without genetic material. Such vaccines are safe and immunogenic, however, are difficult to manufacture.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec10.3"><title>COVID-19 Vaccines Landscape</title><p id="p0145">There has been unprecedented fast track path taken in R&#x00026;D by the World community for developing candidate COVID-19 vaccines. As of 5 May 2020, the global COVID-19 vaccine R&#x00026;D includes 108 candidate vaccines (<xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>). The platform for 108 candidate vaccines are diverse and include live attenuated vaccine (n= 3), inactivated vaccine (n=7), DNA vaccine (n=10), RNA vaccine (n=16), replicating viral vector vaccine (n=12), nonreplicating viral vector vaccine (n=15), protein subunit vaccine (n=36), virus-like particles (n=6) and unknown (n=3). These platforms have been used in the past in 45 instances against a variety of infectious pathogens.</p><sec id="sec10.3.1"><title>COVID-19 Candidate Vaccines</title><p id="p0150">Up till now, several candidate vaccines have completed the exploratory and preclinical stage, obtained Clinical Trial Authorization, and initiated recruitment of volunteers for clinical trials (<xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>). Of these six candidate vaccines stand at the forefront of clinical trials (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><p id="p0155">
<italic>Ad5-nCoV</italic> from CanSino Biologicals Inc. is a recombinant vaccine using Adenovirus-vector. CanSino has an adenovirus-vector vaccine for Ebola (Ad5-EBOV) that is in phase II trials. Phase I trial has been completed on 108 volunteers; however, results have not been disclosed as of today. At present phase II trials are underway and CanSino plans to enroll 500 volunteers to evaluate vaccine safety and immunogenicity (<xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>, <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>).</p><p id="p0160">
<italic>mRNA-1273</italic> from Moderna is a lipid encapsulated mRNA vaccine and is undergoing safety and immune response phase I trial in Seattle. The company has filed for an IND to go for parallel phase II trials (<xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>).</p><p id="p0165">
<italic>PiCoVacc</italic> from Sinovac Biotech is an inactivated virus vaccine and is undergoing parallel phase I-II trials planned on 144 volunteers. Sinovac has partnered with US-based Dynavax. The vaccine produced neutralizing antibodies in mice, rats, and rhesus monkey which are protective in challenge experiments (<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>).</p><p id="p0170">
<italic>ChAdOx1</italic> from the University of Oxford is an Adenovirus vector-based vaccine and plans to run parallel phase I-II trials on 510 volunteers for safety and efficacy. The Oxford group has experience with candidate vaccine for MERS-CoV (ChAdOx-MERS) and has undergone a successful phase I trial for safety. The group is pushing ahead with an aggressive clinical plan and is talking of an emergency-use vaccine ready in September 2020 (<xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>, <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>, <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>).</p><p id="p0175">
<italic>BNT162 (a1, b1, b2, c2)</italic> from BioNTehc is another lipid nanoparticle mRNA vaccine and has received clearance from regulatory authority form Germany to the start of phase I-II trials on 196 volunteers. The trial is dose escalation design (1 to 100 mcg) using 4 vaccine subtypes (a1, b1, b2, and c2). The developers have claimed to have an emergency-use vaccine by September 2020 (<xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>).</p><p id="p0180">
<italic>INO-4800</italic> from Inovio is a DNA plasmid vaccine. The company has experience with such platforms with candidate vaccines for MERS and SARS. The vaccine needs a delivery system through electroporation, which shall add to the cost of the vaccine. Phase I trial using two doses spaced four weeks apart has been completed and results shall be available in June 2020. Inovio is planning to start phase II-III trials soon (<xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>).</p><p id="p0185">Numerous developers at present in the preclinical stage of vaccine development have indicated to procure &#x02018;Clinical Trial Authorization&#x02019; by the regulatory agencies and initiate &#x02018;First-in-human vaccine&#x02019; testing.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="sec11"><title>COVID-19 Vaccine in the Middle of a Pandemic</title><sec id="sec11.1"><title>A race against time in the middle of death and devastation</title><p id="p0190">COVID-19 vaccine development has thrown major challenges in vaccine R&#x00026;D (<xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>). The world is facing a major health catastrophe and economic devastation and one of the definitive solutions is to have an effective and safe vaccine in the shortest possible time. The global vaccine R&#x00026;D efforts have been unprecedented in history. The virus causing CVOID-19 has been sequenced in a few weeks. Ordinarily, it has taken from 5 to 10 years to clone and sequence a virus from the time the disease is discovered. There has been a tremendous race against time, to develop candidate vaccine in a matter of few weeks and as of now, 10 candidate vaccines have entered phase I-II clinical trials. It has taken us from 5 to 10 years in the history of vaccine development against other infectious agents to reach a stage as we are now with the COVID-19 vaccine. However, clinical trials as are undergoing now will be the greatest limiting factor, as these need time to acquire human data. Normally phase I, II, and III trials to be done on humans are completed between 2 to 5 years and sometimes more. This is necessary for qualifying a vaccine to be safe, immunogenic, and efficacious. As of today, candidate vaccines are undergoing phase I or parallel I-II studies and shall take several months for acquiring these data to start phase III trials. Phase III trial once initiated can take as long as 2 years. To compress the period vaccine developers are involved in adopting parallel and adaptive development phases (I-II) to acquire safety and immunogenicity data as soon as possible to initiate phase III trials. By any imagination, these data shall not be available by early 2021 for any vaccine for regulatory authorities to allow vaccine marketing. COVID-19 Vaccines could be available for human use earlier if innovative methods of clinical trials and regulatory processes are employed. One such is the use of &#x02018;Challenge studies&#x02019; to testify vaccine efficacy (<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). Here, following proof of safety and immunogenicity in phase I-II trials, controlled &#x02018;challenge studies&#x02019; which can be completed in a matter of weeks, are done to confirm vaccine efficacy. Challenge studies have been done in the past in other infectious diseases namely influenza, typhoid fever, cholera, and malaria. Whether &#x02018;challenge studies&#x02019; are ethical in COVID-19, considering the risk to the volunteer is a matter of debate before the vaccine developers (<xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>). Also, regularity authorities can use innovative procedures to allow guarded emergency use of a vaccine. This would need careful consideration of interventional animal safety data and data of safety, immunogenicity, and efficacy acquired from phase I-II trials. With all this, vaccine developers have to be ready to scale manufacturing capacity to massive demands once the product is allowed for marketing (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec11.2"><title>No &#x02018;Quick fix&#x02019; and &#x02018;short cuts&#x02019; please</title><p id="p0195">However, concerns are raised about a rush to deploy a COVID-19 vaccine. Applying &#x02018;Quick fix&#x02019; and &#x02018;short cuts&#x02019; can lead to errors with disastrous consequences (<xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>). What regulators have to worry about is the atmosphere of hype about the COVID-19 vaccine? Public claims about breakthrough research based on poorly conducted studies or data collected through fraud is a real possibility. All data which form the basis of any findings need to be scrutinized and should be confirmed by other investigators. Relaxion on regulatory principles based on political pressure and goodwill needs to be resisted and one needs to protect the interests of volunteers who are a part of such experiments (<xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>). Lastly, vaccine development is a risky process, and one critical issue in the COVID-19 vaccine would-be the occurrence of &#x02018;Antibody-Dependent Enhancement (ADE)&#x02019; which may be disastrous for those receiving the vaccine (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). Regulators have to take all precautions to discourage candidate vaccines which may show such a phenomenon.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec12"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="p0200">
<bold>Mohammad Sultan Khuroo:</bold> Conceptualization, Reviewing and Editing, Software. <bold>Mohammad Khuroo:</bold> Software. <bold>Mehnaaz S. Khuroo:</bold> Writing and first draft. <bold>Ahmad A. Sofi:</bold> Supervision, reviewing and editing.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gates</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Responding to Covid-19 - A Once-in-a-Century Pandemic?</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref2">WHO. Naming the coronavirus disease (COVID-19) and the virus that causes it.: World Health Organization, Geneva, Switzerland. ; [updated March 11, 2020. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/technical-guidance/naming-the-coronavirus-disease-(COVID-2019)-and-the-virus-that-causes-it" id="intref0025">https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/technical-guidance/naming-the-coronavirus-disease-(COVID-2019)-and-the-virus-that-causes-it</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref3">WHO. Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) Pandemic: World Health Organization, Geneva, Switzerland. ; [updated March 11, 2020. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019" id="intref0030">https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref4">Anonymous. Worldometer. Covid-19 Coronavirus Pandemic. The United States. : Dadax Limited.; 2020 [updated May 4th, 2020. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/?utm_campaign=homeAdvegas1?" id="intref0035">https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/?utm_campaign=homeAdvegas1?</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Legido-Quigley</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asgari</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teo</surname><given-names>Y.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oshitani</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are high-performing health systems resilient against the COVID-19 epidemic?</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>395</volume><issue>10227</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>848</fpage><lpage>850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32151326</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arun</surname><given-names>T.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coronavirus: Is there an alternative to lockdowns?</article-title><source>Economic Times</source><year>2020 April 20th</year><comment>2020</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref7">WHO. Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) advice for the public. Geneva, Switzerland. 2020 [Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/advice-for-public" id="intref0040">https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/advice-for-public</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref8">WHO. Updated WHO recommendations for international traffic in relation to the COVID-19 outbreak. Geneva, Switzerland. 2020 [Feb 29th 2020.]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/articles-detail/updated-who-recommendations-for-international-traffic-in-relation-to-covid-19-outbreak" id="intref0045">https://www.who.int/news-room/articles-detail/updated-who-recommendations-for-international-traffic-in-relation-to-covid-19-outbreak</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lockdown 2.0: How it impacts the ailing economy</article-title><source>India Times</source><year>April 16th, 2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 disrupts vaccine delivery</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shoenfeld</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Corona (COVID-19) time musings: Our involvement in COVID-19 pathogenesis, diagnosis, treatment, and vaccine planning</article-title><source>Autoimmun Rev</source><year>2020</year><fpage>102538</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32268212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebrahim</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>Q.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gozzer</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlagenhauf</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Memish</surname><given-names>Z.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Covid-19 and community mitigation strategies in a pandemic</article-title><source>BMJ</source><volume>368</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>m1066</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32184233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavanagh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The molecular biology of coronaviruses</article-title><source>Advances in Virus Research</source><volume>48</volume><year>1997</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9233431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Donaldson</surname><given-names>E.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baric</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A decade after SARS: strategies for controlling emerging coronaviruses</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><volume>11</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>836</fpage><lpage>848</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24217413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Assiri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Tawfiq</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Rabeeah</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Rabiah</surname><given-names>F.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Hajjar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Barrak</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiological, demographic, and clinical characteristics of 47 cases of Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus disease from Saudi Arabia: a descriptive study</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><volume>13</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>752</fpage><lpage>761</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23891402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zumla</surname><given-names>A.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Memish</surname><given-names>Z.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus: epidemic potential or a storm in a teacup?</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><volume>43</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>1243</fpage><lpage>1248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24627533</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yong</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>H.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeap</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>W.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recent Advances in the Vaccine Development Against Middle East Respiratory Syndrome-Coronavirus</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><volume>10</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1781</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31428074</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shereen</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazmi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bashir</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddique</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 infection: Origin, transmission, and characteristics of human coronaviruses</article-title><source>J Adv Res</source><volume>24</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32257431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref19">NIH. NIH Clinical Trial Shows Remdesivir Accelerates Recovery from Advanced COVID-19.: National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, Bethesda, MD, USA. ; 2020 [updated April 29th, 2020. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.niaid.nih.gov/news-events/nih-clinical-trial-shows-remdesivir-accelerates-recovery-advanced-covid-19" id="intref0050">https://www.niaid.nih.gov/news-events/nih-clinical-trial-shows-remdesivir-accelerates-recovery-advanced-covid-19</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yea</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Remdesivir in adults with severe COVID-19: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, multicentre trial</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>April 29, 2020</year><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doiorg/101016/S0140-6736(20)31022-9" id="intref0055">https://doiorg/101016/S0140-6736(20)31022-9</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rathi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ish</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalantri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalantri</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydroxychloroquine prophylaxis for COVID-19 contacts in India</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raoult</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsueh</surname><given-names>P.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rolain</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 Therapeutic and Prevention</article-title><source>Int J Antimicrob Agents</source><year>2020</year><fpage>105937</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32151714</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref23">Khuroo M, Sofi AA, Khuroo M. (2020): CHLOROQUINE AND HYDROXYCHLOROQUINE IN CORONAVIRUS DISEASE 2019 (COVID-19). FACTS, FICTION &#x00026; THE HYPE. A CRITICAL APPRAISAL... figshare Preprint <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doiorg/106084/m9figshare12177117v1.%202020" id="intref0060">https://doiorg/106084/m9figshare12177117v1. 2020</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref24">Gates B. THE VACCINE RACE, EXPLAINED. What you need to know about the COVID-19 vaccine GatsNotes The Blog of Bill Gates. 2020 [Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/Health/What-you-need-to-know-about-the-COVID-19-vaccine" id="intref0065">https://www.gatesnotes.com/Health/What-you-need-to-know-about-the-COVID-19-vaccine</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref25">Guarascio F. U.N. calls for the COVID vaccine, treatment available for all. Reuters Health. Brussels. 2020 [Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://in.reuters.com/article/us-health-coronavirus-eu-virus-un/u-n-calls-for-covid-vaccine-treatment-available-for-all-idINKBN22G1MZ" id="intref0070">https://in.reuters.com/article/us-health-coronavirus-eu-virus-un/u-n-calls-for-covid-vaccine-treatment-available-for-all-idINKBN22G1MZ</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Covid-19: Trump sought to buy vaccine developers exclusively for the US, say German officials</article-title><source>BMJ</source><volume>368</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>m1100</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32184216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref27">Anonymous. Vaccine-Preventable Diseases Australian Government. The Dept of Health. July 20, 2010. [Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.health.gov.au/news/health-alerts/novel-coronavirus-2019-ncov-health-alert" id="intref0075">https://www.health.gov.au/news/health-alerts/novel-coronavirus-2019-ncov-health-alert</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref28">Anonymous. Vaccines for Your Children. Diseases You Almost Forgot About (Thanks to Vaccines). Centre for Diseases Control and Prevention. 2020 [Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/vaccines/parents/diseases/forgot-14-diseases.html" id="intref0080">https://www.cdc.gov/vaccines/parents/diseases/forgot-14-diseases.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref29">Aryal S. Vaccines-Introduction and Types with Examples Online Microbiology Notes by Sagar Aryal. March 29, 2018. Updated April 9, 2020. [Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://microbenotes.com/author/sagararyalnepal/" id="intref0085">https://microbenotes.com/author/sagararyalnepal/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clem</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fundamentals of vaccine immunology</article-title><source>J Glob Infect Dis</source><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572612</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref31">Payne S. Chapter 6. Immunity and Resistance to Viruses. viruses: From Understanding to Investigation Academic Press. ; 2017. p. 61-71.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref32">Siegrist C-A. Chapter 2. Vaccine immunology. In: Plotkin S, Orenstein W, Offit P, Edwards KM, editors. Plotkin's Vaccines. 7th. ed. The United States. : Imprint: Elsevier; June 6th, 2017. p. 1-26.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Esser</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchese</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kierstead</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tussey</surname><given-names>L.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chirmule</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Memory T cells and vaccines</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><volume>21</volume><issue>5-6</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12531640</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Randal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis C vaccine hampered by viral complexity, many technical restraints</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><volume>91</volume><issue>11</issue><year>1999</year><fpage>906</fpage><lpage>908</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10359539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref35">Alcorn K. The search for an HIV prevention vaccine. [updated Feb 2020. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aidsmap.com/about-hiv/search-hiv-prevention-vaccine" id="intref0090">http://www.aidsmap.com/about-hiv/search-hiv-prevention-vaccine</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bankwitz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinmann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bitzegeio</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciesek</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friesland</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis C virus hypervariable region 1 modulates receptor interactions, conceals the CD81 binding site, and protects conserved neutralizing epitopes</article-title><source>J Virol</source><volume>84</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>5751</fpage><lpage>5763</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20357091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref37">De Rose R, Kent SJ, Ranasinghe C. Chapter 12 - Prime-Boost Vaccination: Impact on the HIV-1 Vaccine Field. Singh M, Salnikova M, editors: Elsevier Inc.; 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duverlie</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wychowski</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell culture systems for the hepatitis C virus</article-title><source>World J Gastroenterol</source><volume>13</volume><issue>17</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>2442</fpage><lpage>2445</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17552027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref39">Dorp Lv, Aeman M, Richard D, Shaw LP, Ford CF, Ormond L. Emergence of genomic diversity and recurrent mutations in SARS-CoV-2. . Infection, Genetics and Evolution doiorg/101016jmeegid2020104351. 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quadeer</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preliminary Identification of Potential Vaccine Targets for the COVID-19 Coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) Based on SARS-CoV Immunological Studies</article-title><source>Viruses</source><volume>12</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thevarajan</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>T.H.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koutsakos</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Druce</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caly</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Sandt</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breadth of concomitant immune responses prior to patient recovery: a case report of non-severe COVID-19</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><volume>26</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32284614</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref42">Braun J, Loyal L, Frentsch M, Wendisch D, Georg P, al. e. Presence of SARS-CoV-2-reactive T cells in 1 COVID-19 patient and healthy donors. . medRxiv preprint DOI: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doiorg/101101/2020041720061440" id="intref0095">https://doiorg/101101/2020041720061440</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2: virus dynamics and host response</article-title><source>wwwthelancetcom/infection</source><volume>20</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>515</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref44">Russel A. Can you catch coronavirus twice? South Korea reports 91 recovered patients tested positive. Global News. [updated April 10th, 2020. April 10th, 2020. ]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://globalnews.ca/news/6805414/coronavirus-south-korea-reinfection-canada/" id="intref0100">https://globalnews.ca/news/6805414/coronavirus-south-korea-reinfection-canada/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref45">Guzman J. No evidence of coronavirus reinfections, South Korean researchers say. South Korea&#x02019;s infectious disease experts said Thursday reports of coronavirus reinfection were likely testing errors. The Hill. Changing America. [updated May 1, 2020. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://thehill.com/changing-america/well-being/medical-advances/495646-no-evidence-of-coronavirus-reinfections-south" id="intref0105">https://thehill.com/changing-america/well-being/medical-advances/495646-no-evidence-of-coronavirus-reinfections-south</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reinfection could not occur in SARS-CoV-2 infected rhesus macaques</article-title><source>bioRxiy</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/20200313990226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid development of an inactivated vaccine candidate for SARS-CoV-2</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roper</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehm</surname><given-names>K.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SARS vaccines: where are we?</article-title><source>Expert Rev Vaccines</source><volume>8</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>887</fpage><lpage>898</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19538115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peeples</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>News Feature: Avoiding pitfalls in the pursuit of a COVID-19 vaccine</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>117</volume><issue>15</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>8218</fpage><lpage>8221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32229574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hotez</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corry</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bottazzi</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 vaccine design: the Janus face of immune enhancement</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref51"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Alwis</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ooi</surname><given-names>E.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of immune enhancement on Covid-19 polyclonal hyperimmune globulin therapy and vaccine development</article-title><source>EBioMedicine</source><volume>55</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>102768</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32344202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref52"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smatti</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al Thani</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yassine</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Viral-Induced Enhanced Disease Illness</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><volume>9</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>2991</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30568643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref53">WHO. Guidelines on clinical evaluation of vaccines: regulatory expectations. WHO Technical Report Series, No. 1004, 2017.Replacement of Annex 1 of WHO Technical Report Series, No. 924 Geneva, Switzerland. 2017 [Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/biologicals/expert_committee/WHO_TRS_1004_web_Annex_9.pdf?ua=1" id="intref0115">https://www.who.int/biologicals/expert_committee/WHO_TRS_1004_web_Annex_9.pdf?ua=1</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref54">(CHMP). CoHMP. Guideline on clinical evaluation of vaccines. EMEA/CHMP/VWP/164653/05 Rev. 1. The United Kingdom. [updated April 26th, 2018. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/documents/scientific-guideline/draft-guideline-clinical-evaluation-vaccines-revision-1_en.pdf" id="intref0120">https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/documents/scientific-guideline/draft-guideline-clinical-evaluation-vaccines-revision-1_en.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref55">FDA. GUIDANCE DOCUMENT. General Principles for the Development of Vaccines to Protect Against Global Infectious Diseases. Guidance for Industry. New Hampshire Ave, Silver Spring, MD, USA. 2011 [updated DECEMBER 2011. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://da.gov/regulatory-information/search-fda-guidance-documents/general-principles-development-vaccines-protect-against-global-infectious-diseases" id="intref0125">da.gov/regulatory-information/search-fda-guidance-documents/general-principles-development-vaccines-protect-against-global-infectious-diseases</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref56"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cioffi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19: Is Everything Appropriate to Create an Effective Vaccine?</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref57"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D'Amore</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.-P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Advances and Challenges in Vaccine Development and Manufacture</article-title><source>BioProcess International. September</source><volume>21</volume><year>2019</year><comment>[Available from</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bioprocessintl.com/manufacturing/vaccines/advances-and-challenges-in-vaccine-development-and-manufacture/" id="intref0130">https://bioprocessintl.com/manufacturing/vaccines/advances-and-challenges-in-vaccine-development-and-manufacture/</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref58"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The clinical development process for a novel preventive vaccine: An overview</article-title><source>J Postgrad Med</source><volume>62</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26732191</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref59"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plotkin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The complexity and cost of vaccine manufacturing-An Overview</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><volume>35</volume><issue>33</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>4064</fpage><lpage>4071</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28647170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref60"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thanh Le</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andreadakis</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez Roman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tollefsen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saville</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The COVID-19 vaccine development landscape</article-title><source>Nat Rev Drug Discov</source><volume>19</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32273591</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref61">Langreth R. Moderna Soars After $483 Million Covid-19 Agreement With U.S. Robert Langreth. Bloomberg. Quint. 2020 [updated April 17th, 2020. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bloombergquint.com/coronavirus-outbreak/moderna-snares-483-million-u-s-funding-for-covid-vaccine-tests" id="intref0135">https://www.bloombergquint.com/coronavirus-outbreak/moderna-snares-483-million-u-s-funding-for-covid-vaccine-tests</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref62">Steenhuysen J, Eisler P, Martell A, Nebehay S. Race for coronavirus vaccine draws billions of dollars worldwide, with a focus on speed Global News.April 25, 2020 [Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://globalnews.ca/news/6868824/research-coronavirus-vaccine/" id="intref0140">https://globalnews.ca/news/6868824/research-coronavirus-vaccine/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref63">Anonymous. Center News. Center for Health Security report reviews the promise and challenges of vaccine platform technologies John Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health. Center for Health Security. [updated April 25th 20119. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.centerforhealthsecurity.org/newsroom/center-news/2019/2019-04-25-vaccine-platform.html" id="intref0145">https://www.centerforhealthsecurity.org/newsroom/center-news/2019/2019-04-25-vaccine-platform.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref64"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilmott</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Saint Louis University School of Medicine and Vaccine Center Mobilize for COVID-19 Pandemic</article-title><source>Mo Med</source><volume>117</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>125</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32308235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref65">Amesh A. Adalja AA, Matthew Watson M, Anita Cicero A, Tom Inglesby T. Vaccine Platforms: State of the Field and Looming Challenges. John Hopkins Bloomberg School of Medicine. Centre for Health Security. Baltimore. MD. The USA. : <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.centerforhealthsecurity.org" id="intref0150">www.centerforhealthsecurity.org</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref66">Adalja AA. Powerful New Technologies Are Speeding the Development of a Coronavirus Vaccine. Leapsmag. Future Frontiers. Opinion Essay. [updated March 2nd, 2020. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://leapsmag.com/powerful-new-technologies-are-speeding-the-development-of-a-coronavirus-vaccine/" id="intref0155">https://leapsmag.com/powerful-new-technologies-are-speeding-the-development-of-a-coronavirus-vaccine/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref67"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ewer</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambe</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rollier</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorrell</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Viral vectors as vaccine platforms: from immunogenicity to impact</article-title><source>Curr Opin Immunol</source><volume>41</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27286566</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref68"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Progress and Concept for COVID-19 Vaccine Development</article-title><source>Biotechnol J</source><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2000147</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref69"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The race for coronavirus vaccines: a graphical guide</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>580</volume><issue>7805</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>576</fpage><lpage>577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32346146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref70"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[Strategies for vaccine development of COVID-19]</article-title><source>Sheng Wu Gong Cheng Xue Bao</source><volume>36</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32347054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref71">WHO. The draft landscape of COVID 19 candidate vaccines Geneva, Switzerland. May 5th, 2020. [updated May 5th, 2020. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/who-documents-detail/draft-landscape-of-covid-19-candidate-vaccines" id="intref0160">https://www.who.int/who-documents-detail/draft-landscape-of-covid-19-candidate-vaccines</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref72">Lowe D. COVID-19. A Close Look at the Frontrunning Coronavirus Vaccines As of April 28 (updated). Science Translational Medicine. [Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://blogs.sciencemag.org/pipeline/archives/2020/04/23/a-close-look-at-the-frontrunning-coronavirus-vaccines-as-of-april-23" id="intref0165">https://blogs.sciencemag.org/pipeline/archives/2020/04/23/a-close-look-at-the-frontrunning-coronavirus-vaccines-as-of-april-23</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref73">Zhu F. CanSino Biologics&#x02019; Ad5-nCoV the First COVID-19 Vaccine to Phase II Clinical Trials. TrialSiteNews. : Jiangsu Province Centers for Disease Control and Prevention; [updated April 19th, 2020. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.trialsitenews.com/cansino-biologics-ad5-ncov-the-first-covid-19-vaccine-to-phase-ii-clinical-trials/" id="intref0170">https://www.trialsitenews.com/cansino-biologics-ad5-ncov-the-first-covid-19-vaccine-to-phase-ii-clinical-trials/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref74">Anonymous. CanSino Bio enrolls for Ph 2 trial of COVID-19 vaccine: BioSpectrum Asia Edition. ; [April 27, 2020]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.biospectrumasia.com/news/37/15850/cansino-bio-enrols-for-ph-2-trial-of-ad5-ncov-vaccine-for-covid-19.html" id="intref0175">https://www.biospectrumasia.com/news/37/15850/cansino-bio-enrols-for-ph-2-trial-of-ad5-ncov-vaccine-for-covid-19.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref75">Terry M. Moderna's COVID-19 Vaccine Clinical Trial Moves into 2nd Round of Dosing. Biospace. [updated April 23rd, 2020. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.biospace.com/article/moderna-vaccine-clinical-trial-moves-into-2nd-round-of-dosing/" id="intref0180">https://www.biospace.com/article/moderna-vaccine-clinical-trial-moves-into-2nd-round-of-dosing/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref76">Phelamei S. China&#x02019;s first COVID-19 vaccine test shows success, protects Indian monkeys from coronavirus. TIMESNOWNEWS.COM [May 8th 2020. ]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.timesnownews.com/health/article/chinas-first-covid19-vaccine-test-shows-success-protects-indian-monkeys-from-coronavirus/588904" id="intref0185">https://www.timesnownews.com/health/article/chinas-first-covid19-vaccine-test-shows-success-protects-indian-monkeys-from-coronavirus/588904</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref77">Myupchar. Chadox1 by Oxford University becomes 4th COVID-19 vaccine to enter human trials. Firstpost. [updated April 23 2020. . Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.firstpost.com/health/chadox1-by-oxford-university-becomes-4th-covid-19-vaccine-to-enter-human-trials-8291691.html" id="intref0190">https://www.firstpost.com/health/chadox1-by-oxford-university-becomes-4th-covid-19-vaccine-to-enter-human-trials-8291691.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref78"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sarah Gilbert: carving a path towards a COVID-19 vaccine</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>395</volume><issue>10232</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>1247</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32305089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref79"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vaccine designers take first shots at COVID-19</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>368</volume><issue>6486</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32241928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref80">Alatovic J. BIONTECH AND PFIZER ANNOUNCE COMPLETION OF DOSING FOR FIRST COHORT OF PHASE 1/2 TRIAL OF COVID-19 VACCINE CANDIDATES IN GERMANY. Pfizer. [April 29 2020. ]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://investors.pfizer.com/investor-news/press-release-details/2020/BioNTech-and-Pfizer-announce-completion-of-dosing-for-first-cohort-of-Phase-1-2-trial-of-COVID-19-vaccine-candidates-in-Germany/default.aspx" id="intref0195">https://investors.pfizer.com/investor-news/press-release-details/2020/BioNTech-and-Pfizer-announce-completion-of-dosing-for-first-cohort-of-Phase-1-2-trial-of-COVID-19-vaccine-candidates-in-Germany/default.aspx</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib81"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref81">Richardson j. INOVIO Completes Enrollment in the Phase 1 U.S. Trial of INO-4800 for COVID-19 DNA Vaccine; Interim Results Expected in June. INOVIO. [updated April 28th 2020. . Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ir.inovio.com/news-releases/news-releases-details/2020/INOVIO-Completes-Enrollment-in-the-Phase-1-US-Trial-of-INO-4800-for-COVID-19-DNA-Vaccine-Interim-Results-Expected-in-June/default.aspx" id="intref0200">http://ir.inovio.com/news-releases/news-releases-details/2020/INOVIO-Completes-Enrollment-in-the-Phase-1-US-Trial-of-INO-4800-for-COVID-19-DNA-Vaccine-Interim-Results-Expected-in-June/default.aspx</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib82"><label>82</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref82"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vaccine confidence in the time of COVID-19</article-title><source>Eur J Epidemiol</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib83"><label>83</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref83"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Should scientists infect healthy people with the coronavirus to test vaccines?</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>580</volume><issue>7801</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>17</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32218549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib84"><label>84</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref84"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Don't rush to deploy COVID-19 vaccines and drugs without sufficient safety guarantees</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>579</volume><issue>7799</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>321</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32179860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib85"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref85">Callaway E. Hundreds of people volunteer to be infected with coronavirus Nature. April 22, 2020 [Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/32322034" id="intref0205">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/32322034</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>