<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Because animal studies have used several animal-passaged viruses to attenuate viral virulence [
 <xref rid="b42-cep-2020-00759" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], it is possible that individuals infected with viruses that have passed through several persons late in this pandemic may be less symptomatic than those infected earlier. Herd immunity such as cross-immunity obtained from previous coronavirus infections may be responsible for the reported virulence of SARS-CoV-2. For example, during the 1918 H1N1 influenza pandemic, individuals of all ages may have been infected, but the highest reported mortality rate was among those 20–40 years of age. During the 2009 H1N1 influenza pandemic, children and adults &lt;40 years of age were mainly affected with febrile symptoms, whereas those &gt;41 years of age were relatively protected from symptomatic influenza with low mortality rates compared with the 1918 pandemic [
 <xref rid="b43-cep-2020-00759" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="b44-cep-2020-00759" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Between the 2 pandemics, there was the 1968 H2N3 Hong Kong influenza pandemic just 40 years before the 2009 pandemic. Collectively, these findings suggest that a cross-reactive herd immunity across adapted influenza viruses regardless of serotype may develop in humans [
 <xref rid="b44-cep-2020-00759" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. On the other hand, the results of studies on the seroprevalence of cross-reactive antibodies prior to the 2009 pandemic differ somewhat across populations, but the antibody positivity rates do not differ significantly across all adult groups [
 <xref rid="b45-cep-2020-00759" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], suggesting the presence of pre-existing herd immunity not detectable by cross-reactive antibodies [
 <xref rid="b44-cep-2020-00759" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="b46-cep-2020-00759" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. In the early stage of the current pandemic, the mortality rate was higher among older adult groups and might appear to vary among populations. It is unknown at the present time whether the age distribution of all infected patients could differ over time or if the herd immunity obtained from previous coronavirus outbreaks could affect the mortality rates of the older age groups among populations. Severe symptoms may be rare due to the cross-reactive immune status obtained from other coronavirus infections at a young age, which is more likely to persist in children and young adults than in older adults.
</p>
