<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para3800">In 2015, WHO issued a draft Global Health Sector Strategy on Viral Hepatitis 2016–21, calling on all countries to aim to reach concrete targets towards the elimination of viral hepatitis.
 <xref rid="bib404" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>404</sup>
 </xref> The policy response to viral hepatitis until now has been inadequate and considerable challenges exist, particularly in low-income and middle-income countries, which bear most of the burden of viral hepatitis (
 <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>). The Asia-Pacific region experiences a greater challenge from HBV and HCV infection than any other global region, having half of the 20 most heavily burdened countries.
 <xref rid="bib427" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>427</sup>
 </xref> Countries in the Asia-Pacific with a high burden of viral hepatitis span the economic spectrum and there is a negative correlation between GNI and the prevalence of both HBV and HCV, with a greater burden in low-income countries.
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref> Countries need to define target screening populations, improve awareness among health-care workers regarding treatment options, subsidise the costs of drugs, and enhance access to them. Emulating Egypt and Georgia in managing HCV could be useful for countries in the Asia-Pacific region.
 <xref rid="bib428" ref-type="bibr">428</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib429" ref-type="bibr">429</xref> Infant HBV vaccination programmes have been implemented by all countries but often fall short of administering birth doses; Taiwan can be a positive example for HBV vaccination. Although policies on mandatory screening of blood and blood products for HBV and HCV are in place in all countries in the Asia-Pacific region (although nucleic-acid amplification testing is not mandatory in all), as are policies on safe injection practices, the lack of strong political commitment and effective regulations in low-to-middle income countries, especially in southeast Asia, limits the outcomes. Reuse of contaminated needles continues to cause outbreaks of hepatitis B and C in southeast Asia.
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib398" ref-type="bibr">398</xref> Harm reduction strategies targeting people who inject drugs need to be implemented, as has been done in Malaysia using the “Support. Don't punish” philosophy.
 <xref rid="bib430" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>430</sup>
 </xref> The WHO's Global Health Sector Strategy
 <xref rid="bib404" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>404</sup>
 </xref> on viral hepatitis called for elimination of viral hepatitis as a major public health threat by 2030 (ie, 90% reduction in incidence and 65% in mortality). Various targets have been proposed to achieve this, including three-dose coverage of hepatitis B vaccination in infancy (90%), receiving a timely birth dose (90%), blood safety (100%), injection safety (unsafe injections target of 0%), harm reduction (target for syringe and needle per person who injects drugs per year of 300), awareness of status of people infected with HBV and HCV (90%), and awareness of the status of infected people who were on HBV treatment or had started HCV treatment (80%). All countries in the Asia-Pacific should work towards achieving these targets in a time-bound manner.
</p>
