<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">COVID-19, caused by SARS-CoV-2 (severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2) which was provisionally named as 2019-nCoV, belongs to the genus Betacoronavirus and is the third animal coronavirus infection to affect humans.
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref> The high pathogenic tendency of coronaviruses, to affect humans, were considered, only with the emergence of two life threatening epidemics, SARS (Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome) in 2002–2003 in China and approximately ten years later MERS (Middle East Respiratory Syndrome) in the Middle Eastern Countries.
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref> Both SARS coronavirus (SARS-CoV) and MERS coronavirus (MERS-CoV) are considered to have their origin from bats. The genetic sequence of SARS-CoV-2 has been shown to be 79.6% identical to that of SARS-CoV and 96% identical to a bat coronavirus.
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref> Despite the initial zoonotic nature of COVID-19, now the rapid spread is by human to human contact with the typical clinical features of fever, cough which is mostly nonproductive, malaise, dyspnoea and pneumonia.
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref> Other infrequently presented symptoms include sputum production, hemoptysis, headache and gastrointestinal symptoms such as diarrhea, nausea and vomiting.
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref> Therefore, besides the spread of the virus through oral and nasal secretions, a possibility of a fecal-oral transmission has been implicated. Few cases of acute myocardial injury and chronic cardiovascular damage have been reported in patients with COVID-19 as the disease progresses.
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref> Transmission can also occur early in the disease process, even before the symptoms set in, highlighting the transmission potential of asymptomatic or mildly symptomatic patients.
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
