<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0025">Saliva plays an important role in the transmission of infection between persons by contact with the droplets expressed.
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref> It also paves way for a convenient and non invasive mode of diagnosis. Additionally it can be collected by the patients themselves and thus reduces the risk of infection to the healthcare workers. Saliva samples also present with an adequate quantity of analyte, in patients who have insufficient or no sputum. Coronaviruses, including the SARS-CoV, have been detected previously in saliva, almost in par with the levels found in nasopharyngeal specimens.
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>17</sup>
 </xref> SARS-CoV-2 has been detected in saliva of confirmed patients with COVID-19, even up to the 11th day after hospitalization, in one of the cases.
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>17</sup>
 </xref> The presence of the COVID-19 virus in the saliva can have its source from either the salivary glands via the ducts or from the gingival crevicular fluid (from gingiva) or simply from secretions of the lower and upper respiratory tract that combines with the saliva.
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref> The ACE2 epithelial cells of the salivary glands have been shown to be an initial target for the SARS-CoV, early in the disease process, in rhesus macaques.
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref> The mRNA and protein levels of the cellular protease, furin, vary according to the cell type and high levels have been found in the salivary glands.
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref> Similarly, expression of TMPRSS2 has also been seen in the salivary glands.
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref> Thus, the possibility of the role of salivary gland cells in the initial entry, progress of the infection and as a source of the virus, should be considered and validated with further studies. This may also be the reason behind the transmission of infection between asymptomatic cases, since the organism is contained and proliferates within the salivary glands and has not progressed yet to the respiratory tracts. This may be further analyzed by collecting the ductal saliva secretions rather than whole saliva, using appropriate saliva collectors and collection procedures. A modified Carlson–Crittenden/Lashley cup for collection of the parotid ductal secretions as well as the submandibular and sublingual saliva collectors, as described by Wolfe et al.
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref> can be applied for better results, thus probably excluding the virus from the respiratory tract or the gingival crevicular fluid.
</p>
