<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>NoV-positive specimens were further genotyped using specific primers targeting a partial sequence (region C) of the gene encoding the major capsid protein (VP1) in the NoV genome. As Yan et al. described, instead of the complete VP1 gene, a relatively small region of ORF2 (region C) is generally used to genotype strains [
 <xref rid="pone.0209245.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The primer sequences were as follows: G1-SKF (
 <monospace>CTG CCC GAA TTY GTA AAT GA</monospace>) and G1-SKR (
 <monospace>CCA ACC CAR CCA TTR TAC A</monospace>) for GI [
 <xref rid="pone.0209245.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] and COG2F (
 <monospace>CAR GAR BCN ATG TTY AGR TGG ATG AG</monospace>) and G2SKR (
 <monospace>CCR CCN GCA TRH CCR TTR TAC AT</monospace>) for GII [
 <xref rid="pone.0209245.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0209245.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. RT-PCR was performed using a SuperScript III One-Step RT-PCR System kit (Invitrogen, USA) in a 25 μl reaction volume. A negative control sample containing water and a positive control sample containing GI and GII NoV RNA provided by Bioperfectus Technologies Co. were included in each run. The amplification conditions were as follows: 42°C for 30 min; 95°C for 15 min; 40 cycles at 95°C for 30 s, 50°C for 30 s, and 72°C for 30 s; and a final extension at 72°C for 10 min. The expected amplicon size was 330 bp for GI and 387 bp for GII. The amplification products were sequenced using an ABI 3730 XL DNA analyzer (Applied Biosystems, Inc., Foster City, CA) at Beijing Genomics Institute (BGI) in Beijing, China. Genotypes were determined using the Norovirus Typing Tool (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rivm.nl/mpf/typingtool/norovirus/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.rivm.nl/mpf/typingtool/norovirus/</ext-link>) [
 <xref rid="pone.0209245.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The protocol is provided as DOI: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.17504/protocols.io.q3sdyne" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">dx.doi.org/10.17504/protocols.io.q3sdyne</ext-link>.
</p>
