<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat.1008611.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1008611.g002</object-id>
 <label>Fig 2</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Influence of H7N9 PB1-F2 expression on mitochondrial morphology and function.</title>
  <p>(
   <bold>A</bold>) Mitotracker Red CMXRos staining. HEK293T cells over coverslips in 6-well plates were transfected with 1μg of PB1-F2-Flag expression construct. After 48 hours, cells were stained with 500 nM Mitotracker Red CMXRos for 30 min and then fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde. PB1-F2 was probed with anti-Flag and nuclei were stained with DAPI. The stained cells were analyzed by confocal microscopy. Arrows indicated distinct mitochondrial clusters colocalized with PB1-F2. vec: vector control. Bars, 20 μm. (
   <bold>B</bold>) JC-1 staining. HEK293T cells in 12-well plates were transfected with 0.5 μg of PB1-F2-Flag expression construct. After 48 hours, cells were stained with JC-1 dye. For CCCP control, cells were co-treated with 50 μM CCCP and JC-1 dye. JC-1 dye-stained cells were analyzed through fluorescence microplate reader for red and green signals, which respectively indicated healthy and depolarized mitochondria. The data represent mean values ± SD of red-to-green ratio of JC-1 staining of three independent experiments. Unpaired Student’s t-test was used to assess the statistical significance of the difference between vector control (vec) and sample. ***: P &lt; 0.001. **: P &lt; 0.01. *: P &lt; 0.05. n.s.: P &gt; 0.05. (
   <bold>C</bold>) Mitochondrial clustering. Cells with clustered mitochondria colocalized with PB1-F2 as indicated by arrows in (A) were calculated by number of cells with clustered mitochondria over total number of cells. For each experiment, at least 90 total cells were counted. The data represent mean values ± SD of cells (%) from three independent experiments. (
   <bold>D</bold>) COXIV staining. HEK293T cells over coverslips in 6-well plates were transfected with 1 μg of expression construct for Flag-tagged H7N9 PB1-F2. After 48 hours, cells were fixed with 1:1 methanol: acetone solution and probed with anti-Flag for PB1-F2, anti-COXIV for mitochondria and DAPI for nuclei. The stained cells were analyzed by confocal microscopy. Cells with clustered mitochondria colocalized with PB1-F2 were calculated as in (C).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1008611.g002" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
