<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Development of vaccines against ZIKV is being attempted. But as of now, no vaccine is available for use in Zika Virus infected patients. Traditional vaccine development methods with its long history of successes is still a time-consuming and costly affair, poorly suited to the current circumstances where viral epidemics are more frequent and affects large swathes of the human population within a short time. Peptide vaccines developed ab initio against newly emerging viruses and epidemics, as mentioned in 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec4dot2-pharmaceuticals-12-00157">Section 4.2</xref>, hold great promise in the fight to control and stem the spread of the disease. These are comparatively easy to design and manufacture, store and transport, that traditional vaccines like live attenuated or inactivated vaccines come up short on. While peptide vaccines have been in use in veterinary diseases for some time, and there have been many trials as recorded in ClinicalTrials.gov website of the NIH, no license for human applications has been attained by any potential peptide vaccine to date. Some of the hurdles to be overcome include the need for adjuvants and carrier proteins [
 <xref rid="B63-pharmaceuticals-12-00157" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], the careful regulation of stimulus for T-cytotoxic cells [
 <xref rid="B64-pharmaceuticals-12-00157" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>], guard against loss of native configuration, among others. On the other hand, the possibility of making small changes in the peptide composition to retain its effectiveness while at the same time conforming to the immune profile of the local populations promise more effective vaccination against emerging viral epidemics and pandemics. While quantitative and computational initiatives has been made to assist in this agenda, and designs for a Zika virus vaccine have already been advanced using these procedures [
 <xref rid="B62-pharmaceuticals-12-00157" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>], a more robust approach and applications of AI can be expected to boost precision vaccine design and further benefit future efforts in this sphere.
</p>
