<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par67">Passive antibody therapy using convalescent sera is a pioneering step towards combating several lethal diseases. Still, its potential for large-scale application cannot be evaluated without sufficient scientific evidence from randomized controlled trials. Judging from past studies and the recovery rates achieved using this therapy, it is more likely to be useful for prevention than for rigorous treatment of infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR142">142</xref>]. A major risk of this therapy is the possibility of allergic or immune reactions to the serum. This risk can be minimized through appropriate blood screening practices in which donated blood is screened for infectious agents and reactions with the blood of serum recipients. Nonetheless, the administration of sera in patients with pulmonary disease carries the risk of transfusion-related acute lung injury (TRALI) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR158">158</xref>], which should be contemplated in the evaluation and analysis of the risks involved in passive antibody therapy. The other threat that can discourage the use of antibody therapy is antibody-dependent enhancement (ADE) of infection. An escalation of infection can occur due to various antibodies present in the serum, an occurrence that can take place in the case of many viral diseases. This threat is of particular concern in the case of CoVs, where antibodies against one type of CoV can intensify the resulting infection with another CoV. Still, the intensity of the threat can be estimated in the case of the new CoV, as was the case with MERS [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR159">159</xref>]. The suggested administration of passive antibodies may work against the virus, as it would involve using high concentrations of neutralizing antibodies, minimizing the threat of ADE. This is supported by historical evidence, as well as by a recent study in which more than 200 patients were administered serum from recuperated COVID-19 patients, indicating its safety [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR157">157</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR160">160</xref>], but the persistent threat of ADE must be addressed with adequate wariness in clinical trials to prevent any type of intensification of disease. The vulnerability of recovered patients to a secondary infection, enabled by the suppression of the host immune response when antibodies are given to the patients, is an additional theoretical risk of passive therapy. In the case of RSV, treatment with antibodies before administration of the vaccine resulted in the suppression of the humoral immune response [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR161">161</xref>]. Although effective clinical studies can address this problem, it can also be overcome by vaccinating patients against SARS-CoV-2 later when a vaccine becomes available. Considering the high fatality rate of SARS-CoV-2 in elderly and susceptible patients, the advantages of using this therapy appear to be significantly greater than the risks. Nevertheless, it is imperative to evaluate and estimate all of the risks associated with its use, as was done with recent use of monoclonal antibodies in the treatment of Ebola [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>].
</p>
