<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para20">The complex interplay between biological and behavioural risk factors needs to be recognised during the COVID-19 pandemic. It is not yet known whether the higher COVID-19 case fatality rates reported in men compared with women in China, South Korea, and Italy
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> to date are attributed to sex-specific biological susceptibility, variations in pre-existing comorbidities, behavioural risk factors, or some combination of these factors.
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> In terms of behavioural risk factors, women's risk of contracting COVID-19 may be higher than men's risk as women are front-line providers, comprising 70% of the global health and social care workforce, and they do three times as much unpaid care work at home as men.
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Moreover, pregnant women could be at risk of pregnancy-related complications during the COVID-19 pandemic.
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref> Severe acute respiratory syndrome and Middle East respiratory syndrome were associated with increased risk of pregnancy-related morbidity and mortality,
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref> but data on COVID-19 are scarce.
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref> In China, among nine women in their third trimester with COVID-19, clinical outcomes were similar to non-pregnant adults.
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref> Yet another study of 33 neonates born to mothers with COVID-19 identified intrauterine vertical transmission of COVID-19 in three neonates.
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref> However, studies to date have been based on third trimester cases and viral infections during pregnancy are typically most severe during the first 20 weeks of gestation.
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
