<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the absence of any dependable vaccine or drugs with tested efficacy and when the pandemic onslaught is ongoing, a worthy therapeutic approach is passive immunization using purified antibodies. The source of such antibodies could be the sera of convalescing individuals, mAbs, or genetically modified antibodies from an animal host, which can efficiently neutralize the virus. This is an age-old practice, with pioneering work having been done by the Nobel Laureate, Emil Behring, who applied this approach for diphtheria, and has been used whenever there are sudden outbreaks of viral diseases like SARS, MERS, H1N1, H5N1, Ebola, and many others (
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B164" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B165" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>). As opposed to active vaccination, plasma therapy is the only means to provide immediate immunity for viral clearance, as in the case of SARS-CoV-2. As in other epidemic diseases, convalescent sera are currently being employed for COVID-19 in a number of countries (
 <xref rid="B166" ref-type="bibr">166</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B167" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>). Although a randomized controlled trial is yet to be reported, limited studies in 10 patients have been documented with no remission of severe respiratory afflictions on receiving neutralizing antibodies from 39 convalesced donors with antibody titers of 1:160, along with drugs and oxygen support (
 <xref rid="B168" ref-type="bibr">168</xref>). A report from Hong Kong suggested that this therapy had poor outcome in SARS patients, with a number of limitations in their study (
 <xref rid="B169" ref-type="bibr">169</xref>). As with transfusion of any blood products, precautionary screening of infectious agent is warranted in plasma transfusion. Recently, the FDA in the USA has approved trials of convalescent plasma therapy in COVID-19 under specific guidelines; plasma donation is advised 3 weeks after a patient becomes virus-negative on PCR. The major challenge in this therapy is obtaining donors with similar blood antigens with a high antibody titer of SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="B170" ref-type="bibr">170</xref>). Another potential adverse effect of this approach is ADE of infection, which is common in so many other viruses. But, to date, the incidence of ADE has not been reported in the case of SARS-CoV-2. Another major point of contention is the selection of patients for this therapeutic approach. In most clinical trials, patients with severe diseases are being recruited, while the presumed mechanism of action of convalescent plasma, based on its content of virus-neutralizing antibodies, rather points to plausible favorable outcomes in earlier phases of the disease because in the later, more severe phases, the hyper-immune response, rather than the viral load, becomes the more critical pathology. Finally, there are no available data on the heterogeneity of response to convalescent plasma transfusion, which may further illustrate the importance of careful evidence-based patient selection, as heterogeneity of response may result from both virus and host-intrinsic factors which are, to date, not revealed.
</p>
