<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Foot and mouth disease is of major concern to the livestock industry in both developed and developing countries. Strict import measures have been adopted by many countries to prevent introduction of the disease, and various diagnostic tests have been developed to enable rapid and sensitive detection of cases of the disease and for typing the different virus serotypes. A number of radioimmunoassays were developed to aid diagnosis and differentiation, but none of them has been adopted in practice. A radioimmunoassay technique was used to compare different samples of type SAT 2 FMD viruses by measurement of the competition of heterologous virus with homologous virus for previously titrated homologous antiserum. Viruses could be grouped according to their ability to compete with the homologous virus, and statistically significant differences between virus “groups” were observed. The results of a comparison of the relationships between the viruses using RIA and complement fixation tests did not always correlate (Crowther et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">1979</xref>). RNA competition hybridization using 
 <sup>32</sup>P-labeled RNA and competitive radioimmunoassays with 
 <sup>35</sup>S-labeled viruses were used to compare the biochemical and serological characteristics of five isolate of FMD, serotype A (Robson et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR157">1979</xref>). Three A
 <sub>22</sub> viruses were found to be different from A
 <sub>5</sub> and A
 <sub>24</sub> viruses by RNA hybridization. Similar findings were obtained with RIA. A rapid, reproducible solid-phase radioimmunoassay was developed for the detection of antibodies against a specific region of the structural protein VP1 of the A
 <sub>24</sub> and 01 serotypes of FMD virus. The RIA antibody titers showed a positive correlation with neutralizing antibody titers determined by a mouse protection assay (Patzer et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR139">1985</xref>). Competition RIA using 
 <sup>35</sup>S-labeled viruses was used to define four antigenic determinants in the virus capsid. One determinant detected on the intact particle was considered to be of epidemiological importance since it was present on the intact virion, was found to vary in heterologous field strain, induced neutralizing antibody responses, and was important in the immunogenicity of the virus (Haresnape and McCahon 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">1983</xref>). Recombinant complementary DNA (cDNA) probes labeled with 
 <sup>32</sup>P were used to detect and differentiate between FMD viruses (McFarlane et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">1990</xref>). It was possible to differentiate between FMD virus serotypes A, O, and C, using cDNA probes from individual serotypes corresponding to protein VP1. The assays appeared to be more sensitive than complement fixation tests (CFT) and ELISAs, being able to detect 1 pg of virus.
</p>
