<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although adaptive immune responses play a key role in the resolution of influenza infection, innate immune responses play an essential role in restricting virus replication and thus limiting the scale of the initial infection (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Amongst other innate immune players, Natural Killer (NK) cells can kill virus-infected cells and help to orchestrate nascent adaptive immune responses (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Defects in NK cells are associated with increased susceptibility to viral infections (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). NK cell killing is mediated by cell surface cytotoxicity receptors (such as the natural cytotoxicity receptors NKp30, NKp44, and NKp46) binding to viral components or stress-induced ligands on the surface of virus-infected cells, leading to directed release of granzyme- and perforin-containing cytotoxic granules and/or Fas/Fas-ligand interactions (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Additionally, cytokine (particularly interferon (IFN)-γ) production by NK cells plays an integral role in shaping adaptive immunity (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). For example, NK-derived IFN-γ can activate dendritic cell migration, thus promoting T cell priming (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Evidence for the importance of NK cells in influenza virus infection comes primarily from studies in mice, although conclusions vary depending on the precise model employed (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Table S1</xref>). For example, depletion of NK cells with anti-asialo GM1 antibody in mice and hamsters resulted in increased morbidity and mortality from influenza A virus infection (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). In addition, influenza infection is lethal in mice lacking the NK cell specific receptor NKp46 (NCR1) (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), which has been reported to be a receptor for the influenza hemagglutinin (HA) protein (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Conversely, others have reported that NK cell deficiency [whether through depletion with anti-asialo GM1 or anti-NK1.1, or due to a lack of interleukin (IL)-15] reduced weight loss and increased survival (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>–
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Moreover, little is known regarding the role of NK cells in vaccine-induced immunity to influenza. We set out, therefore, to address the role of NK cells during acute influenza infection, before and after vaccination, using diphtheria-toxin (DT) mediated ablation of NK cells in mice in which NKp46 expression drives co-expression of the DT receptor. Given that IL-2 produced from influenza-specific T cells is dependent on the NK cell driven IFN-γ response in early influenza infection (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), we hypothesized that NK cell ablation would impair viral clearance and increase disease severity.
</p>
