<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During 2003–2009, the primary-level epidemic prevention and control system received strong institutional support; however, substantial measures began with the launch of a new healthcare reform (a new phase of reform of the healthcare system). The main achievements of this new reform were in three areas: first, investment in primary healthcare was increased, and prevention and treatment measures were combined. In most regions, the standardised construction of primary medical institutions was completed, and the per capita government subsidy for basic health insurance was increased from 15 RMB in 2009 to 69 RMB in 2019 [
 <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The medical facilities available were further increased, 12 facilities being mainly provided by primary medical institutions, allowing early detection, early diagnosis and early treatment of diseases. Second, primary health service systems were continuously improved, and the infrastructure of the primary medical network was expanded. At present, there are 15 000 county-level hospitals, 36 000 township hospitals, 622 000 village clinics, 9352 community health service centres and 26 000 community health service stations in China; 90% of the national residents can reach the nearest medical facility within 15 min [
 <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Third, the primary medical service capacity has been strengthened. A system of initial medical consultation at primary medical institutions was promoted, the services of general practitioners (GPs) were contracted, the performance-based income allocation system for medical staff was improved and primary medical institutions were integrated with urban medical institutions through four alliance models, urban medical alliance, medical community, specialised medical association and remote medical collaborative networks. In 2019, 3.66 billion people visited primary medical institutions, accounting for 52% of the total number of people who visited medical institutions in China. Thus, the demand of the residents for effective primary medical care was basically guaranteed.
</p>
