<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>SARS-CoV-2 RNA polymerase (Nsp12-RdRp) mediates the replicase/transcription complex (RTC) activity and catalyzes RNA-templated RNA synthesis (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2020a</xref>). Therefore RdRp, a key enzyme of RNA viruses with a pivotal role in viral replication and mutagenesis becomes a target for the design of anti SARS-CoV-2 drugs. Among these, two investigational nucleosidic analogues, namely favipiravir and remdesivir are currently in clinical studies, yet can be obtained through a compassionate programme. Favipiravir is an inhibitor of RdRp with a wide antiviral spectrum, approved for manufacture and sale in Japan and used against influenza viruses. Favipiravir displays an 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> activity against SARS-CoV-2 and has currently entered numerous studies against SARS-CoV-2 in China and Japan, (ChiCTR2000030254, ChiCTR2000029544 and ChiCTR2000029600) (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Coomes and Haghbayan, 2020</xref>). Remdesivir is an adenosine analogue which also controls mTORC1 signalling and has a wide spectrum against coronaviruses including resistant strains (
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">Sheahan et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Agostini et al., 2018</xref>). Remdesivir has shown 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> activity against SARS-CoV-2 in combination with chloroquine (
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">Wang M. et al., 2020</xref>) or in monotherapy, as part of a 10-day intravenous treatment in COVID-19 patients with severe pneumonia (Adaptive COVID-19 Treatment Trial ACTT-NCT04280705) (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Beigel et al., 2020</xref>). Moreover, the intravenous use of remdesivir on a compassionate-use basis to patients with SARS-CoV-2 infection receiving oxygen support, has been associated with a clinical improvement in 68% of patients, according to a study published in April by 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Grein et al. (2020)</xref>. Still, the afore-mentioned study lacked a randomized group and did not control for the viral load, aspects which have stemmed various discussions. The authors have since acknowledged some errors regarding their conclusions and have corrected their article. A large Phase 3 trial has been launched by Gilead to investigate the role of safety and efficiency of remdesivir administered for 5 or 10 days in patients with severe COVID-19 and pneumonia (NCT04292899). The partial results of these study published in May could not assess the real benefit of remdesivir (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Goldman et al., 2020</xref>). Furthermore, another study from April 2020 by Wang et al. (NCT04257656) failed to provide convincing evidence regarding a significant clinical or antiviral effect of intravenous remdesivir in critical patients (
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">Wang Y. et al., 2020</xref>). Nevertheless, the recent results from the phase 3 SIMPLE trial in hospitalized patients with moderate COVID-19 pneumonia recommends the use of Remdesivir early in the course of the disease. Additionally, the preliminary data analysis of the ACTT trial prompted an emergency use authorization (EUA) for remdesivir in the US. At the same time, the ACTT trial also enabled the authorization of remdesivir in Europe, beginning with June 2020, for patients with pneumonia requiring supplemental oxygen.
</p>
