<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">The general model obtained in the present study combines HEV-1 and HEV-2 outbreak data with population density data and other environmental variables selected on the basis of current knowledge on hepatitis E virus. This model predicts a high ecological suitability in regions where HEV waterborne outbreaks are recurrently identified (e.g. India, Pakistan and African countries above the Equator)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>. However, we have not found any reports of HEV outbreaks occurred in Saudi Arabia and only one outbreak has been registered to date in Mexico, while both regions have high predicted suitability under our general model
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>. Nevertheless, in consistence with our results some studies have shown that HEV seroprevalence in adult population living in the cities of Makkah and Djeddah (Saudi Arabia) is very high (18 and 15%, respectively)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>, indicating that at least sporadic or subclinical HEV cases may occur in the region. Other seroprevalence studies conducted in the country have shown lower seroprevalence values in areas of low suitability according to our general model. For example, one study showed that HEV seroprevalence among adult population living in Riyad was around 8%
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup>. Most of these studies have observed higher seroprevalence among non-Saudis as compared to Saudi nationals. Johargy and colleagues found that the seroprevalence among Saudi nationals was 15% while it was to 23% among non-Saudis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. A large proportion of immigration entering Saudi Arabia comes from countries with very high suitability for the occurrence of hepatitis E outbreaks such as India, Indonesia, Pakistan or Bangladesh, for instance (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.iom.int/world-migration" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.iom.int/world-migration</ext-link>). In these countries the seroprevalence for HEV may be as high as 40%
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>, thus migration fluxes may contribute to the occurrence of hepatitis E viruses in Saudi Arabia, where some areas are highly suitable for the occurrence of HEV outbreaks. In the light of these results, ensuring water sanitation, water treatment and hygiene in these locations is highly recommended for the control of HEV. It is worth mentioning that few outbreaks have been recorded in areas where the suitability for HEV estimated by our general model is low to moderate. For example, to date three HEV outbreaks have been reported in the south of Africa (Namibia and Botswana) and four in Central Asia (China and Tajikistan). While this may highlight some deficiency in the model, it may also suggest that favorable conditions may eventually occur in regions with low-moderate susceptibility for HEV triggering the onset of a HEV waterborne outbreak.
</p>
