<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We have identified and described HIV genetic clustering patterns, as these are known to be informative for public health planning [
 <xref rid="B44-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Interestingly, we did not observe many of the clustering patterns reported in other settings. Specifically, in our study, clustering status was not associated with gender, risk group or recent HIV infection. The latter is particularly surprising given that network contacts of recently-infected people were actively recruited in TRIP, and given that multiple previous reports have found that recently-infected individuals are more likely to be included in genetic clusters [
 <xref rid="B45-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Moreover, modelling studies have showed that such clustering can be expected and is explained by intensive transmission during the early stages of HIV infection [
 <xref rid="B48-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Absence of such an association in our analysis can be explained potentially by the low number of observed clusters. Clustering was associated with higher viral load in our sample (though this association lost significance after multiple test correction), which is similar to the findings from the TRIP intervention undertaken in Athens and can be interpreted as a marker of recent infection [
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], but could also be explained by other factors (e.g., co-infections, late-stage HIV infection). Being in a phylogenetic cluster in our study was correlated with younger age, which might be a proxy for more recent transmission events; this is similar to the result of a previous report from Belgium [
 <xref rid="B49-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], but unlike the results reported for some other European countries and Canada [
 <xref rid="B50-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Unfortunately, we were not able to differentiate between heterosexual and MSM transmission in our analysis due to the way the data were collected and all sexually-acquired infections were analysed together. This prevents us from making direct comparisons with other studies that showed that MSM infections are more likely to cluster compared to infections acquired through other transmission routes [
 <xref rid="B46-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>].
</p>
