<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The neglected tropical diseases (NTDs) are a group of chronic, disabling, and disfiguring conditions that occur most commonly in the setting of extreme poverty, especially among the rural poor and some disadvantaged urban populations 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Hotez1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Today, the world's greatest concentration of poverty occurs in sub-Saharan Africa (SSA). According to a recent World Bank analysis, 51% of the population of SSA lives on less than US$1.25 per day, and 73% of the population lives on less than US$2 per day (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000412-t001">Table 1</xref>) 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Previous studies indicate that the NTDs are widespread among the poor in SSA 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Molyneux1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Fenwick1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, with the most common NTDs, such as the soil-transmitted helminth (STH) infections, schistosomiasis, lymphatic filariasis (LF), trachoma, and onchocerciasis together affecting more than 500 million people 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Molyneux1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Fenwick1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Olsen1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. Because of their adverse effects on child development, pregnancy outcome, and agricultural worker productivity 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Hotez1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Molyneux1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Fenwick1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Fenwick2" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Gyapong1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Brooker3" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, the NTDs represent a major reason why the “bottom 500 million” people in SSA cannot escape poverty. Therefore, new and ongoing efforts to control and eliminate the NTDs represent key elements for achieving Africa's Millennium Development Goals (MDGs) for sustainable poverty reduction, including the MDGs to eradicate poverty (MDG 1), promote education (MDG 2), reduce child mortality (MDG 4), improve maternal health (MDG 5), and to combat “other diseases” (MDG 6) 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Hotez1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Fenwick2" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Olsen1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>.
</p>
