<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Forum Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Forum Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ofid</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Forum Infectious Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2328-8957</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>US</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofz309</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ofz309</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Major Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Shedding and Transmission Modes of Severe Fever With Thrombocytopenia Syndrome Phlebovirus in a Ferret Model</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Kwang-Min</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>Hye-Won</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Su-Jin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Young-Il</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Min-Ah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>Hyeok-Il</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Eun-Ha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Se-Mi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Seung-Hun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Seong-Gyu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Young-Ki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/><!--<email>choiki55@chungbuk.ac.kr</email>--></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>College of Medicine and Medical Research Institute, Chungbuk National University, Cheongju, Republic of Korea</aff><aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label>Zoonotic Infectious Diseases Research Center, Chungbuk National University, Cheongju, Republic of Korea</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Correspondence: Y. K. Choi, DVM, PhD, Department of Microbiology, College of Medicine and Medical Research Institute, Chungbuk National University, 1 Chungdae-ro, Seowon-gu, Cheongju, South Korea (<email>choiki55@chungbuk.ac.kr</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>8</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2019-07-05"><day>05</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>05</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>6</volume><issue>8</issue><elocation-id>ofz309</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Infectious Diseases Society of America.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by-nc-nd" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs licence (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial reproduction and distribution of the work, in any medium, provided the original work is not altered or transformed in any way, and that the work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ofz309.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="s0100"><title>Background</title><p>Although human-to-human transmission of severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome <italic>phlebovirus</italic> (SFTSV) via direct contact with body fluids has been reported, the role of specific body fluids from SFTSV-infected hosts has not been investigated in detail.</p></sec><sec id="s0101"><title>Methods</title><p>To demonstrate the virus transmission kinetics in SFTSV-infected hosts, we adapted the ferret infection model and evaluated the virus shedding periods, virus titers, and transmission modes from various specimens of infected ferrets.</p></sec><sec id="s0102"><title>Results</title><p>Large amounts of infectious SFTSV are shed through nasal discharge, saliva, and urine from SFTSV-infected ferrets. Virus could be detected from 2 dpi and persisted until 12 dpi in these specimens, compared with the relatively short virus-shedding period in sera. Further, transmission studies revealed that SFTSV can be transmitted to close direct and indirect contact na&#x000ef;ve animals through various mediums, especially through contact with serum and urine. Further, ferrets contacted with human urine specimens from SFTSV-positive patients were successfully infected with SFTSV, suggesting that urine specimens could be a source of SFTSV infection in humans.</p></sec><sec id="s0103"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Our results demonstrate that the SFTSV can be shed in various body fluids for more than 12 days and that these specimens could be a source for direct or indirect transmission through close personal contact.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>body fluids</kwd><kwd>ferret</kwd><kwd>indirect transmission</kwd><kwd>SFTSV</kwd><kwd>virus shedding</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Korea Health Industry Development Institute</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/501100003710</named-content></funding-source><award-id>HI15C2817</award-id><award-id>HG18C0029</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="7"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>Severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome (SFTS) is an emerging zoonotic infectious disease caused by SFTS phelobovirus (SFTSV), a novel member of the family <italic>Phlevovirdae</italic> [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Since the first report of this virus in rural areas of the Hubei and Henan provinces in Central China in 2009, SFTS has mainly been found in China, Japan, and South Korea, with growing annual incidence and high case fatality rates [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. SFTSV is believed to be maintained in nature by an enzootic tick&#x02013;animal cycle [<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Of the tick species, <italic>Haemaphysalis longicornis</italic> are implicated as a main vector of SFTSV [<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], and their active cycle from March through November is also the epidemic season of SFTSV [<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6&#x02013;9</xref>]. Although SFTSV infection in humans is believed to be predominantly mediated through bites from virus-infected ticks, the first human-to-human transmission of SFTSV through contact or exposure to patient blood was reported in 2012 [<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Since then, possible human-to-human transmissions of SFTS have been reported in families, co-residents of villages, and even in the hospital setting [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11&#x02013;14</xref>]. Further, some secondarily infected patients died with high viral loads and clinical symptoms, including high fever and low platelet counts [<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Investigation of a cluster of SFTS cases provided evidence of person-to-person transmission through contact with blood from an index patient with a high serum virus load [<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. However, detailed information regarding the kinetics of virus shedding in various body fluids and the manner of SFTSV transmission in vivo is quite limited due to the previous lack of an animal infection model.</p><p>Therefore, in this study, we performed direct and indirect contact transmission studies using a ferret model, which was recently characterized as a suitable model for SFTSV human infection [<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In this model, we attempted to trace virus transmission and identify the specimens most likely mediating transmission from infected hosts. The virus-shedding periods and viral loads of various specimens were comparatively analyzed using real-time reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR). In addition, the presence of infectious virus in collected ferret and human specimens was demonstrated through infection in sentinel ferrets.</p><sec sec-type="materials" id="s1"><title>METHODS</title><sec id="s2"><title>Study Design for Animal-to-Animal Transmission</title><p>To demonstrate animal-to-animal transmission of SFTSV, ferrets (&#x02265;4Y, n = 3) were inoculated with the CB1/2014 SFTSV strain [<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] at a titer of 10<sup>6.0</sup> fifty percent of tissue culture infective dose (TCID<sub>50</sub>)/mL by the intramuscular (IM) route, and direct contact (DC) and indirect contact (IC) ferret groups (n = 6/group) were introduced into the cages at 2 days postinfection (dpi), which is the initial day postcontact (dpc). Inoculated and DC ferrets were kept in direct contact in the same cage, whereas IC ferrets were separated from inoculated animals by a partition, which allowed air to move but did not allow direct contact between animals. Blood, fecal, nasal wash, saliva, and urine samples were collected every other day for 22 days from each group of ferrets to detect CB1/2014 SFTSV. Further, to investigate whether each collected specimen contained infectious live virus, groups of ferrets (&#x02265;4Y, n = 3/group) were treated with specimens (serum, fecal, nasal washes, saliva, and urine) by the oro-nasal route. Ferrets were then monitored for clinical symptoms, platelet numbers, and viral titers in body secretions. In addition, 500-&#x003bc;L blood samples were collected in EDTA tubes (MEDISTAR, Seoul, Korea) followed by analysis of hematological parameters using a Celltac hematology analyzer (MEK-6550J/K, Nihon Kohden, Japan).</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Quantitative Real-time RT-PCR to Detect SFTSV RNA</title><p>Collected ferret secretions were resuspended with cold phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) containing antibiotics (5% penicillin/streptomycin; Gibco). For virus titration, total RNA was extracted from the collected samples using the RNeasy Mini kit (QIAGEN, Hilden, Germany) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions [<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. A cDNA synthesis kit (Omniscript Reverse Transcriptase, QIAGEN) was used to synthesize single-strand cDNA using total viral RNA. To quantitate viral RNA and viral copy number, quantitative real-time RT-PCR (qRT-PCR) was performed for the partial M gene with the SYBR Green kit (iQ SYBR Green Supermix kit, Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA), as described elsewhere [<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The number of viral RNA copies was calculated as a ratio compared with the number of copies of the standard control [<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Demonstration of Active SFTSV in Human Specimens</title><p>To determine whether SFTSV-confirmed human specimens had the ability to cause contact infections, groups of ferrets (&#x02265;4Y, n = 2/group) were oro-nasally treated with urine specimens (1 mL) from 2 SFTSV-confirmed patients. For this, patients&#x02019; urine samples were collected within 3 days of the first confirmation of SFTSV infection by RT-PCR assay. Ferrets were then monitored for clinical symptoms, platelet numbers, and viral titers in body secretions, as described above.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s5"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s6"><title>Clinical Features of SFTSV-Inoculated Ferrets Along With Direct and Indirect Contact Ferrets</title><p>To demonstrate ferret-to-ferret transmission in an experimental setting, animals (n = 3) were inoculated with 10<sup>6.0</sup> TCID<sub>50</sub>/mL of the strain CB1/2014 via an IM injection, and the DC and IC ferret groups (n = 2/group) were introduced into cages at 2 dpi. Clinical features of SFTSV infection were then compared between the ferret groups. This study was conducted in 3 independent trials. In CB1/2014-inoculated ferrets, there was a rapid increase in body temperature, from 39&#x000b0;C to 40.6&#x000b0;C, between 3 and 5 dpi, followed by a rapid drop in temperature at 7 dpi, which was when ferrets succumbed. Four of 6 DC and 2 of 6 IC ferrets also showed increased body temperatures (&#x0003e;39&#x000b0;C) from 6 to 10 dpi (4 to 8 dpc) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>). Moreover, 2 of 6 DC ferrets had body temperatures &#x0003e;40&#x000b0;C from 9 to 11 dpc and succumbed to death at 12 dpc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>). However, all surviving DC and IC ferrets recovered to their initial body temperature range between 9 and 12 dpc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Clinical symptoms in ferrets after inoculation with CB1/2014 severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome <italic>phlebovirus</italic>. Three ferrets were inoculated intramuscularly with 10<sup>6.0</sup> TCID<sub>50</sub> of virus, and direct contact (DC) and indirect contact (IC) ferrets (n = 6/group) were introduced into the cage at 2 dpi. Body temperature (A), relative weight (B), platelet count (C), and survival rate (D) were assessed and are shown as means with standard deviations. The number indicates a reduced number of samples collected due to death of ferrets in this group. Red, blue, and green symbols represent the direct infected, DC, and IC ferrets, respectively. Data are presented with the horizontal dotted line as the minimum threshold values. The Mantel Cox method was used to assess survival. Asterisks indicate statistical significance between direct and indirect contact ferrets, as determined from the same dpi as in the 2-tailed, unpaired <italic>t</italic> test (*<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; .05). This experiment was performed in 3 independent trials.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ofz309f0001"/></fig><p>Significant weight loss was observed in all CB1/2014-inoculated ferrets starting at 5 dpi, with an average 30% weight decrease at 7 dpi. In DC ferrets, 4 of 6 ferrets showed 3%&#x02013;15% weight loss between 3 and 11 dpc, but the fatal cases (n = 2) in the DC group showed a loss of morbidity and gradual weight loss up to 20% from 3 dpc until death (12 pdc). After 11 dpc, the surviving ferrets (n = 4) started recovering their body weight, reaching their initial weights by 18 dpc. In IC ferrets, body weight loss was &#x0003c;5%, and all ferrets recovered their body weight by 14 dpc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>).</p><p>As indicated by the name, severe thrombocytopenia is one of the major clinical symptoms of SFTSV. Therefore, we collected blood from each group of ferrets and quantitated platelets. All infected ferrets exhibited thrombocytopenia, with platelet counts &#x0003c;69 &#x000d7;10<sup>3</sup>/uL at 8 dpi (the normal range for ferrets is 200&#x02013;1280 &#x000d7;10<sup>3</sup>/&#x000b5;L [<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref>). In DC ferrets, platelet counts were only reduced by 10%, with the exception of the 2 fatal cases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref>). The 2 ferrets that succumbed showed slightly decreased platelet numbers until 4 dpc, and then a sharp decrease, 97 &#x000d7;10<sup>3</sup>/uL at 10 dpc, before dying at at 12 dpc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">D</xref>). This trend in platelet counts is similar to that of the infection group. In contrast, platelet counts remained within the normal range throughout the study without any fatal cases in the IC group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">D</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Detection of SFTSV in Various Ferret Specimens</title><p>To investigate shedding of SFTSV from each group of animals, we collected body secretions every other day and measured the viral RNA copy numbers. In the inoculated group, viral RNA was detected at 1.20 and 2.56 log<sub>10</sub> copies/mL in all specimens at 2 dpi. The highest amount of viral RNA was detected in nasal washes from inoculated ferrets at 4 dpi (4.44 log<sub>10</sub> copies/mL) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>). In the DC group, viral RNA was detected in sera from 4 to 8 dpc at 1.0 to 3.2 log<sub>10</sub> copies/mL, and the highest titer was observed at 6 dpc (3.2 log<sub>10</sub> copies/mL) in 4 out of 6 ferrets. In the IC group, viral RNA was only detected in sera at 6 dpc in 2 out of 6 ferrets, with a mean of 1.3 log<sub>10</sub> copies/mL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref>). In fecal specimens, viral RNA gradually increased until 6 dpc, when it peaked at 1.6 (DC ferrets) and 0.9 (IC ferrets) log<sub>10</sub> copies/mL and then decreased in the DC group until 10 dpc and disappeared in the IC group after 6 dpc (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2C</xref>). In nasal wash specimens, the highest viral titers were detected at 6 dpc (1.7 and 1.2 log<sub>10</sub> copies/mL in DC and IC ferrets, respectively); viral titers then decreased until 10 dpc in the DC group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2D</xref>). In saliva specimens, the highest titer was seen at 6 dpc (2.0 log<sub>10</sub> copies/mL in DC ferrets and 1.1 log<sub>10</sub> copies/mL in IC ferrets); titers then gradually decreased until 10 dpc in DC ferrets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2E</xref>). Urine specimens from DC ferrets showed viral RNA titers comparable to those seen in the serum with the highest viral RNA titer at 6 dpc in both DC (2.5 log<sub>10</sub> copies/mL) and IC (1.8 log<sub>10</sub> copies/mL) ferrets, which then decreased gradually until 10 dpc in the DC group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2F</xref>). No viral RNA was detected in any specimens (serum, fecal, nasal wash, saliva, or urine) after 6 dpc for IC ferrets and 10 dpc for DC ferrets.</p><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Viral titers in collected specimens from each group of ferrets. Specimens (fecal, nasal washes, saliva, and urine) were collected for 12 days, and blood samples were collected for 10 days (once every 2 days). All specimens from directly infected ferrets (A), and the serum (B), fecal (C), nasal washes (D), saliva (E), and urine (F) of direct contact (DC) and indirect contact (IC) ferrets were titered using real-time polymerase chain reaction. Blue circles and green triangles represent DC and IC ferrets, respectively. Each experiment was performed 3 separate times. The number indicates a reduced number of samples collected due to death of ferrets in this group. Data are presented with the horizontal dotted line as the minimum values (0.2 log<sub>10</sub> copies/mL) observed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ofz309f0002"/></fig><p>To evaluate the virus titers and tissue distributions in the 2 fatal cases in DC ferrets, a qRT-PCR assay was conducted with various tissues taken on the day of death and compared with those of inoculated ferrets. The highest viral RNA titers were detected in the spleens of inoculated ferrets and DC ferrets, 5.42 and 3.71 log<sub>10</sub> copies/mL, respectively (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Interestingly, the fatal cases in the DC group had virus titers in tissues that were overall lower than those seen in infected ferrets; however, the viral load in the spleen was significantly higher than in other organs (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; .05). These results demonstrate that SFTSV can replicate in multiple organs, causing systemic infection, and that it is transmitted by direct contact, which can lead to death, as well as by indirect contact.</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Quantitation of Viral RNA in Organs of Deceased Ferrets in Each Group Using Real-Time RT-PCR</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="5" rowspan="1">Organs of Deceased Ferrets, Log<sub>10</sub> Copies/mL<sup>a</sup></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spleen</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intestine</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kidney</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infected</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.02 &#x000b1; 0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.36 &#x000b1; 0.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.28 &#x000b1; 0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.68 &#x000b1; 0.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.04 &#x000b1; 0.64</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatal cases in DC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63 &#x000b1; 0.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.59 &#x000b1; 0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 &#x000b1; 0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 &#x000b1; 0.15</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-0100"><p>Abbreviations: DC, direct contact; RT-PCR, reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction.</p></fn><fn id="fn-0101"><p>
<sup>a</sup>The virus RNA detection limit was 0.30 log<sub>10</sub> copies/mL.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Demonstration of Direct Transmission Through Ferret Secretions</title><p>Next, to investigate which body secretions could cause infections in na&#x000ef;ve ferrets, specimens collected from inoculated ferrets at 5 dpi were used to treat na&#x000ef;ve ferrets (n = 3/group), and clinical symptoms and viral titers were monitored. Although ferrets treated with fecal specimens did not show SFTS-like clinical symptoms or mortality, serum- and urine-treated ferrets showed increased body temperatures (above 40&#x000b0;C) at 4 and 6 days post-treatment (dpt), respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>), and they showed rapid body weight loss at 5 and 6 dpt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>). These animals eventually succumbed by 9 and 10 dpt, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3C</xref>). Ferrets treated with saliva and nasal washes also showed increased body temperatures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>) and weight loss until 10 to 11 dpt, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>). One of 3 nasal- and saliva-treated ferrets succumbed by 11 and 12 dpt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3C</xref>), whereas the other ferrets showed signs of recovery from 12 dpt.</p><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Clinical symptoms in ferrets (n = 3) after inoculation with collected body secretions (serum, fecal, nasal washes, saliva, or urine) by the oro-nasal route. Body temperature (A), relative weight (B), and survival rate (C) were assessed and are shown as means with standard deviations. The number indicates a reduced number of samples collected due to death of ferrets in this group. The Mantel Cox method was used to assess survival. Blue circles (serum), dark brown squares (fecal), light brown triangles (nasal washes), black inverted triangles (saliva), and blue rhombi (urine) represent each group of specimen-treated ferrets, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ofz309f0003"/></fig><p>To confirm that the observed clinical symptoms and mortality were associated with SFTSV infection, we collected body secretions and measured virus titers in each specimen. The qRT-PCR results revealed that serum, nasal wash, saliva, and urine specimen&#x02013;treated ferrets showed relatively high virus sheading through most routes, with the exception of fecal specimens (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The fecal specimen&#x02013;treated ferrets only shed virus through the serum, and at low levels (&#x0003c;2 log<sub>10</sub> copies/mL) and for a short period of time (4&#x02013;8 dpt). In contrast, SFTSV was detected in all specimens from the saliva and urine specimen&#x02013;treated ferrets between 4 and 12 dpt. It is noteworthy that nasal washes, saliva, and urine specimens showed relatively long virus-shedding periods compared with the serum specimens, which shed between 4 and 8 dpt (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Nevertheless, these data show that a majority of body secretions from SFTSV-infected ferrets contain infectious virus at levels high enough to induce fatal infections in contact animals.</p><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Quantitation of Viral RNA in Specimens (Serum, Feces, Nasal Wash, Saliva, and Urine) From Ferrets Treated With the Indicated Secretions From Inoculated Ferrets</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="6" rowspan="1">Days Post-treatment, Log<sub>10</sub> Copies/mL<sup>a</sup></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Route</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specimen</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 &#x000b1; 0.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59 &#x000b1; 0.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fecal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nasal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16 &#x000b1; 0.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77 &#x000b1; 0.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.28 &#x000b1; 0.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saliva</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 &#x000b1; 0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 &#x000b1; 0.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12 &#x000b1; 0.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 &#x000b1; 0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93 &#x000b1; 0.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15 &#x000b1; 0.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fecal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 &#x000b1; 0.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35 &#x000b1; 0.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fecal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nasal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saliva</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nasal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49 &#x000b1; 0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 &#x000b1; 0.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45 &#x000b1; 1.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fecal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nasal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 &#x000b1; 0.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.64 &#x000b1; 0.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.99 &#x000b1; 0.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.57 &#x000b1; 0.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 &#x000b1; 0.29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saliva</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56 &#x000b1; 0.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 &#x000b1; 0.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 &#x000b1; 0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 &#x000b1; 0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45 &#x000b1; 0.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.33 &#x000b1; 0.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saliva</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 &#x000b1; 0.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32 &#x000b1; 0.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.02 &#x000b1; 0.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fecal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 &#x000b1; 0.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 &#x000b1; 0.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 &#x000b1; 1.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 &#x000b1; 0.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nasal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41 &#x000b1; 0.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73 &#x000b1; 0.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.48 &#x000b1; 1.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.53 &#x000b1; 2.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saliva</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 &#x000b1; 0.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68 &#x000b1; 0.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 &#x000b1; 1.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37 &#x000b1; 0.47</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 &#x000b1; 0.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94 &#x000b1; 0.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.01 &#x000b1; 1.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 &#x000b1; 0.53</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 &#x000b1; 0.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 &#x000b1; 1.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91 &#x000b1; 1.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fecal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48 &#x000b1; 0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39 &#x000b1; 0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.09 &#x000b1; 0.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.82 &#x000b1; 0.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21 &#x000b1; 0.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nasal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49 &#x000b1; 0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 &#x000b1; 1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94 &#x000b1; 1.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43 &#x000b1; 0.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saliva</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37 &#x000b1; 0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 &#x000b1; 0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50 &#x000b1; 0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.28 &#x000b1; 0.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 &#x000b1; 0.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 &#x000b1; 0.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82 &#x000b1; 0.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.61 &#x000b1; 0.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24 &#x000b1; 0.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35 &#x000b1; 0.60</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-0102"><p>
<sup>a</sup>The virus RNA detection limit was 0.30 log<sub>10</sub> copies/mL.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Demonstration of Active SFTSV Transmission by Human Urine Specimens</title><p>As shown above, urine specimens in particular exhibit relatively high virus titers for long periods of time (2&#x02013;10 dpi) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2F</xref>). To demonstrate that SFTSV-positive urine specimens from human patients could be a source of infection for contact persons, we treated ferrets with 2 SFTSV-positive human urine specimens (viral titers of 1.2 and 1.8 copies/mL) by the oro-nasal route, which were collected from the SFTSV-confirmed patients at Chungbuk National University Hospital in September of 2018. Ferrets treated with the urine samples showed elevated body temperatures (39&#x000b0;C&#x02013;40.5&#x000b0;C) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref>). Further gradual decreased platelet numbers were observed between 4 and 6 dpt compared with those of prior infections in both ferret groups, although they were still within the normal range and recovered by 8 dpt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4B</xref>). SFTSV RNA was detected in the nasal washes, saliva, and urine specimens from 4 to 6 dpt. It should be noted that overall virus titers were lower than 2 log<sub>10</sub> copies/mL and no viral RNA was detected in serum and fecal specimens (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4C</xref>). This result demonstrates that infectious SFTSV is transmitted through urine specimens from SFTS patients, which could be a transmission source through direct personal contact, such as to health care workers.</p><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Clinical symptoms in ferrets (n = 2) after inoculation with urine from human severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome <italic>phlebovirus</italic>&#x02013;positive patients. Body temperature (A), platelet counts (B), and virus copy number in collected specimens (C) were assessed and are shown as means with standard deviations. Red circles and blue squares represent patient 1 and patient 2, respectively. Asterisks indicate statistical significance compared with the sample from the start day by 2-tailed, unpaired <italic>t</italic> test (*<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; .05). Data are presented with the horizontal dotted line as the minimum threshold values in (B) and as the minimum values observed (0.2 log<sub>10</sub> copies/mL) in (C).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ofz309f0004"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s10"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Given the increased human-to-human transmission of SFTSV, including patient-associated transmission to health care professionals in the hospital setting [<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12&#x02013;16</xref>], we investigated SFTSV shedding in various body secretions and various modes of transmission of this virus in the ferret model, a previously demonstrated model of human SFTSV infection [<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. We found that a high amount of SFTSV was shed from inoculated ferrets through various body secretions and that ferrets placed in direct contact with infected ferrets were readily infected with SFTSV. Further, 2 of the DC ferrets showed severe clinical symptoms, including high body temperatures, deceased platelet numbers, and ~20% body weight loss, before succumbing. These data clearly demonstrate that SFTSV-infected hosts shed virus in various body secretions and can cause fatal infections in animals kept in close contact.</p><p>Recently, nosocomial transmission of SFTS through respiratory secretions was reported in South Korea indicating that human-to-human transmission does occur in the hospital setting [<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Further, Jeong et al. reported detection of SFTSV RNA in patient's blood, trachea aspirate, gastric aspirate, and urine by semiquantitative RT-PCR [<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. However, the qRT-PCR cycle threshold (C<sub>t</sub>) values were relatively low (up to 35), and the specimens were not assayed to determine if they contained virus titers sufficient to cause contact infection. Although the potential risk of infection from exposure to patient respiratory droplets is considered low, direct treatment of na&#x000ef;ve ferrets with specimens from infected ferrets caused severe virus infections with clear clinical manifestations, including high fever, body weight loss, and even fatality in the case of serum-, respiratory secretion&#x02013;, saliva-, and urine-treated groups. These results imply that there is risk of animal-to-human or human-to-human transmission through many secreted, and easily accessible, fluids from infected hosts.</p><p>In this study, ferrets treated with human urine specimens showed relatively attenuated clinical symptoms compared with those treated with infected ferret urine. This discrepancy might be explained by viral RNA titers in the specimens. Although the viral copy number in ferret urine was &#x0003e;2.0 log<sub>10</sub> copies/mL, the viral copy number in human patient specimens was &#x0003c;1.8 log<sub>10</sub> copies/mL. As a limitation of this study, we could not monitor sequential virus titers in urine specimens from human patients during active SFTSV infection; however, our data might suggest that the specimens utilized were collected during the recovery period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> and <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Nevertheless, the qRT-PCR results demonstrate that active infections occurred in human urine&#x02013;treated ferrets. Therefore, we cannot rule out any bodily secretions from SFTSV patients as possible sources for virus transmission through close personal contact.</p><p>Taken together, our results demonstrate that SFTSV can be shed in various body fluids of infected hosts for more than 12 days and that these specimens are a source for direct and indirect transmission to those in close contact, including other patients or health care professionals. Therefore, we recommend that health care workers and family members caring for SFTS-suspected patients utilize proper personal equipment to protect against direct contact with patient blood, urine, and other body fluids. Further, the data in this study will be useful for updating the guidelines for the prevention and treatment of SFTSV patients to prevent the spread of SFTSV in the hospital setting.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="a1"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>All animal experiments were approved by the Medical Research Institute, a member of the Laboratory Animal Research Center of Chungbuk National University (Approval No. CBNUA-1083-18-02). The use of human specimens collected from SFTS-suspected patients at the Chungbuk National University Hospital was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Chungbuk National University Hospital (No. 2017-05-002-001). Animal management and sample analysis were undertaken in an enhanced Biosafety Level 3 (BSL-3) facility at the Chungbuk National University, as permitted by the Korea Centers for Disease Control &#x00026; Prevention (K-CDC, Permit No. KCDC-14-3-07).</p><p>
<bold><italic>Financial support.&#x02003;</italic></bold>This work was supported by grants from the Korea Health Technology R&#x00026;D Project through the Korea Health Industry Development Institute (Grant No. HI15C2817) and the Government-wide R&#x00026;D project funding for infectious disease research (Grant No. HG18C0029), Republic of Korea.</p><p>
<bold><italic>Potential conflicts of interest.&#x02003;</italic></bold>All authors declare no competing interests. All authors: no reported conflicts of interest. All authors have submitted the ICMJE Form for Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest. Conflicts that the editors consider relevant to the content of the manuscript have been disclosed.</p></ack><ref-list id="r1"><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Fever with thrombocytopenia associated with a novel bunyavirus in China</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2011</year>; <volume>364</volume>:<fpage>1523</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21410387</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lefkowitz</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>AMQ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Changes to taxonomy and the International Code of Virus Classification and Nomenclature ratified by the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses (2017)</article-title>. <source>Arch Virol</source><year>2017</year>; <volume>162</volume>:<fpage>2505</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28434098</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K-H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome, South Korea, 2012</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><year>2013</year>; <volume>19</volume>:1892&#x02013;4.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The first identification and retrospective study of severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome in Japan</article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2014</year>; <volume>209</volume>:<fpage>816</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24231186</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaji</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aonuma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kanuka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Distribution of tick-borne diseases in Japan: past patterns and implications for the future</article-title>. <source>J Infect Chemother</source><year>2018</year>; <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>499</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>504</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29685854</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>
<italic>Haemaphysalis longicornis</italic> ticks as reservoir and vector of severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome virus in China</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1770</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26402039</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Development and biological characteristics of <italic>Haemaphysalis longicornis</italic> (<italic>Acari: Ixodidae</italic>) under field conditions</article-title>. <source>Exp Appl Acarol</source><year>2011</year>; <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>377</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21153756</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Seasonal abundance and activity of the hard tick <italic>Haemaphysalis longicornis</italic> (<italic>Acari: Ixodidae</italic>) in North China</article-title>. <source>Exp Appl Acarol</source><year>2012</year>; <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22113778</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Ecology of the tick-borne phlebovirus causing severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome in an endemic area of China</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2016</year>; <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e0004574</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27035712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Human-to-human transmission of severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome bunyavirus through contact with infectious blood</article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2013</year>; <volume>207</volume>:<fpage>736</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23225899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Two confirmed cases of severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome with pneumonia: implication for a family cluster in East China</article-title>. <source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2017</year>; <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>537</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28774267</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>A cluster of cases of severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome bunyavirus infection in China, 1996: a retrospective serological study</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2018</year>; <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e0006603</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29940000</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Aerosol transmission of severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome virus during resuscitation</article-title>. <source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>238</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>C-j</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X-l</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>A family cluster of infections by a newly recognized bunyavirus in eastern China, 2007: further evidence of person-to-person transmission</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2011</year>; <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>1208</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22028437</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A cluster of cases of human-to-human transmission caused by severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome bunyavirus</article-title>. <source>Int J Infect Dis</source><year>2013</year>; <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>e206</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23218674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>A cluster of person-to-person transmission cases caused by SFTS virus in Penglai, China</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>274</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25687766</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S-J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y-I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Ferret animal model of severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome phlebovirus for human lethal infection and pathogenesis</article-title>. <source>Nat Microbiol</source>. <year>2019</year>; 4:438&#x02013;46.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Qiagen. R Neasy Mini Handbook, <year>2012</year> Available at: <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.qiagen.com/es/resources/resourcedetail?id=14e7cf6e-521a-4cf7-8cbc-bf9f6fa33e24&#x00026;lang=en">https://www.qiagen.com/es/resources/resourcedetail?id=14e7cf6e-521a-4cf7-8cbc-bf9f6fa33e24&#x00026;lang=en</uri>. Accessed June 2012.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Posadas-Herrera</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Therapeutic effect of post-exposure treatment with antiserum on severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome (SFTS) in a mouse model of SFTS virus infection</article-title>. <source>Virology</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>482</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>27</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25817401</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Viral shedding from diverse body fluids in a patient with severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome</article-title>. <source>J Clin Virol</source><year>2016</year>; <volume>80</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27135388</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Nosocomial transmission of severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome in Korea</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>60</volume>:<fpage>1681</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25694652</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>