<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We identified 50 restriction factors, greatly expanding the number of cell intrinsic anti-WNV factors known 
 <xref rid="ppat.1003914-Krishnan1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1003914-Lucas1" ref-type="bibr">[76]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1003914-Brien1" ref-type="bibr">[77]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1003914-Jiang1" ref-type="bibr">[78]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1003914-Diamond1" ref-type="bibr">[79]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1003914-Schoggins1" ref-type="bibr">[80]</xref>. We compared our restriction factors with previous studies (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1003914.s004">Table S4</xref>). A genome-wide siRNA screen against WNV in human cells identified 22 genes that were antiviral of which 6 had Drosophila homologs; none of which were within our validated antiviral genes 
 <xref rid="ppat.1003914-Krishnan1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. A genome wide screen against hepatitis C virus, a distantly related 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic> family member, in human cells identified 25 antiviral genes of which 12 had Drosophila orthologs; again, none of which were within our gene set 
 <xref rid="ppat.1003914-Li1" ref-type="bibr">[81]</xref>. Two screens querying the antiviral role of interferon stimulated genes (ISGs) against flaviviruses were recently published 
 <xref rid="ppat.1003914-Schoggins1" ref-type="bibr">[80]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1003914-Li2" ref-type="bibr">[82]</xref>; however, none of our antiviral genes are known ISGs. The Schoggins screen identified 47 ISGs that when ectopically expressed restricted a flavivirus amongst which there were 12 homologs in Drosophila; none of which we identified as antiviral in our screen. The Li screen identified 47 ISGs that when depleted by RNAi restricted infection amongst which 13 had homologs in Drosophila; none of which were identified in our screen. None of the 
 <italic>Drosophila</italic> homologs from any of these screens were within any other screen making conclusions difficult. Additional screens performed at low levels of infection may reveal additional intrinsic restriction factors.
</p>
