<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In infectious diseases, various types of pathogen-derived molecules (pathogen-associated molecular patterns: PAMPs for short) are derived from extrinsic pathogenic microbes, which may lead to the production of inflammatory cytokines or molecules associated with the innate immune system [
 <xref rid="B37-marinedrugs-18-00228" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-marinedrugs-18-00228" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. For example, bacterial-membrane-derived lipopolysaccharides (LPS) cause acute damage to endothelial cells and body tissue cells [
 <xref rid="B39-marinedrugs-18-00228" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Different from PAMPs, a group of cell-derived molecules (damage-associated molecular patterns: DAMPs for short) that are released in association with cell death or injury may lead to the production of inflammatory cytokines and molecules associated with the innate immune system [
 <xref rid="B37-marinedrugs-18-00228" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-marinedrugs-18-00228" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. For example, DNA and histone that are leaked out from injured or disrupted cells significantly induce inflammation in the endothelial cells, leading to the production of a large quantity of TF, VWF, and TNF-α [
 <xref rid="B40-marinedrugs-18-00228" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. This, in turn, accelerates blood coagulation and platelet aggregation, leading to the formation of microthrombi in the capillary of various organs and the induction of disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC) [
 <xref rid="B41-marinedrugs-18-00228" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], which may result in multiple-organ failure (MOF) [
 <xref rid="B42-marinedrugs-18-00228" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] or severe bleeding. Moreover, hemolytic uremic syndrome (HUS) caused by 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> O-157 infection [
 <xref rid="B43-marinedrugs-18-00228" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], sinusoidal obstructive syndrome (SOS)/veno-occlusive disease (VOD) [
 <xref rid="B44-marinedrugs-18-00228" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-marinedrugs-18-00228" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], and transplantation-associated thrombotic microangiopathy (TA-TMA) [
 <xref rid="B46-marinedrugs-18-00228" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] are all disorders or conditions that result from endothelial damage and are therefore symptoms of endothelial damage. To prevent the onset of these diseases, it is quite important to prevent the inflammation of the endothelium. 
</p>
