<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0235">
 <italic>“Fu Qingzhu's Obstetrics and Gynecology</italic>” was written by Fu Shan, a famous Chinese medical scientist, in the 12th year of Kangxi in Qing Dynasty (1673). It is an authoritative monograph of obstetrics and gynecology with great clinical value (
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Qian, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2015</xref>). Fu Shan emphasized the theory of viscera (Zangfu), Qi and blood, channels and collaterals. He paid attention to the dialectics of the liver, spleen, and kidney, tonifing the qi and blood of women, and dispelling evil by strengthening justice. His medication is precise and close to the clinic, and the prescription he created is still in use today (
 <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">Zhang and Zhang, 1987</xref>). Yihuang Decoction is one of the most classical prescriptions in “
 <italic>Fu Qingzhu's Obstetrics and Gynecology</italic>”. It is composed of 
 <italic>P. chinense</italic> Schneid., 
 <italic>G. biloba</italic> L., 
 <italic>Dioscorea opposita</italic> Thunb. (Dioscoreae Rhizoma), 
 <italic>Plantago asiatica</italic> L. (Plantaginis Semen), and 
 <italic>Euryale ferox</italic> Salisb. (Euryales Semen) with the effect of clearing heat and dehumidifying, tonifying the kidney, and arresting 
 <italic>leukorrhagia</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Jing, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Liu, 2010</xref>). Yihuang Decoction has a remarkable clinical effect on pelvic inflammation, cervicitis, and vaginitis according to clinical study (
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">LI et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Xin and Tan, 2016</xref>). In JZ-1 recipe, 
 <italic>P. chinense</italic> Schneid., bitter in flavor, cold in property, acting on the kidney and urinary bladder channels with the effects of clearing away heat, removing dampness, purging fire, and detoxication, especially be good at clearing away dampness and heat in lower warmer(the term, Sanjiao, is peculiar to TCM). The therapeutic effects of 
 <italic>P. chinense</italic> Schneid. including anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, anticancer, antimicrobial, hypotensive, antiarrhythmic, and antipyretic agents have been confirmed by modern pharmacological studies (
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2019</xref>). 
 <italic>P. chinense</italic> Schneid. can exert its anti-inflammatory effect by down-regulating the release of tumor necrosis factor-α (TNF-α) and interleukin 1β (IL-1β) (
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Cuéllar et al., 2001</xref>). 
 <italic>G. biloba</italic> L., bitter, sweet, and pucker in flavor, natured in property, acting on the kidney and lung channels with the effect of inducing astringency, removing dampness, and curing 
 <italic>leukorrhagia</italic>, mainly treating turbid dampness and 
 <italic>leukorrhagia</italic>. Many experimental and clinical studies have approved the therapeutic effects of 
 <italic>G. biloba</italic> L. including DNA repair, hepatoprotective, antioxidant, photoprotective, and anti-inflammatory activities (
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Mohanta and Zubaidha, 2014</xref>). The extracts of 
 <italic>G. biloba</italic> L. could significantly decrease the release of VCAM-1 induced by TNF-α by inhibiting the NF-κB pathway (
 <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Piazza et al., 2019</xref>). 
 <italic>P. chinense</italic> Schneid. and 
 <italic>G. biloba</italic> L. are both used as monarch drugs (originated from Yihuang Decoction). 
 <italic>S. nigrum</italic> L., bitter and sweet in flavor, slightly cold in property, acting on the lung and urinary bladder channels with the effects of clearing away heat, removing toxicity, detumescence, and relieving itching, mainly treating carbuncle, eczema, and dermatitis. 
 <italic>S. nigrum</italic> L. is wildly used in TCM for the treatment of a wide range of diseases including some eye infections, seizure, epilepsy, inflammation, pain, diarrhea, ulcer, and jaundice (
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Campisi et al., 2019</xref>). 
 <italic>T. mongolicum</italic> Hand.-Mazz, bitter and sweet in flavor, cold in property, acting on the liver and stomach channels with the effects of clearing away heat, removing toxicity, reducing swelling, and dissipating mass. 
 <italic>T. mongolicum</italic> Hand.-Mazz has the effects of anti-virus, antibacterial, anti-inflammation, and enhancing immunity according to modern pharmacological studies (
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Ling and Zheng, 1998</xref>). 
 <italic>In vitro</italic> experiments have shown that 
 <italic>T. mongolicum</italic> Hand.-Mazz could influence certain inflammatory mediators (TNF-α, COX-2, IL-1, iNOS) in leukocytes, astrocytes, and macrophages (
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">González-Castejón et al., 2012</xref>). 
 <italic>T. arvense</italic> Linn., bitter and acrid in flavor, cold in property, acting on the liver, stomach, and large intestine channels with the effects of relieving heat and detoxification, dispelling silt, and purulence. It has been reportedly used for the management of several diseases including abscess of lung, dysentery, enteritis, intestines carbuncle, conjunctivitis, constipation, hepatitis, bellyache, postpartum blood stasis, furuncle, and swollen. 
 <italic>T. arvense</italic> Linn. could decrease the infiltration of inflammatory cells and expression of cytokines in upper genital tract of multipathogen-infected rats (
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Zou et al., 2015</xref>). 
 <italic>S. nigrum</italic> L., 
 <italic>T. mongolicum</italic> Hand.-Mazz, and 
 <italic>T. arvense</italic> Linn. are used as minister drugs. 
 <italic>S. glabra</italic> Roxb., sweet in flavor and natured in property, acting on the liver and stomach channels with the effects of dehumidification, detoxication, and easing joint movement. It is testified in clinic treatment that it can cure syphilitic poisoned sores, morbid leucorrhea, carbuncle toxin, limb hypertonicity, strangury due to heat, eczema pruritus, and many other human ailments (
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Hua et al., 2018</xref>). The extracts of 
 <italic>S. glabra</italic> Roxb. showed immunomodulatory potential by activating macrophages and enhancing host immunity, which makes it a novel immunomodulator for application in immunological diseases (
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2017</xref>). 
 <italic>D. dasycarpus</italic> Turcz., bitter in flavor, cold in property, acting on the spleen and stomach channels with the effects of clearing heat and drying dampness, dispelling wind and detoxication. It has been wildly used in TCM for the treatment of rheumatism, itching, bleeding, chronic hepatitis, jaundice, and skin diseases (
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Lv et al., 2015</xref>). 
 <italic>P. suffruticosa</italic> Andr., bitter and acrid in flavor, slightly cold in property, acting on the heart, liver, and kidney channels with the effects of clearing heat and cooling blood, promoting blood circulation and removing blood stasis. It is clinically used to treat gynecological diseases like endometriosis, breast hyperplasia, and uterine fibroids. It can also be used to treat digestive diseases like acute pancreatitis, ulcerative colitis, and cholecystitis (
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">WU et al., 2019</xref>). 
 <italic>S. glabra</italic> Roxb., 
 <italic>D. dasycarpus</italic> Turcz., and 
 <italic>P. suffruticosa</italic> Andr. are used to clear heat, remove toxicity, eliminate carbuncle, remove dampness, relieve itching, and treat ulcer as assistant drugs. These ingredients and guiding drugs with the functions of clearing and detoxification, aczoiling, relieving itching, and inducing resuscitation are worked together to clear away heat and toxins, remove dampness, cure 
 <italic>leucorrhagia,</italic> and treat ulcer.
</p>
