<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A question of interest is whether VE varies according to dengue transmission intensity. There is a prevailing view in general vaccinology that, in the setting of a “leaky vaccine”, VE may be reduced during periods of high exposure [
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. It has been underlined that in the context of infectious diseases, the temporal pattern of the varying risks of infection should be accounted for in the evaluation of vaccine efficacy, e.g. for the DTaP pertussis vaccine [
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], for which vaccine efficacy was suggested to be lower during periods of higher exposure [
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In an additional study on the RV144 HIV vaccine, a significant effect modification was seen in behavioral risk status over time and VE where VE was 68% for participants who maintained low or medium risk but only 5% for the high risk group [
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In an earlier trial among Thai injecting drug users, Vax 003, of the same AIDSVAX B/E component as RV144, it is hypothesized that the lack of VE may have been due to the stringency of intravenous challenge when compared with the intravaginal and intrarectal routes of RV144 [
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In the related disease setting of malaria, concerns have also been raised about whether the transmission intensity of the disease might impact vaccine efficacy [
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], in particular due to the seasonal variation of the natural force of infection [
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. To address this question, a study in Malawi evaluated effect modification of RTS,S/AS01 malaria vaccine efficacy by seasonal precipitation and found there was none [
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Similar to malaria transmission, dengue transmission is influenced by many factors [
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]; climatic factors such as temperature and rainy season can play a particularly important role in shaping dengue epidemics and should be carefully considered when studying these epidemics [
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Some studies have shown how these factors could be used to predict dengue outbreaks [
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Specifically, several pieces of evidence indicate that dengue transmission is increased at high temperatures. First, 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> or 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> reproduction, bite rate, and survival all increase with temperature until a cut-off of approximately 32°C is reached [
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. High temperature also shortens the extrinsic incubation period, such that mosquitoes become infectious faster [
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Rainy season has also been found to be associated to dengue transmission [
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], although the findings can vary between studies and geographic locations [
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Nevertheless, rain is believed to increase the number of available breeding sites (e.g., water-filled containers) and hence the number of mosquitoes, suggesting increased transmission during the rainy season. We considered rainy season data to provide a better basis than temperature data for defining periods of high dengue intensity due to its direct effect on mosquito habitats. Thus, we used rainy season as a proxy for the force of dengue infection to evaluate the association of rainy season with overall dengue disease and on the efficacy of the CYD-TDV vaccine.
</p>
