<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The H5N1 viruses used in the study, A/chicken/India/NIV33487/2006 (H5N1-33487) (GenBank accession no. EF362420.1) and A/duck/India/TR-NIV4396/2008 (H5N1-4396) (GenBank accession no. CY046104.1), were isolated from outbreaks of HPAI H5N1 in poultry from the States of Maharashtra and Tripura, India, respectively. The following amino acids were present in the respective positions in the NA of the H5N1 viruses: I97, E99, D179, H255 and N275. Thus, these viruses did not possess any known molecular markers for antiviral resistance
 <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>. To prepare stocks, the virus isolates were propagated in 10 day old embryonated chicken eggs (Venkateshwara Hatcheries, Pune) as described previously
 <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>. Briefly, the virus isolates were inoculated in 10 to 11 day old embryonated chicken eggs by the allantoic route. The eggs were incubated for 72 h at 37°C in a humidified incubator (Meta-Lab Scientific Industries, Mumbai) and were observed daily. After completion of the incubation, the embryos were chilled overnight at 4°C. The allantoic fluid was harvested, and HA assay was performed using 0.5 per cent turkey red blood cells
 <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>. The virus stock was stored at −80°C. HPAI H5N1 viruses were handled in a biosafety level (BSL) 3+ laboratory, and other viruses were handled in a BSL 2 laboratory in a class II A2 biosafety cabinet. The standard sensitive and resistant reference viruses for H5N1 are not available; therefore, the sensitive and resistant H1N1, as well as pH1N1 strains provided by the International Society for Influenza and other Respiratory Virus Diseases
 <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> (ISIRV)-antiviral group namely, A/Mississippi/3/2001 (H1N1 wild type), A/Mississippi/3/2001 (H1N1 H275Y variant) (GenBank accession no. JF972564.1), A/Perth/265/2009 [pandemic H1N1 (pH1N1) wild type] (GenBank accession no. HM624082.1) and A/Perth/265/2009 (pH1N1 H275Y variant) which were sensitive and resistant to oseltamivir were used as controls. The experiments were carried out at the Avian Influenza and High Containment Laboratory, ICMR-National Institute of Virology, Pune, India from December 2015 to October 2016.
</p>
