<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">The feasibility of a safe and efficacious ZIKV vaccine is supported by the availability of clinically licensed vaccines for four flaviviruses (yellow fever, tick-borne encephalitis, Japanese encephalitis, and dengue). Compared with the licensed flavivirus vaccines, a successful ZIKV vaccine has to overcome the unique challenge of protecting pregnant women against in utero viral transmission. Thus, it is essential to determine the correlations of protection against ZIKV infection in non-pregnant individuals as well as against in utero transmission in pregnant women. Given the decline of ZIKV human cases, identifying these parameters has become even more critical to guide the ongoing clinical trials
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>. Our study has demonstrated that neutralizing antibody alone is sufficient to protect against apparent ZIKV infection as well as in utero transmission in mice. However, a higher neutralizing antibody titer is required to prevent in utero transmission (NT
 <sub>50</sub> ≥ 1/460) than that required to prevent apparent ZIKV infection in non-pregnant mice (NT
 <sub>50</sub> ≥ 1/130). The requirement of NT
 <sub>50</sub> ≥ 1/460 for prevention of in utero transmission was supported by two different types of experiments: pregnant mice with waned antibody levels (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">9</xref>) and pregnant mice with passively transferred antibodies (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The requirement of NT
 <sub>50</sub> ≥ 1/130 for prevention of apparent ZIKV infection in non-pregnant mice is in agreement with previous studies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. Besides the different requirements for protective NT
 <sub>50</sub> titers between pregnancy and non-pregnancy, we also found that pregnancy has a lower T cell response and cytokine production after 3ʹUTR-∆10-LAV vaccination. This is not surprising as pregnancy has been well documented to alter systemic immunity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup>. Future studies are needed to define the mechanism and impact of such pregnancy-mediated T cell attenuation on the development of humoral immunity.
</p>
