<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Assessment of serum folate (SF) is routinely performed in dogs with chronic enteropathies (CE), most often in conjunction with serum cobalamin. Traditionally, their combination has been used to differentiate intestinal malabsorption from dysbiosis. Despite the fact that the diagnostic and prognostic value of serum cobalamin is well documented, the prevalence of hypo‐ and hyperfolataemia and the clinical and prognostic value of its assessment has not been scrutinised in dogs with CE. The aims of this study were to determine the prevalence of SF abnormalities in dogs with CE, as well as its relationship to other laboratory parameters and outcome. Files of dogs presented for chronic gastrointestinal (GI) signs (&gt; 3 weeks duration) between 2014 and 2017 were retrospectively evaluated. Exclusion criteria were lack of SF assessment, and supplementation of folate or cobalamin beforehand. 321 dogs (100 FN, 109 MN, 34 FE, 78 ME; median age of 65 m, range 2‐171) were included. Hypofolataemia was present in 97/321 (30%), hyperfolataemia in 86/321 (27%), with the remaining 138/321 dogs (43%) having normal SF values. Initially, dogs were divided into groups according to the final diagnosis: CE (n = 215), other GI disease (n = 76), non‐GI disease (n = 30). SF values were not significantly different across those groups (Kruskal‐Wallis, 
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.83). When dividing CE dogs into different subgroups of food‐ (FRE), antibiotic‐ (ARE), steroid‐responsive (SRE) or protein‐losing enteropathy (PLE), no difference in SF values was observed (ANOVA, 
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.92). When all dogs were grouped by their SF status (low, normal, high), significant differences in serum cobalamin (
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.001), alkaline phosphatase (p = 0.01), cholesterol (p = 0.03) and total calcium (p = 0.01) were identified (ANOVA, Dunn's post hoc test). Multivariate analysis confirmed the correlation between SF and cobalamin (
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.009), as well as cholesterol (
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.028) and total calcium (p = 0.038). However, none of these correlations were linear (Spearman, all 
 <italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05). Kaplan Maier analysis of follow‐up and survival times by SF status showed no significant differences. In conclusion, SF was not associated with GI disease or subgroup of CE. Improvement of clinical signs or survival was not associated with SF status. In this study, no diagnostic or prognostic benefit of assessing SF in dogs with chronic GI signs could be detected. Future prospective studies should assess if folate supplementation in the 30% of CE dogs with hypofolataemia can accelerate clinical improvement or influence outcome/ prognosis.
</p>
