<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, we explored the inhibitory effects of proteasome inhibitors on CHIKV replication, with some investigation into their mechanism of antiviral action. A range of proteasome inhibitors from different compound classes were found to reduce CHIKV infectious titers in a dose-dependent manner. Bortezomib, which has been FDA-approved for the treatment of multiple myeloma and mantle cell lymphoma, showed dose-dependent reductions of CHIKV titers in several cell lines (BHK21, HeLa and HSMM). Bortezomib-mediated suppression of CHIKV titers was found to occur at an early, post-entry stage of replication. Western blot analysis showed prominent reductions (50 to 80%) in the levels of structural CHIKV proteins (E2, E1 and capsid) in time-course studies as early as 6 hpi, which was confirmed in dose-dependent studies. Unlike the obvious and consistent reductions in structural proteins, nsP2 and nsP3 levels showed a fluctuating trend over time in western blot assays, with elevations observed from 12 to 20 hpi for nsP2 and at 12 hpi for nsP3. Contrastingly, nsP4 levels showed strong elevations across all time-points. The reductions in structural protein levels and elevated nsP4 levels were also recapitulated upon treatment with MG132, MLN2238, lactacystin and ONX-0914, suggesting a common anti-CHIKV mechanism across proteasome inhibitors with different functional groups. Finally, an increase in CHIKV RNA levels was observed from 12 hpi onwards. This increase was observed for both positive- and negative-sense CHIKV RNA. The major direct antiviral effect of bortezomib is likely to result from its effect on suppressing structural protein levels leading to a decrease in progeny virions and infectious titres. More extensive study would be required to identify the precise mechanisms leading to this effect, especially since the ubiquitin-proteasome system is a major pathway for protein degradation in cells and proteasomal inhibition is likely to modify expression levels of a diverse number of cellular proteins and viral host factors, which may affect CHIKV replication in different ways.</p>
