<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Apart from translational machinery, the stabilization of host and viral factors involved in CHIKV replication may have also contributed to the antiviral effects of bortezomib. For instance, DExH-box RNA helicase 9 (DHX9) has recently been reported to be recruited to CHIKV replication complexes and may function as a switch regulating RNA replication and translation [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008336.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Importantly, DHX9 was shown to be required for translation of CHIKV ns proteins during the early stages of replication while being degraded by the proteasome during later stages of replication. Another example is RpbI, a catalytic subunit of RNA polymerase II. Recently, Akhrymuk and colleagues reported that the nsP2 of CHIKV, SINV and SFV induce the shut-off of host transcription by causing the proteasomal degradation of RpbI [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008336.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. This process occurs very early in infection (within 6 hpi) and is likely to be crucial in blocking the activation of genes involved in the antiviral response [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008336.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Prevention of RpbI degradation by proteasomal inhibition may cause an increase in cellular antiviral responses, restricting viral replication. As discussed previously, modulation of antiviral responses has also been reported for bortezomib-mediated inhibition of viruses like RVFV and SFTSV. The alphavirus nsP3 has also shown some involvement in the ubiquitin-proteasome system. Varjak and colleagues (2010) reported that the nsP3 of SFV carries a degradation signal at its C-terminus and is degraded by the proteasome [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008336.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. While this has not been reported for CHIKV nsP3, our data hints at a similar possibility. In dose-dependent studies, treatment with 0.025 μM of bortezomib caused CHIKV nsP3 levels to increase by about 30% above the vehicle control. At higher concentrations of bortezomib, however, nsP3 levels showed a dose-dependent decrease, which may partly be explained by restriction of virus spread in cell monolayers at these concentrations.
</p>
