<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The robustness of simulation results to changes in the process used to initiate epidemics, together with the empirical evidence for the recrudescence of Hendra virus infections in mammalian hosts provides evidence for the potential role of recrudescence in the persistence of Hendra virus in flying-fox populations. We suggest that recrudescence is a possible mechanism for initiating local epidemics; we do not suggest that recrudescence is more, or less, important than transmission by immigration, nor that the two mechanisms are mutually exclusive. Plowright et al 
 <xref rid="pone.0080430-Plowright1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0080430-Plowright2" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref> argue that the problematic aspects of persistence via migration and horizontal transmission diminish under several hypothesized scenarios. For example, if some young-of-the-year receive maternal immunity (which subsequently wanes), the period of recruitment of susceptible individuals to the population would be extended 
 <xref rid="pone.0080430-Plowright2" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. Further, if anthropogenic perturbations have altered the spatial structure of the metapopulation, this may result in changed spatial dynamics and connectivity between colonies 
 <xref rid="pone.0080430-Plowright1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. However, given the lack of clear empirical evidence indicating the manner in which Hendra virus is maintained within populations, we do suggest that the recrudescence concept remains plausible and merits increased attention. We also would note that our simulated patterns of infection agree with the infection patterns observed in the field in 
 <xref rid="pone.0080430-Breed1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, and that our model structure per se provides a set of ecologically/epidemiologically interpretable cause-effect relationships capable of generating those patterns. Breed et al. 
 <xref rid="pone.0080430-Breed1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref> found increased levels of seroprevalence of HeV during late pregnancy and the first few weeks of lactation, suggesting an endemic infection with periodic pulses of viral transmission during pregnancy. These authors further interpreted their findings as being consistent with a scenario of persistent infection with viral latency and recrudescence, as had been proposed by H.E. Field (unpublished data). Breed et al. 
 <xref rid="pone.0080430-Breed1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref> also noted that an increase in viral transmission associated with pregnancy is consistent with the temporal pattern of some Hendra virus spillover events to horses. The observed temporal synchrony of spill-over events from flying-fox populations separated from each other by considerable distances also raises some questions concerning the ability of the immigration of infected individuals to generate such synchrony.
</p>
