<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ecological drivers of pathogen spillover and emergence in novel hosts, including humans, can be a complex mixture of processes (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b88">Lloyd-Smith et al., 2005</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b89">2009</xref>). Clearly, human activities that increase exposure to bats will increase the opportunity for infections to be transmitted between bats and humans or to intermediate hosts such as pets and livestock. However, our knowledge of how and why emerging pathogens spill over from bats is limited, and improved understanding of these processes will require cross-disciplinary approaches. Traits of the pathogen and the human–pathogen interactions at the cellular level, such as evolutionary mutation rates and receptor-binding affinity, are important when trying to understand spillover and emergence (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b102">Moya et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b125">Pulliam, 2008</xref>; 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b126">Pulliam and Dushoff, 2009</xref>). However, these traits are proximate causes, and the ultimate drivers of spillover and emergence are ecological (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b89">Lloyd-Smith et al., 2009</xref>). Therefore, understanding host ecology and elements of the human–animal interface are essential in the context of pathogen spillover events. For example, host population structure and seasonality may affect the dynamics, viral diversity and virulence of infection in the host population, which may in turn affect the risk of spillover (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">Boots et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b165">Turmelle and Olival, 2009</xref>). Attempts to understand how host ecology impacts the dynamics of infection are relatively few in wild animal populations and fewer still for bat populations, and attempts at understanding how infections themselves evolve to persist in wildlife hosts with different ecologies are rarer still. To understand the role of host ecology in disease dynamics, we recommend combining field and experimental methods iteratively to parameterize mechanistic models, as well as integrative modelling in a comparative context, between species, population cohorts and pathogens (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b119">Plowright et al., 2008b</xref>; 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b121">Plowright et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b59">George et al., 2011</xref>); important also in this context is the use of models to prioritize and plan field studies (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b133">Restif et al., in press</xref>). Only once host and pathogen ecologies are united, can reliable predictions be made regarding ecological drivers of spatiotemporal infection dynamics and spillover (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b75">Keeling and Rohani, 2008</xref>).
</p>
