<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A large number of nanostructured carriers, namely non-metal NPs, QDs, carbon nanomaterials, polymeric NPs (chitosan, PLGA (poly-lactide-
 <italic>co</italic>-glycolides), γ-PGA (poly-γ-glutamic acid), metal/metal oxide NPs, silica NPs, carbon black NPs, liposomes, dendrimers, solid lipid nanocarriers, and VLPs (virus like particles) have been intensively designed and investigated to carry a variety of molecules, e.g., drugs, proteins/peptides, DNA/RNA, antibodies, and vaccines for their utility in both antigen delivery (antigen nanocarriers) and as adjuvants to immune cells via an effective attempt to promote a protective humoral immune response. NPs and/or nanocarriers have been vastly studied as vaccine adjuvants since they possess structural and chemical features that increase their immunogenicity; synthesized NPs have illustrated their potential as nanovaccine delivery platforms (
 <xref rid="nanomaterials-10-01072-t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). In this respect, VLPs provide repetitive immunodominant viral epitopes to improve the activation of a particular, robust immune response comprising humoral or cellular immunities [
 <xref rid="B88-nanomaterials-10-01072" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89-nanomaterials-10-01072" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]; the first licensed VLP nanovaccine for human utility was the HBsAg (hepatitis B surface antigen). Nevertheless, the protective efficacy of nanocarrier/NPs against viruses that exploit diverse infection routes are required to be improved and better characterized. It is not clear whether a nasal or oral nanovaccine would achieve a better, long-lasting mucosal immunity or longer-term protection against a particular virus or whether a sufficient protection would ensue when administered via various routes or at different age groups. Nanocarrier/NP-based delivery systems can generally protect nanovaccines from premature degradation, increase stability, have excellent adjuvant properties, and may help in the targeted/controlled delivery of immunogens to antigen-presenting cells (APCs).
</p>
