<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Here, we report the whole-genome sequences of HB67652 and HB741570 viruses (an Igbo-Ora virus and a Babanki virus), which were both isolated from human serum specimens collected in the Central African Republic in 1966 and 1975, respectively. These viruses were isolated and amplified by serial passages in brains of newborn mice (unknown passage numbers). Brains were homogenized in Hanks’ solution and centrifuged. Supernatants were lyophilized and stored in sealed glass vials at room temperature until 2012. Viral genomic material was extracted from lyophilizates that were resuspended in phosphate-buffered saline using a QIAamp viral RNA minikit (Qiagen). The extracted RNA was retrotranscribed into cDNA using SuperScript III enzyme and random hexamers (Life Technologies). The cDNA fragments were ligated and then amplified using the phi29 DNA polymerase and random hexamers (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Amplified DNA was fragmented using an M220 ultrasonicator (Covaris) and was used to construct genomic libraries with a NEBNext Ultra DNA library prep kit according to the manufacturer’s recommendations (New England Biolabs). Sequencing was performed using a HiSeq 2000 sequencer (Illumina) (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). More than 14 and 20 million 100-bp paired-ended reads were generated for HB741570 and HB67652, respectively. The quality of initial reads was assessed by FastQC (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Because of the chimeric reads generated by Phi29 DNA polymerase, which prevent 
 <italic>de novo</italic> genome assembly, a similarity-based approach using BLASTN was applied to eliminate nonviral chimeric parts of the reads. GenBank accession numbers 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/HM147984" assigning-authority="genbank" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">HM147984</ext-link> and 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AF079457" assigning-authority="genbank" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">AF079457</ext-link> (which were the only 2 complete genomes available) were used as targeted sequences. Finally, 697,876 and 1,412,595 viral sequences, covering overall the target sequences from their 5′ to 3′ ends, were obtained and used for whole-genome assembly with SPAdes version 3.1.0 (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).
</p>
