<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="sec1">As first reported in December 2019, a novel coronavirus, severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), caused an outbreak of atypical pneumonia in Wuhan, China, that has since spread globally.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>
 </sup> The disease caused by this new virus has been named coronavirus disease-2019 (COVID-19) and on March 11, 2020 was declared a global pandemic by the World Health Organization (WHO).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>
 </sup> Currently, there are seven known human coronaviruses classified into two broad genera of alpha- and beta-coronaviruses. The alpha-coronaviruses comprise HCoV-NL63 and HCoV-229E, while the beta-coronaviruses comprise HCoV-OC43, HCoV-HKU1, SARS, Middle East Respiratory Syndrome virus (MERS), and SARS-CoV-2.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>
 </sup> The alpha-coronaviruses and HCoV-OC43 and HCoV-HKU1 are among the causes of the common cold and have been circulating in human and animal populations for many years.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>
 </sup> All these viruses originate from a common ancestor and enter the human population through zoonotic transfer or species jumping.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>
 </sup> Although the first four known human coronaviruses originated from birds, SARS, MERS, and SARS-CoV-2 appear, on the basis of gene sequence analysis, to have originated from bats.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>
 </sup> However, in each case, these more recent viruses appear to have been transmitted through an intermediate host such as a civet, a small nocturnal mammal native to tropical Asia and Africa (SARS), a camel (MERS), or a pangolin (SARS-CoV-2) after acquiring additional mutations.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>
 </sup> Bats harbor more strains of coronavirus than other mammals, estimated to range from 5000 to 10,000 distinct subtypes.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>
 </sup> Therefore, additional epidemics are highly likely to occur in the future due to the abundant number of coronaviruses present in the bat population.
</p>
