<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For more precise data interpretation it is important to note that in our study, we observed 2–3 fold increase in quasispecies with D222G/N mutations in HA of two viral isolates obtained after one passage on MDCK cells compared to the original material, where these mutations were already present in significant quantities (
 <xref rid="pone.0220401.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). This increase in proportion of the mutations may have been caused by selection of the mutations due to receptor properties of MDCK cells [
 <xref rid="pone.0220401.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Receptor specificity mutations such as D222G/N in the HA gene, which increase tropism to 2,3-linked sialic acid receptors, are known to be selected during virus cultivation in embryonated chicken eggs which have avian-like 2,3-linked sialic acid receptors in allantoic cells [
 <xref rid="pone.0220401.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0220401.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0220401.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Cultivation of human influenza viruses on MDCK cells has proved to be a good alternative to egg inoculation. MDCK cells are easy to handle, reliable in maintaining genetic stability and are used as the standard cell line for influenza virus propagation [
 <xref rid="pone.0220401.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. MDCK cells have both 2,6- and 2,3-linked sialic acid receptors and due to this property may potentially favor selection of viral quasispecies that grow well in those cell types. In previously reported genetic stability studies of influenza virus propagation on MDCK cells, it was shown that receptor specificity mutations were not detected in viral isolates obtained after the first passage on MDCK cell [
 <xref rid="pone.0220401.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0220401.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0220401.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], but that these mutations may arise through multiple passages [
 <xref rid="pone.0220401.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Considering demonstrated genetic stability of the viral isolates after the first passage on MDCK cells, the presence of D222G/N mutations in major proportion in viral isolates obtained after one passage on MDCK cells, as was observed in our study, is indicative of the presence of the mutations in the original specimens, possibly in smaller proportions. Probability of the origin and speed of selection of D222G/N mutations in MDCK viral isolates needs to be further investigated in order to more precisely evaluate the significance of the observed genetic changes of seasonal influenza viruses in studies that employ virus isolation using MDCK cells.
</p>
