<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec id="tca13519-sec-0001">
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>The purpose of this study was to investigate the risk factors of postoperative complications and reliable prognostic factors of long‐term survival in HIV‐infected patients with non‐small cell lung cancer (NSCLC).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="tca13519-sec-0002">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>HIV‐infected patients with NSCLC who underwent surgical treatment were retrospectively studied; a single‐institutional analysis was conducted from November 2011 to August 2018. Pre‐ and postoperative clinical data, including age, gender, smoking history, highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART), CD4+ T cell count, HIV viral load, cancer histology, clinical and pathological stage (p‐stage), surgical result, Glasgow Prognostic Score (GPS), the Charlson comorbidity index (CCI), survival time and postoperative complications were collected.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="tca13519-sec-0003">
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>A total of 33 HIV‐infected patients with NSCLC were enrolled of which 18 (54.7%) had preoperative comorbidities and postoperative complications were observed in 22 (66.7%) patients. Thirty‐day mortality was not observed in these patients. Median survival time after surgery was 65 months: the MST of p‐stage I patients was 65 months; p‐stage II MST was unestimable; p‐stage III MST was 21 months. Univariate analyses showed that postoperative complications were associated with HIV viral load (
   <italic>P</italic> = 0.002), CCI (
   <italic>P</italic> = 0.027), HAART (
   <italic>P</italic> = 0.028) and CD4+ T cell count (
   <italic>P</italic> = 0.045). However, multiple logistic regression analysis showed no correlation between HAART and postoperative complications. The p‐stage was an independent prognostic factor for survival time.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="tca13519-sec-0004">
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>In our single‐arm retrospective analysis, the risk factors for postoperative complications in HIV‐infected patients with NSCLC were HIV viral load, CCI and CD4+ T cell counts. The p‐stage was a predictive factor for long‐term survival.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
