<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>RNA viruses form complex distributions of closely related but nonidentical genomes that are subjected to a continuous process of genetic variation, competition, and selection (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). These so-called viral quasispecies have been described in vivo through the analysis of molecular and biological clones isolated from viral populations, and more recently using ultradeep sequencing techniques. The viral quasispecies was first documented with bacteriophage Qβ, during replication in its 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> host (Domingo et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1978</xref>); it was later confirmed for many RNA viruses, including animal viruses (Sobrino et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">1983</xref>) and important human pathogens such as influenza virus (Lopez-Galindez et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">1985</xref>), HIV type 1 (−1) (Meyerhans et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">1989</xref>), human hepatitis C virus (HCV) (Martell et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">1992</xref>), and poliovirus (Vignuzzi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">2006</xref>), as well as for plant viruses and viroids (Ambros et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">1999</xref>). The term quasispecies was first used by Eigen and Schuster to theoretically describe the type of population structure proposed to have mediated the self-reproduction, self-organization, and adaptability of primitive replicons during the early stages of the development of life on Earth (Eigen 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">1971</xref>; Eigen and Schuster 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">1977</xref>). They described the self-reproducing entity not as a single molecule but as a “swarm” or “cloud” of variant reproductive molecules with a numerical distribution governed by an equation; Eigen and Schuster referred to this distribution as “quasispecies” (Eigen and Schuster 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">1977</xref>). 
</p>
