<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The CCHFV M segment encodes a polyprotein glycoprotein precursor (GPC), which is post-translationally processed to intermediate glycoproteins (pre-Gn and pre-Gc). Further processing of the intermediary glycoproteins yields envelope glycoproteins Gn and Gc, nonstructural M protein (NS
 <sub>M</sub>) as well as secreted nonstructural proteins (GP160, GP85, and GP38) and mucin-like domain.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93–95</xref>
 </sup> The secreted GP38 has been demonstrated to localize to viral and cellular membranes of cells expressing the M segment.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>
 </sup> The glycoproteins Gn and Gc have been largely considered as the antigen of choice for the CCHFV vaccine chiefly because they are located on the surface of virus particles and hence considered responsible for inducing neutralizing antibodies. To this end, monoclonal neutralizing antibodies against the pre-Gn and Gc glycoproteins were described.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>
 </sup> Recently all the neutralizing antibodies previously reported to target the pre-Gn interacted with the GP38 and none interacted with the Gn.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>
 </sup> mAb-13G8, a GP38 specific non-neutralizing monoclonal antibody protected IFNAR
 <sup>−/−</sup> mice against lethal infection, whereas Gc-specific neutralizing antibodies could not offer protection
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>
 </sup> despite demonstrating 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> virus neutralization.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>
 </sup> Passive administration of mAb-13G8 (homologous to the IbAr 10200 CCHFV strain) in IFNAR
 <sup>−/−</sup> mice displayed limited protection against a heterologous CCHFV Afg09-2990 strain.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>
 </sup> The diversity of the M segment, especially the region encoding the nonstructural proteins, has long been suspected to impact crossreactivity and ultimately, the neutralization ability against heterologous strains. One factor contributing to the diversity of the M segment is genetic reassortment. The consequence of reassortment on viral aspects, such as replication, transmission, virulence, and immunogenicity is yet to be fully investigated.
</p>
