<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Similar to the RIG-I related adjuvants, neither IL-1β nor IL-18 increased the protective efficacy of our DNA vaccine. However, IL-1β increased antibody levels in low dose immunizations and in particular murine IgG1. As demonstrated by others, this might be the consequence of an increased CD4 T
 <sub>H</sub>2 expansion [
 <xref rid="pone.0231138.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] and the absence of IL-1 receptor 1 expression on T
 <sub>H</sub>1 cells [
 <xref rid="pone.0231138.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. HA-specific antibody responses mostly play a role in infections with the homologous IAV strain by neutralizing the virus before cell entry. However, the increased IgG1 amount did not translate in elevated 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> virus neutralization. In regard to secondary effector functions, murine IgG1 has a low capacity to engage activating Fc receptors and therefore should probably not enhance functions like ADCC 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0231138.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. In regard to the protection against heterologous IAV strains, T cell responses specific for conserved viral proteins can suppress viral replication and thereby reduce morbidity and mortality upon heterologous infection [
 <xref rid="pone.0231138.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0231138.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. NP is such a conserved viral antigen of IAV and therefore NP-specific T cell responses were evaluated in this study. However, there was no substantial influence of plasmid-encoded IL-1β observed and in line with that, the heterologous protection was not affected. In a former study, we used IL-1β as genetic adjuvant in intranasal immunizations with adenoviral vectors against IAV. There, IL-1β revealed strong adjuvant effects and induced an increased protection against several IAV strains [
 <xref rid="pone.0231138.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In particular, it strongly increased the induction of tissue-resident memory CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells in the lung. Similar to the present study, intramuscular application of the viral vector encoding IL-1β did not enhance immunogenicity. Therefore, we claim that IL-1β is a strict mucosal adjuvant with only low adjuvant potential in intramuscular administrations.
</p>
