<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>High-throughput sequencing, which possesses lower background noise and higher sensitivity than microarrays, is a powerful tool for transcriptome and noncoding RNA studies, as it can capture almost all expressed known and novel transcripts[
 <xref rid="pone.0177657.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Sequencing libraries of the previously mentioned samples were generated using a standard TruSeq Small RNA sample preparation kit (Illumina, USA) according to manufacturer recommendations and then prepared for Illumina sequencing. After Illumina sequencing, the sequence reads went through the data cleaning procedure as described earlier: (1) filtering of low-quality sequences, namely, those with undetermined nucleotides (Ns), a quality score (Q-score) less than 10, or reads shorter than 18 nt using fastx_toolkit-0.0.13.2[
 <xref rid="pone.0177657.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]; (2) removal of the adapter sequences; (3) elimination of noncoding RNAs (e.g., rRNA, tRNA, snoRNA, or snRNA) and repetitive RNAs by mapping clean reads of small RNAs (sRNAs) using Rfam (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rfam.janelia.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://rfam.janelia.org/</ext-link>) and piRNA (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pirnabank.ibab.ac.in/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://pirnabank.ibab.ac.in/</ext-link>). The remaining short reads were then mapped to the known miRNA precursors, and the mature miRNAs were deposited in miRBase 19.0 (available online: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mirbase.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.mirbase.org/</ext-link>). It is noteworthy that although high-throughput sequencing found novel sequences of miRNAs, we focused mainly on known miRNAs in this study; novel miRNAs have not recently been identified. Finally, 18- to 35-nt lengths of known and novel miRNAs were selected for further analysis. The sequencing data were deposited in the National Center for Biotechnology Information’s Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) database (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>) and are accessible at series number GSE94551.
</p>
