<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our study corroborates the results of other studies in sub-Saharan Africa pointing to serious patient destabilisation associated with HBV diagnosis, inability to pay for medical care and feelings of injustice.
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> However, the impact of HBV and HCV on life trajectories have rarely been documented in qualitative studies, which mainly focus on patients’ representations and experiences of HBV infection,
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> on obstacles to linkage to care after diagnosis of HBV
 <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> and on access to HCV treatment.
 <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> In line with studies on linkage to care,
 <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4 12</xref> we identified large barriers for patients diagnosed with HBV or HCV, mainly at the structural level, including (i) a lack of adequate training of HCP which resulted in frequent misconceptions about transmission, natural history and diagnosis, (ii) a lack of simple, reliable and low-cost diagnostic tests and (iii) a lack of funding allocated to the fight against hepatitis, which resulted in unaffordable user fees for prevention, care and treatment. In contrast with other diseases such as HIV, TB or malaria, where international funding led to the expansion of prevention and care in low-resource settings, there is currently no financial mechanism dedicated to supporting prevention and treatment of viral hepatitis in these settings. Considering the size of the financial barrier to care and treatment access, this calls for a multilateral commitment from governments, funders, pharmaceutical firms, researchers and patient communities.
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> More specifically, our results highlight the urgent need for a comprehensive national programme in Cameroon for the screening, care and treatment of HBV and HCV. Screening uptake and access to a subsidised pretherapeutic package could be enhanced through technological innovations and point-of-care devices which may improve both geographical and financial accessibility, especially thanks to reduced costs related to transport.
 <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23 24</xref> To reach this goal, national health authorities may rely on WHO guidelines on hepatitis B and C testing which propose simplified algorithms which are easy to implement,
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> as well on recent WHO recommendations for the screening, care and treatment of chronic hepatitis B and C infections.
 <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25 26</xref>
</p>
