<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fn-group>
 <fn fn-type="other">
  <p>
   <bold>Contributors:</bold> MK heads MSF’s Safe Abortion Care Task Force and coordinates related efforts to increase access to contraception and SAC in MSF projects. MD and EDP are reproductive health advisors for MSF and guide related activities, including contraception and SAC. EDP also leads MSF’s Reproductive Health and Sexual Violence Care Working Group. As MSF Director of Operations and Medical Director, respectively, CJ and MM oversee the Safe Abortion Care Task Force and direct many of the MSF operational activities and programmes described in this paper. AM and CB are members of the MSF International Board who contribute to guiding and steering MSF’s recent statements, resolutions and positioning regarding safe abortion care. MK and MD had the idea for the article, performed the literature search and drafted the manuscript. EDP, CJ, MM, AM and CB contributed important reflections and critically reviewed the paper. All authors approved the final version. MK is the guarantor of the article.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="other">
  <p>
   <bold>Funding:</bold> The authors have not declared a specific grant for this research from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>
   <bold>Competing interests:</bold> None declared.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="other">
  <p>
   <bold>Patient and public involvement:</bold> Patients and/or the public were not involved in the design, or conduct, or reporting, or dissemination plans of this research.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="other">
  <p>
   <bold>Patient consent for publication:</bold> Not required.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="other">
  <p>
   <bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; internally peer reviewed.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="other">
  <p>
   <bold>Data availability statement:</bold> Data are available in a public, open access repository.
  </p>
 </fn>
</fn-group>
