<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack id="ceack10">
 <sec>
  <title>Acknowledgments</title>
  <p>The PERCH study was supported by grant 48968 from the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation to the International Vaccine Access Center, Department of International Health, Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health (Baltimore, MD, USA). JAGS was supported by a clinical fellowship from the Wellcome Trust (UK; 098532). We gratefully acknowledge the substantial contributions to the design of the study by the Pneumonia Methods Working Group (Zulfiqar A Bhutta, Robert E Black, Harry Campbell, Thomas Cherian, Derrick Crook, Menno D de Jong, Scott F Dowell, Stephen M Graham, Keith P Klugman, Claudio F Lanata, Shabir A Madhi, Paul Martin, James Nataro, Franco Piazza, Shamim Ahmed Qazi, Heather Zar) and the PERCH Site Selection Committee (David L Blazes, Robert Bollinger, Claire V Broome, John A Crump, Olivier Fontaine, Robert Gie, David Goldblatt, Patrick W Kelley, Sharon J Peacock, Mark S Riddle, Montse Soriano-Gabarró, Annelies Van Rie, Christopher W Woods). The PERCH Expert Group (William C Blackwelder, Harry Campbell, John A Crump, Menno D de Jong, Adegoke Falade, Claudio F Lanata, Kim Mulholland, Shamim Ahmed Qazi, Cynthia G Whitney) provided valuable advice during the conduct of the study and the analysis of the results for which we are indebted. We also recognise the support provided by the Institutional Review Boards for study oversight. We appreciate the helpful discussions with our many colleagues who were conducting aetiology studies of pneumonia, neonatal sepsis, and diarrhoea during the same period, including the EPIC study, the GABRIEL study, the ANISA study, and the GEMS study. We acknowledge the work of all PERCH contributors who were involved in data collection at the local sites and central laboratories, members of the PERCH Chest Radiograph Reading Panel (see 
   <xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">appendix</xref> for the list of members in each group), and Shalika Jayawardena and Rose Watt from Canterbury Health Laboratories. Finally, we gratefully recognise the willingness and confidence in the study by the parents of the participating children and express our gratitude for their commitment to the advancement of knowledge toward better health for children of their community and those of other communities. This paper is published with the permission of the Director of the Kenya Medical Research Institute. The findings and conclusions in this report are those of the authors and do not necessarily represent the official position of the US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, US Department of Health and Human Services, or the US Government.
  </p>
 </sec>
</ack>
