<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0075">Level 4 represents the subset of viruses that are sufficiently transmissible between humans to cause major outbreaks and/or become endemic in human populations without the requirement of a nonhuman reservoir. This equates with the epidemiological condition 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>O</italic>
 </sub>&gt;1, that is, a single primary case generates, on average, more than one secondary case. This is a function of both the transmissibility of the virus (how infectious an infected host is and for how long) and properties of the human population (how human demography and behavior affect opportunities for transmission). From previous reviews of the literature, it is possible to put approximate numbers of virus species at each level of the pyramid. There are greater than 200 viruses at least at level 2. It has been reported that of the virus species known to infect domestic animals (livestock and companion animals)—to which humans are presumably routinely exposed—roughly one-third are also capable of infecting humans. The species barrier exists: but it is clearly very leaky. Based on data from roughly 50% of the viruses that can infect humans can also be transmitted by humans (level 3) and roughly 50% of those are sufficiently transmissible that 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>O</italic>
 </sub> may exceed one (level 4). That a significant minority of viruses (mammalian or avian) should be capable of extensive spread within human populations [or of rapidly becoming so is consistent with experience: there are several examples within the past hundred years alone (HIV-1, SARS, plus variants of influenza A) and many more in the past few millennia (e.g., measles, mumps, rubella, smallpox)]. It is noteworthy that the “shape” of the pathogen pyramid for viruses is very different to that for other kinds of pathogen (bacteria, fungi, protozoa, or helminths), of which much smaller fractions are capable of extensive spread in human populations (
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Towner et al., 2008</xref>). The most straightforward explanation for this is the much more rapid evolution of viruses (especially RNA viruses), allowing them to adapt to a new (human) host much more quickly than other kinds of pathogen.
</p>
