<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Fig. 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Vertebrate host and vector transmission cycles. (A) Enzootic cycle (sylvatic or jungle cycle). The natural transmission of virus between wild animals (vertebrate hosts) and primary or enzootic insect vectors and that leads to the amplification of the virus in the vector. The vertebrate host is the reservoir host that can harbor a virus indefinitely with no ill effects. Therefore, reservoir host is the primary host of a virus and may be re-infected several times during their life. (B) Epizootic cycle (rural cycle). The virus is transmitted between non-wild or domestic animals and the primary or accessory insect vectors. This can lead to an epidemic outbreak of viral disease in a domestic animal population where the virus is amplified (amplifying host), often with the implication that it may extend to humans by insect vectors (e.g., Japanese encephalitis virus, Venezuelan equine encephalitis virus [VEEV]). (C) Urban cycle. Humans are the source of infection for mosquitoes due to high level of viremia. The virus cycles between humans and insect vectors (urban vector e.g., 
   <italic>A. aegypti</italic>) repeatedly, as reinfection occurs with every new insect bite (e.g.,dengue virus, yellow fever virus, St. Louis encephalitis virus, VEEV, chikungunya virus, Rift Valley fever virus). (D) Humans are dead-end hosts in the infection chain and do not develop sufficient viremia and do not serve for amplification of the virus to be transmitted again to insect vector (e.g., Eastern equine encephalitis virus, Western equine encephalitis virus, West Nile virus, and Sindbis virus). 
   <sup>a)</sup>Amplifying host is in which the level of virus can become high enough that an insect vector such as a mosquito that feeds on it will probably become infectious. 
   <sup>b)</sup>Dead-end host or incidental host is an intermediate host that does generally not allow transmission of the virus to the definitive host. They do not develop sufficient viremia to be picked up by the insect vectors. 
   <sup>c)</sup>Bridge vector is an arthropod that acquires virus from an infected wild animal and subsequently transmits the agent to human or secondary host.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="cevr-3-58-g002" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
