<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">COVID-19 is mainly presented with respiratory symptoms. Patients with severe infections usually present with acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) and septic shock. The cardiovascular system involvement in this infection is also a significant feature. Cardiovascular disease (CVD) is a common comorbidity of COVID-19, SARS, and MERS patients. In SARS, the prevalence of diabetes mellitus (DM) and CVD is 11% and 8%, respectively, and their occurrence increases the risk of death [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. About 50% of MERS cases are combined with DM and HTN, and about 30% are combined with CVD [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. COVID-19 also has cardiovascular comorbidities, especially in cases with more severe conditions. By April 2020, the “Analysis of New Coronavirus Pneumonia Epidemiological Characteristics,” published by the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention, indicated that hypertension was the most common underlying disease among the patients. There were 2683 patients with hypertension, accounting for 12.8% of the total number of patients, 39.7% of the dead patients had hypertension, 4.2% of patients and 22.7% of patients with cardiovascular disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], and more than 20% of severe patients had myocardial damage [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Besides, some patients showed symptoms of palpitations. In a study of 137 patients, 7.3% of patients had palpitations as the initial symptom [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Finally, a recent meta-analysis of eight studies from China, including a total of 46,248 infected patients, showed that the most common comorbidities were HTN (17 ± 7%, 95% CI 14–22%), DM (8 ± 6%, 95% CI 6–11%), and cardiovascular disease (5 ± 4%, 95% CI 4–7%) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. However, the mechanism of these associations is currently unclear. The current hypotheses include the common risk factors of CVD and COVID-19 (such as advanced age and low immunity), ACE2, and furin levels.
</p>
