<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Thanks to recent advancements in medication for HCV, most infections can be cured. In fact, HCV elimination is now an achievable goal, and the WHO has set an ambitious but achievable 2030 elimination target [
 <xref rid="b123-ir-2019-09155" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>]. Although patients with IBD are not a high-risk group for HCV infection, those who are infected with HCV should be treated in the same way as the general population. In addition, patients with IBD are at risk of worsening liver function due to immunosuppressive therapy such as TNF-α inhibitors [
 <xref rid="b124-ir-2019-09155" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]. Therefore, we recommend that patients with IBD be tested for IgG anti-HCV antibody at the time of IBD diagnosis. When IgG anti-HCV antibody is detected by screening [
 <xref rid="b125-ir-2019-09155" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>], the patients’ HCV RNA titer should be tested to confirm HCV infection [
 <xref rid="b126-ir-2019-09155" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. If infection is confirmed, patients should be treated according to the HCV clinical practice guidelines [
 <xref rid="b7-ir-2019-09155" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. If possible, HCV infection should be treated before biologic treatments of IBD are initiated. However, if HCV-infected patients with IBD cannot delay their immunosuppressive therapy, their liver function should be monitored closely. In a previous systematic review involving a total of 153 patients with HCV who had been treated using TNF-α inhibitor, mainly for rheumatoid arthritis, worsening HCV infection was identified in only one patient [
 <xref rid="b124-ir-2019-09155" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]. The benefits of immunosuppressive therapy in patients with IBD who have active disease status likely outweigh the risks of the therapy. However, based on current existing evidence, we cannot recommend simultaneous treatment of IBD (using a TNF-α inhibitor) and HCV infection. Drug-drug interactions between HCV and IBD medications may occur, which may increase drug toxicity or reduce drug efficacy [
 <xref rid="b7-ir-2019-09155" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].
</p>
