<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The SARS-CoV causes a severe respiratory illness with fatal outcome in about 10% of the afflicted individuals. The metalloprotease ACE2 has been identified as the SARS-CoV receptor and expression of ACE2 on type II pneumocytes, the major viral target cells, and other pulmonary cells has been demonstrated 
 <xref rid="pone.0035876-Ding1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0035876-To1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. A cornerstone study by Simmons and colleagues showed that infectious SARS-CoV entry into cell lines depends on the activity of endosomal cathepins, particularly cathepsin L 
 <xref rid="pone.0035876-Simmons1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, suggesting that cathepsin activity might be required for viral spread in the respiratory tract. However, several studies showed that TMPRSS2 activates SARS-CoV for cathepsin-independent host cell entry and demonstrated TMPRSS2 expression in type II pneumocytes 
 <xref rid="pone.0035876-Glowacka1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0035876-Shulla1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. In addition, a recent report indicates that HAT can promote SARS-S-driven cell-cell but not virus-cell fusion 
 <xref rid="pone.0035876-Bertram3" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. Thus, the SARS-CoV may use TTSPs in addition to or instead of cathepsins to ensure its activation in key target cells. Our analysis confirms and extends these findings by demonstrating that ACE2 and TMPRSS2 are coexpressed by cells in the nasal and buccal mucosa as well as in the epithelia of bronchus and larynx. Thus, one can speculate that, in the context of the infected host, cathepsin activity might not be essential for SARS-CoV spread in most parts of the respiratory tract. Experiments with cathepsin inhibitors and knock-out mice are required to address this possibility. The gastrointestinal tract is a well-established target of SARS-CoV 
 <xref rid="pone.0035876-Ding1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref> and it has actually been suggested that a wide range of tissues and organs can be infected by the virus 
 <xref rid="pone.0035876-Gu1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. Our finding that TMPRSS2 and ACE2 are coexpressed in colon and various other tissues indicates that also the extrarespiratory spread of SARS-CoV might be promoted by TMPRSS2.
</p>
