<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig1">
 <label>Fig. 1</label>
 <caption>
  <title>The antiviral activities of the test drugs against 2019-nCoV in vitro.</title>
  <p>
   <bold>a</bold> Vero E6 cells were infected with 2019-nCoV at an MOI of 0.05 in the treatment of different doses of the indicated antivirals for 48 h. The viral yield in the cell supernatant was then quantified by qRT-PCR. Cytotoxicity of these drugs to Vero E6 cells was measured by CCK-8 assays. The left and right 
   <italic>Y</italic>-axis of the graphs represent mean % inhibition of virus yield and cytotoxicity of the drugs, respectively. The experiments were done in triplicates. 
   <bold>b</bold> Immunofluorescence microscopy of virus infection upon treatment of remdesivir and chloroquine. Virus infection and drug treatment were performed as mentioned above. At 48 h p.i., the infected cells were fixed, and then probed with rabbit sera against the NP of a bat SARS-related CoV
   <sup>
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>
   </sup> as the primary antibody and Alexa 488-labeled goat anti-rabbit IgG (1:500; Abcam) as the secondary antibody, respectively. The nuclei were stained with Hoechst dye. Bars, 100 μm. 
   <bold>c</bold> and 
   <bold>d</bold> Time-of-addition experiment of remdesivir and chloroquine. For “Full-time” treatment, Vero E6 cells were pre-treated with the drugs for 1 h, and virus was then added to allow attachment for 2 h. Afterwards, the virus–drug mixture was removed, and the cells were cultured with drug-containing medium until the end of the experiment. For “Entry” treatment, the drugs were added to the cells for 1 h before viral attachment, and at 2 h p.i., the virus–drug mixture was replaced with fresh culture medium and maintained till the end of the experiment. For “Post-entry” experiment, drugs were added at 2 h p.i., and maintained until the end of the experiment. For all the experimental groups, cells were infected with 2019-nCoV at an MOI of 0.05, and virus yield in the infected cell supernatants was quantified by qRT-PCR 
   <bold>c</bold> and NP expression in infected cells was analyzed by Western blot 
   <bold>d</bold> at 14 h p.i.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41422_2020_282_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e386" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
