<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig3">
 <label>Fig. 3</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Functions of the influenza A virus NS1 protein and generation of an armed oncolytic influenza A virus.</title>
  <p>
   <bold>a</bold> Schematic representation of the NS1 protein. Major domains are represented and their AA positions indicated above. The yellow line represents parts of NS1 expressed after truncation to 116 AA. Inhibitory functions of NS1 relevant to oncolytic virus development and the domains they have been attributed to are indicated
   <sup>
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>,
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>,
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>,
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>,
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>,
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>,
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>
   </sup>. 
   <bold>b</bold> Example of genetic modifications in an influenza virus designed to be used as oncolytic agent
   <sup>
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>
   </sup>. Modifications are carried out on the NS segment. In the first step NS1 is truncated to a length of 116 AA, leaving NEP intact. In a second step the armed transgene, in this example IL-15, is encoded in the reading frame of NS1. It is connected to an IgK and separated from NS1 with the H2 FMDV. Reading frames for NS1 and NEP have a common beginning. NS1 continues on, while an alternative reading frame is created for NEP through splicing. The short, frame shifted overlap of the end of NS1 and middle part of NEP is indicated by the diagonal hatching pattern. The complete NEP reading frame is generated through splicing in the attenuated and armed examples as well. AA amino acids, IL-15 Interleukin-15, NS1 nonstructural 1 protein, NEP nuclear export protein, IgK mouse-derived IgKappa signal peptide, 2A FMDV 2A cleavage site of the foot and mouth disease virus.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41420_2020_284_Fig3_HTML" id="d30e680" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
