<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The serological approach employed in the present study to assess the exposure of humans and mammals to viruses carried by ticks is highly dependent of the conservation of epitopes conformation. LIPS test developed by Burbelo 
 <italic>et al</italic>. allows the recovery of viral antigens under native conditions using expression system in mammalian cells, limiting therefore this issue (Burbelo et al., 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Since it was impossible to obtain any positive control, and therefore to assess the analytical sensitivity of LIPS assay for each of the targeted antigens, we have successfully validated the protocol using the same approach targeting Hepatitis E virus (HEV), a prevalent zoonotic virus in France (Capai et al., 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Briefly, recombinant viral antigens expressing the external domain of the capsid of HEV were produced and further used for screening of French human sera by LIPS. The assay showed the same sensitivity as the one observed when human sera were tested in parallel by the commercial ELISA (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplemental Table 3</xref>). In addition, LIPS sensitivity has been extensively described in different studies and demonstrated to be at least as sensitive as plaque reduction neutralization test and ELISA (Burbelo et al., 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Tin et al., 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Crim et al., 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). We therefore conclude that the different viruses we studied are not (or very rarely) transmitted to humans and cattle (&lt;0.017% and &lt;0.047%, respectively). Therefore, the six selected viruses may possibly either infect other vertebrates exposed to tick bites [and especially the role of rodents and migratory birds has to be evaluated, as regards to the trophic preference of ticks (Mlera and Bloom, 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Tomassone et al., 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>)], or be restricted to their tick hosts.
</p>
