<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Tick-borne flavivirus, phlebovirus, rhabdovirus, and chuviruses described in this study presented a high global prevalence (ranging from 18 to 22%), which could suggest that they are tick endosymbionts (Bouquet et al., 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Tokarz et al., 
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Sameroff et al., 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). In addition, the low degree of host restriction of these viruses, previously identified in various tick species and genera from distant geographical origins, supports this hypothesis (
 <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Our serological results in humans and cattle also are in favor of this hypothesis. Our results show that LTPV-Thailand phlebovirus, although it has phylogenetic relatedness with Uukuniemi virus [able to infect cattle and humans (Saikku, 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">1973</xref>; Traavik and Mehl, 
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">1975</xref>)], seems not be able to infect these species (or at very low prevalence). This virus, highly prevalent in 
 <italic>Rh. microplus</italic> ticks, and other related bisegmented phleboviruses belonging to the same clade, should more likely be considered as tick endosymbionts that represent viral ancestors of the known trisegmented tick-borne phleboviruses, as previously suggested (Li C. X. et al., 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Similar conclusions could be drawn for Thai strains of tick-borne flavivirus, rhabdovirus, and chuviruses described here. However, it has been suggested that viruses presented a low degree of host restriction, and a high prevalence in ticks populations could be considered as vertebrate-borne viruses, reflecting the origin of bloodmeal of ticks (Sameroff et al., 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Further investigations are therefore needed to conclude on the host spectrum and get primary insights into the ecological cycle of these viruses.
</p>
