<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0115">Teasing apart these possibilities clearly requires understanding of the timing and circumstances of HCV (and EHV) evolution. Up to date, no archaeological sample carrying traces of HCV or EHV has been described and the oldest HCV sequence dates to 1953 
 <xref rid="b0430" ref-type="bibr">[86]</xref> (1979 for EHV 
 <xref rid="b0410" ref-type="bibr">[82]</xref>). Thus, molecular dating efforts have relied on extant sequences, with the difficulties associated with the TDRP. Studies that did not account for the TDRP provided estimates of the time to the most recent common ancestor (TMRCA) of HCV genotypes in a range between ∼200 and 1000 years ago 
 <xref rid="b0320" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0380" ref-type="bibr">[76]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0435" ref-type="bibr">[87]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0440" ref-type="bibr">[88]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0315" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>; the origin of the horse virus was dated around 1800 CE 
 <xref rid="b0425" ref-type="bibr">[85]</xref>. A study that separately accounted for the rate of synonymous and nonsynonymous substitutions estimated HCV to have originated at least 2000 years ago 
 <xref rid="b0445" ref-type="bibr">[89]</xref>. Recently, a method based on an a selection-informed model was used to estimate the divergence time of HCV genotypes and the origin of extant EHV/CHV strains 
 <xref rid="b0350" ref-type="bibr">[70]</xref>. This approach, provided estimates of ∼3000 years ago for the TMRCA of extant HCV genotypes (with a low-bound estimate of ∼5000 years before present) and of ∼800 years ago for EHV/CHV 
 <xref rid="b0350" ref-type="bibr">[70]</xref>. If these dates are taken to provide at least an indication of the real evolutionary scenario, the possibility that HCV was transmitted to humans by horses infected with EHV can be excluded, an observation in line with the low diversity of EHV/CHV 
 <xref rid="b0410" ref-type="bibr">[82]</xref>. The origin of EHV/CHV as reverse zoonosis (i.e., the transmission of a human virus to animals) seems also unlikely, as in this case horse viruses should cluster within HCV diversity, unless the HCV lineage that originated EHV went extinct in the last 800 years. Indeed, as the HBV story exemplifies, viral lineage extinction can occur and was previously documented for other human pathogens such as parvovirus B19 
 <xref rid="b0450" ref-type="bibr">[90]</xref>, and variola virus 
 <xref rid="b0455" ref-type="bibr">[91]</xref>. As anticipated above, breeding practices may facilitate this process in the case of animal viruses. We know, for instance, that a minimum of two horse lineages went extinct during the domestication process and that horse genetic diversity has largely been shaped by events that occurred in the last few centuries 
 <xref rid="b0460" ref-type="bibr">[92]</xref>. It is thus possible that human-mediated selection on the host also resulted in the artificial selection of viral lineages. This would explain the relatively recent origin of extant EHV strains and their low diversity. If viral lineage extinction did occur, the time frames of EHV and HCV evolution would be underestimated and the scenario of HCV originating as a zoonosis from horses (or EHV as a reverse zoonosis) may still hold (
 <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>C). Of course, the alternative possibility that EHV and HCV were transmitted independently to their present-day hosts by a third unknown reservoir is also in line with data on extant diversity and, if the transmission to horses occurred recently, does not require to postulate viral lineage extinction. Thus, a number of open questions remain on the origin of HCV. Hopefully, technological advances that allow sequencing of trace genetic material from ancient samples will provide information on viral strains hosted by humans and horses back in the past. At the same time, the extensive application of metagenomic approaches to different animal hosts across diverse geographic regions will expand our knowledge on hepacivirus diversity and eventually uncover the direct ancestor of HCV (if it still exists). Indeed, the possibility that the different HCV genotypes derived from independent cross-species transmission events 
 <xref rid="b0425" ref-type="bibr">[85]</xref> would imply that viruses related to HCV are relatively common in the wild, thus giving good chances to be recovered in large field surveys.
</p>
