<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par15">
    <italic>Index patient</italic> is contact isolated with own toilet/shower and preferably own decontaminator. Avoid cohort isolation due to repeated outbreaks. The patient cannot walk into the corridor or common patient rooms but can walk directly out of the hospital.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par16">
    <italic>Patients exposed</italic>—have been in the same room as the index patient with symptoms—are isolated separately from the index case during incubation time for a minimum of 2–3 days [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>–
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Treat as possible infected.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par17">
    <italic>Personnel wear PPE</italic> (gown, gloves, surgical mask/cap (air transmission, especially when vomiting) and room-bound shoes that can be disinfected or shoe covers). Follow routines for taking off infection control equipment. Carefully remove any shoe covers with gloves on, and wash hands after wearing gloves.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par18">
    <italic>The use of PPE</italic> must be properly implemented to prevent spread of infection. Taking on PPE is carried out in a defined clean area in the sluice of the isolate or on the corridor outside the patient room. 
    <italic>Only clean equipment must be on the hallway!</italic>
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par19">Wash or disinfect hands before donning.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par20">Gown (single use), long-sleeved cuff.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par21">Gloves pulled over the gown’s cuff.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par22">Room-bound shoes (or disposable cover). Room-bound shoes should be machine-washed at 85 °C or autoclaved.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par23">Surgical mask/cap.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par24">
    <italic>Taking off the PPE</italic> is carried out in the defined area of the isolate sluice or in the patient room at the exit door. 
    <italic>Never doff in the corridor outside the isolate!</italic>
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par25">If using shoe covers, these must be removed first. Gloves are used when gently removing the overcoat shoe deposited in contaminated waste.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par26">Remove the gloves; grab the left glove at the wrist (not higher up) and gently turn it inside out, and use the inverted glove as a cloth to grab through to remove (roll off) the remaining glove. Learn to remove gloves without contamination!</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par27">Hand hygiene.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par28">The gown is taken off by opening behind the back (neck)—avoid touching the front and arms—pull the cuffs over the hands, and roll the gown gently along from the sides and from above downwards without touching the outer side. Place gently in the waste bag.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par29">Hand hygiene.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par30">Remove surgical mask/cap by loosening back on the head—not touching the front.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par31">The hands are finally washed with soap and water.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par32">Use eventually a “cloth” with chloramine 5% in the sluice for wiping off the shoes. Replace this for each shift.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par33">
    <italic>Norovirus and other intestinal pathogenic viruses</italic> attach easily to the skin [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] There may be a failure effect of both handwash and hand disinfection.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par34">
    <italic>Handwash with soap and water</italic> may work probably better than hand disinfection and is therefore used for norovirus [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>–
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Always wear gloves when there is suspected gastrointestinal infections, and perform hand hygiene before and after use of gloves!
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par35">
    <italic>Personnel</italic> with symptoms report sickness and stay at home for at least 2 days after symptom freedom [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par36">
    <italic>Inform</italic> all personnel and visitors.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par37">
    <italic>Visitors</italic> should follow procedures for using PPE and hand hygiene and should not stay in common rooms, corridors, etc. together with other patients/visitors. They may be infected with the same microbiological agent and spread the infection in the department. Visitors with symptoms should be at home until 2–3 days after freedom of symptoms (except for relatives of children and critically ill).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par38">
    <italic>Limit general access</italic>, and avoid thoroughfare.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par39">
    <italic>Limit surveys/treatment</italic> of the actual patients at other departments while the outbreak is going on.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
