<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As some patients with Covid‐19 show an inefficient antiviral response, it has been suggested that immunomodulators might restore the immune system homeostasis. For instance, interferon (IFN) could be used during the early stages of infection to boost the innate immune response and promote viral clearance. IFN treatments are being tested in several clinical trials, but results are not available yet. However, as SARS‐CoV‐2 infection may also be accompanied by a dysregulated immune response leading to a massive production of pro‐inflammatory cytokines, IFN treatment could have unexpected effects.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0083" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>83</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0084" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>84</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0085" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>85</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0086" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>86</sup>
 </xref> Indeed, IFN triggers overexpression of ACE2, even in cell lines with low basal expression level, leading to a larger dissemination of SARS‐CoV‐2.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0087" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>87</sup>
 </xref> Conversely, in the second phase of the disease, the use of molecules that limit the effect of the cytokine storm could be advantageous. For instance, the mAbs mepolizumab against interleukin (IL)‐5, tocilizumab against IL‐6 receptor,
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0088" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>88</sup>
 </xref> as well as anakinra an interleukin 1 receptor antagonist
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0089" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>89</sup>
 </xref> could control the immune response, and be of therapeutic interest for managing the production of pro‐inflammatory cytokines in patients with severe infection.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0090" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>90</sup>
 </xref> Finally, Dexamethasone, used to reduce inflammation, has been tested in RECOVERY clinical trial and shown first promising results. Indeed, treatment with Dexamethasone reduces death by one‐third to one‐fifth.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0091" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>91</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
