<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">Mosquito vector competence for arboviruses depends on several tissue barriers associated with the midgut and the salivary glands
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. The physiological and molecular nature of these barriers is poorly understood, but they are used as conventional phenotypes to characterize vector competence. IR informs on the midgut infection barrier (i.e., preventing infection of midgut epithelium), DR represents the midgut escape barrier (i.e., preventing virus exit from the midgut cells into the haemocoel), and TR relates to both salivary glands infection and escape barriers
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>. Our sylvatic colony of 
 <italic>Ae. malayensis</italic> was experimentally competent for DENV-1, but its overall TE ( = IR x DR x TR) was lower than that of the 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> control. This difference resulted from significantly lower IR and lower DR, but not lower TR (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). This pattern suggests that the lower vector competence of this 
 <italic>Ae. malayensis</italic> population compared to the 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> control is not primarily due to salivary glands barriers, but rather to midgut-related mechanisms hindering virus infection and dissemination. The pattern was different for YFV, for which all vector competence phenotypes were similar between the two species with the exception of IR (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). In our experiment, the same oral infectious dose of YFV infected about twice less 
 <italic>Ae. malayensis</italic> than 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>, whereas subsequently DR and TR did not differ significantly. Nevertheless, the low TR overall limited our ability to detect a difference between the two species. Further studies will be necessary to elucidate the mechanisms underlying differences in vector competence between 
 <italic>Ae. malayensis</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>.
</p>
