<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phylodynamic analyses were performed in BEAST v2.0 (
 <xref rid="msw217-B5" ref-type="bibr">Bouckaert et al. 2014</xref>) using the add-ons “bdsky” (
 <xref rid="msw217-B48" ref-type="bibr">Stadler et al. 2013</xref>), “SA” (
 <xref rid="msw217-B24" ref-type="bibr">Gavryushkina et al. 2014</xref>) and “bdmm” (
 <xref rid="msw217-B34" ref-type="bibr">Kühnert et al. 2016</xref>). Under the birth–death skyline model with sampled ancestors (“SA” module), individuals could transmit with some probability after sampling which improved estimation of the reporting variables in preliminary analyses (round 1 of the exercise). To estimate the proportion of early transmissions, the multi-type birth–death model was used with two compartments (“bdmm” module) to consider individuals in their first 3 months of infection separately from those in later stages of infection. In all analyses, time was partitioned into different intervals to obtain estimates of varying transmission rates through time. As further described in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary text S3, Supplementary Material</xref> online, for both Village and Regional simulations, lognormal priors were used for the effective reproductive number 
 <italic>(</italic>mu = 0 and sigma = 0.75) and the becoming-non-infectious rate (lognormal with mu = −1 and sigma 0.5). Uniform priors were used for the sampling proportion, and specified based on available meta-data. For the Village datasets 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 9, 10, 11 and 12, we assumed a priori a sampling proportion between 15% and 40%; for Village datasets 5, 6, 7 and 8 between 40% and 100%; and for the Regional datasets between 5% and 10%. The prior distribution for the removal probability 
 <italic>r</italic> was chosen based on an estimate of the proportion of sampled infected individuals that are on treatment, and calculated from available survey data before intervention start. Sensitivity analyses on these prior choices were conducted. The reporting variables were estimated from MCMC output of the posterior model parameters using a customized procedure that is fully described in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary text S3, Supplementary Material</xref> online.
</p>
