<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The N-terminal domain of EBOV NP, which contains the R111 residue, is necessary and sufficient to drive oligomerization of NP monomers into long, flexible helices. These oligomers help shape virions and coat viral RNA during the viral life cycle. Many studies have determined NP structures and modeled how NP interacts with itself and RNA [
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. In addition to a flexible oligomerization domain (OD) at the very N terminus of NP that is essential for oligomerization, numerous other residues appear to be involved in NP–NP interactions as visualized in cryo-electron microscopy (cryo-EM) of helical NP oligomers [
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Between vertically adjacent NP proteins, NP-K110 on one monomer appears to form a salt bridge with NP-E349 on another monomer [
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. No naturally occurring mutations have been shown to affect EBOV NP oligomerization, though the proximity of NP-R111 to the NP-K110 residue suggests that the NP-R111C substitution could affect oligomerization. Although many biochemical methods are available for assessing NP oligomerization in vitro, few assays exist to quantitatively measure oligomerization in live cells.
</p>
