<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0090">EBV is one the most common human viruses in the world, affecting more than 90% of the world's population. Its primary infection tends to be generally asymptomatic. However it could lead to infectious mononucleosis and, in the worst case, to various types of cancer. Its genome comprises genes encoding for six EBV nuclear proteins that are expressed only in the latent infection and sustain the viral episome maintenance.
 <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref> Studies on the characterization and role of G4s in EBV showed that the EBV-encoded nuclear antigen-1 (EBNA1), the viral protein pivotal to immune evasion, promotes viral DNA replication by interacting with RNA G4s and recruiting the cellular origin replication complex. The EBNA1 mRNA itself is enriched in folded G4s, which behave as 
 <italic>cis</italic>-acting modulators of viral mRNA translation, producing ribosome dissociation.
 <xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> EBNA1 mRNA G4s have also been found to regulate the endogenous presentation of EBNA1-specific CD8 + T-cell epitopes, seen in persistent infections.
 <xref rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>26</sup>
 </xref> The employment of G4 ligands has helped the investigation of the functional and biochemical characteristics of EBNA1. BRACO-19, for instance, stabilized the viral RNA G4 and, in infected lymphocytes, reduced EBV genome copy numbers. It also negatively modulated transcription levels of EBNA2 and EBNA3A, and inhibited EBNA1-dependent DNA replication.
 <xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> Another G4 ligand, pyridostatin (PDS), enhanced the stability of the EBV G4s, reducing EBNA1 synthesis level in a concentration-dependent way, both 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. As a result, EBV-infected cells were found to be less efficiently recognized by virus-specific T cells, although such a mechanism still needs to be elucidated. These data show that G4-mediated inhibition affects processes that are crucial for viral DNA replication,
 <xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>25</sup>
 </xref> reinforcing the importance of alternative DNA structures in the regulation of virus processes. The cellular protein nucleolin, which has been widely shown to bind G4s,
 <xref rid="bb0140" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>27</sup>
 </xref> recognizes and also binds viral EBNA1 mRNA G4s. As a consequence it downregulates EBNA1 expression and antigen presentation, counteracting EBV stealthiness. Such interactions can be targeted to modulate EBV progression: indeed the PhenDC3 G4 ligand was found to prevent nucleolin binding to EBNA1 mRNA G4s and to increase the endogenous EBNA1 levels in EBV-infected B cells and in cells derived from a nasopharyngeal carcinoma.
 <xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>28</sup>
 </xref> Following on from PhenDC3, variously substituted bis(acylhydrazones) derivatives have also been investigated for their ability to interfere with the nucleolin/EBNA1 mRNA G4s interaction. Two compounds, PhenDH2 and PyDH2, have been found to be more active and less toxic with respect to the lead compound.
 <xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>29</sup>
 </xref> However, it is worth noting that although many of the tested PhenDC3 analogues displayed strong 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> binding and stabilization of RNA G4s, only a few of them were able to interfere with EBV immune evasion. This result suggested that the ability to hamper nucleolin/EBNA1 interaction might require additional activities, independent from G4 stabilization. Indeed, different G4 ligands can generate opposite effects: this is the case of PDS, which, in contrast to PhenDC3, further suppressed EBNA1 mRNA translation,
 <xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>25</sup>
 </xref> as also demonstrated by quantitative proximity ligation assay.
 <xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>30</sup>
 </xref> All these data support the ability of EBNA1 G4s to operate as nucleolin-binding platform. A very recent study reported that they also promote nuclear retention,
 <xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>31</sup>
 </xref> but the relationship between the two processes needs further investigation. Notably, EBV nuclear antigens are involved in B-cells transformation, especially EBNA1, which is expressed in all EBV-related tumors.
 <xref rid="bb0165" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>32</sup>
 </xref> Therefore, it is tempting to speculate that the nucleolin/EBNA1 G4 complex could be involved in virus-related oncogenesis and it might be exploited as a pharmacological target to impair both virus and tumor progression.
</p>
