<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0105">The use of smart technologies has been the focal point of many researches worldwide. Especially in recent times the researchers are focusing on developing phone applications which track infected and potentially infected people in order to suppress the spread of COVID-19. The Pan-European Privacy Preserving Proximity Tracing (PEPP-PT) [
 <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] is a platform on whose development works a team of 130 researchers from 8 European countries. On the basis of this software national authorities remain free to decide how to inform persons that they were in contact with someone who was tested positive. World-renowned companies such as Apple and Google [
 <xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] are developing a smartphone platform that tracks the spread of COVID-19 by using proximity capabilities built into Bluetooth Low Energy transmissions, which enables the actual tracking of physical contacts of phone users who agreed to participate. The user who is tested positive for COVID-19 can enter the result into a health department-approved application. All other participating phone users who recently had a contact at the distance of approximately six feet with the infected user will be contacted by the application. During the largest Ebola epidemic in West Africa (2014–2016) researches developed an Ebola contact tracing (ECT) application for tracing contacts [
 <xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The authors compared results of the application developed with the existing paper-based system. Based on their research, the app-based contact tracing recorded 63 % of contacts of laboratory-confirmed cases, whereas paper-based contact tracing achieved the result of 39 % with often incomplete data. The developed smartphone application is linked to an alert central system to notify the District Ebola Response Centre of symptomatic contacts. The authors agreed that despite many challenges the use of application had benefits, such as improved data completeness, storage and accuracy.
</p>
