<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Oxidative stress and activation of TLRs can mutually promote and develop together. Oxidative stress can serve as a potential activator of TLRs [
 <xref rid="pone.0191793.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. In turn, activations of TLR2, TLR3, and TLR4 can increase lipid and protein oxidation levels [
 <xref rid="pone.0191793.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Activations of TLR2 and TLR4 can increase NADPH oxidase expression and activity [
 <xref rid="pone.0191793.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0191793.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Oxidative stress also can activate PI3K/Akt, MAPK, and NF-κB signaling pathways [
 <xref rid="pone.0191793.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0191793.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. IAV-induced oxidative stress and activations of TLRs, MAPK, and NF-κB signal pathways are essential for efficient IAV replication [
 <xref rid="pone.0191793.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0191793.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Blockade of IAV-induced Raf/MEK/ERK MAPK signal cascade can retard IAV ribonucleoprotein (RNP, consisting of PB2, PB1, PA, NP, and vRNA) export and reduce IAV titers [
 <xref rid="pone.0191793.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. JNK inhibitors SP600125 and AS601245 can decrease IAV amplification by suppressing viral protein and RNA synthesis [
 <xref rid="pone.0191793.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. NF-κB inhibitors can specifically diminish IAV vRNA transcription from the cRNA promoter [
 <xref rid="pone.0191793.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Activation of p38 is also needed for IAV replication [
 <xref rid="pone.0191793.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Beside these pathways, activation of PI3K/Akt pathway is also indispensable for IAV replication. Inhibition of Akt kinase activity can suppress the entry and replication of IAV and prevent IAV infection [
 <xref rid="pone.0191793.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0191793.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Many previous studies have reported that rhein can inhibit the activations of TLRs, MAPK, NF-κB, and PI3K/Akt pathways. Rhein can reduce LPS-induced TLR4 expression and inhibit NF-κB activation in colon tissue [
 <xref rid="pone.0191793.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Rhein can significantly decrease the expressions of TLR4 and MyD88 and inhibit the activations of NF-κB and JNK MAPK pathways in high-fat diet-induced obese male mice [
 <xref rid="pone.0191793.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Rhein can significantly inhibit the activations of PI3K/Akt, p-ERK, NF-κB and COX-2 pathways [
 <xref rid="pone.0191793.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], and significantly suppress the phosphorylation of ERK, p38 MAPK and activation of NF-κB in human nasopharyngeal carcinoma cells [
 <xref rid="pone.0191793.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. In our present study, we find that rhein can significantly decrease IAV-induced expressions of TLR2, TLR3, and TLR4, and suppress IAV-induced activations of Akt, p38/JNK MAPK and NF-κB pathways.
</p>
