<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Most of the important reemerging infectious disease agents first appeared long ago, but have survived and persisted by adapting to changing human populations and to environments that have been altered by humans. Dengue virus and West Nile virus (WNV), distantly related flaviviruses, serve as good examples. They have been spread by geographic movement of humans in association with the mosquito vectors for the diseases. For example, dengue came to the Americas in association with the slave trade of earlier centuries. In this regard, slaves infected by mosquitoes in Africa presumably brought the infection to the Americas by seeding the mosquito population upon arrival 
 <xref rid="ppat.1003467-Laughlin1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. Similarly, WNV came to the United States in 1999 when an infected human, bird, or mosquito came by air travel from the Middle East to the Western Hemisphere, providing a source for introduction of infection to New World mosquitoes and birds. Pathogenic strains of dengue have also spread back from Southeast Asia to the Western Hemisphere, as has a major mosquito vector, 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic>. Unlike most arboviruses, which are partly or completely host-restricted, WNV has become adapted to multiple mosquito and avian species, a major factor in increasing its opportunity to infect humans. The lack of additional hosts undoubtedly drove the mosquitoes that are the vectors of dengue and the dengue virus itself to favor adapting to humans and to their behaviors and environments. The association of dengue with 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitoes that live in and around human habitations mean that crowding, poor sanitation, and poverty provide ideal environments for transmission to humans 
 <xref rid="ppat.1003467-Laughlin1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. Host immunity factors are also thought to be involved in the severe/fatal form of dengue known as dengue shock syndrome 
 <xref rid="ppat.1003467-Laughlin1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>.
</p>
