<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This study showed that males were at a significantly higher risk of past exposure to RVF due to increased IgG prevalence than females. We speculate that men spend more time outdoors in contact with animals as they are herding, and exposure may have happened over time. This increases the risk of exposure to infectious mosquito bites since they usually do not have adequate protection. This is consistent with the findings by Anyangu et al., 2010, which reported a high proportion of acute RVFV infection and severe disease in males [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007979.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Similarly, the occupation of herding and pastoralism is dominated by males, which involves high risk animal-related activities like consuming or handling sick animal products, sheltering sick animals at home and away, birthing, slaughtering, milking, or skinning of dead or sick animals [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007979.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. On the contrary, due to lack of knowledge, women get infected as they take care of sick animals at home hence posing a significant risk of infection to them especially for rural women [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007979.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. RVFV prevalence was lower among the younger age groups [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007979.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007979.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Another study conducted in Kenya also observed that there was a significant association of RVFV seropositivity with age and that the odds of RVFV seropositivity in the elderly was twice that of the younger age group[
 <xref rid="pntd.0007979.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. In our study, increasing age was significantly associated with RVFV infection. This can be attributed to the cumulative effect of exposure over time and the possibility of the older population having been exposed to RVFV infected mosquitoes, sheltering of sick animals, slaughtering infected animals, contact with infected arbutus, disposal of infected fetus or previous exposure during the major outbreak in 1997/98 and 2006/2007 in these regions [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007979.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007979.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007979.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. We speculate that the younger age-group are also less likely to handle these infectious materials and hence the reduced likelihood of exposure. It is therefore possible that the high RVFV prevalence observed in all the sites between the year 2014 and 2015 could be due to the past large outbreaks experienced in Kenya in 1996/97 and 2006/2007 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007979.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007979.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].
</p>
