<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par89">Currently, there is no vaccine that prevents COVID-19. While human behaviors, including social distancing and proper hygiene that plagued the Spanish flu, remain a challenge in battling COVID-19, there is much clamor for evidence-based and science-supported treatments in the current pandemic. In particular, databases for registered clinical trials have been established allowing a much better translation of safe and effective approaches for COVID-19. The genome of the SARS-CoV-2 was sequenced in mid-January triggering researchers around the world to begin developing a vaccine [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>]. The first COVID-19 vaccine candidate began human clinical trial in mid-March (ClinicalTrials.gov: NCT04283461). As of April 8, 2020, there were 115 global COVID-19 vaccine candidates, 73 of which were currently at preclinical stages [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>]. Some of the more advanced candidates include mRNA-1273 developed by Moderna (NTC04283461), Ad5-nCoV developed by CanSino Biologicals (NCT04313127), and INO-4800 developed by Inovio (NCT04336410). These candidates have moved into clinical development. The vaccine development for COVID-19 has included a range of technology platforms. These include nucleic acid, recombinant protein, viral vector, among others. Platforms based on DNA or mRNA such as the vaccine being developed by Moderna offer flexibility in terms of antigen manipulation as well as a potential for speed. Moderna began clinical testing only 2 months after sequence identification. Platforms based on viral vectors offer a high level of protein expression, induce strong immune responses, and offer long term stability. Vaccines based on recombinant proteins can take advantage of other recombinant protein-based vaccines from other diseases giving them a large-scale production capacity (NCT04568988). Public information regarding the specific SARS-CoV-2 antigen used in vaccines is very limited. Many candidates who have revealed information aim to induce neutralizing antibodies against the viral SP. Targeting SP is crucial to developing a potent vaccine that blocks the virus from binding to ACE2 and entering host cells, thus preventing infection from occurring [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>]. Polyclonal murine antibodies against SP already effectively inhibit SARS-Cov-2 uptake in mice [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Knowledge of the exact molecular structure of SP will facilitate the development of human antibody-based vaccines that potently inhibit SP-mediated SARS-Cov-2 cell entry.
</p>
