<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Other flaviviruses such as Yellow fever virus and St. Louis encephalitis viruses do not encode a glycosylated E protein[
 <xref rid="pntd.0007473.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007473.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007473.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Furthermore, non-glycosylated SLEV maintains a lower oral infection threshold, i.e. has been shown to be more infectious, in 
 <italic>Culex</italic> mosquitoes when compared with WNV[
 <xref rid="pntd.0007473.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], again demonstrating that the N-linked glycosylation is not a requisite for flavivirus infection of and transmission by mosquitoes. Reports by others have also demonstrated variable vector competence rates with non-glycosylated WNV isolates[
 <xref rid="pntd.0007473.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007473.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] and in this study, with the exception of NYP and A’DEL all other non-glycosylated viruses were transmitted by 
 <italic>Cx quinquefasciatus</italic>. The effect of the different E154-156 mutations on avian viremia potential was variable and species-specific, indicating that different mutations could be competent for avian viremia generation in certain avian species. Despite having delayed viremia onset, even the A’DEL mutant was capable of eliciting avian viremia conducive for mosquito infection, although this mutant failed to demonstrate transmissibility in 
 <italic>Cx quinquefasciatus</italic>. Data presented herein indicates that WNV E154-156 motif amino identity, rather than specific N-linked glycosylation, dictates acute viral titers in birds and vector competence in mosquitoes and the effect of a particular E154-156 moiety expressed on WNV avian and vector competence was species-dependent. The isolation of many of these E-154-156 mutants in the field is intriguing and coupled with the findings here indicates the strong possibility that non-glycosylated WNV variants could circulate at relatively high frequency. The frequency of WNV genotypes to express a particular E-glycosylation motif (E154-E156) is likely due to selection pressures on viral replicative fitness by the dominant amplification host(s) and vectors utilized during local transmission events. Future studies should be designed to assess the potential fitness advantages for these variants in specific enzootic vectors and/or hosts.
</p>
