<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Current studies link gut microbiota to the development of obesity and its related comorbidities in the following aspects [
 <xref rid="B64-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. First, changes of gut microflora affect adipogenesis or the pathogenesis of obesity. It has been shown that healthy individuals have highly diverse gut microbiota than those with obesity. The association of some bacterial taxonomic groups with obesity and relevant comorbidities was observed such as lower content of Bacteroidetes in obese people and the association of Lactobacillus and Clostridium with insulin resistance. These findings indicate that the disorder of gut microflora could be a drive to obesity development. Second, germ-free (GF) animal models provide eloquent evidence to address the role of gut microbiota in obesity induction. Without gut microbiota colonization, GF mice were highly resistant to obesity induced by a high-fat diet than normal mice despite high food intakes. Furthermore, GF mice that received fecal microbiota transplantation (FMT) from an obese donor had higher weight gain than those receiving it from a lean donor. Misuses and overuses of antibiotics in the animal industry and human medicine impact on gut microbial ecology, leading to antibiotic resistance. Relevant studies using sub-therapeutic antibiotic treatment indicated that it selectively eliminated vulnerable taxonomic groups of the gut microbiome, thus altering microbiome composition that results in elevated hepatic metabolism of lipids and cholesterol in young mice [
 <xref rid="B64-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Mechanistically, gut microbiota affect obesity development in an inter-systemic manner. Locally in the gut, obesity-associated gut microbiota were selected for three properties: (1) a more efficient harvest of energy from the diet; (2) gene reprogramming to facilitate energy anabolism; and (3) secretion of bioactive molecules and hormones to affect host appetite. The decrease in gut microbiota diversity in obese individuals impaired the intestinal barrier function and disturbed immune homeostasis by inducing low-grade inflammation, which was considered an early trigger for adipogenesis [
 <xref rid="B64-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Along with microbiome decomposition, the microbial shedding molecules such as liposaccharides (LPS) induce further gut inflammation and immune-cell infiltration. Short-chain fatty acid (SCFAs) released by microbiota directly fuel insulin-mediated lipogenesis and promote adipocyte differentiation. Beyond the gut, the dysbiosis of gut microbiota also signals inflammation and hepatic T cell infiltration to manifest as fatty liver frequently associated with obesity. Gut microbiota can also directly signal gut afferent neurons and mediate the secretion of appetite hormones to regulate host metabolism through the gut–brain axis and an endocrine pathway [
 <xref rid="B66-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Therefore, collected evidence indicates that local alteration in gut microbiota will lead to systemic reprograming in energy and lipid metabolism, immune response, and endocrine functions that culminate in obesogenesis [
 <xref rid="B64-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>].
</p>
