<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>However, a majority of current studies about microbiota focus on cellular microbiome (including bacteria, archaea, fungi, and protozoa), but overlook the viral community (i.e., virobiota or virome) where it is at least ten-fold over more numerous than its cellular counterpart [
 <xref rid="B68-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Indeed, a human individual regardless of health status contains at least a dozen taxa of eukaryotic viruses and bacterial phages. While phages potentially affect obesity indirectly through modulating bacterial composition, eukaryotic viruses can directly interact with host cells to result in an ideal commensalism (symbiosis) or cause either symptomatic or asymptomatic pathogenesis (dysbiosis). Compared with wild-type mice, significantly higher viral contents were detected in the feces of obese mice. It was also indicated that increased viral content, particularly viral RNA, was tightly correlated with an increase of fat mass and potential hyperglycemia. Only total viral DNA/RNA mass was compared in this study, but the viral taxonomic classification was not performed using metagenomic approaches [
 <xref rid="B70-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. However, their data indicated that this obesity-correlated increase of viral content was mostly ascribed to phages [
 <xref rid="B70-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. This reinforces the points from several recent reviews that the gut virome is a missing link underlying human diseases like cancers and obesity [
 <xref rid="B68-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Further studies are needed to decipher the composition of gut commensal viruses and their role in obesogenesis through direct interaction on host cells [
 <xref rid="B67-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Despite the lack of studies to correlate certain viral taxonomic groups with obesity in humans and animals, they may have an overlapping spectrum with most persistent viruses associated with obesity (
 <xref rid="biomolecules-09-00726-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B13-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-biomolecules-09-00726" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>].
</p>
