<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For evaluating the potential of vaccines and therapeutics against CoVs, including SARS-CoV, MERS-CoVs, and the presently emerging SARS-CoV-2, suitable animal models that can mimic the clinical disease are needed (
 <xref rid="B211" ref-type="bibr">211</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B212" ref-type="bibr">212</xref>). Various animal models were assessed for SARS- and MERS-CoVs, such as mice, guinea pigs, golden Syrian hamsters, ferrets, rabbits, nonhuman primates like rhesus macaques and marmosets, and cats (
 <xref rid="B185" ref-type="bibr">185</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B213" ref-type="bibr">213</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B214">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B218" ref-type="bibr">218</xref>). The specificity of the virus to hACE2 (receptor of SARS-CoV) was found to be a significant barrier in developing animal models. Consequently, a SARS-CoV transgenic mouse model has been developed by inserting the hACE2 gene into the mouse genome (
 <xref rid="B219" ref-type="bibr">219</xref>). The inability of MERS-CoV to replicate in the respiratory tracts of animals (mice, hamsters, and ferrets) is another limiting factor. However, with genetic engineering, a 288-330
 <sup>+/+</sup> MERS-CoV genetically modified mouse model was developed and now is in use for the assessment of novel drugs and vaccines against MERS-CoV (
 <xref rid="B220" ref-type="bibr">220</xref>). In the past, small animals (mice or hamsters) have been targeted for being closer to a humanized structure, such as mouse DPP4 altered with human DPP4 (hDPP4), hDPP4-transduced mice, and hDPP4-Tg mice (transgenic for expressing hDPP4) for MERS-CoV infection (
 <xref rid="B221" ref-type="bibr">221</xref>). The CRISPR-Cas9 gene-editing tool has been used for inserting genomic alterations in mice, making them susceptible to MERS-CoV infection (
 <xref rid="B222" ref-type="bibr">222</xref>). Efforts are under way to recognize suitable animal models for SARS-CoV2/COVID-19, identify the receptor affinity of this virus, study pathology in experimental animal models, and explore virus-specific immune responses and protection studies, which together would increase the pace of efforts being made for developing potent vaccines and drugs to counter this emerging virus. Cell lines, such as monkey epithelial cell lines (LLC-MK2 and Vero-B4), goat lung cells, alpaca kidney cells, dromedary umbilical cord cells, and advanced 
 <italic>ex vivo</italic> three-dimensional tracheobronchial tissue, have been explored to study human CoVs (MERS-CoV) (
 <xref rid="B223" ref-type="bibr">223</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B224" ref-type="bibr">224</xref>). Vero and Huh-7 cells (human liver cancer cells) have been used for isolating SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="B194" ref-type="bibr">194</xref>).
</p>
