<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Further, our work clearly shows that persistence of rabies in Central African Republic is favored by the non-trivial interplay of long-range movements of infected dogs with unusually long incubation periods. Thus, the virus can slowly diffuse in the country and the resulting continuous seeding of asynchronous rabies waves in distant settlements can efficiently counteract the local viral fade out while susceptibles are swiftly renewed elsewhere. This effect was already found in theoretical studies and in prior work addressing other diseases [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008317.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0008317.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. It was only recently considered for canine rabies persistence [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008317.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008317.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Moreover, this effect may be relevant for rabies in other carnivore species behaving in a similar way. It is indeed now evident that rabies virus has long evolved mechanisms to avoid extinction and successfully maintain itself in different reservoir host species during several thousand years, often in fragmented and poorly connected populations [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008317.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008317.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. The intensification and the change of scale of human-mediated dissemination starting in the 15th century only plaid a role in the rapid global spread and maintenance of rabies observed in the 18th and 19th century in the Americas, Africa, Asia and Europe [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008317.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. The prolonged incubation periods occurring in nature in dogs could then be an intrinsic factor of rabies virus pathogenesis that have constantly been selected and maintained during rabies virus genetic evolution as it played an instrumental role to ensure viral dispersion to new dog populations allowing the renewal of naïve domestic dog populations.
</p>
