<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27">In the paired comparisons, plasma IFNα and CCL4 were lower at the time of the reinfection. The fact that repeat episodes had lower IFNα and CCL4 even after excluding the only individual whose baseline syphilis represented an initial infection suggests that each additional episode of syphilis results in a more attenuated immune response than the previous episode. As noted above, this finding is weakened by the fact that in 10 out of 11 individuals the baseline episode of syphilis was not the individual’s first episode of syphilis. What we are comparing is earlier with later episodes of syphilis in the same individual. Our findings of lower plasma IFNα and CCL4 in later episodes of syphilis is commensurate with immunological and clinical findings from other studies. Previous studies have, for example, found that each subsequent diagnosis of syphilis is associated with a step-wise increase in peak RPR at the time of diagnosis, a faster decay in RPR but then a higher nadir RPR result following the episode of syphilis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. One of these studies found that the RPR result did not serorevert in any individuals with four or more episodes of syphilis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. A recent study has found a stepwise increase in the probability that syphilis presents asymptomatically with increasing numbers of episodes of syphilis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. These findings suggest that individuals with multiple episodes of syphilis may develop a degree of immunity to infection by 
 <italic>T. pallidum</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] and that each episode of syphilis has an additive effect in the development of immunity. Further studies are required to assess if the attenuated immune response is correlated with a lower bacterial load and hence infectivity. This would be relevant for studies modeling syphilis spread and might provide clues of use for 
 <italic>Treponema pallidum</italic> vaccine design.
</p>
