<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat.1007360.g008" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007360.g008</object-id>
 <label>Fig 8</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Flt3-L treatment during IAV infection partially protects against secondary pneumococcal infection.</title>
  <p>Mice were i.v. injected with 2μg of a control- or Flt3-L-encoding plasmid and 24h later, mice were infected with IAV. Four days post-influenza infection, mice were infected with 
   <italic>S</italic>. 
   <italic>pneumoniae</italic> (10
   <sup>3</sup> CFUs). (A) Mice were sacrificed 30h after 
   <italic>S</italic>. 
   <italic>pneumoniae</italic> challenge and the number of CFUs was determined in the lungs and spleen. The solid lines correspond to the median values. Data represent pooled results from two independent experiments (n = 16). (B-C) Mice were sacrificed 12h after 
   <italic>S</italic>. 
   <italic>pneumoniae</italic> challenge. (B) mRNA copy numbers of genes encoding Th17-related cytokines were quantified by RT-PCR. All RT-PCR data are normalized to expression of 
   <italic>Gapdh</italic> and are expressed as fold increase over average gene expression in Ctrl-plasmid/co-infected animals (n = 5). (C) Histological analysis of lung sections. 
   <italic>Left panel</italic>: Representative lung sections stained with hematoxylin and eosin are shown. Diffuse alveolar inflammation is marked with interstitial thickening in Ctrl-plasmid-treated animals but remains moderate in Flt3-L-treated animals. Lung images are shown at x4 magnification (
   <italic>upper panel</italic>) and black squares in lung images are shown at x40 magnification (
   <italic>lower panel</italic>). 
   <italic>Right panel</italic>: Blinded sections were scored for levels of alveolitis. Data represent the means ± SEM (n = 4 mice/group). (D) Body weight evolution (in % initial body weight) (means ± SD) and survival rate of co-infected mice treated or not with Flt3-L were monitored daily (n = 10). **, p &lt; 0.01; ***, p &lt; 0.001, ns: not significative.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1007360.g008" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
