<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The results of the spread within China of the SARS‐CoV‐2 are considerable and still unfolding. Given the timing of this outbreak, the inability of the Chinese government's measures to control this epidemic and limit most of these cases to Wuhan is understandable. The question then is, “What's next for China?” As earlier suggested, there remains considerable work to be done.
 <xref rid="jmv25738-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> This study includes many issues that can be determined in the short term as well as some that will require long‐term solutions. Some of these issues are as follows. The timing of colonization, infection, and shedding need to be determined. For example, are infected persons first colonized? Do infected persons shed virus before they have clinical symptoms? Transmission characteristics need to be determined. Is infectious transmission limited to respiratory droplets or can the virus be transmitted by contact with an infected person? Efficient human‐to‐human transmission is required for large‐scale spread (ie, an epidemic or pandemic) of any emerging virus. Therefore, the basic reproductive ratio during this epidemic needs to be determined; the basic reproductive ratio is defined as the average number of secondary cases that an infected person produces during their entire infectious period in a susceptible and uninfected population.
 <xref rid="jmv25738-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref> The case‐fatality rate needs to be accurately determined; the case‐fatality rate of the SARS‐CoV was around 11%. Some of these questions are already being addressed,
 <xref rid="jmv25738-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv25738-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>17</sup>
 </xref> but further work is needed. Often serology is required in such an epidemic to determine how many persons may have had clinically inapparent infections. Detection and identification methods that are accurate and can be performed in real time at the point of care or in the field need to be developed.
 <xref rid="jmv25738-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> The exact relationship between the SARS‐CoV‐2 and animals (eg, bats) needs to be determined.
 <xref rid="jmv25738-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv25738-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv25738-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref> Although bats are suspected, the question of how the virus has moved from bats to the human host needs to be resolved. Does this transmission involve intermediate animal hosts as occurred with SARS‐CoV and MERS‐CoV? If the SARS‐CoV‐2 proves to have an animal sources, the continued presence of live animal markets in China must be seriously questioned. In the long term, the development of vaccines and antiviral therapy needs to be a higher priority than it has been since the SARS pandemic in 2002 to 2003; the lack of a SARS vaccine or SARS antiviral therapy suggests that such research has not been a priority. For example, Ampligen (poly I:poly C124) has been shown to inhibit SARS‐CoV in a murine lung model, yet has not been further evaluated in humans.
 <xref rid="jmv25738-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref> Similarly, Remdesivir (GS‐5734) has been shown to inhibit both epidemic and zoonotic coronaviruses.
 <xref rid="jmv25738-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref> It is likely that continued investigation of new antiviral agents with activity against coronaviruses in the absence of ongoing active epidemics would be enhanced by government incentives. Another issue in the long term that needs to be addressed is the potential of novel coronaviruses to spread within medical centers to health care workers as has happened with SARS‐CoV and MERS‐CoV.
 <xref rid="jmv25738-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv25738-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv25738-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> Most medical centers, whether in China or in the United States, are not prepared for such a problem. For example, negative‐pressure containment rooms with proper anterooms are either not found or found only in limited numbers in medical centers in the United States.
 <xref rid="jmv25738-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>25</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
