<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<trans-abstract xml:lang="en">
 <title>Abstract</title>
 <sec>
  <title>Introduction: </title>
  <p>
   <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> is an arbovirus vector, such as 
   <italic>Flavivirus, Alphavirus</italic>, 
   <italic>Bunyavirus</italic>, 
   <italic>Phlebovirus</italic>, 
   <italic>Orbivirus</italic> and 
   <italic>Picornavirus</italic>. Many are etiological agents of diseases in humans. Currently, 
   <italic>A. albopictus</italic> is in geographical expansion due to its adaptation to different environments and breeding sites. In Colombia this mosquito was first reported in 1998 and currently it has been registered in 10 departments.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Objective: </title>
  <p>To determine the presence of 
   <italic>A. albopictus</italic> in Yopal, Casanare.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Materials and methods: </title>
  <p>In a search of larvae of 
   <italic>A. aegypti</italic> in the industrial zone of Yopal adult mosquitoes of 
   <italic>A. albopictus</italic> were observed for the first time. Then, the inspection was carried out in the indoor and outdoor of houses in eight localities of the municipality, in which larvae and pupae were collected by inspection of breeding sites and adult females were captured by human landing catches.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results: </title>
  <p>Seven hundred and seventy-five larvae were identified, 71.5 % larvae of 
   <italic>A.aegypti</italic>, 24.8 % of 
   <italic>A. albopictus</italic>, 3.2 % of 
   <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> and 0.8 % of 
   <italic>C. coronator</italic> and 
   <italic>C. nigripalpus</italic>. Thirty-seven adult mosquitoes of 
   <italic>A. albopictus</italic> were collected. The most abundant breeding sites of this vector were tires.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusion: </title>
  <p>Given the presence of 
   <italic>A. albopictus</italic> we suggest to intensify the entomological surveillance system to detect new populations within the department and nearby areas. Attention should be given to artificial breeding sites located in areas close to the parking of vehicles of transport of foods, supplies, and machinery from areas with the presence of the vector.
  </p>
 </sec>
</trans-abstract>
