<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0035">The first SARS-CoV vaccine was an inactivated whole virus vaccine, developed by Sinovac Biotech, that was tested in 36 SARS-CoV seronegative healthy adults, aged 21–40 years, in a randomized, double-blinded, placebo-controlled trial in China (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2007</xref>). The vaccine was derived from a clinical strain of SARS-CoV, propagated in Vero cells, inactivated with beta propiolactone and subsequently purified. The antigen content of the vaccine was reported in SARS-CoV units (SU), measured in a passive indirect hemagglutination assay rather than by quantitation of protein. The inactivated vaccine was adsorbed to aluminum hydroxide and the control group received saline injections with aluminum hydroxide. The safety of the vaccine had been evaluated in animals, and the dose range and need for adjuvant was determined from preclinical evaluation in mice, rats, and rhesus monkeys. The study subjects were divided into three groups of 12 (6 males and 6 females) that received 16 SU or 32 SU of vaccine or placebo, given as two doses 28 days apart administered by intramuscular injection. The vaccine was well tolerated, with only mild local reactogenicity and transient transaminase elevation in 3 vaccinees and 1 placebo recipient. The immunogenicity endpoint of seroconversion in 85% of the vaccines on day 56 was achieved in both of the vaccine groups; 100% of the 16 SU group, 91.1% of the 32 SU group, and none of the placebo group seroconverted on day 56. The neutralizing antibody titers were reported in units with respect to a reference serum. The frequency of seroconversion and antibody titers improved with the second dose of vaccine; titers peaked 2 weeks after the second dose of vaccine and decreased 4 weeks later. Titers achieved in the vaccinees were about half of those observed in convalescent patients. The authors concluded that the vaccine was safe and immunogenic and warranted further evaluation to optimize the dose and schedule and to assess its efficacy (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2007</xref>).
</p>
