<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="d1e3420"> Comparison of the prediction by the three models and the viral load data suggests that SARS-CoV-2 infection might have a secondary target. Without the second target cell population, the model shows a single-phase viral load decline after the peak, which does not agree with the data in many patients. The secondary target of SARS-CoV-2 infection might be lymphocytes. Lymphocytopenia is a predominant feature of COVID-19 patients in which a large number of viral RNAs within lymphocytes were detected 
 <xref rid="b31" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b33" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. A recent study also found that SARS-CoV-2 can invade T lymphocytes via spike protein mediated membrane fusion 
 <xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. The molecular mechanism underlying the entry of SARS-CoV-2 into lymphocytes is not fully understood. Lymphocytes do not express ACE2, but SARS-CoV-2 has a polybasic furin-type cleavage site at the S1–S2 junction in the spike protein, which can intensify the capacity of virus to penetrate tissues with low ACE2 expression 
 <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b89" ref-type="bibr">[89]</xref>. Lymphocytes may also be infected via the assistance by other co-receptors. The tropism of SARS-CoV could be altered towards human immune cells enhanced by Fc gamma II receptor 
 <xref rid="b90" ref-type="bibr">[90]</xref>. The initiation of seroconversion in COVID-19 patients is slightly earlier than in SARS-CoV infected patients 
 <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. This might facilitate the entry of SARS-CoV-2 into lymphocytes in humans. In addition to lymphocytes, SARS-CoV-2 may also infect some other cells. The virus replicates to a level in the lung where it hits a threshold for which virus spills over into the blood, causing a viremia. This viremia will allow the virus to travel to the gut where it can further replicate, as gut enterocytes have the ACE2 receptor and have been reported to be infected in human COVID-19 infection 
 <xref rid="b91" ref-type="bibr">[91]</xref>.
</p>
