<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The best-fit substitution models for PVY sequences were assessed using Mega 7 (
 <xref rid="vez037-B65" ref-type="bibr">Kumar, Stecher, and Tamura 2016</xref>), and found to be GTR + Г
 <sub>4</sub> + I (
 <xref rid="vez037-B106" ref-type="bibr">Tavaré 1986</xref>) for nucleotide sequences and LG + Г
 <sub>4</sub> + I (
 <xref rid="vez037-B69" ref-type="bibr">Le and Gascuel 2008</xref>) for their encoded amino acid sequences. Phylogenetic trees were inferred using the neighbor-joining (NJ) option in ClustalX (
 <xref rid="vez037-B49" ref-type="bibr">Jeanmougin et al. 1998</xref>), the SplitsTree method (
 <xref rid="vez037-B47" ref-type="bibr">Huson and Bryant 2006</xref>), and PhyML 3.0 (ML) (
 <xref rid="vez037-B38" ref-type="bibr">Guindon and Gascuel 2003</xref>). In PhyML, the statistical support for their topologies was assessed using the method of 
 <xref rid="vez037-B101" ref-type="bibr">Shimodaira and Hasegawa (1999)</xref>. Most isolate collection dates (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref>) were obtained from GenBank files or from personal communications (
 <xref rid="vez037-B31" ref-type="bibr">Gibbs et al. 2017</xref>). The presence of a linear temporal signal was checked using the TempEst program (
 <xref rid="vez037-B90" ref-type="bibr">Rambaut et al. 2016</xref>), and estimates of the date of the TMRCA obtained by the ‘Least Squares Dating’ (LSD) method of 
 <xref rid="vez037-B107" ref-type="bibr">To et al. (2016)</xref> using Version lsd-0.3beta. The presence of a non-linear temporal signal was checked, and the TMRCA estimated, using the probabilistic methods of BEAST v1.8.2 and Tracer v 1.6 (
 <xref rid="vez037-B18" ref-type="bibr">Drummond et al. 2012</xref>); for checking the signal, ten independently date-randomized replicates were obtained in BEAST analyses (
 <xref rid="vez037-B91" ref-type="bibr">Ramsden, Holmes, and Charleston 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vez037-B21" ref-type="bibr">Duchêne et al. 2015</xref>). Bayes factors (BFs) were used to select the best-fitting molecular-clock model and coalescence priors for the tree topology and node times. We compared strict and relaxed (uncorrelated exponential and uncorrelated lognormal) molecular clocks, as well as four demographic models (constant population size, expansion growth, exponential growth, and the Bayesian skyline plot). Posterior distributions of parameters, including the tree, were estimated from Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) samples taken every 10
 <sup>4</sup> iterations from a total of 10
 <sup>8</sup> iterations after discarding the first 10 per cent, and checked using Tracer v. 1.6 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/tracer/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/tracer/</ext-link>; 27 June 2019). The 'maximum clade credibility tree’ provided the TMRCA. Trees were drawn using Figtree Version 1.3 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/</ext-link>; 12 May 2018) and a commercial graphics package, and pairs of trees were compared using PATRISTIC (
 <xref rid="vez037-B25" ref-type="bibr">Fourment and Gibbs 2006</xref>) to test for mutational saturation and confirmed by the method of 
 <xref rid="vez037-B110" ref-type="bibr">Xia (2013)</xref>. The dates of nodes in trees were compared using the ratios of the mean pairwise patristic distances (
 <xref rid="vez037-B25" ref-type="bibr">Fourment and Gibbs 2006</xref>) of all sequences (i.e. tips) connected through individual nodes; the date of one node providing estimates of others in the same tree.
</p>
