<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Plant-based VLP vaccines can be produced from 
 <italic>Agrobacterium</italic>-mediated transient expression of influenza HA proteins in 
 <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>. Plant-made H1 or H5 VLPs mimicked the structure of influenza virions to some extent, they are immunogenic and elicit both humoral and cellular responses [
 <xref rid="B66-viruses-12-00518" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-viruses-12-00518" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Each HA-only particle contains 30–50 homo-trimer HA incorporated into lipid bilayer envelope of plant cell origin [
 <xref rid="B68-viruses-12-00518" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Plant-based recombinant VLP vaccines elicited humoral and cellular responses and protected against challenges. For example, a plant-derived VLP vaccine based on the HA of influenza H7N9 A/Hangzhou/1/2013 was prepared, with no other influenza proteins included in the vaccine. The immunogenicity of such H7-only VLP vaccine was assessed in mice and ferrets after one or two intramuscular dose(s) with, and without, adjuvant (alum or GLA-SE™). In ferrets, H7-specific cell-mediated immunity was also evaluated. The mice and ferrets were challenged with H7N9 A/Anhui/1/2013 influenza virus. A single immunization with the adjuvanted vaccine elicited a strong humoral response and protected mice against an otherwise lethal challenge. Two doses of unadjuvanted vaccine significantly increased humoral response and resulted in 100% protection with significant reduction in clinical signs, leading to nearly asymptomatic infections. In ferrets, a single immunization with the alum-adjuvanted H7 VLP vaccine induced strong humoral and CMI responses with antigen-specific activation of CD3(+) T cells. This plant-made H7 vaccine therefore induced protective responses after either one adjuvanted or two unadjuvanted doses [
 <xref rid="B39-viruses-12-00518" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Potentially, the plant-based transient expression system can allow the production of VLP structures, which contain HA only, without other influenza proteins.
</p>
