<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0145">The chemokine/chemokine receptor-related immune defenses are the main obstacles to be by-passed by viruses. Some chemokines play a direct anti-viral effect by inducing an array of phenomena that lead cells to determine an “anti-viral “state. These phenomena include activation of apoptosis or direct killing of infected cells by activated immune cells. Chemokines also recruit immune cells to the site of infection, which will fight against the intruder [
 <xref rid="bib0275" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Viral infections are associated with enhanced expression of several chemokines, in particular the interferons-inducible ones. Interferons, which can be produced by any mammalian cell, are involved in the rapid and efficient host innate response against viruses. A powerful IFN response triggered by the first contact with a virus can slow down viral multiplication and “buy time” for the organism to establish a more efficient adaptive immune response [
 <xref rid="bib0280" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. IFNs can stimulate surrounding cells to express potent antiviral proteins including enzymes, transcription factors, cell surface glycoproteins, cytokines and chemokines [
 <xref rid="bib0285" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0290" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Moreover, they can inhibit cell proliferation, regulate apoptosis and modulate the immune response [
 <xref rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Among interferons-induced molecules, the chemokine CXCL10 is currently regarded as a main player in the organism anti-viral response [
 <xref rid="bib0300" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], and particularly in respiratory tract infections. Several studies demonstrated that CXCL10 levels, as evaluated in serum, bronchial-alveolar washing fluid or nasal secretions, consistently correlate with the severity and duration of acute respiratory tract infection due to viral infections [
 <xref rid="bib0300" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0305" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0310" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>].
</p>
