<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We therefore developed a model-inference system that addresses the above challenges. The basic reproductive number 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> is a key epidemiological parameter describing the transmissibility of an infection, defined as the average number of secondary infections that arise from a primary infection in a naïve population. We thus first estimate, for each influenza type/subtype, the average 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> in each week of the year based on the average annual epidemic cycle, i.e. the empirical seasonal cycle. We then incorporate this 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> seasonal cycle (as the prior distribution) in the model-inference system to control for the seasonality observed in Hong Kong. For the second challenge, we combine the IF2 iterated filtering algorithm [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007989.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] with space re-probing [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007989.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007989.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], a technique that allows continuous exploring of state space. The combined SR-IF2 inference method coupled with the empirical seasonal multi-strain SIRS model is thus able to preserve the long-term epidemic feature while adeptly explore the state space to capture the epidemic dynamics. To estimate parameters in high dimensional state space, we take a multi-round inference strategy; in the first round, we parse the entire state space into subspaces and test each to find the optimal subspace; subsequent rounds then build on the previous one until the model estimates converge. Indeed, testing using model-generated mock epidemics indicates that this model-inference system and optimization strategy is able to recover the true model state variables and parameters (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1007989.s001">S1 Text</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1007989.s006">S2</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1007989.s007">S3</xref> Figs).
</p>
