<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our framework provides a data-driven approach to estimating ZIKA emergence risks from potentially sparse and biased surveillance data [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. By mapping observed cases to current and future risks, in the face of considerable uncertainty, the approach can also be used to design public health action plans and evaluate the utility of local versus regional triggers. We demonstrate its application across the 254 ecologically and demographically diverse counties of Texas, one of the two states that has sustained autochthonous ZIKV outbreaks [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. The approach requires local estimates of ZIKV importation and transmission rates. For the Texas analysis, we developed a novel model for estimating county-level ZIKV importation risk and applied published methods to estimate relative county-level transmission risks (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). We expect that most Texas counties are not at risk for a sustained ZIKV epidemic (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), and find that many of the highest risk counties lie in the southeastern region surrounding the Houston metropolitan area and the lower Rio Grande valley. However, 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> estimates are uncertain, leaving the possibility that the 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> could be as high as other high risk regions that sustained epidemics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Our analysis is consistent with historic DENV and CHIKV outbreaks and correctly identifies Cameron county, the only Texas county to have reported local transmission, as a potential ZIKV hot-spot, especially when November estimates are used [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] (Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S9).
</p>
