<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In total, 12 oleanane-type triterpenoid compounds (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-viruses-12-00225">Figure S1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00225-f001">Figure 1</xref>A), including oleanolic acid and its 11 derivatives, and their antiviral activities against H5N1 IAV infection in A549 cells were studied. Oleanolic acid was purchased from Chengdu Gelipu Biotechnology Co., Ltd. (Chengdu, China). Seven derivatives named OA-1, OA-2, OA-3, OA-4, OA-5, OA-6 and OA-7 were synthesized as described previously [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-12-00225" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Four new derivatives named OA-8, OA-9, OA-10 and OA-11, which were confirmed by data from nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) and high-resolution electrospray ionization mass spectrometry (HRESIMS) analysis (shown in the 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-viruses-12-00225">supplementary material</xref>), were synthesized by a method similar to that described previously [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-12-00225" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Briefly, the known saponin 3-(
 <italic>β</italic>-
 <sc>d</sc>-glucopyranosyl)-oleanolic acid benzyl ester or 3-(
 <italic>α</italic>-
 <sc>d</sc>-mannopyranosyl)-oleanolic acid benzyl ester was subjected to PivCl in the presence of pyridine to selectively protect the 3,6-OHs of the 
 <italic>β</italic>-glucopyranosyl or 
 <italic>α</italic>-mannopyranosyl residue, and subsequent glycosylation of the 2, 4-OHs in sugars with 2,3,4-tri-
 <italic>O</italic>-acetyl-L-rhamnopyranosyl trichloroacetimidate using TMSOTf as the promoter, followed by deprotection of the acyl groups with NaOH to produce two tridesmosidic oleanolic acid benzyl ester saponins, respectively. Hydrogenolysis of the above oleanolic acid benzyl ester saponins over palladium/carbon in THF-MeOH led to OA-9 and 3-O-
 <italic>β</italic>-chacotriosyl oleanolic acid, was carried out to furnish OA-10 or OA-11 by four consecutive acetylation, acyl chlorination, amide condensation reaction and alkaline hydrolysis, respectively. The purities of all oleanane-type triterpenoids were ≥98% by HPLC analysis. Ribavirin hydrochloride was purchased from Guangdong Starlake Bioscience Co. Ltd. (Zhaoqing, China) with purities ≥ 99%. Peramivir in sterile 0.9% NaCl solution (0.3 g/100 mL) was purchased from Guangzhou Nucien Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd. (Guanzhou, China). Arbidol hydrochloride was purchased from Dalian Melun Biological Technology Co., Ltd. (Dalian, China) with purities ≥98%. Oleanane-type triterpenoids were dissolved in dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) and diluted with PBS to &lt;0.4% DMSO for in vitro experiments. Ribavirin hydrochloride was dissolved in PBS for in vitro experiments.
</p>
