<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0003">HIV is a virus that attacks the immune system of the human. Untreated HIV breaks and kills CD4 cells, which are a type of immune cell called T cells. Over time, as HIV kills more CD4 cells, the body is more likely to get various types of infections and cancers. In this study, we investigate another virus called HIV-1 
 <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, which is the most serious one. Based on Dr. Amesh Adalja, 
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref> statistical study, thirty-four million people have died of the HIV-1 since the disease was first discovered in the 1980s. However, the powerful antiviral drugs have made it possible to live with HIV for some years. Despite discovering the powerful antiviral drugs, several countries with low-and middle-income are still suffering from HIV, where 95% of new HIV infections occur. Almost more than two-thirds of the people suffering from HIV worldwide live in Africa, where nearly one in every twenty-five adults in Africa has a positive HIV. All these reasons have forced many researchers in bio-mathematics to form a mathematical model of this virus to study the exact and numerical solutions which present a clear image about dynamical behavior 
 <xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. Modeling and simulation of HIV with CD4 Cells by differential equations are reported in many papers 
 <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Guedj et al. studied the practical parameters that affect the transmission and spread of the HIV, with T-cells, in a model of HIV dynamics based on a system of non-linear Ordinary Differential Equations (ODE) 
 <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. Global behavior of delay differential equations model of HIV infection with apoptosis was investigated 
 <xref rid="bib0034" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. Other papers addressed the control and stability analysis of the spread and transmission of HIV virus 
 <xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0036" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>.
</p>
