<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To extract DNA from swab samples, we used an ammonium acetate DNA protocol (
 <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Bruford et al., 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Eastwood et al., 2015</xref>) which we modified for swabs. Modifications were as follows: swabs were heated to 56 °C for five minutes to inactivate potential zoonotic pathogens (
 <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Rush &amp; Timms, 1996</xref>). Swabs were then transferred into fresh tubes containing 250 µl Digsol buffer, and 10 µl Proteinase K were added, followed by an overnight incubation at 37 °C. Then, 300 µl 4M ammonium acetate was added, and samples were centrifuged at 18k g for 25 min. The resulting supernatant was transferred into a fresh tube and centrifuged for 10 min to remove the last remains of swab cotton wool. 1 ml of 100% ethanol was added, and the mixture centrifuged for 15 min. The 100% ethanol was removed and 500 µl of 70% ethanol added to rinse the DNA pellet, then the mix was centrifuged for 10 min. The ethanol was then aspirated and the DNA pellets were left to dry by leaving the Eppendorf tubes upright and open, covered with sterile wipes, in a 25 °C heat block for three hours. Then 100 µl TE buffer was added and the samples were frozen at −20 °C until analysis. We ran extraction controls for a subset of 92 blood samples. None of these extraction controls tested BFDV-positive, suggesting that no lab contamination occurred (see Discussion). The extractions for blood samples, nest swabs and cloacal swabs were done by the same two persons, in the same lab and under the same conditions, so we do not think it is likely that a significant level of lab contamination occurred. Initial trials revealed possible inhibitors in the DNA solution, as none of the nest swabs in these trials, including a sample with added BFDV DNA, tested as BFDV-positive. The extracted DNA samples were then cleaned by spinning them in Zymo OneStep Inhibitor Removal columns (Zymo Research, Irvine, USA) for subsequent analyses.
</p>
