<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The DIR and TER data suggests that the salivary glands of 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> vectors may lead to barriers to CHIKV transmission that vary with mosquito and viral genetics. Our data demonstrated that 93–100% of mosquitoes had salivary gland infections but only 33–86% of saliva samples were positive for the two CHIKVs. This difference was more pronounced in 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> than 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>. We also measured saliva volume from 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and saw little correlation between the volume of expectorate and virus titer. SGEBs have been reported for La Crosse (LACV) and Sindbis virus transmission by 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> and 
 <italic>Culex</italic> species, respectively [
 <xref rid="B36-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. For example, 
 <italic>Aedes hendersoni</italic> was shown to be an incompetent vector of LACV due to a SGEB in which the salivary glands were infected but the mosquito failed to transmit the virus orally [
 <xref rid="B39-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. More recently, a SGEB has been reported that affects Rift Valley Fever virus transmission [
 <xref rid="B40-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Molecular mechanisms that explain SGEB for arboviruses will probably include a combination of vector and viral genetic factors that determine the efficiency of arbovirus transmission from a vector population. Arbovirus infection of salivary glands typically begins in the distal lateral lobes [
 <xref rid="B41-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Certain arboviruses such as CHIKV infect the proximal lateral and median lobes of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> [
 <xref rid="B42-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] and following replication, virus deposits in the apical cavities of acinar cells, which can lead to inoculation of a susceptible host upon refeeding [
 <xref rid="B44-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. We demonstrated here that TER in 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> vary according to the origins of mosquito populations tested and the CHIKV strain.
</p>
