<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The first generation of the EWARS tool identified evidence-based meteorological, epidemiological and entomological indicators predicting a forthcoming outbreak [
 <xref rid="pone.0196811.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. These indicators were later tested across ten districts in each of the three participatory countries in the prospective study: Brazil, Malaysia and Mexico. The information on the plausibility of applying the tool in routine surveillance, user-friendliness and “lessons learned” were collected through a self-applied questionnaire following a seven to ten-months testing period, from December 2016 to February 2017. This was complemented by data from personal semi-structured interviews. Participants in these interviews were staff members from the vector control, epidemiology and health promotion units covering all localities/ districts where the EWARS tool is being implemented. Among the participants are biologists, physicians and social communicators. In Mexico, all staff from different components of dengue surveillance and response were invited to voluntarily and anonymously conduct the semi-structured interviews through organized meetings. In Brazil and Malaysia, however, all recruited staffs were sent these semi-structure interviews via email. These interviews included 17 open-ended questions covering the different components of the EWARS tool and health officers’ opinions/ satisfaction regarding its prospective application. Qualitative content analysis was used as methodology. Concepts were obtained from the interviews and systematically compared with the rest of interviews using a technique from the Grounded Theory, i.e. the constant comparisons technique [
 <xref rid="pone.0196811.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. These concepts were compared and grouped throughout the interviews accounting for patterns and variations. The references selected are representative of the most frequently shared concepts that arose from the interviews. Participation was voluntary and confidentiality was assured to the participants; no personally identifiable information was recorded.
</p>
