<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A 
 <sc>re-emergence of</sc> Rift Valley fever (RVF) in livestock was observed on the island of Mayotte in 2008–2010. Since then, the virus may have circulated at a low level, indicating a current interepidemic period (Métras et al. 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). The mechanisms and reservoirs for RVF virus persistence between epidemics still remain unclear. Although vertical transmission in 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> spp. mosquitoes has been demonstrated (Linthicum et al. 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">1985</xref>), it is possible that wild mammals could play a role in virus persistence (Olive et al. 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Understanding the role of wildlife, therefore, remains an important question (Bird and McElroy 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Mayotte is small (374 km
 <sup>2</sup>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>), with only a few wild mammalian species described, such as bats (
 <italic>Pteropus seychellensis comorensis</italic>, 
 <italic>Chaerephon pusillus</italic>, and 
 <italic>C. leucogaster</italic>), rodents (
 <italic>Rattus rattus</italic> and 
 <italic>Mus musculus</italic>), tenrecs (
 <italic>Tenrec ecaudatus</italic>), civets (
 <italic>Viverricula indica</italic>), shrews (
 <italic>Suncus madagascariensis</italic>), and lemurs (
 <italic>Eulemur fulvus</italic>) (brown lemur, Order 
 <italic>Primates</italic>, Family 
 <italic>Lemuridae</italic>). Previous studies in wildlife indicated that bats and micromammals could be involved in RVF epidemiology (Olive et al. 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Serological evidence of past arboviral infections in lemurs, such as Chikungunya or Flaviviruses (Fontenille et al. 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">1988</xref>, Vourc'h et al. 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), has been found from Madagascar and Mayotte, suggesting that mosquitoes and especially 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> spp. can bite these animals and infect them with other pathogens, such as RVF virus. In Mayotte, in 2012, 50 lemurs, living on the M'bouzi islet (separate from Mayotte main island, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>), were found serologically negative for RVF antibodies (Lernout et al. 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). As this islet is not inhabited by humans nor domestic animals, exposure to RVF during the 2008–2010 epidemic was not expected. In this study, we investigated whether the population of brown lemurs from the main island of Mayotte had been exposed to RVF during the past epidemic, and whether they could play a role in virus persistence during an interepidemic period.
</p>
