<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<app-group>
 <app id="app1-viruses-12-00287">
  <title>Supplementary Materials</title>
  <p>
   <bold>Supplementary Materials S1</bold> Geographical maps illustrating the sampling locations. Maps were generated by R (version 3.4.4) packages “ggplot2” and “tidyverse”. 
   <bold>Supplementary Materials S2</bold> Bioinformatic command lines and parameters used in RNAseq data analysis. 
   <italic>
    <bold>Supplementary Materials S3</bold>
   </italic> List of primers used in this work. 
   <bold>Supplementary Materials S4</bold> Structures of the newly identified viral genomes Structures of Scaphoideus titanus permutotetra-like virus 1 and Scaphoideus titanus toti-like virus 1 are illustrated in 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00287-f002">Figure 2</xref>. In this figure we specifically illustrated the iflavirus assembled from the St_IT1 library. Boxes represent boundaries of ORFs. Conserved domains and families identified by Pfam (
   <uri xlink:href="https://pfam.xfam.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://pfam.xfam.org/</uri>) are reported within the polyproteins of the two iflaviruses: Waikav: Waikavirus capsid protein 1, Rhv: picornavirus capsid protein, CRPV: CRPV capsid protein like, 3C: 3C-like cysteine protease, RdRp: RNA-dependent RNA polymerase. List of of other abbreviations used in the figure: Hyp prt: hypothetical protein, Capsid prt: capsid protein, trypsin Ser protease: trypsin-like serine protease, NS prt: non-structural protein. 
   <bold>Supplementary Materials S5</bold> Maximum likelihood phylogeny of Scaphoideus titanus iflavirus 1 and Scaphoideus titanus iflavirus 2 within the “Iflaviridae-Secoviridae related cluster”. Sequence names and codes are those provided by Shi et al. [
   <xref rid="B28-viruses-12-00287" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The scale bar indicates the evolutionary distance for amino acid substitutions per site. The newly identified viruses are shown in red. 
   <bold>Supplementary Materials S6</bold> Maximum likelihood phylogeny of Scaphoideus titanus sobemo-like virus 1 and Scaphoideus titanus sobemo-like virus 2 within the “Luteo-Sobemo” clade. Sequence names and codes are those provided by Shi et al. [
   <xref rid="B28-viruses-12-00287" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The scale bar indicates the evolutionary distance for amino acid substitutions per site. The newly identified viruses are shown in red. 
   <bold>Supplementary Materials S7</bold> Maximum likelihood phylogeny of Scaphoideus titanus permutotetra-like virus 1 within the “Permutotetra” clade. Sequence names and codes are those provided by Shi et al. [
   <xref rid="B28-viruses-12-00287" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The scale bar indicates the evolutionary distance for amino acid substitutions per site. The newly identified virus is shown in red. 
   <bold>Supplementary Materials S8</bold> Maximum likelihood phylogeny of Scaphoideus titanus bunya-like virus 1 within the “Bunya-Arena” clade. Sequence names and codes are those provided by Shi et al. [
   <xref rid="B28-viruses-12-00287" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The scale bar indicates the evolutionary distance for amino acid substitutions per site. The newly identified virus is shown in red. 
   <bold>Supplementary Materials S9</bold> Maximum likelihood phylogeny of Scaphoideus titanus toti-like virus 1 within the “Toti-Chryso” clade. Sequence names and codes are those provided by Shi et al. [
   <xref rid="B28-viruses-12-00287" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The scale bar indicates the evolutionary distance for amino acid substitutions per site. The newly identified virus is shown in red. 
   <bold>Supplementary Materials S10</bold> Maximum likelihood phylogeny of Scaphoideus titanus reo-like virus 1 within the “Reo” clade. Sequence names and codes are those provided by Shi et al. [
   <xref rid="B28-viruses-12-00287" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The scale bar indicates the evolutionary distance for amino acid substitutions per site. The newly identified virus is shown in red. 
   <bold>Supplementary Materials S11</bold> Maximum likelihood phylogeny of Scaphoideus titanus associated partiti-like virus 1 within the “Partiti-Picobirna” clade. Sequence names and codes are those provided by Shi et al. [
   <xref rid="B28-viruses-12-00287" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The scale bar indicates the evolutionary distance for amino acid substitutions per site. The newly identified virus is shown in red. 
   <bold>Supplementary Materials S12</bold> Sequences of potential endogenous viral elements (EVEs) found in the European RNA-Seq libraries. Each sequence header reports the internal code assigned to the sequence, the best blastx hit and the library code the sequence was identified from. Binding positions of the primers used in PCR to demonstrate the integration into 
   <italic>S. titanus</italic> genome (see Supplementary Materials S3) are highlighted in yellow.
  </p>
 </app>
</app-group>
