<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Humans are highly vulnerable to the threats of infectious diseases imposed by climate change. Therefore, humans themselves must play a prime role in the adaptation and implementation of proactive measures for the alleviation of adverse health influences of climate change. Researchers have confirmed that the effects of changing climate variables throw more challenges and problems in some communities and societies than others. Hence, instead of global projections, regional projections for climate variables are required for minimizing health implications. In addition, due to lack of resources and abilities, specific areas and certain populations are more prone to the associated risks and challenges. There is the utmost requirement of teamwork between healthcare providers, scientific researchers and governments in developing as well as developed countries to work towards the upliftment of underprivileged societies. This can significantly reduce the vulnerability of incapable societies towards elevated health risks linked with climate change. The exposure of infectious diseases to humans can be reduced significantly through effective adaptation measures and positive human responses against climate change; for example, frequent allocation of required resources related to finance and health care and promotion of awareness programs. Integration of health surveillance with terrestrial and marine monitoring systems may prove more beneficial through advanced satellite imaging and forecasts. Effective early alert systems combined with integrated mapping of consequences, expenses and conditions can facilitate efficient public health mediation with proper designing of policies. Human capability to counter the negative health effects posed by climate change depends heavily on the generation of relevant, reliable and accurate information. Strengthening scientific, technological, and informational capacity within local and regional levels can be crucial for the establishment of a rejuvenated public health movement. This capacity enhancement can significantly reduce vulnerability and induce resilience in infrastructures at local, regional and national levels. </p>
