<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Researchers pursuing scientific investigations on climate change and related health risks can be primarily divided into three groups: The first group examines complex issues employing experimental and modeling studies to predict the possible relationship between health risks and climate variables—trying to figure out all possible alternatives to minimize the potential risk of human diseases associated with any change in climatic conditions. The second group of researchers seeks to calculate which climatic variables and to what extent may prove beneficial for a group of disease pathogens, vectors and mode of transmission. The last group deals with extreme weather events and related economic losses. This group also thoroughly analyses the elevated psychological health risks post each extreme weather event. The limited communication and lack of collaboration among these sections have resulted in a void between understanding of climatic variables and the forecast of changing the landscape for human diseases. This can also be seen through various contradictions between authors in their outcomes. As discussed earlier, there is the strong need for precise and accurate prediction for any change in climate variables and to timely identify all possible health risks. Therefore, to improve weather predictions and human adaptation capability, all aforementioned research groups should work under the same umbrella. If not, external support should be provided to enhance effective collaboration and effortless communication so that any negative health effect can be minimized. Furthermore, as multidisciplinary and a variety of approaches are involved in the mitigation processes, a much broader view is required to provide in-depth knowledge and understanding of the correlations between climatic variables and human health. For any detailed research, high-quality and precise modeling is a prerequisite. Time series models such as Error Correction Models (ECM), Auto Regressive Moving Average with exogenous variables (ARMAX), and non-parametric forecasting models; panel data and spatial models such as spatial lag and spatial error models, fixed and random effect models, and dynamic panel data models; and non-statistical approaches such as Computable General Equilibrium (CGE), Comparative Risk Assessments models (CRA), and Integrated Assessment Models (IAMs) are some of the models that need to be properly used wherever required. This will not only help in converging the gap in the present state of understanding but can also provide more realistic data suitable for accurate predictions for any consequences. </p>
