<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Climate change is reported to be responsible for millions of deaths and billions of major or minor disabilities since its start in the 1970s [
 <xref rid="B159-ijerph-16-02799" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>,
 <xref rid="B160-ijerph-16-02799" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>]. The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) also predicted that the existing human health risks will be exacerbated in the coming decades [
 <xref rid="B161-ijerph-16-02799" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>]. Climate change-associated dilemmas such as droughts, floods, heatwaves, fires, water and vector-borne diseases, water scarcity, and shortage of food pose serious threats and will continue to target more vulnerable groups like the poor, children, pregnant women and the elderly [
 <xref rid="B162-ijerph-16-02799" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>,
 <xref rid="B163-ijerph-16-02799" ref-type="bibr">163</xref>]. In this century, adverse health impacts due to climate change will continue to rise; a few diseases may disappear, but a majority will emerge and transmit more rapidly. The most effective approach to reducing climate change induced health risk is through adaptation of proper measures, which can be identified through scientific investigations and social advances. Scientific understandings are required to move beyond the empirical observations to connect the links between climate shift and emerging diseases, and to reach more reliable conclusions. These approaches need accurate information about the climate change related outcome of health implications. Moreover, advanced modeling and simulation techniques are required for proper long-term analysis of climate change-based spatiotemporal processes. Being dexterous in figuring this arduous process can be the foundation of accurate prediction of health consequences of climate change and the espousal of efficient adaptation measures. Finally, for such advancements, new protocols will be required for safe and effective sharing of information, resources, and awareness campaigns.
</p>
