<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0210">Viral load is a critical contributor in the pathogenesis of influenza diseases. Erucic acid presented efficiency against several strains of human influenza viruses, including A/PR/8/34 (H1N1), A/GZ/GIRD07/09 (H1N1), A/HK/8/68 (H3N2), A/HK/Y280/97 (H9N2) and A/Duck/Guangdong/1994 (H7N3) (
 <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Its antiviral properties were confirmed by plaque reduction and progeny virus yield reduction assays (
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figs. 2</xref>A and B). In addition, virus titers and viral antigens were decreased in mice treated with erucic acid (
 <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figs. 7</xref>F and G). In vitro and in vivo experiments demonstrated that inhibition of NF-κB and p38 kinase signaling pathways inhibited viral replication [
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Treatment with specific NF-κB or p38 kinase inhibitors blocked nuclear-cytoplasmic translocation of viral ribonucleoproteins and thereby reduced virus titers [
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Inhibition of the NF-κB signaling pathway effectively impairs transcriptional activities of the viral polymerase complex [
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In this study, data revealed that erucic acid treatment suppressed the influenza virus-mediated activation of NF-κB and p38 MAPK signaling in vitro and in vivo (
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>A). Additionally, viral polymerase transcription activity was reduced further by co-treatment with erucic acid and NF-κB or p38 MAPK inhibitors (
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>C). Therefore, it was proposed that inhibition of influenza virus-mediated activation of the NF-κB and p38 MAPK signaling pathways by erucic acid resulted in decreased transcriptional activities of the viral polymerase complex, thereby inhibiting viral replication. Based on these observations, it is probable that the anti-viral property of erucic acid was a result of reducing transcriptional activities of the viral polymerase complex via inhibition of NF-κB and p38 kinase signaling.
</p>
