<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The occurrence of human cases usually depends on a high infection rate in the mosquito vector population. This is necessary for transmission to be high enough for spill-over cases from birds, which are the natural vertebrate host of these viruses, to humans, which are considered dead-end hosts. Surveillance of mosquitoes for viruses is therefore often utilized as an early warning system for human epidemics. The lack of detection of SINV in 7746 
 <italic>Cx. pipiens/torrentium</italic> mosquitoes in southern Sweden in 2007, can be compared to the infection rate in an endemic area in Sweden in 2009 where 14/668 
 <italic>Cx. pipens/torrentium</italic> were infected with SINV [
 <xref rid="CIT0011">11</xref>]. This shows that vectors in southern Sweden are infected with SINV much more seldom than in central and northern Sweden, which might explain the lack of cases in the southern regions. In addition, an earlier study [
 <xref rid="CIT0020">20</xref>] that focused on species determination of 
 <italic>Cx. pipiens</italic> and 
 <italic>Cx. torrentium</italic> showed that 92% of the adult 
 <italic>Culex</italic> mosquitoes caught in Kristianstad in 2007 were 
 <italic>Cx. pipiens</italic>. In endemic areas further north in Sweden, 
 <italic>Cx. torrentium</italic> is the dominating 
 <italic>Culex</italic> species, comprising over 80% of the 
 <italic>Culex</italic> population [
 <xref rid="CIT0020">20</xref>]. 
 <italic>Cx. torrentium</italic> is also infected with SINV significantly more often than 
 <italic>Cx. pipiens</italic> (infection rates of 36/1000 and 8/1000, respectively) [
 <xref rid="CIT0011">11</xref>]. In central European countries like Germany, 
 <italic>Cx. torrentium</italic> seldom makes up more than 50% of the 
 <italic>Culex</italic> population [
 <xref rid="CIT0021">21</xref>]. This indicates that a high abundance, reaching 80% or more, of 
 <italic>Cx. torrentium</italic> might be necessary for the epidemic spread of SINV to humans to occur.
</p>
