<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Dengue virus is a mosquito-borne flavivirus and the most widely prevalent arbovirus in tropical and subtropical regions of Asia, Africa, and Central and South America (Gubler 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">1997</xref>). Four distinct serotypes, i.e., DEN-1, DEN-2, DEN-3, and DEN-4, produce a spectrum of illness ranging from in apparent infection to moderate febrile illness and severe, fatal hemorrhagic disease. The three basic methods routinely practiced by most laboratories are virus isolation, characterization, detection of dengue virus-specific antibodies, and detection of genomic sequences by nucleic acid amplification techniques (Guzman and Kouri 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">1996</xref>; Innis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">1989</xref>; WHO 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR178">1997</xref>). Both virus isolation and PRNT assays are time-consuming and tedious and require more than a week for completion. Several investigators have reported on fully automatic real-time PCR assays for the detection of dengue virus in acute-phase serum samples (Callahan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2001</xref>; Houng et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2001</xref>; Laue et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">1999</xref>; Seah et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR152">1995</xref>). During the past decade, various nucleic acid amplification techniques such as RT-PCR, nested PCR, Taqman real-time RT-PCR, SYBR Green I real-time RT-PCR, and NASBAs have been developed for the rapid identification of dengue virus to the serotype level with more accuracy (Kuno 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">1998</xref>; Lanciotti et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">1992</xref>; Morita et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">1991</xref>; Seah et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR152">1995</xref>; Sudiro et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR161">1997</xref>). Magnitude of amplification can be obtained easily by these PCR-based methods, but they require either high-precision instruments for the amplification or elaborate methods for detection of the amplified products. In addition, these methods are often cumbersome to adapt to routine clinical use, especially in peripheral health care settings and private clinics. Parida et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR123">2005</xref>) developed RT-LAMP assay for reducing time required for the confirmation of the detection of dengue virus. LAMP assay detects dengue virus within 30 min only (less than 1 h), whereas RT-PCR requires 3–4 h for same detection. Also it was found to be 10- to 100-fold more sensitive than RT-PCR, with a detection limit of 0.1–1.0 PFU of virus.
</p>
