<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Given the alarming increase in antibiotic resistance cases, several human pathogens have been classified as a priority for the design of appropriate preventive and therapeutic strategies. In 2017, WHO published a prioritization list of pathogens (classified as critical, high and medium priority) to guide discovery, research and development of new antibiotic (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). In 2019 an estimation performed by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) in the United States reported that more than 2.8 million antibiotic-resistant infections occur in the U.S. each year, and more than 35,000 people die as a result of these infections. The antibiotic-resistant strains were classified into four categories according to the urgency of intervention (urgent, serious, concerning and watch list) (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). These bacteria can cause severe and often deadly infections and have become resistant to a large number of antibiotics, including carbapenems and third generation cephalosporins (the best available antibiotics for treating multidrug resistant bacteria). A relevant example is provided by 
 <italic>A. baumannii</italic> multi-drug resistant isolates, that frequently cause outbreaks in hospitals. These strains are characterized by an extraordinary ability to rapidly alter their genome surviving on inanimate surfaces and medical equipments even in the presence of disinfectants (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). In 
 <italic>A. baumannii</italic>, “resistance islands” located on the bacterial chromosomes and/or on mobile genetic elements induce a drug-resistant phenotype. For example, AbaR1 is an 86kb resistance- island generated by recurrent insertions of different mobile genetic elements, which can spread by horizontal gene transfer (HGT) within the genera 
 <italic>Pseudomonas, Salmonella</italic>, and 
 <italic>Escherichia</italic>. Genomic islands like AbaR1 confer resistance to various antibiotics by spreading the cluster of genes encoding for 
 <italic>OXA</italic>-type beta-lactamases, aminoglycoside-modifying enzymes, proteins responsible for the modification of the lipid A and overexpression of the AdeABC efflux system (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Tuberculosis (TB), even if not initially included in the WHO list, was already considered one of the most urgent priority because of its growing resistance to traditional treatment. TB now kills more people than any other pathogen (1.8 million in 2015) (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Unfortunately, the resistance to isoniazid (INH), one of the four antibiotics used for the treatment of TB, is constantly increasing. INH leads to the inhibition of mycolic acids (MA) synthesis, the major lipid component of the mycobacterial cell envelope (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). The mechanisms of action of isoniazid are diverse and not fully known due to the involvement of a number of different genes. However, several studies suggest that the catalase KatG activates INH enabling the binding to NAD and the inhibition of enoyl acyl carrier protein (ACP) reductase (InhA). As a result, MA synthesis is blocked leading to mycobacteria death. When mutations in the 
 <italic>katG</italic> gene occur, INH remains in an inactive form, unable to bind NAD and to inhibit InhA activity (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3D</xref>). Consequently, InhA accomplishes its function in cell wall synthesis determining the survival of TB. This type of resistance is of concern as it negatively affects the outcome of TB-treatment facilitating the dissemination of MDR-TB and reducing the efficacy of INH (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). The second and third tiers in the list—the high and medium priority categories—include other increasingly drug resistant bacteria that cause more common diseases, such as 
 <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> (the causative agent of gonorrhea) (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). Since the treatment of 
 <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> with sulfonamides, this bacterium has acquired genetic resistance determinants capable to inhibit the killing by all major classes of antibiotics that are used as first line methods of treatment against gonorrhea infection (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). The main lethal target of cephalosporins is the transpeptidase penicillin binding protein 2 (PBP2), encoded by 
 <italic>penA</italic>. Most of the resistant isolates contain mosaic mutations in 
 <italic>penA</italic> that confer resistance to cephalosporins. In addition, the overexpression of efflux pump, MtrCDE, contributes to resistance through an increase of the drug efflux. The simultaneous mutations in the major porins PorB and mtrR, the repressors of MtrCDE efflux pump, represent an important resistance determinant of gonococcus. Hence, the outstanding capacity of 
 <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> to rapidly acquire resistance has led the World Health Organization and Center for Disease Control (US) to classify this bacterium as “superbug.” As a result, if new prophylactic and/or therapeutic strategies will not be discovered soon, we may enter an era of incurable gonorrhea infections (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Therefore, understanding the mechanisms underlying the AMR will help to rationally design new preventive strategies to effectively tackle these dangerous threats for the human health.
</p>
