<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Historically, ASFV introduction into distant disease-free territories has been attributed to the consumption of contaminated pork or pork products (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Moreover, although prohibited in the EU and in contravention of biosecurity measures, swill feeding is still a common practice all over the world, especially in free-ranging and backyard farms (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Therefore, contaminated pork presents a possible mode of transmission for ASFV. Heated, cooked, and canned meat products are generally considered safe as regards any viable pathogen presence, which has been experimentally demonstrated (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, 
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). Several experiments provided data concerning ASFV stability in raw and processed meat and other pork products (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Frozen raw meat and organs provide ASFV viability for periods lasting from 103 to 118 days, but according to Adkin
 <italic>.et al</italic>. (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) ASFV may remain infectious for even up to 1,000 days. In meat stored at 4–8°C, a viable virus could be detected over 84- to 155-day periods (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Infected spleen samples stored in a refrigerator remained infectious for 204 days, but when buried in soil in June at 8 cm depth it remained so for 280 days. Bone marrow (in boned meat) remained infectious for 180–188 days, skin and fat for 300 days, and offal for 105 days, however the temperature at which these samples were stored was not stated despite its being a key factor for virus survivability (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>).
</p>
