<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The symptoms of SARS-CoV-2 infection appear after an incubation period of 1 to 14 days, similar to those of SARS- and MERS-CoV infections (median approximately 5.2 days in different studies) and 95% of patients are likely to experience symptoms within 12.5 days from contact [
 <xref rid="B24-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B106-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>,
 <xref rid="B107-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>,
 <xref rid="B108-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. However, in an asymptomatic carrier the incubation period was 19 days, complicating the challenge to contain the outbreak [
 <xref rid="B109-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. The median time between onset of symptoms and dyspnea is 5 days, 7 days for hospitalization and 8 days for acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-17-05648-f007">Figure 7</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B24-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] (
 <uri xlink:href="https://www.epicentro.iss.it/coronavirus/sars-cov-2" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.epicentro.iss.it/coronavirus/sars-cov-2</uri>). Patients at this stage in intensive care unit (ICU) with quarantine facilities may require mechanical ventilation. Moreover, bacterial infections can cause a secondary pneumonia [
 <xref rid="B108-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. In addition, the period from the beginning of COVID-19 symptoms to death varied between 6 and 41 days with an average of 14 days [
 <xref rid="B110-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]. This period depends on immune system status and the patient’s age, being shorter in 70-year-old subjects compared with those younger [
 <xref rid="B78-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,
 <xref rid="B110-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]. In people with compromised immune systems and in elderly patients with underlying health problems, SARS-CoV-2 is able to infect the lower respiratory tract leading to severe pneumonia [
 <xref rid="B111-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. In 25–30% of patients presenting acute lung injury, shock, ARDS and acute kidney injury, ICU admission was absolutely required [
 <xref rid="B24-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Recovery started within the 2nd or 3rd weeks with the median duration of hospitalization of 10 days. The virus appears to be more fatal in individuals with underlying co-morbidities (50–75% of fatal cases) [
 <xref rid="B24-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B111-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. Available dataset was obtained from Italian Istituto Superiore di Sanità (ISS) on 34,026 patients dying in-hospitals (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-17-05648-f007">Figure 7</xref>). The mean number of diseases was 3.3 (median 3, SD 1.9). Overall, 4.0% of the reported cases has no co-morbidities, 14.0% with a single comorbidity, 20.6% with 2 and 61.4% with 3 or more (
 <uri xlink:href="https://www.epicentro.iss.it/coronavirus/sars-cov-2" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.epicentro.iss.it/coronavirus/sars-cov-2</uri>).
</p>
