<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27">SARS-CoV-2 is an enveloped non-segmented positive sense single-strand RNA viruses classified into the genus Betacoronavirus in the subfamily Orthocoronavirinae [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. After SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV, it has become the seventh coronavirus that causes infection in human beings. The receptor-binding domain present in the S1 subunit of the spike protein (S) is responsible for targeting the host cells. It binds to the angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) receptor present on the host’s cells surface, and the binding affinity is 10–20 times more than SARS-CoV, which might explain its higher transmission rate among humans. After attachment, S protein undergoes conformational changes that help in the fusion of viral and endosomal membranes. The viral RNA is then released into the host cell, and this is facilitated by host transmembrane protease serine-type 2 (TMPRSS2). After entering the cell, the viral RNA gets uncoated and translated into viral polymerase protein. After this, the viral RNA gets replicated using its RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp). Structural proteins are then synthesized, assembled, and released outside the cell [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The various steps involved in the viral lifecycle provide potential targets for drug discovery and facilitates drug repurposing. The promising drug targets are 3-chymotrypsin-like protease (3CLPro) and papain-like protease (proteolysis of viral polyprotein), RdRp (involved in viral replication), S protein (helps in viral entry by binding to ACE2), and TMPRSS2 (helps in priming of S protein to facilitate its binding to ACE2) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Apart from these, immune regulation and inflammatory pathways, which involve Th-17, interferons, proinflammatory cytokines, lymphocytes as natural killer cells, JAK proteins, and checkpoints such as programmed cell death protein 1(PD1), are also targeted in search of the therapeutic molecules for COVID-19. Biologics such as monoclonal antibodies are being developed to target various pathogenic molecules involved in SARS-CoV-2 infections. Figure 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> summarizes the life cycle of SARS-CoV-2 and major pharmacologic targets for treatments or adjunctive therapies for COVID-19.
</p>
