<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Classic measles with cough, coryza, conjunctivitis, Koplik spots, and a maculopapular rash that starts on the face can more easily target the measles hypothesis. Anyway, a laboratory confirmation is often useful when there are shaded shapes, special cases without exanthema, (for example, in an immunocompromised patient), or in an era (after the introduction of the vaccine) in which clinicians have less experience of this disease [
 <xref rid="B1-microorganisms-08-00276" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Measles may be diagnosed in the laboratory by viral isolation, identification of measles antigen, or RNA in infected tissues (and nucleotide sequencing can be used for precise characterization of diagnostic specimens), or demonstration of a significant serologic response to MV with the detection of specific IgM. Viral isolation is technically difficult, and core facilities for isolation are not always available. Immunofluorescent examination of cells from nasal exudates or from urinary sediment for the presence of measles antigens may be useful for rapid diagnosis of measles. More specifically, the serological method of antibody testing is the most common and simple technique used. In this context, there are various diagnostic options, some more rarely used, such as antibody neutralization or complement fixation, others more commonly used, such as the ELISA method. False-negative and false-positive results, however, may occur with ELISA, in particular the dosage of the increase in IgM title in the acute phase. However, it should be remembered that IgM can also be absent until at least 4 days after the appearance of the rash. The IgM peak is reached in a few weeks from the rash, gradually disappearing within 1–2 months after. The diagnosis can also be made by assessing an increase of at least 4 times in the IgG title between the acute phase and the convalescence phase [
 <xref rid="B75-microorganisms-08-00276" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>].
</p>
