<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The use of face masks will become a vital tool in the future so that humans can move back to a normal day to day setting in dealing with COVID-19. Face mask use is steadily becoming an everyday recommendation from governments with many enforcing their mandatory use outside and the WHO recommending their use. Standards in place prior to the outbreak have enabled the production of quality-controlled equipment that can be used in the current situation and help stem the growth of the pandemic. Current materials used in production including non-woven fibrous substances have been in use since the beginning of the 20th century and have been shown to be still sufficiently viable in their use. Advances in materials have developed coatings such as graphene oxide that are antimicrobial, these can aid both the fabric used and filters helping prevent the transition from the mask to hands and inhalation. Development in nano-sized materials and polymer layers have shown potential in increasing the filtration efficiency of the filters and the use of nanostructures can enhance the structural integrity of the face masks and respirators. The reuse of face masks and respirators has seen limited success, as these are a single use product and extending their use can have negative effects. Ultraviolet treatments were seen to degrade the structure of the mask while chemical based sterilisation methods showed an increase in most penetrating particle sizes in face masks and respirators, reducing their effectiveness. The use of pressurised steam while using steam cookers did however show some success in both the respirators and face mask, with minimal increase in MPS and sufficient sterilisation properties. Development of thermochromatic materials will allow easy identification of individuals showing potential symptoms and the development of reusable materials will greatly help in the coming years. Mathematic modelling of the use of face masks during the pandemic has become a valuable tool, allowing researchers and officials to study the effect of their use over a range of situations. Current legislation, materials and research have provided face mask and respirators that can help deal with the pandemic. However, there is still a significant amount of innovation required for the development of efficient face masks and respirators with anti-viral and thermal regulation properties.</p>
