<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<boxed-text>
 <label>Box 1  Non-traditional tools for epidemics</label>
 <p id="Par10">
  <bold>Artificial intelligence</bold>
 </p>
 <p id="Par11">Advances in computer science and computing speeds have led to a number of applications of artificial intelligence across society
  <sup>
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>
  </sup>. Applications in epidemiology include tracking online searches about disease symptoms to aid early detection of epidemics, although more sophisticated methods may be required before artificial intellegence becomes a reliable detection tool
  <sup>
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>
  </sup>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par12">
  <bold>Crystallography</bold>
 </p>
 <p id="Par13">Modern X-ray diffraction and electron microscopy can reveal structures of viruses and antibodies in such detail that it is possible to identify specific sites of vulnerability on the virus. A previous study showed how such techniques identified an antibody that was much more potent against respiratory syncytial virus than the only currently available intervention
  <sup>
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>
  </sup>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par14">
  <bold>Platform vaccine technology</bold>
 </p>
 <p id="Par15">Developing vaccines for emerging infectious diseases has many challenges, including the time it takes, a limited market and strict regulatory requirements for products that will be given to healthy people
  <sup>
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>
  </sup>. Platform technologies use one underlying approach with standardized processes and some antigen-specific optimization to speed up both development and manufacture of vaccines. For example, vector-based platforms combine an antigen, or a gene for an antigenic protein or peptide, in a virus-like particle or liposome. Such platform technologies have the potential to deliver vaccines a few months after an emerging pathogen is identified and sequenced, rather than years
  <sup>
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>
  </sup>.
 </p>
</boxed-text>
