<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Al‐Qumaizi (
 <xref rid="pa2332-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>) referred that researchers set a number of aspects and requirements for preventive education, these aspects could be divided into:
 <list list-type="order" id="pa2332-list-0001">
  <list-item id="pa2332-li-0001">
   <p>
    <italic>Food and Health</italic>: In this regard, students are taught and trained to apply the foundations of healthy nutrition and familiarity with the means of preparing and eating the food they need both physically and psychologically and persuading them of the benefits of food and its impact on the health of their bodies, as they are defined by the different ways of preserving foods and how to prevent food diseases, and it should also emphasize the importance of accustoming students on breakfast.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="pa2332-li-0002">
   <p>
    <italic>Prevention of endemic and infectious diseases</italic>: In it, students are provided with the appropriate amount of information and preventive trends related to diseases and health problems, which enables them to protect themselves from these diseases before they occur and face them in a proper scientific manner.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="pa2332-li-0003">
   <p>
    <italic>Smoking prevention, drug use, addiction, and narcotic drugs</italic>: These matters are considered one of the dangerous inputs that have occurred to our Arab and Islamic societies and all societies alike and the danger that has spread to our students in the early days of their lives. In preventive education, students are provided with the correct information and directions about the damages resulting from smoking, drug use, addiction, and narcotic drugs.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="pa2332-li-0004">
   <p>
    <italic>Prevention of natural and industrial disasters and their risks</italic>: It is a set of information, knowledge, and safety and security measures that must be given to students about natural or industrial disasters and their effects on the environment in order to help them protect themselves and their environment from their damages. In this aspect, students are also made aware of the importance of self‐control and lack of panic when catastrophes and disasters occur.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="pa2332-li-0005">
   <p>
    <italic>Safety and Security</italic>: In it, students are accustomed to practicing their activities inside the school without exposure to hazards or harming their school, and they are also introduced to how to prevent dangerous animals, the dangers of electricity, gases, fires, elevators, traffic accidents, transit, falls, and slip, as they are trained in first aid and how to prevent sharp and dangerous machines and materials, and chemical and flammable materials.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
