<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">Water-borne and foodborne diseases are a serious public health concern worldwide. Water-borne and foodborne outbreaks are closely associated with climatic changes and disturbances in the ecosystem. They are more common in the summertime and increase with rising temperatures and humidity (Greer et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2008</xref>). In addition, among the expected climate changes is the increase in frequencies of floods and heavy rainfalls due to warming of the oceans and due to the increase in frequency and strength of Al Nino and Hurricanes. This, in turn, will be reflected on the increase in water-borne diseases as giardiasis, cryptosporidiosis, infections with pathogenic 
 <italic>E. coli</italic>, 
 <italic>Shigella</italic>, cholera, 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic>, and viral hepatitis A (Haines and Patz 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2004</xref>). Consequently, floods and the increase in water volume will lead to the overload of sewage drainage systems and their overflow and contamination of drinking water. The increase in global temperature will also enhance the emergence of freshwater snails to free areas which enable the expansion of snail mediated trematodes (McCarthy et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115">2001</xref>; Portier et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR153">2017</xref>). Therefore, global warming will result in a significant and serious increase in the worldwide prevalence of enteric/diarrhoeal diseases, but it can even induce fatal epidemics such as epidemics caused by fatal thermophilic free-living amoeba the 
 <italic>Naegleria fowleri</italic> which induce fatal meningoencephalitis (Huizinga and McLaughlin 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">1990</xref>; Sykora et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR180">1983</xref>). In the USA, the emergence of most water-borne outbreaks was associated with severe precipitation (Rose et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR166">2001</xref>).
</p>
