<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0100">Fluorescence and HDX-MS data suggested an influence of divalent magnesium or calcium cations upon the reversibility of DENV expansion, upon lowering the temperature from 37 °C back to 28 °C, 
 <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> and localized the effect as occurring at peptide segments around the virion 5-fold vertices. In order to investigate the molecular basis for this, we “back-mapped” our expanded CG DENV envelope model to all-atom representation. To do this, geometric projection/reconstruction was performed using a library of mapping definitions (available at 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cgmartini.nl/index.php/tools2/resolution-transformation" id="ir010" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://cgmartini.nl/index.php/tools2/resolution-transformation</ext-link>), followed by several all-atom simulation relaxations 
 <xref rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>. From the back-mapped, relaxed virion structure, we extracted an E protein pentamer and its associated M proteins arranged around a 5-fold vertex. This was performed to reduce the system size in all-atom representation. The virus membrane was approximated as a flat lipid bilayer. This was built using CHARMM-GUI 
 <xref rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0315" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref> and corresponded to a biologically relevant membrane composition, similarly to the preceding whole virion model, of a PC/PE/PS mixture in a ~6:3:1 ratio 
 <xref rid="b0260" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. Subsequently, we embedded the pentamer with its transmembrane (TM) regions inserted into the membrane, and removed clashing lipids within ~0.3 nm of protein atoms. The system was then minimized in vacuum and solvated. In order to retain the higher order pentameric “expanded” structure, with its ectodomain positioned above the membrane according to cryo-EM data, we applied position restraints with a low force constant to the protein Cα atoms 
 <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> during simulations totalling 200 ns. Atomistic simulations revealed that the emergent spaces at the 5-fold vertices are accessible to water and salt, and that divalent cations can ‘‘soak’’ the protein 5-fold interface and competitively interact with acidic residues to break inter-chain salt bridges. This is expected to reduce the stability of the expanded state, enabling reversible contraction of the virion to its smooth form at low temperatures 
 <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>.
</p>
