<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec id="sec001">
  <title>Objectives</title>
  <p>Larval indices have been used for 
   <italic>Ae</italic>. 
   <italic>albopictus</italic> surveillance for many years, while there is limited use in assessing dengue transmission risk and adult mosquito emergence. This study is aimed to explore the relationships between larval indices and the 
   <italic>Ae</italic>. 
   <italic>albopictus</italic> density captured by BG-mosquito trap (BG-trap) method, with considering the meteorological factors.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec002">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>Data on larval density, adult mosquito density and meteorology factors were collected in an entomological survey carried out in Quzhou City, Zhejiang Province of China in 2018. The Spearman’s rank correlation and Pearson correlation were used for the analysis on the correlation of density indices. Generalized additive models were established to analyze the influencing factors of mosquito density.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec003">
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>Breteau index (BI), House index (HI) and Container index (CI) were highly correlated with each other (r&gt;0.7, p&lt;0.05). The 
   <italic>Ae</italic>. 
   <italic>albopictus</italic> density was significantly correlated with CI (rs = 0.260, p&lt;0.05), CI pre one week (rs = 0.259, p&lt;0.05), and CI pre three weeks (rs = 0.329, p&lt;0.05). BI was correlated with female 
   <italic>Ae</italic>. 
   <italic>albopictus</italic> density pre 4 weeks (r = -0.299, p&lt;0.05). Female 
   <italic>Ae</italic>. 
   <italic>albopictus</italic> density was correlated with CI pre 3 weeks (rs = 0.303, p&lt;0.05). The influencing factors of BI were average wind speed pre 1 week, average temperature and female 
   <italic>Ae</italic>. 
   <italic>albopictus</italic> density pre 4 weeks. The influencing factors of CI were average humidity pre 3 weeks and average temperature. The influencing factors of HI were average temperature and precipitation pre 4 weeks. The influencing factor of 
   <italic>Ae</italic>. 
   <italic>albopictus</italic> density and female 
   <italic>Ae</italic>. 
   <italic>albopictus</italic> density was temperature.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec004">
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>The adult 
   <italic>Ae</italic>. 
   <italic>albopictus</italic> density had low correlation with certain larval indices. Some of the meteorology factors played significant roles in the density of adult 
   <italic>Ae</italic>. 
   <italic>albopictus</italic> and larva with or without a time lag.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
