<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="irv12713-abs-0001">
 <title>Abstract</title>
 <sec id="irv12713-sec-0001">
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>Here, we genetically and antigenically analyzed influenza B viruses (IBVs) isolated in Japan during the 2017‐2018 and 2018‐2019 influenza seasons.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="irv12713-sec-0002">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>A total of 68 IBVs (61 B/Yamagata/16/88‐like [B/Yamagata]‐lineage and 7 B/Victoria/2/87‐like [B/Victoria]‐lineage) were antigenically and genetically characterized by using hemagglutination inhibition (HI) assays and phylogenetic analysis, respectively. The susceptibility of IBVs to neuraminidase (NA) inhibitors was assessed by using a fluorescence‐based NA inhibition assay.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="irv12713-sec-0003">
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>All 61 B/Yamagata‐lineage isolates were genetically closely related to B/Phuket/3073/2013, the vaccine strain for these two seasons. Eleven B/Yamagata‐lineage isolates tested were antigenically similar to B/Phuket/3073/2013 by the HI test. Seven B/Victoria‐lineage isolates were genetically closely related to B/Texas/02/2013, the WHO‐recommended vaccine strain for the 2017‐2018 season; however, they were antigenically distinct from B/Texas/02/2013 with an eightfold or 16‐fold difference in HI titer. Of these 7 isolates, 4 possessed a two‐amino‐acid deletion at positions 162 and 163 in hemagglutinin (HA) and the other 3 had a three‐amino‐acid deletion at positions 162‐164 in HA. Importantly, the variants with the three‐amino‐acid deletion appeared to be antigenically different from the B/Colorado/06/2017 virus with the two‐amino‐acid deletion, the vaccine strain for the 2018‐2019 season with a fourfold or eightfold difference in HI titer. One B/Yamagata‐lineage isolate carrying a G407S mutation in its NA showed a marked reduction in susceptibility to zanamivir, peramivir, and laninamivir.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="irv12713-sec-0004">
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>These results highlight the need for continued monitoring for the prevalence of the antigenic variant with the three‐amino‐acid deletion and the variant with reduced NA inhibitor susceptibility.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
