<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <p id="Par1">Infectious bronchitis virus (IBV) control is mainly based on wide vaccine administration. Although effective, its efficacy is not absolute, the viral circulation is not prevented and some side effects cannot be denied. Despite this, the determinants of IBV epidemiology and the factors affecting its circulation are still largely unknown and poorly investigated. In the present study, 361 IBV QX (the most relevant field genotype in Italy) sequences were obtained between 2012 and 2016 from the two main Italian integrated poultry companies. Several biostatistical and bioinformatics approaches were used to reconstruct the history of the QX genotype in Italy and to assess the effect of different environmental, climatic and social factors on its spreading patterns. Moreover, two structured coalescent models were considered in order to investigate if an actual compartmentalization occurs between the two integrated poultry companies and the role of a third “ghost” deme, representative of minor industrial poultry companies and the rural sector. The obtained results suggest that the integration of the poultry companies is an effective barrier against IBV spreading, since the strains sampled from the two companies formed two essentially-independent clades. Remarkably, the only exceptions were represented by farms located in the high densely populated poultry area of Northern Italy. The inclusion of a third deme in the model revealed the likely role of other poultry companies and rural farms (particularly concentrated in Northern Italy) as sources of strain introduction into one of the major poultry companies, whose farms are mainly located in the high densely populated poultry area of Northern Italy. Accordingly, when the effect of different environmental and urban parameters on IBV geographic spreading was investigated, no factor seems to contribute to IBV dispersal velocity, being poultry population density the only exception. Finally, the different viral population pattern observed in the two companies over the same time period supports the pivotal role of management and control strategies on IBV epidemiology. Overall, the present study results stress the crucial relevance of human action rather than environmental factors, highlighting the direct benefits that could derive from improved management and organization of the poultry sector on a larger scale.</p>
</abstract>
