<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">Human papillomavirus (HPV) is the leading cause of cervical cancers, causing 270.000 deaths annually worldwide of which 85% occur in developing countries with an increasing risk associated to HIV infection. This study aimed at comparing HPV’s positivity and genotype distribution in women according to their HIV status and determinants.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p id="Par2">A comparative study was carried out in 2012 at the Chantal BIYA International Reference Centre (CIRCB) among 278 women enrolled consecutively at the General Hospital and the Gynaeco-Obstetric and Paediatric Hospital of the City of Yaoundé. HPV genotyping was performed by real-time PCR, HIV serological screening by serial algorithm, CD4 T cell phenotyping by flow cytometry and HIV viral load by Abbott m2000RT. Statistical analyses were performed using Microsoft Excel 2016 and Graph Pad version 6.0 software; with 
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 considered statistically significant.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p id="Par3">Globally, mean age was 37 ± 3 years; median CD4-count for HIV+ was 414 cells/mm
   <sup>3</sup> [IQR: 264.75–588] and median viremia was 50 RNA copies/mL [IQR: &lt; 40–8288]. Overall HPV rate was 38.49% (107/278); 58.88% for single women vs. others (28.97% married, 2.80% divorced, 9.34% for widows), OR: 2.164; 
   <italic>p</italic> = 0.0319. Following HIV status, HPV rate was 43.48% (80/184) among HIV+ vs. 28.72% (27/94) among HIV- (OR: 1.937; 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0142); HPV genotypes among HIV+ vs. HIV- were respectively distributed as follows: genotype 16 (3.75% vs. 0.00%, 
   <italic>p</italic> = 0.57), genotype 18 (3.75% vs. 3.70%, 
   <italic>p</italic> = 1.00), co-infection 16 and others (8.75% vs. 7.40%, 
   <italic>p</italic> = 1.00), co-infection 18 and others (8.75% vs. 11.11%, 
   <italic>p</italic> = 0.71), co-infection 16, 18 and others (2.50% vs. 0.00%, p = 1.00) and other genotypes (72.50% vs. 77.78%, 
   <italic>p</italic> = 0.80). Among HIV+ participants, HPV rate following CD4 was 62.88% (61/97) for CD4 &lt; 500 vs. 35.71% (20/56) for CD4 ≥ 500 (OR: 3.05; 
   <italic>p</italic> = 0.0012) while HPV rate following HIV viremia was 42.71% (41/96) with &lt; 1000 RNA copies/ml vs. 66.00% (33/50) with &gt; 1000 RNA copies/ml (OR = 0.384; 
   <italic>p</italic> = 0.009).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p id="Par4">In Yaoundé, HPV rate appear to be very high, with higher rates of genotypes other than 16 and 18. In the event of HIV infection, the risk of HPV positivity is two times higher, favoured essentially by immunodeficiency. Thus, HIV-infected women should be closely monitored to prevent the emergence of cervical cancer.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
