<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <p>Infection with (SAg)-producing bacteria may precede or follow infection with or vaccination against influenza A viruses (IAVs). However, how SAgs alter the breadth of IAV-specific CD8
  <sup>+</sup> T cell (T
  <sub>CD8</sub>) responses is unknown. Moreover, whether recall responses mediating heterosubtypic immunity to IAVs are manipulated by SAgs remains unexplored. We employed wild-type (WT) and mutant bacterial SAgs, SAg-sufficient/deficient 
  <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> strains, and WT, mouse-adapted and reassortant IAV strains in multiple 
  <italic>in vivo</italic> settings to address the above questions. Contrary to the popular view that SAgs delete or anergize T cells, systemic administration of staphylococcal enterotoxin B (SEB) or 
  <italic>Mycoplasma arthritidis</italic> mitogen before intraperitoneal IAV immunization enlarged the clonal size of ‘select’ IAV-specific T
  <sub>CD8</sub> and reshuffled the hierarchical pattern of primary T
  <sub>CD8</sub> responses. This was mechanistically linked to the TCR Vβ makeup of the impacted clones rather than their immunodominance status. Importantly, SAg-expanded T
  <sub>CD8</sub> retained their IFN-γ production and cognate cytolytic capacities. The enhancing effect of SEB on immunodominant T
  <sub>CD8</sub> was also evident in primary responses to vaccination with heat-inactivated and live attenuated IAV strains administered intramuscularly and intranasally, respectively. Interestingly, in prime-boost immunization settings, the outcome of SEB administration depended strictly upon the time point at which this SAg was introduced. Accordingly, SEB injection before priming raised CD127
  <sup>high</sup>KLRG1
  <sup>low</sup> memory precursor frequencies and augmented the anamnestic responses of SEB-binding T
  <sub>CD8</sub>. By comparison, introducing SEB before boosting diminished recall responses to IAV-derived epitopes drastically and indiscriminately. This was accompanied by lower Ki67 and higher Fas, LAG-3 and PD-1 levels consistent with a pro-apoptotic and/or exhausted phenotype. Therefore, SAgs can have contrasting impacts on anti-IAV immunity depending on the naïve/memory status and the TCR composition of exposed T
  <sub>CD8</sub>. Finally, local administration of SEB or infection with SEB-producing 
  <italic>S</italic>. 
  <italic>aureus</italic> enhanced pulmonary T
  <sub>CD8</sub> responses to IAV. Our findings have clear implications for superinfections and prophylactic vaccination.
 </p>
</abstract>
