<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The SARS-CoV 3a protein contains oligosaccharides with direct evidence that sialic acids play a critical role in human coronavirus infection.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
 </sup> It has been just shown that the attachment of coronaviruses to the surface of respiratory cells is mediated by the spike (S) viral protein, which binds not only to the angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE-2) receptor for entry
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
 </sup> but also to sialic acid–containing glycoproteins and gangliosides on cell surfaces.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
 </sup> Such a dual receptor/attachment is proposed to be a reason for the increased transmissibility of COVID-19 compared with SARS-CoV that binds only to ACE-2 receptor.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
  <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
 </sup> Of relevance to GBS is that various gangliosides, most commonly those containing either a disialosyl moiety, such as GD1b, GQ1b, and GT1b, or 2 gangliosides that share epitopes with GM2, or a combination of GM2 and GM1, GM1 and GD1b, can serve as antigens in patients with neuropathies.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
 </sup> When IgM recognizes the Gal (pl-3) GalNAc moiety of GM1, which is found on the surface of motor neurons, there is clinically a motor neuropathy, but if recognizes epitopes containing disialosyl groups of GDlb, which is present on the dorsal root ganglionic neurons, there is sensory ataxic neuropathy.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
 </sup> Immunization of rabbits with GDlb also causes sensory ataxic neuropathy mimicking the human disease.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
 </sup> Of interest, the first described patient with sensory ataxic neuropathy and GDlb antibodies had also ophthalmoplegia,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 </sup> as seen in MFS and the present series.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
 </sup> As COVID-19 spike interacts with the GalNAc residue of GM1 and ganglioside dimers for anchoring to cell surface gangliosides,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
 </sup> cross-reactivity between epitopes within the COVID-19 spike-bearing gangliosides and signature sugar residues of surface peripheral nerve glycolipids is a very likely possibility. Such typical molecular mimicry has been shown between peripheral nerve glycolipids and 
 <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> or Zika virus that also trigger GBS.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">–</xref>
  <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
 </sup> Accordingly, all GBS subtypes (AIDP, AMAN, and MFS) can be expected with COVID-19, necessitating screening for ganglioside antibodies to assess autoimmunity. An interesting therapeutic component in this association is the emerging data that chloroquine, an antimalarial drug under investigation for treating COVID-19, binds with high-affinity sialic acids and GM1 gangliosides and, in the presence of chloroquine, the SARS-CoV viral spike cannot bind gangliosides to infect the targeted cells.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
 </sup> If benefit is confirmed and safety is established, chloroquine may be of added therapeutic value in future patients with COVID-19–triggered GBS in conjunction with IVIg.
</p>
