<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There were a number of simplifying assumptions of the model and simulations. For instance, human movement as simulated here is coarse and captures only commuting behavior at a between-neighborhood level, rather than fine-grained distinctions that in reality occur between the distances travelled, time spent at different locations, and frequency at which particular types of habitats (e.g., residential, recreational, commercial, etc.) are visited [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007479.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007479.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Similarly, we assumed that the movement patterns could be well-described with a gravity model, and for some settings, other models of movement may capture reality better (e.g., radiation models [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007479.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]). In other words, the current study represents an important first step at investigating how the level of coordination between different neighborhoods may vary for different spatial compositions of humans, but it is certainly not an exhaustive exploration of the implications of human movement patterns for disease control. One particularly interesting complication relates to the effect of sickness behavior of febrile cases on mobility patterns. In the case of dengue, it has been qualitatively shown that individuals presenting with fever and testing positive for dengue visited fewer locations and spent more time inside their home than afebrile study participants [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007479.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. It is likely that such effects will vary over the course of infection and depend on the severity (or lack) of symptoms. Including such sickness-mediated changes in behavior in a transmission and control model as used here was beyond the scope of the current study, but would be important to consider as both the transmission dynamics and implications for control strategies could change drastically. Another assumption we made relates to the likelihood of infections triggering control. We based this on two humans, and assumed the probability of detecting these infections was informed by an estimate of an symptomatic:asymptomatic ratio of 1:1 (e.g., [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007479.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]). This may still be an overestimate of the probability of detecting an infection, either due to health-seeking behavior or inefficiencies in health care systems. We additionally assumed control would only be triggered upon detection of two infected humans, whereas a single case may be used in reality (e.g., [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007479.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]). These respective over- and underestimates of triggering events will cancel each other out to an extent. The implications of varying the trigger for Zika control has been investigated recently [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007479.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>].
</p>
