<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0120">An ideal RSV vaccine for maternal immunization is one that is not a live virus vaccine, can be administered as a single dose during pregnancy, preferably in the second or early third trimester of gestation to allow for sufficient time for transplacental antibody transfer, is safe for mother and infant, and is able to induce protective antibodies that are efficiently transferred to the infant via the placenta to achieve high concentration of neutralizing antibodies to protect the infant long enough in the first months of life. The natural decay of passively acquired maternal antibodies allows for the highest protection in the infant to be in the first 2–3 months of life, declining afterwards. Therefore, maternal immunization will likely need to be followed by active infant immunization starting as early as the second month after birth, to reduce the impact of RSV in the first year of life. This strategy, maternal followed by infant immunization, would be most effective for infants born at term, for whom passive antibody administration might not be an option. Infants of vaccinated mothers who receive active immunization would less likely acquire RSV infection in the first 3 months of life, the period of greatest vulnerability, or experience acquired infections that are modified or rendered less severe by the presence of maternally derived and vaccine induced antibodies. Maternal immunization is not likely to be an effective method to prevent early disease among premature infants who would not benefit from a sufficient duration of gestation to achieve optimal transplacental transfer and high antibody concentrations at birth. Therefore, administration of passive RSV antibodies (e.g. Palivizumab) followed by active infant immunization would be the most adequate strategy for prevention of RSV in preterm infants. The duration of protection of maternally-derived antibodies in all infants is limited by the concentration of antibodies present at birth, and the relatively short antibody half-life, which results in a rapid natural antibody decay in the first 6 months of life. Therefore, both passive and active immunization will have an important role in the prevention of RSV in infants, even if routine maternal immunization or administration of monoclonal antibodies after birth become available. One remaining challenge in the development of RSV vaccines is the lack of a known serologic correlate of protection to evaluate vaccine efficacy and effectiveness. Until a correlate of protection is identified, large clinical trials are required to assess the efficacy of candidate RSV vaccines for maternal or infant immunization. Another important area of research in the field of RSV addresses the need to better understand the mechanisms of protection beyond antibodies, such as innate and cellular immunity. Definitive progress in the design and development of RSV vaccines was driven by a better understanding of the conformation depending immunogenicity of the F-protein and the need to target neutralization sensitive epitopes on the functional forms of F-protein 
 <xref rid="bb0205" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0290" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>. All RSV vaccines for maternal immunization developed to date have been based on the F-protein of RSV. There are currently four vaccines in development for maternal immunization, two in phase I clinical trials, and one each in phase II and III clinical trials (
 <xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).
</p>
