<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat.1008517.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1008517.g006</object-id>
 <label>Fig 6</label>
 <caption>
  <title>RRV mAbs improve clinical disease and reduce viral RNA burden when given therapeutically in a WT mouse model.</title>
  <p>
   <bold>(A)</bold> Three-week-old WT C57BL/6 mice were inoculated with 10
   <sup>3</sup> FFU of RRV strain T48 before administration of 100 μg antibody by intraperitoneal injection at 24 hpi. Mice were then weighed each day over the course of 18 days and assigned a clinical score based on grip strength, gait, and righting reflex. Blind scoring of mice was performed using the following scoring system: 0, no disease; 1, mild defect in ipsilateral hind paw gripping; 2, mild defect in bilateral hind paw gripping; 3, bilateral loss in hind paw gripping; 4, bilateral loss in hind paw gripping with moderate hind limb weakness, observable mild altered gait, and difficulty or failure to right self; 5, bilateral loss in hind paw gripping with severe hind limb weakness, moderate altered gait, and loss of righting reflex; 6, bilateral loss in hind paw gripping with severe hind limb weakness, severely altered gait with possible dragging hind paw, and loss of righting reflex; 7, moribund. Two independent experiments were performed, for a total of n = 8 mice in each antibody group. Statistical analysis was performed using a one-way ANOVA of area under the curve test (****p &lt; 0.0001). 
   <bold>(B)</bold> Eighteen days post-infection, the spleen, ipsilateral and contralateral gastrocnemius, quadriceps, and ankle tissues were collected following extensive perfusion with PBS. Viral RNA was quantified through qRT-PCR and statistical analysis was performed using a Kruskal-Wallis multiple comparisons test (*p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01; ns = not significant).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1008517.g006" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
