<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Taking into account the epidemiological findings over the five epidemic waves of human infections and biological characterization of both the low pathogenic and highly pathogenic strains of H7N9, the Asian lineage of H7N9 viruses, are recognized by the CDC as the influenza viruses with the highest potential pandemic risk [
 <xref rid="B153-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>]. These viruses display variation in their ability to transit between ferrets with different investigators reporting airborne transmission to 33–100% of contact animals. Based on studies that characterize the HA of the H7N9 viruses, instability of the HA in both low and highly pathogenic H7N9 viruses is likely inhibiting or limiting transmission via the airborne route. While there have been five waves of human infections and highly pathogenic H7N9 variants have emerged, during the expected 6th epidemic wave from October of 2017 to July of 2018, only a single human case of H7N9 infection was reported. The reasons for this decrease in zoonotic infections are unclear; however, the Chinese government initiated a large H7N9 and H5 vaccination campaign in poultry [
 <xref rid="B154-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">154</xref>] and this may be limiting the spread of the disease. Despite this campaign, outbreaks of HPAI H7N9 in poultry are ongoing [
 <xref rid="B155-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>], and the potential for future outbreaks and zoonotic infections remains. Importantly, vaccination of poultry does not typically confer sterilizing immunity, and most avian influenza vaccines reduced clinical illness and spread but do not block infection or viral replication in birds [
 <xref rid="B156-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>,
 <xref rid="B157-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>]. As a result, vaccination may drive antigenic drift of the virus as observed Marek’s disease [
 <xref rid="B158-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>], and this may result in the reemergence of the H7N9 viruses. Therefore, it is now increasingly important to monitor viral evolution with a focus on changes that may stabilize the viral HA, and perform pandemic risk assessment on viruses isolated during poultry outbreaks and from zoonotic infections.
</p>
