<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27">As with other infectious diseases, including SARS and influenza, COVID-19 can trigger ACS
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>
 </sup>. In early studies from China, a small proportion of patients with COVID-19 presented with chest pain on admission to hospital, but the characteristics of the chest pain were not described
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>. In a case series from New York involving 18 patients with COVID-19 and ST segment elevation, which is indicative of potential acute myocardial infarction, five of the six patients with myocardial infarction required percutaneous coronary intervention
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>
 </sup>. In a case series from Italy involving 28 patients with COVID-19 and ST segment elevation myocardial infarction, assessment by coronary angiography showed that 17 patients had evidence of a culprit lesion that required revascularization
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup>. Of note, ST segment elevation myocardial infarction was the first clinical manifestation of COVID-19 in 24 of these 28 patients who had not yet received a positive test result for COVID-19 at the time of coronary angiography. These observations suggest that COVID-19 can cause ACS even in the absence of substantial systemic inflammation. However, the incidence of ACS in patients with COVID-19 is still unknown. Considering the overwhelmed health-care facilities of many cities during the COVID-19 outbreak, the number of cases of acute myocardial infarction among patients with COVID-19 might be underestimated in early studies. The mechanisms underlying COVID-19-induced ACS might involve plaque rupture, coronary spasm or microthrombi owing to systemic inflammation or cytokine storm
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>
 </sup>. For example, activated macrophages secrete collagenases that degrade collagen, a major constituent of the fibrous cap on atherosclerotic plaques, which can lead to plaque rupture
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>
 </sup>. Activated macrophages are also known to secrete tissue factor, a potent procoagulant that triggers thrombus formation when the plaque ruptures
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>
 </sup>. Direct endothelial or vascular injury caused by SARS-CoV-2 infection might also increase the risk of thrombus formation and ACS
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
