<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>RDV (GS-5734, 
 <bold>2</bold>) is a broad-spectrum antiviral nucleotide prodrug with potency against a wide array of RNA viruses, including SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV, in cultured cells and mouse models.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref49">49</xref>
 </sup> It is an adenosine analog that is incorporated into nascent viral RNA chains, leading to premature termination.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref50">50</xref>
 </sup> A recent study conducted by Wang et al. showed that the effective concentration for 90% inhibition (EC
 <sub>90</sub>) and effective concentration for 50% inhibition (EC
 <sub>50</sub>) values of RDV against SARS-CoV-2 in Vero E6 cells were 1.76 μM and 0.77 μM, respectively. The time-of-addition assay confirmed that RDV affects viral replication postviral entry, supporting its mode of action as a nucleotide analog.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>
 </sup> Another 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> study reported potent antiviral activity of RDV against HCoV-OC43 and HCoV-229E in Huh7 cells with submicromolar EC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 0.15 and 0.024 μM, respectively.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref51">51</xref>
 </sup> Additionally, it potently inhibited SARS-CoV in human airway epithelial (HAE) cells with an IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 0.06 μM and SI &gt; 10.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref52">52</xref>
 </sup> Sheahan et al. reported that prophylactic or early therapeutic administration of RDV significantly reduced lung viral loads and improved clinical outcomes in a murine infection model.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref53">53</xref>
 </sup> Holshue and colleagues reported the first patient diagnosed with COVID-19 in Washington, USA, who was compassionately treated with intravenous RDV for the progression of pneumonia on day 7 of hospitalization (illness day 11). Encouragingly, the patient’s clinical condition improved since the next day after RDV administration, and no adverse effects were observed.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref54">54</xref>
 </sup> Grein and collaborators reported that in a cohort of hospitalized severe COVID-19 patients who were treated with compassionate use of RDV, clinical improvement was observed in 36 of 53 patients (68%).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref55">55</xref>
 </sup> In another study, a total of 1063 hospitalized COVID-19 patients were included in a double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled trial to test the efficacy of intravenous RDV against SARS-CoV-2. Preliminary results revealed that RDV therapy resulted in a median recovery time of 11 days compared with 15 days in those who received placebo. This study demonstrated that RDV treatment could shorten the recovery time in hospitalized COVID-19 adult patients with lower respiratory tract infection.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref56">56</xref>
 </sup> However, Wang and collaborators recently reported another study on hospitalized severe COVID-19 adult patients, in which RDV did not yield significant clinical benefits. In this study, 237 patients with severe COVID-19 in 10 hospitals in Wuhan, China, were enrolled and randomly assigned to two groups (158 in the RDV group and 79 in the placebo group) for a treatment course of 10 days. RDV did not significantly shorten time to clinical improvement.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref57">57</xref>
 </sup> Although RDV has been expected to be one of the “powerful weapons” for fighting the current COVID-19 pandemic, its clinical effectiveness remains to be further confirmed.
</p>
