<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are potential limitations in the assumptions adopted in this analysis which are important to consider when interpreting the estimates obtained with our models. When estimating transmission intensity within administratively-defined boundaries, we inherently assumed that cases reported in any one administrative unit were also infected in that same administrative unit, which is less realistic at small administrative levels such as subdistricts. While we explicitly accounted for temporal trends, we assumed no spatial interactions among Jakarta subdistricts. Accounting for spatial structure would increase the complexity of the inferential problem and make parameter inference challenging. Furthermore, we assumed reporting probabilities to be constant in time and age, though fluctuations in reporting may occur over time due to situational awareness (e.g. during epidemics) or by age if any age-related reporting biases were occurring. Additionally, the parameter results shown in this analysis are estimated assuming no overdispersion in the distribution of dengue cases (i.e. we assume a Poisson distribution for the total number of cases and a multinomial distribution for the age distribution of cases), which may result in an underestimation of the uncertainty around the central parameter estimates. In exploratory analysis, we tested the use of over-dispersed case distributions (specifically assuming a negative binomial distribution for the total number of cases and a Dirichlet multinomial likelihood for the age-distribution of cases). However, the use of over-dispersed distributions hindered MCMC convergence. A significant dengue outbreak occurred in Jakarta in 2016, for which our model could not entirely reproduce the high rates of disease observed in the 10–14 years age group (S2 Fig in the 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0008102.s001">S1 Text</xref>). This is likely due to our assumption of equal transmissibility of all 4 serotypes, which does not account for varying levels of population immunity to different serotypes. It is probable that the epidemic in 2016 was the result of the emergence of a newly dominant serotype to which the population had low levels of prior immunity. Due to a lack of serotype-specific data, this is not accounted for in our model, potentially resulting in an underestimation of the force of infection in 2016. In addition, dengue transmission in Jakarta has a distinct seasonal pattern, with case numbers typically peaking in March through May, following the rainy season [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008102.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. In this analysis we assumed that the force of infection is constant within each year, ignoring intra-annual variability and thus producing average annual transmission intensity estimates. Long-term estimates of transmission intensity, however, will hold relevance to decisions when considering the implementation of future control and prevention programmes.
</p>
