<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">
   <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> is a vector of arboviruses that cause severe diseases in humans such as Chikungunya, Dengue and Zika fevers. The vector competence of 
   <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> varies depending on the mosquito population involved and the virus transmitted. 
   <italic>Wolbachia</italic> infection status in believed to be among key elements that determine viral transmission efficiency. Little is known about the cellular functions mobilized in 
   <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> during co-infection by 
   <italic>Wolbachia</italic> and a given arbovirus. To decipher this tripartite interaction at the molecular level, we performed a proteome analysis in 
   <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> C6/36 cells mono-infected by 
   <italic>Wolbachia w</italic>AlbB strain or Chikungunya virus (CHIKV), and bi-infected.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p id="Par2">We first confirmed significant inhibition of CHIKV by 
   <italic>Wolbachia</italic>. Using two-dimensional gel electrophoresis followed by nano liquid chromatography coupled with tandem mass spectrometry, we identified 600 unique differentially expressed proteins mostly related to glycolysis, translation and protein metabolism. 
   <italic>Wolbachia</italic> infection had greater impact on cellular functions than CHIKV infection, inducing either up or down-regulation of proteins associated with metabolic processes such as glycolysis and ATP metabolism, or structural glycoproteins and capsid proteins in the case of bi-infection with CHIKV. CHIKV infection inhibited expression of proteins linked with the processes of transcription, translation, lipid storage and miRNA pathways.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p id="Par3">The results of our proteome profiling have provided new insights into the molecular pathways involved in tripartite 
   <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>-
   <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-CHIKV interaction and may help defining targets for the better implementation of 
   <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-based strategies for disease transmission control.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Electronic supplementary material</title>
  <p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12864-017-3985-y) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
