<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Newer input/output file formats for phylogenetic trees and their accompanying annotations, including the XML-based standards PhyloXML (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>) and NeXML (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>), have the benefit of being more robust for complex analyses and easier to process and extend. In particular, applications of phylodynamics aimed at reconstruction and interpretation of spatio-temporal histories have become broadly and increasingly applied in viral disease investigations. The incorporation of geographical and phylogenetic uncertainty into molecular epidemiology dynamics is now well-established (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>), and dedicated developments from a visualization perspective have soon followed to accommodate the outcomes of these models. Early attempts include the mapping of geo-referenced phylogenetic taxa to their geographical coordinates [e.g., GenGis; (
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>), Cartographer; (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>)], while more recent efforts of joint ancestral reconstruction of geographical and evolutionary histories enable visual summaries of spatial-temporal diffusion through the interactive cartographic projection using GIS- and KML-based virtual globe software (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). The latest developments generalize toward interactive web-based visualization of any phylogenetic trait history and are based on data-driven documents (D3) JavaScript libraries and the JSON format to store geographic and other tree-related information (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). As an example, we have created a web-based visualization of our analyzed RABV data set by loading the obtained MCC tree into the SpreaD3 (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>) phylodynamic visualization software package (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). SpreaD3 actually consists of a parsing and a rendering module, with the former obtaining the relevant information out of the MCC tree and the latter converting this information into a (Geo)JSON file format, potentially in combination with a geographic map, which can easily be downloaded from websites offering GeoJSON files of different regions of the world and with different levels of detail. The generated output consists of an in-browser animation that allows tracking a reconstructed epidemic over time using a simple slider bar, with the possibility to zoom into specific areas of the map. In 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, we show the reconstructed spread of RABV across the United States at four different time points throughout the epidemic, starting with the estimated location of origin in the state of Arizona and tracking the RABV spread as it disperses to all of the 14 states in our data set.
</p>
