<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0180">Coronaviruses are species of viruses belonging to the subfamily 
 <italic>Orthocoronavirinae</italic> in the family 
 <italic>Coronaviridae</italic> of the order 
 <italic>Nidovirales</italic>. Coronavirus is a forward single-stranded RNA [
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], which is endowed with the largest viral genomes (27–32 kb) among the RNA viruses identified to date [
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Genomic RNA complexes with the basic nucleocapsid protein (N) to form a helical capsid within the membrane. The membrane of all coronaviruses is composed of a minimum of three viral proteins: (a) a spike protein (S), which is a type of glycoprotein I [
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]; (b) a membrane protein (M) that spans the membrane; and c) an envelope protein (E) [
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], which is a highly hydrophobic protein that covers the entire coronavirus [
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. For a long time, coronaviruses have been recognized as important pathogens that cause respiratory and gastrointestinal diseases in birds and mammals. Before SARS-CoV-2, six coronaviruses had been found to infect humans: HCoV-229E, HCoV-OC43, HCoV-NL63, HCoV-HKU1, severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) and Middle East respiratory virus coronavirus (MERS-CoV). The first four are constraint endemic strains that cause the common cold, whereas the latter two can cause serious respiratory epidemics [
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>]. SARS is an atypical viral respiratory disease that resulted in 8098 cases and 774 reported deaths in 17 countries (9.6% fatality rate) during a large-scale outbreak in 2003 [
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>]. Fortunately, the SARS epidemic was successfully contained under joint efforts. MERS is a zoonotic respiratory infection that initially broke out in the Middle East in 2012. According to the World Health Organization records, MERS coronavirus has thus far resulted in 2494 cases of infection and 858 deaths. Based on the high prevalence and widespread distribution of coronaviruses, as well as their genetic diversity and the frequent recombination of the genome, coronaviruses pose a continuous threat to humans [
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>].
</p>
