<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Like those of SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV, the SARS-CoV-2 genome comprises of 12 open reading frames (ORFs) in number. At the 5′ end of the viral genome, overlapping ORFs 1a and 1b are present that encode the RNA polymerase and other non-structural proteins of the virus and occupy approximately two-thirds of the genome. Genes encoding structural proteins such as spike (S), membrane (M), envelope (E), and nucleocapsid (N), are present in the remaining one-third of its genome spanning from the 5′ to the 3′ terminal, along with several genes encoding non-structural proteins (NSPs) and accessory proteins scattered in between, as shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>. Despite being in the same serogroup, there is a slight difference in the nucleotide number, sequence, gene order, and expression method among previously known coronaviruses and the novel SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Recent reports highlight that a few amino acid substitutions have occurred in the novel coronavirus genes encoding the S protein, NSP2, NSP3, and receptor-binding domain (RBD). These mutations in the NSP2 &amp; NSP3 are also believed to impart the enhanced infection abilities of the novel coronavirus (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). RNA viruses are prone to acquiring genetic mutations that eventually help them to escape the host immune system and develop drug resistance. Researchers have also found minor mutations in SARS-CoV-2 genotype in different COVID-19 patients (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). One such hotspot of mutation in the SARS-CoV-2 genome is the RNA-dependent RNA polymerase gene. On analyzing 220 sequences across the globe, eight repetitive novel point mutations were observed. Viral genetic sequences accessed from Europe exhibited five mutation hotspots, whereas the remaining three point mutations were solely present in the sequences from North America. These unique mutations suggest that the viral strains are continuously evolving across the globe and that the strains from Europe, North America, and Asia might have co-existed the whole time (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Another similar report analyzed 7,666 global viral genomic sequences and found 198 unique mutation sites on SARS-CoV-2 genome that encodes NSPs and S protein, suggesting that the virus is trying to adapt to its new host (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). As numerous drugs are currently being designed to target the proteins that are essential for the survival of the virus, rapid genetic mutation occurring in these proteins might not prove to be a potential candidate for drug design. Therefore, the invariable region of the virus could be a better target to avoid drug failures.
</p>
