<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pbio.3000217.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.3000217.g002</object-id>
 <label>Fig 2</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Receptors used by viruses are under positive selection at the host–virus interaction interface.</title>
  <p>The cocrystal structures are shown for four human cellular receptors (green) in complex with the surface glycoproteins (blue) of four viruses that use these receptors to enter cells. In each case, we analyzed the evolution of the receptor gene throughout the speciation of the animals that have served as long-term reservoirs for each of these viruses (rodents, bats, and primates in these four cases). In those analyses, amino-acid positions in the receptors that are evolving under positive selection (dN/dS &gt; 1; red spheres) were identified that mapped directly to the interaction interface with the indicated viruses [
   <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref093" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>–
   <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. These residue positions are rapidly evolving, which means that each species within these animal groups tends to encode unique amino acids at these positions. This explains why viruses often have to accumulate mutations in their surface glycoprotein that allow them to use the version of their receptor in a new species. Cocrystals shown are TfR1 (PBD: 3KAS [
   <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]), ACE2 (PDB: 2AJF [
   <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]), CD4 (PDB: 1RZJ [
   <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]), and NPC1 (PDB: 5F1B [
   <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]). The rendering of the CD4 cocrystal is from [
   <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. ACE2, angiotensin I converting enzyme 2; dN, rate of nonsynonymous substitution; dS, rate of synonymous substitution; NPC1, NPC intracellular cholesterol transporter 1; PDB, Protein Data Bank; SARS, severe acute respiratory syndrome; TfR1, transferrin receptor 1.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pbio.3000217.g002" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
