<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0045">Antibodies are a natural response for neutralizing viruses by either blocking the interaction between the virus and cell host or representing the viral antigens on the cell host to effector cells killing antibody-coated target cells. These cells permit the mechanisms as Antibody-Dependent Cellular Cytotoxicity (ADCC), and Antibody-Dependent Cellular Phagocytosis (ADCP) or a way known as Complement-Dependent Cytotoxicity (CDC) to eliminate infected cells 
 <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) owing to the unique properties of target specificity are an important class among therapeutic agents. They have played an unquestionable role in removing the infection 
 <xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. The mAbs neutralize viruses by blocking the interaction between virus and host cell through binding to free virus (opsonization of viruses) or binding to the required receptor on the cell surface for attaching and entering the virus into the cell. They also help to eliminate viral infections by representing the presented antigens on the infected target cell (by opsonization of infected cell) to the immune system effector cells (
 <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> A). The antibodies bind to the antigens by fragment antigen binding (Fab) and mediate the biological activity by fragment crystallizable (Fc) region, for example, with binding to complement or Fc receptors. Fcγ receptors are expressed on the types of effector cells such as phagocytes, natural killer (NK) cells and dendritic cells. Presentation of infected cells by mAbs to the effector cells leads to mechanisms as ADCC, ADCP or activation of cellular and humoral cells, CD8 T cells, CD4 T cells and subsequent activation of B cells. Binding to the complement component also may lead to CDC, virolysis or generates virus opsonized. Such viruses opsonized by complement are then eliminated in ways as ADCP (
 <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>B). The antiviral mAbs that bind to free viruses also can lead to virus elimination through dendritic cells activation, complement activation or ADCP 
 <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>.
</p>
