<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<author-notes>
 <corresp id="cor1">
  <label>*</label>Address correspondence to Ryan R. Hemme, Entomology and Ecology Activity, Dengue Branch, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 1324 Calle Cañada, San Juan 00920, Puerto Rico. E-mail: 
  <email>rhemme@cdc.gov</email>
 </corresp>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>Disclaimer: The findings and conclusions in this report are those of the authors and do not necessarily represent the views of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure">
  <p>Financial support: Funding was provided by the Division of Vector-Borne Infectious Diseases, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="present-address">
  <p>Authors’ addresses: Jeomhee M. Hasty, Environmental Health Services Division, Hawaii Department of Health, Vector Control Branch, Aiea, HI, E-mail: 
   <email>jeomhee.hasty@doh.hawaii.gov</email>. Gilberto E. Felix, Manuel Amador, Roberto Barrera, Stephanie Martinez-Conde, and Ryan R. Hemme, Entomology and Ecology Team, Dengue Branch, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, San Juan, Puerto Rico, E-mails: 
   <email>ckn5@cdc.gov</email>, 
   <email>maa4@cdc.gov</email>, 
   <email>amz9@cdc.gov</email>, 
   <email>mzn4@cdc.gov</email>, and 
   <email>rhemme@cdc.gov</email>. Gilberto S. Santiago, Jorge L. Munoz-Jordan, and Freddy A. Medina, Surveillance and Research Laboratory Team, Dengue Branch, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, San Juan, Puerto Rico, E-mails: 
   <email>fbz3@cdc.gov</email>, 
   <email>ckq2@cdc.gov</email>, and 
   <email>fkt3@cdc.gov</email>. Lynn Nakasone, Environmental Health Services Division, Hawaii Department of Health, Aiea, HI, E-mail: 
   <email>lynn.nakasone@doh.hawaii.gov</email>. Sarah Y. Park, Disease Outbreak Control Division, Hawaii Department of Health, Honolulu, HI, E-mail: 
   <email>sarah.park@doh.hawaii.gov</email>. Steven Okoji and Maricia Save, Environmental Health Services Division, Hawaii Department of Health, Kealakekua, HI, E-mails: 
   <email>steven.okoji@doh.hawaii.gov</email> and 
   <email>maricia.save@doh.hawaii.gov</email>. Eric Honda, Environmental Health Services Division, Hawaii Department of Health, Hilo, HI, E-mail: 
   <email>eric.honda@doh.hawaii.gov</email>. Bernard Asuncion, Environmental Health Services Division, Hawaii Department of Health, Vector Control Branch, Hilo, HI, E-mail: 
   <email>bernard.asuncion@doh.hawaii.gov</email>. Stephen H. Waterman, Dengue Branch, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, San Juan, Puerto Rico, E-mail: 
   <email>shw2@cdc.gov</email>. Lyle R. Petersen, Division of Vector-Borne Diseases, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Fort Collins, CO, E-mail: 
   <email>lxp2@cdc.gov</email>. David I. Johnston, Disease Outbreak Control Division, Department of Health, Honolulu, HI, E-mail: 
   <email>david.johnston@doh.hawaii.gov</email>.
  </p>
 </fn>
</author-notes>
