<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Until now, vaccination remains the most effective preventive measure for reducing the incidence and severity of the disease [
 <xref rid="B63-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. The selection of the influenza B virus strain for the annual trivalent vaccine is challenging, being low the protective effect of vaccination when the lineage opposite the vaccine or both lineages co-circulate in the population [
 <xref rid="B13-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Recent studies in Australia, United States, Europe, Latin America, and the Caribbean show that there is more than one-third of mismatches between the vaccine and the predominant circulating lineage [
 <xref rid="B26-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Indeed, we show here, that both influenza B lineages circulated almost 2012–2019, in different proportions. Mismatches were found between the vaccines and circulating strains. Our findings evidenced that the level of B vaccine mismatch varied during the eight seasons, with the highest impact being observed in 2015. Our data showed that 28% of the influenza B infections that circulated in Uruguay did not correspond to the lineage of the recommended vaccine strain. The potential impact of vaccine mismatch has been broadly investigated and the findings highlighted the effect on the epidemiology of influenza viruses. Furthermore, it was reported that the vaccine efficacy for influenza B was highly reduced when the circulating lineage was not matched with vaccine lineage [
 <xref rid="B13-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Although Uruguay provided the trivalent vaccine free of charge especially those at high risk, the vaccine coverage remained low (on average 24 % and 30% in subjects &lt; 4 years and &gt;64 years, respectively), as it happened in other countries of the region [
 <xref rid="B28-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. The lack of availability of vaccination data and antigenic analysis in our study population limit our possibility to draw any inference on this topic. However, the magnitude of the impact of seasonal vaccine mismatch on influenza epidemiology depends on several factors during a given season and the proportion of each influenza B virus lineage circulating, as reported by Reed and colleagues [
 <xref rid="B68-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Quadrivalent vaccines developed, which contain strains of both lineages, can be expected to increase the effectiveness of the vaccine and reduce the morbidity and mortality that are caused by the virus. It seems a logical consequence that children might benefit most from the implementation of specific vaccine-based preventive measures, with potential to reduce the burden of disease in vaccinated and unvaccinated individuals. However so far, only a few countries actually recommend the Quadrivalent influenza vaccination providing the vaccine free of charge [
 <xref rid="B69-microorganisms-08-00591" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>].
</p>
