<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We varied aspects of transmission dynamics and the sampling frame in the simulations, to obtain a more systematic understanding of methods’ performance (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="msw217-F5">fig. 5</xref>). Most phylogenetic methods did not identify significant differences between the high/low early transmission scenarios, and this was also the case when basic genetic distance measures recovered differences between the high/low early transmission scenarios (regional simulations, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). The true proportions of early transmissions were also frequently outside 95% confidence or credibility intervals. This indicates that further methods’ improvement is needed for estimating the proportion of early transmissions, and potentially for attributing sources of HIV-1 transmission more broadly at the low sequence coverage scenarios considered. Further, nearly all participants reported difficulties in achieving numerical convergence of their methods on full-genome sequence data (unpublished submission reports). This could explain the above observations in part, and in particular why the accuracy of early transmission estimates did not improve when using larger datasets with higher sequence coverage (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="msw217-F5">fig. 5</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). Further investigations are needed. Finally, our error analysis suggests that explicit modeling of unobserved source demes (team Cambridge-London) or identification of spatially localized phylogenetic clusters prior to transmission analyses (team London) could be effective approaches for mitigating the negative impact of viral introductions on phylogenetic analyses on mobile populations (
 <xref rid="msw217-B25" ref-type="bibr">Grabowski et al. 2014</xref>). The simulated PANGEA datasets as well as various aspects of the corresponding true epidemics and interventions are available for future benchmarking.
</p>
