<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A mathematical model that investigated parameters conditioning natural transmission and persistence of DENVs suggested that observed VTR in field settings are insufficient to maintain the virus in nature [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The modeling further suggested that the eVTR must be at least 20–30% to allow virus maintenance in nature in the absence of human-mediated amplification of DENVs. In our studies, MFIR from E2-10d mothers was 1:36 by IFA and RT-N-PCR, values substantially higher than reported for ZIKV (1:290;[
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]), and YFV (1:596;[
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]). The eVTR for E2-10d-F1 adult, infected mosquitos was 14–15% (
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), reflecting VT efficiencies that approach those suggested in the mathematical modeling study for DENV maintenance in nature [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Experimental studies of flavivirus VT in mosquitoes have variable results and indicate multiple factors can affect the frequency of VT and FIRs. These factors include mosquito species and geographic strain, mosquito age and mortality rate, virus genotype, persistence of virus during transstadial transitions, virus assay method, larval rearing temperature, interval between initial infection and second blood meal, and the ovarian cycle [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. These factors could certainly lower the eVTR of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>.
 <italic>aegypti</italic> in nature and their contributions to eVTR in a given vector population should be further studied. Nevertheless 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> biology and virus-vector interactions may enhance their eVTR. These positive factors include the mosquito’s acquisition of blood meals every few days and their demonstrated ability to go through multiple ovarian cycles. DENV maintenance in the vector population could be enhanced further by virus persistence in diapaused embryoes, DENV infection of oocytes and ovaries after the females acquire additional bloodmeals, and the relative efficiency of VNT. We hypothesize these attributes may counter the negative factors and allow the virus to persist in the vector population from one season to the next.
</p>
