<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>HIV prevalence in Uganda is among the highest in the world, with national prevalence estimated at 6.2% [
 <xref rid="pone.0231969.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] and prevalence among high risk populations such as fisherfolk and female sex workers at 30% [
 <xref rid="pone.0231969.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] and 33% [
 <xref rid="pone.0231969.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] respectively. While Uganda has been the site of abundant HIV prevention and research efforts, it is one of only two countries in Sub-Saharan Africa (SSA) in which HIV incidence is increasing, particularly in the general population [
 <xref rid="pone.0231969.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. There is some indication that unaddressed factors including injection and non-injection drug use may be impairing Uganda’s HIV prevention efforts [
 <xref rid="pone.0231969.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0231969.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Countries in SSA have seen rapid increases in injection drug use since 2008 including heroin and cocaine [
 <xref rid="pone.0231969.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0231969.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], and these drugs are also present and increasingly used in Uganda [
 <xref rid="pone.0231969.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0231969.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Heroin and cocaine injection are highly prevalent in the coastal areas of Tanzania and Kenya which have long acted as trans-shipment points but have increasingly opened local markets. A recent review of studies found a substantial proportion of heroin users who inject in Kenya and Tanzania [
 <xref rid="pone.0231969.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] and that these groups may have high HIV prevalence rates. In Kenya, of 101 current injectors, 52.5% were found to be HIV positive, attributed mainly to sharing injection equipment compared to 13.5% of heroin users who had not injected [
 <xref rid="pone.0231969.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In Uganda, the Global Sate of Harm report and studies conducted by Makerere University Crane Surveys have estimated HIV prevalence among people who inject drugs (PWID) at approximately 17% [
 <xref rid="pone.0231969.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0231969.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In 2018, the Kampala Place Study estimated over 18,000 people who inject drugs (PWID) in Uganda [
 <xref rid="pone.0231969.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. A high number of women who use injection and non-injection drugs report selling sex (79%) and may have significantly higher rates of HIV infection [
 <xref rid="pone.0231969.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. There is no reliable data on the prevalence of HCV as PWID are not tested for this in Uganda or other SSA countries [
 <xref rid="pone.0231969.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]
</p>
