<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0080">Every pathogen is capable of surviving on inanimate surfaces for a period [
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. We have come to understand that SARS-CoV-2 is a robust virus capable of surviving on the surfaces of metal and plastic for up to a few days and is not easily removed by standard air filtration systems [
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Thus, another approach to disrupt the chain of pathogen transfer needs to concentrate on the decontamination and sanitization of inanimate and skin surfaces. One agent that has been demonstrated to be viricidal, including activity against coronaviruses, is dilute povidone iodine [
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>]. Dilute povidone iodine was tested against SARS, MERS, and Ebola and found to have absolute efficacy. Other agents with potential activity against viruses, as well as bacterial and fungal pathogens, include hypochlorite and high-concentration alcohol. Thus, it is crucial that all reusable material in the OR, that includes helmets, lead aprons, tourniquets, X-ray machines, navigation consoles, keyboards, screens, and robots be sanitized and decontaminated routinely. The current sterilization systems in the hospitals for instruments and trays are effective in eliminating viruses and may not need to be altered. We may, however, need to implement a practice that requires these instruments to be placed in a bath of antiseptic solution during the procedure to prevent potential contamination. We must also be aware that there is a wide variation in the terminal cleaning of the operating rooms across the globe. Effective infection prevention and viricidal protocols need to be implemented in every operating room and arguably in every patient room after discharge.
</p>
