<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">Porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome (PRRS) caused by PRRS virus (PRRSV) results in economic losses in the swine industry globally. Several studies have investigated the use of plant extracts in the prevention and control of PRRS outbreaks. Thai medicinal plants may be useful for treating PRRSV infection in pigs. Therefore, we investigated the in vitro anti-PRRSV and antioxidant properties of seven Thai medicinal plants: 
   <italic>Caesalpinia sappan</italic> Linn., 
   <italic>Garcinia mangostana</italic> Linn
   <italic>.</italic>, 
   <italic>Houttuynia cordata</italic>, 
   <italic>Perilla frutescens</italic>, 
   <italic>Clinacanthus nutans</italic>, 
   <italic>Phyllanthus emblica</italic>, and 
   <italic>Tiliacora triandra</italic>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p id="Par2">Using antiviral screening, we observed that 
   <italic>T. triandra</italic> extract strongly inhibited PRRSV infectivity in MARC-145 cells [virus titer 3.5 median tissue culture infective dose (TCID
   <sub>50</sub>)/ml (log10)] at 24 h post-infection, whereas 
   <italic>C. sappan</italic> extract strongly inhibited PRRSV replication [virus titer 2.5 TCID
   <sub>50</sub>/ml (log10)] at 72 h post-infection. 
   <italic>C. sappan</italic> extract had the highest total phenolic content [220.52 mM gallic acid equivalent/g] and lowest half-maximal inhibitory concentration [1.17 mg/ml in 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl and 2.58 mg/ml in 2,2-azino-bis (3-ethylbenzothiazo-line-6-sulfonic acid) diammonium salt].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p id="Par3">
   <italic>T. triandra</italic> extract could inhibit PRRSV infectivity, whereas 
   <italic>C. sappan</italic> extract was the most effective in inhibiting PRRSV replication in MARC-145 cells. This study elucidates the antiviral activities of Thai medicinal plant extracts in vivo. The results promise that Thai medicinal plant extracts, particularly 
   <italic>T. triandra</italic> and 
   <italic>C. sappan</italic> extracts, can be developed into pharmaceutical drugs for the prevention of PRRS in pigs.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
