<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">Shenzhen City is a rapidly growing area with a large number of floating populations, thus making it difficult to control HIV. Serial cross-sectional studies are helpful for the prediction of epidemiological tendency. In this study, two parallel cross-sectional studies were compared to explore changes in HIV epidemiology in Shenzhen, China.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p id="Par2">Two hundred and fifty newly reported HIV-positive cases were randomly selected in Shenzhen City in 2013 and 2015. Socio-demographical information was collected with informed consent. Full-length 
   <italic>gag</italic> and partial 
   <italic>pol</italic> genes were amplified using nested RT-PCR followed by sequencing and phylogenetic analysis. The genotypes of anti-HIV drug resistance were also analyzed. The characteristics of the HIV epidemics of 2013 and 2015 were compared to identify patterns.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p id="Par3">The proportion of single, young MSMs dramatically increased in 2015 compared to 2013. Many subtypes, including CRF07_BC (36.4%), CRF01_AE (34.1%), CRF55_01B (10.2%), B (6.4%), CRF08_BC (3.4%), CRF59_01B (0.9%), C (0.7%), D (0.2%), CRF68_01B (0.2%), CRF67_01B (0.2%), and unique recombinant forms (URFs, 7.3%), were identified. Close phylogenetic relationships between strains prevalent in Shenzhen and other areas of China was observed. No epidemic cluster confined to single, young MSMs was identified. 0.4 and 2.8% of the strains contained transmitted drug-resistant mutations in 2013 and 2015, respectively.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p id="Par4">Although the interval period is short, changes in HIV epidemiology in Shenzhen City are distinct. Frequent surveillance of HIV epidemics in Shenzhen City is thus necessary. Single, young MSMs have become a high-risk population for HIV infection and should be considered as focus population for HIV prevention and behavior intervention in Shenzhen City.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Electronic supplementary material</title>
  <p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12985-019-1189-6) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
