<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Before introducing statistical methodologies that are commonly used for parameter estimation, we distinguish model parameters into two categories. Those that can be determined 
 <italic>a priori</italic> with no need for estimation, which we term as 
 <italic>hyperparameters</italic>. Those that cannot be fully determined and need to be estimated using the data at hand, which we term as 
 <italic>target parameters</italic>. The choices of which parameter should be a target parameter versus a hyperparameter vary widely across methods. Intuitively, the more we know about the biological characteristics of a disease, the more parameters can be held fixed 
 <italic>a priori</italic> in the analysis. It is however very difficult to determine most of the model parameters early in an outbreak because of the limited amount of knowledge and data about the disease. Indeed, many model parameters are not identifiable because of the lack of relevant data availability. One such example is the rate parameter of immunity 
 <italic>α</italic> in the SAIR model (
 <xref rid="insr12402-disp-0009" ref-type="disp-formula">6</xref>). As relevant knowledge accumulates, literature reveals increasingly precise characterisation of the disease, such as its latency period, recovery rate, death rate, immunity duration and antibody acquirement. Such information is typically obtained from surveys of high‐quality individual‐level data, which may provide much better quantification of these hyperparameters than having to be re‐estimated by epidemic models, which, on the other hand, are largely based on much coarser surveillance data. In the case of the COVID‐19 pandemic, this survey‐based approach may be too costly to carry out in countries with large and heterogeneous populations. In general, target parameters are mostly those that are location specific, for example, transmission rate and fatality rate. They vary largely across regions because of non‐uniform mitigation effort and hospital resources; hence, data‐driven estimations are preferred. In Section 
 <xref rid="insr12402-sec-0032" ref-type="sec">6</xref>, we introduce an areal spatial modelling approach to account for spatial heterogeneity in the analysis of infectious disease data.
</p>
