<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0260">This study demonstrates a method for producing cellulose derivative nanoparticles containing RTV and EFV with well-defined sizes (100 nm–200 nm). A multi-inlet vortex mixer was used to control the particle size and nucleation rate, and flash nanoprecipitation was shown to be an effective method for making these nanoparticles. The particles were processed by dialysis followed by freeze-drying; the cryoprotectant trehalose was used to inhibit particle aggregation during freeze-drying. The drug loading efficiency of the final particles was 88–96%. The polymers effectively entrapped the drugs in an amorphous state in the particle, which in turn increased the solubility of the drugs in the buffer solution. There was an increase in percent drug release from nanoparticles compared to pure crystalline drug. The microparticles containing RTV and EFV showed peak/trough fluctuations in solubility and drug release values compared to nanoparticles, which showed a comparatively steady pattern. Therefore, nanoparticles of polysaccharides-drug complexes showed the potential for enhancing the solubility and sustained release of poorly soluble drugs (RTV and EFV). The dissolution behavior was dependent on the particle size and properties of the polymer (solubility parameter, degree of substitution, hydrophobicity) as well as the drug (solubility parameter, solubility, presence of hydrophobic groups). Therefore, an optimal hydrophobicity may exist for inhibiting crystallization. A higher degree of substitution (DS) shows more effective inhibition of crystallization (more ionizable carboxylic acids can better inhibit crystal growth). The particle shape, size, polydispersity and morphology vary with preparation method, and thus, care must be taken in the synthesis and purification (separation, drying) techniques to obtain well-defined particles. The use of excipients, such as cryoprotectants (or excipients), to control the particle size would be a useful additional step. This study showed synergy between a high surface area (due to nanoparticles) and suppression of crystallinity (due to amorphous dispersions of cellulose acetate matrix) in enhancing the dissolution of poorly soluble drugs.</p>
