<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par41">COVID-19 is continued to be a threat to public health and presents a global challenge to all the research communities around the world to get over from this crisis. Although many compounds have been tested in both non-clinical (simulations, in vitro, and studies in animals) and clinical settings, but unfortunately, there are no FDA-approved vaccines and specific therapeutic interventions for COVID-19 to date. Several strategies have been employed to target the COVID-19 treatment regimen, and three major strategies that are targeted nowadays are repurposing drugs, investigating the efficacy of antibodies, and developing vaccines. Clinical trials are underway in search of a targeted and efficacious treatment for COVID-19; however, certain barriers have limited the results of previous trials, and these need to be addressed for getting a more reliable and conclusive outcome. The four major issues that need to be pondered upon to avoid the inconclusive results from previous trials are dose optimization, well-defined therapeutic timing window, trial designs (randomized and adequate powered), and selection of specific outcome measures. Further, there is a need for international collaborative work to fight this pandemic and develop a more robust infrastructure to mitigate the COVID-19 pandemic. Also, innovative computational–based methods like artificial intelligence should be applied to accelerate the traditional drug discovery process, so that this can reduce the total time taken and could be helpful in faster development of drugs during any emergency conditions or pandemic. Keeping in view the emergence of novel life-threatening diseases from mutating RNA viruses with a potential of cross-species transmission, there is a need for a broad-spectrum antiviral agent that could effectively reduce the viral load targeting a wide group of viruses and helps in reducing the massive consequences on human health. Further, we recommend the use of combination therapy that includes both antivirals and non-antiviral regimens to combat both viremia and associated immunopathological symptoms like lymphocytopenia and cytokine storm that might lead to acute lung injury and respiratory failure. Also, emphasis should be given to the rational and adequate use of drugs to prevent the resistance, which is quite common with these mutating RNA viruses. Moreover, the heritage of traditionally used medicinal and herbal compounds should be explored more and needs to be validated via clinical trials, so that their clinical efficacy could be established and would help provide protection for any epidemics like COVID-19. Finally, we hope that the current ongoing efforts will be successful and sooner the drugs and vaccines for COVID-19 will be available, and the world will emerge with better and robust infrastructure, funding, and regulatory measures to combat such future pandemics.</p>
