<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mitochondrial reprogramming in tumour progression extends beyond changes in mitochondrial bioenergetics. Tumour metastasis, a process implicated in 90% of cancer deaths, is also dictated by changes in mitochondrial function and distribution [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. Agarwal et al. [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>] demonstrated that the exploitation of mitochondrial trafficking is a key hallmark of myc-driven tumour progression, where subcellular mitochondrial trafficking to the cortical cytoskeleton is vital for tumour cell invasion and metastasis. Myc proteins are products of oncogenes, often amplified in human cancers, which promote tumour growth and progression. They have been associated with the control of the gene network of mitochondrial trafficking and changes in the expression of OXPHOS genes and bioenergetics pathways [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Mitochondrial trafficking and redistribution is a vital and standard process in healthy neurones, where mitochondria are repositioned to axon terminals to fuel highly energy-intensive processes such as synaptic functions and active growth cones [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]; however, the same protein network is exploited by tumour cells to propel metastasis [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. The importance of mitochondrial trafficking in myc-driven tumours is further highlighted by the up-regulation of RHOT2, a mitochondrial atypical GTPase [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>], and the down-regulation of syntaphilin (SNPH), an inhibitor of mitochondrial trafficking [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>] in tumour progression. This recent evidence demonstrates the involvement of mitochondrial dynamics in tumour progression; therefore, the inhibition of myc proteins through doxycycline use, or drug-induced modulation of mitochondrial dynamics may have therapeutic benefit.
</p>
