<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This conundrum was resolved once we noticed that only i.n. immunization induces T
 <sub>RM</sub> responses in the lung. CD8T
 <sub>RM</sub> cells act as sentinels in the host and form the first line of defense, providing rapid and effective protection to fight against pathogens invasion [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008036.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1008036.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1008036.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1008036.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Prior studies have revealed that direct delivery of vaccines to the target tissue is necessary for the generation of T
 <sub>RM</sub> cells [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008036.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1008036.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] and that sustained lung CD8T
 <sub>RM</sub> responses in MCMV-infected mice are generated by immunoproteasome-independent antigenic stimulation [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008036.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], akin to the CD8 expansions in memory inflation [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008036.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], arguing that their induction may share similar or overlapping mechanisms. Some prior studies have claimed that skin-resident CD8T
 <sub>RM</sub> cells may confer protection in an antigen-unspecific manner [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008036.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], whereas others argued that only the antigen-specific CD8T
 <sub>RM</sub> cells respond to cognate antigens [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008036.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. MCMV
 <sup>WT</sup> induced robust CD8T
 <sub>RM</sub> responses in our model, but these were not specific for IAV, and did not provide any protection against IAV in our study. Site-specific anti-CD8α antibody administration depleted CD8T
 <sub>RM</sub>, and increased IAV titers in immunized mice, indicating that CD8T
 <sub>RM</sub> cells facilitated IAV elimination. Thus, the protection against IAV challenge requires antigen-specific CD8T
 <sub>RM</sub> cells in our model. However, the weight loss was not different in the early days upon challenge and T
 <sub>RM</sub> depletion affected chemokine expression and T cell influx at later time points.
</p>
