<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The 
 <italic>effective reproductive number</italic> is defined as 
 <math id="nlm-math-5">
  <msub>
   <mrow>
    <mi>R</mi>
   </mrow>
   <mrow>
    <mi>e</mi>
   </mrow>
  </msub>
  <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
  <mi>t</mi>
  <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
  <mo>=</mo>
  <msub>
   <mrow>
    <mi>R</mi>
   </mrow>
   <mrow>
    <mn>0</mn>
   </mrow>
  </msub>
  <mfrac>
   <mrow>
    <mi>S</mi>
    <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
   </mrow>
   <mrow>
    <mi>N</mi>
   </mrow>
  </mfrac>
 </math>. It represents the expected number of newly infected individuals who contract the virus directly from a contagious individual at time 
 <italic>t</italic>, given that each susceptible individual has a chance of 
 <italic>S</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>)/
 <italic>N</italic> to meet this contagious individual. This is not to be confused with the notation 
 <italic>R</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>), the removed population. In the early outbreak of an infectious disease in a large population, 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>e</italic>
 </sub>(
 <italic>t</italic>)≈
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> because 
 <italic>S</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>)/
 <italic>N</italic>≈1. In contrast to 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub>, which is only descriptive of the disease itself (or the progression of disease near time 0), 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>e</italic>
 </sub>(
 <italic>t</italic>) reflects the progression of the infectious disease in a population at any given time because it directs the sign of 
 <italic>dI</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>)/
 <italic>dt</italic> corresponding to acceleration or deceleration of the infection dynamics. This may be seen by the second‐order derivative 
 <italic>d</italic>
 <sup>2</sup>
 <italic>I</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>)/
 <italic>d</italic>
 <italic>t</italic>
 <sup>2</sup>; a time, say 
 <italic>t</italic>
 <sup>∗</sup>, at which 
 <italic>d</italic>
 <sup>2</sup>
 <italic>I</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>
 <sup>∗</sup>)/
 <italic>d</italic>
 <italic>t</italic>
 <sup>2</sup>=0 or the rate 
 <italic>dI</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>
 <sup>∗</sup>)/
 <italic>dt</italic> reaches a peak, is referred to as a turning point (see the peak in the middle panel of Figure 
 <xref rid="insr12402-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Hence, 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> is of most interest during the early phase of an epidemic, whereas 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>e</italic>
 </sub>(
 <italic>t</italic>) is of most interest later on during the controlling phases of an epidemic. For example, the so‐called herd immunity is the natural immunity developed when an epidemic reaches 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>e</italic>
 </sub>(
 <italic>t</italic>)&lt;1. In other words, without interventions, it requires the proportion of susceptible individuals to be no more than 1/
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub>, or the combined proportion of infectious and recovered to be at least 1−1/
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> in order to contain the spread. As another example, if an effective vaccine becomes available at time 
 <math id="nlm-math-6">
  <mover accent="true">
   <mrow>
    <mi>t</mi>
   </mrow>
   <mo>˜</mo>
  </mover>
  <mo>&gt;</mo>
  <mn>0</mn>
 </math>, knowing 
 <math id="nlm-math-7">
  <msub>
   <mrow>
    <mi>R</mi>
   </mrow>
   <mrow>
    <mi>e</mi>
   </mrow>
  </msub>
  <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
  <mover accent="true">
   <mrow>
    <mi>t</mi>
   </mrow>
   <mo>˜</mo>
  </mover>
  <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
 </math> allows us to estimate the remaining proportion of population that needs to be vaccinated in order to control the epidemic (i.e. for achieving 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>e</italic>
 </sub>(
 <italic>t</italic>)&lt;1). Figure 
 <xref rid="insr12402-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref> shows that the effective reproductive number 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>e</italic>
 </sub>(
 <italic>t</italic>) for Example 
 <xref rid="insr12402-mthst-0001" ref-type="statement">1</xref> decreases as the group of susceptible individuals, 
 <italic>S</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>), shrinks over time, eventually reaching below the threshold of 1 at time 19. The value at time 0 is 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub>=
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>e</italic>
 </sub>(0)=2.5, while 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>e</italic>
 </sub>(19)=1. The time of reaching this threshold also marks a special time of interest—when the number of active contagious individuals starts decreasing at time 19 after reaching its maximum, as shown in the middle panel of Figure 
 <xref rid="insr12402-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>.
</p>
