<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Often forgotten, rabies qualifies as a vaccine-preventable disease. Effective rabies biologics have been available for over a century 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>
 </sup>. Pre-exposure vaccination is highly efficacious for those at risk of exposure, such as veterinarians, laboratory workers, and certain travelers 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, 
  <xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>
 </sup>. After exposure, the prompt and proper application of post-exposure prophylaxis (PEP)—consisting of wound care, infiltration of rabies immune globulin (RIG), and administration of modern rabies vaccines—virtually ensures survival 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>
 </sup>. Nevertheless, the majority of persons at risk do not receive pre-exposure vaccination and most RABV-exposed patients are never provided adequate PEP. This discrepancy between Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices/World Health Organization (ACIP/WHO) recommendations and reality has sparked strong debate and translational research for more novel, less expensive products; simplified schedules; and improved ease of use 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>– 
  <xref rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>
 </sup>. Outstanding questions for resolution include the following: Can PEP be performed safely without RIG (given that limited availability means more than 90% of persons do not receive it)? Are heterologous (for example, equine) RIG products equivalent to human RIG in regard to safety and effectiveness? If so, how should their production be increased? Is the dose of RIG critical in terms of international units per kilograms or is local infiltration more important, regardless of absolute dose? Does administration of vaccine directly into exposure sites improve survivorship if RIG is not available? Could PEP completion be reduced to one week or less? What is the role for rabies pre-exposure vaccine inclusion into childhood schedules? When will GAVI add human rabies vaccine to its portfolio? Will monoclonal antibodies help to resolve the issues with RIG availability and distribution? Should new biologics be developed to increase the breadth of reactivity against non-phylogroup I lyssaviruses? Is there a role for new adjuvants or attenuated RABV vaccines to obviate the need for RIG? Should genes involved in the innate immune response (for example, interferons) be incorporated into genomes of recombinant RABV vaccine strains? Although the field will always profit from relevant advances, much attention is often spent on academic research on new biologics and less on translational research for the appropriate use of existing products and protocols to prevent rabies now ( 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>).
</p>
