<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the last decade, a change of the epidemiology of liver disease has been observed with an increasing trend towards non-viral etiology. However, virus-related hepatitis remains the main cause of liver disease worldwide [
 <xref rid="B1-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The most common causes of viral hepatitis are the five hepatotropic viruses, hepatitis A virus (HAV), hepatitis B virus (HBV), hepatitis C virus (HCV), hepatitis D virus (HDV), and hepatitis E virus (HEV). In 1980, the bulk of hepatitis cases in India were attributed to a hitherto unrecognized pathogen [
 <xref rid="B3-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Three years later, an experimental infection of an HAV-immune volunteer from the research team led to the discovery of HEV. After ingestion of pooled stool extracts from presumed hepatitis patients, he too developed hepatitis. The volunteer’s serum did not contain anti-HAV IgM and HBV. Spherical 27–30 nm viruses were detected by immuno-electron microscopy; these were inoculated in cynomolgus monkeys, where they successfully caused hepatitis and elicited an antibody response [
 <xref rid="B4-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Identification and sequencing of the virus followed; the disease was thereafter known as hepatitis E, with HEV as the causative pathogen [
 <xref rid="B5-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. This organism is most appropriately allocated the letter “E”, which could stand for “enteric”, “epidemic”, or “endemic”, all of which are features ascribed to the epidemiology of HEV [
 <xref rid="B6-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. HEV is possibly the most prevalent cause of acute viral hepatitis around the globe [
 <xref rid="B7-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. HEV has a small particle with a positive-sense RNA genome (≈7.2 kb) [
 <xref rid="B8-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. HEV particles are now considered as “quasi-enveloped particles”, existing as non-enveloped virions in the feces and bile of infected individuals, while cellular membrane-bounded particles are found within the bloodstream [
 <xref rid="B9-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. According to a recent proposal, HEV is classified as a member of the 
 <italic>Hepeviridae</italic> family with two genera. The first genus, 
 <italic>Orthohepevirus</italic> has four species, 
 <italic>Orthohepevirus A</italic>, with eight genotypes including those infectious to humans, and 
 <italic>Orthohepevirus B, C,</italic> and 
 <italic>D,</italic> which are not infectious to human. The other genus 
 <italic>Piscihepevirus</italic> contains one non-human-infecting species [
 <xref rid="B12-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. All human-infecting HEV genotypes belong to species 
 <italic>Orthohepevirus A</italic>. Genotypes 1 and 2 infect humans exclusively, while 
 <italic>HEV3</italic> and 
 <italic>HEV4</italic> infect a wide range of animals in addition to humans. Genotype 7, which was isolated from camels, is also infectious to humans, while genotypes 5 and 6 infect wild boars and are not known to infect humans [
 <xref rid="B12-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. All the genotypes of mammalian HEV are represented by one serotype [
 <xref rid="B13-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. There are many known reservoirs of HEV, with pigs as the most important reservoir. Other species of animals also serve as HEV reservoirs [
 <xref rid="B13-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. HEV infections can cause fulminant hepatic failure, and, with genotypes 1 and 2, a devastatingly high maternal mortality is seen primarily in the second and third trimesters [
 <xref rid="B14-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. HEV is not only responsible for acute sporadic or epidemic viral hepatitis but has been recently shown to be associated with chronic hepatitis as well [
 <xref rid="B17-medicina-56-00206" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].
</p>
