<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The SIR dynamic system in (
 <xref rid="insr12402-disp-0001" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref>) may be interpreted as follows. Let us consider events occurring instantaneously at time 
 <italic>t</italic>. In the first ODE, the ratio 
 <italic>I</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>)/
 <italic>N</italic> represents the proportion of contagious individuals in the population, which may be thought of as a chance that a person in the at‐risk population may run into a virus carrier. If each individual at risk has an independent chance to meet a contagious person, then, according to the binomial distribution, the expected number of susceptible individuals contracting the virus is 
 <italic>S</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>)
 <italic>I</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>)/
 <italic>N</italic>. In reality, a person at risk may run into 
 <italic>β</italic> (say, 2) contagious individuals, leading to a modified chance 
 <italic>βI</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>)/
 <italic>N</italic>. Thus, instantaneously at time 
 <italic>t</italic>, the system gains an additional number of infected cases equal to 
 <italic>βS</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>)
 <italic>I</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>)/
 <italic>N</italic>, and these cases will leave the susceptible compartment to enter the infectious compartment. Such loss to 
 <italic>S</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>) is attributed to the negative sign in the first equation. In the second ODE, the first term is the number of new arrivals of contagious individuals and the second term is the loss of contagious individuals at a rate 
 <italic>γ</italic> who either recover or die and then enter the removed compartment. The third ODE is based on an absorbed compartment that always accumulates with new arrivals with no departure cases. In the literature, the transition rate 
 <italic>γ</italic> represents the fraction of the infectious population that exits the infectious system per unit time. For example, 
 <italic>γ</italic>=0.2 means that the infection compartment will decay (or infectious individuals being recovered or dead) at an average rate 20
 <italic>%</italic>. In other words, 1/
 <italic>γ</italic> describes the expected duration (5 days for 
 <italic>γ</italic>=0.2) over which an individual stays infectious under the exponential distribution of time for his or her sojourn.
</p>
