<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The year 2014 witnessed the largest historical outbreak of dengue with the maximum number of cases and the widest distribution. Of 45,189 reported cases, 45,131 indigenous ones accounted for 99.8%, reaching the trend that local ones were dominant in recent years.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>–
  <xref rid="b40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>
 </sup> Previous studies indicated that although three DENV serotypes (DENV1, DENV2, and DENV3) were identified, DENV1 was the major causative agent of this outbreak which had circulated continuously in multiple geographies.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
  <xref rid="b42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>
 </sup> So far, the results mentioned were consistent with those of our study. The term “lineage” has been used to denote the viruses clustered in clades at a taxonomic level beneath the genotype. The appearance, change, and reappearance of specific lineages are closely linked to the transmission of those viruses.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>–
  <xref rid="b45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>
 </sup> Here, 56 strains of viruses differing in their E genes were obtained, of which nine and 47 strains belonged to genotypes I and V, respectively. Unlike the strains of genotype I which were linked to two lineages, each strain in genotype V branched into the same clade, forming a stable lineage. However, several lineages from different origins were responsible for the DENV outbreak in 2014. Moreover, strains belonging to genotype V were detected in six areas evaluated in this study. All 13 strains from Shanwei, Chaozhou, and Huizhou gathered together also belonged to this genotype, illustrating that the same lineage was prevalent in multiple regions. Coincidentally, some epidemiological data indicate that DENV1 was restricted only to the local epidemics since 1997,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>
 </sup> a phenomenon which was reported by Guo et al.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
 </sup> Overall, the aforementioned evidence strongly opposes the conventional belief that DF in Guangdong was completely imported.
</p>
