<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The first cases of hemorrhagic fever with renal syndrome (HFRS) were reported in northeastern China in the early 1930s [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007091.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. During the past seven decades, this rodent-borne zoonosis, caused by Hantavirus, has been spreading southwards to other parts of China. Currently, 31 provinces, autonomous regions, and metropolitan areas of mainland China, are exposed to significant health risks due to this infectious disease. In particular, the reported HFRS cases correspond to approximately 90% of all global number of cases [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007091.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007091.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Specifically, the 
 <italic>Hantaan</italic> virus (HTNV) and the 
 <italic>Seoul</italic> virus (SEOV), hosted by 
 <italic>Apodemus agrarius</italic> and 
 <italic>Rattus norvegicus</italic>, respectively, are the two predominant sources of HFRS in China (see, e.g., [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007091.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007091.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007091.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]). The hantavirus is transmitted from rodents to humans through inhalation of aerosolized excreta (such as urine and saliva) or direct contact [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007091.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Infected human specimens suffer from fever, headache, abdominal pain, insufficient renal function, and hemorrhagic episodes [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007091.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007091.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. For the period 2004–2008, most HFRS cases reported in China concerned young and middle-age farmers [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007091.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] with case fatality rate (CFR) 1.17%, and females experiencing higher CFRs than males in the age groups of 20–39 and &gt;50 years [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007091.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Also HFRS cases in males were more than three times higher than those reported in females. Evidently, HFRS poses a serious threat to public health in China.
</p>
