<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In a pilot experiment employing selected NS1 positive serum samples NS1 detection by the SD Bioline NS1 antigen rapid test was completely abolished by standard glycine [
 <xref rid="pone.0230337.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0230337.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0230337.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and heat treatment [
 <xref rid="pone.0230337.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0230337.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] (
 <bold>
  <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0230337.s005">S4 Fig</xref>
 </bold>). Several reasons can account for this apparent methodical incompatibility: 1) Acid treatment may (partially) denature DENV NS1, preventing efficient binding of monoclonal antibodies recognizing conformational epitopes and thereby hamper efficient binding to the gold-labeled mouse anti-NS1 antibody and/or the detection antibody on the test line. 2) Even if binding to the gold-labeled anti-NS1 antibody to the acid-treated NS1 protein is still possible, efficient flow of the formed complexes across the membrane strip may be hindered by the denaturation-induced formation of larger protein aggregates. 3) The buffer conditions in the acid treated/neutralized samples may interfere with binding of the NS1 protein to the gold-labeled antibody or the antibody on the test line. Thus, alternative IC dissociation methods employing milder conditions, e.g. 0.1 M glycine pH 2.8 (as is commonly employed for elution of proteins from immunoaffinity columns) and shorter exposure times to dissociating conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0230337.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], should be tested for their compatibility with NS1 antigen detection assays. An elegant alternative approach to enable NS1 antigen detection in samples from patients with secondary infections in an ELISA format would be not to aim for permanent, complete dissociation of serum ICs but to exploit their presence/reformation after a short term, mild dissociation by directly detecting them using an immune complex receptor molecule like C1q, CD16, or CD32 [
 <xref rid="pone.0230337.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] as capture molecule.
</p>
