<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
 <label>FIGURE 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Ability of influenza NS1 proteins to inhibit host gene expression and ISRE promoter activation: Human 293T cells (2.5 × 10
   <sup>5</sup> cells/well, 24-well plate format, triplicates) were transiently co-transfected with 25 ng of polymerase II expression pCAGGS plasmids encoding Gluc together with 1 μg of the indicated HA epitope tagged IAV (PR8 and 1918), IBV, ICV, and IDV NS1 pCAGGS plasmids, or empty (E) pCAGGS plasmid as internal control. At 24 h post-transfection, Gluc activity in the tissue culture supernatants was evaluated using a Lumicount luminometer 
   <bold>(A)</bold>. Results represent the means and standard deviation (SD) of triplicate values. 
   <sup>∗</sup>
   <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.05 using Student’s 
   <italic>t</italic>-test (
   <italic>n</italic> = 3 per time point), for comparisons of cells transfected with E plasmid or plasmids encoding IAV (PR8 or 1918), IBV, ICV, or IDV NS1 proteins. 
   <bold>(B)</bold> NS1 protein expression levels from transfected cells were evaluated by Western blot using an HA tag epitope antibody. Actin was used as loading control. Molecular mass markers (in kDa) are indicated on the left. 
   <bold>(C,D)</bold> Ability of influenza NS1 proteins to inhibit ISRE promoter activation upon SeV infection: Human 293T cells (2.5 × 10
   <sup>5</sup> cells/well, 24-well plate format, triplicates) were transiently co-transfected, using the CaPO
   <sub>4</sub> method, with a reporter plasmid encoding FFluc under the control of an ISRE promoter (pISRE-FFluc), a plasmid constitutively expressing Rluc under the control of a polymerase II promoter (pSV40-Rluc), and the indicated HA epitope tagged IAV (PR8 and 1918), IBV, ICV, and IDV NS1 pCAGGS expressing plasmids, or empty (E) pCAGGS plasmid as control. At 20 h post-transfection, cells were mock infected (SeV–) or infected (SeV +) with SeV (MOI = 3) to induce activation of the ISRE promoter, and, 24 h after SeV infection, cells were analyzed for FFluc and Rluc activities using a Lumicount luminometer (
   <bold>C</bold>). Results represent the means and SD of triplicate values. 
   <sup>∗</sup>
   <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.05 or 
   <sup>∗∗</sup>
   <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.001 using Student’s 
   <italic>t</italic>-test (
   <italic>n</italic> = 3 per time point), for comparisons of expression levels in SeV-infected cells previously transfected with E plasmid or plasmids encoding the NS1 from IAV (PR8 or 1918), IBV, ICV, or IDV. NS1 protein expression levels from total cell lysates were determined by Western blot as indicated above 
   <bold>(D)</bold>. Experiments were repeated twice, with similar results.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="fmicb-10-02862-g001" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
