<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Landsat 8 images of Barranquilla for the year 2014 (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijerph-16-01759">Figure S1</xref>) and 2015 (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijerph-16-01759">Figure S2</xref>) were obtained from the United States Geological Survey website [
 <xref rid="B53-ijerph-16-01759" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. To increase the spatial resolution of multispectral bands (provided at 30 m resolution), a pan-sharpening process was applied, excluding thermal infrared bands, using the 15 m panchromatic band. Atmospheric corrections were then conducted for bands one to eight using the DOS model-based algorithm and assuming 1% minimum reflectance [
 <xref rid="B54-ijerph-16-01759" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Radiance and ground reflectance were subsequently obtained for each band [
 <xref rid="B55-ijerph-16-01759" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Band combinations for ideal enhancement of vegetation were obtained from openweathermap.org [
 <xref rid="B56-ijerph-16-01759" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. A traditional infrared colour map with the band combinations of 5-4-3 was used to highlight areas of vegetation. A modification of the normalised difference water index (MNDWI) image was then created to highlight areas of water [
 <xref rid="B57-ijerph-16-01759" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. These raster images were combined to define areas of vegetation, building and water coverage. Finally, zonal histogram statistics were extracted from the raster to calculate the percentage surface area of each neighbourhood that was occupied by vegetation, buildings or water. Next, the MNDWI image was used to calculate the average distance of each neighbourhood from large bodies of water identified in the raster. The Euclidian (straight-line) distance tool in ArcGIS was used to calculate the straight-line distance from the centroid of each neighbourhood to the nearest pixel of water identified in the MNDWI. All geographical processing was performed in ArcGIS 10.3 (ESRI Inc., Redlands, CA, USA) [
 <xref rid="B58-ijerph-16-01759" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>].
</p>
