<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The theme issue's final section focuses on applied perspectives to detect early spillover events (i.e. surveillance) and the role of interventions focused upstream in the spillover pathway. In particular, early detection is critical for minimizing the spread of zoonotic pathogens following an initial spillover event [
 <xref rid="RSTB20190014C50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. A first series of manuscripts emphasize different approaches to the surveillance of zoonoses. Schmidt 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="RSTB20190014C51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] use machine learning tools (e.g. boosted regression trees [
 <xref rid="RSTB20190014C52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]) to predict which mammal species are more likely to play roles in Ebola virus spillover events. The authors show that large-bodied, frugivorous mammals with slow life histories are likely host species, implicating some insectivorous bats, Old World monkeys and forest antelopes as possible Ebola virus reservoirs. Predictions such as these can help prioritize future wildlife surveillance efforts (e.g. [
 <xref rid="RSTB20190014C53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]). Kuisma 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="RSTB20190014C54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] in turn describe a community-based surveillance effort focused on wildlife mortality reporting and oriented to early detection of Ebola virus disease outbreaks. Spanning over a decade and covering 50 000 km
 <sup>2</sup> of challenging terrain in the Congo basin, this programme has reached hundreds of villages and thousands of hunters and forest gatherers. The programme has educated community members in wildlife carcass reporting and behavioral risk reduction as well as built capacity for safe carcass sampling by trained local responders. This region was not confronted with an Ebola virus outbreak during the period described here, and all reported carcasses tested negative. Nevertheless, given the well-recognized fact that early intervention can avert massive human and economic costs of widespread epidemics, the low-cost and scalable surveillance programme described by the authors could provide key early detection capability more generally.
</p>
