<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0115">Knowledge gained from studies on SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV will be valuable for determining the suitability of IFN-I as a treatment strategy in COVID-19. Two 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> studies have already demonstrated that SARS-CoV-2 has greater sensitivity to IFN-I compared with SARS-CoV (
 <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Lokugamage et al., 2020</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Mantlo et al., 2020</xref>). In these studies, pre-treatment with IFN-α or IFN-β drastically reduced viral titers. These findings suggest that IFN-I may be effective as a prophylactic agent or an early treatment option for SARS-CoV-2. Several efforts are ongoing to test this. The guidelines in China for the treatment of COVID-19 include vapor inhalation of IFN-α, in conjunction with ribavirin (
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Sallard et al., 2020</xref>). This route of delivery has the benefit of targeting IFN-α specifically to the respiratory tract. Several clinical trials to evaluate IFN-I as a single or combination therapy in COVID-19 have been registered across the world. These include the DisCoVeRy trial (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04315948" id="intref0010" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04315948</ext-link>, the first clinical trial by the WHO Solidarity consortium) that compares subcutaneous injection of IFN-β1a in combination with lopinavir-ritonavir, lopinavir-ritonavir alone, hydroxychloroquine, or remdesivir, as well as the Phase II trial on inhaled IFN-β1a as a single agent in UK (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04385095" id="intref0015" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04385095</ext-link>) (
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Sallard et al., 2020</xref>). In a retrospective study of 77 COVID-19 patients in Wuhan, China treated with nebulized IFN-α2b, arbidol, or a combination of the two, IFN-α2b therapy significantly reduced the duration of detectable virus and inflammatory markers, IL-6 and C-reactive protein (CRP) (
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2020</xref>). Another study showed that recombinant IFN-α nasal drops may prevent COVID-19 incidence without adverse effects. In this case series done in Hubei Province, the incidence among the 2944 healthcare workers treated with daily IFN-α for 28 days was zero (
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Meng et al., 2020</xref>). While initial clinical data are encouraging, latest study shows that ACE2 is an ISG, inducible by IFN-α in primary human upper airway cells (
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Ziegler et al., 2020</xref>). Additional results from the ongoing clinical studies, as well as development of animal models, will offer a more instructive answer on the safety and efficacy IFN-I as a therapy in COVID-19.
</p>
