<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0035">In this section, selection criteria of voluntary CCP apheresis donors, from which the plasma will be collected to be used in the treatment of COVID-19 were defined. Candidates of CCP should meet the standard eligibility requirements in accordance with the National Blood and Blood Components Preparation, Use and Quality Assurance Guidelines and European Directorate for the Quality of Medicines (EDQM) instructions with the exceptional criteria of “deferral period of 28 days for previous viral infection”. CCP donors should meet the additional eligibility requirements for the collection of CCP by plasmapheresis defined below, as well as the eligibility requirements for the whole blood donation in accordance with the National Legislation [
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. 
 <list list-type="simple" id="lis0005">
  <list-item id="lsti0005">
   <label>1</label>
   <p id="par0040">For the individuals of CCP donor candidates who has been infected with COVID-19 virus infection and have been recovered afterwards [
    <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
    <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>];
    <list list-type="simple" id="lis0010">
     <list-item id="lsti0010">
      <label>a</label>
      <p id="par0045">The diagnosis of COVID-19 infection should be based on the results of laboratory tests (positive PCR test from the nasopharyngeal swab sample or serological test for SARS-CoV-2 antibodies), AND</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item id="lsti0015">
      <label>b</label>
      <p id="par0050">At least 14 days passed after the complete clinical recovery (cough, fever, shortness of breath, weakness, etc.) AND</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item id="lsti0020">
      <label>c</label>
      <p id="par0055">At least 2 negative PCR test results (one of the tests must have been conducted within the last 48 h) from the nasopharyngeal swab samples. Test negativity is not required in case of 28 days have been passed since the clinical recovery,</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item id="lsti0025">
      <label>d</label>
      <p id="par0060">The record of these individuals related to the disease period should be complete, traceable and documented.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0030">
   <label>2</label>
   <p id="par0065">Individuals who have had COVID-19 infection to be an CCP donor is based on voluntary. In order to become a volunteer CCP donor, candidates should meet the requirements for “Whole Blood Donation”;
    <list list-type="simple" id="lis0015">
     <list-item id="lsti0035">
      <label>a</label>
      <p id="par0070">In addition to the forms related with whole blood donation, “CCP Informed Consent Form”, and “Questionnaire Form of CCP Voluntary Donation” should be conducted to the candidates along with a short physical examination,</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item id="lsti0040">
      <label>b</label>
      <p id="par0075">Microbiological screening tests [(HBsAg, anti-HCV, anti-HIV 1-2 and anti-syphilis serologic tests and HBV-DNA, HCV-RNA, HIV 1,2-RNA Nucleic Acid Amplification Screening Tests (NAT)] should be negative.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0045">
   <label>3</label>
   <p id="par0080">Convalescent plasma donors should preferably be selected from male, and female who have never been pregnant (birth / abortion / curettage), and individuals who have not received any blood transfusion. Women who have been pregnant and individuals who have had blood transfusion should be screened for HLA antibodies and should be negative</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0050">
   <label>4</label>
   <p id="par0085">The antibody screening (indirect-coombs) test result of CCP donors should be negative,</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0055">
   <label>5</label>
   <p id="par0090">Convalescent plasma could be donated no more than 3 times in a month, at least once every 7–10 days, based on the date of the first donation that is accepted as the started date. Within a month at most 1800 mL of plasma can be collected from a donor.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
