<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P8">Initial CRISPR–Cas9 studies involving replication-competent HIV demonstrated efficient inhibition of virus replication in short-term cell culture experiments. However, these studies did not address virus escape, even though HIV-1 is well-known for its capacity to develop resistance against inhibitors [
 <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>–
 <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. We and others therefore tested HIV replication in long-term cultures of T cells stably expressing Cas9 and an antiviral gRNA [
 <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34
  <sup>••</sup>
 </xref>,
 <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35
  <sup>••</sup>
 </xref>,
 <xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>–
 <xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. These studies confirmed that CRISPR–Cas9 can potently inhibit HIV replication, but also showed that the virus frequently escapes from this inhibition, which was due to acquired mutations clustering around the Cas9 cleavage site [
 <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34
  <sup>••</sup>
 </xref>]. Intriguingly, indels of variable size were observed in poorly conserved targets (e.g. in the LTR promoter region), whereas mostly substitutions and 3-nt insertions were found in conserved targets (e.g. in protein-coding domains). This mutational pattern differs strikingly from that observed upon virus escape from other inhibitors like ART drugs or RNA-interference therapeutics, where predominantly nucleotide substitutions are observed that are generated during the error-prone reverse transcription process [
 <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. The frequent indels that cluster at the Cas9 cleavage site implicate the cellular DNA repair mechanism that acts on the Cas9-generated dsDNA breaks in the generation of HIV escape viruses [
 <xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Upon Cas9 cleavage, the proviral DNA is repaired by cellular DNA repair pathways that introduce mutations (mostly indels, but also substitutions) at the cleavage site upstream of the PAM (
 <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). Because this target domain is very important for gRNA/Cas9 binding, most mutations will prevent further Cas9 cleavage. In addition, they can also inactivate the virus (e.g. due to a frameshift mutation or inactivation of an essential RNA or protein domain), but some mutations will be compatible with virus replication, yet prevent gRNA binding, thus resulting in escape viruses. Wang 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35
  <sup>••</sup>
 </xref>] demonstrated that the escape mutations indeed originate from the cleaved and repaired proviral DNA pool, indicating that cellular DNA repair facilitated viral escape. However, a minor contribution of regular RT-generated mutations in virus escape cannot be excluded as some nucleotide substitutions were detected further away from the Cas9 cleavage site [
 <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34
  <sup>••</sup>
 </xref>,
 <xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Moreover, a poorly replicating escape virus resulting from Cas9 cleavage and subsequent DNA repair may accumulate additional RT-produced mutations in the target site or compensatory mutations elsewhere to increase its replication capacity.
</p>
