<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The specific amino acid identity at the E-156 locus influenced mosquito oral infectivity independent of glycosylation status as the NYT virus had a higher infection rate than NYS. The NYP mutant exhibited a severely debilitated infection and dissemination phenotype while the NYF did not significantly affect these phenotypes compared to the NYS virus. The E-154 locus showed similar variable effects on vector competence with restricted infectivity of the KYS mutant observed when compared to the SYS mutant. With the exception of the NYP mutant virus, absence of E protein glycosylation did not significantly attenuate viral growth, infection and/or dissemination rates of NYF, SYS, SYP and KYS viruses when compared with NYS parental WNV in 
 <italic>Cx</italic>. 
 <italic>quinquefasciatus</italic>. Even after bypassing the midgut barrier of infection by intrathoracic inoculation, NYP produced significantly lower viral titers in the saliva. The attenuated profile of NYP virus in 
 <italic>Culex</italic> spp. in the present study could explain the low frequency of isolation of WNV-NYP in nature[
 <xref rid="pntd.0007473.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007473.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. While NYP avian serum titers could presumably overcome WNV oral infection thresholds[
 <xref rid="pntd.0007473.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] in highly competent avian hosts[
 <xref rid="pntd.0007473.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], AMCRs elicited lower serum viremias with this virus. Furthermore, the restricted dissemination and transmission in alternative mosquito vectors such as 
 <italic>Cx</italic>. 
 <italic>tarsalis</italic> could preclude subsequent transmission. In contrast to our study, Murata et al reported the isolation and characterization of a small plaque variant with the NYP motif where no oral infectivity differences were observed with 
 <italic>Culex pipiens pallens</italic> and disseminated viral titers were indistinguishable between the NYS and NYP viruses[
 <xref rid="pntd.0007473.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Alternative mosquito species used and viral genetic differences between the NYP viruses used in the two studies could explain the difference in results. Of note, the SYP virus that was generated as a double mutant to prevent reversion to glycosylated motif as well as to assess the duplicative effect of altering more than one amino acid within the motif did not exhibit an attenuated mosquito infection phenotype as observed for NYP. The additional E-154 mutation could have served to compensate for negative fitness effects of the E-S156P substitution possibly through structural modulation of the envelope surface projections. The lack of significant differences between NYS and NYF, SYS, SYP and KYS viruses suggests that WNV N-linked glycosylation is not a critical determinant of vector competence. The WN02 genotype that displaced the introduced WNV-NY99 genotype, is characterized principally by the incorporation of a nonsynonymous valine to alanine substitution at position E-159[
 <xref rid="pntd.0007473.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007473.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. This new genotype has been reported to exhibit a shorter extrinsic incubation period in certain 
 <italic>Culex</italic> spp. and more efficient transmission rates at warmer temperatures[
 <xref rid="pntd.0007473.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. This E-159 locus, similar to the E-154-156 motif, is present on the surface of the mature envelope protein and could indicate that numerous amino acid variants in this surface exposed envelope domain could significantly modulate vector competence phenotypes. Taken together, the data indicated that specific amino acid identities at E154 or E-156 and potential other sites on the WNV E protein could be critical for modulation of mosquito oral infectivity and vector competence exclusive of the glycosylation status of the E protein.
</p>
