<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Brazilian VP1 sequences from Echovirus 6 (N = 63, 867pb) and Echovirus 30 (N = 80, 876 bp) were aligned with reference and representative sequences using Muscle [
 <xref rid="B7-viruses-11-00690" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], available in the Mega 7.0 package [
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-11-00690" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Reference and representative sequences were blasted, downloaded from Genbank (
 <uri xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nucleotide/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nucleotide/</uri>) and added to our datasets (the accession numbers are described in the respective phylogenetic trees). Furthermore, a North-American CVA6 sequence (AF081297) was used as an outgroup in the Maximum Likelihood (ML) tree. For each dataset, the best nucleotide substitution model was determined by JModeltest, version 2.1.4 [
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-11-00690" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-viruses-11-00690" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. For viral genotyping, the phylogenetic tree was reconstructed using a Maximum Likelihood algorithm (PhyML, v 3.0) [
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-11-00690" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-viruses-11-00690" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], with a GTR+G+I nucleotide substitution model and an aLRT SH-like, as the fast likelihood-based method [
 <xref rid="B12-viruses-11-00690" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Temporal phylogenetic trees were reconstructed by a Bayesian Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) method, accessible in the BEAST software package, version 1.8.4 [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00690" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-viruses-11-00690" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Time calibration was set based on the year of sample collection – available for all sequences, and the general time reversible (GTR) with gamma-distributed rates and invariant sites were employed as the nucleotide substitution model. Beast runs were carried out using the uncorrelated lognormal relaxed molecular clock model and a time-aware Gaussian Markov Random Field (GMRF) Bayesian skyride coalescent tree prior [
 <xref rid="B15-viruses-11-00690" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-11-00690" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The length of MCMC chains were established as 30 and 40 million, sampled every 30,000 and 40,000 steps for Echovirus 6 and Echovirus 30, respectively. Trace files generated through Bayesian phylogenetic inference were visualized and analyzed in Tracer version 1.7 [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-11-00690" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Convergence of parameters was considered in the presence of effective sample size (ESS) values exceeding 200. The target Maximum Clade Credibility (MCC) tree was summarized by TreeAnnotator 1.8.4, with a burn-in corresponding to 10% of states. MCC trees were visualized and edited in FigTree, version 1.4.3 Nucleotide sequences were deposited in GenBank with the accession numbers: MK570308-MK570388 (E-30) and MK570389-MK570451 (E-6).
</p>
