<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0525">In addition, the application of best practices of high surveillance and proper biosafety procedures in public and private institutes of virology that study viruses and new viruses to avoid that may be accidentally spread in surrounding environments with damages for population, vegetation and overall economy of nations. In this context, international collaboration among scientists is basic to address these risks and support decisions of policymakers to prevent future pandemic that creates huge socioeconomic issues worldwide (cf., 
 <xref rid="bb0185" ref-type="bibr">Coccia and Wang, 2016</xref>).
 <xref rid="fn0025" ref-type="fn">4</xref> In fact, following the COVID-19 outbreak, The Economist Intelligence Unit (EIU) points out that the global economy may contract of about by 2.5% and Italy by −7% of real GDP growth% in 2020 (
 <xref rid="bb0255" ref-type="bibr">EIU, 2020</xref>). Italy and other advanced countries should introduce organizational, product and process innovations to cope with future epidemics and environmental threats, such as the expansion of hospital capacity and testing capabilities, reduction of diagnostic and health system delays (also using devices with artificial intelligence, new Information and Communication Technologies for alleviating and/or eliminating effective interactions between infectious and susceptible individuals), and finally of course the development of effective vaccines and antivirals that can counteract future global public health threats in the presence of new epidemics similar to COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0785" ref-type="bibr">Wilder-Smith et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0655" ref-type="bibr">Riou and Althaus, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0820" ref-type="bibr">Yao et al., 2020</xref>; cf., 
 <xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">Coccia, 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr">Coccia, 2017a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr">Coccia, 2017b</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">Coccia, 2017c</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">Coccia, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb2010" ref-type="bibr">Coccia, 2020</xref>). New technology, for years to come, can cope with consequential epidemic outbreaks, also redefining the way governments interact with their citizens, such as the expanded use of surveillance tools, defending against cyberattacks and misinformation campaigns, etc. (cf., 
 <xref rid="bb0140" ref-type="bibr">Coccia, 2016a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">Coccia, 2016b</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0170" ref-type="bibr">Coccia, 2019</xref>). This study here shows that accelerated diffusion of COVID-19 is also likely associated with high air pollution and specific meteorological conditions (low wind speed, etc.) of North Italy and other Northern Italian regions that favor the transmission dynamics of viral infectivity. North Italy is one of the European regions with the highest motorization rate and polluting industrialization (cf., 
 <xref rid="bb0475" ref-type="bibr">Legambiente, 2019</xref>). In 2018, the daily limits for PM
 <sub>10</sub> or ozone were exceeded in 55 provincial capitals (i.e., 35 days for PM
 <sub>10</sub> and 25 days for ozone). In 24 of the 55 Italian province capitals, the limit was exceeded for both parameters, with negative effects on population and subsequent health problems in the short and long run. In fact, Italian cities having a very high number of polluted days are mainly in North Italy: e.g., Brescia with 150 days (47 days for the PM
 <sub>10</sub> and 103 days for the ozone), Lodi with 149 days (78 days for the PM
 <sub>10</sub> and 71 days for the ozone), -these are two cities with severe COVID-19 outbreak-, Monza (140 days), Venice (139 days), Alessandria (136 days), Milan (135 days), Turin (134 days), Padua (130 days), Bergamo and Cremona (127 days), Rovigo (121 days) and Genoa (103 days). These provincial capitals of the River Po area in Italy have exceeded in 2018 at least one of the two limits just mentioned. The first city not located in the Po Valley is Frosinone (Lazio region in the central part of Italy) with 116 days of exceedance (83 days for the PM
 <sub>10</sub> and 33 days for the ozone), followed by Avellino, a city close to Naples in South Italy (with total 89 days: 46 days for PM
 <sub>10</sub> and 43 days for ozone) and Terni with 86 days (respectively 49 and 37 days for the two pollutants). Many cities in Italy are affected by air pollution and smog because of traffic, domestic heating, industries and agricultural practices and private cars that continue to be by far the most used means of transportation (more than 39 million cars in 2019).
</p>
