<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0530">A major source of emissions of nitrogen oxides into the atmosphere is the combustion of fossil fuels from stationary sources (heating, power generation, etc.) and motor vehicles. In Italy, the first COVID-19 outbreak has been found in Codogno, a small city close to Milan (Lombardy region in North Italy, see 
 <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). Although local lockdown on February 25, 2020, the Regional Agency for Environmental Protection showed concentrations of PM
 <sub>10</sub> beyond the limits in almost all of Lombardy region. The day after, February 26, 2020, the high intensity of wind speed swept the entire Po Valley, bringing to Lombardy region a substantial reduction in the average daily concentrations of PM
 <sub>10</sub> (i.e., lower than 50 micrograms of particulate matter/m
 <sup>3</sup> of air). These observations associated with statistical analyses here suggest that high concentration of nitrogen dioxide of particulate air pollutants emitted by motor vehicles, power plants, and industrial facilities in North Italy seems to be a platform to support the diffusion of viral infectivity (cf., 
 <xref rid="bb0360" ref-type="bibr">Groulx et al., 2018</xref>), increase hospitalizations for respiratory disorders (cf., 
 <xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">Carugno et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0575" ref-type="bibr">Nenna et al., 2017</xref>), increase asthma incidence (cf., 
 <xref rid="bb0495" ref-type="bibr">Liao et al., 2011</xref>) and induce damages to the immune system of people (cf., 
 <xref rid="bb0340" ref-type="bibr">Glencross et al., 2020</xref>). As a matter of fact, transmission dynamics of COVID-19 has found in air pollution and meteorological conditions of North Italy an appropriate environment and population for an accelerated diffusion that is generating more than 26,640 deaths and a huge number of hospitalizations in a short period of time (February–March–April 2020).
</p>
