<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Rhamnolipid glycolipids have been shown to have significant antioxidant properties, with a mixed mono and di-rhamnolipid from 
 <italic>Marinobacter litoralis</italic> MB15 showing about a 10% lower DPPH scavenging ability (72.6%) at 5mg/mL than ascorbic acid at the same concentration [
 <xref rid="B106-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]. Similarly, rhamnolipids were also reported as having significant antioxidant ability by Abdollahi et al., although this was lower than for the artificial food antioxidant butylated hydroxyanisole (BHA) [
 <xref rid="B107-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. In a more direct demonstration of the potential of rhamnolipids as antioxidants, Liu et al. [
 <xref rid="B108-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>] compared the ability of rhamnolipids, saponins (a plant derived biosurfactant) and Tween 80 to protect ω-3-fatty acids in polyunsaturated marine oil emulsions. They found that the order of decreasing oxidative stability was rhamnolipids &gt; saponins &gt; Tween 80, highlighting the potential of the biosurfactants. The antioxidant properties of sophorolipids are reported to be weak [
 <xref rid="B109-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>], which may explain the lack of reports on their antioxidant ability. Takahashi et al. 2012 [
 <xref rid="B110-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>] report that all common MEL derivatives (e.g.,MEL A, MEL B and MEL C) have a lower antioxidant ability in DPPH in vitro tests than arbutin, a common positive control known to have strong radical scavenging properties. However, when tested for protection against H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>-induced oxidative stress on human skin fibroblasts (NB1RGB cell lines), MEL C surprisingly had a greater protective effect than arbutin. The different responses of glycolipids to different antioxidant tests may also partly explain the dearth of reported antioxidant properties.
</p>
