<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For 
 <italic>Aedes</italic>-transmitted viruses, especially dengue, examples of successful use of vector control interventions to reduce exposure risk certainly exist, such as a successful larval source management and public education strategy employed for a significant period in Singapore [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007479.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. However, application of vector control interventions often fails to prevent arboviral outbreaks, possibly due to inadequate control responses [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007479.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007479.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The scope and level of response, as well as how long the response is sustained, are all recognized as critical factors that determine the overall success of implementation. Improving implementation strategies is thus critical to improving 
 <italic>Aedes</italic>-borne virus control programs [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007479.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Given the importance of human movement and the focal nature of transmission, it is tempting to consider control strategies that explicitly make use of knowledge of human mobility patterns. For instance, in a previous study, we found that the relative efficacies of area-wide versus more targeted control responses in limiting outbreak size depended on both the daily rate of commuting and the proportion of patches that implemented control interventions [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007479.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. At the same time, while strategies at the household level (e.g., a form of contact tracing whereby households connected to positive cases are treated) may be appealing, contact tracing in urban tropical centers in developing countries may be logistically infeasible [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007479.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Here, we explore a number of straightforward vector control implementation scenarios using a simplified spatial model of Zika transmission by 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic>. Despite their simplifications, patch-based models can nonetheless provide important insights (due to their more tracteable nature) into questions related to the role of commuting and transmission and optimal control (e.g., [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007479.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007479.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]). The simplifications we use here relate largely to the scale of movement and targeting of control within the model (i.e., we use a relatively large patch size, namely at the level of the neighborhood, within which we assume humans are well-mixed). This model is used to develop general insights into when and how human movement and the distribution of humans over the urban landscape should affect decisions regarding the scale of interventions. We explicitly do not intend for this model to be predictive or provide advice to local vector control decision-makers, and would recommend household- or individual-level models specifically parameterized to local conditions for that. Here, we explore the relative efficacy and effort involved in vector control implementation under the following scenarios: (1) focal (individual neighborhood) control implementation; (2) two types of area-wide control; and (3) control implementation in both an individual neighborhood and in the neighborhood most strongly connected to it via 
 <italic>a priori</italic> knowledge of human movement patterns. We specifically investigate whether the derived strategic insights would be consistent among tropical urban centers of varying sizes, layouts, human distributions, and movement patterns, or whether strategies would have to be tailored to individual locations. To do so, we ran extensive sets of simulations for models coarsely capturing the human distributions and movement patterns of San Juan (Puerto Rico), Recife (Brazil), and Jakarta (Indonesia)—all locations where 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> has or could potentially lead to Zika epidemics.
</p>
