<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0004">Evolutionary models and phylogenetic analysis deserve attention for helping to estimate genetic variability and the evolutionary rate, in turn providing important implications for disease progression, drug trials and vaccine development. Zhou et al. reported that the full-length viral genome sequences from patients in the early outbreak were almost identical to each other and shared 79.5% sequence similar to SARS-CoV 
 <xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. In addition, SARS-CoV-2 was 96% identical at the whole-genome level to a bat coronavirus. Wu et al. almost simultaneously and independently discovered the novel RNA virus from the family Coronaviridae 
 <xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Phylogenetic analysis of the complete viral genome revealed that the coronavirus was most closely related (89.1% nucleotide similarity) to a group of SARS-like coronaviruses previously sampled from bats in China. Benvenuto et al. built a phylogenetic tree including the whole-genome sequences of SARS-CoV-2 and highly similar available whole-genome sequences in GenBank 
 <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. The phylogenetic tree showed that SARS-CoV-2 clustered with a bat SARS-like coronavirus sequence isolated in 2015, whilst fast unconstrained Bayesian approximation (FUBAR) analysis revealed mutations in the spike glycoprotein and nucleocapsid protein. Therefore, SARS-CoV-2 was probably transmitted from bats or other hosts, from where it gained the ability to infect humans. Ramaiah et al. speculated that the novel virus closely related to a bat coronavirus, which reminded us that this novel strain might be evolved from the bat coronavirus by accumulating favourable genetic alterations for human infection 
 <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Epitopes in SAR-CoV-2 structural proteins were differentially recognised by HLA-DR alleles, which suggested that a subunit vaccine including the eight immunodominant HLA-DR epitopes might induce an effective antiviral immune responses in various populations. Paraskevis et al. found that SAR-CoV-2 closely resembled the bat coronavirus RaTG13 sequence throughout the genome (similarity 96.3%) 
 <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. The latter does not provide the exact variant that caused the outbreak in humans, but the hypothesis that SAR-CoV-2 has originated from bats is possible. Xu et al. also reported that SAR-CoV-2 shared with the SARS/SARS-like coronaviruses a common ancestor that related to the bat coronavirus HKU9-1 
 <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. They concluded that the SAR-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV S proteins shared an almost identical three-dimensional structure in the receptor-binding domain (RBD), thus maintaining similar van der Waals and electrostatic properties at the interaction interface with human angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) molecules despite the sequence diversity.
</p>
