<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While reduced VE from repeated vaccination has been reported previously [
 <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], this has not been consistently found [
 <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The antigenic distance hypothesis is one potential explanation for reduced VE; if the vaccine strains for the current season and prior season are similar but the current season’s vaccine strain is distinct from the current epidemic strain, negative interference leading to reduced VE for the current season may result [
 <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. However, this hypothesis does not consider the effects of multiple previous vaccine or virus exposures [
 <xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Thompson et al. [
 <xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] examined up to 4 years of previous vaccination history among healthcare workers and observed a greater blunting of serologic response to the A(H3N2) vaccine strain with more doses of previous vaccines received. In addition, two studies have examined vaccination history for up to five previous seasons, with one study observing reduced VE with repeated vaccination [
 <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] while the other did not [
 <xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. However, similar to our results, both studies showed that vaccination in the current season provided some protection against influenza regardless of the number of previous vaccinations. No study has ever examined the impact of repeated vaccination over 10 previous seasons. The residual protection from being vaccinated in previous seasons observed in our study has also been seen elsewhere; this phenomenon may result from cross-reactivity of immune responses elicited by previous vaccinations with current-season virus antigens [
 <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. It is possible that due to this potential residual protection, the incremental benefit of current season vaccination may be difficult to observe for those who have received many previous vaccinations.
</p>
