<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0025">
 <label>Table 5</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Recommendations for the management of paediatric patients with complex chronic disease in the context of the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic.</p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text id="at0025">Table 5</alt-text>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">1. 
     <italic>Maintain effective social distancing measures in all hospital settings</italic>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2. 
     <italic>Establish separate care pathways for patients with suspected COVID and non-COVID patients, with staff exclusively allocated to either pathway</italic>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">3. 
     <italic>Optimise the use of emerging technologies to provide continuity of care while avoiding visits to health care facilities</italic>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">4. 
     <italic>When in-person visits in a health care setting cannot be avoided, maximise the efficiency and productivity of each visit: include as many of the specialists involved in the care of the patient, keep the duration to a minimum and minimise movements within the hospital</italic>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">5. 
     <italic>In case of hospital admission:</italic>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left"> a. Set up a separate care area for COVID patients staffed by personnel specifically trained in their management</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left"> b. Use internal communication channels (videoconferencing or mobile phone calls) to link the patient and/or caregivers to health care staff in order to ensure continuous monitoring and safe delivery of care</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">6. 
     <italic>Promote hospital-at-home units</italic>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">7. 
     <italic>Provide psychological support and social work services to patients and their families</italic>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">8. 
     <italic>Develop individualised plans for leisure and physical activity</italic>
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
