<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="Tab1">
 <label>Table 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Selection of studies on gut virome changes in humans in various disease states</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th>Disease</th>
    <th>Study population</th>
    <th>Major finding</th>
    <th>Authors</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td>Malnutrition</td>
    <td>Healthy twins (
     <italic>n</italic> = 8 pairs) versus twins discordant for severe malnutrition (
     <italic>n</italic> = 12 pairs)
    </td>
    <td>Bacteriophage as well as members of the 
     <italic>Anelloviridae</italic> and 
     <italic>Circoviridae</italic> families of eukaryotic viruses discriminate discordant from concordant healthy pairs
    </td>
    <td>Reyes et al. 2015 [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic> infection (CDI)
    </td>
    <td>CDI patients (
     <italic>n</italic> = 24) versus healthy controls (
     <italic>n</italic> = 20)
    </td>
    <td>Treatment response in FMT associated with a high colonization level of donor-derived 
     <italic>Caudovirales</italic> taxa in the recipient. 
     <italic>Caudovirales</italic> bacteriophages may play a role in the efficacy of FMT in CDI
    </td>
    <td>Zuo et al. 2018 [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Inflammatory bowel disease (IBD)</td>
    <td>Crohn’s disease (
     <italic>n</italic> = 16) and ulcerative colitis (
     <italic>n</italic> = 36) and household controls (
     <italic>n</italic> = 21)
    </td>
    <td>Enteric virome richness was increased in Crohn’s disease and ulcerative colitis, and both forms of IBD were associated with a significant expansion of 
     <italic>Caudovirales</italic> bacteriophages
    </td>
    <td>Norman et al. 2015 [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Colorectal cancer (CRC)</td>
    <td>CRC cases (
     <italic>n</italic> = 74) and controls without CRC (
     <italic>n</italic> = 92) in Hong Kong. Validated in three independent European cohorts
    </td>
    <td>Dysbiosis of the gut virome was associated with early- and late-stage CRC. A combination of four taxonomic markers was associated with reduced survival of patients with CRC</td>
    <td>Nakatsu et al. 2018 [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS)</td>
    <td>HIV-negative (
     <italic>n</italic> = 40), treatment naïve (n = 40), and treated HIV patients (n = 40) in Uganda
    </td>
    <td>Alterations in the enteric virome and bacterial microbiome were associated with low peripheral CD4 T cell counts rather than HIV infection alone</td>
    <td>Monaco et al. 2016 [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Type 1 diabetes (T1D)</td>
    <td>11 infants from Finland and Estonia recruited at birth based on their HLA risk genotype and followed for 36 months</td>
    <td>Significant enrichment of 
     <italic>Circoviridae</italic>-related sequences in samples from controls in comparison with cases. Higher diversity and richness of bacteriophages in controls compared with cases
    </td>
    <td>Zhao et al. 2017 [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Type 2 diabetes (T2D)</td>
    <td>T2D patients (
     <italic>n</italic> = 71) and non-diabetic Chinese adults (n = 74), validated in independent cohort
    </td>
    <td>Observed a significant increase in the number of gut phages in the T2D group and identified seven phage operational taxonomic units specific to T2D. Significant alterations of the gut phageome not explained by co-variation with the altered bacterial hosts</td>
    <td>Ma et al. 2018 [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Hypertension</td>
    <td>Healthy controls (
     <italic>n</italic> = 41), pre-hypertension (
     <italic>n</italic> = 56), and hypertension patients (
     <italic>n</italic> = 99) in China
    </td>
    <td>Noted that certain viruses can be selected as biomarkers to distinguish healthy people, pre-hypertension people, and hypertension patients. Viruses had superior resolution and better discrimination power than bacteria for identifying hypertension samples</td>
    <td>Han et al. 2018 [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Parkinson’s disease (PD)</td>
    <td>PD patients (
     <italic>n</italic> = 31) and control individuals (
     <italic>n</italic> = 28)
    </td>
    <td>Identified shifts of the phage/bacteria ratio in lactic acid bacteria known to produce dopamine and regulate intestinal permeability, both major factors implicated in PD pathogenesis</td>
    <td>Tetz et al. 2018 [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
