<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The continuous advances in next generation sequencing technologies lead to an increasingly easier and inexpensive production of genome and metabarcoding data. The wealth of available data has triggered the development of new models of molecular evolution, algorithms, and software, that aim to improve molecular sequence analyses in terms of biological realism, computational efficiency, or a trade-off between the two. In response to such technological and technical advancements, several fields of biology have undergone a substantial transformation. Sequence-based species delimitation and identification, in the framework of DNA-(meta)barcoding constitutes a representative example that revived taxonomy and systematics (
 <xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr">Tautz et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Moritz &amp; Cicero, 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">Savolainen et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr">Waugh, 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Bucklin et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr">Valentini, Pompanon &amp; Taberlet, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2015</xref>), while it also provided a new means of analysis in several fields (
 <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Galimberti et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Mishra et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Leray &amp; Knowlton, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Bell et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Batovska et al., 2018</xref>). Among others, the development of novel species delimitation tools has substantially advanced the study of biodiversity of microorganism that are often hard to isolate and study (
 <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Taberlet et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Gibson et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr">Thomsen &amp; Willerslev, 2015</xref>). The sequencing of environmental samples in conjunction with algorithms for genetic clustering has led to the identification of a plethora of previously unknown organisms and a re-assessment of the microbial biodiversity in several settings.
</p>
