<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The genome of IAV comprises of eight negative-sense, single-stranded RNA segments. Segments 1, and 4 to 6 encode for a single protein each (PB2, HA, NP, and NA, respectively); Segments 2, 3 and 7 encode for two proteins each (PB1 and PB1-F2, PA and PA-X, M1 and M2, respectively), while segment 8 encodes for two non-structural proteins (NS1 and NS2). Each RNA segment of the genome is wrapped around nucleoprotein (NP) monomers and is associated with polymerase acidic protein (PA) and polymerase basic proteins (PB1 and PB2), forming a ribonucleoprotein (RNP) complex, which is important for viral transcription and replication (
 <xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Taubenberger &amp; Kash, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Noda &amp; Kawaoka, 2010</xref>). The RNP complexes are contained in a spherical lipid envelope lined by M1 proteins and embedded with surface glycoproteins, hemagglutinin (HA) and neuraminidase (NA), and the ion-channel protein, M2. HA protein is key for the entry of the virus through binding to the sialic acid receptor of the host, while NA protein functions in releasing the virus progeny out of the host cell (
 <xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Khanna et al., 2014</xref>). The high sequence diversity exhibited by the virus makes vaccine development a challenging task (
 <xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Dunston, Herbert &amp; Griffiths, 2015</xref>). The diversity is achieved through the accumulation of point mutations (antigenic drift) across the segmented genome of the RNA virus, which encodes for 12 proteins, and the exchange of gene segments between two different strains (antigenic shift). The gradual antigenic drift is caused by the lack of proofreading fidelity by the viral polymerase, thus resulting in a high rate of mutation, approximately one per genome per replication (
 <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Drake et al., 1998</xref>). Antigenic drift can lead to the establishment of viral variants that escape immune recognition and is associated with frequent epidemics (
 <xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Potter, 2001</xref>). Antigenic shift, in contrast, occurs abruptly, producing new “immune-escape” viral variant strains that can potentially give rise to pandemics (
 <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Szewczyk, Bieńkowska-szewczyk &amp; Król, 2014</xref>). The ongoing evolution and diversification of the H5N1 IAV challenges the conventional method of vaccine formulation, which is time-consuming, of limited production and strain-specific. Thus, it is crucial to understand the diversity and the dynamics of viral sequence change to aid in the design of vaccine or development of therapeutics against the virus.
</p>
