<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?OLF?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Trends Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Trends Microbiol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Trends in Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0966-842X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1878-4380</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7167561</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S0966-842X(20)30099-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2020.04.006</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Bat Influenza Viruses: Making a Double Agent of MHC Class II</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>Arinjay</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0010"><name><surname>Mossman</surname><given-names>Karen L.</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0015"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Matthew S.</given-names></name><email>mmiller@mcmaster.ca</email><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="af0015" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="cr0005" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><aff id="af0005"><label>1</label>Michael G. DeGroote Institute for Infectious Disease Research, McMaster Immunology Research Centre, McMaster University, Hamilton, ON L8S 4K1, Canada</aff><aff id="af0010"><label>2</label>Department of Pathology and Molecular Medicine, McMaster University, Hamilton, ON L8S 4K1, Canada</aff><aff id="af0015"><label>3</label>Department of Biochemistry and Biomedical Sciences, McMaster University, Hamilton, ON L8S 4K1, Canada</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cr0005"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Correspondence: <email>mmiller@mcmaster.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Elsevier Ltd</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="ab0005"><p>MHC class II (MHCII) has recently been identified as a cellular receptor for bat influenza viruses. Here, we discuss the possible implications of viral exploitation of this critical host defense molecule and highlight the need for more intense study of bat&#x02013;influenza virus interactions.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="ks0005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>bats</kwd><kwd>influenza virus</kwd><kwd>receptor</kwd><kwd>MHCII</kwd><kwd>transmission</kwd><kwd>tropism</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="p0005">Influenza A viruses (IAVs) circulate globally and, based on WHO estimates, annual epidemics of influenza result in ~1 billion infections, 3&#x02013;5 million cases of severe illness, and 300 000&#x02013;500 000 deaths. The severity of pandemic influenza depends on multiple factors, such as the virulence of the pandemic virus strain and the level of pre-existing immunity in the population. The discovery of two novel bat influenza viruses, H17N10 and H18N11 (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
) [<xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">1.</xref>, <xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2.</xref>, <xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">3.</xref>] has raised several questions about the evolution, host range, tropism, and transmission potential of these viruses.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Serological and Genomic Detection of Bat Influenza Viruses</p></caption><alt-text id="al0010">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Bat species</th><th>Subtype detected</th><th>Location</th><th>Genome positive (no. of bats)</th><th>Antibody positive (no. of bats)</th><th>Refs</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>Artibeus lituratus</italic></td><td>H18N11</td><td>Brazil</td><td>2/129</td><td>NT<xref rid="tf0010" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></td><td>[<xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>H18N11<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>Peru</td><td>0/3</td><td>3/3</td><td>[<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Artibeus obscurus</italic></td><td>H18N11<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>Peru</td><td>0/10</td><td>9/10</td><td>[<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Artibeus planirostris</italic></td><td>H18N11<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>Peru</td><td>1/15</td><td>13/15</td><td>[<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Carollia brevicauda</italic></td><td>H18N11<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>Peru</td><td>0/2</td><td>1/2</td><td>[<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Carollia castanea</italic></td><td>H18N11<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>Peru</td><td>0/2</td><td>0/2</td><td>[<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Carollia perspicillata</italic></td><td>H18N11<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>Peru</td><td>0/29</td><td>11/29</td><td>[<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Desmodus glaucus</italic></td><td>H18N11<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>Peru</td><td>0/1</td><td>0/1</td><td>[<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Desmodus rotundus</italic></td><td>H18N11<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>Peru</td><td>0/8</td><td>7/18</td><td>[<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Diphylla ecaudata</italic></td><td>H18N11<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>Peru</td><td>0/1</td><td>0/1</td><td>[<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Glossophaga soricina</italic></td><td>H18N11<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>Peru</td><td>0/2</td><td>0/2</td><td>[<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Molossus</italic></td><td>H18N11<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>Peru</td><td>0/10</td><td>3/10</td><td>[<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Myotis</italic> sp.</td><td>H18N11<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>Peru</td><td>0/6</td><td>1/6</td><td>[<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Phyllostomus discolor</italic></td><td>H18N11<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>Peru</td><td>0/2</td><td>2/2</td><td>[<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Phyllostomus hastatus</italic></td><td>H18N11<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>Peru</td><td>0/2</td><td>2/2</td><td>[<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Platyrrhinus recifinus</italic></td><td>H18N11<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>Peru</td><td>0/1</td><td>1/1</td><td>[<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Rhinophylla pumilio</italic></td><td>H18N11<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>Peru</td><td>0/2</td><td>1/2</td><td>[<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Sturnira lilium</italic></td><td>H17N10</td><td>Guatemala</td><td>3/29</td><td>NT</td><td>[<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Sturnira</italic> sp.</td><td>H18N11<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>Peru</td><td>0/2</td><td>0/2</td><td>[<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Vampyressa bidens</italic></td><td>H18N11<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td>Peru</td><td>0/2</td><td>1/2</td><td>[<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf0005"><label>a</label><p id="np0005">Based on serological data.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf0010"><label>b</label><p id="np0010">NT, not tested.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0010">The hemagglutinin (HA) of avian IAVs has a preference for sialic acids that display an &#x003b1;2,3 linkage to the penultimate sugar, whereas human IAVs preferentially bind to the &#x003b1;2,6 linkage [<xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In two striking studies, Karakus <italic>et al.</italic> and Giotis <italic>et al.</italic> identified MHCII as a receptor for bat H17N10 and H18N11 viruses [<xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Karakus <italic>et al.</italic> used transcriptomic profiling and genome-wide CRISPR-Cas9 screening of susceptible and nonsusceptible cells to identify and characterize MHCII as an entry determinant for bat H17N10 and H18N11 viruses [<xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The authors also observed that bat H17N10 and H18N11 viruses could initiate virus entry via MHCII homologs encoded by multiple bat species, pigs, humans, and chickens [<xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In a subsequent study, Giotis <italic>et al.</italic> confirmed human HLA-DR as the receptor for H17 using pseudotyped vesicular stomatitis viruses expressing H17 as the surface glycoprotein [<xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p id="p0015">The use of MHCII as a receptor is unique to bat H17N10 and H18N11 influenza viruses, which might suggest altered cellular tropism relative to other known IAVs. In bats, H17N10 RNA was detected in liver, kidney, lung, and intestinal tissues, whereas H18N11 RNA was found exclusively in the intestine [<xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Ciminski <italic>et al.</italic> demonstrated that, in bats experimentally infected with H18N11, virus could be detected in the feces and transmitted to co-housed na&#x000ef;ve bats, presumably via the fecal&#x02013;oral route [<xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. This is akin to the behavior of avian influenza viruses in waterfowl. Going forward, it will be important to determine with greater resolution the specific cell types that are permissive for replication of H17N10 and H18N11 viruses in bats. This will be essential for understanding the coevolutionary relationship of the virus with these hosts. The discovery of MHCII as a receptor for bat influenza viruses also raises several important questions about the consequences of immune cell susceptibility in terms of both viral pathogenicity and host range.</p><p id="p0020">The fact that viruses pseudotyped with bat influenza virus HAs could infect avian and human cells raised concerns regarding the potential for epizootic and zoonotic transmissions. The studies of Giotis <italic>et al.</italic> and Karakus <italic>et al.</italic> using viruses pseudotyped with bat H17 and H18 demonstrated that bat IAVs have broad tropism. In humans, certain cells of the immune system, as well as epithelial cells in human lung and intestine, constitutively express MHCII. However, it remained unclear whether wild-type (WT) bat IAVs were able to replicate and transmit in species other than bats. A recent study by Ciminski <italic>et al.</italic> has provided important insight into this critical question. Using WT and cell-culture-adapted H18N11, the authors performed <italic>in vivo</italic> replication and transmission studies in mice, ferrets, and bats. These viruses were produced from infectious clones since, as yet, there are no natural isolates. Serial passage of WT H18N11 in canine RIE1495 cells selected for adaptive mutations in the viral HA (S235Y or V254F) and deletions of the neuraminidase (NA) ectodomain [<xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Experimental infection of mice with H18N11 also selected for adaptive mutations in HA and deletion mutations in NA. Virus replication was limited to the upper respiratory tract and infected mice were unable to transmit the virus to na&#x000ef;ve contact mice. Ferrets are considered the &#x02018;gold-standard&#x02019; model for studies of influenza virus pathogenesis and transmission. In these animals, a recombinant cell-culture-adapted bat virus (rP11), which contains adaptive mutations in HA and a stop codon in the stalk of NA that results in deletion of the ectodomain, replicated in multiple organs, including trachea, nasal conchae, lung, cerebrum, and cerebellum. However, the virus was not shed or transmitted to na&#x000ef;ve contact ferrets. Interestingly, on passaging of rP11 in ferrets, a single point mutation restored the N11 open reading frame, suggesting that it may have functional relevance. However, viral transcripts could not be detected in nasal lavage of ferrets infected with WT H18N11 [<xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p id="p0025">The rP11 virus also contained K170R and N250S mutations in HA, which were shown to enhance infectivity in mammalian cells <italic>in vitro</italic>. These mutations were maintained in rP11 after passage in ferrets when the mutation restoring NA expression emerged. NA expression was also required for efficient transmission in bats. Infection of <italic>Artibeus jamaicensis</italic> bats (a close relative of <italic>Artibeus planirostris</italic>, the species from which H18N11 was initially characterized) with rP11 also resulted in restoration of the full-length N11 coding sequence collected from both index and contact animals. Therefore, while full-length N11 does not appear to be required for replication and shedding, it is likely to be necessary to facilitate efficient transmission in bats. Ciminski <italic>et al.</italic> demonstrated that ectopically expressed N11 reduced surface expression of MHCII. They speculated that this might facilitate progeny virus egress, just as cleavage of sialic acid facilitates the egress of other IAVs [<xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. However, the ability to downregulate MHCII has implications for adaptive immune responses against bat influenza viruses and may contribute to viral pathogenesis.</p><p id="p0030">MHCII is responsible for presenting antigen to CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, which, along with co-stimulatory factors, promotes their activation [<xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells are then essential for the promotion of high-quality antibody responses by providing B cells with the signals required to induce somatic hypermutation/affinity maturation. Ciminski <italic>et al.</italic> reported seroconversion in bats after experimental infection with WT H18N11, demonstrating that antibody responses are generated in response to infection [<xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Nevertheless, it will be interesting to determine whether H18N11 infection impairs T cell activation and, as a result, the breadth and quality of the antibody response (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>
).<fig id="f0005"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The Ability of Bat Influenza Viruses to Downregulate MHC Class II (MHCII) Expression May Have Immunological Consequences for the Host.</p><p>(A) MHCII-mediated antigen presentation in infected cells, along with other co-stimulatory signals, plays a critical role in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell activation. Activated CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells produce cytokines that prime a strong humoral response against invading viruses. (B) Bat influenza viruses use MHCII as a cellular receptor. These viruses are known to infect epithelial cells. However, it is unclear whether they infect MHCII-expressing antigen-presenting cells. (C) Ciminski <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] demonstrated that N11 reduced surface expression of MHCII. (D) While this is likely to facilitate virus egress from infected cells, it might in turn reduce CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell activation &#x02013; especially if it occurs in antigen-presenting cells. This could have deleterious effects on the host adaptive immune response (E), including the priming of humoral antiviral response. Further studies are required to fully understand the role of N11 in downregulating host MHCII and to discern the potential implications for the adaptive immune response, viral pathogenesis, and disease manifestation. Abbreviations: TCR, T cell receptor.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0005">Figure 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p><p id="p0035">Emerging data have suggested that broadly neutralizing antibodies are capable of neutralizing H17N10 viruses [<xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. However, the titers and prevalence of antibodies capable of neutralizing bat H17 and H18 viruses in humans have not yet been studied. It will be interesting to determine whether humans and other species in areas where bat influenza viruses are endemic (i.e., South America) have already been exposed to these viruses and have mounted specific adaptive immune responses. Sero-epidemiological studies could shed important light on this question.</p><p id="p0040">The observed inability of bat influenza viruses to efficiently transmit within mice and ferrets, alongside their limited reassortment potential with conventional IAVs (reviewed in [<xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]) reduces the probability that these viruses pose an imminent zoonotic threat. However, that does not rule out the potential for epizootic transmission, and gene segments of bat H17N10 and H18N11 viruses are compatible for reassortment [<xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Important questions therefore remain regarding the true diversity of bat influenza viruses and their evolutionary relationship to conventional IAVs. Frugivorous and insectivorous bats diverged over 50 million years ago and there are over 1400 known species of bats. Although H17N10 and H18N11 viruses have only been detected in New World fruit bats (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), <italic>in vitro</italic> studies with pseudotyped viruses demonstrated that ectopically expressed MHCII from the insectivorous bats <italic>Eptesicus fuscus</italic> and <italic>Myotis lucifugus</italic> was sufficient to serve as a cellular receptor for entry of these viruses [<xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Thus, there is a pressing need to perform more detailed and systematic surveys of multiple bat species in different geographical locations to better understand the prevalence and diversity of bat influenza viruses.</p><p id="p0045">The growing frequency of outbreaks caused by emerging viruses reinforces the critical need to adopt a &#x02018;One Health&#x02019; approach to effectively control infectious diseases. Bats have proved to be an especially important reservoir for many pathogens with zoonotic potential, including SARS-CoV, SARS-CoV-2, and Ebola virus. The discovery and ongoing characterization of bat influenza viruses highlights the unpredictable nature of IAVs and the need for more intense study of their evolutionary diversity and pathobiology, especially in non-human hosts.</p></body><back><ref-list id="bi0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bb0005"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A distinct lineage of influenza A virus from bats</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source><volume>109</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>4269</fpage><lpage>4274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22371588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0010"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New world bats harbor diverse influenza A viruses</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog.</source><volume>9</volume><year>2013</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e1003657</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0015"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>A.C.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bat influenza A(HL18NL11) virus in fruit bats, Brazil</article-title><source>Emerg. Infect. Dis.</source><volume>25</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30666923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0020"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gamblin</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The structure and receptor binding properties of the 1918 influenza hemagglutinin</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>303</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>1838</fpage><lpage>1842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14764886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0025"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weis</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of the influenza virus haemagglutinin complexed with its receptor, sialic acid</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>333</volume><year>1988</year><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3374584</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0030"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karakus</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MHC class II proteins mediate cross-species entry of bat influenza viruses</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>567</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30787439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0035"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giotis</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Entry of the bat influenza H17N10 virus into mammalian cells is enabled by the MHC class II HLA-DR receptor</article-title><source>Nat. Microbiol.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>2035</fpage><lpage>2038</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31358984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0040"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ciminski</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bat influenza viruses transmit among bats but are poorly adapted to non-bat species</article-title><source>Nat. Microbiol.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>2298</fpage><lpage>2309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31527796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0045"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roche</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Furuta</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ins and outs of MHC class II-mediated antigen processing and presentation</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Immunol.</source><volume>15</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25720354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0050"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carnell</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The bat influenza H17N10 can be neutralized by broadly-neutralizing monoclonal antibodies and its neuraminidase can facilitate viral egress</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><year>2019</year><comment>Published online January 12, 2019. </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/499947</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0055"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ciminski</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel insights into bat influenza A viruses</article-title><source>J. Gen. Virol.</source><volume>98</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>2393</fpage><lpage>2400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28906230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0060"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of uncultivable bat influenza virus using a replicative synthetic virus</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog.</source><volume>10</volume><year>2014</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e1004420</object-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ac0005"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>A.B. is funded by the <funding-source id="gts0005"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100000038</institution-id><institution>Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>. K.L.M is funded by the <funding-source id="gts0010"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100000038</institution-id><institution>NSERC</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> and <funding-source id="gts0015"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100000024</institution-id><institution>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>. M.S.M. received funding from <funding-source id="gts0020"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100000024</institution-id><institution>CIHR</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>, the <funding-source id="gts0025">Michael G. DeGroote Institute for Infectious Disease Research</funding-source>, and the <funding-source id="gts0030"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100003400</institution-id><institution>Ontario Ministry of Research, Innovation and Science</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> in support of this work.</p></ack></back></article>