<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat-1002094-g003" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002094.g003</object-id>
 <label>Figure 3</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Median-joining phylogenetic network of H7N7 viruses.</title>
  <p>The median-joining network was constructed from the combined HA, NA and PB2 sequence data. This network includes all the most parsimonious trees linking the sequences. Each unique sequence genotype is represented by a coloured circle sized relative to its frequency in the dataset. Genotypes are coloured according to the location of the farm sample and its inclusion in a cluster of infection. Branches in black represent the shortest trees; Additional branching pathways are in grey. Each node is separated by a specific number of mutations represented by grey dots. Mutations corresponding to specific amino acid changes are indicated. For genotypes containing a deletion in the NA stalk region, the type of deletion is indicated between brackets beside the name of the isolate (see 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1002094.s004">Table S1</xref> for the description of deletion types). Names of farm samples involved in likely inter-farm transmission events are in red (see 
   <xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat-1002094-t002">Table 2</xref>). (*) positively selected amino acids linked to adaptation to mammalian hosts. 
   <bold>G1</bold>: group of samples including F38, F54, F64, F113, F162, F194, F199; 
   <bold>G2</bold>: F134, F160, F166; 
   <bold>G3</bold>: F122, F161, F164, F171, F182; 
   <bold>G4:</bold> F2, F5, F12, F21, F43, F60, F91; 
   <bold>G5:</bold> F39, F70, F92, F129; 
   <bold>G6:</bold> F15, F29, F37; 
   <bold>G7:</bold> F16, F19, F52; 
   <bold>G8</bold>: F193, F217, F223, F231; 
   <bold>G9</bold>: F36, F68, F167, F191(d1), F205(d5), F207(d2); 
   <bold>G10</bold>: F203 (d3), F219(d3), F228(d3); 
   <bold>G11</bold>: F197, F242, F232.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1002094.g003" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
