<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10">CoVs depend on activation of their S proteins by host cell proteases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Cleavage or priming of the S protein by TMPRSS2 is essential for the fusion of the virus with the ACE2 receptor needed for viral entry and spread of SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Hoffmann et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] confirmed that SARS-CoV-2 enters the host cells mainly via binding and fusion with ACE2. Inhibition of TMPRSS2 activity is thus an excellent target for antiviral intervention. TMPRSS2 plays a crucial role in modulating the metastatic behavior of certain tumors, e.g., in prostate cancer and in modulating inflammation of organs, such as in the context of pancreatitis. Hoffman et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] suggested that TMPRSS2 could be a potential therapeutic target for COVID-19, since entry of the virus into cells was reduced by camostat mesilate, a TMPRSS2 inhibitor. It is currently only approved for treatment of chronic pancreatitis in Japan [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Very little data are available on the drug’s risk profile with little or no experience with use in children, pregnant women, multimorbid patients, and other high-risk patients. It is a non-selective TMPRSS2 inhibitor, which means that it has greater, more severe side effects than a selective TMPRSS2. Camostat mesilate is currently undergoing Phase 1/2 trial testing in the USA for chronic pancreatitis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. If deemed safe, it could be a potential treatment option of CoV infections [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Nafamostat mesilate is also a serine protease inhibitor widely used as an anticoagulant and used to treat pancreatic and kidney disease. It is structurally closely related to camostat mesilate. Researchers previously identified nafamostat mesilate’s potential to inhibit MERS-CoV [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Risks of complications (including anaphylaxis) must be considered in non-emergency care.
</p>
