<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pcbi.1007683.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007683.g003</object-id>
 <label>Fig 3</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Viral competition predicted future success for clusters with borderline growth rates.</title>
  <p>(A) Clusters with only a slight 
   <italic>R</italic>
   <sub>c</sub>/〈
   <italic>R</italic>〉 advantage were more likely to establish if the background var(
   <italic>R</italic>) was low. Clusters with higher 
   <italic>R</italic>
   <sub>c</sub>/〈
   <italic>R</italic>〉 were successful regardless of var(
   <italic>R</italic>). Contour lines indicate the density of values of 
   <italic>R</italic>
   <sub>c</sub>/〈
   <italic>R</italic>〉 and var(
   <italic>R</italic>). The lines represent the correlation between the variables for successful and transient clusters. (Success-black: r = 0.63, p &lt; 2.2e-16; Transient-grey: r = 0.18, p &lt;1.2e-06). The dots represent clusters with 
   <italic>R</italic>
   <sub>c</sub>/〈
   <italic>R</italic>〉’s between 1.025–1.030, a range within the individual distributions of 
   <italic>R</italic>
   <sub>c</sub>/〈
   <italic>R</italic>〉 for success and transient clusters that do not statistically differ (Wilcox, p = 0.4551). (B) For clusters falling within this ambiguous range of 
   <italic>R</italic>
   <sub>c</sub>/〈
   <italic>R</italic>〉, var(
   <italic>R</italic>) was significantly higher in transient clusters than in established clusters, and (C) in comparison to transient clusters, successful clusters tended to face fewer co-circulating clusters (Wilcox, p = 0.0053), with the current dominant cluster at higher frequency (Wilcox, p = 0.023). Points represent the number of circulating clusters and the frequency of the dominant cluster; shading represents the kernel density estimation of the distribution of points. Across all graphs, values were calculated when the focal clusters reach a 10% surveillance threshold.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1007683.g003" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
