<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A homology model of the Hepatitis B virus Reverse Transcriptase (HBV-RT) was generated by using the crystallographic structure of HIV-1 Reverse Transcriptase (HIV-1-RT) (PDB 3V81) as the template (Daga et al., 2010[
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]; Das et al., 2012[
 <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]). The initial model was obtained with the SWISS-MODEL modeling server (Arnold et al., 2006[
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]) and the tools of DeepView/Swiss-PdbViewer 4.01 software (Guex and Peitsch, 1997[
 <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]). In this model, hydrogen atoms were added, and the partial charges were assigned for energy refinement. After that, the protein model was embedded in a 100 Å water box. Then, energy minimization preserving the enzyme folding and optimizing the relative position between the water molecules and the fixed backbone atoms was performed. The obtained system underwent a one nanosecond (ns) molecular dynamic (MD) simulation with the following characteristics: (a) Periodic Boundary Conditions (PBC) were introduced to stabilize the simulation space; (b) the long-range electrostatic potential was treated by the Particle Mesh Ewald summation method (PME) (Toukmaji et al., 2000[
 <xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]); (c) Newton's equation using the r-RESPA method (Masella, 2006[
 <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]) (every 4 femtoseconds (fs) for long-range electrostatic forces, 2 fs for short-range non-bonded forces, and 1 fs for bonded forces) was integrated; (d) the temperature was maintained 300 ± 5 K by means of Langevin's algorithm (Izaguirre et al., 2012[
 <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]); (e) Lennard-Jones (L-J) interactions were calculated with a cut-off of 14 Å, the switching distance was 10 Å, and the non-bonded pair list distance was 14 Å; (f) a frame every 5 pico seconds (ps) was stored, yielding 2000 frames; (g) constraints with a force constant of 1000kcal/mol/Å
 <sup>2 </sup>were applied to the backbone atoms (N, Ca, C, O) and gradually decreased during the simulation. The simulations were carried out in three phases: an initial period of heating from zero to 300 K over nine ps; an equilibration MD simulation of 0.1 ns, and monitored MD phase of simulation of one ns. The lowest energy frame of the MD simulation was further minimized and represented in the final structure. MD simulations described in the study were performed with NAMD 2.8 (Phillips et al., 2005[
 <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>])/Vega ZZ 3.1.0.21, using the CHARMM force field (Vanommeslaeghe et al., 2010[
 <xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]) and the Gasteiger charges. All reported minimizations were performed using the conjugate gradient algorithm until a root-median square (rms) gradient was smaller than 0.01 kcal/mol/Å. The final model validation was carried out with ProSA (Wiederstein and Sippl, 2007[
 <xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]) and PROCHECK programs (Laskowski et al., 1993[
 <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]).
</p>
