<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Tissue damage in Covid-19 is associated both with direct cytopathic action of the virus on infected cells [
 <xref rid="B28-vaccines-08-00224" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B85-vaccines-08-00224" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>] and with excessive activation of immune reaction with the release of enzymes and cytokines. Interestingly, depletion of lymphocytes and increase of neutrophils in peripheral blood are changes typically associated with worsening of disease course. Although direct infection may account for increased lymphocyte apoptosis, it seems more likely that depletion of lymphocytes depends on the production of inflammatory cytokines, similarly to what has been described for other viral illnesses, even if lymphopenia may also partly be due to accumulation of lymphocytes in diseased lungs [
 <xref rid="B86-vaccines-08-00224" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>,
 <xref rid="B87-vaccines-08-00224" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>,
 <xref rid="B88-vaccines-08-00224" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89-vaccines-08-00224" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. For example, a direct correlation between serum IFN-α and lymphocyte depletion was described in pigs with swine flu [
 <xref rid="B90-vaccines-08-00224" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>] and confirmed in experimental models of viral infection in mice lacking type I interferon receptor IFNAR [
 <xref rid="B91-vaccines-08-00224" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. Thus, the shortage of virus-specific lymphocytes may even be worsened by cytokine mediated immune paralysis. Notably, lymphocytes from patients with severe Covid-19 often present an exhausted phenotype [
 <xref rid="B92-vaccines-08-00224" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>] and this may reflect a functional impairment. Assessment of the immune response in a group of patients with severe Covid-19 with respiratory failure highlighted features supportive of either lymphocyte depletion with low Human Leukocyte Antigen -DR (HLA-DR) expression on monocytes, or macrophage activation syndrome. Subjects with macrophage activation syndrome had higher serum C reactive protein (CRP), ferritin, and IL-1β levels and lower white blood cell count than those with lymphocyte depletion. Conversely, subjects with lymphocyte depletion had higher levels of IL-6 and a trend for higher TNF-α. In these patients anti-IL6 treatment with tocilizumab resulted in increased circulating lymphocytes, highlighting the role of cytokine storm in the immunopathogenesis of the condition [
 <xref rid="B93-vaccines-08-00224" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. However, since in at least a subset of severe cases has been shown an impaired type I interferon activation, it might be possible that lymphopenia persistence in this setting might be type I interferon independent. 
</p>
