<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For the stable production of VEEV specific scFv-Fc fusion proteins, Chinese hamster ovary K1 cells (CHO-K1), from the American Type Culture Collection, (ATCC, Rockwell, MD, No. CCL61) were transfected by using 80 µl Polyfect® (Qiagen GmbH, Hilden, Germany) plus 4 to 5 µg of plasmid DNA. Stable clones were selected for resistance to the aminoglycoside antibiotic Geneticin (G418). For this purpose CHO-K1 cells were cultivated to 60% to 80% confluence overnight in 1000 mm
 <sup>2</sup> Petri dishes (Nunc, Vienna, Austria) in non-selective Dulbecco's Modified Eagle's Medium (DMEM/HAM's F-12), a nutrient mixture supplemented with L-glutamine and sodium bicarbonate, containing 10% (v/v) fetal calf serum (FCS) and 0.1% (w/v) penicillin and 0.1% (w/v) streptomycin (PAA, Parsing, Austria) at 37°C in 4% CO
 <sub>2</sub> atmosphere. In order to support the DNA-lipid complex formation, plasmid DNA and Polyfect® were preincubated in serum- and antibiotic-free medium for 10 minutes at room temperature prior to transfection. While the lipid-DNA complex formation took place, CHO-K1 cells were washed with PBS. Afterwards, 7 ml of medium with FCS and penicillin/streptomycin was added to the complex. The whole mixture was then immediately added to the washed cells by gently swirling. Cells were incubated for 3 h with the transfection complex. Subsequently the medium was removed and replaced with fresh non-selective DMEM/HAM's F-12 containing 10% (v/v) FCS and 0.1% (w/v) penicillin/streptomycin before the plates were incubated overnight at 37°C in 4% CO
 <sub>2</sub>. A further medium change was performed one day after the transfection. The transfected cells were trypsinised and re-sown 1∶20 or 1∶50 in new Petri dishes on selective medium, containing additionaly 700 mg/ml G418. Medium change was performed every 3 to 4 days and first stable and G418-resistant clones were visible about 3 weeks after transfection. Four and five weeks after transfection single clones were isolated and cultivated onto 24 well plates (Nunc, Vienna, Austria). Since the productivity of individual clones varies, we tested the supernatant of 48 clones for VEEV-specific scFv-fusion production in ELISAs as described. Finally, three of the best expressing CHO-K1-clones were cultivated as suspension culture in a miniPerm bioreactor (Sarstedt, Nümbrecht, Germany) in DMEM/HAM's F-12 containing 10% (v/v) (FCS), 1% (w/v) penicillin/streptomycin and 700 mg/ml G418 at 37°C in 4% CO
 <sub>2</sub>. The culture supernatant was harvested twice a week and replaced by fresh medium. Purification of recombinant fusion proteins was done by immunoaffinity chromatography on goat anti-human (GAH) sepharose.
</p>
