<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A common feature to several arboviruses is the virus-induced alteration of the musculo-skeletal system, with a clinical relevance of both arthropathies and myopathies. While arthritis and arthropathies associated with arboviruses have been largely studied [
 <xref rid="B12-viruses-12-00616" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], overall for alphaviruses RRV, SINV, and CHIKV [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-12-00616" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-viruses-12-00616" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-viruses-12-00616" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-12-00616" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-12-00616" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-12-00616" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-12-00616" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-12-00616" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-12-00616" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-12-00616" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], little attention has been given in the past to muscle as an organ potentially targeted by arboviruses. However, as reviewed by Suhrbier et al. [
 <xref rid="B12-viruses-12-00616" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], the frequency of myalgias during infection by arthrogenic viruses, such as CHIKV, RRV, Barmah Forest virus, SINV, O’Nyong-nyong virus and Mayaro virus, range between 40% and 90% among the patients. In a study conducted in Australia, RRV infection in humans was found to be associated with muscle pain in 66.7% of infected patients (
 <italic>N</italic> = 255) [
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-12-00616" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Similarly, as reviewed in Dupuis-Maguiraga in different studies performed during CHIKV outbreaks in La Réunion and Indian Ocean area, myalgia was reported in up to 84% of CHIKV-infected patients [
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-12-00616" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In a comparative study concerning CHIKV and dengue virus infection in Gabon, myalgia was reported among the clinical symptoms in more than 70% of infected patients, 195/270 for CHIKV, and 40/53 for DENV, respectively [
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-12-00616" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. A recent study conducted in French Guiana, points out the occurrence of muscle pain in 66.1% among CHIKV-infected patients (111, 
 <italic>N</italic> = 168), and 80.9% among dengue-infected patients (366, 
 <italic>N</italic> = 452) [
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-12-00616" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Concerning ZIKV, myalgia has been reported in 44% of infected patients (131, 
 <italic>N</italic> = 297) in French Polynesia, and 60% (121, 
 <italic>N</italic> = 203) in Martinique [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-12-00616" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-12-00616" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].
</p>
