<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The “flu season” is typically defined as epi week 40 of one year through 20 of the next; we also include data from the rest of the year as part of the season for the purpose of fitting models. In all mathematical notation, we will number the first week of the season as 1 rather than using the corresponding epi week. Let 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>
    <inline-formula id="pcbi.1006134.e009">
     <alternatives>
      <graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1006134.e009.jpg" id="pcbi.1006134.e009g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      <math id="M9">
       <msubsup>
        <mi>W</mi>
        <mrow>
         <mn>1</mn>
         <mo>.</mo>
         <mo>.</mo>
         <mrow/>
         <mi>t</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mi>t</mi>
       </msubsup>
      </math>
     </alternatives>
    </inline-formula> denote the 
    <italic>t</italic>-th CDC report of the current season, containing wILI values for weeks 1 through 
    <italic>t</italic>, inclusive, which is normally published on Friday of week 
    <italic>t</italic> + 1;
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>
    <italic>T</italic> be the number of weeks in the current season (either 52 or 53); we omit all details regarding differing season lengths, presenting forecasting methods and labeling epi week plot axes as if all seasons were of length 
    <italic>T</italic>;
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>
    <italic>Y</italic>
    <sub>1..
     <italic>T</italic>
    </sub> be the ground truth wILI for the current season: the wILI values used for forecast evaluation, specifically the epi week 28 report for the FluSight comparison, or later revisions as they are available for cross-validation analysis;
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>
    <inline-formula id="pcbi.1006134.e010">
     <alternatives>
      <graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1006134.e010.jpg" id="pcbi.1006134.e010g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
      <math id="M10">
       <msubsup>
        <mi>Y</mi>
        <mrow>
         <mn>1</mn>
         <mo>.</mo>
         <mo>.</mo>
         <mrow/>
         <mi>T</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mi>s</mi>
       </msubsup>
      </math>
     </alternatives>
    </inline-formula> be the ground truth wILI for past season 
    <italic>s</italic>; and
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>
    <bold>Z</bold>
    <sup>
     <italic>t</italic>
    </sup> be a vector containing the forecasting targets of interest at the 
    <italic>t</italic>-th wILI report of the current season: 
    <italic>Y</italic>
    <sub>
     <italic>t</italic>+1..
     <italic>t</italic>+4
    </sub> and the seasonal onset, peak week, and peak percentage; for the FluSight comparison, forecasts for these targets were typically due on Monday of week 
    <italic>t</italic> + 2, and allowed to use ILINet and any other data released before the deadline.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
