<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Like every mathematical model, there are some assumptions and constraints such as boundary conditions that the SIR model needs to satisfy. These restrictions define the circumstances where the SIR model may be appropriate to use in practice. Although some of them have been mentioned earlier, for the sake of self‐contained summarisation, we list all key assumptions as follows. 
 <def-list list-type="simple">
  <def-item>
   <term>Assumption 1:</term>
   <def>
    <p>The population involved in the infection is closed with no additions or leakage of individuals, and the size of the population is fixed, say, 
     <italic>N</italic>. This assumption may be satisfied by an epidemic that is rapid and short lived, during which disease evolution is not affected or is minimally affected by vital changes (e.g. natural births or deaths) and migration (i.e. immigration and emigration). Technically speaking, the three compartments satisfy the condition of the form: 
     <disp-formula id="insr12402-disp-0003">
      <math id="nlm-math-8">
       <mrow>
        <mfrac>
         <mrow>
          <mi>d</mi>
          <mi>S</mi>
          <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
          <mi>t</mi>
          <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
         </mrow>
         <mrow>
          <mi>d</mi>
          <mi>t</mi>
         </mrow>
        </mfrac>
        <mo>+</mo>
        <mfrac>
         <mrow>
          <mi>d</mi>
          <mi>I</mi>
          <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
          <mi>t</mi>
          <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
         </mrow>
         <mrow>
          <mi>d</mi>
          <mi>t</mi>
         </mrow>
        </mfrac>
        <mo>+</mo>
        <mfrac>
         <mrow>
          <mi>d</mi>
          <mi>R</mi>
          <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
          <mi>t</mi>
          <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
         </mrow>
         <mrow>
          <mi>d</mi>
          <mi>t</mi>
         </mrow>
        </mfrac>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mn>0</mn>
        <mo>,</mo>
        <mtext>or</mtext>
        <mspace width="0.3em"/>
        <mfrac>
         <mrow>
          <mi>d</mi>
          <msup>
           <mrow>
            <mi>θ</mi>
           </mrow>
           <mrow>
            <mi>S</mi>
           </mrow>
          </msup>
          <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
          <mi>t</mi>
          <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
         </mrow>
         <mrow>
          <mi>d</mi>
          <mi>t</mi>
         </mrow>
        </mfrac>
        <mo>+</mo>
        <mfrac>
         <mrow>
          <mi>d</mi>
          <msup>
           <mrow>
            <mi>θ</mi>
           </mrow>
           <mrow>
            <mi>I</mi>
           </mrow>
          </msup>
          <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
          <mi>t</mi>
          <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
         </mrow>
         <mrow>
          <mi>d</mi>
          <mi>t</mi>
         </mrow>
        </mfrac>
        <mo>+</mo>
        <mfrac>
         <mrow>
          <mi>d</mi>
          <msup>
           <mrow>
            <mi>θ</mi>
           </mrow>
           <mrow>
            <mi>R</mi>
           </mrow>
          </msup>
          <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
          <mi>t</mi>
          <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
         </mrow>
         <mrow>
          <mi>d</mi>
          <mi>t</mi>
         </mrow>
        </mfrac>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mn>0</mn>
        <mo>,</mo>
        <mspace width="0.3em"/>
        <mi>t</mi>
        <mo>≥</mo>
        <mn>0</mn>
        <mo>.</mo>
       </mrow>
      </math>
     </disp-formula>
    </p>
   </def>
  </def-item>
  <def-item>
   <term>Assumption 2:</term>
   <def>
    <p>Individuals in the population meet each other randomly in that both probability and degree of interactions with one another remain constant over time, regardless of geographical and demographic factors. This is a strong assumption of homogeneity for the SIR dynamic system that is governed by the same transmission and recovery parameters 
     <italic>β</italic> and 
     <italic>γ</italic>. In practice, such a homogeneity assumption may be easily violated. Thus, modelling with heterogeneous dynamics of infection is an important and active research area in the literature on infectious diseases.
    </p>
   </def>
  </def-item>
  <def-item>
   <term>Assumption 3:</term>
   <def>
    <p>One susceptible individual can only develop immunity (or self‐immunisation with antibody against the virus) through infection (i.e. no vaccination). In other words, as shown in Figure 
     <xref rid="insr12402-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, the infectious compartment is the only exit of the susceptible compartment, and there is no other state to which an at‐risk individual would move next. Once recovered from infection, one becomes immune to the virus for the remainder of the study period and would not return to be susceptible again. In effect, this is a rigorous definition of recovered case in the SIR model. From a view of the graphic representation in Figure 
     <xref rid="insr12402-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, this implies that there is no connection from the removed compartment to the susceptible compartment, or in other words the removed compartment is the terminal state of the infection dynamics. It is worth pointing out that to date the validity of this assumption for the COVID‐19 pandemic remains unknown. In the literature, this condition is assumed for a certain period of time over which risk prediction is considered.
    </p>
   </def>
  </def-item>
  <def-item>
   <term>Assumption 4:</term>
   <def>
    <p>The infection has zero latent period in that one becomes infectious once exposed. This is a key distinction of the SIR model from the SEIR model. Like many infectious diseases, the COVID‐19 has a reported average incubation period of between 4 and 7 days (Li 
     <italic>et al.</italic>, 
     <xref rid="insr12402-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>; Pan 
     <italic>et al.</italic>, 
     <xref rid="insr12402-bib-0070" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>), which adds some additional complexity in the modelling of infectious disease dynamics. As a matter of fact, this latency of contagion is really the timing of being contagious and not that of being symptomatic. Some studies have found that COVID‐19 carriers are most contagious in the early phase of illness prior to the occurrence of noticeable clinical symptoms (Ip 
     <italic>et al.</italic>, 
     <xref rid="insr12402-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; He 
     <italic>et al.</italic>, 
     <xref rid="insr12402-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Given these findings, it is tricky to see how the compartment of exposure for incubation would be added to extend the SIR model for the COVID‐19 pandemic.
    </p>
   </def>
  </def-item>
  <def-item>
   <term>Assumption 5:</term>
   <def>
    <p>Because the SIR model has constant transmission and recovery parameters 
     <italic>β</italic> and 
     <italic>γ</italic>, which are not time varying, the underlying infection is assumed to evolve in fully neutral environments with no mitigation efforts via external interventions such as a public health policy of social distancing, effective medication or fast testing kits for diagnosis. As far as the COVID‐19 pandemic is concerned, this is the biggest restriction of the SIR model, which is not reflective of the reality—almost all countries with reported COVID‐19 cases have issued various non‐pharmacological control measures. Many researchers have proposed solutions to overcome this unrealistic assumption of the SIR model in the analysis of COVID‐19 data (see, e.g. Wang 
     <italic>et al.</italic>, 
     <xref rid="insr12402-bib-0094" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>).
    </p>
   </def>
  </def-item>
  <def-item>
   <term>Assumption 6:</term>
   <def>
    <p>The population size 
     <italic>N</italic> is large enough to have enough number of incidences, including the number of infections, the number of deaths and the number of recovered cases, so that the SIR model parameters can be stably estimated with high precision. Technically speaking, this is not a model assumption but a condition of sample size for statistical power. Because this mechanistic model will ultimately be used for risk projection, a well‐trained model with reliable data is necessary to not only produce an accurate prediction but also to adequately assess the prediction uncertainty.
    </p>
   </def>
  </def-item>
 </def-list>
</p>
