<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>African swine fever (ASF) is an infectious disease causing high mortality of pigs, and is notifiable to the World Organisation of Animal Health (OIE). The aetiological agent, African swine fever virus (ASFV), is classified as the sole member of the
 <italic>.Asfarviridae</italic> family and is among the large (200 nm), complex, enveloped double-stranded DNA viruses (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). ASFV affects domestic and wild members of the Suidae family, leading to a wide range of symptoms from chronic or persistent infection to acute haemorrhagic fever, and inflicts up to 100% mortality (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). The main routes for disease transmission are direct contact between susceptible and sick animals or their fluids or excretions, and indirect contact through contaminated feed, pork meat, people, vehicles, or fomites (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). In endemic areas, ASFV also infects soft ticks of the
 <italic>.Ornithodoros</italic> genus, making them actively engaged in the disease epidemiology due to their potential to indirectly transmit the virus to susceptible vertebrate hosts (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). Studies regarding hard ticks 
 <italic>.Ixodes ricinus</italic> and
 <italic>.Dermacentor reticulatus</italic>) as a source of ASFV demonstrated that these parasites facilitate neither virus replication nor tick-to-pig transmission, at least under laboratory conditions; nevertheless, viral DNA can persist in the tick organism up to eight weeks, allowing them to act as mechanical vectors (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Mellor
 <italic>.et al</italic>. (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>) proved that the stable fly,
 <italic>.Stomoxys calcitrans</italic>, is able to mechanically transmit the virus up to 24 h post digestion of ASFV infected blood. Moreover, a recent study conducted by Olesen
 <italic>.et al</italic>. (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>) established that infection of pigs might also occur following the oral uptake of flies fed ASFV-infected blood.
</p>
