<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>From bacteria to plants and insects to humans, it is common to find considerable genetic variation in susceptibility to infection in natural populations (
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Chapman and Hill, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bangham et al., 2008a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Hammond-Kosack and Jones, 1997</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Lazzaro et al., 2004</xref>). This variation in susceptibility can determine the impact of disease on health and economic output (
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Cooke and Hill, 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">King and Lively, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Alonso-Blanco and Méndez-Vigo, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Burgner et al., 2006</xref>). In nature and breeding programs, it determines the ability of populations to evolve resistance to infection. Insect populations, like those of other organisms, typically contain considerable genetic variation in susceptibility to infection (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Bangham et al., 2008a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Lazzaro et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">Tinsley et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Obbard and Dudas, 2014</xref>), and provide a convenient laboratory model in which to investigate basic questions about how this variation is maintained (
 <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Magwire et al., 2012</xref>). Within vector species like mosquitoes, resistant genotypes are less likely to transmit pathogens, and this has the potential to reduce disease in vertebrate populations (
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Beerntsen et al., 2000</xref>). Where pathogens are contributing the decline of beneficial species like pollinators, high levels of genetic variation may allow populations to recover (
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Maori et al., 2007</xref>). Understanding the origins of genetic variation in susceptibility is therefore a fundamental question in infectious disease biology.
</p>
