<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0115">
 <def-list>
  <def-item>
   <term id="dt0010">*ome</term>
   <def>
    <p id="p0120">Suffix that is commonly used to emphasize that a collection of individual elements is considered as a whole. The entirety of all genes, for example, forms the genome. Compare with interactome and exposome.</p>
   </def>
  </def-item>
  <def-item>
   <term id="dt0015">Complex network</term>
   <def>
    <p id="p0125">Complex networks provide holistic models of systems that consist of many interacting elements. Each individual element is represented as a node (also called ‘vertex’) and each interaction between two elements as a link (or ‘edge’). The connection patterns within complex networks are typically neither completely regular, nor completely random.</p>
   </def>
  </def-item>
  <def-item>
   <term id="dt0020">Disease module</term>
   <def>
    <p id="p0130">Genes associated with a particular disease are not scattered randomly within molecular networks, but aggregate in certain neighborhoods or ‘disease modules.’</p>
   </def>
  </def-item>
  <def-item>
   <term id="dt0025">Exposome</term>
   <def>
    <p id="p0135">Organisms are constantly exposed to a multitude of biological and chemical factors through their environment, collectively referred to as ‘exposome.’ The dynamic combination of the internal biological state (homeostatis) and external influx (exposome) results in health or disease.</p>
   </def>
  </def-item>
  <def-item>
   <term id="dt0030">Functional networks</term>
   <def>
    <p id="p0140">Networks in which links represent indirect relationships, for example correlated activity patterns in functional brain region networks or shared biological processes in gene similarity networks. Compare with physical networks.</p>
   </def>
  </def-item>
  <def-item>
   <term id="dt0035">Herd effect</term>
   <def>
    <p id="p0145">Phenomenon observed in epidemiology that the immunization of one part of a population also decreases the risk of infection for the other part that is not immune. The herd effect is important to protect sub-populations that cannot be treated (e.g., immunocompromised people) and allows for the overall success of immunization campaigns even under partial compliance.</p>
   </def>
  </def-item>
  <def-item>
   <term id="dt0040">Interactome</term>
   <def>
    <p id="p0150">In analogy to the genome, the interactome represents the complex network of all molecular interactions within a biological system. More specifically, the term often refers to physical protein-protein interactions within the cell. Over the last two decades the interactomes of several organisms have been mapped out systematically, ranging from model organisms to human.</p>
   </def>
  </def-item>
  <def-item>
   <term id="dt0045">P4 medicine</term>
   <def>
    <p id="p0155">Predictive, preventive, personalized and participative medicine. This approach aims to improve healthcare by progressively reducing the need for one-size-fits-all palliative treatments by leveraging modern therapeutic solutions and personal patient data such as genome or microbiome sequencing.</p>
   </def>
  </def-item>
  <def-item>
   <term id="dt0050">Physical networks</term>
   <def>
    <p id="p0160">Networks in which links represent physical interactions, such as physical binding between proteins in interactome networks, or synapses in neural networks. Compare with functional networks.</p>
   </def>
  </def-item>
  <def-item>
   <term id="dt0055">Protein-Protein Interaction (PPI)</term>
   <def>
    <p id="p0165">Cellular processes rely on the coordinated interaction between different proteins. Several experimental methods are available to detect such interactions, for example yeast two-hybrid approaches or affinity purification combined with mass spectrometry.</p>
   </def>
  </def-item>
 </def-list>
</p>
