<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We report the generation of a full-length cDNA derived from the highly virulent Mediterranean WNV strain IS-98-ST1 that permitted recovery of a fully replicative virus. The establishment of a reverse genetic system for WNV is essential for the study of viral neurovirulence and neuroinvasiveness. Infectious clones allow introduction of genetic modifications and facilitate identification of the molecular determinants of viral virulence. Nevertheless, cDNA constructs comprising the full flavivirus genome have been widely reported to be unstable in prokaryotic expression systems 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Beasley1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Shi1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Yamschchikov1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Seregin1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. To avoid constructs all together, genome-length RT-PCRs have been employed, but pose the risk of generating a heterogeneous RNA population, owing to mutations occurring during RT-PCR or to viral diversity in the original virus stock. Different approaches have thus been used to improve the stability of full-length flavivirus cDNA clones 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Shi1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. Introns have been inserted to interrupt genes encoding products that may be toxic in bacteria 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Borisevich1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, and relatively permissive 
 <italic>E.coli</italic> strains have been identified. Full-length flavivirus cDNA from NY99, B956 and Kunjin WNV strains have previously been cloned in plasmids amplified in the HB101 
 <italic>E.coli</italic> strain 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Shi1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Yamschchikov1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. In the present study, we employed a plasmid cloning strategy to construct an infectious clone of the IS-98-ST1 WNV strain (WNV-IC). Selection of the appropriate plasmid is critical 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Shi1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Ruggli1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. The pBR322 plasmid was chosen because it had been used successfully to generate West Nile infectious clones in the past 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Shi1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Yamschchikov1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. Plasmids encoding flavivirus sequences downstream of cytomegalovirus (CMV) or lac promoters displayed high instability due to expression of products that were toxic for 
 <italic>E.coli</italic>
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Yamshchikov1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. To avoid such problems we selected the promoter for the bacteriophage SP6 RNA polymerase for 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription of viral RNA 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Yamschchikov1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Elghonemy1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Khromykh2" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. An additional G nucleotide was inserted downstream of the promoter to ensure more efficient transcription initiation 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Yamschchikov1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. To this end, the pBR322 plasmid was modified (GeneCust, Dudelange, Luxemburg) to incorporate the SP6 promoter, the WNV 5′UTR (from position 1 to 97), part of the gene encoding the WNV capsid (from position 97 to 120) and the WNV 3′UTR (from position 10437 to 11029), along with the hepatitis δ virus ribozyme (HDVR). The HDVR mediated termination of WNV transcripts at their natural 3′ end, thereby ensuring removal of nonviral sequences downstream of the WNV 3′UTR that might have interfered with the initiation of viral RNA replication 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Yamschchikov1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Fodor1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. Although infectious clones have been generated in the past, they were found to comprise mutations with respect to their parental virus or have been very difficult to handle 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Shi1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Yamschchikov1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Yamshchikov2" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. As a consequence, many of the infectious WNV clones currently in use have been obtained in two pieces 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Beasley1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Kinney1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Audsley1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. Our infectious clone was constructed as a single piece and ensures propagation of recombinant virus. It also displayed remarkable stability, even after numerous passages in bacterial hosts (data not shown).
</p>
