<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Infectious clones of lineage 2, African strain B956 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Yamschchikov1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, lineage 1, American NY99 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Beasley1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Shi1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Kinney1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Borisevich1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Audsley1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Schlick1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, and Australian Kunjin strains 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Khromykh2" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref> have been generated and used to decipher the role of viral proteins in virulence 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Audsley1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Yu1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>, neuroinvasiveness 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Beasley1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Borisevich1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref> and escape from host defences 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Mertens1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Liu3" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, as well as to evaluate the impact of point mutations 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Mertens1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Wicker1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Brault1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>. These tools have substantially facilitated identification of molecular determinants of WNV virulence, albeit in a non-European context. WNV epidemiology differs between Europe and North America, in that outbreaks in Europe are more limited in space and duration. It is presumed that at least part of the difference stems from genetic divergence between North American and Mediterranean viral isolates. It is thus important to extend molecular studies of WNV to European strains, for which results have sometimes been at odds with those for the NY99 strain. Brault 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Brault1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref> identified a point mutation, T249P, in NS3, as playing an important role in the virulence of NY99 in American crows, while Sotelo 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref rid="pone.0047666-Sotelo2" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref> showed that a 2007 Spanish strain bore the same mutation but was much less virulent than the NY99 strain in mice. Clearly, comparison of molecular clones derived from different continents is indispensable for identifying the genetic differences underlying the different epidemiological patterns.
</p>
