<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, the gene targets of cfa-miR-197 and cfa-miR-215 were in silico predicted by three databases: miRDB, TargetScan, and RNAhybrid. It is intriguing that karyopherin alpha 6 (KPNA6) or importin-α7 could be co-targeted by both microRNAs. Nevertheless, luciferase activity revealed that KPNA6 contained the putative binding sites for only cfa-miR-197, but not cfa-miR-215. In addition, the downregulation of KPNA6 mRNA occurred after cfa-miR-197 was overexpressed. There is growing evidence that KPNA6 plays various roles in the pathogenesis and replication of many viruses such as Zika virus [
 <xref rid="B43-viruses-11-00986" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], Ebola virus [
 <xref rid="B44-viruses-11-00986" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-viruses-11-00986" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], and porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome virus [
 <xref rid="B43-viruses-11-00986" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. In addition, the role of KPNA6 has been studied in influenza A viruses, which are more closely related to seasonal influenza B viruses. Recent studies indicated that KPNA6 interacts with some influenza A viral proteins, affecting viral replication and pathogenicity. Viral RNA polymerase basic 2 (PB2) is considered a major virulent determinant of influenza A viruses, which involves in host adaptation [
 <xref rid="B46-viruses-11-00986" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. In mammalian-adapted strains, PB2 is imported into the host nucleus via preferential binding to KPNA6 [
 <xref rid="B47-viruses-11-00986" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-viruses-11-00986" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Besides interspecies transmission, PB2 is thoroughly known to play a key part in the replication and transcription of influenza viruses. Therefore, KPNA6 is also essential for propagation of influenza A viruses [
 <xref rid="B49-viruses-11-00986" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-viruses-11-00986" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-viruses-11-00986" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-viruses-11-00986" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Furthermore, viral nucleoprotein (NP) is another important multifunctional protein interacting with KPNA6, leading to enhancing influenza A virus replication [
 <xref rid="B46-viruses-11-00986" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-viruses-11-00986" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. A recent study has shown that a long N-terminal tail of the influenza B virus NP bound to human KPNA6 [
 <xref rid="B54-viruses-11-00986" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Although the NP of influenza B viruses could possibly be imported into canine nucleus by KPNA6, the interaction between NP of influenza B virus and canine KPNA6 should be experimentally investigated. Moreover, KPNA6 was shown to interact with not only viral proteins, but also host proteins [
 <xref rid="B55-viruses-11-00986" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. For example, KPNA6 mediates Kelch-like ECH-associated protein 1 (Keap1)/Nuclear factor erythroid 2–related factor 2 (Nrf2) signaling pathway, affecting IFNα antiviral response, oxidative stress, and autophagy during hepatitis C virus infection [
 <xref rid="B56-viruses-11-00986" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-viruses-11-00986" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>].
</p>
