<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par9">The antiviral activity of benzimidazole nucleosides was first reported by Tamm, Folker and co-workers in 1954. They designed 5,6-dichloro-1-(
 <italic>β</italic>-D-ribofuranosyl) benzimidazole (DRB), which had various biological activities including antiviral activity against RNA and DNA viruses. The antiviral activity of DRB is via inhibiting cellular RNA polymerase II thus inhibiting viral and cellular RNA synthesis (Migawa et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">1998</xref>; Porcari et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">1998</xref>; Chen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2000</xref>; Townsend et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">1995</xref>). In pharmaceutical chemistry, heterocyclic compounds particularly the benzene-fused are of great importance. In the class of benzene-fused compounds, benzimidazole and its derivatives are known for their wide variety of biological activities. Biologically active compounds such as vitamin B12, albendazole, mebendazole and thiabendazole contain a benzimidazole nucleus in their structure (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">22.2</xref>) (Shaharyar et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">2016</xref>). Structure–activity relationship (SAR) studies show that due to a change in the group on the basic structure, benzimidazoles display a wide array of biological activities including analgesic, antibacterial, antifungal, anticancer and antiviral (Alaqeel 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2017</xref>). Moreover, a range of structurally varied nonnucleoside inhibitors (NNI) of the HCV polymerases sharing the benzimidazole pharmacophore has been reported. Among these classes of compounds, JTK-003, which is an orally active benzimidazole derivative, is in its Phase I and II clinical trial stage in Japan (Tan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">2002</xref>; Tomei et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">2003</xref>). Currently, a number of benzimidazole derivatives are available in the market such as omeprazole and rabeprazole used for gastric ulcers, telmisartan and candesartan for hypertension, astemizole and mizolastine for allergic rhinitis, and albendazole, oxibendazole and mebendazole for parasitosis (Wang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">2015</xref>). Benzimidazoles readily interact with the biopolymers of the living system due to the fact that they are bioisosteres of cellular nucleotides (Starčević et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">2007</xref>).
</p>
