<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28">EV-A71 reemerged in Taiwan in 2000, 2001, 2005, 2008 and 2012. More than 600 severe cases and 51 deaths were reported to the Taiwan Center for Disease Control in both 2000 and 2001 consecutive years [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]. A total of 142 cases (16 fatal) were recorded in 2005 for the entire country, and EV-A71 infection was most common in children ≤4 years of age [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>]. There were 373 severe confirmed cases in 2008, of which 14 were fatal (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]. Infections peaked in June with 39 confirmed cases, similar to previous EV-A71 infection in 1998 in Taiwan [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]. The marked increase in EV-A71 infection paralleled reports from the National Cheng Kung University Medical Center in southern Taiwan that same year, which documented 367 cases. This figure was much higher than the EV-A71 case number in 2007 (1 case) and 2006 (no case) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]. Other studies also confirmed that EV-A71 was also the most prevalent genotype found in northern Taiwan among the HFMD cases in 2008 and that some affected children experienced neurological complications [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>]. For example, two children diagnosed with HFMD presented with brainstem encephalitis and cardiopulmonary failure [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>]. In addition, three HFMD patients had encephalomyelitis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>]. In 2012, HFMD outbreak again reemerged in Taiwan [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>]. EV-A71 in Taiwan appears seasonal and often peaks in the summer [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>].
</p>
