<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Flaviviruses have the capacity to emerge as major human pathogens and cause large scale epidemics. Recent examples include Zika and yellow fever viruses, which have caused large epidemics in South America in the 2010s, and dengue virus, which is still the most prevalent disease-causing arthropod-borne virus worldwide. While, most flaviviruses are transmitted through a classical arthropod-borne cycle between arthropod vectors and vertebrate hosts, and exhibit replication in cells from a wild range of invertebrate and vertebrate host species, some flaviviruses exhibit a more narrow host range. These include flaviviruses that do not infect arthropod hosts (no known vector), fail to replicate in vertebrates (insect-specific) or exhibit host-restriction in vertebrate cells that is cell line- or temperature-dependent [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008166.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0008166.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The mechanisms for emergence of pathogens from enzootic flaviviruses are not clear despite past examples of large-scale epidemics caused by under-studied flaviviruses such as Zika virus [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008166.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The emergence of flaviviruses as pathogens may be linked to the naturally high rate of mutations in the genome of RNA viruses, due to the low proof-reading efficiency of the RNA-dependent RNA polymerase [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008166.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Indeed, flaviviruses are positive-sense, single-stranded RNA viruses with a genome of approximately 11 kilobases (kb), contained in an enveloped icosahedral nucleocapsid [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008166.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008166.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The viral RNA contains an open reading frame (ORF) coding for a single polyprotein that is co- and post-translationally cleaved into three structural (capsid (C), membrane precursor (prM) / membrane (M) and envelope (E)), seven non-structural (NS) proteins and the 2K peptide (NS1, NS2A, NS2B, NS3, NS4A, 2K, NS4B, and NS5) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008166.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008166.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The translated polyprotein is embedded in the membranes of the endoplasmic reticulum 
 <italic>via</italic> several transmembrane domains. It is cleaved by either a host signal peptidase in the endoplasmic reticulum lumen (C/prM, prM/E, E/NS1 and 2K/NS4B) or the viral protease NS2B-NS3 in the cytoplasm (NS2A/NS2B, NS2B/NS3, NS3/NS4A, NS4A/2K, NS4B/NS5). Once replication complexes have been established, with the NS5-encoded RdRp at their core, the viral RNA is replicated using a newly generated genome-length negative-sense strand as a template for new positive strands [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008166.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].
</p>
