<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In transmission studies, mortality was observed in donor ferrets inoculated with the highly pathogenic wild-type and recombinant GD/3 H7N9 viruses, while none of the A/Anhui/1/2013 (H7N9) infected ferrets became severely ill. One GD/3, two rGD/3 NA294R, and one rGD/3 NA 294K infected donor animals died between days 4 and 8 post-infection [
 <xref rid="B152-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>]. Transmission occurred by respiratory droplet to one, three, two, and one out of four exposed animals for GD/3, rGD/3 NA 294R, rGD/3 NA 294K, and A/Anhui/1/2013 (H7N9) viruses, respectively. For respiratory contacts exposed to the rGD/3 NA 294R, two out of three animals that became infected developed severe disease and succumbed to infection on days 6 and 9 post-exposure, and the respective donor ferrets for these animals also succumbed to infection (as noted above) [
 <xref rid="B152-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>]. These studies indicate that the highly pathogenic H7N9 viruses have enhanced virulence in ferrets, while respiratory transmission is inefficient and exhibits a similar degree of variation as reported for the low pathogenic A/Anhui/1/2013 (H7N9) virus [
 <xref rid="B132-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>,
 <xref rid="B133-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>,
 <xref rid="B134-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>,
 <xref rid="B135-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>,
 <xref rid="B136-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>,
 <xref rid="B137-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>]. Therefore, it is likely that as with the low pathogenic H7N9 strains, highly pathogenic variants will also require mutations to stabilize the HA. Given that previously identified mutations do not readily confer stability to the H7 HA, novel mutations or drift variants identified in both highly pathogenic and low pathogenic H7N9 viruses should be rapidly characterized for their effect on pH of fusion, thermostability, and airborne transmission in ferrets.
</p>
