<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12">In the second phase of the pandemic, when the curve of COVID-19 cases started to flatten and COVID-dedicated facilities were partially dismissed, we adopted new strategies for our NMD patients (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). At the time of writing, the number of new daily cases in many western countries is decreasing (see COVID map link), but strategies to effectively resume subspecialty outpatients’ clinics and to reorganize hospital settings in the post-acute pandemic phase still lack. National and international recommendations, though heterogeneous, identify some higher-risk subjects that may need prolonged strict preventive measures even after the worst phases of the pandemic, such as adults older than 65, immunocompromised, and cancer patients (e.g. 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.esmo.org/for-patients/patient-guides/cancer-care-during-the-covid-19-pandemic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.esmo.org/for-patients/patient-guides/cancer-care-during-the-covid-19-pandemic</ext-link>) (Tables 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). NMD patients at higher risks for SARS-CoV-2 complications should be included in this list (see “
 <xref rid="Sec3" ref-type="sec">Risk assessment and stratification</xref>” section) . Depending on the number of new cases, COVID-dedicated hospitals should be reorganized to permit the management of outpatients and the provision of ancillary services, if possible; if not, referral centres for NMD patients should implement robust telemedicine services to allow for proper online visits and patient’s caring (see “
 <xref rid="Sec5" ref-type="sec">Telehealth and telerehabilitation</xref>” section). We believe that low-risk individuals—who include most of NMD patients—could be assessed in COVID hospitals, using proper precautions regarding both facilities and PPE; patients should be cared for in separate, non-COVID buildings, they should wait in uncrowded waiting rooms, and should hygienize their hands and wear face masks and gloves at the facility entrance, similar to measures adopted in previous epidemics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].
</p>
