<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">Combining anti-inflammatory agents with anti-viral agents is another attractive option. Artificial intelligence (AI)-powered algorithm predictions have identified baricitinib, ruxolitinib, and fedratinib as potential candidates [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. These drugs belong to the Janus kinase (JAK) inhibitor class of medications that have been approved and used safely in conditions like myelofibrosis and rheumatoid arthritis. These drugs are powerful anti-inflammatory agents that target the JAK-STAT pathways and are likely to be effective against the deleterious consequences of elevated cytokines. Of particular interest is baricitinib, which is predicted to interfere with the ability of the virus to enter and infect lung cells by receptor-mediated endocytosis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. Due to the favorable pharmacological and safety profile of baricitinib, it can be considered in combination with direct-acting anti-viral agents like lopinavir, remdesivir, and ritonavir to decrease the viral replication, infectivity, as well as to calm the cytokine responses. Statins, another group of drugs that have anti-inflammatory and antithrombotic properties, have also been studied in COVID-19 patients; a retrospective study showed a favorable recovery profile and lower all-cause mortality with the use of statins in 1219 hospitalized patients with COVID-19 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. Convalescent plasma has historically been used to improve outcomes in a variety of viral epidemics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. In theory, recovered COVID-19 patients’ plasma containing anti COVID-19 neutralizing antibodies should provide passive immunity to patients with ongoing disease. However, a recent systematic review failed to demonstrate any benefit of this approach in patients hospitalized with COVID-19, in addition to uncertainty of the safety profile of convalescent plasma therapy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>].
</p>
