<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>When insight is limited and compartmental models are not suited, phenomenological statistical models provide a starting point for estimation of key transmission parameters, such as the reproduction number, and forecasts of epidemic impact.
 <xref rid="c27" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>27</sup>
 </xref> One of the simplest ways to model the epidemics is to observe that the function 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="M72">
   <mi>C</mi>
   <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
   <mi>t</mi>
   <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> is a sigmoid function and perform a statistical fit of the data to extrapolate the long-term behavior of the epidemics.
 <xref rid="c28" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>28,29</sup>
 </xref> Among all the possible sigmoid functions, two have proven useful in fitting epidemic growth: the generalized logistic distribution
 <xref rid="c30" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>30</sup>
 </xref> and the generalized Gompertz distribution.
 <xref rid="c31" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>31</sup>
 </xref> A complete overview of sigmoid functions is presented in Ref. 
 <xref rid="c32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, although applied to in a different context. Since our considerations are independent of the sigmoid function used, we will present results for the generalized logistic model only. The model reads 
 <disp-formula id="d11">
  <math id="M73">
   <mi>C</mi>
   <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
   <mi>t</mi>
   <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
   <mo>=</mo>
   <mi>a</mi>
   <mo>/</mo>
   <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
   <mn>1</mn>
   <mo>+</mo>
   <mi>b</mi>
   <mo>⋅</mo>
   <mi>exp</mi>
   <mo>⁡</mo>
   <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
   <mo>−</mo>
   <mi>c</mi>
   <mo>⋅</mo>
   <mi>t</mi>
   <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
   <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
   <mo>,</mo>
  </math>
  <label>(11)</label>
 </disp-formula> where 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="M74">
   <mi>a</mi>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>, 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="M75">
   <mi>b</mi>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>, and 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="M76">
   <mi>c</mi>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> are parameters of the model. They are linked in a non-explicit way to the solution of the SEIR model. A fit to the Chinese data is presented in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2</xref>. Logistic fits are performed with the MATLAB Nonlinear least-squares solver constraining objective function with gradient. At first sight, one can be tempted to use 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="M77">
   <msup>
    <mi>R</mi>
    <mn>2</mn>
   </msup>
   <mo>≃</mo>
   <mn>0.997</mn>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> as a quality indicator of the fit. However, we stress that 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="M78">
   <msup>
    <mi>R</mi>
    <mn>2</mn>
   </msup>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> is not an appropriate measure for nonlinear regression models: given the smoothness of data, there will be lots of models (e.g., low-order polynomial), which could fit well (get a very good 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="M79">
   <msup>
    <mi>R</mi>
    <mn>2</mn>
   </msup>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>) but would not make credible predictions.
 <xref rid="c33" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>33</sup>
 </xref> These data are, however, collected at a mature stage of the epidemic and as such the characteristics of the logistic fit to these data can be assigned with greater confidence. In Sec. 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s3">III</xref>, we will discuss the performance of the statistical model in the early stage of the epidemics, where the logistic function can be used to extrapolate the behavior of 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="M80">
   <mi>C</mi>
   <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
   <mi>t</mi>
   <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>.
</p>
