<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The study of clinical isolates and naturally-occurring variants has been an essential element in defining pathogenesis or the role of specific viral genes in human infections. For example, the finding of an HIV strain that contained a spontaneous deletion in the 
 <italic>nef</italic> gene in a long term non-progressor and a cohort of individuals who received blood transfusions from this individual was the essential observation in defining the role of this gene in disease[
 <xref rid="pone.0184318.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Up until the identification of this 
 <italic>nef</italic>-deleted mutant, the 
 <italic>nef</italic> gene was thought to be an accessory gene (i.e. not required for virus replication 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>) with an unclear role(s) in pathogenesis [
 <xref rid="pone.0184318.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. It is now well defined that the 
 <italic>nef</italic> gene down regulates several cell surface molecules and that this down-regulation is essential for pathogenesis and virulence [
 <xref rid="pone.0184318.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Ebola virus Reston, closely related to the highly virulent Ebola virus Zaire, appears to be non-pathogenic in humans. By comparing the sequences of the pathogenic and non-pathogenic viruses, potential Ebola virulence factors, such as the virion glycoprotein, were identified [
 <xref rid="pone.0184318.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Therefore, it is a reasonable hypothesis that clinical strains of RSV differ in their pathogenic potential and that the variability of clinical disease observed in RSV-infected children may be due, in part, the variability in virulence factors encoded by the virus. In fact, among laboratory strains of RSV, the capacity to inhibit TLR-dependent and TLR-independent responses in human plasmacytoid dendritic cells differs [
 <xref rid="pone.0184318.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] further supporting our hypothesis.
</p>
