<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The RSV 
 <italic>G</italic> gene has been implicated in directing the host innate immune response to the virus [
 <xref rid="pone.0184318.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0184318.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. The genetic diversity in RSV strains is most pronounced in the 
 <italic>G</italic> gene [
 <xref rid="pone.0184318.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] and, consistent with that observation, the viruses examined in this study displayed the greatest level of diversity in this gene. Notably, NH1067B and the other low-inducing viruses (NH1182B and TX11-56B) all contain a 60 base duplication (not present in NH1125B) which was initially described in isolates in South America [
 <xref rid="pone.0184318.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The duplication in the 
 <italic>G</italic> gene has been reported to augment viral attachment and fitness [
 <xref rid="pone.0184318.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] perhaps providing these viruses with an evolutionary advantage over viruses that do have this duplication. Indeed, subgroup B viruses harboring this duplication have nearly displaced subgroup B viruses that lack this duplication [
 <xref rid="pone.0184318.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Our data correlate the presence of this duplication with “low induction” phenotype however, it is not clear whether this duplication and/or the single amino acid polymorphism at position 229 of the G protein or the amino acid substitution at position 142 of the M2-1 protein are solely responsible for the “low inducer” phenotype. The CX3C motif (amino acid 182–186) was identical in all viruses [
 <xref rid="pone.0184318.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. The M2-1 protein acts as a transcriptional elongation factor that prevents premature termination during transcription and functions as an anti-termination factor as the polymerase switches from the transciptase activity to a genomic replicase activity [
 <xref rid="pone.0184318.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Based on the RNA-SEQ data (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0184318.s006">S6</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0184318.s007">S7</xref> Figs), there does not appear to be a global difference in the gene transcript profile of NH1125B as compared to NH1067B suggesting that this amino acid polymorphism may have an alternative role (if any) in the viral phenotypes. Nonetheless, the contribution of these amino acid polymorphisms will need to be deciphered using alternative approaches. Furthermore, non-synonymous or non-coding region polymorphisms may play a role in the observed differences in the viral phenotypes.
</p>
