<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Prenatal exposure to ZIKV is now a well-documented cause of severe microcephaly in infants [
 <xref rid="B8-pathogens-09-00352" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In addition, evidence indicates that clinical presentation of congenital ZIKV syndrome (CZS) differs in severity and prognosis depending on the head circumference (HC) at birth and the central nervous system (CNS) damage [
 <xref rid="B8-pathogens-09-00352" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Adverse clinical outcomes at birth or over the first year of life have been described in different cohorts, affecting between 10% and 45% of the offspring exposed to ZIKV in utero [
 <xref rid="B9-pathogens-09-00352" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-pathogens-09-00352" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-pathogens-09-00352" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-pathogens-09-00352" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-pathogens-09-00352" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-pathogens-09-00352" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Most of these infants are expected to survive, and their estimated life span is expected to be comparable to other children with microcephaly, epilepsy, and intellectual disability [
 <xref rid="B15-pathogens-09-00352" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. It is important to note that consensus is lacking about the phenotype of CZS; however, fetal brain disruption sequence [
 <xref rid="B4-pathogens-09-00352" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-pathogens-09-00352" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-pathogens-09-00352" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and neuropathology resembling congenital infections, such as toxoplasmosis or cytomegalovirus (CMV), have been reported among infants with CZS [
 <xref rid="B18-pathogens-09-00352" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Therefore, the long-term impact of CZS may be severe for children and their families. The literature to date on CZS and children exposed to ZIKV in utero is dominated by studies conducted in epidemic and endemic settings, where individuals may be (re-)exposed to other flavivirus.
</p>
