<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The study herein also provides data useful for the development of therapeutics and diagnostics, and can aid in the surveillance of existing and future strains of influenza viruses. Highly conserved sequences shortlisted in our analysis could be tested for inhibitory drug design and used as diagnostic tool. There were 68 completely conserved human H5N1 IAV virus sequences (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-7">Table S6</xref>) that could be used to design targets that are sensitive to detect the presence of H5N1 virus strains. However, these sequences would need to be further evaluated for specificity to the subtype. The high propensity for influenza A virus to develop resistance against drugs has been a major problem for the development of therapeutics against the virus. Rapid viral resistance against current antivirals, M2 ion channel inhibitors (amantadine and rimantadine) and NA inhibitors (oseltamivir, zanamivir, peramivir, and lanimivir) have been reported, with side effects and low efficacy (
 <xref rid="ref-63" ref-type="bibr">Yuan, Wen &amp; Zhou, 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2018</xref>). Major research efforts are now focusing on the polymerase protein (such as favipiravir and pimovidir) because they are highly conserved and important machinery in viral replication and transcription (
 <xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2018</xref>). Our analyses have shown that there are a number of highly conserved sequences, of non-polymerase protein origin, such as nucleoprotein, neuraminidase and haemaglutinin, which were conserved only in avian viruses. These sequences can be further studied on their presence in other subtypes of H5N1 so that the drug target will have broad effectiveness. Additionally, the diversity motifs can be further assessed by studying the transmission pathway between avian and human virus populations for adaptation patterns. In particular, by assessing for sequences of low incidence motifs (unique, minor or major motifs) in the reservoir that are selected as index in human. For example, a major motif of PB1 (I525V) in avian H7N9 viruses was selected as the index in human viruses (manuscript submitted). The bioinformatics approaches applied herein to study the dynamics of influenza A virus protein sequence diversity can offer a roadmap for a practical, systematic analyses for rationalized vaccine, drug, and diagnostic targets discovery.
</p>
