<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In IBV, RNA segment 7 encodes both M1 protein and BM2 [
 <xref rid="B38-cells-08-00654" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-cells-08-00654" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Like AM2, BM2 is a pH-activated proton channel [
 <xref rid="B40-cells-08-00654" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] and has a similar monomeric and oligomeric organization as described above for AM2 [
 <xref rid="B41-cells-08-00654" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-cells-08-00654" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Like AM2, a truncated peptide containing its TM, BM2(1–33), conducts protons when incorporated into artificial liposomes [
 <xref rid="B42-cells-08-00654" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] and 
 <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes, with similar conductance and proton-selectivity as that observed in full-length BM2 protein [
 <xref rid="B43-cells-08-00654" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Despite these similarities, AM2 and BM2 share almost no sequence identity, with the exception of an HxxxW motif in the TM domain (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="cells-08-00654-f001">Figure 1</xref>), which may explain some of their common features. AM2 and BM2 also differ in post-translational modifications; while BM2 is only modified by phosphorylation [
 <xref rid="B44-cells-08-00654" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], AM2 contains disulfide bonds and is palmitoylated and phosphorylated [
 <xref rid="B45-cells-08-00654" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-cells-08-00654" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-cells-08-00654" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-cells-08-00654" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Like AM2, BM2 is essential for virus uncoating in the endosome and for pH equilibration between Golgi lumen and cytoplasm during virus protein transport [
 <xref rid="B38-cells-08-00654" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. However, while the AM2 ectodomain is important for its incorporation into virions [
 <xref rid="B49-cells-08-00654" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], the BM2 has only a small ectodomain [
 <xref rid="B41-cells-08-00654" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-cells-08-00654" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="cells-08-00654-f001">Figure 1</xref>). 
</p>
