<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0007">Nevertheless, despite this reassuring data, precautions should be considered to minimize any potential or theoretic risks during the COVID-19 pandemic. There are several relevant safety considerations for clinical teams who participate in gynecologic surgery during this time. Laparoscopy most commonly involves general anesthesia, with the associated intubation, extubation, and mechanical ventilation, which may produce airborne viral droplets in a patient who is COVID-19 positive. General anesthesia is not contraindicated in patients who are confirmed as COVID-19 positive, but the surgical team should minimize exposure to airborne virus during intubation and extubation and OR personnel should don adequate personal protective equipment (PPE), including face shields, N95 filtered masks if available, gowns, and gloves. Even if it is assumed that limited viral particles may become airborne through the pneumoperitoneum during laparoscopy, the OR is one of the safest places in the hospital to avoid COVID-19 exposure because of the air filtration/circulation in most standard ORs, the sterile field, and the fact that surgeons and anesthesiologist will be wearing PPE. Several techniques can be used to minimize the potential risk of airborne viral particles at the time of surgery via any route and specifically during laparoscopy. Performing laparoscopy with lower intra-abdominal carbon dioxide pressures and minimizing the use of energy will limit the production of surgical plume and pneumoperitoneum. In addition, the use of a smoke evacuation/filtration system allows for controlled release and filtration of the surgical plume. Ideally, gas and plume evacuation and filtration are accomplished with the use of an ultralow particulate air filter rated to screen particles of 0.1 μm in diameter (e.g., the ConMed Airseal; ConMed, Utica, NY or Stryker Pneumoclear; Stryker, Kalamazoo, MI). In contrast, high efficiency particulate air filters are only required to filter particles of 0.3 μm in diameter. N95 masks are rated to filter out at least 95% of very small (0.3 μm) particles 
 <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. Whereas smoke evacuation and filtration systems can be used both at the time of laparoscopy and laparotomy, laparoscopy offers the unique advantage of being able to almost entirely contain the surgical plume in the abdominal cavity. In conjunction with tightly fitting laparoscopic ports, an evacuation/filtration system can be used to minimize the release of potential airborne virus into the OR environment, while simultaneously evacuating the surgical smoke actively or passively. It is important to avoid a sudden release of the pneumoperitoneum. This is most relevant before tissue extraction, whether via a minilaparotomy or vaginally, and at the completion of the surgery. At these times, the abdominal cavity should be actively desufflated through a filtration system or with a simple piece of tubing attached to a suction canister, rather than releasing the pneumoperitoneum into the OR. The use of a containment bag for tissue extraction can help maintain the seal and may limit the loss of pneumoperitoneum.
</p>
