<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During an epidemic, disease prevalence increases, and the opportunities to find uninfected hosts dwindle. This may select for prudent exploitation of the remaining host population. In a previous study, we demonstrated the impact of such epidemiological feedback on the evolution of bacteriophage λ [
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Here, we use the same experimental system to study the effect of spatial structure on the evolution of bacteriophage λ. To account for latency and vertical transmission in the life cycle of bacteriophage λ, we extend previous theory on the effect of spatial structure on pathogen evolution by allowing for vertical transmission of the pathogen. Our model tries to capture all the details of the bacteriophage λ life-cycle, but for tractability we do not explicitly model the free living stage of the virus. Our central result is that the fitness of a virulent strain relative to a more prudent strain decreases as the environment becomes increasingly structured. A general insight of previous theory is that the outcome of selection on parasite life-history traits depends on the balance between the genetic and epidemiological structures of the parasite population [
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. At the genetic level, parasites infecting a cluster of hosts tend to be related when transmission occurs locally. Hence, competition for the local host supply tends to take place among related pathogens (kin competition) [
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. At the epidemiological level, local pathogen spread reduces the local density of uninfected hosts, thereby degrading the parasite's local environment and diminishing future opportunities for horizontal transmission [
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. From models without vertical transmission, it has been shown that more prudent strategies of host exploitation are selected for if the genetic structure of the parasite population is above a threshold determined by the epidemiological structure of the host population [
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. As interactions become more localized, genetic structure increases and the balance is tilted at the advantage of more prudent strains [
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. We show that vertical transmission does not alter the general theoretical expectation that spatial structure should select for more prudent host exploitation strategies. Yet our analysis reveals that in a spatially structured environment vertical transmission can affect evolutionary dynamics via two main effects. First, vertical transmission affects opportunities of horizontal transmission through a modification of the local density of susceptible hosts (the first term in 
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.e003" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (1)</xref>). Second, vertical transmission generates a force (the second term in 
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.e003" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (1)</xref>) that may counteract the effect of spatial structure. During the early stage of the epidemic this effect remains very low but further work is required to investigate the impact of the effects of vertical transmission on evolutionary stable virulence strategies. Our model is useful to decouple the change in mutant frequency in horizontally and vertically infected hosts. This distinction between different host types is artificial but it helps to grasp the interplay between spatial structure and transmission routes. As in other situations where the pathogen can appear in different states [
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] or in different hosts [
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], tracking the change in frequency between different compartments enables us to generate a prediction regarding the effect of spatial structure on the relative contribution of the two transmission routes on pathogen fitness (
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2C</xref>).
</p>
