<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The evolution of host exploitation strategies can often be explained at the level of within-host selection. For parasites competing for within-host resources, more prudent host exploitation should be selected for when the probability of multiple infections decreases [
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In our model, superinfection exclusion by a latent λ prophage guarantees that only related pathogen individuals compete within the same host cell and, hence, limits selection for increased replication and virulence at the within-host level. Similarly, many covertly infecting and genome-integrating viral pathogens take within- host competition out of the equation by active exclusion of superinfection. In herpes and retroviruses, for example, superinfection exclusion is well described and might be a key requirement for the maintenance of viral latency [
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Yet some mutations are known to enable λ to break through superinfection exclusion [
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. We did not observe such mutants in our present experiments, but we were able to extend our theory to explore the effect of spatial structure on the epidemiology and evolution of such virulence mutants that can superinfect already infected bacteria (see supporting information Theory in 
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Text</xref>). This analysis shows that mixing does affect the epidemiology and evolution in this alternative scenario: more mixing enhances the spread of the virulence mutant. Hence, this analysis suggests that the effect of spatial structure on the transient dynamics we report in the present study is robust to this modification of the life cycle. We believe that similar predictions may be feasible to understand and predict the epidemiology and evolution of a broad range of pathogens with complex transmission modes.
</p>
