<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>On the other hand, being on ARV treatment is negatively associated with NHIF enrollment. This interesting finding may be a signal of the ‘Lazarus effect’ and/or high-risk tolerance. The ‘Lazarus effect’ is a colloquial term used to refer to the marked improvement in HIV infected patients the longer they continue to take ART that subsequently improves their immunity [
 <xref rid="B75-ijerph-17-02892" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>,
 <xref rid="B76-ijerph-17-02892" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. While the reversal in frailty is welcome, it could lead to higher risk tolerance among HIV positive patients. Given the marked improvement in health, HIV positive patients might opt not to get health insurance, especially given that their access to ARV treatment is free, and the global prices of ARV have markedly declined to as low as $75 for a year’s supply of generic ARV in Africa [
 <xref rid="B77-ijerph-17-02892" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. The potential for increased access to ARV, given lower costs, is welcome, but would likely only be beneficial if adherence is high and viral suppression achieved. Otherwise, treatment failure would lead to hospitalizations associated with worse health outcomes, thus amplifying the need for health insurance. Moreover, evidence from the US shows that the use of generic HIV drugs does present barriers to desired outcomes [
 <xref rid="B78-ijerph-17-02892" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Additionally, from a health systems perspective, increasing risk tolerance among high-risk populations would not be optimal, especially if the patients are dependent on regular uninterrupted care (ART) to maintain good health. Various studies continue to show that adherence to ART is an ongoing challenge across the world [
 <xref rid="B79-ijerph-17-02892" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,
 <xref rid="B80-ijerph-17-02892" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>,
 <xref rid="B81-ijerph-17-02892" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. As such, continued engagement with the healthcare system—which is facilitated by health insurance—is going to be critical for HIV care, as well as achieving the global HIV targets of 90-90-90 [
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-17-02892" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].
</p>
