<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The epidemiology and molecular characterization of low and highly pathogenic avian influenza virus strains (LPAIV &amp; HPAIV, respectively) isolated from Germany were investigated. The complete genome analysis of the two strains showed that both LPAIV and HPAIV had high nucleotide similarity with only ten mutations outside the hemagglutinin cleavage site (HACS) which were spread along the six genome segments of the HPAIV. Of the ten mutations, five were previously identified as minor variants in the quasispecies population of the progenitor virus, LPAIV, with 18–42% significant variable frequency [
 <xref rid="B144-ijms-20-04657" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>]. However, studies focusing on the diversity of quasispecies of avian influenza in the human host are few. Watanabe et al. successfully demonstrated that infections caused by a single-virus in vitro produced an evident spectra of mutants in the H5N1 progeny viruses. Analysis of the genetic diversity of the hemagglutinin (HA) revealed that variants with mutated HA had lower thermostability leading to higher binding specificity. Both traits were deemed beneficial for viral infection. On the other hand, other variants with higher thermostability also emerged but were unable to thrive against mutants with lower thermostability [
 <xref rid="B145-ijms-20-04657" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>]. The quasispecies population of influenza A virus was also reported to be in a state of continuous genetic drift in a given subtype population. A viral single nucleotide polymorphism (vSNP) was reported to be important and was shared by more than 15% of the variants within the quasispecies population of the subtype strain in a given season. However, between the season 2010–2011, various vSNPs in the PB2, PA, HA, NP, NA, M and NS segments were shared among variants with more than 58–80% of the sample population and less than 50% of the shared vSNPs were located within the PB1 segment [
 <xref rid="B146-ijms-20-04657" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>].
</p>
