<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Many more investigations are currently ongoing to engineer alternative drug delivery devices. For instance, to promote the uptake of DNA vaccine by cells, electroporation is one of the traditional and effective strategies to enhance the uptake of plasmids.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref155">155</xref>
 </sup> Different parameters, such as electrical features (voltage, current, and frequency) and length of the electrode (intradermal or intramuscular targets), need to be optimized to ensure efficacy and safety and to minimize pain. This process has recently demonstrated promising clinical phase I results for MERS.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>
 </sup> The same electroporation device (CELLECTRA) is also being investigated for a DNA vaccine of SARS-CoV-2 from Inovio.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref156">156</xref>
 </sup> The S protein of SARS-CoV-2 encoding DNA vaccine demonstrated potent antigen-specific T cell responses and the production of neutralization antibodies in preclinical mice and guinea pigs studies.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref156">156</xref>
 </sup> In order to incorporate the advantages of MNs, electroactive MNs devices have also been developed for the electroporation of DNA vaccine in a minimally invasive manner.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref157">157</xref>
 </sup> Similar devices using iontophoresis can also enhance the transdermal delivery of vaccines.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref158">158</xref>
 </sup> Recently, Tadros 
 <italic>et al</italic>. designed millimeter-scale star-shaped particles, termed STAR particles, based on aluminum oxide for topical vaccine delivery,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref159">159</xref>
 </sup> and the minimally invasive STAR particles elicited an immune response comparable to intramuscular injection.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref159">159</xref>
 </sup> Even though STAR particles are simple to manufacture and well-tolerated by the immune system, a much higher dosage was administered compared to intramuscular injection. In addition, potential human-to-human variability in administration and drug leftovers on the skin may result in differential efficacy and undesirable toxicity.
</p>
