<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The magnitude of projected increases in 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> of 
 <italic>I. scapularis</italic> in the present study is of importance for the ecology and epidemiology of vector-borne diseases in general. This was illustrated by 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> ranges estimated for other globally important parasites and pathogens associated with variations in known key determinants of their ecology and epidemiology (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>). These ranges were of a similar magnitude to projected increases in 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> of 
 <italic>I. scapularis</italic> with climate change. Tick species are likely to respond to the central tendency of increasing temperatures due to 
 <italic>a</italic>) the long periods of inter-stadial development that take place in the surface layers of the soil where fluctuating air temperature are buffered, 
 <italic>b</italic>) latency in responses of development rates to temperature changes minimizing effects of very short-term temperature fluctuations (
 <xref rid="r65" ref-type="bibr">Ogden et al. 2004</xref>), 
 <italic>c</italic>) their ability to return to soil-level refugia during extremes of heat, cold, drought, or rainfall while host seeking, 
 <italic>d</italic>) their associations with woodland habitats within which a microclimate is buffered from extremes of temperature occurring in treeless areas (
 <xref rid="r40" ref-type="bibr">Lindsay et al. 1999b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="r51" ref-type="bibr">Morecroft et al. 1998</xref>), and 
 <italic>e</italic>) ticks have no nonparasitic immature feeding stages whose survival is susceptible to short-term changes in weather as do dipteran vectors such as mosquitoes. Therefore, the increases in 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> projected here represent a possible magnitude of increase in mean 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> values arthropod vectors may experience with climate change. Around this mean, dipteran population 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> may fluctuate seasonally and annually over a much wider range due to the rapid effects of rainfall and temperature on reproduction and mortality rates. Abundance and geographic distributions of many mosquito-borne diseases are currently driven primarily by control efforts that superimpose on any climate effects. Large increases in vector 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> may, however, render current vector and vector-borne disease control methods ineffective as vector multiplication outstrips control efforts (
 <xref rid="r44" ref-type="bibr">Massad, 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="r79" ref-type="bibr">Reithinger et al. 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="r85" ref-type="bibr">Smith et al. 2007</xref>).
</p>
