<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para260">We developed and used the PIA model, a novel application of Bayesian latent class analysis that integrates the case and control data across multiple specimens and tests, resulting in an estimate of the aetiology distribution for each individual case and for the population of cases.
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> This method assumes that infections at body sites peripheral to the lung are indicative of the cause of the putative lung infection and that measurements are independent of one another. This method was tested with use of simulated datasets comprising cases with known aetiology who had a mix of measurements that varied in their sensitivity and specificity, which were prespecified, and it was shown to give accurate estimates of the aetiological fraction, even under mild violations of the independence assumption.
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref> The PIA model uses a Markov Chain Monte Carlo algorithm that, on convergence, samples from the posterior distribution of the aetiology estimates, given the observed measurements (
 <xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">appendix</xref>). The population-level estimate for each pathogen is the average of the individual case probabilities and has a 95% credible interval (95% CrI), the Bayesian analogue of the confidence interval. Sensitivity analyses were done to assess the influence of the values used for aetiology and sensitivity priors (
 <xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">appendix</xref>). To allow for the possibility that the pneumonia event was caused by a pathogen not tested for, we included a pathogen category termed not otherwise specified (NOS). Cases who had negative tests for all pathogens or positive results only in measurements with poor specificity had a higher individual-level probability to be included in NOS category than other cases.
</p>
