<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para280">As a Bayesian analysis, we assigned a-priori estimates for both the aetiology distribution and the sensitivity of each laboratory measurement. These estimates quantify the preceding uncertainty about the model parameters. The a-priori aetiology distribution favoured no pathogen over another (uninformed) because we wanted to estimate the causes using the evidence in the PERCH study alone. The a-priori sensitivity distribution, selected by an internal working group using available information external to the PERCH study, varied by laboratory test method and pathogen (
 <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">appendix</xref>). We classified specimens according to their estimated measurement error as either bronze (ie, imperfect sensitivity and specificity) or silver standard (ie, imperfect sensitivity, but 100% specificity); no test was categorised as gold standard (ie, 100% sensitivity and specificity; 
 <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>, a-priori estimates of measurement-specific sensitivity are detailed in the 
 <xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">appendix</xref>).
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref> Measurements designated as silver standard were those of blood cultures, of cultures or PCR of percutaneous lung aspirate and pleural fluid specimens, and of 
 <italic>M tuberculosis</italic> cultures of induced sputum (or gastric aspirate). PCR results from the NP-OP swab and whole blood (
 <italic>S pneumoniae</italic> alone) specimens were included as bronze standard measurements, with controls providing the data to estimate specificity. We reduced the sensitivity for detecting bacterial pathogens in NP-OP PCR (
 <italic>S pneumoniae</italic> and 
 <italic>H influenzae</italic> only) and blood culture specimens for individuals whose specimens were collected after documented antibiotic exposure and for blood culture specimens with low blood volume (
 <xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">appendix</xref>).
</p>
