<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus and middle east respiratory syndrome coronavirus have previously been studied in non-human primates (
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>–
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>); the use of these models has been proposed for the study of SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>) especially with a view to the development of vaccines or antiviral treatments (
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>). Rockx et al. (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>) used a combined intratracheal and intranasal route to inoculate the SARS-CoV-2 virus to both young and old adult cynomolgus macaques (
 <italic>Macaca fascicularis</italic>). The results of this study showed that these animals tolerated viral infection, presenting symptoms similar to those of COVID-19 in humans. The virus efficiently replicates in epithelial cells throughout the upper respiratory tract, which correlates with the ease of transmission of the virus, whereas replication in the lower respiratory tract correlates with the development of the disease (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>–
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>). Yu et al. (
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>) obtained similar results with intratracheal inoculation of young and old rhesus monkeys (
 <italic>Macaca mulatta</italic>). The authors report that, although viral replication was more active in older adult monkeys, both groups developed interstitial pneumonia together with edema, which was more severe and diffuse in older adult monkeys. Munster et al. (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>) developed a COVID-19 model using rhesus monkeys, inoculating them with the virus through four different but combined routes (intranasal, intratracheal, conjunctival, and oral). The animals presented clinical signs compatible with COVID-19 from day 1 after the inoculation to symptom resolution, between days 9 and 17. All animals presented weight loss, low-grade fever, and pulmonary infiltrates, in addition to a significant increase in IL-6 and IL-10, among other findings; IgG antibodies were present at detectable levels from day 7 after the infection. Nasal, pharyngeal, and rectal samples showed high levels of viral RNA. Furthermore, histopathological analyses showed similar alterations to those caused by SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV (
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>). Deng et al. (
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>) inoculated rhesus monkeys with SARS-CoV-2 through the conjunctival route. They did not observe significant changes in the animals’ weight or body temperature. Antibody analyses detected presence of IgG at days 14 and 21. Furthermore, radiographs of these animals showed bilateral alterations in the upper lobes and right lower lobe, which correlates with the moderate interstitial pneumonia observed microscopically. Histopathological studies showed viral load in the ocular and nasolacrimal system, as well as in the respiratory and digestive tracts. Results of a comparative study of three non-human primate species [rhesus monkey, crab-eating macaque, and common marmoset (
 <italic>Callithrix jacchus</italic>)], which were inoculated with the virus through three different pathways (intratracheal, intranasal, and conjunctival), showed that almost all animals presented clinical signs compatible with COVID-19, although there were differences between species in the histopathological findings (
 <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>). The rhesus monkey is the most susceptible species to viral infection, and therefore a good model for the study of COVID-19, as well as for the development of vaccines and pharmacological studies (
 <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>). De Wit et al. (
 <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>) studied rhesus monkeys intratracheally inoculated with the virus, finding that viral RNA was detectable in the throat during the first days, but with levels subsequently decreasing until becoming undetectable. Bao et al. (
 <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>) and Chandrashekar et al. (
 <xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>) intratracheally and intranasally inoculated rhesus monkeys with the SARS-CoV-2 virus to study the possibility of reinfection. Williamson et al. (
 <xref rid="B113" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>) used rhesus monkeys that had previously been inoculated through the intranasal, oral, ocular, and intratracheal routes for pharmacological research. These animals have also been used for the development of vaccines (
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B114" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B115" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>).
</p>
