<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>India continues to portray a concentrated epidemic. The HIV prevalence among high-risk groups, i.e. FSW, PWID, MSM and TG is about 20 times higher than the general population
 <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>. A recent study conducted in 2013 among PWID from 15 cities showed that estimated HIV prevalence and incidence were 18.1 and 2.9 per cent, respectively
 <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>. Sex work continues to be the most important source of HIV infection in India. The estimated HIV prevalence among MSM ranges between 7 and 16.5 per cent
 <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>. HIV prevalence was characterized among MSM in eight cities from Tamil Nadu where 34 per cent were married and 40 per cent self-identified as homosexual. HIV prevalence was nine per cent, higher among married men (14%)
 <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>. A recent study conducted among MSM across India confirms a relatively high HIV prevalence of seven per cent and a low HIV incidence of 0.87 per cent (0-2.2%)
 <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>. MSM who reported injection drug use were 6.7 times more likely to be HIV-infected. Heterosexual anal sex was reported by 11.9 per cent FSW in four high prevalence States in India
 <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>. A meta-analysis of studies from developed countries has shown that the probability of HIV transmission is higher per act of receptive anal sex (1.7%) as compared to peno-vaginal sex (0.8%)
 <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>. Individuals with acute HIV infection have 8- to 26-fold greater risk for transmitting HIV compared to those with chronic infection because of their high viral load
 <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> while they may remain undiagnosed by routine antibody tests. Phylogenetic clustering of new HIV infections in MSM supports acute HIV infection as one of the main drivers of ongoing HIV transmission in MSM in rising and ongoing HIV epidemics.
</p>
