<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Apart from being the source of DENV inactivators, other regions of E protein can also be potential targets. A previous study reported the existence of a hydrophobic pocket between domain I and II, which acted as a hinge of the E protein structural rearrangement and could interact with the detergent β-
 <italic>N</italic>-octyl-glucoside (
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">Modis et al., 2003</xref>). By molecular docking analysis, 
 <xref rid="B114" ref-type="bibr">Panya et al. (2014)</xref> identified several short peptides targeting the hydrophobic pocket. They found that the dipeptide Glu-Phe (EF for short) could inhibit the infection of all four DENV serotypes, but it was the most effective against DENV-2 with an IC50 value of 96 μM. Different inhibitory effect for the four serotypes of DENV was possible because of the different amino acid sequence of their hydrophobic pockets. Inferred from its mechanism of action, EF peptide can be considered as a DENV inactivator, as potentially confirmed by performing a virus inactivation assay. In addition, the lateral loop of domain III has been verified to play an important role in virus-cell receptor interaction, thus making it another feasible target of protein- and peptide-based DENV inactivators (
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">Hung et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">Mazumder et al., 2007</xref>). Using the BioMoDroid algorithm, 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Alhoot et al. (2013)</xref> screened for anti-DENV peptides targeting a short sequence (residues 380–389) in the lateral loop of DENV-2 E protein domain III. They found that peptides DET2 and DET4 could inhibit DENV-2 infection with IC50 values of 500 and 35 μM, respectively. Observed with transmission electron microscopy, the surface of virions was found to become irregular and have rough edges, suggesting that these peptides could inactivate virions by disrupting integrity of the viral envelope.
</p>
