<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0075">Scientists from Ellington’s group did plenty of work to both improve the specificity of LAMP detection and make readout simpler and more reliable. They replaced the intercalating dye typically used for monitoring in real-time fluorescence with a toehold-mediated strand exchange reaction termed one-step strand displacement (OSD) and applied it for real-time sequence-specific verification of LAMP amplicons [
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>]. The resulting assays could detect 0.02 to 0.2 PFU (5–50 PFU/mL) of MERS-CoV in infected cell culture supernatants within 30–50 min and did not cross-react with common human respiratory pathogens [
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Other strand exchange signal transductions were developed to make LAMP reaction user-friendly. As shown in 
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, by combining LAMP with a thermostable invertase, Du et al. can directly transduce MERS coronavirus templates into glucose signals, which can be easily read by a commercial glucometer, with a sensitivity as low as 20–100 copies/μL, equating to atto-molar (or low zepto-mole) [
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) was also used as the signal as its analyte was already sensitively detected by commercial pregnancy test kits. The hCG was site-specifically conjugated to a DNA oligonucleotide, thereby allowing signal transduction via strand exchange into both capture (signal-off) and release (signal-on) of hCG in the LAMP based virus assay [
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The incorporation of an engineered hCG reporter protein led to LAMP-to-hCG signal transduction on low-cost, commercially available pregnancy test strips. This assay reliably detected as few as 20 copies of virus templates in both human serum and saliva.
</p>
