<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>However, it is fundamentally important to understand how a molecule becomes a drug molecule. Idea of lock and its key is the mechanism behind understanding the concept. When a molecule can optimally bind to the active site of a diseased receptor protein or enzyme to trigger or inhibit its biological response, it has the potential to become a drug molecule for that disease. This concept is also the basis of the idea of pharmacophore in drug discovery. By definition a pharmacophore is “an ensemble of steric and electronic features that are necessary for optimal interaction with a specific receptor target structure (a protein or an enzyme) to trigger or inhibit its biological response” [
 <xref rid="B88-pharmaceuticals-12-00157" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. Therefore, stereoelectronic properties of a potential drug molecule must optimally interact with the corresponding properties at the active site of the diseased receptor molecule (protein or enzyme) to trigger or inhibit the specific biological response. Study of stereoelectronic properties of bioactive molecules should therefor provide valuable information in understanding this intrinsic “interaction pharmacophore” necessary in order to discover a drug molecule for a disease [
 <xref rid="B89-pharmaceuticals-12-00157" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. For accurate estimate of stereoelectronic properties, quantum chemical (QM) methods are the best possible choices despite being more time consuming. The stereoelectronic profiles generated from the property calculations of molecules are known as the “interaction pharmacophores”. Although no anti-Zika drug is currently available, several promising ZIKV drug targets have been reported in recent years [
 <xref rid="B90-pharmaceuticals-12-00157" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. These targets with compounds have shown potent activity against ZIKV and its proteins. Non-structural (NS) flavivirus proteins are believed to play important roles in both replication and virion maturation [
 <xref rid="B91-pharmaceuticals-12-00157" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. Crystallographic structures of several ZIKV related NS proteins are now available from protein structural data banks [
 <xref rid="B92-pharmaceuticals-12-00157" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. The NS proteins from the data bank are primarily useful for performing computational studies and are also important for experimental studies. These proteins include NS1, NS2B–NS3 protease, NS3 helicase, NS5 methyltransferase, NS5 polymerase, NS5 full-protein and envelope glycoprotein. Importantly, three of these NS proteins, NS2B–NS3 protease, NS3 helicase, and NS5 methyltransferase are available with ligands, ATP and RNA in the data bank. Thus, both identification of ligand-binding-site for virtual screening and pharmacophore modeling for discovery of potential anti-Zika drugs have been highly facilitated. Pharmacophore models significantly contributed to the discovery of drugs in the past years for retrieving inhibitors against various drug targets [
 <xref rid="B85-pharmaceuticals-12-00157" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>].
</p>
