<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The 
 <italic>Filoviridae</italic>, of which 
 <italic>Ebolavirus</italic> is a constituent genus, belong to the order 
 <italic>Mononegavirales</italic>. Two other genera complete the family: 
 <italic>Marburgvirus</italic>, itself responsible for a number of outbreaks of haemorrhagic fever across Africa (
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Gear et al., 1975</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Conrad et al., 1978</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib118" ref-type="bibr">Smith et al., 1982</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib125" ref-type="bibr">Towner et al., 2006</xref>) and 
 <italic>Cuevavirus</italic>, recently isolated from bats in northern Spain (
 <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">Negredo et al., 2011</xref>). Five species of 
 <italic>Ebolavirus</italic> have been isolated to date (
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">Kuhn et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">King et al., 2012</xref>); the earliest recognised outbreaks of EVD were reported in Zaire (now the Democratic Republic of the Congo [DRC]) and Sudan in 1976 (
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">International Commission, 1978</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib145" ref-type="bibr">WHO International Study Team, 1978</xref>). The causative viruses were isolated (
 <xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr">Pattyn et al., 1977</xref>) and later identified to be distinct species, 
 <italic>Zaire ebolavirus</italic> (EBOV) and 
 <italic>Sudan ebolavirus</italic> (SUDV). A third species of 
 <italic>Ebolavirus</italic>, 
 <italic>Reston ebolavirus</italic>, was isolated from Cynomologus monkeys imported from the Philippines to a facility in the United States, where they experienced severe haemorrhaging (
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Jahrling et al., 1990</xref>). Whilst serological evidence of infection with this species has been reported in individuals in the Philippines (
 <xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">Miranda et al., 1991</xref>), no pathogenicity has been reported beyond primates and porcids (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Barrette et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Feldmann and Geisbert, 2011</xref>). In 1994 a fourth species, 
 <italic>Tai Forest ebolavirus</italic> was isolated from a veterinarian who had autopsied a chimpanzee in Côte d’Ivoire (
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">Le Guenno et al., 1995</xref>), though the virus has not been detected subsequently. The final species, 
 <italic>Bundibugyo ebolavirus</italic>, was responsible for an outbreak of EVD in Uganda in 2007 (
 <xref rid="bib126" ref-type="bibr">Towner et al., 2008</xref>), as well as a more recent outbreak in the DRC (
 <xref rid="bib142" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2012b</xref>).
</p>
