<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This study also observed higher case fatality among Blacks/AA relative to Whites. Previous studies in the flu pandemic of 1918 and 2009 clearly implicated the socially disadvantaged individuals and populations in survival disadvantage following infectivity [
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-17-04322" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The case fatality is a 
 <italic>proportion of those who died as a result of an exposure, divided by all the exposed cohort as the population at risk for mortality, multiplied by 100</italic> in a proportion and not a rate, and reflects viral symptom severity and poor prognosis from COVID-19. The excess case fatality among Blacks/AA is explained in part by the higher prevalence of chronic diseases, namely hypertension and other cardiovascular diseases, diabetes and cancer, as well as aberrant epigenomic modulation in COVID-19 prognosis and mortality. AA/Blacks are more likely, compared to their White counterparts, to be diagnosed with type II diabetes, primary or essential hypertension, stroke and cancer [
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-17-04322" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and have higher mortality from these conditions [
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-17-04322" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The higher incidence of these conditions among Blacks/AA had been associated with a lack of access to healthcare as well as decreased healthcare utilization due to several obstacles and barriers [
 <xref rid="B19-ijerph-17-04322" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Secondly, the social determinants of health which reflect the needed resources to benefit from optimal health is not equitably available for Blacks/AA. These determinants are characterized by the social gradient upon which the socially disadvantaged individuals or populations are less likely to benefit from early education, quality education through college and a good paying job. The social determinants of health, namely education, socio-economic status, income, employment, food security, racism, safe environment, insurance, transportation, and living conditions, adversely impacts the outcome of morbidity and mortality in Black/AA populations in the US [
 <xref rid="B33-ijerph-17-04322" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].
</p>
