<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An FDA-approved immunosuppressive and anti-malarial parasite drug (chloroquine) can inhibit the entry of COVID-19 into the endosome after binding to ACE-2 receptors, thereby preventing the release of 
 <sup>+</sup>ssRNA for translation.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr89-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr93-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr95-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr96-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>
 </sup> Studies also showed that hydroxychloroquine, an analog of chloroquine, was more potent and could be used in place of chloroquine.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr97-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>
 </sup> Remdesivir, a novel antiviral drug and nucleotide analog used to treat Ebola virus infection, is currently under clinical development. The mechanism of the drug is reported to be at the post viral entry stage.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr89-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>
 </sup> Its mode of action is to inhibit the RdRp, preventing synthesis of the viral 
 <sup>+</sup>ssRNA (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0300060520949077">Figure 11</xref> (2)). This drug is currently in phase 2 clinical trials. The protein inhibitor ritonavir has also been proposed for the treatment of COVID-19. This drug interferes with the protease enzymes (proteinases) by inhibiting the conversion of polyproteins into the mature components (spike proteins, nucleocapsids) needed by the virus for multiplication (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0300060520949077">Figure 11</xref> (3)). Another immunosuppressive drug, tocilizumab, has also been repurposed for COVID-19 because of its ability to block IL-6 and inhibit inflammatory responses. Corticosteroids can also decrease inflammation by inhibiting phospholipases such as phospholipase A
 <sub>2</sub>, and thus suppress the excessive production of prostaglandins (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig11-0300060520949077">Figure 11</xref> (4)).
</p>
