<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Studies of the antiviral activity of host-directed drugs and compounds have identified two classes of molecules (protein biogenesis inhibitors and ligands of the Sigma1 and Sigma2 receptors) as effective inhibitors of viral infectivity. Molecules that target the Sigma1 and Sigma2 receptors perturb the virus through different mechanisms from translation inhibitors, potentially including modulation of cellular stress responses.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr99-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>
 </sup> The ligands haloperidol, PB28, PD-144418, and hydroxychloroquine are currently undergoing clinical trials in COVID-19 patients.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr100-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>
 </sup> These molecules exert their antiviral effects during viral replication by inhibiting nucleoprotein expression after viral entry has occurred. The lack of selectivity of chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine, including off-target effects on the human Ether-à-go-go-Related Gene (hERG) and other molecules, may be related to the adverse cardiac reactions that have limited their use.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr101-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>
 </sup> A recent study by Gordon 
 <italic>et al</italic> identified 332 high-confidence SARS-CoV-2-human protein interactions connected to multiple biological processes, including protein trafficking, translation, transcription and ubiquitination regulation.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr102-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>
 </sup> The study identified 69 ligands, including FDA approved drugs, compounds in clinical trials, and preclinical compounds that might theoretically have therapeutic effects as host-directed interventions against COVID-19. To date, no known antiviral drugs nor vaccines against SARS-CoV-2 with proven clinical efficacy have been identified. Part of the reason for the absence of such agents is limited information regarding the molecular details of the infection. To develop therapeutic interventions against COVID-19, it is crucial to understand how the virus interactions with the host during infection.
</p>
