<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">At present, the pathogenic mechanism of SARS-CoV-2 is still little studied, and its transmission route and transmission mode are also greatly uncertain due to virus mutation and other factors. Epidemiological data show that SARS-CoV-2 has a strong infectious capacity and is highly infectious. The known transmission route is mainly based on the history of the infected person, and the sample of SARS-CoV-2 can be detected to make a guess. The presence of SARS-CoV-2 was found in nasopharyngeal swab specimens of the infected person, and the cases of cluster infection all suggested that airborne droplet transmission was the possible main transmission route [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. Confined space, poor ventilation and so on are important causes of cluster infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. To this end, on January 23, 2020, the Chinese government imposed a “city closure” on Wuhan and travel restrictions on other cities to minimize unnecessary crowds. Currently, disseminated by respiratory droplets and direct contact is clear, a study collected in different regions of the hospital air SARS-CoV-2 testing, found in the region of the medical staff and room toilet space existing in the small area is relatively high concentrations of the virus nucleic acid, but whether these aerosol form of the virus has spread ability is not yet clear, these need to pay attention to the prevention and control of hospital [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. SARS-CoV-2 RNA was also detected in blood samples from infected patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. The real-time fluoresence quantitative PCR showed that the PCR cycle threshold was 35.1, indicating that there was a low concentration of viral nucleic acid in the blood samples, and blood transmission might also be a potential transmission route of SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. It also increases the difficulty of blood donation in blood centers and blood banks. The high expression of ACE2 receptor in the gastrointestinal tract indicates that SARS-CoV-2 can use ACE2 receptor in the gastrointestinal tract to enter the human body, so the fecal-oral pathway may be a potential transmission route of SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. It is reported that the Chinese center for disease control and prevention isolated the SARS-CoV-2 strain from stool samples from a confirmed patient in Heilongjiang Province, indicating that SARS-CoV-2 could survive in feces. A similar study found low levels of SARS-CoV-2 in the feces of some infected children [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. In addition, the government of Paris detected a novel coronavirus in a non-potable water system and an active novel coronavirus in sewage in Massachusetts, USA. These studies have shown that a novel coronavirus can survive in water and be transmitted using water. Therefore, if the water is infected by the virus, even with the current stringent control measures, there is still a high risk of human infection. A newborn born during the outbreak at a local children’s hospital in Wuhan was reported to have been diagnosed with SARS-CoV-2 infection 30 h after birth, and it was considered that SARS-CoV-2 might also cause an epidemic through vertical transmission [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. However, another study did not find the presence of SARS-CoV-2 in the samples of amniotic fluid, breast milk and other body fluids of 9 pregnant women infected with SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. The newborns were not infected, and no evidence of vertical transmission of pregnancy was found, possibly due to the small sample size. For health workers, the possibility of vertical transmission still exists and needs to be taken seriously in the process of disease control [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. In addition, there have been reports of infection in laboratory specimens, and human conjunctival epithelium is susceptible to infection by infectious aerosols [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>].
</p>
