<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The dramatic appearance and spread of West Nile virus (WNV; family 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic>; genus 
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic>) in Northern America is a disquieting reminder of the capacity of arboviruses to establish and cause devastating public health and veterinary impacts in locations with serologically naïve populations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1-ijerph-10-03735">1</xref>]. Despite its presence in the United States for over 13 years, widespread outbreaks of WNV can still occur, as evidenced by epidemic activity in 2012 that resulted in 2,873 cases of neuroinvasive disease and 286 deaths [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2-ijerph-10-03735">2</xref>]. Consequently, there has been much concern regarding the potential introduction and establishment of exotic strains of WNV in Australia, and the subsequent impacts upon human and animal health [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3-ijerph-10-03735">3</xref>]. The establishment of arboviruses in new areas is certainly possible if efficient vectors, suitable vertebrate amplifying hosts and a suitable overwintering mechanism are available [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4-ijerph-10-03735">4</xref>]. A range of other factors could influence potential WNV transmission in Australia, including the mode of introduction, the potential role of native fauna in transmission, suitability of the Australian climate for virus transmission, and virological factors, such as the attributes of the strain/genotype introduced and the presence of closely-related endemic arboviruses. Herein, we examine the interaction of factors that could influence the potential introduction and establishment of an exotic strain of WNV in Australia and discuss this possibility in the context of the circulation of the endemic Australian WNV Kunjin strain (WNV
 <sub>KUN</sub>). We suggest the most likely candidate species for urban transmission and present factors that would influence their roles in transmission. We conclude that given the presence of potential mosquito vectors, urban Australia could be at risk of the importation and establishment of a more pathogenic strain of WNV. 
</p>
