<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The establishment of global health targets, intended for adoption at the national level, seeks to focus the attention of funders, implementers and national-level policy-makers. Setting of targets or goals has occurred in global health since the late 1950s with the global Smallpox Eradication Programme, but has become increasingly commonplace, spanning multiple health issues, as evidenced by the Millennium Development Goals and subsequent Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs) (United Nations; 
 <xref rid="czx132-B26" ref-type="bibr">Shiffman and Smith 2007</xref>). The HIV response alone has had numerous, arguably ambitious, targets: ‘3 by 5’ to treat three million people living with HIV (PLHIV) by 2005; ‘15 by 15’ to treat 15 million PLHIV by 2015; ‘getting to zero’ for zero new HIV infections, zero AIDS-related deaths and zero discrimination by 2015 (
 <xref rid="czx132-B45" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="czx132-B39" ref-type="bibr">UNAIDS 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="czx132-B41" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). In 2014, the Joint United Nations Programme on HIV/AIDS (UNAIDS) set the ‘90–90–90’ targets that operationalize what countries need to do, and what programme coverage targets need to be attained at certain time points, to achieve the policy goal of ending the AIDS epidemic by 2030, as advocated for in the SDGs (
 <xref rid="czx132-B40" ref-type="bibr">UNAIDS 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="czx132-B30" ref-type="bibr">Stover 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2016
 </xref>) (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="czx132-T6">Box 1</xref>). The 90–90–90 targets differ from previous targets, such as 3 by 5; rather than being set arbitrarily, mathematical modelling has accompanied the 90–90–90 targets, utilized to derive the programme coverage levels and estimate the resource needs for achieving the policy goal of ending the AIDS epidemic by 2030 (
 <xref rid="czx132-B30" ref-type="bibr">Stover 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2016
 </xref>). Similar strategies have been developed using modelling for the epidemics of malaria and tuberculosis (TB) (
 <xref rid="czx132-B29" ref-type="bibr">Stop TB Partnership 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="czx132-B46" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization 2015</xref>). 
</p>
