<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0055">Arboviruses transmitted by mosquitoes have been expanding their global distribution in recent years, and new viruses, such as chikungunya and Zika, have emerged and spread globally [
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. This expansion is thought to be attributed to a combination of increased urbanization, global travel, and environmental changes associated with increasing temperatures and changing precipitation patterns [
 <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. That the latter of these is driving arbovirus expansion is not unexpected: mosquitos are ectotherms that depend upon water sources to complete their life cycles, so temperature, precipitation, and humidity play critical roles in the mosquito-vectored arbovirus transmission cycle [
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Global surface temperatures have increased by 0.8–1.2°C above pre-industrial levels, and precipitation data show uncharacteristically extreme variations in rainfall [
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Because of this, the global landscape of mosquito-borne arboviruses is being transformed as suitability for mosquito populations and the viruses they transmit changes. Autochthonous transmission of mosquito-borne arboviruses is occurring more frequently in subtropical and temperate regions, occurring at higher elevations in tropical regions, and becoming increasingly more intense in endemic regions, leading to larger outbreaks [
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">8
  <sup>••</sup>
 </xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">10
  <sup>••</sup>
 </xref>]. In the present work, we investigate recent emergence and expansion of arboviruses transmitted by the anthropophilic mosquito species 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> (and in some case the secondary vector 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic>) as a case study for environmentally driven arboviral expansion. We first describe known relationships among meteorological variables, mosquitoes, and arboviruses. We next describe the ongoing global expansion of dengue as it relates to climate and discuss the novel outbreaks of chikungunya and Zika virus that began in 2013 and 2015, respectively. We discuss recent arbovirus activity in the temperate Argentinian city of Córdoba, where the emergence of dengue began in 2009 and has been ongoing. Finally, we review recent work aimed at better understanding the impacts of climate and changes thereof on present and future arbovirus activity and highlight gaps in empirical and modeling studies that could help us better understand the future of arbovirus transmission under a changing climate.
</p>
