<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Perkins et al (2013) identify three salient complexities of mosquito-borne transmission systems essential to account for in order to understand the epidemic potential in a group of houses: (1) some people are exposed to more bites than others, (2) mosquitoes and hosts do not completely overlap in their spatial distributions (“poor mixing”) and (3) the density of susceptible hosts is finite [
 <xref rid="pone.0144451.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0144451.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Multiple physiological and behavioral mechanisms may give rise to these complexities, many of which are not fully understood. Nonetheless, our ABM incorporates specific processes of human and 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> ecology that previous studies suggest contribute to these features of dengue transmission in a group of houses. Heterogeneous exposure (Perkins’ feature 1) in the dengue system is driven by the fact that residents are more likely be exposed to 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> bites than visitors[
 <xref rid="pone.0144451.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], even though house-to-house visits between residents of dengue endemic cities are sufficiently frequent to play a role in transmission dynamics[
 <xref rid="pone.0144451.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. In our model residents have on average 5 times the likelihood of visitors to be bitten a mosquito in a particular house, consistent with previous models [
 <xref rid="pone.0144451.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Poor mixing in dengue is driven by the overwhelmingly consistent finding that most 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> emerge in only a few houses which change over time [
 <xref rid="pone.0144451.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0144451.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0144451.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], a pattern that strongly influences transmission dynamics in a two-block patch [
 <xref rid="pone.0144451.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Our model readily incorporates this feature by using house-to-house pupal counts from two-block patches collected over 2.5 years in the La Fachada neighborhood to parameterize the house of each emergent host-seeking 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic>. This feature, which can significantly affect transmission dynamics [
 <xref rid="pone.0144451.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], sets our model apart from other simulations that assume mosquito recruitment to be spatially random, in equilibrium, aggregated over larger spatial scales or do not explicitly simulate mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="pone.0144451.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0144451.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0144451.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0144451.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0144451.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. We incorporate Perkins’ third feature, finite host density, by modeling the counteracting forces that together determine susceptible dynamics in an area that has experienced prior epidemics: susceptible recruitment (birth, death and immigration of non-immunes) and viral introduction through either susceptible resident infection by external vector populations (not within the simulatation area) or infectious visitor transmitting to local 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> populations. We focused analysis on exploring how the processes generating Perkins’ features 2 and 3 combine to influence daily dengue dynamics, mainly because of their strong potential to vary over time and at small spatial scales such as the block or neighborhood. Sensitivity analyses (see supplement) also considered interactions between Perkins’ features 1 and 3.
</p>
