<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Infection with pathogens can occur not only through direct (host-host) transmission, but also through indirect (host-environment-host) transmission (
 <xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Guan &amp; Holley, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr">Seymour &amp; Appleton, 2001</xref>). Indirect transmission is highly dependent on the ability of a pathogen to survive outside of the host (
 <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Heaton &amp; Jones, 2008</xref>). Some pathogens can persist for months (
 <xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Nicholson, Groves &amp; Chambers, 2005</xref>) or even years outside of the host, and thereby pose a threat of infection through contact with the pathogen-contaminated environment (
 <xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Kramer, Schwebke &amp; Kampf, 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Murray et al., 2016</xref>). In most wildlife, the role of environmental contamination and the resulting possible indirect transmission of pathogens are little studied, often because suitable non-invasive methods have not been developed (
 <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Hudson et al., 2002</xref>). Yet as shown by various modelling approaches, neglecting sources of indirect transmission can lead to considerably less accurate predictions of pathogen persistence, outbreak probability, outbreak duration (
 <xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">Rohani et al., 2009</xref>) and of the need for management efforts (
 <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Lange, Kramer-Schadt &amp; Thulke, 2016</xref>). This is particularly concerning as many emerging diseases causing epidemics in humans originate in wildlife (
 <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Daszak, Cunningham &amp; Hyatt, 2000</xref>), as demonstrated most recently in a novel coronavirus strain (
 <xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2020</xref>). Studies on suitable methodology and thus field data on detection of pathogens at potential fomites, such as nesting sites or feeding stations, could provide improved disease surveillance and hygiene protocols in species recovery programs.
</p>
