<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0115">The equilibrated model of the immDENV:pr (pH = 8) complex was subsequently used as a starting point for TMD simulations, to explore the molecular pathway towards the intermediate-mature structure solved at pH = 5 (
 <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>B). The initial RMSD between the ectodomain backbone in the initial versus target structures was ~5 nm. Initially, all E protein chains were simultaneously biased towards the target structure, but this led to significant clashes between E protein trimers (blue) and pentamers (red) (
 <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>B). Thus, we instead applied a sequential series of biases to the E proteins; this involved first biasing all chains between RMSD values from 5 to 3.5 nm along the pathway, followed by a bias of the blue and green chains only between RMSD values from ~3.5 to 2.5 nm, and finally a bias of all chains from ~2.5 nm RMSD until the end of the simulation (
 <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>C). These simulations revealed that the neighbouring blue E protein molecule was approached by the pr:red-E protein complexes, dislodging the pr molecule from the 5-fold symmetry axes; based on additional modelling studies, this was predicted to be accelerated in the presence of bound antibodies due to clashes between Fab domains. This extent of pr binding site occlusion on the red E protein was not observed for the blue or green molecules (
 <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>C). Similar conclusions were drawn when running TMD simulations in which biases were instead applied independent either to red (5-fold), blue (3-fold), or green (2-fold) E protein molecules alone. These results matched nicely with cryo-EM data, and combined with co-floatation assays and HDX-MS measurements, this study indicates that pr:Fab complexes dissociate as a complex from DENV E proteins due to steric clashes, thereby facilitating maturation and infectivity 
 <xref rid="b0325" ref-type="bibr">[65]</xref>.
</p>
