<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We generated infectious disease outbreaks with within-host pathogen evolution under various mutation rates and bottleneck sizes by simulation, using the R (R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria) package Seedy (
 <xref rid="kwx182C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). In contrast to other simulation approaches, this method explicitly simulates within-host evolution and allows sampling of mixed pathogen populations across time. We expanded upon methods previously used to infer transmission routes using deep sequence data (
 <xref rid="kwx182C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>–
 <xref rid="kwx182C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), comparing their performance with analogous genetic distance–based approaches. We additionally proposed hybrid approaches that combine SV information with phylogenetic distance data. We considered the following approaches: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>Weighted variant tree: For each host, we weighted potential sources by the number of observed SVs, such that the host sharing the largest number of variants is attributed the largest weight. Hosts sharing no variants with any other were not assigned a source. Weighting edges provided an extension to previous approaches (
    <xref rid="kwx182C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>–
    <xref rid="kwx182C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Maximum variant tree: For each host, we defined the source to be the individual with whom the largest number of SVs was observed. Hosts sharing no variants with any other host were not assigned a source.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Weighted distance tree: Using consensus sequences, the genetic distance (number of single nucleotide polymorphisms) between isolates was calculated, and potential sources were weighted inversely by this metric. This approach has been described previously (
    <xref rid="kwx182C3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Minimum distance tree: Using consensus sequences, the source of a given host was defined to be the carrier of the genetically closest isolate to that of the host. This approach, with the incorporation of sampling times to provide directionality, has been described previously (
    <xref rid="kwx182C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Hybrid weighted tree: First, the weighted variant tree was constructed. Hosts with no source were then assigned potential sources based upon weighted genetic distance.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Hybrid maximum tree: First, the maximum variant tree was constructed. Hosts with no source were then assigned potential sources based upon minimum genetic distance.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
