<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We used this approach to design serotype-specific primers aiming to match all possible DENV strains circulating worldwide, by considering 2,056 available GenBank DENV sequences (2004–2014). This is the greatest difference compared to other previously published RT-LAMP assay designs in which primer design focused on the conserved 3’ UTR, NS1 or C-prM regions but detailed limited information about the DENV sequences used to develop the primers. As the LAMP primers were designed from different clusters of each DENV serotype obtained after PCA and phylogenetic analyses, the individual LAMP amplicons locate to several regions across the DENV genome conserved in these clusters (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0006381.g001">Fig 1</xref>). This allows an overall detection of DENV variability surpassing any other molecular amplification assay. The final amplicons were selected through a combination of 
 <italic>in silico</italic> primer dimer formation assessment (Visual OMP) and 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> assessment by checking amplicons selected in the first step for unspecific amplification in the NTC. A similar methodology has been used to design RT-LAMP primers to detect Chikungunya virus (manuscript submitted to PLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases) and we consider this approach would be suitable for the assay development of other infectious diseases. The final DENV1-4 specific RT-LAMP assays contained 84, 72, 48 and 18 oligonucleotides respectively. The challenge was to find a working concentration of these oligonucleotide mixes, which would allow for sensitive detection. A 2-fold dilution series approach for the individual final primer mix allowed to identify a working concentration window in the dynamic range of these assays. This however came at the cost of run time. In order to increase the reaction speed without losing sensitivity, several combinations of enzymes were tested. We tested the combination of AMV RT (Promega, Southampton, UK) and GspSSD DNA polymerase (Optigene) recommended by others who successfully developed rapid RT-LAMP assays with 10–15 minute run times [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006381.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] (Manuguerra personal communication). We also tested 
 <italic>Bst</italic> 3.0 DNA polymerase (New England BioLabs), but found that none offered an advantage over the enzyme combination we used (Transcriptor Reverse Transcriptase and 
 <italic>Bst</italic> 2.0). As a matter of fact, we saw an increased level of unspecific amplification with 
 <italic>Bst</italic> 3.0 DNA polymerase (data non-shown).
</p>
