<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cardiomyopathies are frequent in cats and their diagnosis relies on a combination of physical examination, thoracic radiography, electrocardiography and echocardiography. Additionally, in the last decade, assays to measure circulating biomarkers of heart disease, such as cardiac troponin I and N‐terminal pro‐brain natriuretic peptide (NT‐proBNP), have become available for cats. These assays have been proven useful in the diagnosis of feline cardiomyopathies, although in certain cases they may be less reliable. Therefore, the aim of this study was to detect new circulating proteins that may improve the identification of cats affected by cardiomyopathy using biomarker discovery. Client‐owned cats were prospectively enrolled. Evaluation comprised complete blood count and biochemical profile with T4 determination, blood pressure measurement, thoracic radiography and echocardiography. Based on diagnosis, cats were allocated to 5 groups, namely symptomatic cardiomyopathy with signs of congestive heart failure (group CM‐Sx), asymptomatic cardiomyopathy (group CM‐aSx), respiratory diseases (group Resp‐Ds), systemic diseases without systemic hypertension (group Sys‐Ds), and healthy controls (group Healthy). Plasma samples were processed untreated or following enrichment in low‐abundant proteins, submitted to mass spectrometry and their protein profiles compared with statistical software. Putative biomarkers were evaluated by western immunoblotting experiments. Eighty‐nine cats were included; 9 in CM‐Sx, 9 in CM‐aSx, 14 in Resp‐Ds, 30 in Sys‐Ds and 27 in Healthy. In CM‐Sx, 7/9 cats had hypertrophic cardiomyopathy and 2/9 restrictive cardiomyopathy; lung edema was identified in 7, pleural effusion and aortic thromboembolism in 2. In CM‐aSx, all cats had hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. By mass spectrometry, several differential proteins were identified among groups. Putative biomarkers were tested by western immunoblotting and 2 of them (Protein 1 and Protein 2), were differentially detected in CM‐Sx, compared to the others. In particular, Protein 1 was identified in 6/9 (66.7%) cats in CM‐Sx, while plasma samples from cats in CM‐aSx, Resp‐Ds, Sys‐Ds and Healthy had a visible band in 2/9 (22.2%), 2/14 (14.3%), 1/30 (3.3%) and 1/27 (3.7%), respectively (P &lt; 0.001). Protein 2 was detected in the plasma of 4/9 (44.4%) cats in CM‐Sx, 1/9 (11.1%) in CM‐aSx and 1/30 (3.3%) in Sys‐Ds, while no bands were detected in Resp‐Ds and Healthy (
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.005). These data suggest 2 novel putative biomarkers for differentiating cats with symptomatic cardiomyopathy. Further studies with a higher number of cardiomyopathic cats and different symptomatic status are mandatory to optimize the tests and evaluate sensitivity and specificity of the candidate biomarkers.
</p>
