<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par33">An emerging exciting field of disease surveillance is infectious disease modeling and incorporation of artificial intelligence. Notably, these are 
 <italic>predictive techniques</italic> applicable to each of the three facets of disease surveillance (Siettos and Russo 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2013</xref>). A classical epidemiological surveillance parameter is quantitation of 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> (
 <italic>R</italic> nought, basic reproductive number) using mathematical models (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://wwwnc.cdc.gov/eid/article/25/1/17-1901_article" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://wwwnc.cdc.gov/eid/article/25/1/17-1901_article</ext-link>). 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> is a crucial metric indicating that on average the number of new infection cases are generated by a confirmed infection case, i.e., the potential transmissibility of an infectious disease. 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> of COVID-19 infection is estimated as 2–3.5 in the early phase, as even the asymptomatic patients or with mild pneumonia extruded large amounts of virus (Wang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2020</xref>). Important characteristics of 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> are:
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par34">It is a dynamic number and changes with
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par35">Each stage of the disease</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par36">With interventions, e.g., vaccination, antivirals</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par37">Precautionary measures such as personal/community disinfection, social distancing, and travel restrictions</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par38">With the knowledge of 
    <italic>R</italic>
    <sub>0</sub>, one can predict:
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par39">New cases expected on a daily basis, and hence facilitate arrangement of healthcare services and interventions locally</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par40">Outbreak size and the dates of peak infection of the pandemic</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par41">Probable decline timeline</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par42">The extent of vaccination coverage required to prevent future outbreaks</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par43">An 
    <italic>R</italic>
    <sub>0</sub> &gt; 1 indicates that each infected individual is transmitting the disease to more than 1 new individual, and the infection is spreading increasingly. 
    <italic>R</italic>
    <sub>0</sub> = 1 indicates stable transmission and 
    <italic>R</italic>
    <sub>0</sub> &lt; 1 indicates the decline in disease transmission (Fig. 
    <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">14.1</xref>). The aim of pandemic action plans is to monitor and depreciate the 
    <italic>R</italic>
    <sub>0.</sub>
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list> 
</p>
