<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par50">The application of artificial intelligence (AI) in close conjunction with technology in pandemic surveillance has demonstrated manifold advantages in surveillance activities as exemplified by China and other severely hit nations during the present COVID-19 outbreak. AI, data analytics, and technological support amalgamated to facilitate:
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par51">
    <italic>Track and forecast community outbreaks</italic>:
   </p>
   <p id="Par52">BlueDot is a Canadian AI company using natural language processing and machine learning algorithms to monitor news outlets, worldwide official healthcare reports in several different languages, and air-travel data and flag the mention of contagious or novel diseases such as coronavirus. Importantly this is followed by scrutiny by epidemiologists and thus also has a component of human analytics. BlueDot alerted its clients to the potential outbreak in Wuhan, China, on December 30, 2019, 9 days prior to the WHO recognized it as an epidemic (
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bluedot.global/products/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://bluedot.global/products/</ext-link>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par53">
    <italic>Disease diagnosis and verification of infected individuals</italic>:
   </p>
   <p id="Par54">Chest computed tomography (CT) scans have been endorsed as a primary diagnostic tool for COVID-19 (Ai et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2020</xref>). Ali-baba group’s research academy has developed a deep-learning AI-enabled system that can diagnose COVID-19 in 20 s with 96% accuracy and hence possibly automate the diagnosis activity in the face of overburdened healthcare systems. The AI system identifies an infectious individual based on the chest CT scans. The algorithm has been trained with data and CT scans from nearly 5000 confirmed coronavirus cases from across China. It can be used to track the efficacy of treatment during the course of infection as well as rapidly diagnose COVID-19 (
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.alizila.com/how-damo-academys-ai-system-detects-coronavirus-cases/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.alizila.com/how-damo-academys-ai-system-detects-coronavirus-cases/</ext-link>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par55">
    <italic>Implementing public hygiene guidelines</italic>:
   </p>
   <p id="Par56">Risk communication in places of potential communication is critical to alert the public and implement mass hygiene measures such as use of sanitizers and face masks when in public places. Google Trends was used in Taiwan to monitor the public risk awareness following the first imported case of COVID-19 which correlated with the increased search keywords “COVID-19” and “face masks.” Moreover, search for “handwashing” increased coinciding with the face mask shortage. High to moderate correlations between Google relative search volume and COVID-19 cases were evident in several major cities of Taiwan (Husnayain et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2020</xref>). Similarly, in China an AI-based company SenseTime has developed a “Smart AI Epidemic Prevention Solutions”—a quick and effective system based on facial recognition and thermal imaging to screen for individuals with fever in a crowd without physical contact and hence preventing transmission. It can also monitor if any individual is wearing a face mask or violating the quarantine rules (
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.sensetime.com/en/news/view/id/140.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.sensetime.com/en/news/view/id/140.html</ext-link>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par57">
    <italic>Contact tracing</italic>:
   </p>
   <p id="Par58">Health Code, a Chinese government monitoring system, for which users can sign up through Alipay or WeChat, assigns individuals a color code (red—14 days self-quarantine/yellow—7 days self-quarantine/green—free movement) based on their travel history, time spent in outbreak hotspots and exposure to potential carriers of the virus. The software can be used to check the color of an individual on entering their identity numbers.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par59">
    <italic>Characterization of the CoV-2 and vaccine/therapy development</italic>:
   </p>
   <p id="Par60">The Genome Detective Coronavirus Typing Tool is a web-based, user-friendly software application that can identify the novel severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS)-related coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) sequences isolated in the original outbreak in China and later around the world. The tool accepts 2000 sequences per submission, analyzing them in approximately 1 min. This tool facilitates tracking of new viral mutations as the outbreak expands globally, which may help to accelerate the development of novel diagnostics, drugs, and vaccines to stop the COVID-19 disease (Cleemput et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2020</xref>).
   </p>
   <p id="Par61">Google’s AI platform DeepMind-based protein structure prediction tool AlphaFold has predicted and released the 3D structures of several understudied proteins of the CoV-2 as an open source. These can be useful in designing antivirals/vaccines against COVID-19 in future outbreaks (Jumper et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2020</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
