<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Reovirus-based monotherapy has been conducted for solid tumors including soft-tissue sarcomas, melanoma, breast cancer and head and neck cancer [
 <xref rid="B145-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>]. One study included 18 patients and was mainly designed to verify the safety and tolerability of reovirus intralesional administration [
 <xref rid="B146-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>]. Monitoring was done over a period of six weeks. The toxic effects were measured according to the criteria of the National Cancer Institute Clinical Trials Group. The tumor responses were measured using the Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors. After the trial period of six weeks, one patient showed complete response (CR), two demonstrated partial responses (PRs), four patients had stable disease (SD) and ten showed progressive disease (PD) [
 <xref rid="B146-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>]. However, the results indicated that intralesional reovirus monotherapy was safe, well tolerated and did not reach dose-limiting toxicity. Local administration of reovirus in phase I/II malignant melanoma studies was as well tolerated as monotherapy [
 <xref rid="B147-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>,
 <xref rid="B148-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>]. Intravenous reovirus monotherapy was applied in a malignant melanoma phase II trial in 21 patients receiving a 3 × 10
 <sup>10</sup> 50% tissue-culture infective dose (TCID50) once every 60 min on days 1–5 every four weeks [
 <xref rid="B73-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Clinical benefits as CR or PR were monitored for eight weeks. One patient demonstrated extensive tumor necrosis (75%–90%) in two metastatic lesions after two treatment cycles, whereas no other patient met the criteria for CR or PR [
 <xref rid="B119-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. Moreover, reovirus was detected in two out of 13 biopsies containing melanoma metastases. The findings from the phase II trial further support the positive clinical outcome obtained from phase I studies [
 <xref rid="B149-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>,
 <xref rid="B150-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>]. Furthermore, 2 out of 13 patients showed productive reoviral replication in melanoma metastases. Unfortunately, the trial could not progress as initially planned, as the clinical objective of having two or more patients reaching CR or PR was not achieved. According to these results, the phase II trial did not support the application of reovirus as a monotherapy for metastatic melanoma, but rather as part of a combination therapy with other therapeutic or chemotherapeutic agents [
 <xref rid="B146-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>]. 
</p>
