<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Flaviviruses are arthropod-borne viruses that plague both tropic and sub-tropic regions. These viruses belong to the family 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic> and genus 
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic>. There are slightly over 70 species of flaviviruses that have been discovered so far [
 <xref rid="B1-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Of these, roughly half are mosquito-borne, including the heavily studied: yellow fever (YFV), West Nile (WNV), dengue (DENV), Japanese encephalitis (JEV), and Zika (ZIKV) viruses, which will be the focus of this review [
 <xref rid="B2-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. These viruses appear to affect tropic and sub-tropic regions but pose a serious global health risk due to geographic expansion of mosquito vectors [
 <xref rid="B3-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].Only a small subset of infections result in symptoms, ranging from mild fever to hemorrhagic fever or encephalitis to potentially death. The 2015–2016 outbreak of ZIKV in South America was also associated with microcephaly in infants and the development of Guillain-Barre syndrome in adults [
 <xref rid="B2-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. There are only a few Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approved vaccines for humans currently available for a few mosquito-borne flaviviruses (namely YFV, JEV, and DENV). However, the DENV vaccine has shown limited efficacy against all DENV serotypes [
 <xref rid="B7-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] and resulted in injury to children in the Philippines, causing safety concerns [
 <xref rid="B9-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Even with developments in the design of safe and efficacious vaccines, there are unfortunately no anti-viral treatments clinically available for infected individuals. As the features of the life cycle appear to be conserved across flaviviruses, there has been much work done to identify pan-flaviviral anti-viral targets and to engineer drugs to halt pathogenesis at various stages [
 <xref rid="B1-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Thus, it is important to work towards a greater understanding of the molecular mechanisms throughout the viral life cycle.
</p>
