<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A number of traits, such as shifts in social structure, inbreeding tolerance, and adaptability to human-disturbed habitats, are disproportionally presented in invasive ants [
 <xref rid="B1-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Among these traits, supercolonies—where workers work in physically separated colonies, and exhibit limited aggression towards each other but maintain high aggression to those from other supercolonies—are believed to be associated with the ecological success of a subset of invasive ants such as the Argentine ant (
 <italic>Linepithema humile</italic> [Mayr]), the big-headed ant (
 <italic>Pheidole megacephala</italic> [Fabricius]), and the yellow crazy ant (
 <italic>Anoplolepis gracilipes</italic> [Jerdon]) [
 <xref rid="B4-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, the absence of visible intercolonial boundaries may also facilitate the transmission of pathogens among colonies in the same supercolony, causing supercolony-wide epidemics if no disinfection mechanisms exist or the pathogen, with limited fitness, costs to their host [
 <xref rid="B7-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The “vulnerable supercolony hypothesis” was proposed by Ugelvig and Cremer [
 <xref rid="B8-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] and has been empirically tested by Tragust et al. In [
 <xref rid="B7-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], supercolony structure was shown to be more susceptible to fungal infections due to the high frequency of intercolonial interactions in the invasive garden ant, 
 <italic>Lasius neglectus</italic>. Furthermore, such a pattern is likely more profound for viral pathogens because viruses are generally more readily transmitted horizontally than other pathogen groups [
 <xref rid="B9-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Consequently, one would predict that a population comprised of mutually tolerant colonies likely has a higher level of viral prevalence as a result of intensive intercolonial interactions, while variations of prevalence should be registered in a population with mixed supercolonial groups (i.e., aggression is only observed when workers are from different supercolonies). To assess such transmission dynamics, a critical step is to understand if intercolonial interactions serve as a potential transmission pathway of a given virus.
</p>
