<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although many drugs have been reported to show promising results against SARS-CoV-2, none of these drugs have gained much attention like the antimalarial drugs Chloroquine (CQ) and Hydroxychloroquine (HCQ) [
 <xref rid="B14-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. HCQ is a CQ analog that has the same mechanism of action with a safer profile making it the prioritized drug to treat malaria, viruses, and autoimmune conditions [
 <xref rid="B51-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. There are several potential molecular mechanisms of HCQ action against SARS-CoV-2 that have been postulated. Generally, HCQ is a weak base drug that accumulates in the cell acidic compartments such as lysosomes and endosomes. This accumulation increases the pH and inhibits the maturation of these endosomal compartments. Therefore, HCQ might be interfering with the endocytosis of SARS-CoV-2 and subsequently affecting the virus entry and exit from the host cell [
 <xref rid="B7-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Moreover, HCQ might reduce glycosylation of ACE2, interfering with SARS-CoV-2 to bind effectively to the host cell [
 <xref rid="B51-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. On the other hand, a recent publication hypothesizes that HCQ reduces the production of pro-inflammatory cytokines (such as interleukin-6, IFN-alpha, and TNF), thereby inhibiting various immune pathways that might lead to acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) [
 <xref rid="B52-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Currently, the use of hydroxychloroquine is approved by many of COVID-19 treatment protocols, especially in combination with other antibiotics and antiviral drugs, where others seriously considering it [
 <xref rid="B1-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].
</p>
