<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0085">The SARS-CoV-2 like other beta-coronaviruses undergoes a few steps to enter into and affect the host cell. SARS-CoV-2 binds to same ACE2 receptor present in the respiratory epithelium and alveoli of the lungs (
 <xref rid="bb0470" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2020a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0475" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2020b</xref>). In SARS-CoV, upon binding to the receptor, proteases are recruited to cleave the S protein into S1 and S2 domains. This cleavage induces a conformational change that activates S2, this is followed by the insertion of the FP into the membrane and membrane fusion occurs facilitating the entry of the virus into the cell. Since the nucleotides are conserved in RBD binding motif that is associated with ACE2, it is possible that SARS-CoV-2 utilizes the same mechanism as well. Once the virus enters the cell, ACE2 gets cleaved and shed by ADAM17 into the extra membrane space. Reduced ACE2 has been known to be concomitant with alveoli injury and increases pulmonary vascular permeability (
 <xref rid="bb0435" ref-type="bibr">Li and Clercq, 2020</xref>). This could be due to the conversion of angiotensin I to angiotensin II by ACE2, which is a negative regulator of the renin-angiotensin pathway. Angiotensin II stimulated ATIR results in the lung pathology associated with respiratory distress (
 <xref rid="bb0435" ref-type="bibr">Li and Clercq, 2020</xref>). Once the virus translates its proteins in the cell, the ORF3a protein is produced and codes for a Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> ion channel that is similar to SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2. It interacts with TRAF3 and activates the transcription of the NF-kB pathway, resulting in the transcription of the pro-IL-1B gene (
 <xref rid="bb0710" ref-type="bibr">Siu et al., 2019</xref>), ORF3a along with TRAF3 also recruits the inflammasome complex. This complex consists of NLRP3, ASC and caspase 1. A second signal such as Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> influx, caspases activation, ROS production and mitochondrial damage converts pro-IL-1B to IL-B and results in cytokine production. Another, ORF8b protein also activates the inflammasome pathway through NLRP3, and this protein is longer in SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="bb0685" ref-type="bibr">Shi et al., 2019</xref>). The extra nucleotides present in this virus need to be further studied to figure out if that has caused an added advantage. The E protein forming an ion channel, is also conserved in the two viruses and is involved in the overproduction of cytokines through the NLRP3 inflammasome pathway (
 <xref rid="bb0575" ref-type="bibr">Nieto-Torres et al., 2015</xref>). All these pathways combined together cause a cytokine storm resulting in respiratory distress a common symptom of COVID-19. Another pathway involved in SARS-CoV includes the JNK pathway; which is activated by ORF3a, ORF3b and ORF7a which may lead to an increased production of pro-inflammatory factors, escalating lung damage (
 <xref rid="bb0465" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2014</xref>). The JNK pathway can also be considered as a target for SARS-CoV-2 as it also involves the proteins that are analogous in both viruses.
</p>
