<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The Hepatitis B virus is an enveloped virus with a circular and partially double-stranded DNA that belongs to the 
 <italic>Hepadnaviridae</italic> family (Group VII). HBV includes several viruses that infect liver cells and cause hepatitis in humans and animals. In the viral genome, the large negative stranded DNA encodes the envelope, core and non-structural proteins, the DNA polymerase and an oncogenic transactivator [
 <xref rid="B156-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>,
 <xref rid="B157-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>]. The synthesis of the short strand is completed by cellular DNA polymerases after infection. There are 8 HBV strains, from A to H that differ from their geographic repartition [
 <xref rid="B156-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>,
 <xref rid="B157-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>]. Worldwide, between 2 and 8% of the population is infected by HBV but in most of the cases being asymptomatic. An acute HBV infection is however characterized by yellow eyes and skin, severe fatigue, vomiting and abdominal pain. In less than 5% of the cases, the infected people could develop a chronic infection which can further lead to a cirrhosis (in 20% of the cases) [
 <xref rid="B156-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>,
 <xref rid="B157-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>]. Several studies showed an association link between plasma selenium levels and progression of HBV infection [
 <xref rid="B158-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>,
 <xref rid="B159-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>,
 <xref rid="B160-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>]. For example, the selenium level is not correlated with the responsiveness to interferon treatment [
 <xref rid="B161-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>] but an elevated plasma selenium concentration is associated with a low level of transaminases [
 <xref rid="B161-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>]. Theses hepatic enzymes are implicated in amino acid catabolism, and their release in the plasma is linked to hepatocellular damage. In intervention studies, selenium supplementation decreased cancer incidence in HBV infected patients [
 <xref rid="B162-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>], but when the supplementation was stopped, the incidence became similar to control patients. Finally, 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>, when hepatic cell lines were grown with different selenium concentration, lower viral proteins, viral transcripts and viral genomic DNA were detected with high selenium culture conditions [
 <xref rid="B161-nutrients-11-02101" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>].
</p>
