<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Total microbial activity (active fungi, bacteria, and protists present) of the surface organic material samples were analyzed at each site [
 <xref rid="pone.0232481.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Before analysis, 2 g samples were prepared and stored in 50 ml centrifuge tubes in a refrigerator (at 4°C). Fluorescein diacetate (FDA) hydrolysis [
 <xref rid="pone.0232481.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] was performed using methods outlined by Adam and Duncan [
 <xref rid="pone.0232481.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], as modified by Zabaloy et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0232481.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The 2 g soil sample was mixed with a 200 ml, 60 mM sodium phosphate buffer, at a pH of 7.6, in a 50 ml plastic centrifuge tube. Then 0.2 ml of the 2 mg/ml FDA stock solution was added [
 <xref rid="pone.0232481.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The FDA stock solution was prepared by adding 200 mg FDA to 100 ml acetone and stored at -20°C until it was used to determine the microbial activity. The 50 ml tubes containing the samples were incubated for 20 minutes at 28°C in a Labcon growth chamber (Air &amp; Vacuum Technologies, South Africa). During the incubation period, the tubes were shaken manually three times. After the incubation period, the tubes were placed on a Multi Reax shaker (Heidolph, Germany) at 300 rpm for 10 minutes at room temperature. To end the hydrolysis reaction, 15 ml of a 2:1 chloroform methanol solution was added. Approximately 1.5 ml of the supernatant was then placed in an Eppendorf tube (Hamburg, Germany) and centrifuged at 200 rpm for 3 minutes. An aliquot was subsequently placed in a microtiter plate and absorbance measurements were taken at 490 nm. For each sample, two controls were also prepared. The first control consisted of 2 g of sample and the phosphate buffer, without any FDA stock solution added. The second control contained the phosphate buffer and FDA stock solution without any sample.
</p>
