<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Most physicians who are actively involved in WNV clinical research now accept a poliomyelitis to be the most common cause of WNV-associated acute flaccid paralysis. Patients with WNV poliomyelitis commonly have associated signs of meningitis, encephalitis, or respiratory distress from involvement of spinal motor neurons supplying the phrenic nerves to the diaphragm, however acute flaccid paralysis also may occur in the absence of fever or meningoencephalitis [
 <xref rid="B24-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Moreover, cases of WNV-poliomyelitis frequently occur in the absence of acute flaccid paralysis, since the current CDC classification recognizes only the most severe cases associated with flaccid paralysis and fails to include poliomyelitis cases with lesser degrees of motor neuron loss that do not produce profound flaccid weakness (Leis, personal observation). Prognosis for recovery of function is dependent on the degree of motor neuron loss; limbs with absent motor responses on nerve conduction studies and no voluntary muscle activation on needle electromyogram (EMG) have a poorer long-term prognosis, while those with relatively preserved motor responses and some voluntary activity have a more favorable outcome [
 <xref rid="B25-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Although the anterior horns are the major site of spinal cord pathology, autopsy series show that pathologic changes may not be limited to spinal cord gray matter. Focal inflammatory changes may extend into the adjacent white matter, which may explain the infrequent occurrence of WNV-associated transverse myelitis with clinical involvement of spinal sensory and motor pathways [
 <xref rid="B29-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. In addition, neuronophagia, neuronal disappearance, and pathologic alterations have been described in dorsal root ganglia and sympathetic ganglia [
 <xref rid="B29-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The involvement of dorsal root ganglia may explain some of the sensory deficits and reduced sensory nerve action potentials on electrodiagnostic testing that occasionally are reported in patients with WNV infection [
 <xref rid="B24-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. However, sensory loss attributed to WNV has not been a prominent clinical finding.
</p>
