<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0040">Another question that is increasingly being asked in the medical community is whether SARS-CoV-2 is transmissible by the fecal-oral route.
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> The above studies did not test for RNA of the virus in the stool, so correlation cannot be made between digestive symptoms and active viral RNA replication in the digestive tract. However, a case report of a 25-year-old female who presented with respiratory symptoms and fever suggested that the virus could be excreted in feces.
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref> Ten days after the initial presentation, she underwent real-time PCR of a pharyngeal sample that was negative for SARS-CoV-2, but a separate fecal sample was positive. Over the following 7 days she had 4 additional samples from the respiratory tract, all of which were negative for SARS-CoV-2. This suggests that her only documented source of virus was in the gastrointestinal tract, and thus may have been transmitted via the fecal-oral route, although this is not proven. In addition, the first case of COVID-19 in the United States presented with a 2-day history of nausea and vomiting along with a dry cough and passed a loose bowel movement on hospital day 2.
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref> The stool and respiratory specimens later tested positive for SARS-CoV-2 again highlighting the possibility for viral shedding and potentially transmission in the stool. Interestingly, in a recent Singaporean study, 50% of patients with COVID-19 had SARS-CoV-2 detected in their stool samples, but detection of this did not correlate with digestive symptoms.
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref> The duration of viral RNA after recovery was examined in a recent study.
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref> In this study, the median time from the onset of symptoms to first negative RT-PCR test from oropharyngeal swab was 9.5 (6.0–11.0) days, but 16.7% (11/67) patients tested positive for viral RNA from stool specimens for a median of 11.0 (9.0–16.0) days after symptom onset. In addition, the duration of viral RNA in the stool was longer (20 days vs. 11 days, p &lt; 0.0001) in those who received glucocorticoid treatment compared non-glucocorticoid group. These observation merit further examination since there is a potential, although unproven, for fecal-oral transmission risk for many days after clinical recovery.
</p>
