<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>From June 1987 to May of 1988, CeMV infected both inshore and estuarine 
 <italic>T. truncatus</italic>, starting from New Jersey and, eventually, reaching Florida [
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B92-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>,
 <xref rid="B148-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>]. This mass mortality was associated with the stranding of at least 645 
 <italic>T. truncatus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B148-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>]. DMV infection was also detected in a 
 <italic>S. coeruleoalba</italic>, indicating that multiple species were affected during that outbreak [
 <xref rid="B92-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. Starting in July 2013, another outbreak affected these populations along the Atlantic coast from New York through northern Florida and is currently ongoing [
 <xref rid="B71-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Over 1500 
 <italic>T. truncatus</italic> have died and the majority of the individuals tested by RT-PCR have been positive for DMV [
 <xref rid="B71-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,
 <xref rid="B130-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>]. Contacts between inshore 
 <italic>T. truncatus</italic> and offshore species (offshore 
 <italic>T. truncatus</italic>, 
 <italic>Globicephala</italic> sp., 
 <italic>S. coeruleoalba</italic>, 
 <italic>L. hosei</italic>, and false killer whales (
 <italic>Pseudorca crassidens</italic>)) in which CeMV is endemic [
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] may have been the sources of infection for the 1987–88 and 2013–2014 outbreaks. Seasonal overlap between resident coastal 
 <italic>T. truncatus</italic> stocks at certain times of the year, and migration of the coastal migratory stock, may have favored transmission of the disease down the coast [
 <xref rid="B149-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>]. A serological survey performed on samples collected from live capture-released coastal and estuarine 
 <italic>T. truncatus</italic> along the east coast of the US in 1999–2004 indicated that the seroprevalence decreased over the years of the study, suggesting that CeMV did not persist as an endemic infection in these populations, as had been predicted [
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Therefore, population immunity likely continued to decrease over time leading to increased numbers of susceptible individuals and resulting in the 2013–2014 epidemic. The role of environmental and anthropogenic factors in this mortality and the population impacts is being investigated [
 <xref rid="B71-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>].
</p>
