<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Indeed, it is not easy to establish a small animal model for research purposes. An ideal animal model for human viral disease should closely recapitulate the spectrum of clinical symptoms and pathogenesis seen during the course of human infection. Moreover, a perfect animal model should meet other criteria, viz., maximum permissibility to the pathogens, nil resistance to the pathogens, subservience to the same human pathogenic strain, and having the route of infection similar to the human condition. Fulfilling the “Animal rule” of the US Food and Drug Administration [
 <xref rid="B130-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>] is essential for approval and optimally characterized animal models are critical. This rule suits conditions where vaccines and therapeutics cannot be tested safely or ethically on humans; in these cases, approval is possible only after preclinical tests are conducted on animal models. Research in many fields in virology is focussing on standardized models that meet the institutional requirements to evaluate the efficacy of vaccines and therapeutics. In this manuscript, we have summarized available mouse models, such as knockout mice, transgenic mice, and humanized mice models, for HIV-1, influenza, and dengue viruses, and discussed their applications in research. The characters of an ideal animal model cannot always be fulfilled. Since viruses frequently change, mice models need to be changed accordingly, otherwise the natural course of infection will not be accurately mirrored in the animal model. Humanized mice, (CD34+-HSC transplanted immunodeficient mice and BLT mice, NSG, NRG, NOD-SCID) are great models, allowing researchers to recapitulate the key aspects of viral pathogenesis in humans by recreating functional human immune systems in mice. Humanized mouse models are serving as important research tools to experimentally characterize human viral diseases and immune responses. Though humanized mice have advantages over other mouse models, the limitations include: (i) Mouse-to-mouse species variation during the development of a humanized mouse is frequently observed, leading to difficulties in interpreting the results at the end of the experiment; (ii) development of the molecules and cells is not complete in mouse–human chimeric models, and this incompleteness may interrupt the interactions between the cells; (iii) the mechanism of viral pathogenesis is also differently regulated in humanized mice, for example, with regard to B-cell maturation, antibody production, and the coagulation cascade, which are not regulated in the same way [
 <xref rid="B44-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B130-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>,
 <xref rid="B131-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>,
 <xref rid="B132-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>,
 <xref rid="B133-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>]; (iv) drawbacks include the substantial cost and limited supply and handling of animals in comparison to other models. Despite these limitations, recent developments involving transgenic humanized mice expressing different human genes regulating cellular development are also being attempted [
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Moreover, in traditional KO and Tg mice models, the resulting phenotype due to the knocked out gene or transgenes is expressed during embryonic development itself, and disease onset in these mice models might occur earlier than in humans. To tackle this issue, researchers have developed mice models that can be made to express transgenes when needed using the Cre/lox site specific recombination system. This method provides the opportunity to control gene expression in time and space. These mouse strains express the Cre recombinase enzyme under the control of a promoter that can be induced by drugs such as tetracycline or doxycycline. Then, Cre can activate the expression of transgenes that are flanked by Lox P sites [
 <xref rid="B133-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>,
 <xref rid="B134-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>,
 <xref rid="B135-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>]. Such conditional KO and Tg mice are available for studying cancer and need to be developed for studying viral diseases. With recent advances in genomics, complete information about the mouse genome will serve as an important resource for developing new mice models that will help to completely understand the disease pathogenesis mechanisms and might lead to the discovery of novel therapeutic interventions and prophylactic approaches.
</p>
