<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For naturally immunizing infections, investigators sometimes restrict enrollment in a trial to those who have not previously been infected to ensure that trial participants are truly at risk of becoming infected; this is especially relevant when selecting individuals thought to be at high risk for infection. However, selecting participants who both have risk factors for infection and are uninfected at enrollment may be problematic. First, it means that all potential participants must be tested for evidence of prior infection. Second, individuals who have remained uninfected despite many opportunities for exposure may be more resistant to infection (or have lower-risk exposures) than is typical in the general population [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002632.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Serodiscordant couples, for example, may tend to be those who practice safer sex or for whom the infected partner is less infectious than in other couples. Likewise, healthcare workers who remain uninfected despite apparent intense exposure may be ones who practice excellent personal protection. In the early stages of the recent Ebola epidemic, health workers were identified as a group with particularly high incidence (and a good population for a vaccine trial), but when the high incidence was recognized, personal protective measures against infection were rapidly implemented, leading to a dramatic decline in their risk of infection. Failure to account for such factors may lead to overestimating the likely infection rate during the trial [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002632.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Moreover, if the vaccine is differentially effective in different populations, such as because of the intensity of exposure, then the effect estimate from such a trial may be different than it would be for the general population [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002632.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>–
 <xref rid="pmed.1002632.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].
</p>
