<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Povidone iodine is an example of an iodophor, which is a mixture of elemental iodine and a carrier polymer‐ polyvinylpyrrolidone in this case. The carrier polymer has no virucidal activity on its own.
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0096" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>96</sup>
 </xref> Iodine, the active and powerfully‐virucidal agent, exists as a complex mixture of many species (e.g. I
 <sub>2</sub>, I
 <sup>−</sup>, I
 <sub>3</sub>
 <sup>−</sup>, IO
 <sup>−</sup>, IO
 <sub>3</sub>
 <sup>−</sup>) at equilibrium in water, but aqueous iodine solutions can be cytotoxic and cause irritancy.
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0097" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>97</sup>
 </xref> Hence, the polyvinylpyrrolidone polymer entraps the various iodine‐containing species by hydrogen bonding (Figure 
 <xref rid="viw216-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>), providing a reservoir of iodine for its sustained release in small doses at a time, maintaining its virucidal properties for prolonged periods while decreasing toxicity. Povidone‐iodine is a broad‐spectrum virucidal agent manufactured in formulations containing 7.5‐10% iodophor in solution, and are used in clinical applications such as sterilizing agents for pre‐ and post‐operation skin cleaning, in surgical swabs, scrubs and ointments, as well as everyday products including antiseptic handwashes, mouthwashes and gargles that contain lower concentrations of the iodophor.
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0098" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>98</sup>
 </xref> Povidone‐iodine is not suitable for use with silicone products such as silicone catheters as iodine can cause accelerated deterioration of the material.
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0099" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>99</sup>
 </xref> The iodophor is capable of inactivating (≥ 4.0 reduction of log
 <sub>10</sub> viral infectivity) a large range of viruses which include the enveloped coronaviruses, influenza A
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0100" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>100</sup>
 </xref> and vaccinia virus, as well as non‐enveloped polyomavirus and adenovirus
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0101" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>101</sup>
 </xref> within 1 minute (Table 
 <xref rid="viw216-tbl-0003" ref-type="table">3</xref>). For the most‐resistant non‐enveloped polioviruses however, aqueous formulations of povidone‐iodine (Betaisodona ® solution, containing 11% available iodine), required at least an hour for reduction of infectivity of ≥ 4.0log
 <sub>10</sub> units. In contrast, alcohol‐containing povidone‐iodine formulations (e.g., Betaseptic Mundipharma®, containing 10% available iodine and ca. 40% 2‐propanol and 40% ethanol) could inactivate these polioviruses within 5 min,
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0101" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>101</sup>
 </xref> owing to the synergistic virucidal activity of the iodophor and the alcohols. Although it is generally safe and more effective in inactivating viruses than many other antiseptic agents (e.g., benzalkonium chloride, chlorhexidine digluconate),
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0102" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>102</sup>
 </xref> povidone‐iodine may cause thyroid dysfunction with long‐term prolonged use,
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0103" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>103</sup>
 </xref> as well as allergic contact dermatitis,
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0104" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>104</sup>
 </xref> necessitating careful medical monitoring.
</p>
