<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par55">One virus-targeted approach under investigation is passive antibody therapy. This approach involves the infusion of sera from convalescent patients into infected patients with the aim of transferring neutralizing SARS-CoV-2 antibodies to patients with active disease
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR258">258</xref>
 </sup>. To date, little is known about the efficacy of this treatment as most data are derived from uncontrolled case studies of patients with COVID-19. All case reports of patients with severe COVID-19 have described a rapid improvement in clinical symptoms over the course of 3 days, with resorption of lung lesions within a week, as revealed by radiological examination
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR259">259</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR261">261</xref>
 </sup>. A small clinical trial of six critically ill patients with COVID-19 treated with convalescent plasma reported elimination of SARS-CoV-2 RNA within 3 days of therapeutic plasma infusion, although the mortality of these patients did not differ from that of 15 patients who received placebo
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR262">262</xref>
 </sup>. Moreover, a larger randomized clinical trial of 103 patients with COVID-19 (ref.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR263">263</xref>
 </sup>), as well as a preprint report from India
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR264">264</xref>
 </sup>, showed no significant clinical improvements after convalescent plasma therapy. Future studies should focus on developing approaches to isolating SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibodies from convalescent plasma, which may increase the efficacy of this treatment. In addition, two important factors mentioned earlier need to be taken into consideration when performing plasma collection. First, if protective neutralizing antibodies are short-lived, plasma should be collected early after recovery from COVID-19. Second, patients with more severe disease have higher antibody levels than patients with asymptomatic or mild disease; however, the extent of protection provided by antibodies in patients with severe disease is unclear, and it might therefore be counterproductive to select plasma donors based only on antibody levels. As an alternative approach, a number of neutralizing human monoclonal antibodies have been developed, some of which are entering phase I clinical trials
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR265">265</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR270">270</xref>
 </sup>. If successful, such an approach would avoid the limitations and the time-consuming procedures required to obtain plasma or to purify polyclonal antibodies from convalescent patients.
</p>
