<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We demonstrated how the effective population size of subtype B HIV-1 in east Andalusia underwent exponential growth from the early 1980s to the early 1990s, which is in line with reports from other countries [
 <xref rid="pone.0168099.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0168099.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0168099.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Our study suggests that the early East Andalusian lineages originated in the 1980s among intravenous drug users in coastal areas. Epidemic growth stabilised in the early 1990s (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0168099.g006">Fig 6</xref>), when prevention measures were first implemented in Spain [
 <xref rid="pone.0168099.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Since then, the transmission pattern in Spain has gradually evolved from IVDUs to MSMs [
 <xref rid="pone.0168099.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. This partially explains why we detected an emergence of clustering among the MSMs for these dates, which fell in line with increased high-risk behaviour by MSMs reported in Europe for these years [
 <xref rid="pone.0168099.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0168099.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. From this period, access to highly active antiretroviral treatment (HAART) in 1996 in Spain has helped reduce the effective population size for HIV-1 among infected patients [
 <xref rid="pone.0168099.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0168099.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. However from 2005, the subtype B epidemic in east Andalusia underwent new exponential growth, which indicates that dedicated preventive measures to avoid growth must be implemented and maintained. Multiple studies [
 <xref rid="pone.0168099.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] have interpreted the timing of changes in phylodynamic patterns in the context of other changes. Hence we believe that this type of studies may serve as a tool to implement preventive strategies.
</p>
