<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="T3" position="float">
 <label>Table III</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Ethical issues for consideration during outbreaks/epidemics</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Topic</th>
    <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Details</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Social value</td>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public health relevance, importance of using unapproved interventions to save lives, prevent spread of infection in care of outbreaks or epidemics</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scientific design and conduct</td>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Use of unapproved interventions after thorough scientific consultation for trial (placebo/intervention). Clear inclusion exclusion criteria</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benefit risk assessment</td>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benefit and risks assessed at both individual and population level. Supportive care, adequate monitoring/follow up, management of adverse events, 
     <italic>etc</italic>.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Selection of study population/recruitment of participants</td>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fair selection of participants following defined methodology removing the possibility of any bias or discrimination of particular group or individual</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protection of privacy and confidentiality</td>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Identifying information of confirmed cases to be reported to public health authorities but protected from unauthorized access to media or others</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Community consideration</td>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Efforts be made to engage with communities to communicate, discuss sensitivities involved. Release timely, accurate updates to remove panic</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qualification and site facilities</td>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site well equipped to deal with outbreaks/appropriate facility for isolation and quarantine. Investigators and health workers trained/qualified to understand ways of infection control</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Informed consent process</td>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prior approvals with dummy protocol/informed consent forms. EC may be requested to allow oral consent/waiver of consent depending on situation, efforts be made to simplify informed consent in local language</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Collaboration</td>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urgent need to join hands to make collective efforts for infection control. Adequate safeguards needed and sharing data, sample storing for future use, biobanking, 
     <italic>etc</italic>., and fast-track systems to facilitate collaboration
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Governance mechanism</td>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Well informed, responsive governance mechanism involving all stakeholders who can work towards a common goal of outbreak control and guide research</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn>
   <p>
    <italic>Source</italic>: Ref. 
    <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
   </p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
