<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
 <p>CX designed the study, performed the analysis, and drafted and revised the manuscript. LP conceived and designed the experiments, performed the analysis and revised the manuscript. YW and CC conducted the investigation, collected the data, performed the analysis and commented on the manuscript. HF and LL collected the specimens, prepared the experiments and commented on the manuscript. WZ and QS designed the study, supervised the study and commented on the manuscript. BX designed and supervised the overall study, as well as conceptualized, drafted and revised the manuscript. All authors ensured the accuracy and integrity of this article. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
 <sec id="FPar1">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <p id="Par40">Appreciation for the 12 sentinel hospitals of AGE surveillance of Pudong New Area, Shanghai, China.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar2">
  <title>Competing interests</title>
  <p id="Par41">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar3">
  <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
  <p id="Par42">The dataset used and analyzed during the current study is available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar4">
  <title>Consent for publications</title>
  <p id="Par43">Not applicable.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar5">
  <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
  <p id="Par44">The study protocol was approved by the Ethics Review Board of Pudong Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Shanghai, China.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar6">
  <title>Funding</title>
  <p id="Par45">This work was supported by Young Medical Talent Training Program of Health System of Pudong New Area, Shanghai (PWRq2016-17). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar7">
  <title>Publisher’s Note</title>
  <p id="Par46">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
 </sec>
</ack>
