<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>PITC was conceptually acceptable for both users and providers and positively envisaged as a testing modality that would normalise HIV testing and promote earlier HIV diagnosis. For the majority of users interviewed, health facilities were convenient testing venues and the offer of an HIV test by a HP was appreciated. Many users reported that PITC was the testing modality that offered the greatest advantages in terms of convenience, reliability and confidentiality suggesting that it is a promising approach to promote testing amongst foreign-born sexual minorities who are reluctant to attend community-based services. However, HPs’ reports suggest that endorsement of and adherence to the 5Cs principles underpinning the WHO rights-based response to HIV varied widely across health settings. Counselling was often skipped, confidentiality could not be strictly safeguarded, and a few HPs acknowledged testing users for HIV without asking for consent. Linkage to treatment was a time-consuming process, further complicated by uncertainties and confusion in the case of undocumented migrants. In spite of—and sometimes because of—questionable adherence to some of the 5Cs principles, PITC continued to be acceptable for most users, suggesting that instances of poor adherence to ethical standards in HIV testing services could remain uncontested. Widespread claims that HIV testing should be normalised coexisted with blaming and moralising attitudes amongst both users and providers, which continued to frame HIV as an exceptional disease. The operational challenges identified point to shortcomings in the range of services that should be provided together with HIV testing [
 <xref rid="pone.0150223.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], and suggest a call for caution in the implementation of PITC in contexts were persisting and overlapping sources of HIV stigma coexist with partial endorsement of the core principles underpinning the rights-based response to HIV.
</p>
