<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diabetes Metab Syndr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Diabetes Metab Syndr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Diabetes &#x00026; Metabolic Syndrome</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1871-4021</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1878-0334</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Diabetes India. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7195043</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S1871-4021(20)30077-1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dsx.2020.04.012</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Artificial Intelligence (AI) applications for COVID-19 pandemic</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Vaishya</surname><given-names>Raju</given-names></name><email>raju.vaishya@gmail.com</email><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scholar.google.co.in/citations?user=2Lu3gQ0AAAAJ&#x00026;hl=en">https://scholar.google.co.in/citations?user=2Lu3gQ0AAAAJ&#x00026;hl=en</ext-link><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Javaid</surname><given-names>Mohd</given-names></name><email>mjavaid@jmi.ac.in</email><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scholar.google.co.in/citations?user=rfyiwvsAAAAJ&#x00026;hl=en">https://scholar.google.co.in/citations?user=rfyiwvsAAAAJ&#x00026;hl=en</ext-link><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Ibrahim Haleem</given-names></name><email>ibrahimhaleemkhan.ihk@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Haleem</surname><given-names>Abid</given-names></name><email>haleem.abid@gmail.com</email><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scholar.google.co.in/citations?user=4047148AAAAJ&#x00026;hl=en">https://scholar.google.co.in/citations?user=4047148AAAAJ&#x00026;hl=en</ext-link><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Orthopaedics, Indraprastha Apollo Hospital, SaritaVihar, Mathura Road, 110076, New Delhi, India</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Mechanical Engineering, Jamia Millia Islamia, New Delhi, India</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Jamia Hamdard, New Delhi, India</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. <email>mjavaid@jmi.ac.in</email><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scholar.google.co.in/citations?user=rfyiwvsAAAAJ&#x00026;hl=en">https://scholar.google.co.in/citations?user=rfyiwvsAAAAJ&#x00026;hl=en</ext-link></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>14</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub" iso-8601-date="2020-08-01"><season>July-August</season><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>339</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>10</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Diabetes India. Published by Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Diabetes India</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Background and aims</title><p>Healthcare delivery requires the support of new technologies like Artificial Intelligence (AI), Internet of Things (IoT), Big Data and Machine Learning to fight and look ahead against the new diseases. We aim to review the role of AI as a decisive technology to analyze, prepare us for prevention and fight with COVID-19 (Coronavirus) and other pandemics.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>The rapid review of the literature is done on the database of Pubmed, Scopus and Google Scholar using the keyword of COVID-19 or Coronavirus and Artificial Intelligence or AI. Collected the latest information regarding AI for COVID-19, then analyzed the same to identify its possible application for this disease.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We have identified seven significant applications of AI for COVID-19 pandemic. This technology plays an important role to detect the cluster of cases and to predict where this virus will affect in future by collecting and analyzing all previous data.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Healthcare organizations are in an urgent need for decision-making technologies to handle this virus and help them in getting proper suggestions in real-time to avoid its spread. AI works in a proficient way to mimic like human intelligence. It may also play a vital role in understanding and suggesting the development of a vaccine for COVID-19. This result-driven technology is used for proper screening, analyzing, prediction and tracking of current patients and likely future patients. The significant applications are applied to tracks data of confirmed, recovered and death cases.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0015"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010"><list-item id="u0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0010">Artificial Intelligence (AI) is an innovative technology which is helpful to fight the COVID-19 pandemic.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0015">This technology is helpful for proper screening, tracking and predicting the current and future patients.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0115">The major applications of this AI are for early detection and diagnosis of the infection.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0420"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p7115">AI is used for the development of drugs and vaccines, and the reduction of workload of healthcare workers.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Artificial Intelligence (AI)</kwd><kwd>AI Applications</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>Coronavirus</kwd><kwd>Pandemic</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Background</title><p id="p0020">In this worldwide health crisis, the medical industry is looking for new technologies to monitor and controls the spread of COVID-19 (Coronavirus) pandemic. AI is one of such technology which can easily track the spread of this virus, identifies the high-risk patients, and is useful in controlling this infection in real-time. It can also predict mortality risk by adequately analyzing the previous data of the patients. AI can help us to fight this virus by population screening, medical help, notification, and suggestions about the infection control [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>]. This technology has the potential to improve the planning, treatment and reported outcomes of the COVID-19 patient, being an evidence-based medical tool. <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>
shows the general procedure of AI and non-AI based applications that help general physicians to identify the COVID-19 symptoms.<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>General procedure of AI and non-AI based applications that help general physicians to identify the COVID-19 symptoms.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Fig.&#x000a0;1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p><p id="p0025">The above flow diagram informs and compares the flow of minimal non-AI treatment versus AI-based treatment. The above flow diagram explains the involvement of AI in the significant steps of treatment of high accuracy and reduces complexity and time taken. The physician is not only focused on the treatment of the patient, but also the control of disease with the AI application. Major symptoms and test analysis are done with the help of AI with the highest of accuracy. It also shows it reduces the total number of steps taken in the whole process, making more procurable in nature.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Main applications of AI in COVID-19 pandemic</title><p id="p0030">
<list list-type="simple" id="olist0010"><list-item id="o0010"><label>I)</label><p id="p0035">Early detection and diagnosis of the infection</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="p0040">AI can quickly analyze irregular symptom and other &#x02018;red flags&#x02019; and thus alarm the patients and the healthcare authorities [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. It helps to provide faster decision making, which is cost-effective. It helps to develop a new diagnosis and management system for the COVID 19 cases, through useful algorithms. AI is helpful in the diagnosis of the infected cases with the help of medical imaging technologies like Computed tomography (CT), Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan of human body parts.<list list-type="simple" id="olist0015"><list-item id="o0015"><label>II)</label><p id="p0045">Monitoring the treatment</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="p0050">AI can build an intelligent platform for automatic monitoring and prediction of the spread of this virus. A neural network can also be developed to extract the visual features of this disease, and this would help in proper monitoring and treatment of the affected individuals [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>]. It has the capability of providing day-to-day updates of the patients and also to provide solutions to be followed in COVID-19 pandemic.<list list-type="simple" id="olist0020"><list-item id="o0020"><label>III)</label><p id="p0055">Contact tracing of the individuals</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="p0060">AI can help analyze the level of infection by this virus identifying the clusters and &#x02018;hot spots&#x02019; and can successfully do the contact tracing of the individuals and also to monitor them. It can predict the future course of this disease and likely reappearance.<list list-type="simple" id="olist0025"><list-item id="o0025"><label>IV)</label><p id="p0065">Projection of cases and mortality</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="p0070">This technology can track and forecast the nature of the virus from the available data, social media and media platforms, about the risks of the infection and its likely spread. Further, it can predict the number of positive cases and death in any region. AI can help identify the most vulnerable regions, people and countries and take measures accordingly.<list list-type="simple" id="olist0030"><list-item id="o0030"><label>V)</label><p id="p0075">Development of drugs and vaccines:</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="p0080">AI is used for drug research by analyzing the available data on COVID-19. It is useful for drug delivery design and development. This technology is used in speeding up drug testing in real-time, where standard testing takes plenty of time and hence helps to accelerate this process significantly, which may not be possible by a human [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. It can help to identify useful drugs for the treatment of COVID-19 patients. It has become a powerful tool for diagnostic test designs and vaccination development [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>]. AI helps in developing vaccines and treatments at much of faster rate than usual and is also helpful for clinical trials during the development of the vaccine.<list list-type="simple" id="olist0035"><list-item id="o0035"><label>VI)</label><p id="p0085">Reducing the workload of healthcare workers</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="p0090">Due to a sudden and massive increase in the numbers of patients during COVID-19 pandemic, healthcare professionals have a very high workload. Here, AI is used to reduce the workload of healthcare workers [<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>]. It helps in early diagnosis and providing treatment at an early stage using digital approaches and decision science, offers the best training to students and doctors regarding this new disease [<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. AI can impact future patient care and address more potential challenges which reduce the workload of the doctors.<list list-type="simple" id="olist0040"><list-item id="o0040"><label>VII)</label><p id="p0095">Prevention of the disease</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="p0100">With the help of real-time data analysis, AI can provide updated information which is helpful in the prevention of this disease. It can be used to predict the probable sites of infection, the influx of the virus, need for beds and healthcare professionals during this crisis. AI is helpful for the future virus and diseases prevention, with the help of previous mentored data over data prevalent at different time. It identifies traits, causes and reasons for the spread of infection. In future, this will become an important technology to fight against the other epidemics and pandemics. It can provide a preventive measure and fight against many other diseases. In future, AI will play a vital role in providing more predictive and preventive healthcare.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0105">Artificial Intelligence is an upcoming and useful tool to identify early infections due to coronavirus and also helps in monitoring the condition of the infected patients. It can significantly improve treatment consistency and decision making by developing useful algorithms. AI is not only helpful in the treatment of COVID-19 infected patients but also for their proper health monitoring. It can track the crisis of COVID-19 at different scales such as medical, molecular and epidemiological applications. It is also helpful to facilitate the research on this virus using analyzing the available data. AI can help in developing proper treatment regimens, prevention strategies, drug and vaccine development.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0110">None.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haleem</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Javaid</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaishya</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of COVID 19 pandemic in daily life</article-title><source>Curr Med Res Pract</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmrp.2020.03.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>H.X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Halsey</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Performance of radiologists in differentiating COVID-19 from viral pneumonia on chest CT</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiol.2020200823</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref3">Hu Z, Ge Q, Jin L, Xiong M. Artificial intelligence forecasting of COVID-19 in China. <italic>arXiv preprint</italic> arXiv:2002.07112. 2020 Feb 17.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ai</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlation of chest CT and RT-PCR testing in coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) in China: a report of 1014 cases</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiol.2020200642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Q.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>Y.X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Can Chinese medicine be used for prevention of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19)? A review of historical classics, research evidence and current prevention programs</article-title><source>Chin J Integr Med</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11655-020-3192-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haleem</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaishya</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Javaid</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>I.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Artificial Intelligence (AI) applications in orthopaedics: an innovative technology to embrace</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Clin Orthop Trauma</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcot.2019.06.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref7">Biswas K, Sen P. Space-time dependence of coronavirus (COVID-19) outbreak. arXiv preprint arXiv:2003.03149. 2020 Mar 6.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stebbing</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phelan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oechsle</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19: combining antiviral and anti-inflammatory treatments</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2020 Feb 27</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sohrabi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alsafi</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Neill</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerwan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Jabir</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iosifidis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agha</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>World Health Organization declares global emergency: a review of the 2019 novel coronavirus (COVID-19)</article-title><source>Int J Surg</source><year>2020 Feb 26</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e4;rnighausen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 control in China during mass population movements at New Year</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30421-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bobdey</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Going viral&#x02013;COVID-19 impact assessment: a perspective beyond clinical practice</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Mar Med Soc</source><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020 Jan 1</year><fpage>9</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref12">Gozes O, Frid-Adar M, Greenspan H, Browning PD, Zhang H, Ji W, Bernheim A, Siegel E. Rapid ai development cycle for the Coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic: initial results for automated detection &#x00026; patient monitoring using deep learning ct image analysis. arXiv preprint arXiv:2003.05037. 2020 Mar 10.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pirouz</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>ShaffieeHaghshenas</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>ShaffieeHaghshenas</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Piro</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigating a serious challenge in the sustainable development process: analysis of confirmed cases of COVID-19 (new type of coronavirus) through a binary classification using artificial intelligence and regression analysis</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><volume>12</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2020 Jan</year><fpage>2427</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ting</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dzau</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>T.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Digital technology and COVID-19</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2020 Mar 27</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31932805</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Precautionary measures needed for ophthalmologists during pandemic of the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19)</article-title><source>Acta Ophthalmol</source><year>2020 Mar 29</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Artificial intelligence distinguishes COVID-19 from community-acquired pneumonia on chest CT</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2020 Mar 19</year><fpage>200905</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32191588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smeulders</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Ginneken</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An analysis of pathology knowledge and decision making for the development of artificial intelligence-based consulting systems</article-title><source>Anal Quant Cytol Histol</source><volume>11</volume><issue>3</issue><year>1989 Jun 1</year><fpage>154</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2663007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contentious issues and evolving concepts in the clinical presentation and management of patients with COVID-19 infection with reference to use of therapeutic and other drugs used in Co-morbid diseases (Hypertension, diabetes etc.)</article-title><source>Diabetes, Metab Syndrome: Clin Res Rev</source><volume>14</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>254</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical considerations for patients with diabetes in times of COVID-19 epidemic. Diabetes &#x00026; Metabolic Syndrome</article-title><source>Clin Res Rev</source><volume>14</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>212</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>