<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Transmission of hantavirus to humans occurs via inhalation of aerosolized viral particles present in the urine, feces, and saliva excreted into the environment by rodents infected with it [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006881.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006881.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Consequently, rodent-to-human hantavirus transmission depends on the following factors: 1) the frequency of contact between human and rodent populations, which is associated with human activities, living conditions, working conditions, host species distributions, rodent population densities, and virus prevalence in rodents [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006881.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0006881.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], and 2) external environmental factors including temperature, rainfall, relative humidity, land type, vegetation status, soil moisture status, and elevation, which play important roles in reservoir host density and the level of exposure to infectious viruses [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006881.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0006881.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Previous studies have shown the tendency for rodent species to thrive in restricted habitats. 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>agrarius</italic>, for example, prefers humid and food-rich environments and is abundant in forested regions and fields. In contrast, 
 <italic>R</italic>. 
 <italic>norvegicus</italic> is found predominantly in residential areas and is the main vector for zoonotic diseases in rural and urban populations [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006881.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006881.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Environmental factors can influence the occurrence of HFRS through their effects on the reservoir hosts and their living conditions [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006881.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0006881.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. However, the specific relationships among different environmental factors, different rodent species, and the occurrence of HFRS remain unclear.
</p>
