<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Enriched and unenriched libraries were constructed and sequenced on an Illumina MiSeq (Duke-NUS Genome Biology Facility, Singapore) and Illumina HiSeq 4000 (Genome Institute of Singapore). FastQC [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] was used to confirm the quality of the reads generated, and Trim Galore [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] was used to trim and filter the reads with a minimum quality cutoff of 20 and a minimum read length of 35 nt. As the viral species and strain is unknown in most of the cases, it is necessary to identify the nearest species and the strain present in the sample. Therefore, Blast toolkit [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] was used to search the nearest hit in the NCBI nucleotide database for every read using the megablast option. A metagenomic analysis software MEGAN [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] was used to cluster reads at the species level to visualize. As Blast analysis is time-consuming, only a portion of the reads were used to identify the species and strain. The species cluster with the maximum number of reads assigned was selected as the initial reference strain and used to generate a consensus genome. The consensus genome was generated by using bam2cons_iter.sh script from the ViPR pipeline [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The bam2cons_iter.sh uses BWA [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] to perform iterative mapping of the reads to the reference genome and a consensus is generated based on the maximum frequency of a nucleotide at a given position. From the obtained consensus genome, the nearest NCBI hit is found and used as a reference genome to rerun the bam2cons_iter.sh script with default parameters. This iterative consensus genome generation approach enables generation of a full genome consensus for the virus present in the sample. For final mapping with BWA mem v0.7.5 aligner was used to map the reads to the consensus reference genome and picard tools v1.95 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] were used to mark PCR duplicates. Base calibration and indel realignment was done by GATK v3.3 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Single nucleotide variants for each sample were detected using LoFreq2 software [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], which incorporates base-call quality scores as error probabilities into its model to distinguish SNVs from the average sequencing error rate, and assigns a p-value to each position (Bonferroni-corrected p-value &gt; 0.05). LoFreq has previously been applied to DENV datasets, and its SNV predictions on these datasets have been experimentally validated down to 0.5% allele frequency [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], hence we filtered the SNPs with a threshold of coverage (&gt;1000) and allele frequency (&gt;0.5%). Finally, the genome coverage graph along with the baits positions and SNP positions were plotted using Circos [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>].
</p>
