<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Hepatitis B virus (HBV) is the prototype of hepadnaviruses. It infects humans and can be classified into 8 genotypes. More than one billion people have contracted hepatitis B virus (HBV) and more than 200 million patients are chronically infected with hepatitis B (CHB) [
 <xref rid="B153-ijms-20-04657" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>]. CHB infections result in the development of hepatocellular carcinoma and chronic liver failure [
 <xref rid="B151-ijms-20-04657" ref-type="bibr">151</xref>] and every year CHB causes 880,000 deaths worldwide [
 <xref rid="B153-ijms-20-04657" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>]. Analysis of the immunodominant motifs of the HBV core region from the amino acids 40 to 95 indicated that the positions exhibiting peak rates of variability were found in the main core epitopes, thereby confirming their role in stimulating the immune system. Moreover, the distribution of the variability was observed to occur in a genotype-dependent manner. For instance, HBV isolated from genotype A had higher variability within the core epitope regions but no significant differences in genotype D were observed in the core epitopes and other positions. Further sequential analysis of the samples put forth the dynamic nature of the HBV quasispecies whereby a strong selection for a single baseline variant was linked to a lower variability within the core region pre- and post-treatment. Leucine (L) at position 76 was determined to be the most highly conserved residue and the role of this amino acid was assessed by substitutions of Valine (V) or Proline (P) at position 76. Proline at position 76 was shown to drastically lower the production of Hepatitis B core antigen protein (HBsAg), likely due to the chemical and physical properties of the amino acid. However, substitution with Valine (V) at a similar position brought about a four-fold increase in the Hepatitis B e antigen protein (HBeAg) production when compared to Leucine at position 76. The decrease in the variability observed was associated with a stable quasispecies population after positive selection of the variant exhibiting high fitness level [
 <xref rid="B154-ijms-20-04657" ref-type="bibr">154</xref>].
</p>
