<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Most studies in Southeast Asia currently focus on human infection linked to humid habitats and rice cultivation 
 <xref rid="pntd.0002902-Kawaguchi1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0002902-Singleton1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. Without calling into question the importance of this route of transmission, our results suggest alternate routes of infection, which deserves further study. Human infection could also occur in other humid habitats, such as standing water and forest streams. Moreover, rodents are the subject of traditional hunting and trade in many parts of Southeast Asia. Close contact between rodents and humans during these activities, as well as rodent preparation before consumption, could present a significant route of infection, which should be evaluated. In line with our results, frequent human activity in forests was identified as a significant risk factor in Laos 
 <xref rid="pntd.0002902-Kawaguchi1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. On the other hand, and fortunately, human contamination by commensal small mammals is probably low in Southeast Asia, despite the abundance of rodents and shrews in human dwellings. To our knowledge, our work is the first ecological evidence supporting different transmission routes for 
 <italic>L. interrogans</italic> and 
 <italic>L. borgpetersenii</italic> species in nature. Clearly this last point deserves more study, notably in order to strictly demonstrate the predominance of 
 <italic>L. borgpetersenii</italic> direct transmission in ecological systems, as well as to determine if this transmission mode holds true for all 
 <italic>borgpetersenii</italic> serovars, or for only some specific serovars. Together, this work brings to light novel perspectives on leptospiral epidemiology, reinforces the existence of species-specific transmission routes in nature, and stresses the need for the precise diagnosis of 
 <italic>Leptospira</italic> involved in human and animal infections in order to better understand and foresee epidemics.
</p>
