<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The yeast 
 <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> (
 <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>) and 
 <italic>Scizosacchromyces pombe (S. pombe)</italic> have been model organisms for studying all the basic cellular processes in the eukaryotic cell, including transcription and transcription regulation, translation, RNA processing, signal transduction and de novo (M12)(M13) synthesis of amino acids and nucleotides [
 <xref rid="B103-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>,
 <xref rid="B104-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>,
 <xref rid="B105-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Important processes, such as cell cycle, autophagy, regulation of chemical energy (ATP), basic signaling pathways (e.g., MAP kinase cascades) and vesicle trafficking, were first discovered in yeast [
 <xref rid="B106-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]. Most findings in yeast turned out to be relevant to all eukaryotic cells, including mammals, making 
 <italic>S. cerevisiae,</italic> and 
 <italic>S. pombe</italic> relevant and legitimate systems for studying all the basic biochemical, physiological, metabolic and genetic processes of the eukaryotic cell. 
 <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> is more widely used than 
 <italic>S. pombe</italic> has been termed the ‘
 <italic>E.coli</italic> of the eukaryotic cell’ [
 <xref rid="B107-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>,
 <xref rid="B108-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>,
 <xref rid="B109-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>,
 <xref rid="B110-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]. As the yeast biochemical machinery is so similar to that of mammals, in many cases, mammalian proteins can functionally replace the relevant yeast ortholog [
 <xref rid="B111-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. These observations made yeast an in vivo test tube in which to study foreign proteins such as the bacterial pathogenic factors [
 <xref rid="B112-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>,
 <xref rid="B113-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>], mammalian transcription factors and steroid receptors [
 <xref rid="B114-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. 
 <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> cells have also been used to reconstitute mammalian enzymatic complexes and biochemical pathways such as Ras and its regulators, MAP kinases, GCN2/PKR and even the olfactory pathway from the taste receptor to the activated enzyme [
 <xref rid="B107-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>,
 <xref rid="B115-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>,
 <xref rid="B116-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. As yeast has become a central system in biological studies, various sophisticated experimental tools have been developed. Some of them are not available yet in any other model organism, For example, one-step knockout and knock-in processes [
 <xref rid="B120-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>,
 <xref rid="B121-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>], the availability of a knockout library of all non-essential genes, the ability to harbor a foreign gene at the number of copies desired and the availability of libraries with all yeast genes tagged with various tags, including GFP. Furthermore, as 
 <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> is a simple single-cell organism with just about 6400 genes, advanced bioinformatics and system-biology tools are most powerful and accurate in yeast [
 <xref rid="B111-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. Importantly, 
 <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> have been used to study viral-induced apoptosis, viral mediated cell cycle regulation [
 <xref rid="B10-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] and for drug screening [
 <xref rid="B122-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>].
</p>
