<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<contrib-group>
 <contrib contrib-type="author">
  <name>
   <surname>Raoult</surname>
   <given-names>Didier</given-names>
  </name>
  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
 </contrib>
 <contrib contrib-type="author">
  <name>
   <surname>Zumla</surname>
   <given-names>Alimuddin</given-names>
  </name>
  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
 </contrib>
 <contrib contrib-type="author">
  <name>
   <surname>Locatelli</surname>
   <given-names>Franco</given-names>
  </name>
  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
 </contrib>
 <contrib contrib-type="author">
  <name>
   <surname>Ippolito</surname>
   <given-names>Giuseppe</given-names>
  </name>
  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref>
 </contrib>
 <contrib contrib-type="author">
  <name>
   <surname>Kroemer</surname>
   <given-names>Guido</given-names>
  </name>
  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref>
  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref>
  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff8">8</xref>
  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff9">9</xref>
  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff10">10</xref>
  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
 </contrib>
 <aff id="aff1">
  <label>1</label>Aix-Marseille Univ., Institut de Recherche pour le Développement (IRD), Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Marseille (AP-HM), MEPHI, 27 boulevard Jean Moulin, 13005 Marseille, France; IHU Méditerranée Infection, Marseille, France.
 </aff>
 <aff id="aff2">
  <label>2</label>Division of Infection and Immunity, Center for Clinical Microbiology, University College London, London, UK.
 </aff>
 <aff id="aff3">
  <label>3</label>The National Institute of Health Research Biomedical Research Centre at UCL Hospitals, London, UK.
 </aff>
 <aff id="aff4">
  <label>4</label>Department of Pediatric Hematology and Oncology IRCCS Ospedale Pediatrico Bambino Gesù, Rome, Italy.
 </aff>
 <aff id="aff5">
  <label>5</label>National Institute for Infectious Diseases, Lazzaro Spallanzani, IRCCS, Rome, Italy.
 </aff>
 <aff id="aff6">
  <label>6</label>Centre de Recherche des Cordeliers, Equipe labellisée par la Ligue contre le cancer, Université de Paris, Sorbonne Université, INSERM U1138, Institut Universitaire de France, Paris, France.
 </aff>
 <aff id="aff7">
  <label>7</label>Metabolomics and Cell Biology Platforms, Institut Gustave Roussy, Villejuif, France.
 </aff>
 <aff id="aff8">
  <label>8</label>Pôle de Biologie, Hôpital Européen Georges Pompidou, AP-HP, Paris, France.
 </aff>
 <aff id="aff9">
  <label>9</label>Suzhou Institute for Systems Medicine, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, Suzhou, China.
 </aff>
 <aff id="aff10">
  <label>10</label>Karolinska Institute, Department of Women's and Children's Health, Karolinska University Hospital, Stockholm, Sweden.
 </aff>
</contrib-group>
