<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Participants were enrolled into this cross-sectional study from two TB clinics in the state of Kaduna, Nigeria: the National TB and Leprosy Training Center (NTBLTC), Zaria, and at the Barau Dikko Hospital (BDH), in Kaduna City [
 <xref rid="pone.0191387.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Kaduna is located at 10.52° North latitude, and 7.44° East longitude. It is situated some 614 meters above the sea level with an estimated population of 1,582,102. The NTBLTC is the largest TB referral center in northern Nigeria, while the BDH located in the city of Kaduna, is the major referral center within the state. Several hundred patients receive TB/HIV treatment at these facilities. Inclusion criteria included suspected cases with symptoms suggestive of TB and unknown HIV status visiting the facilities for the first time were enrolled. Participants had to be 18 years or older and provided written informed consent. For each patient, a supervised spot sputum sample was collected in the clinic, and HIV status was determined. To obtain an unbiased estimate of HIV among patients presenting with TB symptoms, we excluded known HIV-infected cases referred from the HIV clinic. Detailed description of the population and enrollment into this study, including the ethical challenges, were previously described [
 <xref rid="pone.0191387.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0191387.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The protocol for this study was reviewed and approved by the University of Maryland’s Institutional Review Board and the Nigerian Health Research Ethics Committee. The initial sample size for this study was estimated based on the expected proportion of TB cases in the study population that would be due to 
 <italic>Mycobacterium bovis</italic>. We used a 95% confidence interval with a desired margin of error within 3% of the true proportion and a previously reported 
 <italic>Mycobacterium bovis</italic> prevalence of 15% to arrive at 544 as the number of confirmed TB cases required to estimate the prevalence.
</p>
