<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Moreover, to fully appreciate the discourses on epidemics and pandemics, it is necessary to look at the use of viruses and bacteria made within national defence programs. Indeed, in recent decades commercial bioindustrial facilities in the USA have developed vaccines, laboratories, and other technologies that can be used for both civilian and military purposes.
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="cnt12300-note-0044">
  <sup>43</sup>
 </xref> Over the past century and despite the international norms against the military use of poison and disease, countries such as the USA, Soviet Union, and Japan have developed and deployed microbes as part of national defence programs.
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="cnt12300-note-0045">
  <sup>44</sup>
 </xref> Such actions raise significant questions as to the relationships between microbial epistemologies and the administrative activities of national, international, and intergovernmental institutions, such as the UN and the WHO. The lack of transparency surrounding classified microbial research hinders the evaluation of related risks and threats. In contrast, when virologic research is carried out for civil uses, it encourages scientists to express their doubts about the research and voice their distrust of both the national agencies and international institutions that authorize these highly dangerous endeavours.
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="cnt12300-note-0046">
  <sup>45</sup>
 </xref> Given that in the past biological warfare research has been carried out under civilian cover, further research is required to analyse the interaction between virology, bacteriology, and biotechnology companies, and the national and international institutions in which civilian and military purposes overlap.
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="cnt12300-note-0047">
  <sup>46</sup>
 </xref> As geopolitical equilibria shift, illness does not simply disrupt social and economic regimes; it can be implemented as a diplomatic or military mean of persuasion and offence.
</p>
