<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29">Like the basic reproductive number, 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sup>
  <italic>j</italic>
 </sup> can be regarded as a function of duration of infectiousness, incubation period, transmission probability, vector mosquito density, and host-vector contact rate. The adjusted 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sup>
  <italic>j</italic>
 </sup> in this study could reflect vector mosquito density and host-vector contact rate, which are also highly heterogeneous in space
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup>. Meanwhile, the dispersal of vector mosquitoes is largely confined to neighboring areas (average radius of 28–199 meters
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup>), providing an effective infectious zone of an infector. An exponential spatial weighting function herein represents this infectious zone. Guzzetta
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup> estimated the mean transmission distance of dengue in a metropolis area to be approximately 127 m and further indicated that an exponential distribution described the data better than a radiation model which is a more dispersed distribution effectively describes human mobility
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. Kissler, 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup> also reported the aptness of the exponential distribution when an outbreak is typically dominated by short-range transmission. Therefore, the exponential spatial weighting function in this study is an appropriate substitute for the effective infectious zone for measuring dengue transmission. The exponential distance-decayed function also avoids overestimating the transmission probabilities of infector-infectee pairs with long geographic distances, especially for large-scale dengue epidemics. In sum, areas with high 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sup>
  <italic>j</italic>
 </sup> are potential risk areas for high dengue transmission; knowledge of such areas is important for spatial targeting during dengue epidemics.
</p>
