<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The current study also identified an additional proviral signaling pathway, the HIPPO signaling pathway, that was unique to H7N9 activation only in CEF cells (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="cells-09-00448-f003">Figure 3</xref>D, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="cells-09-00448-f004">Figure 4</xref>D and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="cells-09-00448-f005">Figure 5</xref>C). We did not observe this pathway when we compared the DEGs in the microarray data with other avian influenza subtypes (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="cells-09-00448-f006">Figure 6</xref>). This is the first study that reported the HIPPO signaling pathway in influenza A virus infections. The HIPPO signaling pathway contains a cascade of threonine and serine kinases that regulates a number of growth and developmental physiological processes in controlling organ size by regulating homeostasis, and regenerations in mammalian hosts [
 <xref rid="B31-cells-09-00448" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. This pathway was named after one of the key component, protein kinase Hippo (Hpo) whose gene mutations lead to tissue overgrowth, resulting in a hippopotamus phenotype. Dysfunction of the HIPPO signaling pathway has been implicated in human diseases, including cancer [
 <xref rid="B32-cells-09-00448" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. It was first discovered in Drosophila in 2003, but later on found to be greatly conserved in mammalian cells and responsible for cell proliferation and apoptosis [
 <xref rid="B33-cells-09-00448" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The YES associated protein (YAP), a major downstream effector of the HIPPO signaling pathway, was reported to be associated with cancer-causing viral proteins, such as the Hepatitis B virus X protein [
 <xref rid="B34-cells-09-00448" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-cells-09-00448" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], and murine polyomavirus small T antigen [
 <xref rid="B36-cells-09-00448" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Increased level of YAP protein was also found accumulating in the nucleus of human papillomavirus-positive oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma [
 <xref rid="B37-cells-09-00448" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], whereas, the reverse was reported for hepatocellular carcinomas caused by hepatitis C [
 <xref rid="B38-cells-09-00448" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The HIPPO pathway was also reported to be involved in the modulation of antiviral response by other virus infections, e.g., Sendai virus [
 <xref rid="B39-cells-09-00448" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Recently, it was reported to be implicated in Zika-virus induced microcephaly [
 <xref rid="B40-cells-09-00448" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. These reported results suggested that the involvement of the HIPPO signaling pathway during virus infection can either lead to an overactive induction resulting in cancer, or cross-talk with other signaling cascade to maintain the virus in an antiviral state.
</p>
