<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The Loewe additivity and Bliss independence form the basis of sophisticated protocols for assessing drug combinations, especially in cancer-targeted chemotherapy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Research on biological network systems, as well as the biochemical characteristics of drugs, has also unraveled the mechanisms by which drug combinations produce synergistic effects (reviewed in [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]). Such research is important because (1) it facilitates rational drug discovery and (2) it predicts unknown connectivities in biological networks. Regarding the first point, the effects of a developing drug combined with conventional drugs are maximized by investigating biological networks, and rational drug targets are decided. For example, using computational modeling of cancer signaling networks and animal experiments, Kirouac 
 <italic>et al.</italic>[
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>] identified the optimal inhibitor combination for suppressing the growth of 
 <italic>ERBB2</italic>-amplified breast cancer. They adopted Bliss independence as a synergy criterion. Supplementing this computational approach with experimental data is useful for developing theoretically effective novel drugs. Regarding point (2), the biological networks of signaling pathways constructed by various components can be predicted from the dose–response shapes of drug combinations (reviewed in [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]). Lehar 
 <italic>et al.</italic>[
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>] used several drug combination criteria, including Loewe additivity and Bliss independence, to connect biological components from the results of cellular responses to chemical combinations. This approach assumes that the dose–response shape of a drug combination depends on how drug targets are connected in a biological system.
</p>
