<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the 1920s, two parallel approaches were taken to develop a live attenuated vaccine against YFV. In 1927, YFV was isolated from a Ghanaian patient suffering from mild yellow fever and inoculated into rhesus macaques by direct blood/serum transfer [
 <xref rid="B157-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>]. Max Theiler and colleagues discovered that this “Asibi” strain, which was refractory for growth in other small laboratory animals, was able to replicate in the brains of mice following intracranial injection. Following sequential passage in mouse brains, reduced viscerotropic virulence was observed, coupled with enhanced neurotropic properties. Therefore, the Asibi strain subsequently underwent serial passage in chicken embryo tissue, after head and spinal column removal. After 176 passages, the attenuated YFV-17D strain had lost its viscerotropism, neurotropism and mosquito competence, while retaining its immunogenicity [
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Concurrently, French researchers isolated YFV from a patient in Dakar, followed by serial passage in mouse brains. This attenuated strain, termed the French neurotropic vaccine (FNV), was isolated at passage 260 and was widely used in the francophone countries of Africa, virtually eradicating the disease. However, serial passaging in mouse brain increased FNV’s neurotropism, leading to high levels of post-vaccinal encephalitis in children. Consequently, the use of FNV was discontinued in the 1980s [
 <xref rid="B158-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>]. The 17D subculture is the seed strain for all modern-day YFV vaccines. There are three sub-strains obtained from the original 17D vaccine: the 17DD (Passage 195), 17D-204 (Passage 204) and the 17D-213, derived from 17D-204 and used by the Robert Koch Institute, Germany. These strains have slightly different genomic sequences: in particular, glycosylation sites on the envelope protein vary, although no differences in attenuation or immunogenicity have been observed [
 <xref rid="B159-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>]. The original passage 176 virus no longer exists, and comparisons are mainly made between the three strains outlined above [
 <xref rid="B160-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>].
</p>
