<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Such drugs that target host processes required for pathogen replication and spread are considered to provide a novel means to limit infection. Because they impact basic cell functions, the development of viral resistance, as is frequently seen with drugs directly targeting the pathogen, such as the influenza virus NA inhibitor oseltamivir, is less likely [
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-12-00703" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-12-00703" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Indeed, screening libraries of already approved compounds for novel uses (drug repurposing), has been established as a core drug development strategy, reducing the time and costs, due to the established safety profiles and known side effects of the tested compounds. Although drug repurposing for host-directed antiviral therapy is an approach that is considered a promising avenue, there are shortcomings to be considered, such as off-target and associated side effects on the host, as repurposed drugs often require high concentrations for their new use. Mechanistically, host-directed antiviral agents will slow down viral replication rather than eradicate the virus, and failure of HDT might result from the inappropriate time window of application (early vs. late infection stages) and a suppression rather than a complete elimination of the infectious agent, requiring long treatment duration which is often associated with poor patient compliance. Recently, combination therapies utilizing both host- and pathogen-directed strategies have been explored to overcome these limitations, as the combined use of two or more drugs might allow reduce the concentrations of the individual drugs in the cocktail [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-12-00703" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-12-00703" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-12-00703" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. As expected from established and clinically used drugs, no cytotoxic effects were observed when both, itraconazole and oseltamivir, were used individually and combined application reduced cell viability only at the highest concentrations tested. The pairwise combination was effective in reducing virus titers for both pdm09 and the Panama IAV variant. Oseltamivir and itraconazole EC
 <sub>50</sub> values indicated that both drugs worked effectively and did not antagonize each other. This assumption was confirmed by Bliss independence drug interaction analysis, which pointed at independent drug actions [
 <xref rid="B33-viruses-12-00703" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Notably, we detected significantly decreased viral titers in the combination treatments when compared to monotherapy with oseltamivir, at lower drug concentrations than required for the single treatments. Moreover, the additional antiviral effect of itraconazole might function as a safeguard mechanism to combat IAV infection caused by strains with heightened oseltamivir resistance.
</p>
