<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phylogenetic analysis performed in this study showed high levels of transmission networking among Romanian PWIDs: three HIV clusters and thirteen HCV clusters have been identified. The majority of HIV strains fell in two F1 clusters that were nested within Romanian reference strains. This suggests that F1 strains circulating for a long time among Romanian patients, infected sexually and nosocomially were the origin of the subtype F1 outbreaks in PWID and that these strains were restricted to Romania. The CRF14_BG strains circulating in PWID are related with those described earlier in Spain and Portugal in the same risk group population [
 <xref rid="pone.0185866.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. However, due to the limited number of CRF14_BG sequences available in public databases, direct filiation between the two epidemiologic events cannot be ascertained. Previous results indicated that the CRF14_BG sequences from Romanian PWID were closely related with the Greek PWID sequences and formed a single monophyletic cluster. Molecular clock analysis revealed that CRF14_BG strains circulating in PWID from Athens originated from one or several strains circulating in Bucharest [
 <xref rid="pone.0185866.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Our phylodynamic analyses indicated that all HIV transmission networks originated at similar time points, dating back 7 to 10 years ago, coincident with the availability of these new injectable amphetamine type stimulants on the market. The patients infected with CRF14_BG had significantly lower CD4 counts at baseline than those infected with F1 subtype strains despite the fact that phylogenetic and seroconversion data suggest their being infected at similar time points. Although we have included in our analysis all the PWID presented in our clinical settings during this period of time, the number of patients infected with CRF14_BG recombinants was smaller than those infected with subtype F1 and this might have impact on the statistical analysis. However, these data are in agreement with previous studies showing an association between CRF14_BG infection, CD4 T cells decline and disease severity, characterized by CXCR4 usage [
 <xref rid="pone.0185866.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0185866.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0185866.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>].
</p>
