<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Kucharski 
 <italic>et al</italic>. (2016) and Rahman 
 <italic>et al</italic>. (2019) used a mathematical model to examine the 2013–14 outbreak in the six major archipelagos of French Polynesia. They found that ZIKV may exhibit similar dynamics to dengue virus with a 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> ranging from 2.6–4.8 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>], and 2.03–3.20 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] and that reducing mosquito-to-human contact by at least 60% can reduce the peak prevalence by nearly 10% [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. In the event of ZIKV introduction into Australia in the period 1996–2015, our study shows that from an imported infected case, the yearly epidemic potential would have been below one for all UCLs studied, though potentially really close to one in Cairns, Rockhampton, and Thursday Island during the warmer months where 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> is established. The risk of an outbreak remains theoretically low in Darwin, where 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> was established in the past, but for which there is currently no evidence of persisting populations. These results suggest a temperature suitability of Darwin for ZIKV transmission, should 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> mosquitoes become established there again. Likewise, theoretically an epidemic of ZIKV would not be able to spread in these four UCLs, if only 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> was established. However, due to its presence in the Torres Strait and frequent detections at international First Points of Entry, preventing its expansion onto the Australian mainland remains a key priority [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Our analyses also highlight a modest contribution of sexual transmission to the basic reproduction number when only 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>Aegypti</italic> is considered, whereas a high contribution with only 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic>.
</p>
