<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para1006">
 <boxed-text id="tbox0002a">
  <caption>
   <title>Research in context</title>
  </caption>
  <sec id="sec1001a">
   <title>
    <bold>
     <italic>Evidence before this study</italic>
    </bold>
   </title>
   <p id="para0006">
    <bold>Very few studies have reported the long-term prognosis or medical follow-up of patients with A(H7N9) virus infection after hospital discharge. A study by Tang et al. reported findings of short-term follow-up (5-7 months) of 5 survivors of A(H7N9) virus infection after the first outbreak of human infections in Shanghai in 2013. A single center study by Chen et al. assessed outcomes in 56 A(H7N9) survivors in Zhejiang Province up to two years.</bold>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec1002a">
   <title>
    <bold>
     <italic>Added value of this study</italic>
    </bold>
   </title>
   <p id="para0007">
    <bold>To further improve understanding of long-term clinical prognosis and recovery of patients infected with avian influenza A(H7N9) viruses in China, we conducted a multi-center prospective medical follow-up study of A(H7N9) patients after their hospital discharge up to 64 months after illness onset. A substantial proportion of these survivors had persistent pulmonary dysfunction, including both ventilation capacity and diffusion capacity abnormalities. Lung abnormalities identified by CT scans also persisted for prolonged periods after hospital discharge.</bold>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec1003a">
   <title>
    <bold>
     <italic>Implications of all the available evidence</italic>
    </bold>
   </title>
   <p id="para0008">
    <bold>This multi-center study of the long-term clinical prognosis, sequelae, and prolonged recovery period for A(H7N9) patients who survived severe illness highlights the severity of A(H7N9) virus infections after hospital discharge. These findings reinforce the importance of long-term longitudinal studies to monitor the health impact and medical needs of patients who survived severe illness due to infections with avian influenza A viruses.</bold>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <notes notes-type="alt-text" specific-use="for-accessibility" id="alte1a">
   <p>Alt-text: Unlabelled box</p>
  </notes>
 </boxed-text>
</p>
