<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0205">Some limitations should be mentioned. Although the study covers a large sample, it is not representative of the German general population in terms of socio-demographic variables (79.8 % female, 
 <italic>M</italic>
 <sub>age</sub> = 33.36 years, 39.4 % students). In addition, the type of recruitment (including social media) as well as the online nature of the study probably appealed more to people with an Internet affinity. It is possible that persons with a higher affinity for the Internet and online activities also show higher overall values in cyberchondria. Compared to the study by 
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">Barke et al. (2016)</xref>, however, the sample of this study showed lower values in two subscales (and a higher and a comparable value in another subscale each). Concerning the information on the pandemic, the subjective evaluation of being informed was assessed, as it was assumed that the subjective experience is more associated with anxiety than with objectively assessed knowledge (e.g., through a quiz). However, it would have been interesting to examine whether the subjective evaluation is related to the objectively assessed knowledge and how the latter is related to anxiety. The virus anxiety in December 2019 and end of January 2020 was retrospectively recorded. This data could be influenced by memory bias, by interpretations depending on the current context (e.g., “Currently the pandemic is much stronger, I was hardly worried at all at an earlier time”), or by assumptions about a possible course. Overall, it would be promising for future studies to conduct longitudinal studies (e.g., ecological momentary assessments) to assess anxiety during virus outbreaks in order to be able to draw causal conclusions. Since the implementation of this study, three standardized self-report measures have been published that were specifically designed to assess anxiety and distress during the coronavirus pandemic, the "COVID Stress Scales" (CSS; 
 <xref rid="bib0350" ref-type="bibr">Taylor et al., 2020</xref>; e.g., "I am worried about catching the virus."), the "Fear of COVID Scale" (FC-19S; 
 <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Ahorsu et al., 2020</xref>; e.g., "I am most afraid of coronavirus-19."), and the "Coronavirus Anxiety Scale" (CAS; 
 <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">Lee, 2020</xref>; e.g., "I had trouble falling or staying asleep because I was thinking about the coronavirus."). Due to the heterogeneity of measurement methods and individual, non-validated, questions in previous studies, it would be essential for the comparability and validity of studies on anxiety and distress in the context of the COVID-19 pandemic that these instruments continue to be tested and are increasingly used in future COVID-19 studies.
</p>
