<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0165">Considering the sample characteristics, this sample reported a slightly higher trait health anxiety (SHAI) compared to the average in previous non-clinical samples, however overall, the level of health anxiety can be described as relatively low compared to individuals with hypochondriasis (
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">Alberts et al., 2013</xref>). It is possible that participants in the COVID-19 pandemic may have reported higher scores in the SHAI, as the self-report also covers the last 6 months. Alternatively, previous studies in non-clinical samples have been conducted almost exclusively on student samples that differ from the sample examined here in terms of socio-demographic variables (e.g., younger average age, higher average educational level), which could possibly also explain (smaller) differences in the SHAI scores. In comparison to an earlier study on cybechondria in the German general population (
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">Barke et al., 2016</xref>), we found higher average scores in the subscale "compulsion" and lower average scores in the subscales "excessiveness" and "reassurance". Because we have adapted the CSS for the pandemic (e.g., search for symptoms associated with SARS-CoV-2 infection), the results are only comparable to a limited extent. It is possible that due to the current media presence of the COVID-19 pandemic (
 <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2020</xref>), during the pandemic people may be more often distracted from their activities and occupations by this topic, which could explain the increased scores in the subscale "compulsion". With regard to the subscales "excessiveness" and "reassurance", the lower levels found here could be explained by the fact that possible symptoms of an infection are searched online less often compared to other topics of the pandemic, and that during the COVID-19 pandemic doctors are visited less often (
 <xref rid="bib0240" ref-type="bibr">Mehrotra, Chernew, Linetsky, Hatch, &amp; Cutler, 2020</xref>).
</p>
