<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Besides that, the presence of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> in Brazil was first recorded in 1986 in Rio de Janeiro,
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>30</sup>
 </xref> while in Recife it was detected only after 1996, within PNCD larval surveillance. Its first notification in a silvatic area was in a remnant of the Atlantic Forest
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref> closely located to Sítio dos Pintos, our study area. The present study showed a widespread population of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>, in this neighbourhood whose eggs were found in 67% of s-ovts in T1 and 75% in T2. In those same samples, most s-ovts were colonised by both species demonstrating their co-occupation of the environment and the potential colonisation of the same oviposition sites in that area. Moreover, no difference was observed in the relative abundance of 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> species in the samples collected eight years later, when ~70% of the eggs were laid by 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and ~30% by 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>. Dataset showed that 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> coexist in the same physical space in an area of ongoing human population expansion with vegetation spots that displays both urban and rural characteristics, and our dataset from two independent moments do not provide evidence of the displacement of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> by 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>. Therefore, their populations are not concentrated in clearly distinct territories, as it has been observed in other studies which showed 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> was associated with more vegetation and 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> in urban sprawl,
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>28</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>30</sup>
 </xref> and Sítio dos Pintos area could be under transition. The high percentage of traps simultaneously containing eggs of both species appears to indicate a process of continuous dispersion and naturally occupying the breeding sites available in the environment, as expected from invasive species.
</p>
