<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">61870</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-61870-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Tracing the transmission dynamics of HIV-1 CRF55_01B</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zai</surname><given-names>Junjie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Haizhou</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Zhenzhen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chaillon</surname><given-names>Antoine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Davey</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Yi</given-names></name><address><email>liyi@whsw.edu.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Xingguang</given-names></name><address><email>xingguanglee@hotmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2331 6153</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.49470.3e</institution-id><institution>Hubei Engineering Research Center of Viral Vector, </institution><institution>Wuhan University of Bioengineering, </institution></institution-wrap>Wuhan, 430415 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Centre for Emerging Infectious Diseases, The State Key Laboratory of Virology, Wuhan Institute of Virology, University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Wuhan, 430071 China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8803 2373</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.198530.6</institution-id><institution>Non-communicable Chronic Disease Prevention &#x00026; Control Division, Guangxi Center for Disease Control and Prevention, </institution></institution-wrap>Nanning, 530028 China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2107 4242</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.266100.3</institution-id><institution>Department of Medicine, </institution><institution>University of California San Diego, </institution></institution-wrap>California, United States of America </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>5098</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">To investigate the genetic diversity, spatiotemporal dynamics, and transmission networks of HIV-1 CRF55_01B epidemic in China. A total of 209 partial <italic>pol</italic> gene sequences of HIV-1 CRF55_01B were sampled during 2007&#x02013;2015 from 7 provinces of China. Phylogenetic analyses and trait diffusion process of these sequences were performed using Bayesian methods. Distance-based molecular network analyses were performed to infer putative relationships. Characteristics of genetically linked individuals were analyzed. Our study identified that HIV-1 CRF55_01B likely originated among men who have sex with men (MSM) in Guangdong province in January 2003 (April 2000&#x02013;April 2005), and that Guangdong province and MSM are major hubs for the spread of the HIV-1 CRF55_01B epidemic in China. A Bayesian Skygrid plot revealed that the effective population size of HIV-1 CRF55_01B experienced increased phase followed by a plateau. All sequences from persons of unknown risk clustered within groups who reported MSM risk. This could be because Chinese MSM may not report such risk due to HIV/AIDS-related stigmatization and discrimination. This study inferred the transmission dynamics of the HIV-1 CRF55_01B epidemic in China at high resolution. The methods developed in this study may be critical for designing effective HIV prevention strategies in China and beyond.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Genome informatics</kwd><kwd>Evolutionary genetics</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100001809</institution-id><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China (National Science Foundation of China)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>31470268</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Yi</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">The prevalence of HIV-1 among men who have sex with men (MSM) continues to increase in China, especially in its big cities, like Beijing, Shanghai, Guangzhou, Shenzhen, Shenyang, Shijiazhuang<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. The main HIV-1 subtypes circulating in China are subtype B&#x02019; and circulating recombinant forms (CRFs), including CRF01_AE, CRF07_BC, CRF08_BC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Co-circulation of multiple subtypes of HIV-1 strains among high risk groups, like injecting drug users (IDUs) and MSM, favors the generation of new CRFs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Interestingly, CRF 55_01B was first reported in 2013 among MSM from Changsha city of Hunan province and Dongguan city of Guangdong province in China and it was composed of CRF01_AE and subtype B<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. However, the earliest known strain of CRF55_01B was traced back to 2007 in sample from Shenzhen of Guangdong province among MSM<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Now, CRF55_01B is mainly distributed in Guangdong and neighboring provinces in China, and is found across all risk groups<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Despite this research, we still have an incomplete understanding the origin and evolutionary history of the CRF55_01B epidemic in China.</p><p id="Par3">In the present study, we employed state-of-the-art methods to define the spatiotemporal dynamics, transmission networks, geographic origins, and migration patterns of CRF55_01B based on 209 partial <italic>pol</italic> gene sequences of CRF55_01B with known sampling dates (2007&#x02013;2015) and geographic locations (7 provinces) primarily among MSM in China. We also estimated the maximum posterior probability risk group for each sequence with unknown risk, for the first time, to uncover the key socio-cultural factors (e.g. HIV/AIDS-related stigmatization and discrimination) behind it. Our study provides insights into the origin and evolutionary history of CRF55_01B epidemic in China. The methods developed in this study may be critical for designing effective HIV prevention strategies in China and beyond.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Sequence data set</title><p id="Par4">All available partial <italic>pol</italic> gene sequences of CRF55_01B (2253&#x02013;3308 nt relative to HXB2) with known sampling year and province of collection were retrieved from the Los Alamos National Laboratory (LANL) HIV Sequence Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hiv.lanl.gov">http://www.hiv.lanl.gov</ext-link>). Where multiple sequences were available per individual, only one was selected. Quality Control and RIP v.3.0<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup> from the LANL site were used to analyze the quality and confirm the genotype assignment of all sequences, respectively. Hypermut v2.0 from the LANL site was performed to analysis the hypermutation of all sequences<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. For this data set, sequences were aligned using Gene Cutter from the LANL site and then adjusted manually using BioEdit v7.2.5<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. The final dataset included 209 partial <italic>pol</italic> gene sequences of CRF55_01B with known sampling year and province between 2007&#x02013;2015.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Phylogenetic analyses</title><p id="Par5">To examine the phylogenetic signal for this data set, a likelihood-mapping analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup> was performed using TREE-PUZZLE v5.3.rc16<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. To evaluate the temporal structure for this data set, we performed root-to-tip genetic distance against year of sampling using TempEst v1.5<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. We then employed a Bayesian phylogenetic approach to estimate the rate of evolution and the time to the most recent common ancestor (tMRCA) for this data using a GTR&#x02009;+&#x02009;G substitution model with an uncorrelated lognormal relaxed-clock model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> and a Bayesian Skygrid coalescent tree prior<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup> in BEAST v1.8.2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. The Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) analysis was run for 500 million steps with sampling every 50,000 steps. Convergence was evaluated by calculating the effective sample sizes (ESSs) of the parameters using Tracer v1.7.1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Trees were summarized as maximum clade credibility (MCC) trees using TreeAnnotator after discarding the first 10% as burn-in, and then visualized in FigTree v1.4.3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree</ext-link>).</p><p id="Par6">To test the hypothesis that a tip with a province or risk group is more likely to share that discrete-trait with a neighboring adjoining tip than would be expected by chance, we calculated the association index (AI), Fitch parsimony score (PS), and monophyletic clade size (MC) statistics for each discrete-trait using Bayesian Tip-Significance Testing (BaTS) v0.9 beta<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, as previous described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. We reject the null hypothesis for a significance level of 0.001, 0.001, and 0.05 for AI, PS, and MC statistics, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Ancestral reconstructions of discrete traits</title><p id="Par7">We employed a Bayesian phylogenetic method to infer the ancestral discrete traits for this data set. To do this, we modelled two types of traits (e.g. geographic location and risk group) as a diffusion process among discrete states<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> in BEAST v1.8.2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Diffusion among discrete traits was modelled using a non-reversible continuous-time Markov chain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Bayesian stochastic search variable selection was used to identify non-zero migration rates between each pair of traits. In addition, we estimate the expected number of viral migrations using &#x02018;Markov jump counts&#x02019; approaches<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> between each pair of traits. The phylogeographic history was visualized using SpreaD3 v0.9.6<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Transmission network reconstruction</title><p id="Par8">We employed HIV TRAnsmission Cluster Engine (HIV-TRACE; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hivtrace.org">www.hivtrace.org</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> to infer transmission network clusters for this data set (e.g. closely related sequences inferring a transmission network). All pairwise distances were calculated and a putative linkage between each pair of two sequences was considered whenever their divergent was &#x02264;0.02 substitutions/site (TN93 substitution model). When calculating pairwise genetic distance, all nucleotide ambiguities were resolved and only sequences with less than 0.2% ambiguities were retained. Multiple linkages were then combined into putative transmission clusters. Clusters comprised of only two linked nodes were identified as dyads. This approach detected clusters of recent transmission in which the clustering viruses are genetically similar, implying a direct or indirect epidemiological connection<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Social-demographic characteristics of this data set</title><p id="Par9">This data set included 209 sequences of CRF55_01B strains from various risk groups: heterosexuals (Hetero, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;27), injecting drug users (IDUs, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1), MSM (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;169), and unknown risk (n/a, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;12). The samples are obtained from 7 Chinese provinces: Anhui (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2), Guangdong (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;166), Guangxi (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8), Hebei (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10), Hunan (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2), Shanghai (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;18), and Zhejiang (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3), with sampling years between 2007 and 2015 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). The main risk groups were MSM (80.86%) and Hetero (12.92%). The samples were primarily from Guangdong (79.43%) and Shanghai (8.6%).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Geographic source, sampling year, and risk factor for HIV-1 CRF55_01B strains used in the present study.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Geographic source</th><th rowspan="2">Sampling year</th><th rowspan="2">n</th><th colspan="4">Risk factor<sup>a</sup></th></tr><tr><th>Hetero</th><th>IDU</th><th>MSM</th><th>n/a</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Anhui</td><td>2011</td><td>2</td><td/><td/><td>2</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Guangdong</td><td>2007&#x02013;2013</td><td>166</td><td>23</td><td>1</td><td>142</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Guangxi</td><td>2009&#x02013;2013</td><td>8</td><td>1</td><td/><td/><td>7</td></tr><tr><td>Hebei</td><td>2013&#x02013;2015</td><td>10</td><td>2</td><td/><td>4</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>Hunan</td><td>2010&#x02013;2011</td><td>2</td><td/><td/><td>2</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Shanghai</td><td>2011&#x02013;2013</td><td>18</td><td/><td/><td>18</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Zhejiang</td><td>2013&#x02013;2014</td><td>3</td><td>1</td><td/><td>1</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Total</bold></td><td/><td><bold>209</bold></td><td><bold>27</bold></td><td><bold>1</bold></td><td><bold>169</bold></td><td><bold>12</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Risk factor: Hetero, heterosexual; IDU, injecting drug user; MSM, men having sex with men; n/a, not available.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Transmission network analysis</title><p id="Par10">To identify putative genetic linkage between 2 individuals, we first performed a sensitivity analysis across a plausible range of genetic distance threshold ranging from 0.1% to 2.0%. We found that transmission clusters started to coalesce and the transmission network lost resolution when the genetic distance &#x0003e;0.2% for this data set (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Therefore, we considered individuals as being genetically linked when the genetic distance between HIV-1 CRF55_01B <italic>pol</italic> sequences was &#x0003c;0.2%. This allowed us identify 27 clusters that included 98/209 (46.89%) sequences. Clusters ranged in size from 2 to 15 sequences, and 13 (48.15%) had 3 or more sequences (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>; Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>; Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). Two clusters included at least 10 sequences, and were considered &#x02018;large&#x02019; clusters. Both of the two large clusters included sequences exclusively from Guangdong, ranging in size from 10 to 15 sequences (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>; Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). The largest cluster of 15 sequences included exclusively from MSM. However, the other large cluster of 10 sequences included both from MSM and Hetero, and was a predominantly comprised of sequences from people with &#x02018;Hetero&#x02019; risk (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>; Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Number of clusters and maximum cluster size, as a function of the TN93 distance threshold. Genetic distance at 0.002 substitutions/site was highlighted with a dash line. Color-coded network parameters are shown on the top left.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_61870_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e749"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Transmission clusters of HIV-1 CRF55_01B. The structure of inferred CRF55_01B transmission clusters from our data set are illustrated. Nodes (circles) represent connected individuals in the overall network, and putative transmission linkages are represented by edges (lines). Nodes are color coded by the province of origin.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_61870_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e758"/></fig></p><p id="Par11">Of the 27 inferred clusters, 84 (85.71%), 7 (7.14%), and 6 (6.12%) included individuals sampled in Guangdong, Hebei, and Shanghai. Notably, 19 (70.37%) and 3 (11.11%) of 27 clusters were comprised of individuals from only Guangdong and Hebei, respectively. 5 (18.52%) of 27 clusters included sequences from two provinces: 4 clusters included sequences from Guangdong and Shanghai, and 1 from Guangdong and Hebei (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>; Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>).</p><p id="Par12">We found that 6 clusters (22.22%) included persons reporting both Hetero and MSM, and only 1 cluster (3.70%) included persons only reporting Hetero risk (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>; Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>).</p><p id="Par13">Of the 27 (12.92%) sequences from individuals identifying as Hetero, 14 (51.85%) clustered with at least one other sequence, and 83 (49.11%) of the 169 sequences from individuals identifying as MSM clustered.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Likelihood-mapping and evolutionary divergence analysis</title><p id="Par14">For this data set, our likelihood-mapping analysis revealed a strong phylogenetic signal (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). The correlation between root-to-tip distances and sampling year indicated a relative strong temporal signal (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.307), with an estimated substitution rate of 1.64&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> substitutions per site per year and the time to the most recent common ancestor of July 2003 (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>).</p><p id="Par15">Bayesian evolutionary analyses revealed that the evolutionary rate of CRF55_01B was 1.68&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> substitutions per site per year [95% highest posterior density (HPD) interval: 1.33&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>&#x02013;2.05&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>), and tMRCA of CRF55_01B was January 2003 (95% HPD interval: April 2000 and April 2005).</p><p id="Par16">We further investigated the estimated population dynamics of CRF55_01B using a Bayesian Skygrid plot, which reflects the changes in effective population size (<italic>Ne</italic>) over time. The dynamic of the <italic>Ne</italic> showed two distinct phases: (1) exponential growth (2005&#x02013;2008 and 2008&#x02013;2010) followed by (2) declining phase (2011&#x02013;2013) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Bayesian Skygrid demographic reconstruction of HIV-1 CRF55_01B. The vertical axis shows the effective number of infections (<italic>N</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub>) multiplied by mean viral generation time (&#x003c4;). The solid line and shaded region represent the median and 95% credibility interval, respectively, of the inferred <italic>N</italic><sub><italic>e</italic></sub>&#x003c4; through time.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_61870_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e844"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Phylogenetic association with geographic location and risk group</title><p id="Par17">Based on the AI and PS statistics of geographic location and risk group traits, we rejected the null hypothesis with <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). For the MC statistic of geographic location trait, we also rejected the null hypothesis (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), with the exception of the MC (Anhui) and MC (Shanghai) statistics (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). However, for the MC statistic of risk group trait, we accepted the null hypothesis (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Both the transmission network and MC statistic model analyses showed mixed between risk group (e.g. MSM and Hetero).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Statistical analysis of province of CRF55_01B sequences used in the present study.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Statistic</th><th>No. of sequences</th><th>Observed mean (95% CI)</th><th>Null mean (95% CI)</th><th><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>AI</td><td/><td>5.2 (4.5, 5.8)</td><td>8.4 (7.4, 9.4)</td><td>0*</td></tr><tr><td>PS</td><td/><td>31.9 (30.0, 33.0)</td><td>42.1 (40.7, 42.9)</td><td>0*</td></tr><tr><td>MC (Anhui)</td><td>2</td><td>1.0 (1.0, 1.0)</td><td>1.0 (1.0, 1.0)</td><td>N/A</td></tr><tr><td>MC (Guangdong)</td><td>166</td><td>15.3 (14.0, 17.0)</td><td>10.6 (8.2, 14.8)</td><td>0.0356*</td></tr><tr><td>MC (Guangxi)</td><td>8</td><td>2.0 (2.0, 2.0)</td><td>1.1 (1.0, 1.8)</td><td>0.0263*</td></tr><tr><td>MC (Hebei)</td><td>10</td><td>2.0 (2.0, 2.0)</td><td>1.1 (1.0, 2.0)</td><td>0.0484*</td></tr><tr><td>MC (Hunan)</td><td>2</td><td>2.0 (2.0, 2.0)</td><td>1.0 (1.0, 1.0)</td><td>0.0011*</td></tr><tr><td>MC (Shanghai)</td><td>18</td><td>2.0 (2.0, 2.0)</td><td>1.4 (1.0, 2.0)</td><td>0.1724</td></tr><tr><td>MC (Zhejiang)</td><td>3</td><td>2.0 (2.0, 2.0)</td><td>1.0 (1.0, 1.0)</td><td>0.0028*</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>AI, association index.</p><p>PS, parsimony score.</p><p>MC, monophyletic clade statistic.</p><p>95% CI, 95% credbility interval.</p><p>*Statistically significant (P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p><p>N/A, not available because of the observed 95% CI contains the null 95% CI.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Statistical analysis of risk group of CRF55_01B sequences used in the present study.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Statistic<sup>a</sup></th><th>No. of sequences</th><th>Observed mean (95% CI)</th><th>Null mean (95% CI)</th><th><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>AI</td><td/><td>5.2 (4.3, 6.2)</td><td>7.6 (6.6, 8.6)</td><td>0*</td></tr><tr><td>PS</td><td/><td>32.5 (30.0, 35.0)</td><td>38.4 (36.6, 39.7)</td><td>0.0001*</td></tr><tr><td>MC (Hetero)</td><td>27</td><td>2.4 (2.0, 4.0)</td><td>1.8 (1.1, 2.3)</td><td>0.4126</td></tr><tr><td>MC (IDU)</td><td>1</td><td>1.0 (1.0, 1.0)</td><td>1.0 (1.0, 1.0)</td><td>N/A</td></tr><tr><td>MC (MSM)</td><td>169</td><td>13.0 (9.0, 18.0)</td><td>11.3 (8.7, 15.2)</td><td>0.2809</td></tr><tr><td>MC (n/a)</td><td>12</td><td>2.0 (2.0, 2.0)</td><td>1.2 (1.0, 2.0)</td><td>0.0700</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>AI, association index.</p><p>PS, parsimony score.</p><p>MC, monophyletic clade statistic.</p><p>95% CI, 95% credbility interval.</p><p>*Statistically significant (P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p><p>N/A, not available because of the observed 95% CI contains the null 95% CI.</p><p><sup>a</sup>Risk factor: Hetero, heterosexual; IDU, injecting drug user; MSM, men having sex with men; n/a, not available.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Dynamics analysis of ancestral discrete traits</title><p id="Par18">Our phylogeographic analysis revealed that the most probable root location of CRF55_01B ancestor was in Guangdong among MSM in January 2003 (posterior state probability&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.0) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>; Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). Our results also revealed that Guangdong acted as a diffusion center to other provinces (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). After the introduction of the virus from Guangdong to Shanghai, Shanghai acted as a secondary diffusion province. In addition, there were one bidirectional transition event from the Shanghai to Guangdong (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Most viral transitions between epidemiologically linked provinces were from Guangdong to Shanghai (mean estimate 14.81; 95% HPD interval: 11.70&#x02013;17.67; Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5</xref>). Our results also showed that the estimated of the most posterior probability of all of 12 sequences with unknown risk were grouped into MSM ranging from 0.67 to 0.93.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Maximum-clade-credibility tree estimated from partial <italic>pol</italic> gene sequences of HIV-1 CRF55_01B. Nodes are color coded by the most probable geographic location of the descendent branches.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_61870_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1234"/></fig><fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Visualization of geographic location transitions for HIV-1 CRF55_01B overlaid on a geographical map. Points are color coded by the geographic location of origin. Lines are color coded by the geographic location of destination.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_61870_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e1243"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par19">Our evolutionary analyses, based on 209 partial <italic>pol</italic> gene sequences of HIV-1 CRF55_01B that included province of origin and year of sampling, confirmed that this subtype had spread widely within China (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Our estimates of the evolutionary rate for CRF55_01B was reassuringly consistent across different methods and models. Further, our estimate of the 95% HPD interval of the evolutionary rate for CRF55_01B (1.33&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>&#x02013;2.05&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>) had a very narrow range and also included in those obtained from previous study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Our estimate of the 95% HPD interval of tMRCA for CRF55_01B (April 2000&#x02013;April 2005) was overlapping with, but not similar to, the reported estimates from two previously studies, which ranged from February 1996 to June 2004<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup> and from June 1996 to January 2004<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. The uncertainty in our estimate is much smaller than those of previous estimates because of the wider temporal span and more provinces of the samples included in our data set.</p><p id="Par20">Coalescent-based demographic inference revealed a rapidly increasing population size for CRF55_01B from initial phase during 2005&#x02013;2010, consistent with the outbreak during this period of time. However, we also detected a subsequent phase of rapid declining population size during 2011&#x02013;2013 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Furthermore, we found that province was indeed having a significant influence on the complex transmission dynamics of CRF55_01B (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Phylogeny of CRF55_01B was more likely structured by discrete geographic location traits, especially for Guangdong and Hebei provinces. However, phylogeny of CRF55_01B did not structure by risk group traits, especially for MSM and Hetero risk groups, indicating that MSM and Hetero were mixing with each other (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). This may be explained by that many men in China who reported heterosexual exposure were actually bisexual with ongoing risk exposures to men and women, but they did not report their male sexual contact due to HIV/AIDS-related stigmatization and discrimination<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Our results showed that all sequences from persons of unknown risk clustered within groups who reported MSM risk. This could be because Chinese MSM may not report such risk due to HIV/AIDS-related stigmatization and discrimination.</p><p id="Par21">Our phylogeographic reconstruction for this data set demonstrated that the origin of CRF55_01B was located among MSM in Guangdong between April 2000 and April 2005 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>; Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). However, we found that Guangdong was the most important hub of dissemination of CRF55_01B outbreak, fueling the origin of new local epidemics in Shanghai and other provinces (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). We also identified one bidirectional transition event between Shanghai and Guangdong. These results indicate the complex spatial dynamics of CRF55_01B.</p><p id="Par22">In the present study, we identified 27 highly related clusters within the CRF55_01B outbreak, including two large clusters detected among MSM and heterosexual men and women in Guangdong (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>; Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>; Supplementary Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). Among the 27 highly related clusters, 22 included sequences from a single province (19 from Guangdong and 3 from Hebei). These clusters ranged in size from 2 to 15 sequences, and included sequences from persons with MSM and heterosexual risk. The other 5 clusters included sequences from two provinces (e.g. Guangdong and Hebei/Shanghai) exclusively from persons with MSM risk. These clusters ranged in size from 2 to 3 sequences. We acknowledge that large clusters are theoretically more likely to include sequences from multiple origins and that these larger clusters may have been identified because of a more intense sampling in a specific region or during a specific period. These results supported a complex scenario of CRF55_01B that was introduced into epidemiologically linked, high-risk groups in China. Such knowledge can be used to help identify new outbreaks of HIV or specific CRFs in near real-time. Since HIV-1 CRF55_01B is primarily exclusive to China, sequences that did not cluster likely represent missed links from inadequate sampling, which is an issue for all molecular epidemiology studies using real world data. Sequences without these links could not be assessed for their origin, therefore we cannot exclude that the possibility that sampling depth hindered our network inferences. Further deep and wide sampling might reveal the presence of additional CRF55_01B clusters. As more sequences are characterized within other provinces of China, more local, regional, and national clusters are likely to emerge, presenting a challenge to HIV control.</p><p id="Par23">Taken together, our results shed light on the spatial and temporal origins of HIV-1 CRF55_01B, and its mode of spread across comparable geographic areas, and suggest that socio-cultural factors (e.g. HIV/AIDS-related stigmatization and discrimination) should attract enough attention in China and beyond. People&#x02019;s attitudes and practices concerning HIV/AIDS have an important influence on prevention and control HIV spread. Our results also emphasize the importance of using phylodynamic analyses and transmission networks to provide insights into the role of MSM in the spread of HIV in China. These efforts, combined with epidemiological investigation, are needed to track changes in HIV epidemics. Understanding these epidemic dynamics in real time is increasingly public health importance in terms of guiding prevention efforts.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec14"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2020_61870_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>SUPPLEMENTARY INFO.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>These authors contributed equally: Junjie Zai, Haizhou Liu, Zhenzhen Lu, Yi Li and Xingguang Li.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p>is available for this paper at 10.1038/s41598-020-61870-x.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by a grant from National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 31470268) to Prof. Yi Li. Dr. Smith was supported for this work by the San Diego Center for AIDS Research (NIH AI036214). The authors would like to thank Prof. Philippe Lemey, Prof. Simon Y. W. HO, Prof. Marcia L. Kalish, Prof. Brian Foley and Dr. Gytis Dudas for their technical support.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>X.L. conceived and designed the study, performed the experiments, and drafted the manuscript. X.L. and A.C. analyzed the data. X.L., D.S., A.C., H.L., Z.L., Y.L. and J.Z. interpreted data and provided critical comments. All authors reviewed and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par24">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HIV and syphilis prevalence among men who have sex with men: a cross-sectional survey of 61 cities in China</article-title><source>Clin. Infect. Dis.</source><year>2013</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>298</fpage><lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/cit210</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23580732?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23580732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A rapidly increasing incidence of HIV and syphilis among men who have sex with men in a major city of China</article-title><source>AIDS Res. Hum. Retroviruses</source><year>2011</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1139</fpage><lpage>1140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/AID.2010.0356</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21388334?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21388334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular epidemiology of HIV-1 in Jilin province, northeastern China: emergence of a new CRF07_BC transmission cluster and intersubtype recombinants</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e110738</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110738</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25356726?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25356726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Near full-length genome sequence of a novel HIV-1 recombinant form (CRF01_AE/B) detected among men who have sex with men in Jilin Province, China</article-title><source>AIDS Res. Hum. Retroviruses</source><year>2014</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>701</fpage><lpage>705</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/AID.2014.0008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24521207?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24521207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Near full-length genome sequence of a novel HIV type 1 second-generation recombinant form (CRF01_AE/CRF07_BC) identified among men who have sex with men in Jilin, China</article-title><source>AIDS Res. Hum. Retroviruses</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1604</fpage><lpage>1608</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/AID.2013.0116</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23809010?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23809010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Han, X. <italic>et al</italic>. Genome Sequences of a Novel HIV-1 Circulating Recombinant Form, CRF55_01B, Identified in China. <italic>Genome Announc</italic><bold>1</bold>, 10.1128/genomeA.00050-12 (2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Origin and outbreak of HIV-1 CRF55_01B among MSM in Shenzhen, China</article-title><source>J. Acquir. Immune Defic. Syndr.</source><year>2014</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>e65</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/QAI.0000000000000144</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24662297?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24662297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A Large-scale Survey of CRF55_01B from Men-Who-Have-Sex-with-Men in China: implying the Evolutionary History and Public Health Impact</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>18147</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep18147</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26667846?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26667846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siepel</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Halpern</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Macken</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Korber</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A computer program designed to screen rapidly for HIV type 1 intersubtype recombinant sequences</article-title><source>AIDS Res. Hum. Retroviruses</source><year>1995</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1413</fpage><lpage>1416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/aid.1995.11.1413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8573400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Korber</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detecting hypermutations in viral sequences with an emphasis on G&#x02013;&#x0003e; A hypermutation</article-title><source>Bioinforma.</source><year>2000</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>400</fpage><lpage>401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/16.4.400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hall, T. A. BioEdit: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for Windows 95/98/NT. <italic>Nucleic Acids Symposium Series</italic><bold>41</bold>, 95&#x02013;98, doi:citeulike-article-id:691774 (1999).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strimmer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>von Haeseler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Likelihood-mapping: a simple method to visualize phylogenetic content of a sequence alignment</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>1997</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>6815</fpage><lpage>6819</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.94.13.6815</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9192648?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9192648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Strimmer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Vingron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>von Haeseler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TREE-PUZZLE: maximum likelihood phylogenetic analysis using quartets and parallel computing</article-title><source>Bioinforma.</source><year>2002</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>502</fpage><lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/18.3.502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Max Carvalho</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pybus</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring the temporal structure of heterochronous sequences using TempEst (formerly Path-O-Gen)</article-title><source>Virus evolution</source><year>2016</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>vew007</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ve/vew007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27774300?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27774300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relaxed phylogenetics and dating with confidence</article-title><source>PLoS Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e88</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0040088</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16683862?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16683862</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improving Bayesian population dynamics inference: a coalescent-based model for multiple loci</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mss265</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23180580?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23180580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Suchard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bayesian phylogenetics with BEAUti and the BEAST 1.7</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1969</fpage><lpage>1973</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mss075</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22367748?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22367748</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Baele</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Suchard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Posterior Summarization in Bayesian Phylogenetics Using Tracer 1.7</article-title><source>Syst. Biol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>901</fpage><lpage>904</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sysbio/syy032</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29718447?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29718447</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pybus</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlating viral phenotypes with phylogeny: accounting for phylogenetic uncertainty</article-title><source>Infection, Genet. evolution: J. Mol. Epidemiol. Evolut. Genet. Infect. Dis.</source><year>2008</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2007.08.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tracing the epidemic history of HIV-1 CRF01_AE clusters using near-complete genome sequences</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>4024</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-03820-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28642469?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28642469</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Suchard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bayesian phylogeography finds its roots</article-title><source>PLoS computational Biol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e1000520</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000520</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minin</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name><name><surname>Suchard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Counting labeled transitions in continuous-time Markov models of evolution</article-title><source>J. Math. Biol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00285-007-0120-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17874105?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17874105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minin</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name><name><surname>Suchard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast, accurate and simulation-free stochastic mapping</article-title><source>Philos. Trans. R. Soc. London. Ser. B, Biol. Sci.</source><year>2008</year><volume>363</volume><fpage>3985</fpage><lpage>3995</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2008.0176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18852111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Brien</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Minin</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name><name><surname>Suchard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Learning to count: robust estimates for labeled distances between molecular sequences</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. evolution</source><year>2009</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>801</fpage><lpage>814</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msp003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bielejec</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SpreaD3: Interactive Visualization of Spatiotemporal History and Trait Evolutionary Processes</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. evolution</source><year>2016</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>2167</fpage><lpage>2169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msw082</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kosakovsky Pond</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Leigh Brown</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wertheim</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HIV-TRACE (TRAnsmission Cluster Engine): a Tool for Large Scale Molecular Epidemiology of HIV-1 and Other Rapidly Evolving Pathogens</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1812</fpage><lpage>1819</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msy016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29401317?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29401317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wertheim</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Social and Genetic Networks of HIV-1 Transmission in New York City</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog.</source><year>2017</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>e1006000</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1006000</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28068413?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28068413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The dynamics of the HIV epidemic among men who have sex with men (MSM) from 2005 to 2012 in Shenzhen, China</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>28703</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep28703</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27352965?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27352965</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>