<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Plaque size is a common feature of viral characterization. Primary isolates of CHIKV containing variants with different plaque sizes were previously reported [
 <xref rid="B70-ijms-20-04657" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-ijms-20-04657" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Viral variants with different plaque morphology such as small and large plaques had been reported in the 2005 CHIKV outbreak isolates [
 <xref rid="B72-ijms-20-04657" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. It is curious how small plaque variants with lower fitness were maintained as a natural viral quasispecies. Plausible explanations indicated that the plaque size might not represent the in vivo growth conditions and that cooperation among variants with different plaque sizes might be required for optimal in vivo replication and transmission fitness. Jaimipak et al. reasoned that if the plaque size did not represent the in vivo growth conditions and the small plaque variants had a similar fitness as the large plaque variants, they would be similarly virulent in a murine model. In order to explore the virulence of the small plaque CHIKV variant in vivo, the pathogenicity of the purified small plaque variant of the CHIKV virus isolated from the sera of the patient in Phang-nga, Thailand in 2009, was tested in neonatal mice [
 <xref rid="B73-ijms-20-04657" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. The small plaque variant (CHK-S) showed stable homogenous small plaques after 4 plaque purifications. It also grew slower and produced lower titers when compared with the wild-type virus. After 21 days of infection in the suckling mice with the wild-type and CHK-S variants (injected 103 pfu/mouse), mice which received the CHK-S virus showed 98% survival rate while only 74% of mice survived after infection with the wild-type virus. The small plaque variant of CHIKV obtained by plaque purifications exhibited decreased virulence that makes it appropriate to serve as candidates for live-attenuated vaccine development. The CHIKV variant with the small plaque size formed a major subpopulation in the CHIKV primary isolate during multiple passages in C6/36 cells. This is in line with the reduction of virulence in the suckling mice and indicated that the small plaque variant had reduced in vivo fitness. This suggested that replication cycles in mosquito vectors might play an important role in maintaining the small plaque variant in natural infections. The persistence of the small plaque variant CHK-S clone after multiple passages in C6/36 cells showed that the CHK-S variant might be able to outcompete the large plaque variant when infecting the same cell by an unknown mechanism. Alternatively, small and large plaque variants might cooperate in a way that provided a selective advantage for maintaining the small plaque variant [
 <xref rid="B73-ijms-20-04657" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>].
</p>
