<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The novel coronavirus is spreading rapidly. On January 19, the first patient was reported on the West Coast of the United States. The patient developed respiratory symptoms after a family visit to Wuhan (Holshue 
 <italic>et al.</italic>, 
 <xref rid="mbt213557-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). During hospitalization, the patient developed diarrhoea and the stool was weakly virus‐positive. This observation is important since it could indicate a gut tropism in addition to lung tropism, not unusual for coronavirus. One might therefore count on a changing symptomatology in the unfolding of the current epidemic, necessitating public health measures against faecal–oral transmission (Danchin 
 <italic>et al.</italic>, 
 <xref rid="mbt213557-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). This scenario is not unlikely, since the ACE2 host receptor for the novel coronavirus is highly expressed on gut enterocytes (Liang 
 <italic>et al.</italic>, 
 <xref rid="mbt213557-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Some change in symptomatology was already seen for Chinese patients outside of Wuhan. Among the first 2019‐nCoV patients from Beijing, upper airway congestion was the dominant finding (Chang 
 <italic>et al.</italic>, 
 <xref rid="mbt213557-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2020a</xref>). Disease in 62 laboratory‐confirmed patients from Zhejiang province showed mostly mild to moderate disease; 9% had diarrhoea, and only one patient needed ICU (Xu 
 <italic>et al.</italic>, 
 <xref rid="mbt213557-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). When analysing 72 314 cases, an overall case fatality rate (CFR) of 2.3% was calculated. However, when the analysis was limited to cases outside of the Hubei province (where Wuhan is located), the CFR was only 0.4% (Wu and McGoogan, 
 <xref rid="mbt213557-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>), possibly suggesting change of the epidemic to milder diseases with larger chains of transmission (Vetter 
 <italic>et al.</italic>, 
 <xref rid="mbt213557-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>).
</p>
