<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par40">Ecuador has in recent years experienced increases of arboviral diseases, from increased numbers of dengue infections to introductions of novel viruses - chikungunya and Zika - and their sustained spread in the country. The same pattern has also been observed in other nearby Andean countries in South America, such as Colombia and Venezuela. In addition, Venezuela’s growing social, political and economic crisis has resulted in hyperinflation, poverty, and a collapse of basic support systems, such as health care and vector control to combat the infectious diseases that are common in this area of the world. This has led to an additional increase of infections within Venezuela, with diseases such as malaria, measles, dengue, chikungunya and Zika on the rise [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. As the citizens are fleeing from the increasingly harsh living conditions in Venezuela, the concerns of spread and further rise of infectious diseases in the neighboring countries have been growing [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. In Ecuador, an increase of malaria cases has recently been observed, with the parasite reemerging in regions previously declared malaria-free [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. This includes regions in the south of the country, near the Ecuador-Peru border, which are located along the migration route from Venezuela, through Colombia and Ecuador, and into Peru. The samples analyzed in this study came from the southern coastal city of Machala. This tropical city is an important sentinel site, as it is a major port located along the Pan American Highway, near the Ecuador-Peru border. DENV is hyperendemic in Machala, and is transmitted by the 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> mosquito vector (
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> has not been detected) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. By analyzing the arboviral genomes collected in 2014–2015 from the active surveillance site in Machala, we attempt to understand the dissemination of these pathogens throughout the region, including their introductions into Ecuador and their connections to the pathogens from Venezuela and Colombia.
</p>
