<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Having established the many similarities between ZIKV and CHIKV epidemics regarding transmission and reporting, we assumed that information could be transported (as defined in [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006526.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]) between diseases and between places. Bayesian approaches allow such transportation using informative 
 <italic>a priori</italic> distributions on model parameters [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006526.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Historical data on CHIKV epidemics was therefore used to build informative 
 <italic>a priori</italic> distributions on the two key parameters 
 <inline-formula id="pntd.0006526.e038">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="pntd.0006526.e038.jpg" id="pntd.0006526.e038g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M38">
    <msub>
     <mi mathvariant="script">R</mi>
     <mrow>
      <mn>0</mn>
      <mo>,</mo>
      <mi>Z</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </inline-formula> and 
 <italic>ρ</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>Z</italic>
 </sub>. Hierarchical models are particularly adapted to this task, as they naturally pool information among several past epidemics and capture both within- and between-location variability [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006526.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. We used separate hierarchical models to obtain information about (i) transmissibility and reporting during CHIKV outbreaks in the French West Indies and (ii) relative transmissibility and reporting between ZIKV and CHIKV in French Polynesia, rather than from a global joint model (as in [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006526.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]). This choice was made to show that prior information can be combined from separate sources in a modular way. We finally considered two versions of informative priors to capture different degrees of knowledge. The “Local” priors corresponded with estimates for the previous CHIKV epidemic in the same island, therefore including island-specific epidemic drivers, such as population structure and distribution, socio-economic circumstances and environmental conditions. On the other hand, the “Regional” priors encompassed the diversity of past observations within the region, making priors valid for a typical island of the West Indies, especially when no other epidemic has been observed previously.
</p>
