<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Adenovirus in tissue specimens was detected by immunofluorescence staining. The Psittacine adenovirus HKU1 fiber protein was cloned and expressed to generate specific antibodies. The gene was amplified by primers 
 <named-content content-type="gene">5′-GCGAGCTAGCATGTGGCATTTTACTGCAGCCAGT-3′</named-content> and 
 <named-content content-type="gene">5′-CACTAAGCTTTTATTGTAGTGAAATAAAAGCAGAA-3′</named-content>. The fiber fragment was then cloned into the 
 <italic>Nhe</italic>I and 
 <italic>Hind</italic>III sites of expression vector pET-28b(+) (Novagen, Madison, Wisconsin) in frame and downstream of a series of six histidine residues. The His6-tagged recombinant fiber protein was expressed and purified by Ni2+-loaded HiTrap chelating system (GE Healthcare, Buckinghamshire, United Kingdom) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Specific guinea pig antiserum was produced by injecting 200 µg of purified His6-tagged recombinant fiber protein, along with an equal volume of complete Freund's adjuvant, into the thighs of guinea pigs intramuscularly. Incomplete Freund's adjuvant was used in subsequent immunizations. Three inoculations were completed in six weeks, with one injection every two weeks. Serum samples were collected two weeks after the last injection. Immunofluorescence staining for adenovirus fiber protein antigen was performed as described previously 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003318-Woo1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. The tissue sections were deparaffinized and rehydrated, followed by blocking with 1% bovine serum albumin in PBS to minimize non-specific binding. The sections were incubated overnight with immune serum from guinea pigs at 4°C. After washing three times with PBS, the sections were incubated with FITC-conjugated rabbit anti-guinea pig IgG (Life technology, Invitrogen, Carlsbad, California) at 1∶50 dilution for 30 min at room temperature. The images were captured by Nikon 80i imaging system with Spot Advanced Software. The animal experiment has been approved by the Committee on the Use of Live Animals in Teaching and Research, The University of Hong Kong, in accordance with the Guidelines laid down by the NIH in the USA regarding the care and use of animals for experimental procedures (CULATR 2489-11).
</p>
