<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Coronaviruses produce RNA intermediates such as dsRNA and ssRNA during replication in host cells. In contrast, mammalian host cells cannot produce such RNA species from RNA templates. These RNA intermediates can be detected through innate immune sensors, leading to antiviral effector activation. However, the RNA intermediates can shield their features in the replication organelles (ROs) from PRR detection, thereby suppressing the intracellular innate immune responses in the cytoplasm [
 <xref rid="B89-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. The intracellular membrane ROs are convoluted double-membrane vesicles formed by the host endoplasmic reticulum, which are thought to be associated with the viral synthesis of positive-stranded RNA [
 <xref rid="B90-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. Coronaviruses, like all positive-stranded RNA viruses, hijack endoplasmic reticulum membranes to form their headquarters for viral RNA synthesis exclusively in the cytosol. A previous study showed that nonstructural proteins (nsp) 3, 4, and 6 of SARS-CoV are specific hydrophobic viral proteins that contain transmembrane domains for the formation of double-membrane vesicles [
 <xref rid="B91-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. Similarly, MERS-CoV nsp3 and nsp4 can also mimic the formation of ROs, shielding their viral dsRNA from innate immune sensors in the cytosol, such as MDA5 and RIG-I [
 <xref rid="B92-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. Compared with the formation of convoluted membranes of Alpha and Betacoronaviruses, the specific formation of a zippered endoplasmic reticulum with tethered double-membrane spherules was observed in the Gammacoronavirus avian infectious bronchitis virus [
 <xref rid="B93-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>] and porcine Deltacoronavirus [
 <xref rid="B94-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>,
 <xref rid="B95-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. However, there is still little known about the detail of the interplay between ROs and the antiviral defense. Most of the studies on such organelles of RNA viruses have involved cells, and thus, it is important to study the presence of ROs during coronavirus infection in hosts. In addition, how the RNA intermediates are released from ROs, and whether the ROs can be dissolved or still exist in the cytosol after viral RNA synthesis, need to be further elucidated.
</p>
