<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0350">
 <italic>Orthopoxviruses</italic> (OPXVs), family 
 <italic>Poxviridae</italic>, are viruses of high interest for scientists because of their potential use as bioterroristic agents and in gene therapy. Reports of OPXV infections in animals and humans have been increasing during the last few decades leading to the perception of an increasing risk for humans (
 <xref rid="bib235" ref-type="bibr">Vorou et al., 2008</xref>). In cats, there are a number of reports of poxvirus infections, but the causative agent has been characterized mostly as cow OPXV (
 <xref rid="bib208" ref-type="bibr">Schaudien et al., 2007</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib210" ref-type="bibr">Schöniger et al., 2007</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib211" ref-type="bibr">Schulze et al., 2007</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr">Johnson et al., 2009</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib106" ref-type="bibr">Kaysser et al., 2010</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">Herder et al., 2011</xref>). The first full genome sequences of two feline ortopoxviruses were obtained by NGS approach (
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Dabrowski et al., 2013</xref>) from strains collected as part of the routine diagnostic work at the German consultant laboratory for poxviruses. Phylogenetic analysis showed that the two cat strains clustered into cowpox clade. Later, five novel feline OPXV whole genome nucleotide sequences were generated by NGS from a collection of isolates obtained from several localities in the United Kingdom and Norway (
 <xref rid="bib150" ref-type="bibr">Mauldin et al., 2017</xref>). Phylogenetic analyses demonstrated the presence of five different clades (A–E) from cowpox. More recently, a cat with multicentric nodular ulcerative dermatitis was found positive for OPXV (
 <xref rid="bib113" ref-type="bibr">Lanave et al., 2018</xref>). The virus differed from cowpoxes common in cats and was grouped with an OPXV strain identified from captive macaques in Italy (
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Cardeti et al., 2017</xref>), related to ectromelia viruses (
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2003</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib155" ref-type="bibr">Mendez-Rios et al., 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib152" ref-type="bibr">Mavian et al., 2014</xref>).
</p>
