<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cox proportional hazard models with time-varying covariates were used to determine the association of rainy season with dengue disease and with CYD-TDV efficacy; the proportional hazards assumption was assessed by considering interactions with time and assessing plots of the scaled Schoenfeld residuals. The Cox model was selected to make full use of the time-to-event dengue data and the time-dependent rainy season variable. The rainy season variable was defined as a binary time-dependent variable equal to 1 during the rainy season and 0 otherwise. For each site in each country, the rainy season was determined using climatological information from the World Meteorological Organization (WMO) [
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. This information was based on monthly averages for the 30-year period from 1981 to 2010; contemporaneous rainfall data for the time period in which the trials occurred were not available. If rainy season data were not available on the WMO website, they were obtained from country-specific member websites [
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Based on this information, the rainy season was defined as all months with average total precipitation (in mm) greater than the average monthly precipitation during the year. The site-specific rainy seasons for CYD14 and CYD15 sites are reported in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0207878.g003">Fig 3A and 3B</xref>, respectively. All models were estimated by adjusting on the baseline covariates sex, protocol-specified age category (2–5, 6–11, 12–14 years in CYD14; 9–11, 12–16 years in CYD15; 9–11, 12–16 years in combined analysis of CYD14 and CYD15), and country (using a nominal categorical variable taking values Indonesia, Malaysia, Philippines, Thailand, and Vietnam in CYD14 and Brazil, Colombia, Honduras, Mexico, and Puerto Rico in CYD15). The expression of the Cox model for the combined analysis of CYD14 and CYD15 is provided in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0207878.s001">S1 File</xref> and a map of the sites is available in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0207878.s002">S1 Fig</xref>. Analyses were performed in R Statistical Software version 3.0.1 with the R 
 <italic>survival</italic> package [
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0207878.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. All p-values are two-sided with significance declared for p-values below 0.05.
</p>
