<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite the huge potential of proved drugs or vaccines in curbing the menace of EVD, it remains crucial that strengthening of existing health systems and acknowledging and incorporating cultural beliefs and practices in containment strategies in the affected regions take higher priority (
 <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>).
 <xref rid="bib89 bib90" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>89,90</sup>
 </xref> In the longer term only functioning health systems are capable of overcoming the enormous challenges of EV containment and preventing future outbreaks supported by results from international research efforts (
 <xref rid="tbox1" ref-type="boxed-text">Box 1</xref>).
 <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>91</sup>
 </xref>
 <boxed-text id="tbox1">
  <label>Box 1</label>
  <caption>
   <title>Priority areas for future research</title>
  </caption>
  <p>
   <list list-type="simple">
    <list-item id="u0010">
     <label>•</label>
     <p>Identification of surrogate markers for transmission that can be traced through bodily fluids in order to detect infection before presenting symptoms</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0015">
     <label>•</label>
     <p>Development of new diagnostics that can identify infected patients before the onset of clinical symptoms</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0020">
     <label>•</label>
     <p>Host immune mechanisms involved in viral shedding rate or disease susceptibility (HIV and other coinfections)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0025">
     <label>•</label>
     <p>Asymptomatic infections: correlates of protection/severity</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0030">
     <label>•</label>
     <p>Effect of genetic modification of the virus on the potential for changes in transmissibility</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0035">
     <label>•</label>
     <p>Development of appropriate strategies for communicating risk factors and evaluation of the effect of such strategies on mitigating virus transmission</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0040">
     <label>•</label>
     <p>Contact tracing strategies</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
 </boxed-text>
</p>
