<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0080">Wastewater may potentially contain a certain concentration of the 
 <italic>Coronavirus</italic>, beyond enteric viruses; the sludge deriving from wastewater treatment plants, and class B bio-solids, for examples, was demonstrated containing 
 <italic>Coronavirus</italic> genes in more than 80% of the examined samples (
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Wigginton et al., 2015</xref>). However, whether the SARS-CoV-2 is active in the above mentioned environmental, allowing either fecal or oral transmission has not been yet clarified. Studies on the persistance of 
 <italic>Coronavirus</italic> in water (
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Gundy et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Casanova et al., 2009</xref>) underlined the strong inhibiting effect on the virus survival, given by the temperature parameter. The composition of the water, included the presence of microorganisms, together with proteins, is able to highly influence virus survival (non sterilized wastewater allowed an lower survival of 
 <italic>Poliovirus</italic> 1 and HAV), although the viral survival is highly reduced with temperatures &gt; 20 °C. It was demonstrated that surrogate viruses in sterilized wastewater (autoclaved at 121 °C for 30 min) are inactivated with different rates, compared to those tested in non-sterilized wastewater (
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Nasser et al., 1993</xref>). Based on the same experimental protocol, the study demonstrated that 
 <italic>Coronavirus</italic> surrogates are able to survive longer in non-filtered primary effluents, compared to filtered samples (
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Gundy et al., 2009</xref>). The increased survival rate in presence of sediments or organic matter may be due to the protection that such components offer towards chemical or biological inactivating agents in the water. The presence of exogenous material is indeed capable of causing a rapid viral inactivation, as demonstrated in a study by 
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Casanova et al., (2009)</xref>, evaluating the persistance of 
 <italic>Coronavirus</italic> in pasteurized sludge, compared to the viral survival in distilled water. Based on the collected data, the effects of the matrix on the inactivation of the viral load result complex, and highly variable from a viral strain to another, and from sample to sample. SARS-CoV, for example, has been demonstrated to lose infectivity in vitro in culture media earlier than Human 
 <italic>Coronavirus</italic> 229E (H–CoV 229E), considering the same conditions (
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Rabenau et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Wigginton et al., 2015</xref>). The available studies on surrogate SARS-COV-2 viruses suggest to suppose that the novel 
 <italic>Coronavirus</italic> may be less persistant in wastewater, mainly due to the presence of either organic matter, or inhibiting matrix autochtonous flora: such factors are indeed able to activate metabolic pathways causing the faster die-off of the viruses. The extreme infectiousness of SARS-CoV-2 led many countries to suggest a monitoring of wastewater in order to evaluate the presence of the virus in the community, mainly to extimate the asymptomatic individuals, and aiming to quantify the potential infection risks for wastewater and solid waste plants’ employees (
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Water &amp; Energy Sustainable Technology Center, 2020</xref>). The persistance of SARS-CoV-2 was recently evaluated in wastewater at the Amsterdam Schiphol Airport (Tilburg, Netherlands) and at the wastewater treatment plant in Kaatsheuvel (Netherlands), collecting samples weekly, from February to March 2020. The quantitative monitoring of the virus, brought out the detection of the new 
 <italic>Coronavirus</italic> in the airport wastewater and in the wastewater treatment plant samples collected in March 2020. The monitoring resulted crucial, allowing to associating the presence of the SARS-CoV-2 and the occurrence and registration of the first COVID-19 cases in Netherlands. The genetic material from the virus was indeed detected in wastewater samples taken from the wastewater treatment plants starting from March 2020, while the first official COVID-19 cases in Netherlands were registered on February 27th, 2020 (
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">RIVM Netherlands, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Gale, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Nabi, 2020</xref>) the outcomes, considering the mean SARS-COV-2 incubation period between 2 and 11 days, up to a maximum of 14 days (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Ministero della Salute, 2020</xref>), consent to hypothesize that the first cases of COVID-19 in Netherlands may be actually placed in the time period reported by Netherland Health authorities.
</p>
