<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For dynamic assessment of the interaction, we first identify the earliest week at which the cumulative incidence of the index virus (i.e., dominant virus type) becomes predictable. Subsequently, we show that the cumulative incidence of complementary virus types can also be predicted based on a negative correlation with the index virus. To accomplish the first task, we assumed that the epidemic size for the index virus in each season 
 <italic>Y</italic> can be estimated using the linear regression model 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm1">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mi mathvariant="normal">Y</mi>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mrow>
      <mi mathvariant="sans-serif">β</mi>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">X</mi>
     </mrow>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> at the time point (epidemiological week 
 <italic>s</italic>) when one of the following conditions is first met: the cumulative incidence of the index virus in the last 5 weeks reaches the threshold 
 <italic>h</italic> or the cumulative complementary incidence reaches the threshold 
 <italic>h</italic>
 <sub>c</sub>. Here, covariate 
 <italic>X</italic> is linked to the growth of the incidence of the index virus before epidemiological week 
 <italic>s</italic>, expressed as 
 <disp-formula id="FD1-ijerph-16-04179">
  <label>(1)</label>
  <math id="mm2">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mi>X</mi>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mfrac>
      <mrow>
       <mi>I</mi>
       <mfenced>
        <mi>s</mi>
       </mfenced>
       <mo>+</mo>
       <mi>I</mi>
       <mfenced>
        <mrow>
         <mi>s</mi>
         <mo>−</mo>
         <mn>1</mn>
        </mrow>
       </mfenced>
      </mrow>
      <mrow>
       <mi>m</mi>
       <mi>a</mi>
       <mi>x</mi>
       <mfenced>
        <mrow>
         <mi>h</mi>
         <mo>,</mo>
         <msubsup>
          <mstyle mathsize="100%" displaystyle="true">
           <mo>∑</mo>
          </mstyle>
          <mrow>
           <mi>a</mi>
           <mo>=</mo>
           <mn>0</mn>
          </mrow>
          <mrow>
           <mi>a</mi>
           <mo>=</mo>
           <mn>4</mn>
          </mrow>
         </msubsup>
         <mi>I</mi>
         <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
         <mi>s</mi>
         <mo>−</mo>
         <mi>a</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
       </mfenced>
      </mrow>
     </mfrac>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula> where 
 <italic>I</italic>(
 <italic>s</italic>) indicates that the incidence for the index virus in week 
 <italic>s</italic>. Here the latest two-week data are summed in the numerator for smoothing purpose, and the denominator is the sum over the latest five weeks to compare against the numerator and understand the growth in the recent time. As the size and pattern of epidemics are quite different among the three influenza virus types, thresholds 
 <italic>h</italic> and 
 <italic>h</italic>
 <sub>c</sub> were chosen for each virus type. To determine the thresholds 
 <italic>h</italic> and 
 <italic>h</italic>
 <sub>c</sub>, we calculated the residual standard error (RSE) for the epidemic size using the equation:
 <disp-formula id="FD2-ijerph-16-04179">
  <label>(2)</label>
  <math id="mm3">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mi>R</mi>
     <mi>S</mi>
     <mi>E</mi>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <msqrt>
      <mrow>
       <mfrac>
        <mrow>
         <msup>
          <mrow>
           <mfenced>
            <mrow>
             <msub>
              <mi>Y</mi>
              <mrow>
               <mi>o</mi>
               <mi>b</mi>
               <mi>s</mi>
              </mrow>
             </msub>
             <mo>−</mo>
             <msub>
              <mi>Y</mi>
              <mrow>
               <mi>p</mi>
               <mi>r</mi>
               <mi>e</mi>
               <mi>d</mi>
              </mrow>
             </msub>
            </mrow>
           </mfenced>
          </mrow>
          <mn>2</mn>
         </msup>
        </mrow>
        <mrow>
         <mi>D</mi>
         <mi>F</mi>
        </mrow>
       </mfrac>
      </mrow>
     </msqrt>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula> where DF denotes the number of the degrees of freedom, calculated as the number of influenza seasons minus 1. 
 <italic>h</italic> and 
 <italic>h</italic>
 <sub>c</sub> for each virus type were chosen from the combinations of 
 <italic>h</italic> and 
 <italic>h</italic>
 <sub>c</sub> that gave the smallest RSE. Namely, abovementioned thresholds represent the most reasonable early week at which the cumulative incidence has become predictable.
</p>
