<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Entomological surveillance data were acquired from 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> infestation surveys, conducted by Brazilian Municipal Health Secretariats at a local level. The 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> Infestation Rapid Survey (
 <italic>Levantamento Rápido de Índice para Aedes aegypti</italic>, LIRAa) is a sample survey that randomly selects properties for inspection for immature forms (mosquito larvae and pupae). Municipalities are divided into areal groups of between 8,100–12,000 properties, from which a sample of 450 properties is drawn. LIRAa was introduced in Fortaleza in October 2011 to replace the 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> Infestation Survey (
 <italic>Levantamento de índice de infestação amostral</italic>, LIA), which covered a much larger sample of properties in the municipality (about 10%), and required considerably more time to complete. LIRAa is repeated three to four times per year, with a national survey conducted every October. The Brazilian Ministry of Health uses three categories of infestation intensity to classify risk: (i) satisfactory, &lt;1% infestation; (ii) alert, 1–3.9%; and (iii) risk of outbreak, &gt;3.9% [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006990.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. We obtained data on all surveys available for LIA in 2011 and for LIRAa from 2011 to 2015. For the purposes of this analysis we used data from the January surveillance of both programs–immediately preceding the early-spring rainy season characteristic of NE Brazil–that is considered the most valuable for forecasting regional epidemic risk. In 2014, the January LIRAa survey was delayed until February, resulting in elevated 
 <italic>bairro</italic> infestation indexes relative to the other years; as a result, we designated 2014 LIRAa results as missing, and used a missingness indicator variable [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006990.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Under the assumption of representative sampling, we used total houses sampled by 
 <italic>bairro</italic> as a denominator to create a 
 <italic>bairro</italic>-level household infestation variable for each year.
</p>
