<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Decreased plasma levels of vitamin C may be due to inadequate intake, acute or chronic consumption secondary to increased oxidative stress or increased loss [
 <xref rid="B105-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Low levels of vitamin C have been documented in critically ill patients in several studies [
 <xref rid="B106-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]. Furthermore, levels &lt;10 µmol/L have been reported in these patients despite the administration of the recommended daily requirements [
 <xref rid="B103-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. Diminished levels of this vitamin are linked to severity of organ failure and mortality [
 <xref rid="B107-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. In a study where the safety of vitamin C administration in patients with severe sepsis was evaluated and two different doses of vitamin C were compared (50 mg/kg/24 h and 200 mg/kg/24 h) with placebo. The results showed decreased levels in all septic patients (17.9 ± 24 µM). Plasma levels increased dramatically in both treatment groups. No adverse effects were reported in the patients who received vitamin C infusion. The patients who received vitamin C had a greater decrease in the SOFA score compared to the placebo group. Decreased C-reactive protein and procalcitonin were reported in the vitamin C group. Lower levels of thrombomodulin were found in the vitamin C group compared to placebo. 28-day mortality was also lower in the low-dose vitamin C group (38.1%) compared to the high-dose group (50.6%) and the placebo group (65.1%). There was no difference in terms of mechanical ventilation days or days of ICU stay. A 96-h infusion of vitamin C in contrast to placebo did not improve vascular injury, organ dysfunction scores and inflammation markers in a preliminary study of patients with sepsis and ARDS. The authors concluded that further research was necessary to evaluate the potential role of vitamin C for other outcomes in ARDS [
 <xref rid="B108-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>].
</p>
