<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p> Comment 2: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>“Responses to infectious disease epidemics use a growing body of data sources to inform decision making (Cori 
    <italic>et al</italic>., 2017; Fraser 
    <italic>et al</italic>., 2009; WHO Ebola Response Team 
    <italic>et al</italic>., 2014; WHO Ebola Response Team 
    <italic>et al</italic>., 2015). While new data—such as whole genome pathogen sequences—are increasingly useful complements to epidemiological data (Gire 
    <italic>et al</italic>., 2014), epidemic curves—which describe the number of new cases through time (incidence)—remain the most important source of information, particularly early in an outbreak.” - Rephrase avoiding four "—" in the same sentence.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list> Partial genome sequencing is useful to complement epidata/infect. disease epi. If you wish to highlight the WGS/extensive sequencing, consider several aspects: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>Confirm change in infectiousness or epidemiology (CFR, change in clinical presentation, shift in risk group.)</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Relationships between cases (mapping Lassa, Ebola transmission chains ...)</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Emergence and patterns of transmission (vector, host, reservoir)</p>
  </list-item>
 </list> Suggested examples from the recent literature: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>Kraemer MUG, Cummings DAT, Funk S, Reiner RC, Faria NR, Pybus OG, Cauchemez S. Reconstruction and prediction of viral disease epidemics. Epidemiol Infect. 2018  Nov 5:1-7. doi: 10.1017/S0950268818002881. [Epub ahead of print] PubMed PMID: 30394230; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC6398585. 
    <sup>
     <xref rid="rep-ref-48153-2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
    </sup>               
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Siddle KJ 
    <italic>et al</italic>. Genomic Analysis of Lassa Virus during an Increase in Cases in Nigeria in 2018. N Engl J Med. 2018 Nov. 
    <sup>
     <xref rid="rep-ref-48153-3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
    </sup> 
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Kafetzopoulou LE 
    <italic>et al</italic>, Metagenomic sequencing at the epicenter of the Nigeria 2018 Lassa fever outbreak. Science. 2019 Jan 4;363(6422):74-77. 
    <sup>
     <xref rid="rep-ref-48153-4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
    </sup>
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list> Comment 3: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>“which describe the number of new cases through time (incidence)—remain” -Proposed change of 'through' to 'over'</p>
  </list-item>
 </list> Comment 4: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>“important source of information, particularly early in an outbreak.” - Not only. This can be helpful to look at the magnitude and pattern (recurrent environmental sources, detect outliers ...).</p>
  </list-item>
 </list> Comment 5: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>“Specifically epidemic curves(often” - Missing space.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list> Comment 6: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>“[…] often referred to as ‘epicurves’) represent the number of new cases […]” - New cases = incident case in epidemiology. Might be more accurate to say, "incident cases of a disease” and add within bracket “(corresponding to the vertical y-axis)”.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>“[…] per time unit based […]” - Consider 'time interval' instead of 'unit' as ‘unit’ can be misunderstood (e.g. unit = hour, min, sec). The interval is at the user's discretion (3 hours = 'time interval’).</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>“[…]: on the date or time of symptom onset” - Consider replacing symptoms by “time of illness onset among cases” (and add within bracket “(corresponding to the vertical x-axis)”.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list> Comment 7: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>“provide a simple, visual outline of epi­demic dynamics, which can be used for assessing the growth or decline of an” - That is the main purpose in practice. You may consider being more assertive, by replacing "can" with "is". Very well-known added-values. No need for six references to support this statement.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list> Comment 8: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>“[…] by a range of modelling techniques for short-term forecasting (Cori 
    <italic>et al</italic>., 2013; Funk 
    <italic>et al</italic>., 2018; Nouvellet 
    <italic>et al</italic>., 2018; Viboud 
    <italic>et al</italic>., 2018)” - Could you please consider developing with few sentences pointing to ad hoc examples in relation with the features of the cited references.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list> Comment 9: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>“[…] as well as in outbreak detection algorithms from syndromic surveillance data” - Consider more references that are recent. Note such analytical frameworks are not restricted to syndromic surveillance but to any regularly collected count data from epidemiological time-series in health surveillance system (syndromic or not).</p>
  </list-item>
 </list> Comment 10: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>“[…] But despite the existence of packages dedicated to time series analysis (Shumway &amp; Stoffer, 2010) as well as surveillance data (Höhle, 2007)” - Time series analysis is a generic term, consider “time series of epidemiological data” to be more accurate. Numerous time-series packages are available for count data that can be "re-used" for human epi.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list> Comment 11: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>“a lightweight and 
    <italic>well-tested </italic>package solely dedicated to building, handling and plotting epidemic curves directly from linelist data (e.g. a spreadsheet where each row represents an individual case) is still lacking.” - Perhaps “lightweight” is something relative in package development and might be changed. More importantly, as mentioned above, please, consider mentioning other previous packages supporting specifically epi-curve creation (for instance: epitools, EpiCurve). These packages can manage aggregated/no aggregated data with and without factor. Current presented package has an added-value is its interoperability, the presence of simple modelling tools and further graph customization. Stricto sensu, epicurve were able to be done in R form user customization of ggplot2 and cited package.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
 <bold>Section: Methods</bold>
</p>
