<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p> Comment 23: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>“Here, we highlight three simple functionalities in 
    <italic>incidence </italic>for estimating parameters via modelling or bootstrap and the two specialized data classes that are used to store the models and parameter estimates.” - Consider structuring the following section according to the five elements mentioned (=three functions [ 
    <underline>fit() , </underline>estimate_peak() , fit_optim_split()] and two specialized data classes) using for instance bullet points/subtitles. For each function, the goal, data input, statistical methods and output object(s) can be grouped in single section.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list> Comment 24: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>“we implement the simple log-linear regression approach in the function 
    <underline>fit()</underline>, which can […]" - Please add more information about the structure of the 'incidence_fit objects containing log-linear models'
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list> Comment 25: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>“[…] fit exponential increase or decrease of incidence over time by log-transforming case counts … “ - Can be simplified to “fit exponential increase or decrease using a linear regression over time on log-transformed case counts…“.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list> Comment 26: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>“where 
    <italic>y </italic>is the incidence, 
    <italic>r </italic>is the growth rate, 
    <italic>t"</italic> - Replace “incidence” with number of new case/incident case.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list> Comment 27: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>“serial interval” - Consider adding “serial interval of the infectious agent”</p>
  </list-item>
 </list> Comment 28: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>“uses multinomial bootstrapping to estimate the peak, assuming” - Some explanation about the method and references would be desirable.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list> Comment 29: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>“Both object classes can be plotted separately or added to an existing epicurve using the function add_incidence_fit() (Figure 5)." - The customization of the epicurve is well described. However, it is not mentioned how to change the layout of the model outcome and confidence interval. Indeed, some users might wish to use an alternative ggplot2 geometric object such as geom_range with a shaded grey semi-transparent band instead of two dotted lines. It would an added-value to provide some capacities or explanation and an example of customization of the layout of the “incidence_fit objects”.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
 <bold>Section: Use cases</bold>
</p>
