<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">Data analysis included three steps. Step 1: assigning climatic and environmental data to each surveillance record based on the GPS location of the record, regardless of the status of occurrence of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus.</italic> Step 2: sorting sampling points into groups based on similarity in environmental conditions and the known 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> occurrence months, then assigning occurrence months to missing records due to lack of longitudinal observations, which was carried out using k-medoids clustering [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Step 3: predicting the conduciveness of environmental conditions for 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> populations using a machine-learning regression model. The model was evaluated by examining 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> occurrence against model-predicted probability of occurrence at each sampling site in each month. The cutoff predicted probability for determining ‘presence’ or ‘absence’ was based on accuracy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], which balances specificity and sensitivity. The accuracy is calculated as the sum of correctly predicted positives and correctly predicted negatives over a total number of samples. The eventual model sensitivity and specificity were calculated based on a cutoff predicted probability that gives the optimal accuracy, i.e., if the predicted risk rate was greater than cutoff, the prediction was considered ‘presence’; otherwise it was considered ‘absence’. Sensitivity was estimated based on the proportion of sites with 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> that were predicted as ‘presence’ and specificity was estimated based on the proportion of sites without 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> that were predicted as ‘absence’. In addition to sensitivity, specificity, and accuracy, we also calculated area under curve (AUC) based on receiver operating characteristic curve or ROC curve. AUC provides an aggregate measure of performance across all possible classification thresholds. Subsequently, the predicted monthly 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> occurrence maps were generated.
</p>
