<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Foot-and-mouth disease (FMD) is a highly infectious transboundary disease that affects domestic and wild cloven-hoofed animal species. The disease has tremendous direct and indirect economic consequences resulting mainly from constraints in international trade in animals and animal products originating from infected countries, as well as costs associated with controlling disease outbreaks [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. However, FMD consequences are not the same throughout the world [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] as the impacts of the disease vary markedly between FMD endemic and FMD non-endemic countries, developed and developing countries, and also within many developing countries [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The etiological agent of FMD is a small, non-enveloped, positive-sense, single stranded RNA (8.4 kb in length) virus belonging to the genus 
 <italic>Aphthovirus</italic> of the family 
 <italic>Picornaviridae</italic> called foot-and-mouth disease virus (FMDV). The primary mode of transmission of FMDV is via direct contact from infected to susceptible animals [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The virus can also be spread mechanically by contaminated organic debris, fomites or personnel and materials from infected farms that may carry the virus to susceptible animals in another farm [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Furthermore, FMDV transmission can also be airborne, a mechanism by which virus exhaled into the air by infected animals can be spread over long distances depending on the wind speed and direction [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Additionally, FMDV can be transmitted locally between livestock housing of susceptible animals when there is no clear linkage other than geographical proximity [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. This occurred in 2001 in the UK after the introduction of movement restrictions following the first FMD outbreaks. In these circumstances, the spread was limited to a 3 km distance from an infected premise [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], however long distance spread continued to occur even at a reduced level [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The rapid spread of FMDV highlights the need for measures to effectively prevent and/or control the disease. Development of control policies for different scenarios requires a deep understanding of FMD epidemiology that can be supported by accurate and relevant epidemiological models [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].
</p>
