<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">Respiratory tract infections (RTIs) are illnesses that spread through either direct or indirect contact, such as sneezing or coughing, and most RTIs are the result of viral or bacterial infections, with bacterial infections being less common causes. These microbial infections can interfere with and damage the normal physiology of the respiratory tract, resulting in the deterioration of the lungs and airways [
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. These infections occur most commonly in the fall and winter include the common cold, influenza, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), asthma, and pneumonia. Because of the atypical presentations of influenza infections, which make effective control difficult, a self-healing approach is taken for the management of common cold [
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. However, seasonal prophylactic treatment with antiviral drugs and adjunct vaccine therapies still remain an attractive strategy for preventing and controlling seasonal infections [
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. COPD is likely to become the third leading cause of death worldwide by 2020 [
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Currently, the prevalence of COPD in the adult population (aged ≥40 years) is estimated to be around 10 % [
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Although it is a preventable infection, increasing air pollution may result in an increase in COPD prevalence, making it a priority for individuals and health-care providers [
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. People with COPD commonly experience symptoms, including dyspnea, wheezing, and coughing and have an increased susceptibility to microbial infections and complications that damage lung function [
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. COPD also increases vulnerability to adverse events, including bruising, oropharyngeal candidiasis, and pneumonia. As there is no cure for COPD, improving quality of life, reducing complications, and managing symptoms are the primary objectives for novel COPD treatment strategies [
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Asthma is an inflammatory disease leading to mucus hyperproduction, airway hyperresponsiveness, and airway wall remodeling and affects more than 300 million people worldwide. Asthma is a typical Th2 inflammatory disease that causes increased IgE levels in the airway [
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Similar to asthma, pneumonia, commonly caused by 
 <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic>
 <italic>,</italic> is an inflammatory disorder of the lungs primarily affecting the air sacs and resulting in chest pain, dry or productive coughing, fever, and difficulty in breathing. Pneumonia is most damaging in infants and older people as a result of their reduced immune function [
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].
</p>
