<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Past population demographic events leave distinctive signatures in DNA sequence polymorphisms and gene genealogies (
 <xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">Tajima 1989</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr">Simonsen 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 1995
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">Schneider and Excoffier 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Excoffier 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib108" ref-type="bibr">Zeng 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2006
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Gutenkunst 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2009
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Naduvilezhath 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2011
 </xref>). For example, a population bottleneck increases the variance of coalescence times and reduces the number of variants at low frequency in the site frequency spectrum (SFS) (
 <xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">Tajima 1989</xref>). Population expansion creates star-shaped genealogies and increases the mean number of variants at low frequency in the SFS (
 <xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">Tajima 1989</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">Slatkin 1996</xref>). Population sub-division leads to long internal branches in the genealogy and increases the number of fixed variants (
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Harpending 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 1998
 </xref>). It also results in “structured” genealogies in which the means and variances of coalescence times (
 <italic>e.g.</italic>, time to the most recent common ancestor) are large, resulting in an excess of intermediate frequency variants in the SFS (
 <xref rid="bib102" ref-type="bibr">Wakeley 1999</xref>). Balancing selection leads to a similar structure, and to an excess of variants at intermediate frequency (
 <xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">Tajima 1989</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Fay and Wu 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Barton and Etheridge 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib108" ref-type="bibr">Zeng 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2006
 </xref>). Directional selection leads to genealogies with both star shapes (leading to the common ancestor of the selected lineages) and long branches (due to remaining ancestral lineages and/or recombination with the selected haplotype), and generates an excess of variants at both low and high frequency (
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Barton 1998</xref>).
</p>
