<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Vaccination campaigns represent the only current approach to control and prevent the spread of YFV in endemic regions (see 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec6-viruses-11-00960">Section 6</xref>). Indeed, despite the long history of humankind being afflicted by YFV and the large populations in tropical Africa and Central and South America at risk of potentially catastrophic epidemics, today, treatment options for infected individuals are limited to relief of symptoms and intensive care support of patients with severe disease. Presently, no specific licensed treatment options for YFV-associated severe disease are available. As development of new drugs is expensive and time-consuming, one potential option includes repurposing drugs already licensed for other diseases. This includes drugs targeted at other members of the family 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic>, most prominently hepatitis C virus (HCV) and DENV. Ribavirin, a nucleoside analog, in combination with pegylated interferon-α (PEG IFN-α), is effective for the treatment of HCV, a related member of the family 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic> (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00960-f001">Figure 1</xref>), as well as a variety of other RNA and DNA viruses. In vitro studies and mouse models yielded promising results against YFV, but these results could not be replicated in non-human primates [
 <xref rid="B33-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. More recently, considerable efforts have been invested in the development of direct-acting antivirals (DAAs) against HCV and DENV. Sofosbuvir, a DAA licensed for use against HCV, is a nucleotide analog inhibitor of the viral RdRp NS5B. It also has described antiviral activity against the related flaviviruses, ZIKV [
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] and DENV [
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Computer modelling and in vitro experiments in hepatoma cell lines demonstrated sofosbuvir’s inhibitory effects on YFV replication: in a mouse model, sofosbuvir was able to decrease mortality and weight loss associated with liver injury, however, only in the case of pre-exposure treatment [
 <xref rid="B36-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. A varying efficacy against YFV has also been demonstrated for other compounds targeting the NS5 RdRp [
 <xref rid="B37-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], the NS3 helicase [
 <xref rid="B38-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] and capsid protein [
 <xref rid="B39-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Screening compound libraries via high-throughput in vitro approaches were successful at identifying additional compounds with in-vitro activity against YFV. Patkar et al. (2009) identified two compounds with proposed activity against the NS4B protein [
 <xref rid="B40-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] and Guo et al. (2016) were able to successfully apply a benzodiazepine compound (BDAA) in a hamster model of YFV infection, where it protected 90% of animals from death via targeting of NS4B [
 <xref rid="B41-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Using RNA interference (RNAi) technology, shRNAs (short hairpin RNAs) targeted at the YFV E and NS1 regions were effective in inhibiting YFV replication in cell lines as well as improving survival in mice when injected intracerebrally prior to exposure to the YFV-17D strain [
 <xref rid="B42-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. However, for all the approaches outlined above, demonstration of efficacy in humans or non-human primates remains outstanding.
</p>
