<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Dengue fever, also known as "break-bone fever", is an acute mosquito-borne viral disease caused by dengue virus (DENV) [
 <xref rid="pone.0224676.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Patients infected with DENV can have flu-like symptoms, including a high fever, headache, and vomiting, which generally last for ten days. In a small proportion of cases, the disease develops into dengue hemorrhagic fever (DHF) or dengue shock syndrome (DSS) [
 <xref rid="pone.0224676.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0224676.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Dengue is principally spread by 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> mosquitoes in tropical and subtropical regions where the warm and humid climate indicates favorable mosquito habitat. In other words, dengue fever is also a seasonal infectious disease, and mosquito densities and climatic conditions are strongly associated with the incidence of dengue fever. In recent decades, dengue fever, as a growing threat to human health, has presented a tremendous challenge to health service providers throughout the world [
 <xref rid="pone.0224676.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. According to a published study, an estimated 390 million dengue infections occur in over 100 countries every year [
 <xref rid="pone.0224676.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0224676.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Globally, the vast majority of the world population is exposed to DENV, making dengue one of the most dangerous vector-borne viral diseases worldwide [
 <xref rid="pone.0224676.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Dengue outbreaks have a devastating effect on public health and economic sectors [
 <xref rid="pone.0224676.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In the stricken areas, the disease leads to a slowdown in the local economy as it inflicts a significant health burden on the population, impairs people's quality of life and impedes the development of the tourist industry. With vector management as the primary means to control and prevent DENV transmission, it should be noted that improper use of insecticides is a waste of resources and a source of environmental pollution that threatens both human and environmental health [
 <xref rid="pone.0224676.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0224676.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. So it is important to know the structure of dengue virus.
</p>
