<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Platelet transfusion was performed after admission because ITP was not suspected due to his age. However, his platelet count was only 12 000/µL after platelet transfusion (Figure 
 <xref rid="ccr32581-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). IVIG (1 g/kg) was subsequently administered because of the refractoriness to transfusion, which was suspected to be due to ITP. Despite IVIG administration, his platelet count decreased to 2000/µL. Although another platelet transfusion was performed, his platelet count increased only to 9000/µL. A subsequent bone marrow examination showed a nuclear cell count of 105 000/µL without morphologically abnormal cells and megakaryocyte count of 8/µL. After the exclusion of malignant diseases, prednisolone (PSL; 1 mg/kg) was administered as a second‐line therapy for ITP with another platelet transfusion. After the initiation of PSL therapy, his platelet count increased to 31 000/µL, but decreased to 18 000/µL after 2 days. CMV infection was diagnosed based on the presence of CMV IgM (1.64) and IgG (14.2), and the results of a CMV antigenemia assay using monoclonal antibodies C10/C11 (4 positive cells/ 150 000 leukocytes) at admission. IVIG (1 g/kg) were re‐administered, and PSL dose was increased to 2 mg/kg. Thereafter, his platelet count gradually normalized. Thrombocytopenia has not recurred after the discontinuation of PSL. The patient has been normal development, without recurrence, for more than 6 months after onset. Using quantitative PCR analysis, CMV‐DNA was detected in his urine after treatment but not in his dried umbilical cord. Based on these results, thrombocytopenia was associated with acquired CMV infection. No abnormalities were observed on brain magnetic resonance imaging. Auditory brainstem responses revealed normal waves from I to V at 90 dB and V wave was detected at 30dB. These clinical findings indicate that the patient was infected with CMV after birth, excluding a congenitally acquired infection.
</p>
