<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The devastating HIV and viral hepatitis epidemics amongst people with hemophilia from viral contamination of plasma-derived products in the 1980’s spurred the development and transition to recombinant products 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, 
  <xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>
 </sup>. However, long-standing debate has ensued in the field regarding the relative immunogenicity of pdFVIII and SHL rFVIII products because of conflicting results of retrospective studies 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>– 
  <xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>
 </sup>. Recently, the only prospective, randomized trial (SIPPET) comparing the immunogenicity of VWF-containing pdFVIII products to SHL rFVIII products in HA demonstrated increased immunogenicity with SHL rFVIII (hazard ratio 1.86) 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>
 </sup>. How best to apply these results in clinical decision making is complicated by the emergence of EHL–rFVIII products since SIPPET. EHL products, especially EHL–rFIX, may increase compliance by decreasing infusion frequencies, but it is unknown if EHL–rFVIII products are more or less immunogenic than SHL rFVIII or pdFVIII products. Although certain factors can guide clinicians to risk of inhibitor formation (e.g. disease severity, underlying mutation, and family history), inhibitor risk stratification is an imprecise science 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>
 </sup>. Furthermore, in SIPPET subanalysis, use of pdFVIII versus SHL rFVIII surprisingly proved beneficial only for “low”- rather than “high”-risk patients 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>
 </sup>. SIPPET results also pose a dilemma for clinicians who are hesitant to return to pdFVIII because of the history of prior blood-borne infectious epidemics or the potential for new ones. Though current virucidal techniques to date have successfully mitigated the risk of emerging viruses (e.g. West Nile 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>
 </sup> and Zika 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>
 </sup> virus), the risk posed by prions 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>
 </sup> and other unidentified infectious agents remains unknown. Preliminary data also suggest that EHL products may fare better for ITI 
 <bold>,</bold> both for those who fail with rFVIII and as first-line therapy 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
  <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
