<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0026">Recently published studies revealed that chloroquine could highly reduce COVID-19 replication with an acceptable effective concentration (EC
 <sub>90</sub>) value of 6.90 μM which could be easily achieved with standard doses of 500 mg twice daily. The most important advantage of chloroquine in COVID-19 treatment is good penetration to tissues especially lungs which are highly affected in COVID-19 pneumonia. Chloroquine could stop viral infection by enhancing the pH of endosomes which is required for virus-cell fusion and interfering with COVID-19 cellular receptor glycosylation which could interfere with post-translation modification of COVID-19 viruses (inhibition of entry and post-entry stages).
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>40</sup>
 </xref> Chloroquine is a weak base that could be entrapped in organelles that are membrane-enclosed and have low-pH, so interfering with their acidification process. Therefore chloroquine could inhibit pH-dependent viral fusion and replication. Also, it might inhibit viral assembly in endoplasmic reticulum-Golgi intermediate like structures.
 <xref rid="bib0047" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>47</sup>
 </xref> Another possible antiviral mechanism of chloroquine is its immunomodulatory effect through cell signaling pathways and regulating the action of pro-inflammatory cytokines that can enhance its antiviral effect synergistically
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>40</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib0048" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>48</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib0049" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>49</sup>
 </xref> Chloroquine/hydroxychloroquine could prevent from COVID-19-induced ARDS by attenuating the pro-inflammatory cytokines and receptors.
 <xref rid="bib0047" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>47</sup>
 </xref> Hydroxychloroquine can enhance intracellular pH and avoid lysosomal activity in antigen presenting cells containing B cells, also they can avoid antigen processing and MHC-II presentation to T cells. So, T cell activation could be reduced by the action of hydroxychloroquine. It can suppress the cytokine release syndrome (CRS), which is a result of immune system over-activation, caused by COVID-19. According to this mechanism, hydroxychloroquine could alleviate symptoms of mild to severe COVID-19 pneumonia.
 <xref rid="bib0038" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>38</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
