<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A more commonly used strategy to increase expression and immunogenicity is the delivery of mRNA in complex with additional components. Among the first approaches was a format, whose two components, free and 
 <bold>protamine-complexed</bold> mRNA (a small arginine-rich nuclear protein that stabilizes nucleic acids), provide both strong antigen expression and immunostimulation (
 <xref rid="B147" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>–
 <xref rid="B150" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>). This vaccine format has proved to be immunogenic and capable of inducting protection against lethal challenge infections with influenza or rabies virus in several animal models (
 <xref rid="B124" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B151" ref-type="bibr">151</xref>). Using this format, CV7201, a candidate vaccine against rabies, was investigated as the first ever prophylactic mRNA-based vaccine in healthy human volunteers. The subjects received 80–640 μg of the mRNA vaccine three times by conventional needle-based injection or needle-free injection devices via the intradermal (ID) or intramuscular (IM) route. The vaccine was generally safe with a reasonable tolerability profile and led to the induction of neutralizing antibody titers at levels of 0·5 IU/mL or higher (as the correlate of protection) in 71% of subjects who had received ID injections of 80 or 160 μg mRNA vaccines by needle-free intradermal injection, while needle-based injection was ineffective (
 <xref rid="B152" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>). Antibody responses waned one year after first vaccination but could be boosted to 0·5 IU/mL or higher in 57% of subjects using 80 μg of mRNA delivered ID with a needle free injection device, indicating the induction of B cell memory responses. Although the mRNA vaccine candidate was able to induce antibody responses, further improvements to increase the magnitude and longevity of the immune responses are imperative for the development of an effective vaccine.
</p>
