<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the initial stage of infection, the spike (S) protein of SARS‐CoV‐2 first combines with a cell surface receptor (Wrapp et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0098" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). The S protein consists of two subunits: the S1 (bulb) and S2 (stalk) subunits. S1 is responsible for receptor binding, while S2 is responsible for membrane fusion (Liu et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). More specifically, S1 combines with the cognate receptor to induce a strong conformational change in S2, thereby resulting in the fusion of the virus envelope and host cellular membrane, followed by release of the nucleocapsid into the cytoplasm (Sekimukai et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0084" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). In view of this mechanism, targeting the S protein is likely to block SARS‐CoV‐2 infection, which can be regarded as the primary factor that needs to be studied in depth. Based on past experience, SARS‐CoV‐2 S protein‐neutralizing antibodies (nAbs) are most likely to become the preferred research and development strategy that should be modelled and considered by researchers and drug R&amp;D institutions to provide passive immunization against the infection (Ahmed, Quadeer, &amp; McKay, 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). According to the functional analysis of the S2 subunit, the interaction between heptad repeat 1 (HR1) and HR2 of S2 can form a six‐helical bundle (6‐HB), which facilitates the fusion process of the viral and host cell membranes. Drawing on experience with SARS‐CoV, Xia et al. designed HR1‐ and HR2‐derived peptides, designated SARS‐CoV‐2‐HR1P (aa 924‐965) and SARS‐CoV‐2‐HR2P (aa 1168‐1203), respectively (Xia et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0103" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). As SARS‐CoV‐2 and SARS‐CoV S‐HR2 sequences are 100% identical, SARS‐CoV‐2‐HR2P most likely acts as a membrane fusion inhibitor in a way similar to SARS‐HR2P, the reported SARS‐CoV fusion inhibitor (Liu et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>). A fusion experiment of SARS‐CoV‐2‐HR2P showed a potent fusion inhibitory effect with a half maximal inhibitory concentration (IC
 <sub>50</sub>) of 0.18 μM, while SARS‐CoV‐2‐HR1P exhibited no obvious fusion inhibitory activity up to 40 μM, indicating that SARS‐CoV‐2‐HR2P may be a promising therapeutic agent for SARS‐CoV‐2. However, the safety and actual effect await verification (Xia et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0101" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Research did not end there, so in a subsequent experiment, a pan‐coronavirus fusion inhibitor denoted as EK1 was designed based on the properties of the HR1 region (Xia et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0102" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). The results showed that EK1 also exhibited a potent fusion inhibitory effect with an IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 0.19 μM, suggesting that EK1 is also a promising treatment as a SARS‐CoV‐2 drug pending verification and development. According to other research results, we know that SARS‐CoV‐2 enters the host cell by binding to a membrane protein, the angiotensin‐converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) via the S protein receptor binding domain (RBD) (Yan et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0106" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Based on this observation, Zhang et al. synthesized a first‐in‐class peptide binder, named 23‐mer peptide binder (SBP1), by using automated fast‐flow peptide synthesis technology. After careful analysis, they found that SBP1 can potentially restrict the entry process of SARS‐CoV‐2 into human cells through binding to the SARS‐CoV‐2‐RBD with extremely low affinity (
 <italic>K</italic>
 <sub>D</sub> value = 47 nM) (Zhang, Pomplun, Loftis, Loas, &amp; Pentelute, 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0112" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Moreover, the human protein‐derived sequence of SBP1 prevented the binder from being immunogenic, which further promoted the peptide binder SBP1 as a promising preclinical drug lead for anti‐SARS‐CoV‐2 drug discovery and development.
</p>
