<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As novel cellular targets of licensed antiviral drugs, DNA terminase, helicase, and primase have a promising future. Letermovir has shown prophylactic effects against HCV in phase 2 and 3 of a clinical trial, by influencing the synthesis of the viral terminase complex (
 <xref rid="B120" ref-type="bibr">Kropeit et al., 2017</xref>). It did not demonstrate cross-resistance with other antiviral drugs, but did demonstrate a promising efficacy against cidofovir, foscarnet, and ganciclovir-resistance viruses (
 <xref rid="B154" ref-type="bibr">Melendez and Razonable, 2015</xref>). The primary inhibitors of terminase, benzimidazole derivatives (
 <xref rid="B232" ref-type="bibr">Valiente‐Echeverría et al., 2015</xref>), were initially introduced and developed as anticancer drugs. The efficacy of these derivatives on CMV replication did not comprise the DNA synthesis inhibition on viruses but led to virions production, which had a left-end-truncated genome inside their capsid (
 <xref rid="B153" ref-type="bibr">McVoy and Nixon, 2005</xref>). The results showed that benzimidazole derivatives inhibited the replication of CMV at the final steps of viral DNA synthesis (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Champier et al., 2008</xref>). The other new licensed antiviral drugs have affected the DDX3 (Asp-Glu-Ala-Asp(DEAD)-box polypeptide 3), that is a member of ATP-dependent RNA helicases. DDX3 plays various roles in RNA metabolism, such as transcription, translation, nuclear export, and stress granules assembly. Moreover, the evidence showed that DDX3 is a part of the innate immunity response against viral infections. It is interesting to note that some RNA viruses, such as HCV and HIV-1, use DDX3 to perform different replication cycles stages. Therefore, it appears that viruses have progressed to use DDX3’s boxes to coincide with threatening, so the innate immune response (
 <xref rid="B232" ref-type="bibr">Valiente‐Echeverría et al., 2015</xref>) and targeting helicase could be a novel strategy to combat viral diseases. One of the other new classes of antiviral drugs with the potential to treat HSV infections is the helicase-primase inhibitors (
 <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">Kleymann et al., 2002</xref>), through affecting the non-structural protein-3 helicase (NS3h) and 5B (NS5B) RNA-dependent RNA polymerase, which are necessary for RNA replication of viruses. The helicase-primase complex is also the target of prilelivir and amenamevir with antiviral activities against HSV-1 and HSV-2 (
 <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">Kleymann et al., 2002</xref>). This class of antiviral drugs also showed a potential efficacy against varicella-zoster virus (VZV) (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Chono et al., 2010</xref>). Altogether, these proteins are unique targets for the discovery and development of direct-acting antivirals (
 <xref rid="B258" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2017</xref>).
</p>
