<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para150">What must be done to mitigate the impact of large outbreaks of COVID-19 in prisons? The public health importance of prison responses to influenza outbreaks has been recognised in the USA,
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref> where the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention have developed a checklist for pandemic influenza preparedness in correctional settings. WHO has also issued prison-specific guidance for responding to COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="box1" ref-type="boxed-text">panel</xref> ).
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref>
 <boxed-text id="box1">
  <label>Panel</label>
  <caption>
   <title>Prison-specific guidance for responding to COVID-19</title>
  </caption>
  <p id="para10">
   <bold>Joint planning</bold>
  </p>
  <p id="para20">Include prison health and correctional authorities in the overall public health response, rather than permitting them to plan and operate in isolation.</p>
  <p id="para30">
   <bold>Risk management</bold>
  </p>
  <p id="para40">Design and implement adequate systems for limiting importation and exportation of cases from or to the community, and transmission and spread within prisons.</p>
  <p id="para50">
   <bold>Prevention and control</bold>
  </p>
  <p id="para60">Develop protocols for entry screening, personal protection measures, social distancing, environmental cleaning and disinfection, and restriction of movement, including limitation of transfers and access for non-essential staff and visitors.</p>
  <p id="para70">
   <bold>Treatment</bold>
  </p>
  <p id="para80">Explicitly and transparently align prison health systems with the wider health and emergency planning systems, including transfer protocols for patients requiring specialised care. Isolate cases and contacts if required to control the spread of infection in prisons. However, special consideration of the potentially serious mental health effects of isolation in these settings is essential.
   <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
   <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> In high-income countries, maintaining isolation without depriving incarcerated people of human contact might be possible.
   <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">
    <sup>12</sup>
   </xref>
  </p>
  <p id="para90">
   <bold>Information sharing</bold>
  </p>
  <p id="para100">Close collaboration between health and justice ministries should be established to ensure continuity of information, which is a crucial component of an effective, coordinated, whole-of-government response. Governance of prison health by a ministry of health, rather than a ministry of justice or similar, is likely to facilitate timely information sharing.
   <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">
    <sup>13</sup>
   </xref>
  </p>
 </boxed-text>
</p>
