<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phylodynamic analyses are not without limitations. Dense and representative sampling at a scale equivalent to epidemiological surveys is required to fulfill the potential of phylodynamics for understanding epidemics of rapidly-evolving viruses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b51-viruses-03-00379">51</xref>]. The construction of phylogenetic trees from these viral sequences may be complicated by 
 <bold>recombination</bold> and, in the case of segmented viruses, 
 <bold>reassortment</bold> of viral genomes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36-viruses-03-00379">36</xref>]. As a result of these processes, the genes on a single viral sequence may have very different origins (see the discussion of the different origins of the hemagglutinin and neuraminidase segments of H5N1 avian influenza in Lemey 
 <italic>et al.</italic> 2009 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44-viruses-03-00379">44</xref>]). Therefore, concatenated analysis of multiple genes may be confounded. The ability to construct phylogenies is further limited by the total viral genetic information available. GenBank is a vast public database that contains records of genetic sequences; however, its usefulness is dependent upon the willingness and/or ability of individuals and organizations to submit viral sequences. Governments and industrial institutions may be reluctant to report sequences of economically important viruses (
 <italic>i.e.</italic>, avian influenza) due to the potential negative economic impacts that may ensue. Although phylodynamics is currently encumbered by the aforementioned factors, there is hope for progress. Advancements in coalescent theory will help us to deal with the phylogeny construction problems caused by recombination and reassortment. They will also facilitate better utilization of genomic and spatial data, provided these advancements are also accompanied by a simultaneous increase in computing power, which is also currently limiting.
</p>
