<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Viruses exist in living system since living cells first evolved, so found wherever there is life exist. Viruses do not form fossils so the mode of their investigation/detection is only by using molecular techniques (Iyer et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">2006</xref>). Most of the viruses are harmful to animals (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Introduction_to_viruses" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Introduction_to_viruses</ext-link>) and cause a number of infectious diseases. Common human diseases caused by viruses include the common cold, influenza, chickenpox, and cold sores. Ebola, AIDS, avian influenza, and SARS are various serious diseases caused by viruses (Emiliani 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">1993</xref>). The relative ability of viruses to cause disease is known as virulence of virus. Viral diseases sometimes cause confusion with any other causative agent such as the possible connection between human herpesvirus six (HHV6) and neurological diseases such as multiple sclerosis and chronic fatigue syndrome (Thomas 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR164">2008</xref>). There is controversy over whether the bornavirus, previously thought to cause neurological diseases in horses, could be responsible for psychiatric illnesses in human (Mandal 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2013</xref>). According to Shors (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR156">2008</xref>) viruses transmit by two modes, i.e., vertical (from mother to child) and horizontal (from person to person). Vertical transmission include hepatitis B virus and HIV where the baby is born already infected with the virus. 
 <italic>Varicella-zoster</italic> virus is another but rarest example of vertical transmission. Although this virus causes relatively mild infections in humans, it can be fatal to the fetus and newly born baby (Mandal 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2013</xref>). Generally living populations are affected by horizontal transmission of viral infection where viral transmission occurs via exchange of blood and by sexual activity (HIV, hepatitis B, and hepatitis C), through mouth by exchange of saliva (Epstein-Barr virus), through contaminated food or water (norovirus), by breathing viruses in the form of aerosols (influenza virus) and by insect vectors such as mosquitoes (dengue) (Collier et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">1998</xref>). Currently, 21 families of viruses are known to cause disease in humans (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/virus%20classification" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/virus classification</ext-link>). So due to broad spectrum of harmful infections/diseases caused by viruses, a rapid and accurate diagnosis is essential for timely therapeutic interventions (Barenfanger et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2000</xref>).
</p>
