<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0135">
 <italic>In silico</italic> drug repurposing methodologies have accelerated the studies in drug discovery through the use of data mining approaches, bioinformatics techniques, and predictive models for determining the efficacy and safety of the drugs. However, there is still a long way to reach the high success rates with repurposed drugs (e.g., repurposed candidates succeeded 9%–67%, depending on the similarity between indicated and repurposed therapeutic areas, and the novel molecular entity success rate is ∼10%) (
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Hay et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Neuberger et al., 2019</xref>). This is presumably attributable to the (1) heterogeneity and incompleteness of the available data, (2) flexibility and complexity of the entire biological system and pathophysiological conditions, and (3) lack of reliable experimental data and accurate parameters related to absorption, distribution, metabolism, excretion (ADME) and toxicity, just to name a few (
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Brown and Patel, 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Ekins et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2020a</xref>). Future studies should be directed toward obtaining a more improved test standardization and proof of concept as well as integrating the big and heterogeneous amount of data into a harmonious workflow. To leverage the benefits, drug repurposing must be performed through aforethought procedures based on the advanced stage innovation. On account of clinical trials for drug development, regardless of repositioned drug or novel molecular entity, these are expensive and time consuming, so basic science methodologies (i.e., improved animal models, accurate toxicology assessment, biomarker identification, and novel targeted delivery technologies) that undertake and reduce the possibility of hypothesis risk will be essential to increase the success rate of repurposed drugs in the product development process (
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Oprea et al., 2011</xref>).
</p>
