<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The clinical application of protein drugs requires a cost-effective large-scale production procedure to meet the high volume needed in a clinical setting. For efficient GRFT production, seven different production methods have been developed and optimized (
 <xref rid="marinedrugs-17-00567-t008" ref-type="table">Table 8</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B45-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Giomarelli et al. used a fermenter and a rich, auto-inducing medium, which led to an approximately 45-fold increase in the total amount of GRFT per liter with approximately 70% of the protein expressed in the soluble fraction [
 <xref rid="B49-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. O’Keefe et al. were able to produce GRFT in multigram quantities by using 
 <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> plants transduced with a tobacco mosaic virus vector expressing GRFT [
 <xref rid="B45-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Hahn et al. employed a simple spraying method to introduce agrobacterium vectors into Nicotiana plants in the presence of a surfactant as a substitute for vacuum inoculation [
 <xref rid="B50-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. They found that recombinant GRFT is stable during the storage of plant biomass as silage, which is suitable for mass production of cost-sensitive products [
 <xref rid="B50-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Fuqua et al., however, developed a simplified GRFT purification method [
 <xref rid="B48-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. They achieved &gt;99% pure GRFT by generating the initial green juice extract in pH 4 buffer, heating the extract to 55 °C, incubating it overnight with a bentonite MgCl
 <sub>2</sub> mixture, and purifying it via chromatography [
 <xref rid="B48-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Vamvaka et al. successfully produced GRFT by using the endosperm of transgenic rice plants (
 <italic>Oryza sativa</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B52-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. They found that both crude and pure GRFT had potent anti-HIV activity, and the crude extracts were not toxic in human cell lines [
 <xref rid="B52-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. This suggests that crude GRFT with minimal processing could be administered to reduce costs associated with purification [
 <xref rid="B52-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Petrova et al. expressed GRFT in the probiotic strains 
 <italic>Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> GG and 
 <italic>L. rhamnosus</italic> GR-1 for gastrointestinal and vaginal mucosal delivery, respectively [
 <xref rid="B51-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Hoelscher et al. used stably transformed tobacco chloroplasts to produce GRFT, which accounted for up to 5% of the total soluble protein of the plant [
 <xref rid="B53-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. They also found that the tobacco, when dried, provides a storable source of GRFT that can be purified at a later date [
 <xref rid="B53-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. However, when produced in 
 <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>, Kim et al. found that GRFT had pathologic effects on plants because it was directed to the apoplast during production, resulting in necrotic symptoms associated with hypersensitive response (HR)-like cell death [
 <xref rid="B54-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. They found that a specific interaction between GRFT and an apoplast-located endogenous glycoprotein, XYL1, initiated the HR response. To suppress GRFT-induced cell death in 
 <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana,</italic> exogenous expression of naphthalene hydroxylase was suggested by the authors [
 <xref rid="B54-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. To avoid the emergence of HIV-1 strains resistant to single microbicides, Vamvaka et al. expressed components of multiple anti-HIV proteins including GRFT, 2G12 mAb, and cyanovirin-N in rice endosperm [
 <xref rid="B55-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. They found that extracts from plants expressing all three proteins showed enhanced in vitro binding to gp120 and synergistic HIV-1 neutralization [
 <xref rid="B55-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Unexpectedly, they also found that synergistic HIV neutralization caused by the triple microbicide was enhanced by production in rice endosperm because rice globulin protein enhances gp120 binding in the expressed proteins [
 <xref rid="B55-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. 
</p>
