<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is also important to note that New York City has a high background rate of VLS attributable to NYC’s robust HIV infrastructure,[
 <xref rid="pone.0215965.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0215965.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] and therefore the potential benefit of the scaled-up intervention, and its cost-effectiveness, was less favorable than would be likely in other major cities with large HIV epidemics and lower VLS levels. While 85.0% of PLWH were diagnosed and only 57.9% had VLS in 2015 in the US overall,[
 <xref rid="pone.0215965.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0215965.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] 95.0% of PLWH were diagnosed and approximately 80.0% of diagnosed PLWH had VLS in 2016 in NYC.[
 <xref rid="pone.0215965.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] In addition, NYC has a particularly robust infrastructure for HIV care, such that NYC “usual care” for PLWH includes a variety of other comprehensive care management programs, such as NYS Medicaid “health homes,” the NYS Ryan White Part B-funded Retention and Adherence Program (RAP), supportive HIV housing programs, and the NYS AIDS Drug Assistance Program (ADAP) and ADAP Plus (with health insurance/primary care coverage). The CCP intervention may have a greater additive effect, and therefore more favorable cost-effectiveness, in environments that lack these many complementary programs. Given all of the existing HIV care resources and high background levels of VLS in NYC, the subset of New Yorkers diagnosed with HIV who remain unsuppressed (the final 20%) may also represent a group with particularly complex barriers to treatment engagement, requiring greater effort and cost to resolve in VLS than would be required to achieve VLS among most unsuppressed PLWH in other areas of the US. Similarly, the cost of living in NYC is substantially higher than in other regions and, as a substantial portion of the intervention cost is derived from personnel salary costs, the intervention may also be less costly to implement in other settings outside of NYC. Finally, targeting the program to individuals at highest risk of transmission, as well as at the highest risk of HIV-related complications, may increase the potential for CCP implementation to be cost-effective in NYC, even with current program costs and observed levels of effectiveness.
</p>
