<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In response to the COVID-19 pandemic, the U.S. FDA continues its work to ensure safe and effective treatments. Potential therapies that are being investigated and developed for the treatment and management of COVID-19 now comprise of numerous antiviral agents, immunotherapies, and vaccines (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). The antiviral nucleotide analog agent remdesivir can inhibit the replication of SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV in multiple 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> systems, such as primary human airway epithelial cell cultures (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Remdesivir has shown promising results in rhesus macaques infected with SARS-CoV-2, and the Adaptive COVID-19 Treatment Trial for remdesivir, sponsored by the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Disease, has been completed (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clinicalTrials.gov" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">clinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>, NCT 04280705) (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). Based on this trial and the Gilead-sponsored trial (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clinicalTrials.gov" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">clinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>, NCT 04292899), the U.S. FDA has authorized emergency use of remdesivir for the treatment of COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Lopinavir/Ritonavir, an HIV protease inhibitor, was found to inhibit SARS-CoV-2 replication in Vero E6 cells (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). Hospitalized COVID-19 patients in Wuhan, China, were treated with the combinational therapy of lopinavir/ritonavir. However, the effect was moderate, and 13% of the patients had to be removed early in the treatment due to adverse side effects (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). New triple antiviral therapy combination of interferon beta-1b, lopinavir-ritonavir, and ribavirin in the treatment of mild to moderate COVID-19 patients was safe and superior to lopinavir-ritonavir treatment alone in alleviating symptoms, shortening the duration of viral shedding, and hospital stay. However, the lack of a placebo group was one of several limitations to this trial (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>).
</p>
