<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>These three relevant public health problems produce a high burden of disease for the population, as well as giving more complexity to the disease notification system, case by case, due to the similarity of the clinical features in the acute phase of these arboviruses, which are transmitted by the same vectors and in the same population spaces. Thus, there is no doubt that the actions of health services for its prevention and control should be developed in an integrated manner. However, it is necessary that the public health surveillance system seeks to improve its specific diagnostic strategies, not only to know the epidemiological profile in each space, but especially to enable appropriate clinical management in the acute form, as the cases with suspected dengue that need more massive and immediate hydration to prevent deaths; when it comes to Zika, patients should be warned of the possibility of post-acute neurological forms requiring hospitalization, as well as special attention to pregnant women and guidance for women of childbearing age to protect themselves from insect bites and sexual transmission; as for chikungunya, an important proportion of cases require monitoring and management of joint pain. Thus, improving case definitions requires conducting validation studies as well as training health professionals involved in patient care in order to make them better able to make diagnostic suspicions. It is essential to expand the offer of specific laboratory tests, but nowadays such tests for acute phase of the disease are almost restricted to molecular tests (due to the similarity of antibodies against dengue and Zika), which are very expensive to use on a large scale. In this sense, studies focused on the development, with different technologies, of sensitive and specific serological tests for these two flaviviruses, are a good prospect to be used in the routine of health services, as they are cheaper and easier to use. It is understood that, alongside the integration of surveillance of urban arboviruses, these initiatives should be adopted to overcome the difficulties of clinical management, such as the production of more reliable epidemiological data, which are of the greatest relevance for the planning of public health actions and for the prevention of these diseases.</p>
