<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Direct administration of monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) may play an effective role in CoV control as an intervention in exposed individuals. It has been observed that patients recovering from SARS display potent neutralizing antibody responses.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0009">9</xref>
 </sup> A clinical trial proposed the use of a set of mAbs that functionally target specific domains in MERS-CoV S protein. These mAbs bind to six specific epitope groups interacting with the receptor binding, membrane fusion, and sialic acid-binding sites, which represent the three important entry functions of MERS-CoV S protein.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0021">21</xref>,
  <xref rid="CIT0038">38</xref>
 </sup> Moreover, passive immunization with poorly and potently neutralizing antibodies induces substantial protection in mice subjected to lethal MERS-CoV challenge. Thus, use of these antibodies may represent a novel approach to increase humoral protection against emerging CoVs by targeting various S protein epitopes and functions. The cross-neutralization capacity of SARS-CoV RBD-specific neutralizing mAbs greatly depends on the similarity between their RBDs. This is why SARS-CoV RBD-specific antibodies can cross-neutralize SARS-like (SL) CoVs, 
 <italic>i.e</italic>., bat-SL-CoV strain WIV1 RBD that had 8 amino acid differences to SARS-CoV, but not bat-SL-CoV strain SHC014 (24 amino acid differences).
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0039">39</xref>
 </sup> Such cross-neutralizing SARS-CoV RBD-specific mAbs can be evaluated for efficacy with SARS-CoV-2. This requires a comparative analysis of SARS-CoV-2 RBD with SARS-CoV so that suitable RBD-specific mAbs can be identified and evaluated in clinical trials. Regeneron is trying to identify mAbs specific and effective for COVID-19. Combination therapy with mAbs and the drug remdesivir could be an ideal therapeutic option for COVID-19.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0040">40</xref>
 </sup> Further evaluation is required before confirming the efficacy of such combination therapy.
</p>
