<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Dengue, chikungunya, and Zika are an increasing global public health concern as a result of their dramatically increased burden of disease and rapid geographical spread [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Dengue is the most important arthropod-borne viral disease in humans. It is endemic in 125 countries mostly in America, South-East Asia and Western Pacific regions [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Approximately 4 billion people are now at risk of dengue [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. A dengue virus (DENV) infection causes a flu-like illness and occasionally progresses to severe forms of dengue: dengue hemorrhagic fever (DHF) and dengue shock syndrome (DSS) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Individuals infected with chikungunya virus (CHIKV) generally have symptoms such as high fever, skin rash and debilitating polyarthralgia, which usually persist 1–2 weeks. However, a proportion of cases progresses to the chronic stage of CHIKV infection, in which some symptoms, such as arthralgia, last for months to years [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Zika virus (ZIKV) infection has been linked to adverse fetal outcomes, including microcephaly and other congenital abnormalities in the developing fetus and newborn. Also, it has been associated with Guillain- Barré syndrome (GBS)[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], but one must take into account that GBS is also associated with other bacterial and viral infections, e.g. Campylobacter jejuni, Influenza and other Vector-Borne Diseases (VBDs) such as dengue and chikungunya [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. These VBDs present with flu-like symptoms and are generally self-limiting, barring the development of the aforementioned complications [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].
</p>
