<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Secondary bacterial infections develop in patients during or after initial infection with an infective pathogen, often a virus (
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Morris et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2018</xref>) and are associated with high morbidity and mortality rates (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Mallia et al., 2012</xref>). Co-infections, secondary infections, or “superinfections” occur during viral epidemics; around 50 million deaths were ascribed to bacterial co-infections during the 1918–1919 Spanish Flu pandemic; although clinical records often do now record such infection complications (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Kash and Taubenberger, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">MacIntyre et al., 2018</xref>). While secondary infections occur in succession to the primary infection, co-infections are caused by multiple pathogens of viral, bacterial, or fungal origin and occur simultaneously at the same time. There tends to be a strong focus on a single pathogen rather than a combination of pathogens, especially for the viral–bacterial infections most commonly observed in patients (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Jamieson et al., 2010</xref>). 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, 
 <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic>, 
 <italic>Neisseria meningitides</italic>, 
 <italic>Haemophilus influenzae</italic>, 
 <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic>, and members of the genus 
 <italic>Proteus</italic>, 
 <italic>Enterobacter</italic>, and 
 <italic>Citrobacter</italic> spp., are some of the most commonly isolated bacteria during secondary infections (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Handel et al., 2009</xref>). Hospitals are a common source of the pathogens that cause secondary infections, these so-called nosocomial pathogen infections are acquired from an environment in which antibiotics are commonplace, and as such; many have acquired resistance to a broad range of antibiotics. Decades of misuse and, over-prescribing of antibiotics has resulted in selection of pathogens that show multi-drug resistance (MDR). MDR is a global health challenge as in many cases no (chemical) antibiotics exist to treat such infections, including secondary infections. Secondary bacterial infections are facilitated by the exposure to a pathogen together with an immune system that is inapt to appropriately react to both pathogen types, as a consequence of the primary viral infection. For such patients, the only option is to support their immune system and prevent progression of the infection that could lead to the death of the patient such as septic shock. Antibiotics therapies deployed as a “last resort” or the use of exceptionally high doses of antibiotics often have negative consequences. Many key human pathogens are showing resistance to antibiotics including Methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> (MRSA), multidrug-resistant 
 <italic>Streptococcus</italic>, Vancomycin-resistant 
 <italic>Enterococci</italic> (VRE), resistant 
 <italic>Mycobacterium</italic>, Carbapenem-resistant 
 <italic>Enterobacteriaceae</italic> (CRE), Colistin-resistant 
 <italic>Klebsiella</italic>, Carbapenem-resistant 
 <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, and Carbapenem-resistant 
 <italic>Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Kumar and Chordia, 2017</xref>). The problem is exacerbated by the discontinuation by big pharma of chemical antibiotics discovery programs in the search for chemical antibiotics (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Loh and Leptihn, 2020</xref>). Other options to treat MDR infections would be beneficial.
</p>
