<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0060">Data from the MERS, SARS, and influenza epidemics provide enough evidence that viral infections can cause acute and chronic cardiovascular injury.
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref> Acutely, COVID-19 has been shown to trigger acute coronary syndromes (ACSs), myocarditis, arrhythmias, acute onset heart failure, and venous thromboembolism (VTE) 
 <bold>(</bold>
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>
 <bold>)</bold>. The overall incidence of acute cardiac injury caused by COVID-19 ranges from 7 to 28% among hospitalized patients.
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref> The mechanisms include direct myocyte injury via the ACE-2 receptors, infection-induced proinflammatory state, and cytokine storm, and subsequently increased metabolic demand in the background of lung injury induced hypoxia (
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). All these mechanisms have been explained in detail previously. COVID-19 may exacerbate underlying CVD and may also give rise to new cardiovascular injuries.
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref> Evidence is now available, supporting the fact that the risk of developing cardiovascular complications is more among patients who have pre-existing CVD compared with those who do not.
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref> In a retrospective analysis of 187 confirmed patients with COVID-19, those with underlying CVD were more likely to exhibit elevation of troponin T levels compared with the patients without CVD (36 [54.5%] vs. 16 [13.2%]).
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
