<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The simplest way to predict NLG addition is to identify a sequon, Asn-X-Ser/Thr, within the primary glycoprotein amino acid sequence. However, not all sequons are fully or even partially occupied, for various reasons including amino acid sequence [
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51–53</xref>] and the specific cell type infected by the virus. Amino acid sequence also does not allow accurate prediction of the nature of the glycans added to different sites [
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Approaches for more detailed analysis of influenza virus NLG have been comprehensively described in a recent review [
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Briefly, these approaches can be divided into two major groups: those providing information on the nature and relative abundance of the glycoforms present on a glycoprotein, and those that further determine the degree to which each sequon is actually occupied by glycans. The first group of methods requires the initial release of glycans from the glycoproteins (e.g. by using hydrazine or the enzymes PNGase F and PNGase A) followed by mass spectrometry (MS) [
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56–58</xref>] or high-performance liquid chromatography [
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] for analysis of the released glycoforms. The second group of methods for NLG analysis involves immobilization of glycoproteins (using lectins or periodate-treated glycopeptides linked to hydrazide-activated beads) prior to enzymatic treatment with PNGaseF [
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61–63</xref>]. During the process of glycan release, the Asn-X-Thr/Ser sequence converts to Asp-X-Thr/Ser, resulting in a mass difference. Subsequent MS/MS analysis of the eluted peptides allow identification of the glycosylated sites. Determination of precise glycoforms present at specific glycosites on intact glycoprotein consists of a complex of various techniques and procedures including sophisticated fragmentation by collision-induced dissociation, or high-energy collision dissociation, or electron-transfer dissociation [
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64–67</xref>].
</p>
