<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Acute respiratory disease (ARD) accounts for a large proportion of all acute morbidities, as well as mortalities, worldwide, among which acute viral respiratory tract infection is the leading cause (appropriate 80%).
 <xref rid="jmv25674-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> The major viral pathogens include influenza virus, respiratory syncytial virus (RSV), coronavirus, adenovirus, and rhinovirus. In children below the age of five, the combined global mortality of only influenza and RSV reaches 300 000 deaths each year.
 <xref rid="jmv25674-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>2</sup>
 </xref> Other respiratory viruses, such as adenovirus and rhinovirus, are associated with lower mortality, but significant morbidity, causing a huge economic burden.
 <xref rid="jmv25674-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> The highly pathogenic emerging and reemerging coronaviruses that may cause epidemics or pandemics, such as severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS‐CoV) and Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS‐CoV), have posed great threat to global public health. Most recently, a novel coronavirus 2019‐nCoV (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.who.int</ext-link>) has caused the pneumonia in 41 confirmed cases of patients, including 7 in serious condition, 1 dead, and 2 recovered (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.shine.cn/news/nation/2001119576/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.shine.cn/news/nation/2001119576/</ext-link>). The full genomic sequence of this coronavirus was released on January 10, 2020 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://virological.org/t/initial-genome-release-of-novel-coronavirus/319?from=groupmessage&amp;isappinstalled=0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://virological.org/t/initial-genome-release-of-novel-coronavirus/319?from=groupmessage&amp;isappinstalled=0</ext-link>), which is more than 82% identical to those of SARS‐CoV and bat SARS‐like coronavirus (SL‐CoV).
 <xref rid="jmv25674-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
