<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Currently available inactivated influenza vaccines are suboptimal, particularly in the groups that are most highly at risk, and do not induce sufficiently broad cross protective activity to protect against strains that have antigenically drifted (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). Alternative strategies for the development of more highly effective and cross protective and long-lasting influenza vaccines must be pursued. Influenza viruses in which the NS1 protein is deleted are avirulent and are postulated to be more immunogenic, due to the absence of the immune response suppression usually mediated by the NS1 protein. With this assumption, we established a panel of DelNS1 live attenuated influenza viruses (LAIVs) bearing adaptive mutations that support their replication in MDCK cells and embryonated chicken eggs, enabling large-scale production without helper virus assistance. Master donor backbone viruses were established for both influenza A virus and influenza B virus and were verified in 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> systems. The currently available LAIV vaccine utilizes cold adaptation and temperature restriction to ensure attenuation in humans. We found that DelNS1 LAIVs are nonpathogenic and have a spontaneous preference for replication at the lower temperature of 33°C. Given the rapid evolution of influenza viruses and the uncertainty regarding the emergence of novel strains, future influenza vaccines should ideally provide cross protection against antigenically drifted viral strains and novel subtypes of zoonotic influenza viruses. Our data strongly support the use of a strategy involving removal of the NS1 protein, a viral antagonist of the host immune response, to make DelNS1 LAIV vaccines which induce more-effective and broader immunity for protection against seasonal and pandemic influenza virus strains. We have shown DelNS1 H1N1, H3N2, and B LAIVs to possess marked cross protective activities in terms of cross subtype and/or antigenically drifted variants in mouse challenge experiments. Importantly, we have also tested a strategy to enhance specific immunity through expression of additional viral antigens in the DelNS1 LAIV system. These findings clearly demonstrate that DelNS1 LAIVs with adaptive mutations that support replication in MDCK cells and embryonated chicken eggs and the capacity to express extra viral antigens will make better influenza vaccines, addressing some critical pitfalls of existing products.
</p>
