<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One of the advantages of LAIV vaccines over inactivated split or subunit influenza virus vaccines is the ability to induce both humoral and cellular immunity. The currently available commercial LAIV (Influenza Mist) is based on cold adaptation/temperature sensitivity/attenuation (ca/ts/att) phenotypic features which allow the vaccine virus to replicate at the lower temperatures experienced in the upper respiratory tract but which restrict or attenuate replication at the higher temperature within the lungs (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). LAIVs have been shown to induce a significant amount of mucosal IgA but modest levels of serum IgG (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Blocking virus transmission is one of the key criteria for seasonal and pandemic influenza vaccines. The superior ability of LAIVs to induce potent mucosal immunity could be important for limiting virus transmission, especially when used in response to a pandemic or a severe epidemic. However, this cold-adapted LAIV vaccine replicates so efficiently in the upper respiratory tract of young children who are seronegative or who have not experienced previous infection with influenza viruses, being shed at a comparatively high titer for a long period of time (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>), that it is not recommended for use in children below 2 years old, who are commonly naive with respect to influenza virus infection. On the other hand, preexisting immunity from previous exposure to similar viruses may limit the replication of the current LAIV vaccine in adults. Therefore, an improved LAIV with a lower level of associated virus shedding that more potently induces a full spectrum of protective immunity in the elderly is necessary. Other strategies used to construct different forms of LAIV include acquisition of interferon-sensitive mutations and use of premature termination codons to attenuate or completely block influenza virus replication in normal cells (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Those studies were performed mainly on the basis of the genetically well-characterized A/WSN/1933 or A/PR8/1934 H1N1 strains, and it is not clear if such strategies can be applied in other subtypes of influenza A or influenza B viruses, given that strain-specific adaptive mechanisms are relatively common in influenza viruses. There is also concern regarding the stability of attenuation and the risk of reversion resulting in the virulence of original strains being regained during infection with LAIV vaccines. Live attenuated influenza vaccines with modified NS1 or lacking the entire NS1 coding region have been extensively explored and evaluated in two previous human trials (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). DelNS1 LAIV is made by permanently removing the 
 <italic>NS1</italic> coding region from the viral genome, making the resultant vaccine virus fully attenuated and unable to cause disease in the host. The NS1 protein has important roles in virus replication, and the introduction of a novel NS segment would make the constellation of viral genes unfit for replication. As such, the risk of DelNS1 LAIV reassortment with a recently emerged novel strain to regain the NS1 in the situation of a pandemic is greatly minimized. However, the lack of an effective production system has limited the further development of modified and NS1-deleted vaccines. The panel of DelNS1 LAIVs described here contained adaptive mutations facilitating efficient replication in vaccine-producing MDCK cells or in embryonated eggs. These DelNS1 LAIVs are not expected to release significant levels of virus particles from normal epithelial cells in the upper respiratory tract, as suggested by the attenuation seen in 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> cultures of A549 cells (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2A</xref>). This property will make the DelNS1 virus safer than the current LAIV vaccine, preventing excess shedding of virus following immunization of immunologically naive or seronegative young children or of individuals who had not previously been infected with influenza virus. The safety features inherent with the removal of a key virulence element, together with the advantage of inducing more-potent immunity in the absence of NS1 interference, make DelNS1 LAIV a much-improved version of the LAIV vaccine for use against both seasonal and pandemic influenza virus strains.
</p>
