<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We performed the serologic assays, hemagglutination inhibition assay, virus neutralization test, and IgM ELISA with all serial serum samples collected from all 10 patients (
 <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>7</italic>
 </xref>) and real-time reverse transcription PCR (RT-PCR) (
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>8</italic>
 </xref>) on the serum fractions of clotted blood collected from the first 6 patients with suspected cases described previously (
 <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>6</italic>
 </xref>). We extracted nucleic acid from EDTA whole blood samples collected from the initial 4 patients with probable cases using the MagMax Pathogen RNA/DNA Kit (Applied Biosystems, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.thermofisher.com" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.thermofisher.com</ext-link>) and then tested by RT-PCR. We determined the partial genome sequences of viruses from RT-PCR–positive whole blood samples using sequence-independent single-primer amplification combined with sequencing in triplicate on an Illumina MiSeq (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.illumina.com" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.illumina.com</ext-link>) and raw data processing, as described previously (
 <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>9</italic>
 </xref>). After quality and host filtering and using a requirement of 
 <underline>&gt;</underline>3× coverage per base, we mapped raw reads to reference sequences representing the RVFV large (L), medium (M), and small (S) segments (GenBank accession nos. KX611605–7). We concatenated sequence fragments of segments, prepared alignments in MEGA6 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.megasoftware.net" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.megasoftware.net</ext-link>), performed phylogenetic analyses using RAxML version 8.2.10 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://evomics.org/learning/phylogenetics/raxml" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://evomics.org/learning/phylogenetics/raxml</ext-link>), and visualized trees with Figtree version 1.4.3 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree</ext-link>).
</p>
