<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The first G12 genotype (G12P[4]) was discovered in 1987 from the Philippines, in children less than 2 years old, affected with acute diarrhea [
 <xref rid="pone.0220387.ref098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0220387.ref099" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. A decade later, G12 was identified as an emerging genotype in several countries of Asia, Europe, North America and South America mostly in combination with P[8] and P[6] [
 <xref rid="pone.0220387.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0220387.ref100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0220387.ref101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>]. Now, G12 has been spreading as a devastating genotype in many Asian countries including Pakistan [
 <xref rid="pone.0220387.ref102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. These unusual strains such as G12P[6] are not included in the formulation of two available rotavirus vaccines Rotarix (GlaxoSmithkline) and RotaTeq (Merck). Hence, it has not yet been determined, whether or not these two available vaccines provide protective immunity against these unusual strains [
 <xref rid="pone.0220387.ref102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. The continuous monitoring and whole genome-based analyses are essential in understanding the evolutionary dynamics and the spread of G12 strains in Asia. In Pakistan, G12 strains were reported by Alam and colleagues in two children of Rawalpindi, Pakistan for the first time in 2009 [
 <xref rid="pone.0220387.ref103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. Other studies from the same region by Tamim in 2010 and Umair in 2014 detected G12 with 6.7% and 16.7% prevalence, respectively [
 <xref rid="pone.0220387.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0220387.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In the present study genotype G12P[6] was found as the second most abundant genotype with 21% prevalence in Pakistan. This emphasises the continuous spread of the G12 genotype in Pakistan from 2009 to 2016, as well as in Asian countries. On phylogenetic observation, Pakistani G12 strains were most closely associated with Thailand strain (B1373). This reflects the close connection with this country in terms of travel and other business activities [
 <xref rid="pone.0220387.ref104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0220387.ref105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. The high prevalence of G12 genotype during the same period was also detected in neighbouring country Bangladesh [
 <xref rid="pone.0220387.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Therefore, it is suggested that the emergence of G12 in 2015 as a dominant strain in Pakistan more likely was due to their spread from other Asian countries to Pakistan.
</p>
