<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="mpp12917-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 4</label>
 <caption>
  <p>The 5′‐end of the movement protein (MP) of the tomato leaf curl New Delhi virus (ToLCNDV)‐OM is required for mechanical transmissibility. (a) Schematic illustration of the pCB1B and pOM1B infectious clones showing eight different amino acid residues in MP between the ToLCNDV‐OM and CB isolates. Four different amino acids (3rd, 6th, 8th, and 19th) were found at the N terminus, and four other amino acids (193rd, 225th, 233rd, and 262nd) were found at the C terminus of MPs. Two clusters of different amino acids were separated via the 
   <italic>Pst</italic>I restriction enzyme recognition site. Four recombinant constructs, pCB1B::OM
   <sub>5′</sub>
   <italic>
    <sub>MP</sub>
   </italic>, pCB1B::OM
   <sub>3′</sub>
   <italic>
    <sub>MP</sub>
   </italic>, pOM1B::CB
   <sub>5′</sub>
   <italic>
    <sub>MP</sub>
   </italic>, and pOM1B::CB
   <sub>3′</sub>
   <italic>
    <sub>MP</sub>
   </italic>, were produced by exchanging the 5′
   <italic>MP</italic>‐intergenic region (IR) fragment (455 bp) and the 3′‐end 
   <italic>MP</italic> fragment (817 bp) between two isolates using 
   <italic>Eco</italic>RV, 
   <italic>Pst</italic>I, and/or 
   <italic>Hin</italic>dIII cleavage. (b) 
   <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>, oriental melon, and cucumber plants after mechanical inoculation with the infectious clones, either developed viral symptoms (O) or exhibited no symptoms (X) at 10–12 days post‐inoculation. The viral inoculum used for mechanical sap inoculation was prepared from 
   <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> with symptoms after agroinoculation with an appropriate combination of the clones. Symptoms were observed only in plants inoculated with the constructs carrying the 5′ region of the ToLCNDV‐OM 
   <italic>MP</italic> gene. (c) PCR detection of the 
   <italic>NSP</italic>‐
   <italic>MP</italic> DNA fragment in plants after mechanical inoculation with pCB2A + pCB1B (lanes 1, 7, and 13), pCB2A + pCB1B::OM
   <sub>5′</sub>
   <italic>
    <sub>MP</sub>
   </italic> (lanes 2, 8, and 14), pCB2A + pCB1B::OM
   <sub>3′</sub>
   <italic>
    <sub>MP</sub>
   </italic> (lanes 3, 9, and 15), pOM2A + pOM1B (lanes 4, 10, and 16), pOM2A + pOM1B::CB
   <sub>5′</sub>
   <italic>
    <sub>MP</sub>
   </italic> (lanes 5, 11, and 17), and pOM2A + pOM1B::CB
   <sub>3′</sub>
   <italic>
    <sub>MP</sub>
   </italic> (lanes 6, 12, and 18). Amplicons were obtained only from plants inoculated with the constructs carrying the 5′ end of the 
   <italic>MP</italic> of ToLCNDV‐OM
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic id="nlm-graphic-9" xlink:href="MPP-21-571-g004" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
