<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="mpp12917-fig-0005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 5</label>
 <caption>
  <p>A single glutamate residue in the tomato leaf curl New Delhi virus (ToLCNDV)‐OM movement protein (MP) determines mechanical transmissibility. 
   <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>, oriental melon, and cucumber plants after mechanical inoculation with pCB2A paired with pCB1B
   <italic>
    <sub>MP</sub>
   </italic>
   <sub>(3I→T)</sub>, pCB1B
   <italic>
    <sub>MP</sub>
   </italic>
   <sub>(6D→E)</sub>, or pCB1B
   <italic>
    <sub>MP</sub>
   </italic>
   <sub>(8V→M)</sub> carrying a single amino acid substitution at the 3rd, 6th or 8th position of the MP of the CB isolate did not develop visible symptoms (X). However, plants that were mechanically inoculated with pCB2A and pCB1B
   <italic>
    <sub>MP</sub>
   </italic>
   <sub>(19G→E)</sub> carrying a substitution mutation at the 19th amino acid, resulting in a change from glycine to glutamate, developed viral symptoms (O). Plants that were mechanically inoculated with pOM2A and pOM1B
   <italic>
    <sub>MP</sub>
   </italic>
   <sub>(3T→I)</sub>, pOM1B
   <italic>
    <sub>MP</sub>
   </italic>
   <sub>(6E→D)</sub>, or pOM1B
   <italic>
    <sub>MP</sub>
   </italic>
   <sub>(8M→V)</sub> also developed visible symptoms. In contrast, plants that were mechanically inoculated with pOM2A and pOM1B
   <italic>
    <sub>MP</sub>
   </italic>
   <sub>(19E→G)</sub>, carrying a single amino acid substitution at the 19th amino acid, resulting in a change from glutamate to glycine, failed to develop symptoms. The viral inoculum used for mechanical sap inoculation was prepared from 
   <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> with symptoms after agroinoculation with an appropriate combination of the clones. Abbreviations for amino acids: G, glycine; E, glutamate; I, isoleucine; T, threonine; D, aspartic acid; V, valine; M, methionine
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic id="nlm-graphic-11" xlink:href="MPP-21-571-g005" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
