<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, we analyzed baseline HIV drug resistance among PWID enrolled in a randomized, controlled, vanguard clinical trial in Indonesia, Ukraine, and Vietnam (HIV Prevention Trials Network [HPTN] 074) [
 <xref rid="pone.0223829.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. These study sites were selected because the HIV epidemics in these countries are concentrated among PWID [
 <xref rid="pone.0223829.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0223829.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]; other factors considered in site selection were high HIV prevalence or incidence and the availability of medication-assisted treatment (MAT) for substance use. The goal of the HPTN 074 study was to assess the feasibility of performing future HIV prevention studies in PWID. The study enrolled active injection drug users, including HIV-infected index participants and their HIV-uninfected injection partners. Index participants were required to have HIV viral loads ≥1,000 copies/mL at study screening. The study limited enrollment of index participants who reported that they were on ART. Participants were randomized to a standard of care arm or an intervention arm. The intervention package was designed to increase use of local services for ART and MAT for substance use and included facilitated referral for ART at any CD4 cell count. Interventions for ART and MAT included systems navigation and counseling that encouraged engagement and retention in care and adherence to ART and substance use treatment. ART regimens were selected based on local treatment guidelines; recommended first-line ART regimens at the time of study included two nucleoside/nucleotide reverse transcriptase inhibitors [NRTIs] with a non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor [NNRTI] [
 <xref rid="pone.0223829.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. After 52 weeks of follow-up, index participants in the intervention arm were more likely to report being on ART and MAT, were more likely to be virally suppressed, and had reduced mortality [
 <xref rid="pone.0223829.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].
</p>
