<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cells were incubated in a T-75 cell culture flask (ThermoFisher, Waltham, MA, USA) until a confluency of 70% was attained. HEK293T cells were then co-transfected with p3XFLAG-tagged eqMx1 (4 μg) together with PB1, PB2 (2 μg each), PA, FF-Luc (1 μg each), and NP expression plasmids either from (1) H7N9, and its mutants H7N9-S34G and N52H; or (2) H3N8
 <sub>JL89</sub> and its mutants JL89-G34S and H52N; or (3) an empty control vector (4 μg each) by using PolyJet™ In Vitro DNA transfection reagent (SignaGen, Rockville, MD, USA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. At24 hr post-transfection, co-immunoprecipitation was performed as previously described [
 <xref rid="B38-viruses-11-01114" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Briefly, transfected cells were lysed using an ice-cold lysis buffer (50 mM of Tris-HCL [pH 8], 150 mM of NaCl, 5 Mm of EDTA, and 1% NP-40), protease inhibitors (1:100), and freshly prepared 2 M N-ethylmaleimide (NEM) at 1:80 (Sigma Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) and centrifuged at 4 °C for 10 min at 13,000× 
 <italic>g</italic>. Post centrifugation, using Anti-FLAG M2 magnetic beads (Sigma Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA, M8823) or Anti-NP magnetic beads (made by incubation of MCE protein A/G magnetic beads along with the NP antibody from our lab) the lysates were co-incubated for 2 hr at 4 °C. Using a magnetic separator, the resins were harvested and washed thrice with cold PBS. In order to elute the resin-bound materials, we added a 3X Flag peptide and incubated the samples at 4 °C for 30 min, and then the eluted samples were boiled and SDS-PAGE was performed. The samples were shifted on the nitrocellulose membrane. 5% skim milk in Tris-buffered saline (TBS) was used as a blocking buffer for 2 hr and then the membranes were incubated with specific primary antibodies-TBST (TBS with 0.05% Tween20) at room temperature for 2 hr. Washing was performed thrice and the membranes were then incubated in TBST, containing secondary antibody (Sigma Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA, 1:10,000) at room temperature for 1 hr. Subsequently, membranes were washed three times in PBST and scanned using a LI-COR Odyssey Imaging System (LI-COR, Lincoln, NE, USA).
</p>
