<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During the past few years, several critically important issues have emerged in developing a UIV. While identification of a number of broadly protective antibodies presents an optimistic prospect for pan-influenza therapeutics, induction of such antibodies at a sufficiently protective level by vaccination has not been accomplished yet. A variety of viral targets have been identified to induce broad protection, including M2e and the conserved regions in the HA, such as stalk, RBS, and VE, and the long-neglected NA has emerged as an essential target for durable and broad protection. In virtually all cases, the rationale for broad protection is to redirect the immune responses from the variable immunodominant regions to conserved immunosubdominant regions. While effective in eliciting cross-protection, concerns were raised to non-neutralizing antibodies that potentially trigger the enhancement of disease. T-cell immunity has also been considered as an important correlate of cross-protection. LAIVs are able to induce multifaceted immune response and thus have increasingly received close attention as a promising vaccine platform, either alone, or in boosting format. Preexisting immunity or immunologic imprinting, established by prior exposure to influenza by infection or vaccination, may influence or thwart the desired breadth of immune response by UIVs. Therefore, disparities may exist between pre-clinical evaluation of a UIV without due recognition of immune imprinting and human challenge studies. Lastly, the correlates of protection and their precise molecular mechanisms have not been determined yet, which remains a significant gap between development and licensing of a UIV. Given the limited antigenic diversity of IBVs among humans and the lack of animal reservoir, pan-influenza B virus vaccine may be attainable in the near future. On the other hand, IAVs continually change their antigenicity via antigenic drift and shift and zoonotic spillover from animal reservoirs, requiring multi-faceted immune arms to increase the breadth of protection. Judicious choice of antigens and their efficient designing to confer a broad protection for a prolonged period are required to counterfeit the immune evasion and provide a truly universal protection against the ever-changing influenza viruses.</p>
