<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fn-group>
 <fn>
  <p>
   <bold>Twitter:</bold> Follow Derek Ward at 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://twitter.com/OfficialNHSC" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">@OfficialNHSC</ext-link>
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn>
  <p>
   <bold>Contributors:</bold> DJW and AJS conceived the original study idea, and EH and LL-P contributed to the development of the study design and methods. EH collected the data and carried out the analysis with assistance from LL-P and DJW. All authors (DJW, EH, LL-P and AJS) were involved in the interpretation of the results. DJW produced the initial draft of the paper, which was then circulated repeatedly to all authors for critical revision. DJW, EH, LL-P and AJS read and approved the final version. All authors had full access to all of the study data (including statistical reports and tables), and can take responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the analysis. DJW is the guarantor.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn>
  <p>
   <bold>Funding:</bold> The study was undertaken as part of the research programme of the NIHR Horizon Scanning Research &amp; Intelligence Centre (NIHR HSRIC). HSRIC is funded by the National Institute for Health Research (NIHR). The NIHR had no role in the study design; in the collection, analysis and interpretation of the data; in the preparation of the manuscript; or in the decision to submit the article for publication. This article presents independent research funded by the NIHR. The views expressed are those of the authors and not necessarily those of the NHS, the NIHR or the Department of Health.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn>
  <p>
   <bold>Competing interests:</bold> All authors have completed the ICMJE uniform disclosure form at 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.icmje.org/coi_disclosure.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.icmje.org/coi_disclosure.pdf</ext-link> and declare: all authors have financial support from the National Institute for Health Research (NIHR) for the submitted work; all authors have no financial relationships with any organisations that might have an interest in the submitted work in the previous 3 years; and all authors have no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn>
  <p>
   <bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn>
  <p>
   <bold>Data sharing statement:</bold> No additionaldata are available.
  </p>
 </fn>
</fn-group>
