<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0215">The typical release pathways used by viruses may vary under some conditions. For example, during chronic infection, numerous viruses use alternative cell-to-cell transmission that may help the virus avoid host neutralization (
 <xref rid="bb0775" ref-type="bibr">Hulo et al., 2017</xref>). Syncytium formation, an HIV-induced cell fusion, was recognized in the early 1990s (
 <xref rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr">Callahan, 1994</xref>). Another type of cell-to-cell transmission through tight junctions was shown for HIV (
 <xref rid="bb0765" ref-type="bibr">Hübner et al., 2009</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb1795" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2017</xref>) and murine leukemia virus (
 <xref rid="bb1580" ref-type="bibr">Sherer et al., 2010</xref>). Receptors on tight junctions that specifically recognize hepatitis C virus (
 <xref rid="bb0245" ref-type="bibr">Carloni et al., 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb1390" ref-type="bibr">Ploss et al., 2009</xref>) and reovirus (
 <xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">Barton et al., 2001</xref>) have been identified. Some viruses are able to modify cellular pathways to reprogram both the synthesis and metabolism of lipids and membrane compartmentalization for their transmission and to evade cellular defense mechanisms (
 <xref rid="bb1175" ref-type="bibr">Mazzon and Mercer, 2014</xref>). Despite a general understanding that poliovirus spreads through cellular lysis, it was recently found that it may also be transferred between cells by an autophagy-dependent mechanism, called autophagosome-mediated exit without lysis (
 <xref rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr">Bird and Kirkegaard, 2015b</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0140" ref-type="bibr">Bird et al., 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0970" ref-type="bibr">Lai et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb1480" ref-type="bibr">Richards and Jackson, 2012</xref>). Similar mechanisms have been described for varicella-zoster virus and human cytomegalovirus (
 <xref rid="bb0630" ref-type="bibr">Grose et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb1185" ref-type="bibr">Meier and Grose, 2017</xref>). Poxviruses encode several proteins that block the apoptotic cellular response to the presence of their dsDNA in the cytoplasm. This allows cell-to-cell passage of poxviruses by a mechanism known as apoptotic mimicry (
 <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">Amara and Mercer, 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb1285" ref-type="bibr">Nichols et al., 2017</xref>). In this process, enveloped viruses expose surface phosphatidylserine to mimic apoptotic bodies. These cells are then macropinocytosed by either dendritic cells or macrophages (
 <xref rid="bb1205" ref-type="bibr">Mercer and Helenius, 2010</xref>).
</p>
