<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>SARS-CoV infection induces upregulation of proinflammatory cytokines/chemokines, such as interleukin (IL)-1β, IL-6, IL-8, IL-12, monocyte chemotactic protein 1 (MCP-1), and IFN-γ inducible protein (IP-10), in the tissues and serum during the first two weeks of illness onset [
 <xref rid="B73-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Similarly, most of the patients infected with severe SARS-CoV-2 exhibit elevated levels of numerous proinflammatory cytokines in serum, including IL-1β, IL-1Ra, IL-2, IL-6, IL-8, IL-10, granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G-CSF), granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF), IP-10, macrophage inflammatory protein-1 alpha (MIP-1α), and TNF-α [
 <xref rid="B12-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. However, these proinflammatory cytokines were not significantly increased in patients with mild COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="B75-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Thus, it is important to understand the dynamic changes in the proinflammatory response at the early stage of SARS-CoV-2 infection. In this context, Ong et al. conducted daily transcriptional profiling of whole blood from COVID-19 patients, and the data revealed that the early immune response was highly dynamic during COVID-19 progression. Meanwhile, the increased expression of IL-1 and its associated proinflammatory pathway might be correlated with severe respiratory disease [
 <xref rid="B69-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. To better understand the modulation of the immune response in target tissues of COVID-19 patients, a previous study analyzed immune signatures using bronchoalveolar lavage collected from COVID-19 patients. The results indicated that COVID-19 patients display robust innate immune responses with chemokine-dominated hypercytokinemia, such as elevated expression of chemokine (CXC motif) ligand 17 (CXCL17), CXCL8, CXCL1, CXCL2, and chemokine (CXC motif) receptor 2 (CXCR2), suggesting the importance of the recruitment of neutrophils and monocytes in controlling viral infection [
 <xref rid="B68-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>].
</p>
