<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Globally, pig farming provides an estimated 25% of energy and 9% of the protein that humans obtain from animal source. During the course of history, it can be observed that with the increase in the level of agricultural production, the consumption of pork has also increased. Pig production is an expanding livestock sector in every continent, but this increase is greatest in developing and developed areas of Asia. Whilst an increasing proportion of Asian pork is produced in intensive systems, in developing areas, most of the population is still engaged in small-scale farming, with households keeping ‘backyard’ livestock including pigs. Their productivity is constrained by multiple factors, including infectious diseases where NiV represents an emerging one, further aggravated by its zoonotic characteristics. In this specific case, vaccination would not only prevent pig farming loss of productivity but would also prevent the infection transmission from pig to human. As a result, vaccination also contributes to poverty alleviation by increasing household benefits and freeing income for food, healthcare, or child education. Therefore, new effective vaccines that target diseases that hamper farming in developing countries will have great social and economic benefit [
 <xref rid="B65-vaccines-08-00115" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. It is noteworthy that NiV is classified as BSL4 agent and could be used in biological terrorism. Despite the pandemic potential of NiV, no vaccines are approved to be used in livestock and humans. Experimentally attenuated NiV have the potential to generate protective immune responses [
 <xref rid="B66-vaccines-08-00115" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-vaccines-08-00115" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]; however, as an RNA lethal virus there are safety concerns over live attenuated NiV vaccines. Furthermore, live attenuated vaccines typically do not possess DIVA characteristics and a DIVA NiV vaccine would be of great value to facilitate sero-surveillance programs in livestock and speed up strategies for disease control and eradication. DIVA vaccines can be applied not only with gene-deleted marker vaccines [
 <xref rid="B68-vaccines-08-00115" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], but also with sub-unit and recombinant vector-based vaccines [
 <xref rid="B69-vaccines-08-00115" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>].
</p>
