<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par1">Coronaviruses are large, enveloped, positive-strand RNA viruses. Several coronaviruses are pathogenic in humans, including severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV), Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) and this novel virus, SARS-CoV-2, which has caused the global pandemic currently. Genetic sequencing suggests that SARS-CoV-2 is related to SARS-CoV and its close relatives (Chen
 <italic> et al</italic>. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2020</xref>). There are four genera of coronavirus, including 
 <italic>Alphacoronavirus</italic>, 
 <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic>, 
 <italic>Gammacoronavirus</italic> and 
 <italic>Deltacoronavirus</italic>. Like other 
 <italic>Betacoronaviruses</italic>, the genome of SARS-CoV-2 codes four major structural proteins, including the spike surface glycoprotein which is called S protein, small envelope protein, matrix protein, and nucleocapsid protein. S proteins are type I transmembrane proteins with a large ectodomain and a short endodomain. Coronavirus replication is initiated by the binding of S protein to the cell surface receptor(s). The S protein is composed of two functional subunits, S1 (bulb) for receptor binding and S2 (stalk) for membrane fusion. Specific interaction between S1 and receptor triggers a drastic conformational change in the S2 subunit, leading to the fusion between the virus envelope and the cellular membrane and release of the nucleocapsid into the cytoplasm. Receptor binding is the major determinant of host range and tissue tropism for a coronavirus (Cui
 <italic> et al</italic>. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2019</xref>). SARS-CoV-2 is able to use human angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) as an entry receptor in ACE2-expressing cells, indicating that ACE2 is likely the cell receptor of SARS-CoV-2 (Zhou
 <italic> et al</italic>. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2020</xref>). McLellan
 <italic> et al</italic>. showed biophysical and structural evidence that SARS-CoV-2 S protein binds ACE2 with higher affinity than SARS-CoV S protein (Wrapp
 <italic> et al</italic>. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2020</xref>).
</p>
