<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are also new models of the human brain that are being developed that have not yet been applied to MBF research but have potential applications in the field, such as brain region-specific organoids characterized by multiple components that correspond to the structures of various brain regions, such as the cerebral cortex (Kadoshima et al., 
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Mariani et al., 
 <xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Pasca et al., 
 <xref rid="B160" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Qian et al., 
 <xref rid="B168" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), midbrain (Jo et al., 
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Qian et al., 
 <xref rid="B168" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), and hypothalamus (Merkle et al., 
 <xref rid="B139" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Sakaguchi et al., 
 <xref rid="B181" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Wang L. et al., 
 <xref rid="B222" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Qian et al., 
 <xref rid="B168" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). For example, cerebral organoids (also called mini brains) were initially described by Knoblich's laboratory (Lancaster et al., 
 <xref rid="B114" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). This model presented intrinsic self-organizing processes which display a cellular organization similar to early stages of the developing human brain. These feature allow scientists to study important key events during early brain development. The new tridimensional structure allows higher cell to cell interaction and maturation of the model. For example, Pasca's group have reported a method for generating pyramidal neurons from hiPSCs in a 3D cerebral cortex–like structure (Pasca et al., 
 <xref rid="B160" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). However, due to the lack of vasculature, necrotic centers form with in these tissues when the spheroid size is larger than 500 μm. Therefore, other models which are smaller in size but less complexity, have also been developed. For example. BrainSpheres developed in Hartung's laboratory have been able to recapitulate some of the key processes during CNS differentiation (Pamies et al., 
 <xref rid="B156" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). This model does not present spatial self-organization, however, has shown to be highly reproducible and presents a very high level of glial maturity in comparison with other models; showing maturate oligodendrocytes and partial axonal myelination (Pamies et al., 
 <xref rid="B156" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). There have also been different attempts to incorporate vascularization into the system to avoid hypoxia in the center of organoids (McGuigan and Sefton, 
 <xref rid="B138" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Pham et al., 
 <xref rid="B163" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Grebenyuk and Ranga, 
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Homan et al., 
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). However, to date, vasculature formation has not been accomplished in 3D 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> brain models.
</p>
