<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fn-group>
 <fn fn-type="abbr">
  <p>Abbreviations: aIRR = adjusted incidence rate ratio, ART = antiretroviral-therapy, CDC = Centre of Diseases Control, HIV = human immunodeficiency virus, ICD-9-CM = International Classification of Diseases, 9th revision, clinical modification, MSM = men who have sex with men, NHIRD = national health insurance research database, RPR = rapid plasma regain, STIs = sexually transmitted infections, TPHA = treponema pallidum hemagglutination assay.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="other">
  <p>How to cite this article: Lee N-Y, Chen Y-C, Liu H-Y, Li C-Y, Li C-W, Ko W-C, Ko N-Y. Increased repeat syphilis among HIV-infected patients: a nationwide population-based cohort study in Taiwan. 
   <italic>Medicine</italic>. 2020;99:28(e21132).
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="equal">
  <p>N-YL and Y-CC contributed equally to this work.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="supported-by">
  <p>This study was supported by the grants for publication fee from National Cheng Kung University Hospital (NCKUH 109-02060), as well as supported by the grants of National Science Council (NSC 101-3114-Y-006-001) and Ministry of Health &amp; Welfare (MOHW 104-TDU-B-211-113002), Taiwan.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="other">
  <p>This study was based in part on data from the National Health Insurance Research Database, which was provided by the Bureau of National Health Insurance (NHI), MOHW, and managed by the National Health Research Institutes (NHRI). The interpretations and conclusions in this manuscript do not represent those of the Bureau of NHI, MOHW, or NHRI.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="other">
  <p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from a third party, but restrictions apply to the availability of these data, which were used under license for the current study, and so are not publicly available. Data are available from the authors upon reasonable request and with permission of the third party.</p>
 </fn>
</fn-group>
