<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The early recognition of CHIKV with the subsequent measures could have limited the autochthonous cases in Panama. The first imported cases were detected during the viremic phase, with one case detected at the airport [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005338.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The available epidemiological data shows that around half of CHIKV cases in Panama were detected during the first days of symptoms. This suggests that the surveillance program was able to detect clinical chikungunya cases during the acute phase. DENV and CHIKV laboratory surveillance plays an important role in Panama. All suspected chikungunya cases were laboratory tested, whereas around 50% of Dengue cases are laboratory confirmed (MINSA-NED.). This differs from the situation in other countries during 2014, like El Salvador or Colombia that had only 157 confirmed cases from the 135,226 CHIKV suspected cases, or 611 confirmed from 90,481 suspected respectively [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005338.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Moreover, ICGES not only tested all chikungunya suspected cases, in addition its sensibility to detect viral RNA in acute samples was increased by using specific CHIKV detecting methods complemented with genus-specific alphavirus RT-PCR in dengue suspected cases that were dengue negative. The epidemiological surveillance algorithm establishes testing of convalescent paired samples to confirm positive and negative CHIKV results, to avoid false negatives results by RT-PCR due to an inaccurate onset symptoms description, low viral load or sample handling. Although patients were encouraged to attend a second medical visit to obtain the convalescent sample, few participated, especially as symptoms disappeared. For the convalescent paired samples obtained, serological tests were performed as a confirmation of acute samples. PRNT was suggested by PAHO for diagnosis confirmation and would be helpful to confirm seroconversion, especially when circulation of chikungunya has to be proven in a new country[
 <xref rid="pntd.0005338.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], this technique was not used at the beginning of the outbreak in Panama as Chikungunya first detected cases were acute, thus Chikungunya circulation was proven in Panama by molecular methods and viral isolation[
 <xref rid="pntd.0005338.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Once Chikungunya circulation was confirmed in Panama, the CHIKV surveillance program was adapted to the capacity of GMI laboratory and Chikungunya PRNT was not available to confirm serologic results at the time of the outbreak. However, this limitation in the chikungunya surveillance was also shared by most Latin American countries.
</p>
