<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In Sub-Saharan Africa, RVFV appears to be spread by movement of viremic livestock between countries [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005226.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005226.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], or though introduction of infected mosquitoes to neighboring countries [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005226.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005226.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. We used Markov Jumps to infer possible introduction events and movement routes of RVFV. Two types of RVFV movements can be considered: short- and long-distance jumps [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005226.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005226.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005226.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Inferred movements between distant countries may omit the effects of unsampled lineages in countries on the route between them. For example, studies attributed the 1977–1978 epidemics in Egypt to viral introductions from Sudan [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005226.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005226.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], but our study saw strong support for Zimbabwe as a country of origin for Egyptian strains. This result suggests that, although Zimbabwe was the sampled origin for these lineages, they travelled north over Sudan to Egypt; all available Sudanese sequences came from more recent outbreaks in 2007–2010, which presumably originated in Kenya, and are genetically distant from Egyptian strains in the outbreak of the 1970s [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005226.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. With no earlier Sudanese sequences available [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005226.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005226.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>], this analysis could not find an origin in Sudan, and hence tracked lineages back to Zimbabwe; this result should thus not be taken to indicate that the hypothesis of a Sudanese origin for Egyptian epidemics is incorrect.
</p>
