<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">The high neurotropism of β-CoVs in experimental animals has been known for decades. In fact, the first evidence that CoVs may infect the CNS was gathered at the end of 1940s when a neurotropic strain of the β-CoVs mouse hepatitis virus-4 (MHV-4), the JHM virus (JHMV) named in honor of the microbiologist John Howard Mueller (
 <xref rid="bb0595" ref-type="bibr">Pappenheimer, 1958</xref>), was isolated from mice developing spontaneous hind leg paralysis, and was shown to induce a diffuse encephalomyelitis with patchy areas of demyelination when inoculated in mice (
 <xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr">Cheever et al., 1949</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">Bailey et al., 1949</xref>). In newborn and weanling rats, JHMV induces either an acute panencephalomyelitis, which is usually fatal in a few days, or a subacute paralytic disease which progresses over several months, or a chronic progressive paralysis appearing 6–8 month after virus inoculation (
 <xref rid="bb0545" ref-type="bibr">Nagashima et al., 1978a</xref>). These conditions differ significantly in their gross and microscopic pathology with widespread neuronal death, necrosis and polymorphonucleate infiltration in the acute form, perivascular cuffing consisting of plasma cells and macrophages and large demyelinating lesions in which axons are largely preserved in the subacute form, and diffuse myelomalacia, cerebral cortex thinning and hydrocephalus in the chronic form (
 <xref rid="bb0545" ref-type="bibr">Nagashima et al., 1978a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0550" ref-type="bibr">Nagashima et al., 1978b</xref>), suggesting multiple pathogenic mechanisms. The demyelinating lesions found in the subacute paralytic disease displayed considerable histopathological resemblance to those of multiple sclerosis (MS); therefore, JHMV infection has become a widely used experimental model for this disease (
 <xref rid="bb0695" ref-type="bibr">Sorensen and Dales, 1985</xref>). JHMV is not the only neurovirulent CoV in rodents. In fact, a few years after its identification, Dick et al. (
 <xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr">Dick et al., 1956</xref>) isolated a mutant neurotropic strain of the mouse hepatitis virus-3 (MHV-3), that did not cause hepatitis but induced a fatal meningo-encephalitis when injected intracerebrally in mice. It was later reported that, in a few susceptible mice strains such as CH3 and AG2 mice, also the wild type MHV-3 variant induced neurological manifestations with lack of coordination and limb paresis associated to histological evidence of brain vasculitis and meningoependymitis (
 <xref rid="bb0800" ref-type="bibr">Virelizier et al., 1975</xref>). Interestingly, CoVs may induce neurological diseases also in species different from rodents, as seen in the β-CoV porcine hemagglutinating encephalomyelitis virus (PHEV) of the VW572 strain that causes encephalomyelitis in piglets (
 <xref rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr">Desforges et al., 2013</xref>), and the feline α-CoV (FCoV) that produces significant CNS damage in cats (
 <xref rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr">Desforges et al., 2013</xref>).
</p>
