<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Genome-wide association study (GWAS) is a study of the genome for small variations, typically the single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) of an ill individual. GWAS involves the examination across the genome-wide set of genetic variants in different individuals to pinpoint any variations that are associated with a trait of certain diseases [
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The construction of GWAS genes associated with the disease traits involves an extensive database [
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. For instance, the GWAS database from the U.S. National Human Genome Research Institute was used in the study conducted by Sanseau and colleagues [
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The database studied by Sanseau et al. includes an extensive collection of publications accompanied by &gt;4800 rows of data with respect to a trait and SNP [
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Upon investigation, they were 991 GWAS genes identified relevant to the disease traits. The analysed rows of GWAS data that corresponded to the trait and SNPs are subsequently investigated for the druggable potential or otherwise. Then, 15.6% of the 991 selected GWAS genes are associated with drug projects in pharmaceutical pipelines, in which 51 GWAS traits are different from the drug indication for 92 genes, giving opportunities to drug repositioning [
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. For example, the drug Denosumab, which was initially intended for postmenopausal osteoporosis, is now a potential drug candidate for Crohn’s disease associated with variations in tumour necrosis factor member 11 (
 <italic>TNFSF11</italic>), discovered with the aid of GWAS [
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. In another study, a similar approach was used with three different drug-target databases (DrugBank, Therapeutic Target Database and PharmGKB) and a gene prediction platform known as 
 <italic>Gentrepid</italic>. The study successfully discovered 184/192 predicted candidate genes as novel therapeutic targets for coronary artery disease (CAD), and 981/993 potential drugs from the drug databases for repositioning, giving new directions in repositioning existing drugs for CAD at a reasonable cost [
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Nonetheless, GWAS has its limitations where detailed pathophysiological information is absent, and the lack of functional studies on the effect of a gene variant. Hence, GWAS data should be used in concert with other computational approaches in predicting targets for drug repositioning [
 <xref rid="B11-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. 
</p>
