<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par9">The latent HIV-1 reservoir has been studied extensively, and the HIV-1 reservoir establishment is associated with the seeding of virus during the acute HIV-1 infection before the adaptive arm of the immune system starts to partially control the virus replication [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. It is also well established that HIV-1 remain quiescent in long-lived CD4+ memory T-cells. Moreover, viral rebound is normally seen only a few weeks after secession of ART even in patients with previous long-term virus suppression. Hence, virus latency in these cells remain one of the main challenges for finding a functional cure against HIV. The size of the virus reservoir has been measured using different protocols, including qPCR of cell-bound virus DNA and mRNA, quantification of ex vivo reactivation of virus mRNA and proteins, as well as in ex vivo virus outgrowth assays. In HIV-1 long-term non-progressors (LTNP) and elite controllers (EC), that have been suggested as models for functional cure, the reservoir of latently infected cells is reduced compared with HIV-1 viraemic and treated individuals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Interestingly, conflicting results about proviral DNA levels in HIV-2 compared with HIV-1 infection have been reported. Two studies indicated similar proviral levels after adjusting for disease stage [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]; whereas a study by Gueudin et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] reported the opposite. Thus, further studies are needed to establish proviral DNA loads at different disease stages of HIV-2 infection, and how they differ from HIV-1 infection. Moreover, even though quantification of virus DNA by qPCR correlate with the size of the latent HIV-1 reservoir, these assays often overestimate the size of the replication competent latent HIV-1 reservoir. Although few studies have characterized the HIV-2 reservoir, it was recently reported that HIV-2 DNA could be quantified in transitional-memory cells from four of 14 ART naive HIV-2-infected individuals, and in central-memory cells from one of 14 ART naive HIV-2-infected individuals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Approximately 100 HIV-2 DNA copies/10
 <sup>6</sup> cells were detected in each of the specific memory cell subsets, respectively. However, HIV-2 in vitro reactivation was only observed in cells from three of the 14 individuals, suggesting presence of defective proviruses. In line with this, the predominance of defective proviral DNA in HIV-2 infected individuals on successful ART has recently been reported from studies of three virally suppressed individuals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. In this study, most of the HIV-2 genomes had large deletions, whereas hypermutations were noted in a smaller fraction of the sequences. However, complete understanding of the HIV-2 reservoir will require larger studies and the use of different protocols. Moreover, both in vitro and ex vivo studies of latency reversal agents used in HIV-1 clinical settings are needed for HIV-2 (reviewed in [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]). Still, from available proviral load data and studies of HIV-1 in LTNP and EC (that in many ways resemble HIV-2) it is plausible that the remission of HIV-2 would be relapse-free or delayed, and less frequent compared with the general HIV-1 case (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). 
</p>
