<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In 2018, ASF unexpectedly emerged in eastern Asia where dozens of outbreaks in pigs were reported in China and Mongolia, and in 2019 ASF struck also in Vietnam (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Molecular characterisation of the intergenic region (IGR) between the I73R and I329L genes revealed a high level of DNA sequence similarity between recent Chinese and Eastern European (IGR II) ASFV isolates, but not between Chinese and Siberian ones (of the Irkutsk 2017 strain) (IGR I) (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). The exact origin of the disease in eastern Asia still remains unknown and needs further investigation; nevertheless a recent phylogenetic analysis indicated that ASFV in China might have had at least two independent introductions due to some level of divergence in nucleotide sequences obtained from cases which occurred far from each other (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). Most of the outbreaks which recently emerged in China were separated by thousands of kilometres, suggesting that the spread of the disease might be associated with contaminated feed. This hypothesis seems to be probable, in particular having regard to the fact that ASFV DNA has been detected in pig feed and feed ingredients like dried pig blood (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, 
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). In Europe, besides on backyard farms, the disease has been reported on numerous high-biosecurity operations (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). In Romania, ASFV was introduced into a high biosecurity breeding farm containing up to 140,000 pigs; however, the exact source of the disease has not been determined. Hypothetically it may have originated from contaminated water in the nearby Danube River (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>).
</p>
