<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to its confirmatory role, analysis of virus genomes can answer questions of relevance to infectious disease control that cannot be addressed using incidence reports alone. For example, viral phylogenies can indicate if an outbreak in a specific region is the result of a single introduction followed by onward transmission within the host population of that region, or is composed of multiple independent chains of transmission, each initiated by a separate introduction from elsewhere or from a zoonotic reservoir species. For example, analysis of viral genomes from the Ebola epidemic in west Africa that began in Guinea in early 2014 indicated that it developed from a single introduction from the virus's reservoir in central Africa, and that the epidemic in Sierra Leone arose from the transmission of two distinct viral lineages from Guinea [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. By contrast, phylogenetic investigation of the HIV-1 subtype B epidemic in the UK showed that it comprised hundreds of independent viral introductions from other countries, at least six of which established large and persistent chains of transmission in the UK [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Epidemiological differences among observed transmission chains can help to focus epidemic control efforts more efficiently on specific populations or risk groups. Further epidemiological insights can be obtained by using evolutionary ‘molecular clock’ models, which place viral phylogenies on a real time scale of months and years [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], and enable estimation of the age of the most recent common ancestor (MRCA) of transmission chains in different locations. It is not always appreciated that the MRCA of an outbreak does not necessarily represent the same infected individual as the index case; the former can be more recent (but never older) than the latter. Despite this condition, estimated MRCA ages are sometimes weeks to years earlier than reported dates of virus discovery. Thus, this difference indicates a ‘time lag’ of epidemiological surveillance, the duration of which might be used to evaluate the efficiency and timeliness of systems of pathogen detection and notification.
</p>
