<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0180">SARS-CoV-2 has spread rapidly since its outbreak and has now posed a risk to countries worldwide, making it urgent to develop a safe and effective vaccine against the infection. This review introduces the structure and functions of coronavirus S protein and summarizes the advancements and potential strategies of SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV vaccines based on CoV S protein. The CoV S protein-based vaccines are further classified into different types, including viral vector, nucleic acid (DNA and RNA), VLP and protein-based vaccines. Subunit vaccines have become the focus of current research due to their numerous advantages, but it often requires appropriate adjuvants to enhance their immunogenicity. In the USA, aluminum, MF59, and CpG are adjuvants included in licensed vaccines. These three adjuvants have shown induction of serum neutralizing antibodies and protection against infection in mice challenged with an infectious virus, which might be used for CoV subunit vaccine administration
 <xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>85</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>88</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib104" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>104</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib106" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>106</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib122" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>122</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib123" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>123</sup>
 </xref>. However, alum alone cannot induce a potent Th1 response unless combined with another adjuvant, such as CpG. This adjuvant combination will improve the effectiveness of the CoV subunit vaccines
 <xref rid="bib124" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>124</sup>
 </xref>. Similarly, in order to effectively activate the complex and orderly natural immune system and produce the expected acquired immune response, it is sometimes necessary to use an adjuvant combination
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>30</sup>
 </xref>. Here, we believe that adjuvant formulations that induce a balanced Th1 and Th2 immune response can more effectively improve the immunogenicity of the antigen
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>73</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>84</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib104" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>104</sup>
 </xref>, becoming a new trend in the development of coronavirus adjuvants. Ideally, an effective CoV vaccine is required to induce both robust humoral and cell-mediated immunities. Even though many promising vaccine candidates have been reported, there are still no commercial vaccines available against SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV. The comprehensive lessons and experiences brought by the outbreak of SARS and MERS provide valuable insights and progress on how to respond to COVID-19.
</p>
