<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0185">With the spread of COVID-19, scientific institutions and pharmaceutical companies around the world are racing against time to develop SARS-CoV-2 vaccine. According to WHO, there are at least 100 research projects on SARS-CoV-2 vaccines in the world
 <xref rid="bib129" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>129</sup>
 </xref>. In addition to traditional inactivated virus and live-attenuated virus vaccines, the developments of most SARS-CoV-2 vaccines are also based on some new technological routes, such as mRNA vaccines, subunit vaccines, viral vector vaccines, and DNA vaccines. Up to now, eight candidate vaccines have entered clinical trials, including three inactivated vaccines from Wuhan Institute of Biological Products
 <xref rid="bib130" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>130</sup>
 </xref>, Beijing Institute of Biological Products
 <xref rid="bib131" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>131</sup>
 </xref> and Sinovac
 <xref rid="bib132" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>132</sup>
 </xref>, two adenovirus vector vaccines (Ad5-nCoV from CanSino Biologicals
 <xref rid="bib133" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>133</sup>
 </xref> and COV001 from Inovio
 <xref rid="bib134" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>134</sup>
 </xref>), two mRNA vaccines (mRNA-1273 from Moderna
 <xref rid="bib135" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>135</sup>
 </xref> and BNT162 from BioNTech
 <xref rid="bib136" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>136</sup>
 </xref>) and one DNA vaccine (INO-4800 from Inovio
 <xref rid="bib137" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>137</sup>
 </xref>). Although some progress has been made in the development of SARS-CoV-2 vaccines, it is important to realize that vaccine development is a rigorous scientific exploration process. Due to many challenges of verifying the effectiveness of vaccines, it is still very likely that no SARS-CoV-2 vaccine will be available in the market for human in near future. Therefore, SARS-CoV-2 vaccine development still requires the unremitting efforts of researchers in the world.
</p>
