<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Bone loss is another hallmark of CHIKV arthritis, and osteoblasts are a site of CHIKV replication and persistence [
 <xref rid="B86-viruses-11-00175" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>,
 <xref rid="B163-viruses-11-00175" ref-type="bibr">163</xref>,
 <xref rid="B164-viruses-11-00175" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>,
 <xref rid="B165-viruses-11-00175" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>]. Ex vivo infection of human osteoblasts induced the secretion of IL6 and receptor activator of nuclear factor-kB ligand (RANKL), and a concomitant decrease in the osteoproteogerin (OPG) content in culture supernatants. This perturbation in the RANKL/OPG ratio has been evidenced in infected murine joints and in patients’ sera [
 <xref rid="B165-viruses-11-00175" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>]. The dysregulation in the RANKL/OPG ratio in CHIKV-infected joints, and the upregulation of monocyte chemoattractant proteins observed in mice joints (CCL2, CCL7, and CCL8) and in the serum of CHIKV patients (CCL2) [
 <xref rid="B122-viruses-11-00175" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>,
 <xref rid="B123-viruses-11-00175" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>,
 <xref rid="B129-viruses-11-00175" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>,
 <xref rid="B165-viruses-11-00175" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>] favors an osteoclastogenic and chemo-attractive microenvironment. This was confirmed by the local infiltration of monocytes in CHIKV-infected animals [
 <xref rid="B125-viruses-11-00175" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>,
 <xref rid="B166-viruses-11-00175" ref-type="bibr">166</xref>,
 <xref rid="B167-viruses-11-00175" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>], and by the ability of supernatants of CHIKV infected synovial fibroblasts to induce migration and differentiation into the osteoclast-like cells of primary human monocytes [
 <xref rid="B159-viruses-11-00175" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>]. Importantly, the inhibition of monocytes/macrophages recruitment or macrophages depletion attenuated arthritis and joint swelling in mouse models [
 <xref rid="B165-viruses-11-00175" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>,
 <xref rid="B167-viruses-11-00175" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>], but resulted in prolonged viremia, suggesting that macrophages are also required for the clearance of the virus [
 <xref rid="B167-viruses-11-00175" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>] (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00175-f002">Figure 2</xref> for CHIKV tropism in muscle, joint, and bone).
</p>
