<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par84">From 2005 through 2011, the CDC funded seven health departments to conduct enhanced hepatitis C surveillance throughout the USA. Experiences from this collaboration suggest that certain elements are critical to the success of conducting complete, useful surveillance:
 <list list-type="alpha-lower">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par85">
    <italic>Electronic infrastructure to receive and process hepatitis C laboratory reports</italic>. Most clinical laboratories have the capacity to report tests associated with all notifiable diseases in an electronic format to the health departments. However, because laboratories lack a standardized system and health departments vary in their capacity to receive and process electronic information, the large number of hepatitis C reports easily overwhelmed their systems. The lesson learned was that health departments needed to invest in electronic data systems that allowed significant numbers of test results to be received, de-duplicated to result in patient-level information, and then processed to determine electronically whether the patient had been reported previously or was a new case [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par86">
    <italic>Funding for staff at health departments to conduct follow</italic>-
    <italic>up investigation</italic>. Because of limited human resources, it became clear that attempting to follow-up on all de-duplicated cases was not feasible. The solution to this problem was to conduct follow-up investigation on a random sample of cases. In most sites, sampling was conducted prospectively on recently reported cases, allowing a 3-month waiting period to ensure that providers had notified patients of their test results. The goal in most sites was to sample ≥10 % of reported cases and to obtain supplemental information from the healthcare provider associated with the positive test result.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par87">
    <italic>Flexibility of data collection instruments and data entry and storage systems</italic>. Previously, information on mode of transmission was considered desirable, but more helpful to prevention was the identification of which individuals were linked to care. Several health departments had the flexibility to pilot new information items including whether the individual had seen a healthcare provider for hepatitis-related care, and whether they had ever been treated for hepatitis C.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par88">
    <italic>Secure and standardized transmission of data to a central office</italic>. Difficulties with the larger electronic system for notifiable diseases resulted in the use of an independent, secure transfer protocol mechanism to receive electronic data from sites.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par89">
    <italic>Capacity to conduct analyses at the central office</italic>. The application of standardized case definitions was complicated at the local level by subjective interpretations and applications of the definition. Data collected on all positive HCV antibody tests allows surveillance programs to understand the population testing positive, and not only those who have the additional confirmatory testing requirements to meet the case definition (e.g., RIBA, RNA). Therefore, a best practice is to receive all data elements and observations health departments are able to collect and send them to a central office. Then, standardized selection criteria can be applied prior to data analyses. For example, the current US hepatitis C case definition requires a confirmatory antibody test; however, understanding the frequency with which persons test positive and are then not reported to have a follow-up test is useful for prevention [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
