<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pntd.0008135.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0008135.g003</object-id>
 <label>Fig 3</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Screening of mosquitoes collected in Iran using the BioMark dynamic array system (96.96 chip).</title>
  <p>A. First batch of 95 mosquito pools. B. Second batch of 27 mosquito pools. Each square corresponds to a single real-time PCR reaction, where rows indicate batches of mosquitoes tested and columns represent the targets of each primer/probe set. Cross indicate cross-reaction of assays. Ct values for each reaction are indicated in color; the corresponding color scale is presented in the legend on the right. The darkest shades of blue and black squares are considered as negative reactions with Ct &gt; 30. The 37 viruses targeted (95 primers/probe sets for different genotypes/serotypes) were: Banna; Banzi; Barmah Forest; Batai; Bwamba; Chikungunya (Chik_ECSA, Chik_IndECSA, Chik_Asia, Chik_Wafri, ChikV); Dengue (D1, D2 D3, D4, Deng_1, Deng_2, Den_3, Deng_4); Murray Encephalitis (EnM_gI, Enm_gII, EnM_gIII, EnM_gIV, EnM_gV); Yellow fever (YFV, FJ_AO_1, FJ_AO_3_6, FJ_AO_4, FJ_AC_AE, FJ_AmS_1, FJ_AmS_2); Germiston; Ilesha; Inkoo; Japanese Encephalitis (JEV, JEV_I, JEV_II, JEV_IIIa, JEV_IIIb, JEV_IV, JEV_V); Kedougou (KedV); Kokobera group (Kok_ I, Kok_II, Kok_Bai, Kok_Tor, Kok_Map, Kok_Strat); Koutango (Kout_I, Kout_II); Middelburg; Ndumu; Ngari; Nyando; O’nyong-nyong (ONN); Orungo; Pongola; RossRiver (RossRiver, Ross1, Ross2); Rift Valley Fever (RVFV, RVF_SegS); Saboya; Semliki forest; Simbu; Sindbis (Sindbis, Sind_I, Sind_2_3, Sind_IV, Sind_V, Sind_VI); Spondweni (Spond_I, Spond_II); Tahyna; Uganda; Usutu; Wesselsbron; West Nile (WN, WN_1A, WN_1B, WN_1C, WN_2.1, WN_2.2, WN_3, WN_4); Yaounde; Zika (Zika2, Zika3, Zika4, Zika6, Zika7, Zika8). Sequences of primers/probe sets are available in S1 Table of [
   <xref rid="pntd.0008135.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] or under request.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pntd.0008135.g003" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
