<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, we have identified specific viral motifs associated with BgV host-restriction from BgV replication-competent variants, which arose quickly upon passaging on Vero cells (NS4A-S124F, NS4B-N244K and NS5-G2C). The direct involvement of these mutations in BgV host-restriction 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and BgV attenuation 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> was confirmed using reverse engineered CPER-generated BgV clones. We demonstrated that 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>, the NS4B and NS5 mutations are sufficient to restore BgV replication in Vero and DF-1 cells at 37°C while the NS4A mutation facilitates quicker replication and to higher titres. While the functional significance of these mutations is not yet clear, their position in close proximity to, but outside of the viral protease cleavage sites (NS4A/2K and NS4B/NS5) suggests a possible involvement in modulating the cleavage efficiency of BgV viral protease at these sites. Indeed, the prototype BgV sequence is sufficient to mediate efficient viral replication and presumably viral protease cleavage in all vertebrate cell lines at 34°C and a subset of cell lines at 37°C, which suggests that BgV viral protease cleavage must be significantly altered in cells such as Vero, DF-1 or MEF at 37°C. While including the two substitutions flanking the NS4B/5 cleavage site significantly enhanced BgV replication in all cell lines tested, those were only selected for in Vero cells, even in those passaged at 34°C, not in any BSR cells passage. Our data could suggest that these mutations are an essential adaptation to growth in Vero and other vertebrate cells, rather than adapting to replication at 37°C. In contrast, the NS4A substitution only occurred when BgV was passaged in Vero cells at 37°C and in conjunction with the NS4B/5 mutations. The three substitutions observed in BgV could occur in order to compensate for a restricted access to viral protease cleavage sites, due to some variation in the topology of the viral polyprotein in some cell membranes. The NS4A substitution may further optimise viral protein topology in the cell membranes, by regulating membrane remodelling as the temperature is increased to 37°C [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008166.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].
</p>
