<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Based on ISO/TR 13154 recommendations, a screening setup was established as shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>. The setup consisted of a webcam (C920, Logitech, Lausanne, Switzerland) and two IRTs (IRT-1: 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="math7">
   <mrow>
    <mn>320</mn>
    <mo>×</mo>
    <mn>240</mn>
    <mtext>  pixels</mtext>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>, A325sc, FLIR Systems Inc., Nashua, NH and IRT-2: 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="math8">
   <mrow>
    <mn>640</mn>
    <mo>×</mo>
    <mn>512</mn>
    <mtext>  pixels</mtext>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>, 8640 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="math9">
   <mrow>
    <mi>P</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>-series, Infrared Cameras Inc., Beaumont, TX) that were mounted in adjacent positions on a tripod. A WTP with dimensions of 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="math10">
   <mrow>
    <mn>320</mn>
    <mo>×</mo>
    <mn>240</mn>
    <mtext>  pixels</mtext>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> was identified for each IRT—the entire image for IRT-1 and a subset of the image in the most uniform region for IRT-2. We developed a graphical user interface with MATLAB to simultaneously control the webcam and two IRTs, and to collect images and patient/environmental information. Both IRTs had 30-Hz frame rates, and detailed specifications and fundamental performance testing results—including IRT measurement linearity with respect to a BB—can be found in our prior study.
 <xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>28</sup>
 </xref> The laboratory accuracy of both IRTs with a BB satisfies the standard requirements (i.e., 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="math11">
   <mrow>
    <mo form="prefix">≤</mo>
    <mn>0.5</mn>
    <mo>°</mo>
    <mi mathvariant="normal">C</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>). A BB (SR-33, CI Systems Inc.) with a 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="math12">
   <mrow>
    <mn>4</mn>
    <mo>×</mo>
    <mn>4</mn>
    <mtext>  </mtext>
    <mi>in.</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> emitter (image 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="math13">
   <mrow>
    <mtext>size</mtext>
    <mo>≥</mo>
    <mn>20</mn>
    <mo>×</mo>
    <mn>20</mn>
    <mtext>  pixels</mtext>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>) was set at 35°C then positioned perpendicular to the sightline of the cameras and placed within the frame alongside the subject’s face for temperature drift compensation. We previously verified that BB drift and uncertainty satisfied relevant standards.
 <xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>28</sup>
 </xref> The subject-to-camera distance was 0.6 to 0.8 m to ensure that both the subject’s face and the BB were included in the WTP with a resolution that satisfied recommended specifications (face image 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="math14">
   <mrow>
    <mtext>size</mtext>
    <mo>≥</mo>
    <mn>240</mn>
    <mo>×</mo>
    <mn>180</mn>
    <mtext>  pixels</mtext>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>). Room temperature was maintained between 20°C and 24°C and relative humidity between 10% and 62%, as measured by a weather tracker (Kestrel 4500 NV, Weather Republic LLC, Downingtown, PA). The relative humidity was not exactly controlled within 10% to 50% as suggested by ISO/TR 13154:2017, with 7.5% of the subjects measured with relative humidity between 50% and 62%. Ambient temperature and subject 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="math15">
   <mrow>
    <mi>ε</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> (0.98 for human skin
 <xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>36</sup>
 </xref>) were entered into the IRT control program as input parameters for calibrating measured temperature. To prevent direct airflow to a subject’s face, an air vent in the room was blocked by a magnetic air deflector. A black, low-reflectivity cloth (
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="math16">
   <mrow>
    <mi>ε</mi>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mn>0.97</mn>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>; Type 822 E0.97, Group 8 technology, Provo, UT) was used as the backdrop.
</p>
