<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par118">The inflammasome complex is involved in the inflammation-reaction-mediated sensing of microbial and viral components, and endogenous antigens [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116">116</xref>]. At least two major types of inflammasomes, i.e., intracellular NLR family and the interferon-inducible protein absent in melanoma 2 (AIM2)-like receptor (ALR) family, have been identified [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">117</xref>]. Mitochondrial proteins are involved in the NOD–NLR family, and pyrin domain-containing 3 (NLRP3) inflammasome regulation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">118</xref>]. Pathophysiological changes were observed in mitochondria, including the imbalance of mitochondrial dynamics, cytochrome c secretion, mitochondrial DNA damage, or ROS production, which can either activate or inhibit the NLRP3 inflammasome [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119">119</xref>]. NLRP3 was activated by exogenous ligands such as PAMPs, including bacterial toxins, and by endogenous stimuli derived from the host, such as damage-associated molecular patterns. Upon IAV infection, the mitochondrial fusion protein mitofusin 2 can regulate the activation of the NLRP3 inflammasome [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120">120</xref>]. The IAV PB1-F2 protein, which is translocated to mitochondria, can cause mitochondrial fission associated with the defective NLRP3 inflammasome [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121">121</xref>]. However, there is not sufficient information regarding how dynamin-related protein 1 (DRP1)-mediated mitochondrial fission is generated in the innate immune signaling in IAV-infected cells. Swine IV (SIV) infection resulted in NLRP3 inflammasome activation, leading to IL-1β production in primary porcine alveolar macrophages (PAMs) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">122</xref>]. Furthermore, upon SIV infection of PAMs, mitochondrial fission occurred through the RIPK1/DRP1 axis, which acted on the NLRP3 inflammasome-regulated production of IL-1β [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR123">123</xref>]. IAV produced endogenous ROS 
 <italic>via</italic> NOX2-containing NOXs and mitochondria, to circumvent anti-IAV responses. These evolutionarily conserved processes were enhanced by glycolysis, the pentose phosphate pathway, and the tricarboxylic acid (TCA) cycle, which drove inflammation. These metabolites involved succinate, which stimulated the inflammation reaction through the ROS-mediated stabilization of hypoxia-inducible factor-1α, promoting production of interleukin-1β by the inflammasome. In addition, itaconate was investigated for its role as an anti-inflammatory and antioxidant metabolite of the TCA cycle [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124">124</xref>]. NLRP3 inflammasome activation by decreased ROS through mitophagy might play a crucial role in berberine (BBR)-mediated alleviation of IV-induced inflammatory lesions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">125</xref>].
</p>
