<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="pone.0228634.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0228634.t001</object-id>
 <label>Table 1</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Description of research utilization indicators and stakeholder engagement indicators.</title>
 </caption>
 <alternatives>
  <graphic id="pone.0228634.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0228634.t001" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
   <colgroup span="1">
    <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
    <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
    <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
   </colgroup>
   <tbody>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" style="background-color:#D9D9D9" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
      <bold>Research Utilization Indicators</bold>
     </td>
     <td align="left" style="background-color:#D9D9D9" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
      <bold>Types of Documents Reviewed</bold>
     </td>
     <td align="left" style="background-color:#D9D9D9" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
      <bold>Evidence Examples</bold>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Have stakeholders developed an Interpretation and Use Plan for size estimation data?</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country Operational Plans (COP), Global Fund (GF) Country Coordinating Mechanism (CCM) concept notes, WHO HIV/AIDS guidelines, Global Fund Procurement and Supply Management (PSM) plans, Global Fund regional expressions of interest, UNAIDS progress reports, Phase 1 PSE study documents</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Language around guidance and suggestions for interpretation of data in local context and uses for study for guiding future key population data collection, program development, or service delivery</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Have size estimation data been used to identify a problem?</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COPs, GF CCM concept notes, UNAIDS epidemiological data publications, UNAIDS surveillance guidelines, WHO HIV/AIDS guidelines, National AIDS/HIV Program or Council documents, DHS, peer-reviewed documents, PEPFAR country frameworks, Global Fund PSM plans, UNFPA manuals, UNAIDS 2015 progress reports</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
      <list list-type="simple">
       <list-item>
        <p>Language around gaps in key population HIV response; Scale of services or resources; Contextualizing service utilization data</p>
       </list-item>
      </list>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Have size estimation data been used to develop a plan of action/recommendation to address that problem?</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COPs, GF Framework, GF CCM concept notes, UNAIDS data publications, National AIDS/HIV Program or Council documents, PEPFAR country frameworks, GF PSM plans, MEASURE Evaluation publications, United Nations Population Fund (UNFPA) manuals, UNAIDS 2015 progress reports, Phase 1 PSE study documents</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Using PSE to propose specific changes in level and areas of program coverage or resource allocation</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Have size estimation data been used to direct service delivery?</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COPs, National Strategic Plan documents, GF CCM concept notes, WHO HIV/AIDS guidelines, PEPFAR country frameworks, PEPFAR COPs GF PSM plans, GF regional expressions of interest, MEASURE Evaluation publications, UNAIDS 2015 progress reports</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Language linking PSE to proposed direction of resources or services towards or away from key populations</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Have size estimation data been used to change a Global Fund program or policy as documented in concept notes?</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GF concept notes, GF Funding Model, GF Secretariat briefing notes</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Language linking size estimates to adjustments in key populations priority areas, program development, program coverage targets, or changes in resource allocation around key population-tailored services</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Have size estimation data been used to change a PEPFAR program or policy as documented in country operational plans?</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEPFAR COPs, PEPFAR Strategic Direction Summaries</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Language linking size estimates to adjustments in key populations priority areas, program development, program coverage targets, or changes in resource allocation around key population-tailored services</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Have size estimation data been used to change a national MOH program or policy as documented in NSPs?</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National Strategic Plan documents (HIV/AIDS strategies, health strategies), GF CCM concept notes, National AIDS/HIV office documents, GF PSM plans, UNAIDS progress reports</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Language linking size estimates to adjustments in key populations priority areas, program development, program coverage targets, or changes in resource allocation around key population-tailored services</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Results/data translated into non-academic resources (briefs/ advocacy tools)</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phase I PSE study documents; Gray literature</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Results dissemination briefs, presentations, or advocacy reports</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" style="background-color:#D9D9D9" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
      <bold>Stakeholder Engagement Indicators</bold>
     </td>
     <td align="center" style="background-color:#D9D9D9" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
      <bold>Types of Documents Reviewed</bold>
     </td>
     <td align="center" style="background-color:#D9D9D9" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
      <bold>Evidence Examples</bold>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Have stakeholders been identified, who would be needed to make policy/program decisions?</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phase 1 PSE study document, COPs, GF CCM concept notes, Global Fund PSM plans, MEASURE Evaluation publications, UNAIDS epidemiological data publications, UNAIDS progress reports</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Language around involvement of National AIDS Council or Ministry of Health members, local program implementing non-governmental organizations (NGOs) and key population community and advocacy groups</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Have stakeholders been identified that represent the target population?</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COPs, GF CCM concept notes, UNAIDS epidemiological data publications, Global Fund PSM plans, MEASURE Evaluation publications, UNAIDS surveillance guidelines, UNAIDS progress reports</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Language of key population members involved in study design, implementation, dissemination</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Have stakeholders been engaged throughout study design?</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phase 1 PSE study document</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Language that evidences 1) working with stakeholders (including program implementers, policy makers, and the target population) to identify opportunities for use of the study’s data, findings, and recommendations; 2) enhancement of the protocol and study design with stakeholders’ knowledge of local context; 3) documentation of the stakeholders’ role and responsibilities in the study’s research utilization process; and 4) development of stakeholder’s capacity to understand and manage research utilization processes</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Have stakeholders been engaged throughout study implementation?</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phase 1 PSE study document</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Involvement of site mapping and participation in estimation exercises (such as peer educators distributing unique objects)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Were study data/results shared by stakeholders with other groups?</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peer-reviewed academic journals, UNAIDS surveillance guidelines</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Language referencing dissemination of study data with other organizations or groups</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Were stakeholders included as authors on published document?</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peer-reviewed academic journals, Phase 1 PSE study document</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Was a study-specific advisory panel established?</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phase 1 PSE study document</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Language referencing a technical working group, advisory panel, community advisory board, or other group of stakeholders established for the purpose of advising study activities</td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
 </alternatives>
</table-wrap>
