<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Turkeys infected intranasally with influenza H7N1 virus and influenza H7N3 virus exhibited histopathological changes in the pancreas, including infiltration by inflammatory cells, necrosis of acinar cells, fibrosis, and ductal hyperplasia (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Capua et al., 2013</xref>). We found that high-dose intraperitoneal infection of mice with H3N2 or WSN resulted in sclerosis of the adipose tissue covering the abdomen in the peritoneal cavity, sclerotic lesions of the pancreas, and massive destruction of the pancreatic structure. Furthermore, we observed apoptosis in pancreatic tissue sections 4 days post infection. It has been reported that influenza A infection induces cell death through apoptosis (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2001</xref>), necrosis (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Mosavi et al., 2015</xref>), and necroptosis (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Sridharan and Upton, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Nogusa et al., 2016</xref>). Influenza A virus induces apoptosis in macrophages, dendritic cells, monocytes, and epithelial cells of the airway and lungs by intrinsic (mitochondrial-dependent) and extrinsic pathways (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Atkin-Smith et al., 2018</xref>). The mitochondrial membrane proteins ANT3 and VDAC1 sense the PB1-F2 protein of the influenza H1N1 virus, triggering cytochrome c release and apoptosis induction (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Zamarin et al., 2005</xref>). The influenza NP protein also induces apoptosis by interacting with the anti-apoptotic factor API5 and the E3 ubiquitin ligase RNF43 (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Mayank et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Nailwal et al., 2015</xref>). The influenza NS1 protein induces apoptosis via an extrinsic pathway by upregulating FasL (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Schultz-Cherry et al., 2001</xref>). In order to protect the host against influenza A virus, the cytoplasmic protein RIPK3 activates the parallel pathways of FADD-driven apoptosis and MLKL-driven necroptosis (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Nogusa et al., 2016</xref>). Our previous results showed that interaction of the influenza HA protein with α-2,6-linked and α-2,3-linked sialic acids in B cells and macrophages induces apoptosis of those cells in the peritoneal cavity (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Gautam et al., 2019</xref>). Although we detected expression of influenza virus receptors in the pancreas, spleen, ovary, and uterus, influenza A infection only induced apoptosis in pancreatic cells. At early time points after intraperitoneal infection with H3N2 or WSN, we detected virus in the lungs, heart, blood, kidneys, pancreas, spleen, uterus, and ovaries. By contrast, 4 days after initial infection, the viruses were detectable only in the uterus and ovaries. Those results suggest that influenza A viruses that enter the host via the intraperitoneal route can circulate to various abdominal and pelvic organs but only induce apoptosis in pancreatic cells. The mice infected with H3N2 displayed hyperglycemia 4 days post infection, which was probably the result of severe structural damage to the pancreas. A previous study reported similar hyperglycemic conditions in turkeys that were infected intranasally with influenza virus (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Capua et al., 2013</xref>). Our results and the previous results are in line with reports that diabetic patients are more sensitive to influenza viruses than non-diabetic patients (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Ruiz et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
