<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We tested hypotheses representing how trust in formal/informal information might influence knowledge of influenza cause and perceived effectiveness of interventions, perceived susceptibility to and worry about influenza, and thereby personal hygiene. The null hypothesis of a fully saturated model was rejected in favour of a parsed final model partially approximating to that hypothesized. PHP variance was consistently explained by perceived PHP effectiveness, which in turn was associated with trust in formal information. However, counter intuitively, causal knowledge, while consistently associated with reported PHPs only associated with trust in formal information for A/H1N1 data. Counter to what was hypothesized, perceived susceptibility was unrelated to trust in information and reported PHP, being only associated with influenza worry, which itself contributed to PHP variance only for A/H5N1 data. Trust in formal/informal information explained significant variance in influenza worry only for A/H5N1. Otherwise, the hypothesized model showed good fit to different data sets, from different times and influenza types. Variability in influenza characteristics probably contributed to differences in the model path weights. Despite A/H5N1, having a high case-fatality-rate [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>], no deaths were attributed A/H5N1 in Hong Kong since 2002. Primarily a poultry disease, urban dwellers fear A/H5N1 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>], liking it to SARS [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. Rural dwellers, being familiar with zoonoses are less concerned [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. In contrast, A/H1N1 is perceived as a mild non-threatening event in Hong Kong [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].
</p>
