<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 2.</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Siglec-1 expression is dependent on Mtb-induced type I IFN signaling.</title>
  <p>(
   <bold>A</bold>) Vertical scatter plot showing the relative abundance of IFN-I in cmCTR (white) and cmMTB (black) media, as measured indirectly after 24 hr exposure to the HEK-Blue IFN-α/β reporter cell line yielding reporter activity in units (U) per mL. (
   <bold>B–D</bold>) Vertical scatter plots displaying the median fluorescent intensity (MFI) of Siglec-1 cell-surface expression after three days of monocyte differentiation into macrophages either with cmMTB (black) or cmCTR (white), the indicated recombinant cytokines (
   <bold>B</bold>), the presence of an IL-10 depletion (α-IL-10) or a control (α-IgG) antibodies (
   <bold>C</bold>), or the presence of an IFNAR-2 blocking (α-IFNAR) or control (α-IgG) antibodies (
   <bold>D</bold>). (
   <bold>E</bold>) Representative serial immunohistochemical images of lung biopsies of a co-infected (ATB-SIV) NHP stained for Siglec-1 (brown, top) and pSTAT1 (brown, bottom). Scale bar, 250 µm. Insets are 10x zooms. (
   <bold>F</bold>) Correlation of the percentage of cells positive for Siglec-1 and pSTAT1, as measured per mm
   <sup>2</sup> of lung tissue from the indicated NHP groups. Mean value is represented as a black line. (
   <bold>G</bold>) Representative immunohistochemical images of lung biopsies from the indicated NHP group stained for pSTAT1 (brown). Arrowheads show pSTAT1-positive nuclei. Scale bar, 500 µm. (
   <bold>H</bold>) Upper panel: Vertical Box and Whisker plot illustrating the percentage of pSTAT1
   <sup>+</sup> alveolar macrophages in lung biopsies from the indicated NHP groups. Quantification analysis from n = 600 alveolar macrophages grouped from three independent animals per NHP group. Lower panel: Correlation of the percentage of alveolar macrophages positive for Siglec-1 and pSTAT1, from the indicated NHP groups. Mean value is represented as a black line. (
   <bold>A–D</bold>) Each circle within vertical scatter plots represents a single donor and histograms median value. Statistical analyses: Two-tailed, Wilcoxon signed-rank test (
   <bold>A–D</bold>), Spearman correlation (F, H lower panel), and Mann-Whitney unpaired test (H, upper panel). *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001, ****p&lt;0.0001. ns: not significant. See 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="fig2sdata1">Figure 2—source data 1</xref>.
  </p>
  <p>
   <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="fig2sdata1">
    <label>Figure 2—source data 1.</label>
    <caption>
     <title>Raw data and statistical analyses supporting that IFN-I induced by M. tuberculosis is responsible for Siglec-1 expression in human and non-human primate macrophages.</title>
    </caption>
    <media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-52535-fig2-data1.xlsx" orientation="portrait" id="d35e1492" position="anchor" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </supplementary-material>
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="elife-52535-fig2" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
