<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In December 2019, a provincial health commission in China reported a cluster of pneumonia cases with unknown cause in Wuhan of Hubei province. The symptom onset date for the first patient identified was 1 December, 2019.
 <xref rid="ppul24810-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>30</sup>
 </xref> According to Wuhan health officials, the pneumonia appeared to be viral in nature and patients were placed in isolation. Potential causes including influenza, avian infleuenza, adenovirus, SARS‐CoV, and MERS‐CoV were ruled out.
 <xref rid="ppul24810-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>31</sup>
 </xref> Since there was highly suggestive evidence that the outbreak was associated with exposure in Wuhan's Huanan Seafood Wholesale Market, the market was closed on 1 January, 2020.
 <xref rid="ppul24810-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>32</sup>
 </xref> From 31 December, 2019 to 3 January, 2020, a total of 44 cases of pneumonia of unknown etiology from Wuhan of Hubei province were reported to the WHO. The virus was identified to be a new type of coronavirus on 7 January, 2020. Thailand reported the first case outside China on 13 January, 2020. Subsequently, cases were reported from other provinces in China, Japan, and South Korea. The epidemic has since been spreading rapidly and exponentially worldwide. The first known serious outbreak outside mainland China happened on the “Diamond Princess” cruise ship, where more than 700 people were infected and six died. The first case in Hong Kong was confirmed on 22 January, 2020 in a patient who returned from Wuhan.
 <xref rid="ppul24810-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>33</sup>
 </xref> At the time of writing, there are in excess of 3.6 million confirmed COVID‐19 cases and more than 257 000 deaths globally, the case‐fatality rate being 7%,
 <xref rid="ppul24810-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>34</sup>
 </xref> however, in the absence of sufficient testing to determine the true levels of morbidity, this number should be viewed as an approximation.
</p>
