<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Besides IAVs, ~25% of all human influenza virus infections in each epidemic season is caused by IBVs that are classified into two distinct lineages, Victoria-like and Yamagata-like lineages (Ambrose and Levin, 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). The current seasonal influenza vaccine is prepared in a trivalent or quadrivalent formulation, depending on the inclusion of one or two lineages of IBV antigens. Although priority is given to IAVs owing to a greater impact, IBVs may be more vulnerable targets against which to develop a UIV (
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) because of their low antigenic diversity and lack of animal reservoir (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) (Tan et al., 
 <xref rid="B225" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Indirect evidence is being accumulated by the isolation of cross-protective antibodies against IBVs. Several broadly protective antibodies binding to head or stalk domain of influenza B HA have been isolated in humans. Overall, these monoclonal antibodies show lineage-specific neutralizing activity 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>. Further, 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> protection against both lineages was also demonstrated in mice by passive transfer, through non-neutralizing antibody-dependent effector functions (Shen et al., 
 <xref rid="B210" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Hirano et al., 
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Vigil et al., 
 <xref rid="B237" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Asthagiri Arunkumar et al., 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Liu et al., 
 <xref rid="B157" ref-type="bibr">2019b</xref>). Notably, some of B HA stalk antibodies demonstrated extremely broad binding ability (Hirano et al., 
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) or protection against both IAVs and IBVs (Dreyfus et al., 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Influenza B NA-reactive broadly neutralizing antibodies were also isolated in animals and humans. Seasonal QIV induced NA antibodies with broad and potent antiviral activity against both lineages in humans (Piepenbrink et al., 
 <xref rid="B192" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Additionally, murine NA antibodies also showed broad protection against both lineages of IBV (Wohlbold et al., 
 <xref rid="B251" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>).
</p>
