<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ADCC represents a promising strategy for vaccine development, but there are still several questions to be addressed. First, the pre-existing neutralizing antibodies may affect the efficacy of the ADCC-based vaccine. He et al reported that the HI-positive antibody can inhibit the potency of ADCC activity induced by HA stalk-specific antibodies by competing in HA binding [
 <xref rid="B83-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Therefore, the efficacy of the ADCC-based vaccine may be affected by pre-existing immunity. Besides, the activation of pre-existing B cells may induce class switching from IgG to non-ADCC isotypes [
 <xref rid="B132-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>]. Second, vaccines that elicit antibodies targeting the M2 or the internal proteins may confer protection against severe influenza diseases, however, may not prevent viral infection since these antibodies mainly recognize proteins expressed on the infected cell membrane [
 <xref rid="B99-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. Third, whether sufficient ADCC-Abs can be induced by vaccination is unclear. The antigen needs to be carefully designed and inclusion of an adjuvant is also critical to protective outcome. Four, there are reports of antibody-dependent enhancement (ADE) in ADCC-mediating antibodies [
 <xref rid="B71-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,
 <xref rid="B133-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>]. In these studies, ADCC epitopes were identified and these epitope-based vaccines were generated and tested in mice. The immunized animals with ADCC epitopes showed robust ADCC activities but had lower survival rates in comparison with the control group. In addition, it was shown that ADCC epitope-based vaccines might have side effects including extra tissue damage as seen in the lungs, which was caused by the high level of cytotoxic granules (perforin) induced by ADCC activation [
 <xref rid="B71-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>].
</p>
