<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The spatiotemporal analysis presented in this paper differs from the existing studies, both in methodology and scope. By using Richards model and G* statistic [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], wavelet analysis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], and compartmental model [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], these researchers found that the initial hot spot for the outbreak was Yuexiu district, and then the disease spread to its neighboring districts in Guangzhou and other cities in GD province in 2014. By using Moran’s I method and geographical detector, Cao et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] found that central Guangzhou was the hot spot of dengue infection, and that temperature, precipitation and road density were the main factors leading to dengue transmission in Guangzhou in 2014. By using geographically weighted regression model, Ren et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] found that population size, road density, and economic status are the determinants of spatial variability of the 2014 dengue epidemic across Guangzhou and Foshan. Cheng et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] decomposed dengue risk in the 21 cities of GD by a multivariate time series model. They found that endemic component contributed much more in the Pearl River Delta area, while areas with relatively low incidence are highly dependent on spatiotemporal and local autoregressive spread. These analyses were mainly based on the city level of GD [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] or district level of Guangzhou [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Our study focus on the 128 districts and counties of GD, a finer scale and a larger area, allowing for better understanding dengue transmission patterns.
</p>
