<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As an enveloped virus, DENV stimulates the lipid biosynthesis pathway for essential membrane formation. Fatty acids, triglycerides, and other lipid compositions of the host are utilized by Flaviviruses for envelope formation. Membrane composition is not only required for the formation of the envelope but is also needed for inducing viral infection in many ways. Replication includes virion egress and assembly requires a great number of fatty acids and their derivatives that generate membrane. In DENV-infected cells, fatty acid synthesis is regulated to utilize acetyl-coenzyme A (AcCoA) for generating most distinct membrane lipids (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="microorganisms-07-00296-f002">Figure 2</xref>). DENV stimulates fatty acid biosynthesis by the help of the important cofactor fatty acid synthase (FASN), which was first identified through the DENV-2 replicon mediated siRNA screening [
 <xref rid="B60-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Lipophagy is known as a type of selective autophagy that transports lipids for β-oxidation. Several studies indicate that DENV infection induces pro-viral autophagy [
 <xref rid="B62-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The lipids accumulated in auto-phagosomes next transport to mitochondria, increasing the β-oxidation rate, which generates energy and plays a key role in lipophagy, thus assisting DENV replication. Additionally, NADPH that arises through β-oxidation utilizes a cofactor of FASN and it may stimulate the fatty acid synthesis for DENV replication. In DENV-infected cells, both fatty acid synthesis and lipophagy process take place at the same time. In contrast, both processes do not occur in natural cells at the same time [
 <xref rid="B67-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Extant research has shown that pharmacological inhibition of FASN [
 <xref rid="B68-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>] and mevalonate diphosphate decarboxylase, an enzyme required for cholesterol biosynthesis [
 <xref rid="B60-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], can decrease DENV production in host cells.
</p>
