<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0085">These are antimalarial drugs which are also believed to have antiviral activity 
 <xref rid="b0260" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. Both HCQ/CQ demonstrated potent in vitro activity against SARS-CoV-2 with an EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 6.14 μM and 23.90 μM, respectively 
 <xref rid="b0295" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>. The drugs have recently gained notoriety due to much sociopolitical hype that has led to a spate of newly launched clinical trials- more than 240 studies are currently underway around the world. There is very limited data to advocate the use of HCQ/CQ as therapeutic options in COVID-19. In a small open-label non-RCT of 36 patients (20 treated/ 16 controls), significantly improved virologic clearance was observed in the HCQ (N = 14) group. All six patients in the HCQ plus Azithromycin group had significantly better viral clearance 
 <xref rid="b0300" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>. However, six patients in the HCQ group were removed from the study due to adverse effects or intolerance of the medication. A study in Brazil (NCT04323527) was forced to prematurely halt patient recruitment due to the high fatality rate in the CQ group 
 <xref rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>. The authors of the study opined that treatment providers should refrain from administering high doses of CQ to critically ill patients with COVID-19 because of its potential safety hazards. There was also no reported evidence of a decrease in viral load or improvement in other clinical outcomes. A recent multinational observational study on more than 96,000 patients across six continents reported an increased occurrence of ventricular arrhythmias in patients who received hydroxychloroquine or chloroquine, when used alone or in conjunction with macrolides 
 <xref rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>. The authors reported that the drug regimen did not have any beneficial effect on treatment outcomes in COVID-19 patients, and exhibited an increased risk of mortality in the treatment group as compared to the control. HCQ/CQ has several potential Adverse Drug Reactions (ADR), such as the risk of cardiac arrhythmias (e.g., QT prolongation), GI Disturbances, ECG abnormalities, hypoglycemia, and retinal damage upon long-term/high dose use. In a recent single-center study on 2541 patients, treatment with HCQ alone and HCQ + Azithromycin demonstrated a significant reduction in mortality among hospitalized COVID-19 patients 
 <xref rid="b0315" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>. However, a randomized double-blind placebo-controlled trial which tested HCQ as postexposure prophylaxis did not find the drug to be effective in preventing COVID-19 after a high-risk exposure 
 <xref rid="b0320" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>. Hydroxychloroquine was discontinued from the RECOVERY trial owing to no evidence of beneficial effect on either mortality or clinical improvement outcomes 
 <xref rid="b0325" ref-type="bibr">[65]</xref>. The WHO also discontinued the Hydroxychloroquine trial arm of the SOLIDARITY trial as it did not produce any reduction in mortality of COVID-19 patients when compared to the standard of care 
 <xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. Similarly, the FDA has warned against the use of HCQ/CQ as therapeutic interventions against COVID-19 due to the risk of potential ADRs, and has revoked its status as an emergency-use drug for hospitalized patients who are not enrolled in registered clinical trials 
 <xref rid="b0330" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref>.
</p>
