<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="f0005">
 <label>Fig. 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>(A) Inferred HIV Transmission clusters. HIV-1 transmission cluster diagrams illustrating the structure and demographics of the putative transmission clusters identified in the San Diego–Tijuana border region. Color indicates transmission risk factor, and shape denotes gender. All edges represent a genetic distance of ≤ 1.5% separating nodes. Edges connecting viruses from San Diego and Tijuana are shown in bold. (B) Estimated timing of cross border transmissions. A time-scaled phylogenetic tree was created using Bayesian inference implemented in the BEAST software package (
   <xref rid="ec0015" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>). This tree was used to infer the time of most recent common ancestor (TMRCA) of each inferred cross border transmission cluster. In this table, the network diagram of each of the clusters is illustrated in the column titled “Cross-Border Clusters”. Within each of these clusters, putative cross border transmission events are highlighted with a bolded edge. Arrowheads represent directionality of these cross border transmission events where supported by the phylogenetic analysis. In the second column, the mean posterior probability of the TMRCA of the cluster as inferred from the time-scaled phylogenetic tree (
   <xref rid="ec0015" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>) is presented. TJ = Tijuana, SD = San Diego). (For interpretation of the references to color in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of this article.)
  </p>
  <p>(A) Inferred HIV Transmission clusters. HIV-1 transmission cluster diagrams illustrating the structure and demographics of the putative transmission clusters identified in the San Diego–Tijuana border region. Color indicates transmission risk factor, and shape denotes gender. All edges represent a genetic distance of ≤ 1.5% separating nodes. Edges connecting viruses from San Diego and Tijuana are shown in bold. (B) Estimated timing of cross border transmissions. A time-scaled phylogenetic tree was created using Bayesian inference implemented in the BEAST software package (Supplementary Fig. 2). This tree was used to infer the time of most recent common ancestor (TMRCA) of each inferred cross border transmission cluster. In this table, the network diagram of each of the clusters is illustrated in the column titled “Cross-Border Clusters”. Within each of these clusters, putative cross border transmission events are highlighted with a bolded edge. Arrowheads represent directionality of these cross border transmission events where supported by the phylogenetic analysis. In the second column, the mean posterior probability of the TMRCA of the cluster as inferred from the time-scaled phylogenetic tree (Supplementary Fig. 2) is presented. TJ = Tijuana, SD = San Diego).</p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="gr1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
