<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="t0005" position="float">
 <label>Table 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Descriptions of participating cohorts.</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th align="left">Cohort</th>
    <th align="left">Description</th>
    <th align="left">Dates</th>
    <th align="left">Subjects</th>
    <th align="left">Location</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Detection of HIV-infected unaware Latinos in San Diego (San Diego Latino Study)</td>
    <td align="left">A pilot respondent-driven sampling (RDS) study to identify HIV-infected Latino population in San Diego border region.</td>
    <td align="left">3/2010–5/2010</td>
    <td align="left">11</td>
    <td align="left">San Diego South Bay</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">El Cuete
     <xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref>
    </td>
    <td align="left">An ongoing research program studying injection drug users in Tijuana, Mexico that used both RDS (2006–2009) and convenience sampling (2010–present) approaches.</td>
    <td align="left">2006 to present</td>
    <td align="left">29</td>
    <td align="left">Tijuana</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Hombre Seguro
     <xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref>
    </td>
    <td align="left">An ongoing study of male clients of female sex workers working in the Tijuana, Mexico that used convenience sampling approaches.</td>
    <td align="left">9/2010–10/2012</td>
    <td align="left">12</td>
    <td align="left">Tijuana</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Amigos
     <xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">⁎</xref>
    </td>
    <td align="left">Study of male clients of female sex workers in partnership with the 
     <italic>Hombre Seguro</italic> study who were: ≥ 18 years old, reported heroin, methamphetamine, or cocaine use in the past four months, and having paid or traded something of value for sex with a female sex worker in Tijuana in the past four months.
    </td>
    <td align="left">6/2011–8/2012</td>
    <td align="left">3</td>
    <td align="left">Tijuana</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Mujer Segura</td>
    <td align="left">A research program studying female sex workers in Tijuana, Mexico, some of who use injection drugs. The study used time location sampling and convenience sampling approaches.</td>
    <td align="left">2004–2009</td>
    <td align="left">25</td>
    <td align="left">Tijuana</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Mujer Más Segura</td>
    <td align="left">A research program studying female sex workers in Tijuana, Mexico who use injection drugs. The study used targeted sampling approaches.</td>
    <td align="left">2008–2012</td>
    <td align="left">6</td>
    <td align="left">Tijuana</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Proyecto Parejas</td>
    <td align="left">A research project studying female sex workers and their non-commercial partners in the Tijuana Mexico that used convenience sampling approaches.</td>
    <td align="left">2010–2013</td>
    <td align="left">9</td>
    <td align="left">Tijuana</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">San Diego Primary Infection Cohort</td>
    <td align="left">An ongoing study to recruit and characterize acute and early HIV infected individuals. This study has used venue based and RDS recruitment approaches.</td>
    <td align="left">6/1996–6/2013</td>
    <td align="left">693</td>
    <td align="left">San Diego</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Study to Assess Hepatitis C Risk (STAHR)</td>
    <td align="left">An ongoing research program studying 18–40 year-old (STAHR) and 18 + year-old (STAHR-II) injection drug users in San Diego, CA recruited through RDS and convenience-based approaches.</td>
    <td align="left">3/2009–6/2010</td>
    <td align="left">17</td>
    <td align="left">San Diego</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Study to Assess Hepatitis C Risk II (STAHR-II)</td>
    <td align="left">An ongoing research program studying 18–40 year-old (STAHR) and 18 + year-old (STAHR-II) injection drug users in San Diego, CA recruited through venue based, targeted and convenience sampling approaches.</td>
    <td align="left">6/2012–1/2014</td>
    <td align="left">40</td>
    <td align="left">San Diego</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn id="tf0005">
   <label>⁎</label>
   <p>El Cuete, Hombre Seguro, and Amigos studies all included at least one individual living in San Diego but sampled in Tijuana.</p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
