<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Effective vaccines are important to prevent and control sporadic viral attacks and emerging virus-mediated epidemics, such as the recent outbreak caused by SARS-CoV-2. Although SARS-CoV was fully controlled during 2003, and MERS-CoV has been prevented from causing high mortality rates, the newly emerged SARS-CoV-2 is spreading efficiently with a significant increase in the number of cases and fatalities during each passing day. Vaccines are required to prevent SARS-CoV-2 from causing COVID-19. Live-attenuated vaccines, such as has been designed for SARS (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), may be evaluated for SARS-CoV-2 infected patients. In addition rhesus θ-defensin 1 and protein cage nanoparticles are innate immunomodulators with high anti-SARS-CoV efficiency (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). Based on the high similarity and phylogenetic relatedness between SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2, protein cage nanoparticles designed for SARS-CoV can be evaluated for SARS-CoV-2. Meanwhile, following similar strategies utilized for SARS-CoV, novel protein cage nanoparticles specified for novel coronavirus can be designed on an emergency basis. Given the urgency in the current scenario of COVID-19 outbreak, vaccination strategies based on viral vectors, recombinant protein, and viral-like particles, which have been developed or are being developed for SARS and/or MERS, could be modified for utilization against SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). Despite the current progress, further work is needed to develop safe and effective vaccines, available for individuals at high risk of SARS-CoV-2 endemics, to control the ongoing and risk of future epidemics. Further, an interesting feature of plasma from recovered patients is the presence of active antibodies. The transfer of plasma from people who have recovered from COVID-19 into infected individuals might enhance immunity against SARS-CoV-2. Monoclonal antibodies that could inhibit virus-cell receptor binding and interrupt virus-cell fusion have been developed (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Combining two or more monoclonal antibodies may be suitable for the quicker recovery of patients. Lastly, antiviral peptides that target different regions of S, such as HP2P-M2 peptide (effective against viral infections) (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), should also be considered against COVID-19.
</p>
