<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>With concerted effort and advocacy along with academic and government funding and recognition from regulatory agencies, the pediatric TB trial landscape has substantially improved, as evidenced by the number of ongoing and planned studies of treatment for the diverse forms of TB in children (
 <bold>
  <xref rid="pmed.1002882.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>
 </bold>). The ways in which pediatric and adult TB differ inform the type of pediatric TB drug trials needed and their key design considerations. If children are to be included in adult trials, different inclusion and exclusion criteria may be needed, and definitions used to determine study endpoints (e.g., unfavorable outcome) require careful consideration because of differing clinical features and diagnostic challenges of TB in children compared with adults. Diagnosis, treatment response monitoring, and characterization of treatment outcome in children often depend on clinical measures that are relatively imprecise compared with the diagnostic standard used in adults. Limited availability of pediatric-friendly formulations also poses a barrier to enrollment of younger children. Large Phase III clinical trials may not be feasible or always needed for children, yet timely PK and safety data in children, especially in young and HIV-infected children, is critical to inform policy guidance on new therapies deemed to be safe and efficacious in adolescent and adult populations. Modified study designs should be explored to accelerate implementation of PK and safety studies in children while ensuring the validity of the trial results and the safety of all child participants. Unlike younger children, adolescents (typically ≥10 years old) have TB disease characteristics similar to adults, including frequent cavitating disease. Adolescents should therefore be routinely considered for inclusion in adult Phase IIb and III trials. However, similar to pregnant and lactating women, legal requirements for child participation in clinical trials are often barriers (perceived or real) and vary by country. When feasible and justified through appropriate consultation, the inclusion of children should be carefully considered and supported early during protocol development. Summaries of considerations for the types of trials needed for children, including practical and ethical considerations regarding inclusion of children in TB trials, can be found elsewhere [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002882.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pmed.1002882.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Highlights and considerations discussed at the WHO technical consultation are discussed below based on updated information.
</p>
