<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To estimate our model, we placed the same normal and inverse gamma priors on our regression and variance parameters 
 <italic>β</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>s</italic>
 </sub>~
 <italic>N</italic>(0,100) and 
 <italic>σ</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>s</italic>
 </sub>~
 <italic>IG</italic>(0.5,0.5) respectively. Regimes are sampled using multi-move Gibbs sampling via the Carter-Kohn recursion [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007839.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] with up to 3 regimes considered. The recursion first conducts a forward pass filtering step to infer the probability of arriving at a regime given the first 
 <italic>t</italic> observations for all 
 <italic>tϵ</italic>{1,…,
 <italic>T</italic>}, where 
 <italic>T</italic> denotes the final time point. Next, the backward pass smoothing step provides the probabilities of being in a regime at 
 <italic>t</italic>, given its future observations {
 <italic>t</italic>+1,…,
 <italic>T</italic>}. The second step allows the recursion to consider the full data likelihood and provides assignment of datapoints to each regime, which were then post-hoc labelled based on their behavior. The Dirichlet prior 
 <italic>ξ</italic>
 <sub>1</sub>~
 <italic>Dir</italic>(25,5),
 <italic>ξ</italic>
 <sub>2</sub>~
 <italic>Dir</italic>(5,25) was also placed on each row of the transition matrix, dictating the belief that the probability of staying within one regime is higher than the probability of transitioning to another. We impose the identifiability constraint 
 <italic>σ</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>epidemic</italic>
 </sub>&gt;
 <italic>σ</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>endemic</italic>
 </sub> to account for label switching. This is reasonable as dengue transmission counts should fluctuate more in absolute numbers within an epidemic compared to endemic period. These steps are nested within a Gibbs sampling framework due to prior-likelihood conditional conjugacy. Gibbs sampling for BRS is run with 50000 iterations with a burn-in of 5000. Full computational details are provided in the 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1007839.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>.
</p>
