<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We used Program R [
 <xref rid="pone.0232705.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] to create a simplified island landscape to simulate the spread of infectious disease through a population of ~1,000 island foxes. We divided the island into four blocks, with each block reflecting the density of foxes observed at four study sites on San Clemente Island where fox home range sizes and contact rates had been previously measured (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0232705.g001">Fig 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="pone.0232705.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. From north to south, the blocks were “high” density with 21 foxes/km
 <sup>2</sup> representing sand dune habitat and developed areas, “medium-low” density with 5 foxes/km
 <sup>2</sup> representing maritime desert scrub vegetation on gently sloping marine terraces, “medium-high” density with 9 foxes/km
 <sup>2</sup> representing maritime desert scrub vegetation in rugged canyons and drainages, and “low” density with 2 foxes/km
 <sup>2</sup> representing the grasslands dominating the central plateau extending the length of the island (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0232705.g002">Fig 2</xref>). The center points of simulated fox home ranges were placed at a random xy-coordinate on the island landscape, then a circular home range was generated based on the fox density block that the home range was centered in. The radius of each home range was sampled from a normal distribution derived from the observed relationship between fox density and home range size in SCI foxes (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0232705.s001">S1 Table</xref>) [
 <xref rid="pone.0232705.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. We sampled a daily contact rate for each pair of foxes from a normal distribution derived from the observed relationship between two-dimensional home range overlap [
 <xref rid="pone.0232705.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] and contact rates for SCI foxes (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0232705.s001">S1 Table</xref>) [
 <xref rid="pone.0232705.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0232705.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The intercepts of both regressions were constrained to be nonnegative to reflect the impossibility of negative contact rates.
</p>
