<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We used the simulation to evaluate two aspects of monitoring effort: monitoring intensity (i.e. number of sentinels monitored) and monitoring frequency (i.e. how often the mortality status of sentinels was determined). The level of monitoring intensity was simulated by randomly selecting 50, 75, 100, 125 or 150 foxes to be sentinel animals, representing approximately 5–15% of the total fox population. When a sentinel died from disease, we recorded its day of death and the number of foxes in the population that were infected (including the latent, infectious, and dead classes) on that day. Most monitoring schemes currently used on the California Channel Islands check the status of sentinels weekly. This means that a carcass will be a minimum of 1–7 days old before it is detected. Depending on ambient environmental conditions, tissues can rapidly decay beyond the point where a necropsy can identify the cause of death even when carcasses are collected quickly following a status check revealing a mortality. Consequently, it is not unreasonable that multiple sentinels could perish from a disease before the discovery of a burgeoning epidemic. Epidemic response plans in place for San Clemente Island, Catalina Island, and the Channel Islands National Park call for increased monitoring frequency if more than 2–3 sentinels (depending on the number of sentinels monitored) die within a 30 day period, regardless of cause [
 <xref rid="pone.0232705.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0232705.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. To account for these potential delays in the identification of disease and elevation in mortality rates, we assume that under typical monitoring frequencies, an epidemic is not confirmed until the fifth sentinel has died. This corresponds to an expected 80% of sentinel carcasses being too far decomposed to determine the cause of death, similar to the delay in detection estimated by Doak et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0232705.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. We also evaluated the maximum possible benefits of increasing monitoring frequency by assuming a high-frequency monitoring strategy sufficient to confirm an epidemic with the first sentinel mortality.
</p>
