<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Primary EBV infection is subclinical in the majority of immunocompetent individuals; it may lead to IM in adolescents and adults. It is generally self-limiting; therefore, in immunocompetent individuals, symptomatic treatment alone is recommended. This includes rest, adequate hydration and nutrition, and analgesics or antipyretics as needed. In patients suffering from IM, avoidance of exertion and participation in sports is recommended for at least 3 weeks due to the rare risk of splenic rupture. Rare patients suffering from severe complications of acute EBV are usually treated with corticosteroids even though there is little evidence to support their use [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. The dose used varies in different reports. The use of antivirals in the management of severe EBV infections in immunocompetent hosts is debatable. However, it is suggested as an adjunct to steroid treatment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], especially in cases of refractory disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Several antiviral drugs, including acyclic nucleoside and nucleotide analogues and pyrophosphate analogues, inhibit replication of EBV in cell culture via inhibition of EBV DNA polymerase. Acyclovir inhibits in vitro EBV replication and transiently reduces viral shedding in the oropharynx but does not reduce viremia or symptoms. Ganciclovir was effective in the treatment of EBV hepatitis in a small number of children and in adults [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. Valganciclovir, the oral pro-drug of ganciclovir, has been successfully used in the treatment of severe acute EBV hepatitis (900 mg × 2/daily for 15 days) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Additional drugs with antiviral activity against EBV include valacyclovir, famciclovir, and foscarnet. Patients with acute liver failure should be considered for urgent liver transplantation, as the likelihood of spontaneous recovery is small [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Patients with immunodeficiencies are at increased risk of liver failure and the development of lethal lymphoproliferative diseases. The major pathogenic causes thought to be important in the development of lymphoproliferative disorders/lymphomas are primary immunodeficiency (XLP, ataxia telangiectasia, Wiskott-Aldrich syndrome, Chediak-Higashi syndrome, SCID, CVID, and others), immunosuppressive therapy, and HIV/AIDS. In these patients, primary EBV infection should be treated preemptively with ex vivo-generated EBV-specific CTLs or effective antiviral medication. In seronegative patients with XLP, monthly prophylaxis with IVIG is recommended. Patients who have developed EBV-associated lymphoproliferative disease may benefit from chemotherapy, radiation therapy, or biological therapy with monoclonal antibodies or EBV-specific CTLs. Hematopoetic stem cell transplantation is the only potentially curative therapy for many patients but is usually recommended only in children [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>].
</p>
