<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0060">The gene encoding FIPV–3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> was amplified from the cDNA of FIPV strain 79–1146 (ATCC, VR–990) with forward primer (5′-CATG
 <underline>CCATGG</underline>CT
 <italic>ATCGAGGGAAGG</italic>TCCGGATTGAGAAAAATGGCAC–3′) containing an 
 <italic>Nco</italic>I site (underlined) and an FXa protease cleavage site (Ile-Glu-Gly-Arg, italicized), and reverse primer (5′-CCG
 <underline>CTCGAG</underline>TTACTGAAGATTAACACCATACATTTGC–3′) containing an 
 <italic>Xho</italic>I site (underlined). The PCR product was digested using 
 <italic>Nco</italic>I and 
 <italic>Xho</italic>I, and then ligated into a pET32a vector. The recombinant protease plasmid was then used to transform 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5α-competent cells that were then streaked on a Luria-Bertani (LB) agar plate containing 100 μg/mL ampicillin. Ampicillin-resistant colonies were selected from the agar plate and cultured in 5 mL of LB broth containing 100 μg/mL ampicillin overnight at 37 °C. The correct constructs were subsequently transformed to 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21 (DE3) for protein expression. The 5-mL overnight culture of a single transformant was used to inoculate 500 mL of fresh LB medium containing 100 μg/mL ampicillin. The cells were grown to the appropriate optical density (OD
 <sub>600</sub> = 0.6) and induced with 1 mM Isopropyl- β-D-1 thiogalactopyranoside. After 4–5 h, the cells were harvested by centrifugation at 7,000×
 <italic>g</italic> for 15 min. The protein purification was carried out as described previously (
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Kuo et al., 2004</xref>). Briefly, the gene encoding FIPV 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> was amplified using PCR and inserted into the commercial vector pET32a for the expression of the enzyme with thioredoxin, hexa-His tag, and a cleavage site for FXa protease on the N-terminus. After cleavage of the tag by FXa protease, the mixture was loaded onto another Ni-NTA column to remove the thioredoxin and hexa-His tag. The purity of the tag-free FIPV 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> was evaluated using SDS-PAGE. The protein having a purity of more than 90% was first dialyzed in a buffer containing 12 mM Tris-HCl (pH 7.5), 120 mM NaCl, 0.1 mM EDTA, 7.5 mM β-mercaptoethanol, and 1 mM dithiothreitol (DTT), and then subjected to the next experiment.
</p>
