<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <title>Acknowledgements</title>
 <p>The content of this paper is largely based on results of a meeting of subject matter experts held at the University of Alaska Fairbanks, Fairbanks, Alaska August 11–12, 2010. The meeting reviewed the state of knowledge on zoonotic and parasitic diseases in Alaska, the potential impact of climate change on the distribution and prevalence of disease in animals and humans, and identified gaps and actions that would contribute to earlier detection of disease and inform research, prevention and control strategies. We thank the following experts for their input on important pathogens of concern: Thomas Hennessy (Facilitator); Centers for Disease Control &amp; Prevention, Arctic Investigations Program, Anchorage, Alaska; Louisa Castrodale, Section of Epidemiology, Alaska Division of Public Health, Anchorage, Alaska, USA; Sue Hagius (
  <italic>Brucella</italic>) Department of Veterinary Science, LSU Agriculture Center, Baton Rouge LA; Harvey Artsob (retired) (Arboviruses) National Microbiology Laboratory Public Health Agency of Canada, Winnipeg Manitoba; Manon Simard (
  <italic>Trichinella</italic>) Wildlife Parasitologist, Nunavik Research Center Makivik Corporation Kuujjuaq, Québec, Charles Rupprecht (Rabies), National Center for Emerging and Zoonotic Infectious Diseases, CDC Atlanta, GA. Emily Jenkins (
  <italic>Echinococcus, Toxocara</italic> and 
  <italic>Toxoplasma</italic>) University of Saskatchewan, Saskatoon SK, Canada, Michael Beach (
  <italic>Giardia</italic> and 
  <italic>Cryptosporidium</italic>) National Center for Emerging and Zoonotic Infectious Diseases, CDC Atlanta GA; Charles Beard (
  <italic>Francisella</italic>) National Center for Emerging and Zoonotic Infectious Diseases, CDC, Fort Collins Colorado; Jonathan Runstadler (Avian Influenza) University of Alaska Fairbanks, Alaska.
 </p>
 <p>This project was supported by grants from the National Center for Research Resources (5P20RR016466-12) and the National Institute of General Medical Sciences (8 P20 GM103395-12) from the National Institutes of Health.</p>
</ack>
