<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">Identification of immune epitopes is important in designing new vaccine candidates and in diagnostics. An epitope is the part of an antigen that is recognized by the receptors of immune system components such as antibodies, B cells or T cells. Epitopes have been generally classified as either linear or conformational epitopes. T cells recognize linear epitopes, short continuous strings of amino acids derived from protein antigen, presented with MHC class I molecules. B cells and antibodies, on the other hand, recognize conformational epitopes which are formed by interactions of amino acids with multiple discontinuous segments forming a three-dimensional antigen (Barlow et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1986</xref>). Owing to the simple linear structure of T cell epitopes, their interaction with receptors can be modelled with high accuracy (DeLisi and Berzofsky 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">1985</xref>). A large number of prediction databases and servers thus are available for linear epitope prediction. MHCPEP (Brusic et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1998</xref>), SYFPEITHI (Rammensee et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">1999</xref>), FIMM (Schonbach et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2005</xref>), MHCBN (Bhasin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2003</xref>) and EPIMHC (Reche et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2005</xref>) are some of the commonly used T cell epitope prediction programs. Immune epitope database and analysis resource (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.iedb.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.iedb.org</ext-link>) (Vita et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">2015</xref>) offers the most comprehensive set of tools for epitope analysis for epitope prediction covering HLA-A and HLA-B for humans as well as chimpanzee, macaque, gorilla, cow, pig and mouse and is one of the few databases that cover such a variety of organisms. Since 2011, IEDB uses NetMHCpan as prediction method. NetMHC server uses the artificial neural network method to predict binding of peptides to different alleles from human as well as 41 animals including cattle and pig (38 from core). The database also contains curated data for many viruses including influenza and herpesviruses. B cell receptors and epitope interactions are more complex in nature than the linear epitopes for T cells; thus, accuracy of B cell epitopes is relatively low. Furthermore, most of the current databases are centred on linear rather than conformational epitopes. Bcipep is a tool developed for predicting the linear epitope of B cells (Saha et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2005</xref>). Epitome is a database of structure-inferred antigenic residues in proteins (Schlessinger et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2006</xref>). Epitome is especially useful in the prediction of antibody-antigen complex interaction. The database is available at 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rostlab.org/services/epitome/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.rostlab.org/services/epitome/</ext-link>. AntiJen is an intricate database with entries on both T cell and B cell epitopes. It emphasizes on integration of kinetic, thermodynamic, functional and cellular data within the context of immunology and vaccinology (Toseland et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">2005</xref>) (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">23.1a</xref>).
</p>
