<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="f0010">
 <label>Fig. 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Simplified scheme of replication of ss (+)RNA viruses (A), dsRNA and (-)RNA viruses (B), retroviruses (C) and DNA viruses (D) (the schemes A-C were modified from: (Ahlquist, 2006).</p>
  <p>A: Following endocytosis, the genome of (+)RNA viruses may directly serve as mRNA for translation of virus encoded proteins. Among them, there are proteins of RNA-replication machinery that recruit (+)RNA into a membrane-associated replication complex. The genomic RNA is replicated by using (–)RNA template, which is transcribed in a low copy number Amplified (+)RNA is then packaged into newly assembled virions that exit the host cell either through secretion or cell lysis.</p>
  <p>B: Upon the virus attachment, a core containing both gRNA and virus encoded RNA polymerase is delivered into the cytoplasm by endocytosis. Cytoplasmic transcription of the (–)RNA template provides (+)RNA that serves as mRNA for translation of viral proteins. In dsRNA viruses, the (+)RNA is packaged into new cores which undergo maturation by synthesizing (–)RNA (dotted strand) and acquiring surface proteins. In the (–)RNA viruses, the (+)RNA strand is transcribed into genomic (–)RNA in the cytoplasm and then packaged. The new virions egress the cell either through secretion or cell lysis.</p>
  <p>C: Following fusion of viral and cell plasma membrane, the retroviral core is released into cytosol, RNA genome is transcribed into dsDNA by viral reverse transcriptase concomitantly with uncoating of the viral core, ds DNA is transferred into nucleus where it is integrated into host cell genome by viral integrase, following translation of retroviral structural and enzymatic polyproteins, the unspliced gRNA is packaged into the immature particles that usually assemble at the plasma membrane and the viral particles bud from the cell.</p>
  <p>D: Three mechanisms (I.-III.) of DNA viruses replication are shown: (I): Following entry and uncoating, the DNA genome is transported to the nucleus; products of early genes (regulatory proteins, transcription factors) regulate the synthesis of viral enzymes (e.g. DNA polymerase) required for genome replication; expression of late genes encoding structural capsid proteins in the cytosol, they are then transported into nucleus where packaging and pre-assembly take place; preassembled procapsids exit the nucleus and leave the cell (e.g. Herpesviruses). (II) unique replication cycle of Hepatitis B virus (HBV): following entry, the viral particle is internalized by endocytosis and the nucleocapsid is released into the cytoplasm; the genome (relaxed circular rcDNA) is transported into the nucleus, where it is converted to a covalently closed circular form (cccDNA); which serves as a template for transcription of pregenomic RNA (pgRNA) for translation of the core protein and the viral polymerase and three subgenomic mRNAs used for translation of regulatory and envelope proteins; following viral transcription and translation, the HBV core proteins self-assemble in the cytoplasm into viral nucleocapsid with concurrent incorporation of pgRNA and HBV polymerase, pgRNA is reversely transcribed into a rcDNA within the nucleocapsid; nucleocapsid containing rcDNA can either re-enter the nucleus to amplify cccDNA, or can be enveloped by HBV envelope proteins in the endoplasmic reticulum. The particles are then secreted from the infected hepatocyte by exocytosis. (III) Upon entering the cell, the replication, transcription and translation take place entirely in the cytoplasm, within discrete juxtanuclear sites called virus factories (e.g. poxviruses)</p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text id="al0010">Fig. 2</alt-text>
 <graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 <attrib>Adapted from: Ahlquist, P., 2006. Parallels among positive-strand RNA viruses, reverse-transcribing viruses and double-stranded RNA viruses. Nat Rev Microbiol 4(5), 371-382.</attrib>
</fig>
