<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The IIV split virus vaccines, produced in 8–10 day-old chicken embryonic eggs as previously reported for the manufacture of pandemic H5N1 split virus vaccine, were provided by GlaxoSmithKline (GSK). The cH5/1
 <sub>Cal09</sub>N1
 <sub>Cal09</sub> (cH5/1) IIV is composed of an HA head domain of A/Vietnam/1203/04 (H5N1), an H1 stalk domain and N1 NA from the Cal/09 strain while the internal genes were derived from the H1N1 A/Puerto Rico/8/34 (PR8) virus. The cH8/1
 <sub>Cal09</sub>N1
 <sub>Cal09</sub> (cH8/1) IIV consists of an HA head domain from A/mallard/Sweden/24/02 (H8N4) while the remaining genes as well as the stalk domain are the same as for the cH5/1 IIV. All IIV vaccines used in this preclinical study were adjuvanted with Adjuvant System 03 (AS03) in the same formulation as for our previous study (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), and which has been licensed for use in humans for pandemic influenza virus vaccines (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). The backbone of the cH8/1 and cH11/1
 <sub>Cal09</sub>N1
 <sub>Cal09</sub> (cH11/1) LAIVs are based on the Leningrad vaccine strain (A/Leningrad/134/17/57, Len/57), which has been licensed and successfully used in humans (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). The H3N2 LAIV virus used in this study was based on the LAIV strain, A/Ann Arbor/6/60, which has been used to produce FluMist LAIV vaccines. The H3N2 LAIV expresses the H3 HA and N2 NA from the H3N2 influenza virus, A/Wyoming/03/03. pDZ plasmids for the virus rescue were cloned at the Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai (ISMMS) as our previous study described (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). cH8/1 LAIV seed virus was rescued by reverse genetics at the US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>) and produced at ISMMS. The composition of recombinant B cH9/1 virus (a B/Yamagata/16/88 virus that expresses a cH9/1 HA) was as previously described (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>).
</p>
