<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza A viruses (IAV) belong to the 
 <italic>Orthomyxoviridae</italic> family, and they contain a single-stranded (ss) negative-sense viral (v)RNA genome formed by eight segments that are encapsidated into particles with an envelope (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-08-00168-f001">Figure 1</xref>A). Each of the vRNA segments contains a long central coding region flanked at 5′ and 3′ termini by non-coding regions (NCRs), which work as promoters to initiate viral RNA synthesis (transcription and replication). Moreover, the packaging signals playing a role in the efficient encapsidation of the viral segments into nascent virions, are located at the 3′ and 5′ end of the coding regions (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-08-00168-f001">Figure 1</xref>B) [
 <xref rid="B1-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Structurally, vRNAs form viral ribonucleoprotein complexes (vRNPs), where vRNAs are coated with multiple subunits of the viral nucleoprotein (NP) and are associated with the heterotrimeric polymerase, which contains the polymerase basic 2 and 1 (PB2 and PB1, respectively) and acidic (PA) proteins (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-08-00168-f001">Figure 1</xref>A) [
 <xref rid="B2-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Each vRNP acts as an independent transcription-replication unit using an uncommon mechanism among negative-sense RNA viruses, given that viral RNA synthesis occurs in the infected-cells nucleus. vRNAs are used as templates by the viral polymerase to synthesize two positive-sense RNA molecules, the complementary RNAs (cRNAs), from which the same viral polymerase synthesizes more copies of genomic vRNA, and the mRNAs for viral protein synthesis [
 <xref rid="B1-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The small IAV genome encodes for up to 16 viral proteins through multiple mechanisms, although there are some differences between strains. For that genome plasticity, IAV take advantage of multiple strategies, such as alternative splicing, frameshift mechanisms, and overlapping open reading frames (ORFs) [
 <xref rid="B7-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In addition, the coding capability of the viral genome is extended by encoding multifunctional proteins that act at different steps during virus infection.
</p>
