<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>RSV infection is the most common cause of both upper and lower respiratory tract infection in children, and seroprevalence approaches 100 % of the population by 2 years of age (Papenburg and Boivin 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2010</xref>). The peak incidence is from 6 weeks to 6 months of age (Hustedt and Vazquez 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2010</xref>). Clinically, RSV infection of the upper respiratory tract causes coryza, cough, hoarseness, rhinitis, and conjunctivitis. Acute otitis media is a frequent complication. Lower respiratory tract infection due to RSV results in a syndrome of bronchiolitis (65 %) or pneumonia (21 %) and less commonly croup (11 %) or asthma exacerbation (3 %) (Williams et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2004</xref>). Vomiting is seen in a significant percentage of children (31 %). Hospitalization is required in 1–2 % of infected infants and mortality is relatively rare (0.02 %) but accounts for approximately 500 deaths annually in the United States (Hustedt and Vazquez 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2010</xref>; Hammond et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2007</xref>). The histopathologic findings in RSV infection include circumferential inflammation of bronchiolar mucosa and infection of type 1 and 2 pneumocytes (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">17.2</xref>) (Johnson et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2007</xref>). The inflammatory infiltrate consists of bronchocentric mucosal and transmural mononuclear cells (primarily T lymphocytes and monocytes) and neutrophils. Neutrophilic infiltration centers on the bronchioles, whereas mononuclear infiltration affects both bronchioles and parenchyma. As with other viruses, airway obstruction results from epithelial and inflammatory cell debris mixed with fibrin, mucus, and edema, compounded by extrinsic compression of bronchioles by hyperplastic lymphoid follicles (Johnson et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2007</xref>). Syncytial giant cell formation is rare in immunocompetent children but characteristic of the histopathologic features in immunocompromised patients (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">17.3</xref>) (Coffin 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2005</xref>; Hammond et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2007</xref>; Welliver 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2003</xref>). Therapy for RSV includes use of ribavirin, a synthetic nucleoside analogue. High-risk populations of children may also be preventatively treated with palivizumab, a monoclonal antibody targeting the F protein of RSV (Papenburg and Boivin 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2010</xref>). 
</p>
