<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>First, epitope selection is necessary to design vaccines that produce strong neutralizing antibody responses and minimal ADE effect. Traditional live attenuated vaccines have the advantages of strong immunogenicity and mimicry of wildtype virus. However, the antibody responses elicited by intact or recombinant dengue or Zika viruses still maintain the dual functions of neutralization and enhancement. One prominent source of antigens that induce enhancing antibodies is the immature or partially mature viral particles within the vaccine produced 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> or viruses replicated 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>, and the percentages of which are difficult to determine due to variability in cell cultures for different virus strains. Epitopes on “pr” peptides are probably exposed on immature ZIKV virus surface and elicit abundant ADE inducing antibodies, similar to what happened in DENV infected patients. The same issue must be dealt with for DNA or RNA vaccines that incorporate prM and E genes in order to make virus like particles 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Beckett et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B141" ref-type="bibr">Porter et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B148" ref-type="bibr">Richner et al., 2017a</xref>). Similarly, 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> produced virus like particle vaccines will not be ideal unless the immature virus-like particle can be eliminated through procedures such as exogenous Furin cleavage, but how to produce enough immunogens is another problem even more complicated to deal with (
 <xref rid="B178" ref-type="bibr">Urakami et al., 2017</xref>). Therefore, the exact effect and ratio of “pr” antibodies elicited by these vaccines have to be determined during development. In comparison, subunit proteins are easier for epitope selection and quality control. In most subunit candidate vaccines of DENV and ZIKV, soluble EDIII or E80 as antigens were chosen (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Block et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">Liang et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B115" ref-type="bibr">Manoff et al., 2019</xref>) to induce neutralizing antibodies that block virus attachment or/and inhibit post-entry membrane fusion. Nevertheless, fusion-loop epitope antibodies can still be induced by E80 due to the probable re-exposure of fusion-loop under acidic environment even for an envelope dimer immunogen. One study has attempted to abolish fusion loop through site-directed mutation in mRNA vaccine (
 <xref rid="B148" ref-type="bibr">Richner et al., 2017a</xref>), but both neutralization and enhancement activities were attenuated, indicating this region was probably essential for E dimeric structure on VLP surface. Alternatively, cross-linking of two E80 proteins through additional disulfate bonds in domain II and domain III could stabilize the anti-parallel structure of the soluble E80 dimer, limiting the exposure of fusion-loop, but enabling the presentation of cross-serocomplex broadly neutralizing EDE epitopes (
 <xref rid="B156" ref-type="bibr">Rouvinski et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>). Consistently, in a recent study, the covalently stabilized ZIKV E dimer has successfully elicited protective antibody responses against ZIKV infection in mice, without causing cross-reactivity to dengue viruses or ADE of DENV (
 <xref rid="B170" ref-type="bibr">Slon-Campos et al., 2019</xref>). Currently, both Zika EDIII and Dengue tetravalent EDIII vaccines are under development. The EDIII component theoretically has more serotype/complex specificity and produce less ADE effect. Whether these type-specific neutralization antibodies induced are strong enough to provide 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> protection toward multiple viruses is to be determined.
</p>
