<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">To this end, we evaluated the antiviral effect of HCQ against SARS-CoV-2 infection in comparison to CQ in vitro. First, the cytotoxicity of HCQ and CQ in African green monkey kidney VeroE6 cells (ATCC-1586) was measured by standard CCK8 assay, and the result showed that the 50% cytotoxic concentration (CC
 <sub>50</sub>) values of CQ and HCQ were 273.20 and 249.50 μM, respectively, which are not significantly different from each other (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). To better compare the antiviral activity of CQ versus HCQ, the dose–response curves of the two compounds against SARS-CoV-2 were determined at four different multiplicities of infection (MOIs) by quantification of viral RNA copy numbers in the cell supernatant at 48 h post infection (p.i.). The data summarized in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref> and Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref> show that, at all MOIs (0.01, 0.02, 0.2, and 0.8), the 50% maximal effective concentration (EC
 <sub>50</sub>) for CQ (2.71, 3.81, 7.14, and 7.36 μM) was lower than that of HCQ (4.51, 4.06, 17.31, and 12.96 μM). The differences in EC
 <sub>50</sub> values were statistically significant at an MOI of 0.01 (
 <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) and MOI of 0.2 (
 <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) (Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). It is worth noting that the EC
 <sub>50</sub> values of CQ seemed to be a little higher than that in our previous report (1.13 μM at an MOI of 0.05)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>
 </sup>, which is likely due to the adaptation of the virus in cell culture that significantly increased viral infectivity upon continuous passaging. Consequently, the selectivity index (SI = CC
 <sub>50</sub>/EC
 <sub>50</sub>) of CQ (100.81, 71.71, 38.26, and 37.12) was higher than that of HCQ (55.32, 61.45, 14.41, 19.25) at MOIs of 0.01, 0.02, 0.2, and 0.8, respectively. These results were corroborated by immunofluorescence microscopy as evidenced by different expression levels of virus nucleoprotein (NP) at the indicated drug concentrations at 48 h p.i. (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Taken together, the data suggest that the anti-SARS-CoV-2 activity of HCQ seems to be less potent compared to CQ, at least at certain MOIs.
</p>
