<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In each country, semi-structured interviews were conducted with purposively sampled individuals in the MOH, NACs, AIDS Control Program, organizations providing programme funding or technical assistance [Department for International Development; The Global Fund; World Health Organization (WHO); UNAIDS; United Nations’ Children’s Fund (UNICEF); US Government entities such as PEPFAR, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), and United States Agency for International Development (USAID)], and major programme implementers. Informants were selected first by sensitizing each key organization and asking senior staff to nominate individuals for interview based on their role in the response to 90–90–90 and knowledge of programme, policy or budget changes. Informants were asked for names of other key individuals from the same or other organizations crucial in the response until representatives from all major organizations cited by respondents as important in the response were covered from both countries; thus resulting in a slightly different profile of those interviewed based on the composition of each network responding to 90–90–90 in each country. Interviews were conducted in-person and individually, except for three interviews in Ghana (two conducted by telephone and one with three informants). Thirty-seven interviews were conducted with key informants, lasting on average 60 min (ranging from 40 to 105 min) (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="czx132-T2">Table 2</xref>). All interviews were conducted in English. Interviews were also held with informants in malaria and TB programmes to enable comparison of the response to other diseases and assess perceptions of financing for HIV from individuals working outside HIV. Interviews were audio recorded where consent was given (two respondents, one from Ghana and one from Uganda, asked to not be audio recorded) and transcribed. Transcripts were managed and analysed thematically in Dedoose. Coding was initially deductive applying the pre-existing policy frameworks of Dolowitz and Marsh and GHAPP, with additional inductive coding cycles. Qualitative interview data was triangulated with the document review. Results are presented where informants contradicted findings from the document review. Emerging themes and summary findings from each country were reviewed by local study teams and discussed. Findings were shared with key informants in both countries to assess if findings were a fair reflection of the response in their country; enabling further validation of the findings. 
</p>
