<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Systematic studies are of paramount importance to identify virus–host protein–protein interactions (PPIs), since they provide an unbiased view of molecular complexes and therefore insights into viral mechanisms of replication, host resources exploitation and immune evasion strategies [
 <xref rid="B11-viruses-11-00878" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-viruses-11-00878" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-11-00878" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-11-00878" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Applying AP-MS in a systematic and comparative fashion can help elucidate similarities and differences in virus-specific replication strategies and even pathogenesis determinants [
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-11-00878" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-viruses-11-00878" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. A few studies recently reported combined proteomic and gene perturbation approaches integrating complementary methods to investigate the cellular interactome of each of the 10 ZIKV proteins (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00878-f002">Figure 2</xref>a). A discrete number of previously reported bona fide interactors were consistently identified across all these studies, and appear to be shared across different flavivirus members, highlighting the relatively high degree of conservation within the genus and across diverse cellular backgrounds, thereby revealing cellular components critically required for virus replication. However, these studies also revealed specificities, reflecting the different methodologies, cellular backgrounds, enrichment strategies, gene-delivery methods and experimental designs used. For instance, using an AP-LC-MS/MS (affinity purification coupled with liquid chromatography and tandem mass spectrometry) approach in SK-N-BE2 neuroblastoma cells [
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-11-00878" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], we identified in the ZIKV capsid interactome a strong enrichment in nuclear and nucleolar-resident proteins such as nucleolin (NCL), nucleolar RNA-dependent helicases of the DDX family, core histones (H2A), as well as peroxisomal proteins including Pex19, that have been previously reported as cellular targets of Dengue (DENV) and West Nile virus (WNV) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00878-f002">Figure 2</xref>b) [
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-11-00878" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-viruses-11-00878" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-viruses-11-00878" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Interestingly, among the capsid-specific interactors, a completely new set of proteins associating with the ZIKV capsid was identified. Among these, a poorly characterized nucleolar protein involved in cell-growth regulation and maintenance of stem cell identity called LYAR was identified [
 <xref rid="B38-viruses-11-00878" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. LYAR was recently implicated in viral transcription and replication of Influenza A virus (IAV) through interaction with the viral ribonucleoprotein [
 <xref rid="B39-viruses-11-00878" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], indicating a more global role of this protein in virus–host interactions. Additionally, several members of the LARP family (e.g., LARP1 and LARP7) and ZC3HAV1 (also known as ZAP) were identified as specific capsid interactors, suggesting the propensity of ZIKV capsid to interact with RNA-binding proteins. Importantly the functional relevance of some of these ZIKV capsid interactors was underlined by knock-down studies, confirming a strong reduction of viral replication upon gene depletion. In similar studies, Coyaud and collegues [
 <xref rid="B40-viruses-11-00878" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] as well as Shah et al. [
 <xref rid="B41-viruses-11-00878" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] confirmed these observations, identifying NCL, LYAR, LARP1, several members of the DDX family and ZC3HAV1, among the specific ZIKV capsid interactors using BioID- and AP-LC-MS/MS in 293T cells, respectively. Furthermore, recent work by Li et al. reported analogous enrichment for LARP1, LARP7 and ZC3HAV1 in a global proteomic survey for WNV-interacting proteins [
 <xref rid="B42-viruses-11-00878" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Complementary functional experiments validated a conserved role for ZC3HAV1 in restricting flaviviruses since depletion of ZC3HAV1 led to a 4- to 8-fold increase in ZIKV, DENV and WNV virus titers. Interestingly, the antiviral activity of ZC3HAV1 has been investigated for several virus families including human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) and Sindbis virus (SINV) [
 <xref rid="B43-viruses-11-00878" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-viruses-11-00878" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The protein appears to recruit cellular RNA degradation machineries to specific ZAP-responsive elements on the viral mRNAs as well as the DCP1–DCP2 complex to initiate 5′-3′ RNA degradation of viral mRNA. Its activity has been mechanistically studied in the context of Japanese encephalitis virus, whereby ZC3HAV1 has been described to recruit the 3′-5′ degradation machinery [
 <xref rid="B45-viruses-11-00878" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. However, the exact mechanisms of virus restriction by ZC3HAV1 remain to be elucidated.
</p>
