<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">This analysis has several important limitations. The data used to populate the models were the most complete and up to date that could be obtained at the time of analysis. A crucial limitation is our reliance upon estimates of the proportions of individuals requiring hospitalization and ICU access, across different ages, reported by a CDC report based on limited data: in time, these proportions may prove to be overestimates and the calculations we provide seen as overestimates. There are no known estimates of R0 for COVID-19 in a given prison or detention population, so we relied on an analogous population. To account for this imprecision, we modeled three plausible R0 estimates, elevating the likelihood that the system’s actual R0 was modeled within this range. Our estimates of eventual prevalence for a confined population substantially exceed available data from cruise ship and navy ship outbreaks but are very much in line with recent reports from a prison setting. Full analysis of data from confined populations will be an excellent topic for full retrospective analysis. The treatment capacity of local hospitals was calculated using data made public the first week of April, but actual capacity over time will vary depending on the rate at which the virus spreads in the general population, and we may therefore have underestimated need. While data reporting the current number of ICE detainees may differ from those used in this analysis, they lack the facility-level specificity needed to calculate ICU bed demand. For example, news reports indicate that ICE bookings have decreased and summary deportations after attempting to enter the USA have reportedly increased as a result of the COVID-19 pandemic [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. If these data were publicly available at the facility level, our results could be rendered more precise. A dearth of similar studies resulted in the need to approximate key values. The actual age distribution of ICE detainees at each facility is unknown, and we relied on aggregate estimates from 2019 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. We assumed a fixed contact rate over the course of the epidemic; a variable rate may be more appropriate, especially if ongoing studies derive a variable rate specific to the COVID-19 epidemic. Our model included counties in their entirety if any part of them fell within the specified radii of 10 and 50 miles, so it is likely that community health care capacities within these radii are overestimated. We note that our key assumption in determining how many ICE facilities would overwhelm hospital ICU capacity within a 10- and 50-mile radius was that all available ICU beds in these hospitals would be allocated to detainees in need of care. Overall, these assumptions suggest that our findings may have underestimated the number of infections and the number of facilities that will overwhelm the community ICU capacity.
</p>
