<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The structures of MNV (genotype GV.1) and RHDV (genotype GIV) have this “extended” conformation and represent two different genotypes. However, neither infect humans and it was possible that it is a feature not found in the human noroviruses. It was therefore important that the cryo-EM structure of the human Vietnam026 (GII.10) VLP was determined [
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-11-00235" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The cryo-EM reconstruction of the GII.10 norovirus VLP at ~10 Å resolution showed a number of features very similar to MNV and RHDV. The GII.10 S domain was noticeably surface exposed at the three- and five-fold axes. As with MNV and RHDV, the P domain appeared as a second outer shell, and a half-section through the VLP revealed that the P domain was raised off the S domain by ~15 Å. Importantly, these studies also showed that this apparent P domain flexibility may play an important role in antibody binding. They determined the structure of the P domain complexed with the Fab fragment from an antibody (5B18) that broadly recognized a number of different GII viruses. The crystal structure of the P domain/Fab complex [
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-11-00235" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] showed that the 5B18 Fab bound to a conserved region of the protruding domain. This binding site is involved in interactions with other regions of the capsid and partially buried in the virus particle in the “compressed” state where the P domain sits on top of the shell. Despite the occluded nature of the recognized epitope in the VLP structure, ELISA binding indicated that the 5B18 antibody was able to capture intact VLPs. The base of the P domain is only exposed to the antibody if there is extreme flexibility in the tether region between the shell and the P domain. This result has been further substantiated by more recent results in genotypes GI.1 [
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-11-00235" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] and GII.4 [
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-11-00235" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] where various epitopes are clearly buried in the compressed particle and only exposed with if the P domain is allowed to lift off the shell.
</p>
