<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P59">Interferons have been used in treating multiple viral infections and are most commonly used for treating chronic viral hepatitis.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R112">112</xref>
 </sup> Interferon-α was the first drug approved for treatment of compensated liver disease due to CHB; it is not approved for treating acute hepatitis B. For CHB, IFN α-2a or α-2b is given parenterally, depending on dosing schedule, for 4 to 6 months or up to 48 weeks.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R112">112</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R113">113</xref>
 </sup> Interferon was most effective in patients with recently acquired hepatitis B virus (HBV), high pretreatment levels of alanine aminotransferase (ALT), and low levels of HBV DNA. Subcutaneous peginterferon-α is as effective or slightly more effective than SC IFN-α.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R114">114</xref>
 </sup> Likewise, SC peginterferon-α may be more effective than lamivudine in hepatitis B e antigen (HBeAg)–positive and HBeAg-negative patients with CHB,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R115">115</xref>-
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R117">117</xref>
 </sup> and the addition of lamivudine to peginterferon-α did not significantly enhance efficacy.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R118">118</xref>
 </sup> Interferon-α is effective in patients with HBV and hepatitis D virus coinfection,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R119">119</xref>
 </sup> although they are less responsive than patients infected with HBV alone.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R120">120</xref>
 </sup> Guidelines for the management of CHB in HIV-infected patients were recently published
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R121">121</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R122">122</xref>
 </sup>; for patients not requiring anti-HIV therapy, peginterferon-α for 12 months is considered a therapeutic option. Lamivudine and the other antiviral nucleos(t)ides for the treatment of HBV often have anti-HIV properties and may result in the development of HIV resistance if given as monotherapy in HBV-HIV coinfected patients.
</p>
