<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0005">
 <label>Table 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Anxiety related to COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text id="at0020">Table 1</alt-text>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th align="left">Sl.</th>
    <th align="left">Items</th>
    <th align="left">% of responses who feel anxious (often and always) (N = 662)</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">1</td>
    <td align="left">From the last week, how often do you think about Novel Coronavirus Pandemic?</td>
    <td align="left">82.2</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">2</td>
    <td align="left">From the last one week, how often you feel paranoid about contacting the novel Corona Virus infection?</td>
    <td align="left">37.8 %</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">3</td>
    <td align="left">From the last week, how often you avoid partying?</td>
    <td align="left">90.1</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">4</td>
    <td align="left">From the last week, how often you avoid social contact?</td>
    <td align="left">82.1</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">5</td>
    <td align="left">From the last week, how often you avoid large meetings and gatherings?</td>
    <td align="left">89.1</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">6</td>
    <td align="left">From the last week, how often you avoid ordering food online?</td>
    <td align="left">76.7</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">7</td>
    <td align="left">From the last week, how often you have talked to your friends about the corona Pandemic?</td>
    <td align="left">80.7</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">8</td>
    <td align="left">From the last one week, how often you have had difficulty sleeping by being worried about the Coronavirus pandemic?</td>
    <td align="left">12.5</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">9</td>
    <td align="left">From the last week, how often you feel affected by the posts on social media about corona Virus infection?</td>
    <td align="left">36.4</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">10</td>
    <td align="left">From the last week, how often do you feel affected by the talks of Novel Corona Virus Pandemic on the newspaper and news channels?</td>
    <td align="left">46.1</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">11</td>
    <td align="left">From the last week, how often do you feel the need to buy and stock all essentials at home?</td>
    <td align="left">31.7</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">12</td>
    <td align="left">From the last week, how often do you get afraid if anyone in your social circle reports of being sick?</td>
    <td align="left">41.3</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">13</td>
    <td align="left">From the last week, how often do you feel the need to use the sanitizer/gloves?</td>
    <td align="left">77.4</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">14</td>
    <td align="left">From the last week, how often do feel the need to constantly wash your hands?</td>
    <td align="left">84.5</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">15</td>
    <td align="left">From the last one week, how often do you feel worried about yourself, and close ones regarding the spread of Novel COVID19 Viral Infection?</td>
    <td align="left">72</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">16</td>
    <td align="left">From the last week, how often do you use a mask without any apparent signs and symptoms of the infection?</td>
    <td align="left">36.6</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">17</td>
    <td align="left">From the last week, how often does the Idea of Novel Corona Viral Infection freak you out leading to inappropriate behaviours with anyone?</td>
    <td align="left">30.5 %</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">18</td>
    <td align="left">From the last week, how often does the Idea of Novel Corona Viral Infection freak you out post on social media?</td>
    <td align="left">44.7 %</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
