<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fn-group>
 <fn id="FN1">
  <label>*</label>
  <p>Data reported as of October 4, 2019.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="FN2">
  <label>†</label>
  <p>The CDC influenza surveillance system collects five categories of information from eight data sources: 1) viral surveillance (U.S. World Health Organization collaborating laboratories, the National Respiratory and Enteric Virus Surveillance System, and novel influenza A virus case reporting); 2) outpatient illness surveillance (U.S. Outpatient Influenza-Like Illness Surveillance Network); 3) mortality (the National Center for Health Statistics Mortality Surveillance System and influenza-associated pediatric mortality reports); 4) hospitalizations (FluSurv-NET, which includes the Emerging Infections Program and surveillance in three additional states); and 5) summary of the geographic spread of influenza (state and territorial epidemiologist reports). 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/flu/weekly/fluactivitysurv.htm" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.cdc.gov/flu/weekly/fluactivitysurv.htm</ext-link>.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="FN3">
  <label>§</label>
  <p>Influenza viruses that circulate in swine are called swine influenza viruses when isolated from swine but are called variant influenza viruses when isolated from humans. Seasonal influenza viruses that circulate worldwide in the human population have important antigenic and genetic differences form influenza viruses circulating in swine. 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/flu/swineflu/variant/preventspreadfactsheet.htm" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.cdc.gov/flu/swineflu/variant/preventspreadfactsheet.htm</ext-link>.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="FN4">
  <label>¶</label>
  <p>In temperate climates, the onset and peak of influenza activity might vary substantially from one influenza season to the next, but generally begins to increase in the late fall. In the Northern Hemisphere’s temperate regions, annual epidemics of influenza typically occur during October–February, but the peak of influenza activity can occur as late as April or May. In temperate regions of the Southern Hemisphere, influenza activity typically peaks during May–August. Although temperate regions of the world experience a seasonal peak in influenza activity, influenza viruses can be isolated year-round. The timing of seasonal peaks in influenza activity in tropical and subtropical countries varies by region. Multiple peaks of activity during the same year have been observed in some areas, and influenza infection can occur year-round.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="FN5">
  <label>**</label>
  <p>A virus is considered similar to a vaccine virus if it is well inhibited by ferret antisera raised against the cell culture– or egg culture–propagated reference virus representing the appropriate vaccine component for the specified season and hemisphere. The 2019–20 Northern Hemisphere vaccine components were A(H1N1)pdm09 subtype, A/Brisbane/02/2018-like (genetic group 6B.1A); A(H3N2) subtype, A/Kansas/14/2017-like (genetic group 3C.3a); B/Yamagata lineage, B/Phuket/3073/2013-like; and B/Victoria lineage, B/Colorado/06/2017-like (V1A.1) viruses.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="FN6">
  <label>††</label>
  <p>
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/influenza/vaccines/virus/recommendations/2020_south/en/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.who.int/influenza/vaccines/virus/recommendations/2020_south/en/</ext-link>. 
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="FN7">
  <label>§§</label>
  <p>Persons at high risk include 1) children aged &lt;5 years; 2) adults aged ≥65 years; 3) persons with chronic pulmonary conditions (including asthma), cardiovascular disease (except hypertension alone), renal, hepatic, hematologic (including sickle cell) disease, metabolic disorders (including diabetes mellitus), or neurologic and neurodevelopmental conditions (including disorders of the brain, spinal cord, peripheral nerves, and muscles, such as cerebral palsy, epilepsy [seizure disorders], stroke, intellectual disability [mental retardation], moderate to severe developmental delay, muscular dystrophy, or spinal cord injury); 4) persons with immunosuppression, including that caused by medications or by human immunodeficiency virus infection; 5) women who are pregnant or postpartum (within 2 weeks after delivery); 6) persons aged ≤18 years who are receiving long-term aspirin therapy; 7) American Indians/Alaska Natives; 8) persons with extreme obesity (i.e., body mass index ≥40); and 9) residents of nursing homes and other chronic care facilities.</p>
 </fn>
</fn-group>
