<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">Viewing COVID-19 with a Critical Medical Ecological lens suggests three important interpretations: 1) COVID-19 is equally — if not more — a socially-driven disease as much as a biomedical disease, 2) the present interventions available for primary prevention of transmission are social and behavioral interventions, and 3) power dynamics and political relationships well beyond the level of the individual likely determine, at least in part, the risk that a person will become infected. Human sociocultural factors (e.g., consumption of pangolins, travel exposures, face-to-face interaction) and socially-involved predisposing conditions (hypertension, diabetes, smoking) provide a platform for this virus to spread. Many — if not most — deadly viruses circulating throughout the world arose from the human-animal interface, challenging agricultural and dietary practice, disease effects of modernity, and culture. Class privilege contributes to some groups willfully disregarding social-physical distancing orders while disadvantaging others who serve them in restaurants, stores, and delivery services. The healthcare workforce at the forefront of caring for those infected are at-risk for contracting SARS-CoV-2 because of shortages of personal protective equipment (attributable to differential access to supply chain by many actors) as are workers considered “essential” throughout the service industy similarly without access to protective gear [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Patients are differentially disadvantaged by lack of universal screening and testing policies and the supply chain of tests to support them, combined with unequal access to equipment to treat the most serious cases. Supply chains across the spectrum of testing and treatment are subject to competition and privileged access depending on political and economic relationships. Cities especially are challenged due to logistics and volume of patients, and lack of access to sustaining products and services for many residents living in isolation. What happens to people is largely a function of who and where they are. Wide variation in hospitalization rates and death rates from COVID-19 are not expected to be attributable significantly to a more virulent and rapidly-evolving virus, but to social and behavioral factors — and power dynamics — rather than (solely) biological and clinical factors. In the end, SARS-CoV-2 is acting upon dynamic social human beings, entangled within structures and relationships that include but extend far beyond their cells, and in fact beyond their own individual behavior. As a comprehensive way of thinking, the Critical Medical Ecology model helps identify these elements and intersections in the context of ecological processes that create, shape, and sustain people in their multidimensional, intersecting environments.
</p>
