<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In contrast, we observed that drought conditions, as determined by the SPI-6, were associated with dengue risk over longer periods of time (5-month lag). Barbados is among the 10 most water-scarce countries in the world [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002613.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], and water scarcity is exacerbated during periods of drought. Drought is a slow-onset climate hazard. The depletion of surface water reservoirs occurs over 6 or more months, and the depletion of groundwater reservoirs occurs at 9- to 12-month time scales. As households are alerted to water scarcity, they take measures to store water in containers around the home, increasing the availability of larval habitat for 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic>. As a result, we hypothesise that household water storage during drought periods may increase the risk of dengue transmission. Alternatively, we hypothesise that the increase in containers in the environment during drought may increase the risk of dengue transmission months later, when the rainy season begins and water storage is no longer a necessity. Prolonged drought could result in changes in human behaviour associated with water storage, habits that could extend beyond the period of water scarcity. In our experience, water storage containers become a greater hazard for dengue when they are not used and maintained regularly and instead serve as a ‘backup’ water source [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002613.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. When a drought is followed by heavy rainfall, the risk of dengue could increase, as observed in 2010–2011, a year of exceptionally high dengue transmission across the Americas and an El Niño event. That year, DENV serotypes 1 and 4 were re-introduced after no circulation for several years, and an outbreak occurred with all 4 serotypes in cocirculation (2,000 suspected cases, 575 confirmed cases in Barbados) [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002613.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].
</p>
