<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In Barbados, over the last 5 years, there have been 3 outbreaks of dengue fever (2013–2014, 2014–2015, and 2015–2016), 1 outbreak of chikungunya virus (2014–2015), and 1 outbreak of Zika virus (2015–2016). Better management of arboviruses is a high priority for Caribbean SIDS given the burden of 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic>–transmitted arboviruses in the region, suitable climatic conditions for vector proliferation, and susceptible human populations, as well as the potential for transmission via widespread intra- and extraregional travel in the Caribbean [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002613.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. To address this need, the CIMH—as part of its implementation of a regional multisectoral Early Warning Information Systems Across Climate Timescales (EWISACTs) programme—has partnered with the Caribbean Public Health Agency (CARPHA), national Ministries of Health, National Meteorological and Hydrological Services, and an international research team to support the development of regional arbovirus forecast models using climate information. This programme aims to codesign, codevelop, and codeliver sector-driven climate early warning information. One avenue for communicating warnings of dengue risk is through the Caribbean Health-Climatic Bulletin, a new joint quarterly bulletin of the CARPHA, the Pan-American Health Organization, and the CIMH [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002613.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. The bulletin offers consensus-based expert statements of probable health outcomes extrapolated from a review of the CIMH’s suite of monitoring and forecast products contextualised to the Caribbean health context up to 3 to 6 months in advance. Integration of quantitative probabilistic forecasts of dengue risk generated by the modelling framework described in this paper represents a significant emerging research-to-operations advance that has the potential to respond to the health community’s need for empirical risk estimates for periods of operational relevance to public health. Quantitative probabilistic forecasts of disease risk will enhance the quality of warning information and provide improved guidance for decision-making.
</p>
