<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">The findings of this review have important inference for clinical practice, researchers, and health policies for the continent. To date, there is no effective antiviral treatment for dengue fever
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>. With the high prevalence we found, especially among patients presenting with fever, implementation of routine diagnostic for people living in endemic areas or for people presenting fever with history of a travel in dengue endemic area may be explored
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup>. This can be motivated by the fact that, proper medical management of early detected can lower fatality rates below 1% and there is no specific treatment against DENV infection
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>. It would be also interesting to explore the implementation of routine diagnostic of DENV infection in endemic countries with the aim to make differential diagnosis with other infectious diseases (like malaria) with close clinical presentation. However, for endemic areas with most of them locating in developing countries like in Africa, it will be difficult to implement routine diagnostic of DENV infection at a large scale as most of countries have weak health systems with low funding. Our findings call for cost-effective strategies to curb the burden DENV infection in Africa since severe dengue fever can rapidly lead to serious illness and death, especially among children
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>. To date, the efficacy of dengue vaccine has been accessed in eleven countries with immune response of 59% of vaccinated people
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>, suggesting that high quality studies are needed to have highly effective vaccine and antiretroviral treatment to rapidly curb the burden of dengue fever in Africa. Another approach for curbing the burden of dengue fever is vector control. For curbing the burden of vector-borne disease, WHO suggests an integrated vector control. This vector control should be environmentally safe when using insecticides for the elimination of mosquitoes Laval from their artificial and natural habitats. This is to ensure the protection of individuals, communities, and households in an ecological context to be effective and efficient
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
