<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>EEEV is a zoonotic virus transmitted by mosquitoes and originating in birds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. In North America, EEEV is an important cause of disease in domestic animals and humans. The disease is severe in horses, pigs, dogs, and some species of birds. EEEV was first isolated in 1933 from the brains of affected horses during a widespread outbreak in the northeastern US, in New Jersey and Virginia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. However, horse deaths have recently been reported further north along the eastern coast of the US (New Hampshire and Maine) and Canada. In 1936, South American EEEV was first isolated from a horse in Argentina [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. The EEEV strains present in South and North America are antigenically and genetically different from each other and also differ in human pathogenicity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. There are four lineages (I, II, III, and IV) of EEEV based on their antigenicity and distribution in various geographic regions (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. The closely related North American EEEV (NA-EEEV) lineage I viruses that occur in the US, Canada and the Caribbean are the most virulent to horses and humans. In contrast, infection of horses or humans with more genetically and antigenically diverse virus strain, enzootic in Central and South America (lineages II, III, and IV [SA-EEEV]), rarely results in significant clinical disease. The lineage II strains are distributed along the coasts of South and Central America, lineage III in the Amazon Basin, and lineage IV in Brazil [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>].
</p>
