<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The basic reproductive number, 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub>, the average number of secondary cases caused by a single infection in a totally susceptible population, justifiably dominates any discussion of infectious disease epidemiology [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. If 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> &lt; 1, there will certainly not be a major outbreak [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. When 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> is above this threshold, however, major outbreaks can but do not always occur [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In large populations, the distribution of epidemic sizes is bimodal when 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> &gt; 1, and either the disease dies out with very few ever becoming infected, or it becomes widespread [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1004836.s001">S1 Fig</xref>). A major outbreak can therefore naturally be defined as one where the disease becomes widespread, i.e. the total number of hosts that ever become infected lies in the part of the distribution of possible final sizes that contains the larger mode. A well-known approximation to the probability of a major outbreak in a large population can be derived from simple stochastic epidemiological models, 
 <disp-formula id="pcbi.1004836.e001">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1004836.e001.jpg" id="pcbi.1004836.e001g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M1">
    <mrow>
     <mtext>Prob</mtext>
     <mrow>
      <mo>(</mo>
      <mrow>
       <mtext>Major outbreak</mtext>
      </mrow>
      <mo>)</mo>
     </mrow>
     <mtext> </mtext>
     <mo>≈</mo>
     <mtext> </mtext>
     <mn>1</mn>
     <mo>−</mo>
     <msup>
      <mrow>
       <mrow>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mrow>
         <mfrac>
          <mn>1</mn>
          <mrow>
           <msub>
            <mi>R</mi>
            <mn>0</mn>
           </msub>
          </mrow>
         </mfrac>
        </mrow>
        <mo>)</mo>
       </mrow>
      </mrow>
      <mrow>
       <mi>I</mi>
       <mo>*</mo>
      </mrow>
     </msup>
     <mo>,</mo>
    </mrow>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </disp-formula> where 
 <italic>I*</italic> is the number that are infected at the time of estimation [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. This estimate is widespread in the theoretical epidemiology literature particularly in the case where disease first arrives in the system and so 
 <italic>I*</italic> = 1 [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. We note that this formula has also been used in the context of the spread of the recent Ebola outbreak to Nigeria, to estimate the chance that a single undetected infected case will spark a major outbreak [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. More sophisticated approximations to the probability of a major outbreak can be derived for models containing additional epidemiological detail, for example population structure [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], more refined models of individuals’ infectious periods [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], and differences in infectivity between individuals [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Crucially, however, the approximation above illustrates that estimates of the probability of a major outbreak require knowledge not only of the values of disease transmission parameters, but also of the total number of currently infected hosts, 
 <italic>I*</italic>. This includes those individuals that have not yet developed symptoms. Modelers have concentrated on developing increasingly elaborate statistical machinery to estimate the parameters that constitute 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Other work, most notably back-calculation [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], focuses on estimating the number of individuals that are currently infected, accounting for delays before symptoms emerge. What has never been examined, however, is how the lack of knowledge of precisely how many are infected in the early stages of a potential major outbreak affects predictability of whether or not a large epidemic will in fact go on to occur. In practice, epidemic forecasts for specific pathogens are typically conducted via simulation [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1004836.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Consequently, we conduct a simulation-based study into the impact of presymptomatic infection—which the formula from the theoretical epidemiology literature suggests might disrupt forecasting—on predictions of major epidemics.
</p>
