<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Contrasting with classical KD, systemic inflammation following SARS-COV-2 infection affects older children and teenagers. Other intriguing findings are that patients with severe forms are less commonly Caucasians than the expected frequency in their general population (many of African-American or Afro-Caribbean ethnicity). In addition, such cases were not reported in Korea and Japan; these populations have the highest incidence of KD and SARS-COV-2 pandemic has been present in these areas as well; hence, a genetic background for these severe cases is likely. Regarding the clinical feature, most reported cases do not meet the AHA’s case definition for KD or in a minority of cases present only as incomplete forms. 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17 18</xref>
 </sup> Myocardial involvement is a hallmark of this hyper-inflammatory state, whereas coronary aneurysms are the hallmark of KD. Intravenous immunoglobulins (IVIG), which are also given frequently in other causes of myocarditis anyway, were apparently effective in those patients. Indeed, the immunomodulatory properties IVIG are not specific but result in strong anti-inflammatory effect. Therefore, we think that despite some similarities, there are epidemiological, clinical and laboratory evidences that support the concept of a new syndrome separated from KD. We find it quite important at least in the present time since the name Kawasaki has generated confusion in the media and the public, and patients and families who have suffered from this condition in the past require reassurance. Moreover, the general population is now aware that SARS-COV-2 can cause damage to the vessels of children, and it is crucial to emphasise that up to now the virus has minimal morbidity and exceptional mortality in the pediatric age. For cases with inflammatory multisystem syndrome, the European Centers for Disease Prevention and Control has stated that overall risk in the EU/EEA and the UK is considered low, based on a very low probability of PIMS in children and a high impact of such condition.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
