<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>These findings should be interpreted within this study’s limitations. First, the influenza vaccine UTD variable does not capture vaccinations after December 31
 <sup>st</sup> or through the date of the interview (first dose), or after January 31st (second dose), [
 <xref rid="pone.0234466.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] though influenza vaccine distribution is usually complete before these dates, [
 <xref rid="pone.0234466.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>] meaning that this limitation is minor. Further, the provider-verified nature of the NIS complete vaccination outcome improves on the typical annual self-reported measure of influenza vaccination, which is subject to recall bias and only covers one influenza season. Second, this study excludes children without provider-verified data, who may lack this type of data because they lack a usual source of care, which has been linked to lower preventive care use in adults. [
 <xref rid="pone.0234466.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>] However, because those excluded may use less preventive services, the implication is that our findings contain less vulnerable individuals and are likely thus conservative. Third, accounting for successive non-response first from households, then providers, and then the PC module, more than half of target children are lost due to NIS non-response issues, introducing concerns of non-response bias. This is a limitation of the data source itself that warrants investigation and needs to be addressed in future surveys. Nonetheless, the NIS still provides the only opportunity to examine nationally-representative, provider-verified uptake of multiple vaccines in young children that includes key constructs for vaccine-related parental perceptions. Fourth, the parental concerns variables refer to vaccination generally and not to any one specific vaccine, which could explain some of the non-findings (such as parent perception of physician recommendation for vaccination not being associated with our outcomes, contradicting other studies [
 <xref rid="pone.0234466.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0234466.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0234466.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0234466.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0234466.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0234466.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]). Fifth, this analysis is cross-sectional and thus cannot make causative claims; all findings are associative. That said, the main identifying strategies were to use only provider-verified vaccine outcomes and to include in one model a myriad of conceptually- and empirically-grounded covariates more comprehensive than in other literature, most notably the aforementioned constructs for vaccine-related parental perceptions which have seldom been utilized due to their limited availability and the restricted access required to obtain them. Though we cannot rule out the possibility of bi-directionality in our findings, we believe this to be less likely as the determinants studied here are thought to temporally precede the decision to use a health service. [
 <xref rid="pone.0234466.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] For example, predisposing (child’s race/ethnicity) and enabling factors (mother’s education) precede personal health services use factors at the behavior level (history of vaccine refusal or delay), all of which precede health services utilization (vaccine uptake).
</p>
