<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Analogous to the impact of the antibiotic era in enabling rapid and significant improvements in human health, the potential of antimicrobial surfaces to help control future outbreaks of infectious disease is enormous. However, just as the antibiotic era has been marred by antibiotic-resistant infections arising from overenthusiastic antibiotic use, it is important that we exert caution in introducing antimicrobial surfaces, and ensure that their use is appropriate. Whilst the benefits of antimicrobial surfaces in high-traffic and high-risk areas, such as transport hubs and healthcare facilities, may seem obvious, it must be borne in mind that exposure to microorganisms from the environment is crucial for microbiome development which, in turn, is needed for proper immune function. Given this knowledge, it would seem appropriate that a system of stewardship is established, at least for clinical application of antimicrobial surfaces, comparable to that recommended for traditional antimicrobials by the National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE) [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008880.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. This system would ensure selection of the most appropriate antimicrobial mechanism, appropriate location, efficacy, durability, stakeholder education, and end-user acceptance. It would also be prudent to consider that introducing antimicrobial surfaces into the healthcare setting may have unpredictable adverse effects. Firstly, regular contact could affect the skin microbiome of the hands of healthcare workers. Products of the normal skin flora—including fatty acids—can be bactericidal and reduce the survival of ‘transient’ opportunist pathogens that may be inadvertently passed between patients on the hands of healthcare workers. Ablation of this skin microbiota may, theoretically, result in persistent colonisation of hands with an abnormal flora. Secondly, surfaces with allergenic potential could result in dermatitis with implications for healthcare workers’ health and practices. Skin affected by dermatitis is prone to colonisation by 
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>aureus</italic>, an important overt healthcare pathogen. Thirdly, an overreliance on antimicrobial surfaces may induce a false sense of security in the healthcare setting; it is essential that standard hand hygiene practices are maintained. These and other considerations should be addressed in a programme of stewardship.
</p>
