<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We have seen that if the fitness losses that hamper RNA viruses 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> also affect an influenza virus escaping host immunity, drift speed can be affected. Not only does the relative fitness of the virus, 
 <italic>χ</italic>, influence the rate of antigenic escape, there is a feedback between the evolutionary and epidemic processes, with susceptibility and transmission at the population level deciding the impact 
 <italic>χ</italic> has, and vice versa. As seen in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSPB20111168F3">figure 3</xref>, under fitness constraints, 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> can become disproportionately important in dictating dynamics. This implies that two strains with identical antigenic space and mutation rates could evolve at very different rates with only a marginal difference in 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub>, unlike that required by the deterministic model of Gog &amp; Grenfell [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20111168C16">16</xref>]. This is illustrated by the drop-off we see between regions of high and low rates of emergence. We have shown that its location can be estimated from the probability that a strain emerges in a branching process; the theoretical prediction coincides well with the simulated results. It also explains the switch between the two stable patterns (locked and drifting) observed by Gog [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20111168C19">19</xref>]. As 
 <italic>χ</italic> decreases, the probability of switching from a drifting to a locked (or extinct) state becomes much larger, as emergence gets rarer. The drop-off in the overall rate of emergence reflects this reduction in tendency to drift. Further, the existence of such a ‘drift cliff’ between regions of high and low rates of emergence may affect the impact of antivirals, which have been known to reduce the infectious period (and hence the 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub>) of influenza [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20111168C41">41</xref>].
</p>
