<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the North Sea and NE Atlantic Ocean, the first cetacean morbillivirus mortalities were detected in 
 <italic>P. phocoena</italic> stranded along the coasts of Ireland, England and the Netherlands in 1988–1990 [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Sporadic morbillivirus infections were further observed in 
 <italic>L. albirostris</italic> and fin whales (
 <italic>Balaenoptera physalus</italic>) beached in Northern Europe in 1990–2011 [
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B126-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. Serological surveys of stranded 
 <italic>D. delphis</italic> and 
 <italic>P. phocoena</italic> in the UK and the Netherlands in 1988–1999 showed that prevalence of DMV-seropositivity was declining over time and that only adult porpoises and dolphins were positive in 1997–1999. This suggested that the virus had not persisted as an endemic infection in these populations [
 <xref rid="B61-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Similarly, with the exception of a 
 <italic>P. phocoena</italic> with systemic morbillivirus infection beached in Kent, UK, in late 1990, systemic morbilliviral disease was not detected in any porpoise that stranded along the coasts of Belgium, northern France, England and Germany in 1990–2000 [
 <xref rid="B132-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>,
 <xref rid="B133-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>,
 <xref rid="B134-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>,
 <xref rid="B135-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>]. Though the number of 
 <italic>P. phocoena</italic> in the North Sea and adjacent waters was theoretically large enough to sustain an endemic infection (341,366 individual [95% confidence interval = 260,000–449,000] in 1994 [
 <xref rid="B136-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>]), their solitary behavior likely did not favor morbillivirus transmission and maintenance in this population. The presence of high titers of DMV antibodies in the serum of a juvenile 
 <italic>G. melas</italic> collected in the English Channel in 1996 suggested that this species could be involved in the maintenance of the virus in the NE Atlantic [
 <xref rid="B61-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. However, further serological surveys and molecular investigations are needed to understand the ecology of CeMV in this ocean basin.
</p>
