<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par36">Defensins have been confirmed to be effective to resist pathogens. Chen et al. argued that higher expression levels of PBD-2 and other β-defensins in Meishan pigs than those in crossbred pigs conferred stronger immunity of Meishan pigs against diseases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Our previous study revealed that PBD-2 overexpressing pigs and PBD-2 TG mice showed enhanced resistance to bacterial infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. In this study, we further verified that PBD-2 TG mice displayed increased resistance to viral infection. Thus, PBD-2 can be a useful target to generate disease-resistant animals against both bacterial and viral infections. PRV is an important pig pathogen which is still present in China, Japan, USA and some European countries [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. The inhibitory effect of PBD-2 in vitro and in vivo discovered in this study provided possible new strategies to control PRV, such as overexpressing PBD-2 in pig tissues. In transgenic mice infected with PRV, PBD-2 could reduce viral loads and alleviated tissue lesions at different degrees in different tissues (Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Our previous study has discovered that PBD-2 expression level in organs differed in TG mice [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], which suggests a correlation between PBD-2 expression level and its anti-PRV effect in different organs. It is worth noting that PRV loads of brain tissues (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) were the highest and damages of brain tissues were the severest (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) either in TG mice or in WT mice, confirming that PRV had a distinct tissue tropism [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Herein, increasing PBD-2 expression in animals, especially in brains, using gene-editing techniques might promote the resistance of animals to PRV in vivo.
</p>
