<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Indirect ELISAs were developed to analyze hemolyzed serum samples that could be cytotoxic and, as such, could prevent the detection of morbillivirus antibodies at low dilutions in virus neutralization tests [
 <xref rid="B61-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. These assays used whole DMV [
 <xref rid="B61-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] or the recombinant N protein of RPV [
 <xref rid="B75-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] to detect morbillivirus antibodies. Cetacean antibodies were detected using horseradish-peroxidase-conjugated protein A, a cell wall constituent of 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> that binds non-specifically the immunoglobulins of several species of vertebrates including odontocetes [
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B76-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. Recently, purified DMV-N protein expressed from a baculovirus (
 <italic>Autographa californica nuclear polyhedrosis virus</italic>) vector was used as the coating antigen in the iELISA and permitted the detection of morbillivirus antibodies in the sera of odontocetes [
 <xref rid="B77-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. The iELISA appears to be more sensitive than the classical VN test and may be useful as a serological tool for the mass screening of morbillivirus antibodies in cetaceans. A competitive ELISA using MoAbs to CDV and PDV was developed for testing sera from various species of marine mammals. Its main advantage over iELISAs is that a single anti-mouse immunoglobulin conjugate can be used on serum from any animal species [
 <xref rid="B74-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. However, sensitivity was lower for detection of cetacean compared to carnivore morbilliviruses [
 <xref rid="B74-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>].
</p>
