<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para310">Previous reviews are limited in that they either have not provided any evidence from COVID-19 or did not use direct evidence from other related emerging epidemic betacoronaviruses (eg, SARS and MERS) to inform the effects of interventions to curtail the current COVID-19 pandemic.
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref> Previous data from randomised trials are mainly for common respiratory viruses such as seasonal influenza, with a systematic review concluding low certainty of evidence for extrapolating these findings to COVID-19.
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref> Further, previous syntheses of available randomised controlled trials have not accounted for cluster effects in analyses, leading to substantial imprecision in treatment effect estimates. In between-study and within-study comparisons, we noted a larger effect of N95 or similar respirators compared with other masks. This finding is inconsistent with conclusions of a review of four randomised trials,
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref> in which low certainty of evidence for no larger effect was suggested. However, in that review, the CIs were wide so a meaningful protective effect could not be excluded. We harmonised these findings with Bayesian approaches, using indirect data from randomised trials to inform posterior estimates. Despite this step, our findings continued to support the ideas not only that masks in general are associated with a large reduction in risk of infection from SARS-CoV-2, SARS-CoV, and MERS-CoV but also that N95 or similar respirators might be associated with a larger degree of protection from viral infection than disposable medical masks or reusable multilayer (12–16-layer) cotton masks. Nevertheless, in view of the limitations of these data, we did not rate the certainty of effect as high.
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref> Our findings accord with those of a cluster randomised trial showing a potential benefit of continuous N95 respirator use over medical masks against seasonal viral infections.
 <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>79</sup>
 </xref> Further high-quality research, including randomised trials of the optimum physical distance and the effectiveness of different types of masks in the general population and for health-care workers' protection, is urgently needed. Two trials are registered to better inform the optimum use of face masks for COVID-19 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04296643" id="interrefs30" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04296643</ext-link> [n=576] and 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04337541" id="interrefs40" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04337541</ext-link> [n=6000]). Until such data are available, our findings represent the current best estimates to inform face mask use to reduce infection from COVID-19. We recognise that there are strong, perhaps opposing, sentiments about policy making during outbreaks. In one viewpoint, the 2007 SARS Commission report stated:
</p>
