<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par82">COVID-19 has disrupted the lives of people worldwide in an eerily similar fashion. The virus originated in Wuhan, China with the first case documented in December 2019. After only a few months, the virus began spreading worldwide. By March, COVID-19 was declared a pandemic by the World Health Organization (WHO). Many schools and universities shut down beginning in the middle of March and transitioned into virtual classes taken online at home. Adults have also been quarantined at their homes with jobs and businesses shutting down around the same time as schools in March with an exception to essential workers such as healthcare workers and grocery store workers. Having individuals stay home largely limits the number of people gathering in public. These measures, more commonly known to the public as social distancing, are implemented to reduce the number of interactions between individuals. This prevents individuals who are infected with the virus but have not been diagnosed with COVID-19 or are asymptomatic to interact with healthy individuals. COVID-19 is transmitted by one individual to another when in close proximity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]. Social distancing aims to reduce transmission of the virus by physically separating individuals. This includes the closure of office buildings, a ban on large public gatherings, and the separation of individuals in public [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]. Guidelines created by the CDC recommend that people avoid any close contact with individuals who are sick and maintain 6 feet of distance from others. Another method used to prevent the spread of COVID-19 is isolation. Patients who are diagnosed with COVID-19 or are suspected to have been exposed are isolated in hospitals to prevent the transmission of the disease to non-infected individuals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]. Patients are typically isolated for the full duration of the virus’s incubation period to ensure that they are no longer infected when leaving isolation. Isolation can occur individually or in groups. Individuals have also started to self-isolate themselves at their own homes. When individuals begin to feel ill, they refrain from any public activity such as their job and will isolate themselves at home. Individuals also practice this when they have been exposed to another individual who has COVID-19 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]. The CDC also recommends avoiding any mass gatherings and crowded areas and covering the mouth and nose with a mask or face cover when around others.
</p>
