<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">Exosomes are gaining attention as a rising star due to their multifaceted role from therapeutics to drug delivery vehicles and diagnostics. However, despite these advantages, there are only a handful of clinical studies available using these nano-vesicles (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). This is due to several challenges associated with exosomes, thereby requiring further investigations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]. One of the major challenges that need to be addressed is to maintain their stability and functionality over a period of time [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]. Unlike MSCs, exosomes are much more stable and viable at −80 °C for a longer period of time. However, after storage, the freeze-thaw cycles result in the exosome clustering. Furthermore, maintaining low temperature during handling and transportation also causes hindrance in their translational application [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>]. Thus, alternative strategies for their storage needs to be evaluated to improve their stability and transportation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]. To overcome these challenges, several studies have evaluated the applicability of freeze-dried exosomes to preserve them at room temperature. Freeze drying formulations are one of the most reliable methodologies for highly unstable molecules like proteins, nucleic acids, etc. This enhances their practicality by increasing shelf life, lowering storage demands, reducing costs by curtailing cold chain maintenance during transportation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>]. However, clumping of exosomes and degradation of their cargo might be a problem during the freeze-drying process. This can be overcome by adding various stabilizers like sucrose, trehalose, glucose, etc. which aid by replacing the hydration sphere around the exosomes during the freeze-drying process, thus preventing their aggregation and maintaining their membrane integrity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>]. Keeping the aforementioned challenges and applicability of the freeze-dried method in mind, we compared the freeze-dried formulation of exosomes with that of non-freeze-dried formulation. We chose Wharton’s Jelly derived MSCs as a source for exosomes owing to their high immuno-modulatory properties and applicability in COVID-19 like situations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>]. We presented that the freeze-dried formulation maintained the exosome integrity as evident by their size, morphology, and specific surface marker expression (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>; unpublished data). Furthermore, functional assessment of these exosomes at day7 showed freeze-dried exosomes faring better than the non-freeze-dried exosomes (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>; unpublished data). Thus, demonstrating the advantage of this methodology in enhancing the availability and applicability of exosomes. These results further validate the fundamental basis for exosome application in biomedical research.
</p>
