<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <title>Acknowledgements</title>
 <p>The 
  <italic>Max</italic>ART Consortium would like to thank the health workers and community members in Swaziland for their participation in and support of the implementation of the 
  <italic>Max</italic>ART EAAA trial.
 </p>
 <sec id="FPar6">
  <title>Funding</title>
  <p id="Par85">We are grateful for the support of the Dutch Postcode Lottery in the Netherlands, the Embassy of the Kingdom of the Netherlands in South Africa/Mozambique, British Columbia Centre of Excellence in Canada, Mylan, and Médecins Sans Frontières. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar7">
  <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
  <p id="Par86">The trial data will be shared with the Swaziland National Health Research Board, which has a process in place for managing public requests for access to the full protocol, participant-level anonymized dataset, and the statistical code.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar8">
  <title>Trial oversight</title>
  <p id="Par87">The Primary Research Team (PRT) comprises the Principal Investigator and Co-Investigators and is responsible for the conduct of the trial and its ethical compliance. The PRT serves as the main decision body for all scientific and administrative issues to ensure the correct implementation of the study protocol.</p>
  <p id="Par88">A Community Advisory Board has been established for communities to protect community interests, including providing substantive input into all aspects of this trial in accordance with community values, culture, and social practices. An independent Data and Safety Monitoring Board (DSMB) has been established to periodically review and evaluate the accumulated study data for participant safety, study conduct and progress, and make recommendations to the 
   <italic>Max</italic>ART research team on the continuation, modification, or termination of the study. In addition, the trial team will also notify DSMB of all protocol violations and deviations for review.
  </p>
  <p id="Par89">The objective of this study is to inform the policy decisions of the Government of the Kingdom of Swaziland, and therefore the main priority at the completion of the study will be to prepare the final results for policymakers’ review. To support broader dissemination, the findings of this trial will also be shared through presentations and publication in peer-reviewed journals irrespective of the nature of the outcomes of the research. Authorship eligibility guidelines will be followed.</p>
 </sec>
</ack>
