<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0200">The NS1 protein is abundantly expressed in virus-infected cells and the main antagonistic protein enabling IBV to interfere with the innate type I interferon (IFN) defense and to propagate efficiently in mammalian hosts. Hence, there are strong parallels to the functions of the IAV NS1 protein although they share a sequence identity of less than 25%, and there are also type-specific activities of the two NS1 proteins. The IBV NS1 protein has a conserved length of 281 amino acids with a predicted molecular mass of 32 kDa. It is described as a non-structural protein although low levels of NS1 were detected in purified virions by mass spectrometric analysis. Early biochemical analyzes identified in the N-terminal NS1 domain an RNA binding activity (amino acids 1–93) and the ability to bind to the IFN-induced protein ISG15 (1−103), a ubiquitin-like modifier of nascent proteins. Later on, it was found that the C-terminal part of NS1 (94−281) can also bind RNA. Reverse genetic analysis confirmed that in epithelial cells the NS1 protein inhibits the accumulation of IFN-β transcripts and activation of IRF3, a central transcriptional regulator of IFN-β expression. For this activity the C-terminal NS1 domain was essential. However, IBV is a stronger activator of type I and III IFN expression early in infection compared to IAV. This depends on the cellular pattern recognition receptor RIG-I and it is possibly caused by a more rapid release of vRNPs from endosomes. Interestingly, the IBV NS1 protein does not bind RIG-I, but rather targets the ubiquitin E3 ligase TRIM25 that activates RIG-I by ubiquitination, whereas the type A NS1 protein binds RIG-I and TRIM25 directly. Phenotypic analyzes of recombinant mutant IBV demonstrated that NS1 facilitates efficient viral propagation in vitro and in vivo by blocking the activation of the central immune kinase PKR that can shut-off protein synthesis in infected cells. Silencing of PKR strongly depended on a binding interaction of the N-terminal NS1 domain with the kinase domain of PKR. Structural information from X-ray crystallography has been reported for the N-terminal domain (15−93) of NS1 that adopts a six helical dimeric fold and a large C-terminal fragment (141−281). It is uncertain whether the IBV NS1 protein forms higher order structures as was recently shown for the type A NS1. ISG15 has been shown to regulate influenza A and B virus infections. It was therefore not surprising to find out that the IBV NS1 protein not only binds ISG15, but it can also prevent its conjugation to target proteins. Interestingly, the IBV NS1 protein binds strongly to the human ISG15 and only poorly to ISG15 homologs in other mammalian species, which provides an important example of a species-specific viral antagonism of the type I IFN response.</p>
