<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>These highly diverse epidemic dynamics, however, also present major challenges for inference on transmission dynamics. In an exploratory analysis, we coupled a commonly used multi-strain susceptible-infected-recovered-susceptible (SIRS) model [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007989.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] with a particle filter [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007989.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007989.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], a Bayesian inference method, and applied it to the Hong Kong dataset. While this model-inference system was able to reproduce the observed epidemic pattern, the model state did not appear to converge (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1007989.s005">S1 Fig</xref>). Three major challenges exist. First, the seasonality of influenza in part shapes the epidemic dynamics and thus should be accounted for in the model. However, unlike the winter-time epidemics in temperate regions that have been well-characterized by seasonal forcing of climate variables (humidity alone or with temperature) [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007989.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007989.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], to date no models capable of capturing the diverse seasonal pattern in tropical and subtropical climates exist. Second, to estimate epidemiological parameters such as the duration of immunity, the inference system must be able to preserve such long-term epidemic features. Single-pass filters (e.g., the particle filter) did not appear to do so as seen in our exploratory analysis. Multi-pass filters (e.g., iterated filters [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007989.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007989.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]) have such built-in capability, however, are less adept in modeling diverse epidemic dynamics [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007989.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Finally, it is challenging to estimate a large number of parameters needed to characterize the interactions between virus-pairs.
</p>
