<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The Th1/Th2 phenotype of the T cell response can profoundly influence B cell responses [
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-09-00234" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-09-00234" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-viruses-09-00234" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-viruses-09-00234" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. In the mouse model, IgG2A and IgG2B provide better protection against viral infections than IgG1 Abs [
 <xref rid="B62-viruses-09-00234" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-viruses-09-00234" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. The Th1/Th2 phenotype of the immune response induced by rAdH5/M2e immunization is critical for the type of immunoglobulins induced and level of protection of the respiratory tract. In this study, we observed that rAdH5/M2e immunization induced secretion of Th2 type cytokines, IL-4, IL-6, and IL-10 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-09-00234-f003">Figure 3</xref>). These Th2 cytokines are important for proliferation and differentiation of B cells, isotype class switching, regulation in humoral immunity [
 <xref rid="B11-viruses-09-00234" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-09-00234" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], and accelerated inflammatory responses [
 <xref rid="B47-viruses-09-00234" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. The elevated levels of Th2-type cytokines are consistent with superior levels of HA stalk-specific IgG1 and IgA induced by rAdH5/M2e immunization. Cholera toxin is a strong agonist of IL-4 responses [
 <xref rid="B46-viruses-09-00234" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] and accordingly we noted that immunization with FiPR8+CT induced the highest levels of IL-4. Although we observed that immunization with rAdH5/M2e resulted in a lower level of IL-4 production as compared to immunization with FiPR8+CT, these responses further indicate that rAdH5/M2e immunization induces a Th2 response. Interestingly, these Th2 responses are not sufficient to completely counteract Th1 responses as indicated by the levels of HA-stalk specific IgG2A and IgG2B induced by rAdH5/M2e immunization. Interestingly, the elevated levels of IL-10 induced by immunization with live PR8 and rAdH5/M2e suggests the possible activation of regulatory T cells (Treg) during the adaptive immune response.
</p>
