<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Formaldehyde is one of the earliest and most widely used chemical methods to inactivate virus for vaccine production; however, this method of treatment can cause irreversible modifications by cross-linking antigens and damaging key antigenic epitopes leading to reduced immunogenicity [
 <xref rid="B64-viruses-09-00234" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-viruses-09-00234" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. It has been reported from studies that compared immune responses to live influenza virus against seasonal formaldehyde-inactivated influenza virus vaccine (i.e., TIV) that: (i) live influenza virus induced significantly better protection than inactivated vaccine in infants and young children; (ii) elicited stronger influenza virus-specific serum Ab levels; and (iii) stimulated greater T-cell responses that could provide cross-protection against heterologous challenge in small animal models of influenza virus disease [
 <xref rid="B5-viruses-09-00234" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-viruses-09-00234" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-viruses-09-00234" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. We conjectured that the HA stalk domain and more importantly its native epitopes play an important role in development of protective immunity against infection with heterosubtypic influenza viruses. As shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-09-00234-f006">Figure 6</xref>A and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-09-00234-f007">Figure 7</xref>A, we found that formaldehyde treatment of baculovirus-expressed chimeric HA protein (cH9/1) reduced binding of HA stalk domain-specific Abs. However, formaldehyde treatment did not significantly reduce binding of Abs to virus particles (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-09-00234-f006">Figure 6</xref>B), or alter binding of HA head-specific mAbs to whole virus particles (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-09-00234-f007">Figure 7</xref>B). These findings suggest that formaldehyde treatment altered antigenic epitopes, and thus the antigenicities, of the HA stalk, the M2e ectodomain, and NP protein (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-09-00234-f008">Figure 8</xref>A,B), and support the speculation that recognition of the native conformation of the HA stalk domain is important for heterosubtypic immunity. Our results also indicate that immunization with rAdH5/M2e induced Abs that are specific for native HA stalk epitopes that contributed to cross-protection against other influenza virus subtypes (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-09-00234-f003">Figure 3</xref>D and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-09-00234-f004">Figure 4</xref>A). Thus, immunization with rAdH5/M2e induced long-lived antibody responses that recognize native epitopes of the HA stalk.
</p>
