<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As shown in 
 <bold>Figure </bold>
 <xref rid="psp412510-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>4</bold>
 </xref> (top), the model given by Eq. 
 <xref rid="psp412510-disp-0003" ref-type="disp-formula">3</xref> can reproduce the patterns of viral load observed in clinical data where the peaks of viremia and cytokines coincide.
 <xref rid="psp412510-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>56</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="psp412510-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>61</sup>
 </xref> Consistent with the standard model of viral dynamics, viral decline after peak viremia results from a lack of susceptible cells; however, in this model, the peak viremia does not correspond to an exhaustion of noninfected cells, but rather to the fact that most noninfected cells have been set into an antiviral state. Thus, the model allows one to quantify the “race” between the virus and the innate immune response to “get first in contact” with the susceptible cells. In absence of treatment, this race triggers an inflammatory response to counter the exponential viral replication and this “cytokine storm” is directly related to clinical symptoms, as shown in influenza infection.
 <xref rid="psp412510-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>62</sup>
 </xref> Thus, in this dynamic interaction between the host and the virus, an antiviral treatment can be beneficial even if it does not abrogate viremia, as long as it can reduce it to such an extent that transmission risk is reduced and an exacerbated immune response is averted. This is illustrated in 
 <bold>Figure </bold>
 <xref rid="psp412510-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>4</bold>
 </xref>, where a treatment initiated at D0 with an effect of 50%, which is lower than the critical efficacy (here equal to 83%) is sufficient to reduce viral growth, giving time for the IFNα response to put more cells into a refractory state, leading to both a delay and a reduction in peak viremia by about 4 logs. This prediction is different from the target cell limited model (Eq. 
 <xref rid="psp412510-disp-0002" ref-type="disp-formula">2</xref>), where 
 <italic>ε</italic> = 50% would impair viral growth and, hence, delay peak viremia, but with only little effect on the peak viremia value shown (
 <bold>Figure </bold>
 <xref rid="psp412510-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>4</bold>
 </xref> bottom).
</p>
