<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Prevention</italic>:
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>Effective disinfection of contaminated material. A spray composed of 0.1 % o-phenylphenol and 79 % ethanol is an effective surface disinfectant for rotaviruses.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Careful hand washing.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Vaccine: The objective of rotavirus vaccine is to prevent moderate-to-severe disease but not mild disease associated with rotavirus, to duplicate the degree of protection that follows natural infection and to decrease the number of hospitalizations with dehydration, especially in resource-poor countries, where mortality associated with rotavirus is high. The different vaccines available/under development for rotaviruses are as under:</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p>Vaccines based on animal rotaviruses: Considered to be naturally attenuated for humans, the Jennerian vaccines. Three monovalent animal rotavirus vaccines, two bovine rotavirus strains, RIT 4237 (P6[1]G6) and WC3 (P7[5]G6), and a simian (rhesus) rotavirus reassortant vaccine (RRV) strain (P[3]G3) have been studied. Variable efficacy was seen in field trials with these vaccines. China introduced live attenuated oral LLR vaccine that was derived from a lamb strain of rotavirus, the efficacy of which is not known (Dennehy 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR251">2008</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Human–rhesus RRV (RotaShield): This was the first multivalent live oral reassortant vaccine (a rhesus rotavirus tetravalent [RRV-TV] vaccine), which contained a mixture of four most common G serotypes, G1 to G4: three rhesus–human monoreassortant strains containing the VP7 genes of human serotypes G1, G2, and G4 strains were substituted for the VP7 gene of the parent RRV, and the fourth strain comprised serotype G3 of rhesus RRV (Kapikian 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">1996</xref>). This vaccine was licensed for use in the United States but was then withdrawn from the market because it was causally linked with intussusceptions with an estimated frequency of 1 in 10,000 vaccinated infants.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Currently licensed vaccines: Currently, two vaccines have been licensed for human use. First is a pentavalent human-bovine (WC3) reassortant live attenuated oral vaccine (RotaTeq) developed by Merck Research Co. Another is a live attenuated human rotavirus vaccine, strain 89-12, that was originally developed from P1A[8]G1 by tissue culture passage of a wild-type human rotavirus isolate. GlaxoSmithKline Biologicals further modified the vaccine by cloning and tissue culture passaging of the parent 89-12 vaccine strain to develop the resulting vaccine, RIX4414 (Rotarix). Salient features of these two vaccines are shown in Table 
    <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4.4</xref>. 
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Candidate Vaccines: The National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID) has developed a tetravalent human-bovine rotavirus reassortant vaccine candidate, which incorporates four reassortants with VP7 specificity for G1, G2, G3, and G4 human serotype and 10 genes from the bovine rotavirus UK strain (P[7]G6). This vaccine showed safety and efficacy in a clinical trial at Finland (Midthun et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">1985</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
