<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This 30-year study provided epidemiological information of myxomatosis and has enabled us to better assist the rabbit producers with their vaccination’s schedules. Also, as reported in a previous study it has made the continuous training and motivation of farm staff possible, based on technical evidence [
 <xref rid="B34-animals-09-00780" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Vaccination is a key aspect of myxomatosis control. According to our observations, the percentage of farms using vaccines elaborated with homologous strains of MYXV increased from 1988 to 2018; this could have a favorable effect on decreasing the prevalence of myxomatosis. During 2014–2018 producers vaccinated against myxomatosis on 95.5% of the 200 visited farms; 90% of vaccines used were “homologous”. From 2010 till 2013 there were 274 visited rabbitries: 93.6% vaccinated, 88% with a “homologous” one. In 1994 we visited 193 farms; producers vaccinated against myxomatosis in 81% of cases. In the same year, 59% used “homologous” vaccines either alone or after administering a “heterologous” one [
 <xref rid="B32-animals-09-00780" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. We explicitly monitored and supervised the occurrence of myxomatosis, the protection of vaccines on farms, and the diagnosis of side effects, as indicated by Knight-Jones et al. [
 <xref rid="B54-animals-09-00780" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Post-vaccination side effects on visited farms could not be related to each individual, as is the case in pet rabbit clinics [
 <xref rid="B55-animals-09-00780" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], nor was it possible to study each side effect in detail. Possible vaccine failures due to causes related to its origin, transport or inadequate administration, is an interesting matter (as pointed out in [
 <xref rid="B56-animals-09-00780" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]). Apart from errors related to biosecurity, e.g., inefficient culling of sick animals showing mild signs, such failures could also explain the endemic persistence of myxomatosis, even though vaccination was implemented on 95.5% of the farms we visited.
</p>
