<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0145">For the spread of viruses, there are no borders between countries as more and more interactions and cooperation were established worldwide. Since the CoVs and IAVs were identified as the major pathogens for respiratory diseases in last century, they have traveled to many corners of the world [
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The transmission and infectivity related information of these viruses were summarized in 
 <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> . There are two seasonal flu viruses included, HCoVs and H3N2 IAV (HCoVs represents four CoVs that cause seasonal cold, HCoV229E, HCoV-OC43, HCoV-NL63, and HCoV-HKU1, for convenience in following discussion, they will be denoted as one CoV in this article.). They usually cause moderate clinical symptoms and spread globally [
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The rest of six viruses either show high pathogenicity or are highly transmissible, which could cause much danger for human society. These viruses are called here as HPHTs, which stands for high pathogenicity or highly transmissible viruses. Of the HPHTs, the spread of SARS-CoV-2 is accelerated due to its ability to transmit through airborne droplets during the incubation period [
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. That it may also transmit between human and animals becomes another challenge in the control of the pandemic [
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Another two viruses, MERS-CoV and SARS-CoV, reported in 2012 and 2003 respectively, caused mortalities of 35% and 9% in patients respectively. Their transmission mostly started after the patients started showing clinical symptoms [
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Therefore, they could not travel in humans too long before being discovered and controlled. All ages of people were susceptible to these 3 CoVs, but senior people were more likely to be infected with SARS-CoV-2 and develop more severe clinical symptoms, while mostly younger people were infected with SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].
</p>
