<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec id="sec001">
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>Within the last 10 years Zika virus (ZIKV) has caused unprecedented epidemics of human disease in the nations and territories of the western Pacific and South America, and continues to escalate in both endemic and non-endemic regions. We evaluated the vector competence of Australian mosquitoes for ZIKV to assess their potential role in virus transmission.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec002">
  <title>Methodology/Principal Findings</title>
  <p>Mosquitoes were exposed to infectious blood meals containing the prototype African ZIKV strain. After 14 days incubation at 28°C and high relative humidity, infection, dissemination and transmission rates were assessed. Infection in 
   <italic>Culex annulirostris</italic> and 
   <italic>Cx</italic>. 
   <italic>sitiens</italic> could not be detected. 8% of 
   <italic>Cx</italic>. 
   <italic>quinquefasciatus</italic> were infected, but the virus did not disseminate in this species. Despite having infection rates &gt; 50%, 
   <italic>Aedes notoscriptus</italic> and 
   <italic>Ae</italic>. 
   <italic>vigilax</italic> did not transmit ZIKV. In contrast, 
   <italic>Ae</italic>. 
   <italic>aegypti</italic> had infection and transmission rates of 57% and 27%, respectively. In susceptibility trials, the virus dose required to infect 50% (ID
   <sub>50</sub>) of 
   <italic>Ae</italic>. 
   <italic>aegypti</italic> was10
   <sup>6.4</sup> tissue culture infectious dose
   <sub>50</sub> (TCID
   <sub>50</sub>)/mL. Additionally, a threshold viral load within the mosquito of at least 10
   <sup>5.1</sup> TCID
   <sub>50</sub> equivalents/mL had to be reached before virus transmission occurred.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec003">
  <title>Conclusions/Significance</title>
  <p>We confirmed 
   <italic>Ae</italic>. 
   <italic>aegypti</italic> to be the most likely mosquito vector of ZIKV in Australia, although the restricted distribution of this species will limit the receptive zone to northern Queensland where this species occurs. Importantly, the role in ZIKV transmission of 
   <italic>Culex</italic> and other 
   <italic>Aedes</italic> spp. tested will be negligible. Despite being the implicated vector, the relatively high ID
   <sub>50</sub> and need for a high titer disseminated infection in 
   <italic>Ae</italic>. 
   <italic>aegypti</italic> suggest that high mosquito population densities will be required to facilitate epidemic ZIKV transmission among the currently immunologically naïve human population in Australia.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
