<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Human resources for healthcare are identified as one of the core building blocks of a health system and workforce crisis are one of the major obstacles to the quality healthcare.
 <xref rid="hpm3016-bib-0068" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>68</sup>
 </xref> According to the WHO, the overall Pakistani health sector is confronted with an imbalance in the number, expertise and distribution of healthcare professionals and insufficient allotment of resources across various levels of healthcare.
 <xref rid="hpm3016-bib-0069" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>69</sup>
 </xref> Currently, one physician is available to serve every 963 persons in Pakistan.
 <xref rid="hpm3016-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref> With regard to availability of healthcare professionals, a total of 220 829 registered doctors, 22 595 registered dentists and 108 474 registered nurses are actively working in Pakistan.
 <xref rid="hpm3016-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref> The availability of pharmacists in Pakistan (1.6 pharmacists per 10 000 person population) is also meager compared to the target (five pharmacists per 10 000 person population) set by the WHO.
 <xref rid="hpm3016-bib-0070" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>70</sup>
 </xref> In addition, a number of studies have indicated that existing healthcare workforce were overburdened,
 <xref rid="hpm3016-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="hpm3016-bib-0071" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>71</sup>
 </xref> and the mean consultation time (1.2‐2.2 minutes) and the dispensing time (8.7‐38 seconds) in the public sector facilities were suboptimal.
 <xref rid="hpm3016-bib-0072" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>72</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="hpm3016-bib-0073" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>73</sup>
 </xref> Moreover, unavailability of qualified and trained community pharmacists at drug retail outlets add fuel to the fire,
 <xref rid="hpm3016-bib-0074" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>74</sup>
 </xref> as patients are not provided with required consultation and infection prevention measures for common infections.
 <xref rid="hpm3016-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>38</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="hpm3016-bib-0075" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>75</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="hpm3016-bib-0076" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>76</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="hpm3016-bib-0077" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>77</sup>
 </xref> However, there are growing debates that pharmacists—being the first to be reached by patients in resource deprived settings—have all the abilities and expertise to forestall and resolve minor health issues, including infectious diseases, through proper counseling.
 <xref rid="hpm3016-bib-0076" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>76</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="hpm3016-bib-0078" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>78</sup>
 </xref> Well‐trained community pharmacists can refer the critically ill patients (eg, presumptive COVID‐19 patients) to specialized healthcare facilities. This has been borne out by a recent study, according to which “pharmacist job” was one of the substantial determinants of good COVID‐19 infection control practices.
 <xref rid="hpm3016-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>42</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
