<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="Tab1">
 <label>Table 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Similarities and differences between seasonal and pandemic influenza.</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th>Seasonal influenza A and B</th>
    <th>Pandemic influenza A</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">Occurrence</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> Annual (in temperate regions)</td>
    <td>
     <p>Four true pandemics in last 100 years</p>
     <p>Shortest inter-pandemic interval 11 years, longest interval 39 years</p>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">Predictability</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <p> Occurrence: predictable seasonality, but dominant antigenic type/subtypes vary</p>
     <p>Impact: difficult to predict until dominant type/subtype is known</p>
    </td>
    <td>
     <p>Occurrence: difficult to predict when it will happen and what the subtype will be</p>
     <p>Impact: difficult to predict, although historical trend is for major impact, particularly for younger adults and children</p>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">Antigenic change</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> Antigenic drift (subtle changes in existing HA/NA)</td>
    <td>Antigenic shift (major change in HA/NA resulting in new virus and subtype)</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">Immunity</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> Some naturally-acquired immunity is likely in adults, through previous infection and/or vaccination. Antigenic drift facilitates immune escape, leading to recurrent infections. Young unvaccinated children will lack immunity until infected or vaccinated</td>
    <td>
     <p>Specific antibody-mediated immunity is lacking and most of the population will not have significant cross-protective immunity from previous influenza infections</p>
     <p>The effect of T-cell mediated immunity is largely unknown but could potentially give some cross-reactive protection against severe disease (especially in the mucosa)</p>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">Risk groups for severe influenza</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> Elderly persons, infants, those with certain underlying health conditions (asthma, COPD, heart disease), obesity, pregnancy</td>
    <td>As for seasonal influenza, but there may be over-representation of younger adults and children, and otherwise healthy individuals. Spread depends on absent or low herd immunity</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">Impact</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <p> Varies season-to-season</p>
     <p>WHO estimates between 3 and 5 million cases and 290,000 to 650,000 global annual deaths</p>
     <p>In wealthy countries, most deaths occur in those &gt;65 years of age</p>
    </td>
    <td>
     <p>Mortality varies between different pandemics and is difficult to predict in advance</p>
     <p>1918 H1N1 pandemic believed to have caused at least 50 million deaths globally</p>
     <p>2009 H1N1 pandemic is believed to have caused 250,000–500,000 deaths globally</p>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">Vaccines</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> Readily available in many countries before influenza season begins. Annual vaccine recommendations made for Northern and Southern hemispheres, dependent on predictive algorithms and epidemiology. Recently vaccine effectiveness poor in H3N2-dominated years</td>
    <td>
     <p>Strategic preparedness in some countries for viruses with pandemic potential e.g., avian influenza viruses</p>
     <p>Pandemic influenza viruses arise from diverse sources and are unpredictable</p>
     <p>Likely lag-time between a pandemic commencing and vaccine being available lessens the probability that vaccines will have a major impact</p>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">Antivirals</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <p> Predominantly neuraminidase inhibitors</p>
     <p>Other classes of antivirals are in development and may have additional impact alone or in combination</p>
    </td>
    <td>Sensitivity to existing antivirals cannot be guaranteed. Some countries stockpile existing antivirals as countermeasures, but demand may outstrip supply during a higher-impact pandemic. Resistant, highly transmissible pathogenic influenza variants could be devastating</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
