<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Specific PeV-A genotypic prevalence varies globally. In Europe and the USA, PeV-A1 is most prevalent followed by PeV-A3 and PeV-A4, while PeV-A2, and A7-A19 are rarely reported [
 <xref rid="B38-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. In Asia, similar to Europe and the USA, PeV-A1, A3, and A4 are the most prevalent but a higher diversity of genotypes has been reported in India and Pakistan [
 <xref rid="B47-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. In the African continent, PeV-A1, A2, and A3 are the most prevalent but nearly all PeV genotypes are detected, indicating a much wider circulation of genotypes. Different genotype distributions have further been reported, for example in Pakistan and Ghana, underlining differences in prevalence and diversity between continents [
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. These genetic variations arise from not only error-prone RNA-dependent RNA polymerase, but also from recombination (see section on evolution for further details) [
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. The frequency of recombination was higher among PeV-A1 and PeV-A4 to A6 sequences as compared to PeV-A3 isolates [
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. However, a recent outbreak of neonatal sepsis in Australia was caused by a recombinant PeV-A3 strain [
 <xref rid="B52-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>].
</p>
