<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The interaction between virus infection and the host response was further characterized in our study by comparing the gene expression profiles in infected and in bystander cells. Several genes, including the IFIT2, OASL and RSAD2 (also known as viperin) genes, with known antiviral activity (
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>), and IFIH1 or MDA5, which contributes to viral sensing (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>), showed higher expression in infected versus bystander cells, suggesting that these ISGs, in addition to being inducible by type I or III IFN, have also an autocrine component of activation. Indeed, the induction of some ISGs was detected as early as 4 hpi (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>), with such an early upregulation consistent with direct induction by viral infection. This is in contrast to the highly accepted concept that type I or type III IFN signaling is necessary for the induction of antiviral genes (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>), with a few exceptions such as ISG15 and CXCL10 (
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>). The well-described mechanism of activation of transcription of ISGs upon type I/III IFN induction involves assembly and translocation to the nucleus of ISGF3, which binds to the DNA sequences in the promoters of ISGs known as interferon-stimulated response elements (ISRE) (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Interestingly, Daly and Reich found two complexes in addition to ISGF3, interferon responsive factor 3 (IRF3) and the transcriptional coactivator CREB-binding protein (CBP)/p300, which could recognize ISRE sequences and activate transcription upon dsRNA stimulation in the absence of IFN (
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>). The abilities of these transcription factors to interact with ISRE differ among various ISGs, due to variations in their DNA sequences. A later study identified IFIT2, ISG15, IFIT3, IFIT1, and GBP1 as IRF3 target genes (
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>). With the exception of these highly informative studies, literature in this specific topic is scarce. Therefore, direct induction of ISGs in infected cells might be an important player in promoting effective early antiviral responses.
</p>
