<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There is few information about the initial events in the process of virus elimination and inflammatory reactions during SARS‐CoV infection. However, the innate immune reactions is mediated to the adaptive immunity development and disease severity in SARS‐CoV.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0129" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>129</sup>
 </xref> Of note, SARS‐CoV evolved escape mechanisms to avoid IFN responses in infected host cells. Besides, inflammatory reactions are regulated by inflammatory cytokines and chemokines such as IL‐6, interferon‐γ‐inducible protein‐10 (IP‐10), monocyte chemoattractant protein‐1(MCP‐1) as well as the penetration of inflammatory cells such as macrophages into infected host tissues.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0129" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>129</sup>
 </xref> The suppression of antiviral type I interferons is one of the marked characteristics of SARS‐CoV infection as well as other group II coronaviruses including mouse hepatitis virus.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0130" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>130</sup>
 </xref> It has been shown that the formation of type I interferons is impaired in host cells infected with SARS‐CoV, but pretreatment of cells with IFN suppresses the growth of SARS‐CoV.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0131" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>131</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0132" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>132</sup>
 </xref> This shows that these viruses have developed mechanisms to overcome IFN responses in infected cells. Type I interferons are rarely found in acute SARS patients, and SARS‐CoV is sensitive to Pegylated IFN‐α, as shown in in vivo murine models.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0133" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>133</sup>
 </xref> Studies indicated that type I interferon suppression in SARS‐CoV‐infected hosts is mediated by the inactivation of the IRF‐3 (interferon regulatory factor 3) protein, a transcriptional factor that controls the transcription of interferons.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0132" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>132</sup>
 </xref> Also, other SARS‐CoV accessory proteins act as powerful interferon antagonists through various strategies.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0129" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>129</sup>
 </xref> For instance, N proteins inhibit the expression of interferons, whereas open‐reading frame 3b and 6 proteins oppress the signaling pathway and expression of interferons.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0129" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>129</sup>
 </xref> Also, open‐reading frame 6 proteins can halt the translocation of signal transducer and activator of transcription 1 (STAT1). The open‐reading frame 3b protein is a shuttling protein, impeding the stimulation of type I interferon, which is triggered by retinoic acid‐inducible gene 1 (RIG‐I) and mitochondrial antiviral‐signaling (MAVS) protein.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0134" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>134</sup>
 </xref> Additionally, M proteins suppress the production of type I interferon by inhibiting the generation of the TNF Receptor Associated Factor 3 (TRAF3)–TRAF Family Member Associated NFKB Activator (TANK) – TANK binding kinase 1 (TBK1)/IκB kinase ε (IKKε) complex.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0134" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>134</sup>
 </xref> Besides, SARS‐CoV NSP1 proteins are able to halt the expression of IFN‐β in host cells by promoting the degradation of the host mRNA and the suppression of the translation process.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0135" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>135</sup>
 </xref> A polyprotein complex of SARS‐CoV named papain‐like protease is able to inhibit the phosphorylation and nuclear translocation of IRF‐3, resulting in disrupting the activation of type I IFN response via either Toll‐like receptor 3 (TLR‐3) or RIG‐1/melanoma differentiation‐associated gene 5 (MDA5) complex.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0136" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>136</sup>
 </xref> Also, infected cells with SARS‐CoV can stimulate the expression of protein kinase R (PKR) and PKR‐like endoplasmic reticulum kinase (PERK).
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0137" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>137</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
