<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0205">Tetracyclines (doxycycline, tetracyclines, minocycline) are a class of polyketide antibiotics having a broad-spectrum bacteriostatic activity against various bacterial infections. The bactericidal activity of tetracycline is mainly due to its ability to reversibly bind to the bacterial ribosomes and there by leading to the leakage of the intracellular components from the bacterial cell by altering the cytoplasmic membrane [
 <xref rid="bb0690" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>]. Several studies have shown that along with anti-bacterial activity tetracyclines also possess a potential antiviral activity against a host of virus including SARS-CoV-2. Tetracycline act by three possible mechanism against SARS-Cov-2 virus. Coronavirus depends on matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs) for replication, survival, cell to cell adhesion and cell infiltration having zinc as a part of MMPs complex [
 <xref rid="bb0695" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>]. Tetracyclines are known to chelate with the zinc compounds present on the MMPs complex and thereby helps in decreasing the severity of COVID-19 infection. Secondly, tetracyclines decreases the levels of cytokines and other inflammatory agents by down regulation of NFKB pathways [
 <xref rid="bb0700" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>] and thereby aiding in the treatment of COVID-19 as corona virus causes an elevated release of cytokines (IL-6, TNF-α and IL-1β) and triggers the release of inflammatory agents like protease and histamine along with cytokines by inducing proliferation of the respiratory submucosa mast cells. The third possible mechanism of tetracycline in treating COVID-19 is by inhibiting the replication of viral DNA in the lungs which is mainly attributed to the high tissue penetrating ability and lipophilic nature of tetracycline. The bioavailability of tetracycline upon intramuscular injection is 40% and the oral bioavailability is around 60–80%. It is a highly protein bound drug with a half-life of 6–12 h. Vomiting, diarrhoea, loss of appetite and oral sores are the possible adverse effects of tetracyclines. Nantes University Hospital, France has been given approval to start a double blinded, randomized, placebo controlled, multi centred clinical trial. The aim of this study is to assess the efficacy of doxycycline in reducing/ abolishing the cytokine storm which is induced by the SARS-CoV-2 virus in the COVID-19 positive patients upon hospitalization [
 <xref rid="bb0705" ref-type="bibr">141</xref>].
</p>
