<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Emerging viral infections pose a constant threat to humans and animals. Viral emergence causing an epidemic of disease in a new host is a rare event, despite the wide diversity of viruses that are known to exist [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007531.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] and the constant exposure of hosts to viruses that circulate in other species that share the same habitat. Multiple virus introductions may precede large-scale epidemics, as was seen in the cross-species transmissions of simian immunodeficiency viruses leading to the epidemic spread of the human immunodeficiency virus groups O, N, and P, with only the group M viruses becoming pandemic [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007531.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1007531.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Transmission of H3N8 equine influenza virus (EIV) to dogs has been reported in Australia [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007531.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], the United Kingdom [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007531.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] and United States of America [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007531.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] but only in the latter did the canine influenza virus (CIV) emerge and become established as a novel pathogen of dogs, in which it has been circulating for over 15 years. In contrast, and despite hundreds of human zoonotic infections being reported for H5N1 avian influenza virus (AIV), this virus has not acquired the ability to transmit among humans [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007531.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The apparently low proportion of successful cross-species jumps could be explained by the actions of ecological, genetic and immunological barriers barriers. For example, the transmitted pathogens often lack key (but poorly understood) phenotypic features required to undergo efficient transmission, and the structure of the recipient host population may not provide sufficient contacts between infected and susceptible individuals [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007531.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Viral emergence could also be impaired in the presence of ample ecological opportunities if mutations required to adapt to a new host are difficult to acquire or have a high fitness cost in the donor or recipient host [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007531.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Indeed, even in the presence of the “right” ecological and evolutionary factors, influenza virus emergence could be impaired by hemagglutinin imprinting, a biological process by which the first IAV infection of an individual confers lifelong cross-protection against severe infection by viruses carrying an HA of the same phylogenetic group [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007531.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007531.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].
</p>
