<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Multiplex assays are significantly more sensitive and specific compared with rapid immunochromatographic tests and immunofluorescence assays; however, as multiplex assays detect both viable and non-viable viruses and bacteria, they can lead to debatable results (Beckmann and Hirsch, 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Esposito et al., 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2016a</xref>; Biomerieux, 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Fast Track Diagnostic, 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Generally, the presently developed and marketed multiplex assays exhibit comparable performance with regards to sensitivities and specificities, and detection of coinfections. A previous comparison of the (Luminex, 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) Nx TAG RPP assay, BioFire Film Array Respiratory Panel (FA-RP) (Biomerieux, 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), RespiFinder22 (RF22) (Beckmann and Hirsch, 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), and the (Luminex, 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) RVP FAST Assay v2 (Esposito et al., 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2016a</xref>) in terms of the ability to detect common pathogens revealed that the discordance was lower than 10%, although the turnaround time, workflow simplicity and risk of contamination were lower for the (Luminex, 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) Nx TAG RPP (Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Tang et al., 
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). A systematic review and meta-analysis (Huang et al., 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) of studies on the accuracy of FA-RP, Nanosphere Verigene RV+ test (Hologic, 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Luminex, 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) Gen-Probe Prodesse assays (Hologic, 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) in the detection of IV A, IV B virus, RSV, hMPV, and AV showed that all of these assays had high diagnostic accuracy, with an area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUROC) equal to or &gt;0.98 for all tested viruses. The only exception was adenovirus, for which the AUROC was 0.89. Finally, a similarly high accuracy was demonstrated for Anyplex II RV16, AdvanSure RV, and Real-Q RV (Yun et al., 
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>).
</p>
