<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0010">Due to the close similarity to SARS-CoV, the biochemical interactions and the pathogenesis of SARS-CoV-2 are highly likely to be similar [
 <xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The virus entry into the host cell is mainly mediated through the binding of the SARS spike (S) protein to the angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE-2) receptor on the cell surface [
 <xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Among coronaviruses, the main protease (M
 <sup>pro</sup>, also called 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup>) has emerged as the best-described drug target [
 <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The polyproteins that are translated from the viral RNA are processed by this enzyme together with the papain-like protease(s) [
 <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The M
 <sup>pro</sup> recognizes and acts remarkably on eleven cleavage sites typically Leu-Gln↓(Ser,Ala,Gly) on the large polyprotein 1ab (replicase 1ab) of approximately 790 kDa. Blocking the activity of this enzyme would help in inhibiting viral replication. There are no reported human proteases with a similar cleavage specificity and therefore, inhibitors against this enzyme are less probable to be toxic [
 <xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The three dimensional X-ray crystal structure of this enzyme in complex with α-ketoamide inhibitor 13b (O6K) was recently solved by Zhang et al. [
 <xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] (PDB ID: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:6Y2F" id="ir0005" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">6Y2F</ext-link>) which offers an opportunity for structure-based drug design against the enzyme target. Understanding the relevance of the steady rise in the number of infected and death cases in recent time from COVID-19 and lack of effective therapeutic interventions such as drugs and vaccines, computer-aided drug design is an important strategy to be sought after. This rational based drug design will reduce the cost and time incurred in the drug discovery process. Structure-based drug design primarily relies on molecular docking to identify lead molecules against the target proteins from chemical libraries [
 <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Compared to the synthetic inhibitors plant based-drugs have less toxicity and much safer to use. The natural products such as traditional medicines and plant-derived compounds (phytochemicals) are the rich sources of promising antiviral drugs [
 <xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Around 44% of the approved antiviral drugs between 1981 and 2006 were derived from natural products [
 <xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The plant extracts have been extensively used and screened for drug molecules to evaluate theirs in vitro antiviral activities. Few examples of medicinal plants with proven antiviral activities include 
 <italic>Phyllanthus amarus</italic> Schum. and Thonn which blocks human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) replication both in vitro and in vivo [
 <xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]; 
 <italic>Azadirachta indica</italic> Juss. (Neem) shows in vitro and in vivo inhibition properties against Dengue virus type-2 (DENV-2) [
 <xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]; 
 <italic>Geranium sanguineum</italic> L. significantly inhibits the replication of Herpes simplex virus type-1 and 2 (HSV-1 and HSV-2) in vitro [
 <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]; 
 <italic>Acacia nilotica</italic> L. possesses activity against Hepatitis C virus (HCV) in vitro etc. [
 <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].
</p>
