<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Pneumocystis carinii</italic> (now known 
 <italic>Pneumocystis jiroveci</italic>) is an opportunistic pulmonary pathogen in infants and children with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) and other primary immunodeficiencies, malnutrition, hematological malignancies, solid organ and bone marrow transplant recipients, and patients on high dose corticosteroid therapy for inflammatory and collagen-vascular diseases. It is a unicellular organism that exists as a cyst (the diagnostic form). The organism attaches to the type I alveolar cells resulting in an alveolitis characterized by ventilation-perfusion mismatch and decreased pulmonary compliance. If untreated, PCP carries a mortality rate of 25–50%, and nearly 100% in the HIV-seropositive child. Fortunately, the incidence has markedly decreased with the administration of chemoprophylactic agents to high risk patients. Children typically present with fever, tachypnea, non-productive cough, and hypoxia with an absence of rales on auscultation of the chest. Initially, they may have an elevated pH and low carbon dioxide levels. Lactate dehydrogenase levels are generally elevated. Bilateral diffuse alveolar infiltrates are seen with initial hilar involvement subsequently spreading to the periphery (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4_25" ref-type="fig">25-4</xref>). Diagnosis is made by demonstrating the organism with the methenamine silver nitrate stain on pulmonary tissue, respiratory secretions, or lung fluid. Bronchoalveolar lavage is the most widely used technique to obtain lung fluid for diagnosis. Treatment consists of supportive therapy with supplemental oxygen; ultimately continuous positive airway pressure or mechanical ventilation may be necessary if respiratory failure occurs. Trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole (TMP-SMX) is the recommended initial treatment. In patients that cannot tolerate TMP-SMX, then pentamidine isoethionate should be used. Corticosteroids in anti-inflammatory doses as an adjunct to antimicrobial therapy have improved clinical outcomes. Concurrent pulmonary infections were found in 35% of patients, most frequently bacterial or cytomegalovirus pneumonia. 
</p>
