<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A balanced diet is essential for metabolic and cardiovascular health, but variations in diet can also have a marked effect on (auto)immunity. Moreover, it is now clear that changes in the functions of T cells, macrophages and dendritic cells are closely related to their metabolic states.
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">58</xref> Most laboratory animals are fed standard laboratory diets, so changes in immune responses are generally due to administered immunological stimuli, but this is not necessarily translatable to the clinical situation where dietary conditions vary considerably. Although diet can be controlled during phase 1 clinical trials in human volunteers, such dietary control is much less feasible in later stage trials. Intake of various types of fatty acids, trace elements and fruits rich in vitamins can all affect immune responses. For example, adequate zinc and selenium intake is necessary for the effective functioning of the immune system.
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">59</xref> Among other effects, zinc is important as a cofactor for T‐cell signaling, thereby facilitating differentiation and maturation of T lymphocytes, as well as promoting phagocyte and NK cell function.
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">59</xref> It is often used as an adjuvant treatment for infections and is recommended by the WHO for infectious diarrhea in children in developing countries.
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">60</xref>, 
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">61</xref> Selenium is crucial for the function of the antioxidant glutathione peroxidase family of enzymes and other endogenous selenoproteins, such as thioredoxin reductases. Deficiency of selenium is associated with neutrophil and lymphocyte defects, probably due to inadequate protection of membranes from oxidative injury.
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">62</xref> Vitamin E also exerts a similar protective action on membrane integrity.
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">59</xref> These findings have provided considerable stimulus to the use of dietary supplements to strengthen the immune response. There is also increasing evidence that probiotics such as 
 <italic>Lactobacillus</italic> can not only modify the constitution of the gut microbiome but also promote innate immunity. In this way, they also indirectly enhance adaptive immunity.
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0063" ref-type="ref">63</xref>, 
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0064" ref-type="ref">64</xref>, 
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0065" ref-type="ref">65</xref> Even in laboratory animals, though, dietary changes can occur unexpectedly. In one study in which one of us (MJP) was involved, eicosanoid metabolites, including PGE2, were determined over a period of several years in platelets and inflammatory exudates from different experiments on laboratory rats fed an essential fatty acid deficient diet. With time, the quantities of eicosanoids generated enigmatically increased.
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">66</xref> The source was eventually found to be an unannounced change made by the diet manufacturer in the source of the oil used to ensure essential fatty acid deficiency.
</p>
