<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The COVID-19 pandemic broke out in December of 2019 in a city called Wuhan in the Hubei province of China [
 <xref rid="B1-materials-13-03363" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. COVID-19 is a pneumonia-based disease that is the result of the infection of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). This is believed to be related to Middle East respiratory disease (MERS) and severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) [
 <xref rid="B2-materials-13-03363" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The origin of the disease is suspected to be from a seafood market, however this has not been corroborated [
 <xref rid="B3-materials-13-03363" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The pandemic was declared a global health emergency by the World Health Organisation (WHO) on the 30th of January [
 <xref rid="B4-materials-13-03363" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] with the coronavirus obtaining its official name of COVID-19 on the 11th of February [
 <xref rid="B5-materials-13-03363" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] by the WHO’s director general. As of the 17th of July 2020, there have been 13,788,300 reported cases worldwide with 589,688 deaths [
 <xref rid="B6-materials-13-03363" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. On the 19th of March, WHO issued guidelines for the prevention of infection of COVID-19. They recommended that health care workers use medical masks when treating suspected patients and that these patients also wear masks or covered their mouths when coughing or sneezing [
 <xref rid="B7-materials-13-03363" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The main routes of infection are believed to be from “respiratory fluid droplets” [
 <xref rid="B8-materials-13-03363" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] containing the virus that are between 10 and 5 µm and through aerosols that are less than 5 µm [
 <xref rid="B9-materials-13-03363" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. These droplets can spread the viruses through three different methods; airborne, contact and fomites. Airborne transmission results in direct infection due to the inhalation of droplets in the air. Contact transmission is a result of the droplets landing on an individual and then being transmitted to an area where infection can occur, for example, a hand touching a face. Both airborne and contact droplets can be transmissible within 1 m of an individual who is infected with the virus and coughs or sneezes [
 <xref rid="B10-materials-13-03363" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Fomites are an indirect method whereby the droplets land on a surface and are then transmitted to an individual, for example a door handle [
 <xref rid="B8-materials-13-03363" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In previous influenza infections, the effectiveness of each transmission method was not ranked and guidelines have informed healthcare workers to be vigilant against all forms of transmission by wearing N-95 respirators [
 <xref rid="B11-materials-13-03363" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].
</p>
