<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The innate immune response is the first host defense against virus infection. Influenza A virus (IAV) targets epithelial cells in the respiratory tract for replication. Therefore, it is critical to understand the innate immune mechanisms that protect these cells from infection by IAV. In airway epithelial cells, IAV double-stranded and triphosphorylated RNAs are pathogen associated molecular patterns (PAMPs) detected by receptors such as retinoic acid-inducible gene I (RIGI), melanoma differentiation-associated protein 5 (MDA5), and Toll-like receptor (TLR) 3 (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Upon PAMP detection, several autocrine signaling pathways are initiated, leading to expression of type I and III interferons (IFNs) and other cytokines (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Engagement of type I and type III IFN to their receptors, IFN alpha/beta receptor (IFNAR1-IFNAR2) or IFN lambda receptor 1 (IFNLR1-IL10R2), respectively, results in a paracrine response and subsequent activation of hundreds of IFN-stimulated genes (ISGs), which have antiviral activity and therefore will protect neighboring cells from viral infection (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Signaling events downstream of IFNAR1-IFNAR2 and IFNLR1-IL10R2 are highly similar, despite the sequence and structure of these receptors being extremely different (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). These events include activation of Janus kinase (JAK) family kinases, phosphorylation and dimerization of the signal transducer and activator of transcription 1 (STAT1) and STAT2, association between STAT complexes and interferon responsive factor 9 (IRF9) to form interferon-stimulated gene factor 3 (ISGF3), and translocation of ISGF3 to the nucleus, where it binds to specific DNA elements to induce ISG expression (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Nevertheless, one important difference which confers distinct functions to the two receptors is their cellular and tissue distributions. While type III IFN signaling is particularly important in the epithelial surfaces of the respiratory tract, gastrointestinal tract, skin, liver, or the lining of the blood-brain barrier (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), type I IFN receptor expression in tissues is ubiquitous. In particular, expression of IFNLR1-IL10R2 by respiratory epithelial cells has been shown to be important for antiviral immunity against IAV 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> and in cell culture (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>).
</p>
