<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Most of the viruses that infect humans have developed strategies to counteract the innate immune system by diverse mechanisms. One of the best-characterized examples is mediated by IAV nonstructural protein 1 (NS1). It is known that NS1 inhibits the detection of viral RNA by interacting with RIGI (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) and with the ubiquitin ligases TRIM25 (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) and RIPLET (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), which leads to reduced IRF3 and NF-κB activation and decreased type I IFN production. NS1 also binds directly to double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) and sequesters it, preventing recognition and activation of the 2′,5′-oligo(A) synthetase (OAS)-RNase L pathway (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) and the type I IFN-induced protein kinase RNA activated (PKR) (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). NS1 has also been shown to counteract immune cellular responses by interacting with the RNA posttranscriptional processing machinery (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) and to promote translation of viral mRNA (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). NS1 is involved in the regulation of phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (PI3K) activation by binding to the p85β subunit (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Additionally, the C-terminal tail of H3N2 NS1 was found to act as a histone tail mimic and reduce host transcription (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Other viral components in addition to NS1 may also contribute to viral immune antagonism. For example, the hemagglutinin (HA)-encoding segment of pandemic IAV has been reported to suppress immunogenic cell death (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). The PB1-F2 and PB2 viral proteins have been shown to prevent mitochondrial antiviral-signaling protein (MAVS) activation and IFN induction (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>), and the PA-X protein has been reported to degrade cellular mRNA (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>).
</p>
