<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In comparison to Europe where transnational epidemics of sexually acquired HCV were detected, the molecular epidemiology in the Asia‐Pacific region does not show signs of the parallel existence of an international outbreak [
 <xref rid="jia225618-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="jia225618-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">37</xref>]. By contrasting the genotype profiles of different countries/cities in our review, the high degree of heterogeneity of the leading subtypes, including subtype 1a, 1b, 2a, 3a and 3k, indicated the generally discrete pattern of local transmission of HCV with little spread between territories. The diversity, that sharply contrasted the shared genotypes across European territories, could be the results of the geographical separation between countries in the Asia‐Pacific region, as well as the relatively low connectedness among Asian communities [
 <xref rid="jia225618-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="jia225618-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">37</xref>, 
 <xref rid="jia225618-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">38</xref>]. The molecular evidence reported in the included studies were too slim to confirm the existence of any cross‐border and intercity transmission networks of HCV [
 <xref rid="jia225618-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="jia225618-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="jia225618-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">20</xref>]. The identification of a related sequence between Taiwan and Hong Kong could have been driven by occasional travels without the growth of a sustained transmission network among MSM [
 <xref rid="jia225618-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">20</xref>]. For the related cases reported in China, the delineation of the cluster could be due to the lack of discrimination, given the utilization of the conserved core region for genotyping [
 <xref rid="jia225618-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="jia225618-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">39</xref>]. The inclusion of Australian samples from different cities in the same cluster was not robust enough to assert a genuine transmission event, since the founding subtypes in different regions of Australia were largely identical [
 <xref rid="jia225618-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="jia225618-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">40</xref>]. Demonstration of HCV spread between regions could only be confirmed if a larger intercity cluster is detected. More data at city and national level are required to understand the scale and transmission dynamics of within‐territory and cross‐border HCV networks. Therefore, currently there is no evidence to support the overlap of HCV transmission networks among MSM between territories in the Asia‐Pacific region and with other continents. Yet, in light of the escalating popularity of gay party along with the growing ease of transportation worldwide, the potential risk of cross‐border HCV transmission should not be underestimated [
 <xref rid="jia225618-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">41</xref>].
</p>
