<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Overall, the growth of HCV epidemics among MSM in the Asia‐Pacific region, alongside the lack of information, is a cause for concern. With reference to a systematic review and meta‐analysis, the HCV seroprevalence among HIV‐positive MSM, based on ten included studies in Australia, China, Japan and Taiwan, averaged 9.42% (range: 1.2% to 24.3%), which was higher than that in Europe (n = 21, 7.7%, 2.6% to 18%) but slightly lower than North America (n = 9, 10.7%, 4.3% to 17.9%) [
 <xref rid="jia225618-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">8</xref>]. In comparison to the global HCV seroprevalence among the general population varying between 0.5% and 2.3%, considerably higher estimates were also recorded in some Asian countries: Myanmar (1.0%), Laos (1.1%), Indonesia (2.1%), Cambodia (2.3%), Thailand (2.7%) and Vietnam (6.1%) [
 <xref rid="jia225618-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="jia225618-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">42</xref>]. Furthermore, the high prevalence of HIV (2% to 29%) among the Southeast Asian sex workers, transgender people and MSM has also rendered them to an enhanced risk of sexually acquired HCV infection [
 <xref rid="jia225618-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="jia225618-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">43</xref>]. At present, there is a paucity of published molecular epidemiological data, at both city and country level, on HCV infection resulting from sexual transmission in the Asia‐Pacific region, despite the existence of epidemic risks. From a regional perspective, it is important to conduct molecular studies to illustrate the evolution of HCV, infer phylogenetic relationships and identify sexual networks. The functioning of collaborative HCV cohorts with a regional context might be one of the solutions in strengthening preparedness against HCV epidemics, through the establishment of a regional database, and facilitating epidemiologic analyses [
 <xref rid="jia225618-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">44</xref>].
</p>
