<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The third primate lentiviral protein in which tetherin antagonism has been described is the envelope glycoprotein encoded by HIV-2. As with Vpu, the ability of HIV-2 Env to promote virus release from certain cell types was recognized long before this was attributed to the antagonism of tetherin [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b71-viruses-03-00520">71</xref>]. HIV-2 Env is able to directly interact with tetherin, and like Vpu promotes its cell surface downregulation and sequestration in intracellular compartments, thus excluding tetherin from the site of virus assembly and budding [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31-viruses-03-00520">31</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b65-viruses-03-00520">65</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b72-viruses-03-00520">72</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b73-viruses-03-00520">73</xref>]. The exact determinants of tetherin antagonism in HIV-2 Env have yet to be deciphered, but it is clear that a highly conserved endocytic sorting motif (GYxxϕ) in the gp41 cytoplasmic tail is essential. This motif binds to the clathrin adaptor complex AP-2, and presumably facilitates the re-direction of tetherin molecules away from the plasma membrane, sequestering them in a perinuclear compartment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31-viruses-03-00520">31</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b65-viruses-03-00520">65</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b72-viruses-03-00520">72</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b73-viruses-03-00520">73</xref>]. Several studies have implicated the ectodomain of gp41 in tetherin antagonism [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31-viruses-03-00520">31</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b72-viruses-03-00520">72</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b74-viruses-03-00520">74</xref>], but which regions are important for direct interactions and which are needed to maintain a specific structural conformation of the Env complex is unclear. In this respect, proteolytic processing of the envelope into the subunits gp120 and gp41 is also required, as the unprocessed form (gp160) is unable to promote virus release [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31-viruses-03-00520">31</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b75-viruses-03-00520">75</xref>]. Mutations in the ectodomain of human tetherin render HIV-2 Env incapable of counteracting restriction [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b76-viruses-03-00520">76</xref>] (specifically, an alanine to aspartic acid substitution at position 100 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14-viruses-03-00520">14</xref>]), supporting the model of an interaction between the ectodomains of both proteins.
</p>
