<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are no antiviral drugs or specific therapeutics against RRV infection [
 <xref rid="B311-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">311</xref>]. Vaccination studies are being conducted and one vaccine candidate has even completed phase III clinical trials, but it is still unlicensed, hence, currently unavailable to the general population [
 <xref rid="B314-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">314</xref>]. Therefore, new outbreaks of RRVD are a continuous threat in Australia [
 <xref rid="B318-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">318</xref>], and the virus may also pose a threat to other regions where conditions to enable its propagation are present [
 <xref rid="B309-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">309</xref>]. According to Harley and collaborators [
 <xref rid="B309-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">309</xref>], the conditions that determine the human risk for RRVD are adequate populations of reservoir hosts, vector mosquitoes, and climate conditions for transmission. Since evidence suggests that RRV may be a multi-host pathogen, this must be investigated in-depth across different ecosystems [
 <xref rid="B332-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">332</xref>]. Addressing this issue is definitely challenging, though of utter importance to improve our knowledge about the RRV dynamics and its epidemic potential. Additionally, among climate variables, local rainfall is probably the most important factor that supports RRV spreading in endemic locations, as increased rainfall may increase the abundance and survival of adult vector mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="B328-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">328</xref>,
 <xref rid="B330-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">330</xref>]. However, given the high complexity of RRV ecology, it is imperative to analyze these factors at the local level in order to better predict and control RRVD epidemics [
 <xref rid="B328-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">328</xref>]. Finally, long term studies of RRVD on affected patients, as well as potential effects of previous conditions to induce severe forms of disease by RRV infection are warranted to further explore the impact of this infection.
</p>
