<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The ectodomain of flavivirus envelope protein can be structurally divided into three sub-domains: Domain II is a long finger-like area lying parallel to virus surface and it contains a fusion peptide on its tip; Domain III is an immunoglobulin-like folded structure projecting slightly away from virus surface, and it is linked to the C-terminal stem region and thought to be involved in virus binding; Domain I is an eight-stranded β-barrel that connects domain II and domain III. Previous study with dengue specific mouse monoclonal antibodies indicated that E domain III was the predominant targets for DENV neutralizing antibodies, and antibodies to this region are mainly serotype specific (
 <xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr">Lok et al., 2008</xref>); whereas antibodies specific for fusion loop epitopes (FLE) are usually highly cross-reactive with modest neutralization activities (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Crill and Chang, 2004</xref>). However, in convalescent dengue patient, anti-E Domain III specific neutralizing antibodies only constitute a small proportion of DENV antibody repertoire. Mapping antibody epitope using recombinant envelope proteins, it was found that neutralizing antibody epitopes in human distributed widely across both domain III and domain I/II regions (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Beltramello et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B173" ref-type="bibr">Stettler et al., 2016</xref>), and the depletion of EDIII specific antibodies did not affect the neutralization activity of human immune sera significantly (
 <xref rid="B196" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al., 2012</xref>). Subsequent studies with human samples revealed another class of antibodies that target quaternary epitopes on virus surface, and that these antibodies do not bind to recombinant envelope proteins, but recognize epitopes spanning one dimer or two adjacent dimers of E proteins on the intact virus surface. One group of such antibodies, also called envelope dimer epitope (EDE) antibodies, usually have broad neutralizing activities to all four serotype dengue viruses (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Dejnirattisai et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B157" ref-type="bibr">Rouvinski et al., 2015</xref>).
</p>
