<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This study had several limitations. First, the percentage of positive results for influenza was lower than that anticipated in the sample size calculation (39% vs. 45%). As a result, the accuracy of the estimation of sensitivity and specificity was lower than expected. Second, this study was conducted during an epidemic peak and so the results should be viewed in the context of the conditions during such a period. Positive predictive values decrease when tests are performed with a lower prevalence of the disease, thus the results cannot be extrapolated to a lower prevalence period. Moreover, it must be noted that the results may differ slightly depending on influenza strains and epidemics. Third, this study was conducted in a single care center setting. The results may therefore be specific to the population of this center and may not necessarily be applicable to other patient groups or settings such as children or smaller facilities, for example. Use of the rapid RT-PCR assay at triage in other care settings would depend on the organization of each emergency department and, importantly, on the availability of appropriately trained staff. Fourth, high rates of missing values are reported in 
 <xref rid="pone.0216308.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. This may be partly explained by the lack of a dedicated research nurse or clinical research assistant at triage. Case report forms were completed by the triage nurse under the indirect supervision of a research nurse. This was deliberate in order to evaluate real-world conditions. Finally, patients without fever either at home or on admission to the emergency department were not included. Not all patients who actually have influenza have fever, particularly older people, which may have led to sampling and spectrum bias.[
 <xref rid="pone.0216308.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] Nevertheless, this criterion is very commonly used in studies investigating the performance of novel PCR assay to diagnose influenza.[
 <xref rid="pone.0216308.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0216308.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] Moreover, we decided to include patients if they reported fever at home even if body temperature was normal at inclusion. This decision was made to consider a possible treatment-induced decrease in fever (e.g. paracetamol intake during the hours prior to emergency department admission).
</p>
