<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0100">Of the six studies on mRNA-encoded antibodies reported to date, five used i.v.
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> and one used intratracheal (IT) aerosol
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref> routes of delivery. The i.v. route method primarily delivers mRNA to the liver and spleen to mediate expression of the encoded antibody, whereas the IT route can achieve local expression of antibody in the lung. The liver is an attractive target tissue for mRNA-mediated expression efforts when high serum concentration of antibody is needed, because the liver has an extensive vascular network that provides access to a large number of target cells. Alternatively, if only local expression of antibody is necessary to mediate protection at the site of infection, the number of target cells may not be a critical limiting factor. Since IM administration likely delivers mRNA to a limited number of target cells, we focused on maximizing protein secretion on a per-cell basis to achieve protective serum IgG protein concentrations. We used alphavirus-derived repRNAs, which combine self-amplification of an mRNA message encoding the antibody sequence with co-expression of viral genes that antagonize the host innate immune response.
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> Additionally, with a rapid-response application in mind, we used a nanostructured lipid carrier
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>26</sup>
 </xref> to allow for independent manufacturing of the delivery formulation and target RNA, such that a stockpiled formulation could be mixed at bedside with an RNA encoding a mAb to any target prior to IM administration. In contrast to lipid nanoparticles (LNPs), which encapsulate the target RNA and require co-manufacturing of each component, NLCs bind RNA to the surface upon simple admixing.
</p>
