<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0125">Our experiments suggest that repRNA offers an advantage over modified or unmodified non-replicating mRNA after IM delivery, resulting in over 30-fold increase in serum concentrations of antibody. Additionally, pseudouridine-modified mRNA did not improve antibody expression 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> compared to unmodified mRNA, in contrast with other studies demonstrating improved translation using the former approach. However, a number of factors differ between studies including the type of encoded transgene, the route of administration, and method of formulation. Most studies reporting large increases in translation due to pseudouridine-modifications did so using intracellular reporter genes such as luciferase or green fluorescent protein,
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>37</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>67</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>68</sup>
 </xref> which are less likely to induce ER stress-related shutdown of gene expression. For studies that did evaluate the effect of pseudouridine modification on protein secretion, those reporting enhancement did so within the context of dendritic cell transfections 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>68</sup>
 </xref> or following intraperitoneal (i.p.) injection 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> with the same formulation.
 <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>38</sup>
 </xref> In contrast, those reporting no enhancement or reduction in protein secretion 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> associated with pseudouridine modification did so using LNP formulation and i.v. injection
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>69</sup>
 </xref> or using TransIT formulation and i.p.injection.
 <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>70</sup>
 </xref> We used IM injection of NLC-formulated modified or unmodified mRNA and did not observe an improvement in antibody secretion into the serum of mice nor any difference in expression kinetics.
</p>
