<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">The genome sequence of SARS-CoV-2 was rapidly determined and revealed the virus is most closely related to bat coronavirus RaTG13 and clusters phylogenetically with SARS-CoV, which emerged in 2002, in the genus 
 <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic> of the family 
 <italic>Coronaviridae</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Based on homology to other known coronaviruses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], the genome sequence was used for viral transcript prediction and the annotation of ORFs. Coronaviruses use a complex strategy to express their genetic information [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], involving a process of discontinuous transcription during minus-strand RNA synthesis that is regulated by defined transcription regulatory sequences (TRS) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Similar, to other coronaviruses, the SARS-CoV-2 29.9 kB RNA genome contains two large ORFs, ORF1a and ORF1ab, predicted to be initially translated into the polyproteins, pp1a and pp1ab that arises by programmed (− 1) ribosomal frameshifting (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). The polyproteins are post-translationally processed by viral encoded proteases to produce 16 proteins that are conserved between coronaviruses and proposed to function in the synthesis of viral RNA and immune evasion [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. During viral genome replication a set of “nested” subgenomic mRNAs are produced that are predicted to encode the structural proteins spike (S), envelope (E), membrane (M) and nucleocapsid (N) and at least nine small accessory proteins, some of which are unique to SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The subgenomic mRNAs have a common 5′ leader sequence and are 3′ co-terminal with a polyA tail derived from the viral genome. 
</p>
