<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The cooler climate experienced in northern latitudes (above 50°) means that there are fewer species and less diversity among particular arthropod species and the viruses they harbour than found in subtropical and tropical regions. Currently, there are few arthropod-borne diseases of livestock in Europe and as a result, livestock in the UK and many areas of northern Europe may be highly susceptible to many arthropod-borne viruses listed in 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab2">Table 2</xref>. The health impact of an emergence of one could likely be severe. An exception to this is the presence of louping ill virus, which is considered to be the only arbovirus of veterinary importance that is endemic within the UK. The virus has been present for hundreds of years and is restricted to moorland locations, particularly in Devon, Cumbria, Wales, and Scotland [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. This tick-borne virus causes fatal encephalitic disease in sheep, although it has been reported in a range of other species. A number of reports have suggested that West Nile virus and two other mosquito-borne viruses had been introduced into the UK, although cases of disease in horses have not been reported [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. This is in clear contrast to the situation in Italy where WNV has repeatedly emerged to cause neurologic disease in horses from the Tuscany Region [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Recurring outbreaks of disease have occurred in both livestock and humans suggesting the permanent establishment of this virus in the mosquito population [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. This has made assessment of future climate change trends essential to understanding the impact on both the ecology of the UK and risk of vector-borne disease introduction and establishment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Such changes might enhance the establishment of invasive arthropod species such as the Asian tiger mosquito (
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic>) that in turn could directly import an exotic virus. It could also boost the population of indigenous vectors that could in turn increase the numbers of biting events, enhancing the likelihood of virus transmission. Furthermore, increases in temperatures can shorten the extrinsic incubation period, the time between the vector taking a blood meal and becoming infectious to a new host, thus enhancing virus persistence in a new area. 
</p>
