<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Additionally, some of the smaller TAP and CRL (CAP projects) studies demonstrated higher impact and success than the larger CBR projects because the project activity could be performed with a smaller number of researchers and required less coordination that would be necessary with researchers from various institutes in Kazakhstan. KZ-29 and TAP-2 were performed concurrently and leveraged the same project resources to fulfill both studies. The TAP-2 tick identification study which was designed to apply molecular methods, including using quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) assays, to confirm the identification of ticks to the level of genus and species when the conventional visual identification was questionable due to inconclusive morphology and life stage presentation. Questing adult ticks were collected by tick drag during spring and summer from 2012–2014 in seven administrative rayons (county level) of West Kazakhstan oblast (province level). The total number of ticks collected (n = 2232) were identified according to visual morphological methods which resulted in four genera: 
 <italic>Dermacentor</italic> (n = 2097), 
 <italic>Hyalomma</italic> (n = 4), 
 <italic>Rhipicephalus</italic> (n = 126), and 
 <italic>Ixodes</italic> (n = 5). After DNA extraction, 
 <italic>Dermacentor</italic> and 
 <italic>Ixodes</italic> tick pools were tested using tick genus-specific assays that produced results in concordance with conventional visual identification [
 <xref rid="B2-tropicalmed-04-00136" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Additional tests were run to exclude cross-reaction and ensure fidelity of the 
 <italic>Dermacentor</italic> and 
 <italic>Ixodes</italic> assays. A partner country scientist from UAPS presented this data in a poster at the 2013 Conference of Research Workers in Animal Diseases (CRWAD) and demonstrated the utility of a molecular PCR-based method to complement and enhance tick identification [
 <xref rid="B12-tropicalmed-04-00136" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The KZ-29 and TAP-2 examples demonstrated synergy through linking the studies in a practical manner.
</p>
