<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>From previous pandemics, we know that only two substitutions in the HA RBD may be required to confer binding preference for receptors on cells of the human URT.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib98">98</xref>
 </sup> When previous pandemic viruses were evaluated for their receptor recognition, it was demonstrated that amino-acid substitutions in HA resulting in a human receptor binding preference were a prerequisite for cross-species transmission and human adaptation of avian influenza viruses.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib99">99</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib100">100</xref>
 </sup> However, just changing the receptor specificity of HPAI H5N1 virus was insufficient to confer airborne transmission between ferrets.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib101">101</xref>
 </sup> A reassortant virus carrying the surface proteins of an avian H9N2 virus with the other genes derived from a human H3N2 virus was transmitted efficiently via the airborne route between ferrets. The airborne transmissible H9 HA protein contained the Q226L RBD substitution and two others; T189A and R192G.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref>
 </sup> Inefficient transmission between ferrets was observed for a virus containing a clade 2.2 H5N1 influenza virus HA with human receptor specificity, a human NA gene and six other gene segments from a clade 1 HPAI H5N1 virus.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib97">97</xref>
 </sup> This study elaborated on the complexity of genetic changes in influenza viruses required for adaptation and airborne transmission. Herfst 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref>
 </sup> demonstrated that the HPAI H5N1 virus A/Indonesia/5/05 (clade 2.1), harboring E627K in PB2 and Q226L and G228S in HA, was not transmitted via the airborne route between ferrets. However, when this virus was forced to adapt to replicate in cells of the mammalian URT by repeated passage in ferrets, this virus was transmitted. Besides the three substitutions that were introduced by reverse genetics, only few additional substitutions were observed in the virus genome, of which two in HA were consistently detected in airborne-transmissible virus isolates (H110Y and T160A). The receptor binding properties of this airborne-transmissible H5N1 virus HA were determined via structural and biophysical studies, which showed increased affinity for human receptors and decreased affinity for avian receptors.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib102">102</xref>
 </sup> Imai 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref>
 </sup> showed that similar changes in the HA that changed the receptor binding preference (N224K and Q226L) yielded an airborne-transmissible H5, but also here additional substitutions in HA were required. This virus contained the HPAI H5 HA of A/Vietnam/1203/04 (clade 1) and the remaining seven gene segments from a A(H1N1)pdm09 virus. The airborne virus had only four amino-acid substitutions in HA compared to the wild-type HA. Quantitative biophysical measurements demonstrated that this airborne-transmissible H5 HA acquired specificity for human over avian receptors, comparable to previous pandemic strains.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib103">103</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib104">104</xref>
 </sup> The Q226L amino-acid substitution contributed substantially to the human receptor binding preference and to the marked decrease in avian receptor binding. The studies on the airborne-transmissible H5 viruses enabled structural analyses of the HA RBD from these viruses, and consequently, highlighted the features necessary for human receptor binding.
</p>
