<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0195">The influence of the CCR5Δ32 variant on HCV infection susceptibility was investigated by several studies. 
 <xref rid="bib1615" ref-type="bibr">Woitas et al. (2002)</xref> found a significantly higher frequency of the CCR5Δ32 homozygous genotype in HCV-infected individuals compared to controls, HIV-infected and HCV/HIV co-infected individuals, suggesting the CCR5Δ32 as a risk factor for HCV infection. In agreement, the Δ32 allele was a significant risk factor for infection when the authors compared the HCV-infected group to both controls and HIV-infected individuals. Moreover, the CCR5Δ32 homozygous genotype was associated with increased HCV loads. In their study, it was observed an important deviation from the Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium in data from HCV-infected individuals; and a high portion of the individuals included in the study was hemophiliac (
 <xref rid="bib1615" ref-type="bibr">Woitas et al., 2002</xref>). Hemophiliac individuals were at high risk of exposure to HCV and HIV until the mid-1980s (
 <xref rid="bib1175" ref-type="bibr">Promrat et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib1670" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2003</xref>). Considering that the CCR5Δ32 homozygous genotype provides protection against HIV infection, a high frequency of this genotype in an HCV-infected group may be due to HIV resistance, but not to HCV, among individuals highly exposed to both viruses. Due to those and other reasons, the results of 
 <xref rid="bib1615" ref-type="bibr">Woitas et al. (2002)</xref> were criticized by different authors (
 <xref rid="bib0755" ref-type="bibr">Klein, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0970" ref-type="bibr">Mangia et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib1170" ref-type="bibr">Poljak et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib1175" ref-type="bibr">Promrat et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib1670" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2003</xref>). In this sense, no influence of CCR5Δ32 on susceptibility to HCV infection were reported in studies performed with various populations (
 <xref rid="bib0510" ref-type="bibr">Glas et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0970" ref-type="bibr">Mangia et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib1170" ref-type="bibr">Poljak et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib1175" ref-type="bibr">Promrat et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib1670" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib1240" ref-type="bibr">Ruiz-Ferrer et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib1590" ref-type="bibr">Wald et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib1600" ref-type="bibr">Wasmuth et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib1490" ref-type="bibr">Thoelen et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0555" ref-type="bibr">Goyal et al., 2006</xref>). Reinforcing the observations of those different studies, our group found no association between the CCR5Δ32 and susceptibility to HCV infection or HCV/HIV co-infection in a study that evaluated a large number of Brazilian individuals (
 <xref rid="bib0410" ref-type="bibr">Ellwanger et al., 2018b</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr">Bineshian et al. (2018)</xref> did not detect the CCR5Δ32 allele in any Iranian HCV-infected individual and controls included in their study, preventing any conclusion in terms of susceptibility in that population. Finally, it is important to mention that in addition to the study by 
 <xref rid="bib1615" ref-type="bibr">Woitas et al. (2002)</xref>, a study performed in 2013 also found an association between the CCR5Δ32 homozygous genotype with chronic HCV infection in Europeans, but the authors of the study mentioned that specific factors regarding selection bias (
 <italic>e.g.</italic>, co-exposure to HIV) may have influenced their results (
 <xref rid="bib1435" ref-type="bibr">Suppiah et al., 2013</xref>). Taken together, the above-mentioned results called attention for the importance of performing genetic variant studies in different populations, exposed to different social and environmental factors and presenting distinct ethnic backgrounds.
</p>
