<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>HFRS is transmitted to human by contact with rodent urine, feces or saliva 
 <xref rid="pone.0061536-Jonsson1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0061536-Lee1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. For this reason, the fluctuations in abundance of rodent host are considered as an important reason for temporal variations in human infections of HFRS. Human nephropathia epidemica (NE) epidemics, a mild form of HFRS, have been observed a close relation with bank vole populations in many countries in Europe 
 <xref rid="pone.0061536-BrummerKorvenkontio1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0061536-Niklasson1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0061536-Olsson1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Human hantavirus epidemics can be accurately predicted solely by the population dynamics of the host, even without knowledge of the degree of hantavirus infection of the involved rodent reservoir 
 <xref rid="pone.0061536-Kallio1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. In recent years, the relationship between HFRS and host population have been observed in China as well. The rise and falls of incidence rate was found generally coincident with rodent density, and a statistical correlation was presented between the incidence rate and rodent density 
 <xref rid="pone.0061536-Qin1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. It is therefore important to know more about the laws between rodents and environment, which have implications for HFRS control and prevention. Population fluctuations generally are driven by a combination of multiple environmental factors 
 <xref rid="pone.0061536-Bjrnstad1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0061536-Stenseth1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. The climatic variables and food supply are important indicator for the rodent population 
 <xref rid="pone.0061536-Ernest1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. the close relationship among rodent population, rainfall and food was found by compared the two rodent species utilizing exploratory analyses of species densities with time series statistical tools 
 <xref rid="pone.0061536-Previtali1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. It is therefore necessary to have more knowledge about the dynamics of the rodent host and their interactions with natural environment. However, the quantitative relationship among climatic variables, food available and host population remains to be determined.
</p>
