<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0010">Regarding transfusion resources, what do those pandemics say? The majority of recent emergent viruses did not widely threaten blood safety as, even theoretically possible or in some cases described (WNV, dengue, Zika), the transmission by blood seems to be less efficient than the natural transmission. Moreover, the majority of infected donors become viremic principally during the symptomatic phase (and are excluded from blood donation), or shortly before it (24 h). This is to be tuned down, however, as there are asymptomatic carriers. Apparently, at least according to the current knowledge, SARS-CoV-2 infection is not responsible for asymptomatic viremia; conditions of transmission through blood will have to be verified on a large scale. However, the inventory has been threatened, because of exclusions due to the precaution, to quarantine or confinement applied by many countries to the global population, and fears causing self-exclusions. In the meantime, the needs have been reduced because of the limitation of planed surgery, but patients suffering cancer, hematological disorders of various causes, and injured persons still need that blood components are made available and prescribed. The situation is extremely serious in remote areas depending on metropoles to be shipped blood components in total or part, due to the limitation of flights. To which extent COVID-19 care requires blood transfusion remains to be estimated; at a glance, virus-induced inflammation could lead to severe anemia requiring assistance. A next question which promptly arose was the relevance of accessing convalescent plasma by apheresis and to apply safety means to it (i.e., by pathogen reduction or inactivation technologies) 
 <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>; same as for previous infectious threats, decisions to collect may anticipate basic immunological data: Does past-infection lead to neutralizing antibodies (NAbs), in which amount, at which time after virus clearance? And do NAbs help, when symptoms clearly evoke cytokine storms; in other words, to which category of patients would NAbs be infused? 
 <xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref> Further, is it safe (for himself/herself) to collect 600 mL of plasma — or more — in a just recovering patient? Which ethical clearance for so doing in a rush? Clearly, choices are to be made.
</p>
