<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As presented earlier, at least four independent GWAS studies provide significant evidence for the role of the IL28B gene in the pathogenesis of HCV infection (Ge et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2009</xref>; Suppiah et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR165">2009</xref>). However, still more pieces of data are needed to complete the mechanistic picture (Thio and Thomas 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR167">2010</xref>). The IL28B gene encodes IFN-lambda-3, which is one of the recently discovered type III interferons (or lambda interferons), and belongs to the IL10 superfamily (Dellgren et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2009</xref>). Other type III interferons are the cytokines IL28A and IL29. Some murine studies have revealed the preferential expression of IFN-lambda receptors on epithelial surfaces and have suggested that type III interferons may allow the host to rapidly eliminate viruses at the major portals of entry into the body before infection is established, without activating other arms of the immune system (Ank et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2006</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2008</xref>; Ank and Paludan 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2009</xref>). Nonetheless, one important difference established between the murine and human systems is that the interleukin (Liapakis and Jacobson 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">2010</xref>); receptor alpha chain (receptor complex induced by IFN-lambda) is expressed in human hepatocytes, whereas the murine liver seems unlikely to respond to IFN-lambda (Ank et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2006</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2008</xref>; Ank and Paludan 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2009</xref>). This finding suggests that IFN-lambda contributes to host defense against hepatotropic viruses, such as HCV in humans. Like type I interferons, lambda interferons have activity against HCV and other viral infections in vitro and in vivo (Marcello et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">2006</xref>). However, in vitro exogenous IFN-lambda induces a slower, more sustained abundance of IFN-stimulated genes than IFN-alpha (Marcello et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">2006</xref>). Although these findings answer why IFN-lambda might play a key role in HCV recovery, they do not explain why treatment-associated resolution of HCV infection is associated with certain base sequences located upstream of the start codon for the cytokine IL28B (Thio and Thomas 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR167">2010</xref>).
</p>
