<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The current PPR control and eradication strategy includes administration of a live-attenuated vaccine, which following one inoculation provides lifelong immunity to all PPRV lineages as well as detectable antibodies. There is an ongoing debate about the recruitment rate of newly susceptible sheep and goats into small ruminant populations following vaccination, and how this may require more frequent vaccinations than the annual ones that proved so successful during rinderpest eradication. In addition, currently, a lot of vaccination (carried out for political reason in the pastoral areas close to elections) do not reach sufficient levels of immunity to interrupt transmission. The most challenging practical issues are related to the delivery of vaccines to small ruminants at sufficient intensity to generate herd immunity levels that are able to prevent the re-introduction of disease. This could be investigated through estimating the R
 <sub>0</sub> value for the PPRV through computer modelling; however, empirical data would be persuasive. Within the pastoral area, there is often a lack of harmonisation of vaccination campaigns at the epizone level. This is also due to the lack of simultaneous funding of PPR activities in neighboring countries. Of note, it was difficult enough to generate these levels of herd immunity for rinderpest, and we must acknowledge the fact that small ruminant numbers are far greater than those of cattle and buffaloes are. Indeed, the virus could be cycling persistently at a low frequency among extensive rural small ruminant populations, much as rinderpest did in eastern African pastoral cattle. There is therefore a need for countries to define precise eradication strategies and implement them in a dynamic manner. The concept of using repeat pulses of extremely efficient vaccination, separated by short time intervals, in defined areas was developed for measles control and was adapted successfully for eliminating rinderpest in Tanzania in 1997 [
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-12-00313" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. This technique might be explored further by epidemiological modelling with the hope that it can break virus transmission in endemic areas, when supported by good clinical disease surveillance. Recent mass pulsed vaccination in southern Ethiopia demonstrated the feasibility of rapid area-wide clearance of PPRV infection [
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-12-00313" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. A study in Karamoja (Uganda) suggested that integrating the supply chain of PPR vaccine with other veterinary or health commodities could reduce costs, as well as increase uptake [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-12-00313" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Separately, maintenance of an effective cold chain for this vaccine has also proven difficult in subtropical countries. Implementation of a thermotolerant live-attenuated conventional or recombinant vaccine may represent the best way to avoid cold chain-associated problems in these areas.
</p>
