<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="vaccines-07-00045-f002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Framework for computational influenza universal vaccine design. (
   <bold>A</bold>) Model-free consensus-based optimized approach. Consensus sequences from previously defined clusters are generated by aligning and comparing multiple sequences and selecting the most common residue at each position. It may go through several steps until the generation of a final consensus. (
   <bold>B</bold>) Model-based ancestral sequence reconstruction approach. Maximum likelihood and Bayesian approaches are the most commonly used statistical phylogenetic methods to reconstruct ancestral sequence at the ancestral node (shown as black dot on the tree) [
   <xref rid="B46-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
   <xref rid="B47-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
   <xref rid="B48-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Evolutionary models that incorporate protein structural domains can be used to separately estimate the evolutionary history on each functional partition as the HA head and stalk domains. Based on the evolutionary relationship among different subtypes of influenza A virus, common ancestral sequences of head and stalk domains can be generated within influenza A virus Group 1 (H1, H2, H5, H6, H7, H8, H9, H11, H12, H13, H16, H17, and H18) and within Group 2 (H3, H4, H7, H10, H14, and H15), respectively. (
   <bold>C</bold>) Immunomics approach. The T-cell epitope prediction tools can be used to identify the potential CD4+ T-cell and CD8+ T-cell epitopes from the pathogen proteome or protein(s) based on the high binding affinity between epitope-Major Histocompatibility Complex (MHC) complex. Some epitopes will be presented by the MHC-I on the surface of infected cells or by MHC-II on the surface of antigen presenting cells (APC) to the host CD8+ or CD4+ T-cells, respectively. These processes elicit the cellular and/or humoral immunity. The predicted T-cell epitopes that are evolutionarily conserved and common across or within subtypes will be constructed into peptides or proteins. All outputs from these three approaches, like epitopes, peptides, proteins or virus-like particles (VLPs), will be tested at in-vitro and/or in-vivo models to evaluate their immunogenicity. The proposed concept as shown is based on HA gene sequences, but these approaches should be used for all the gene segments of influenza viruses to generate a full profile of viral immunogenicity.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="vaccines-07-00045-g002" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
