<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0006">As of 21 February 2020, more than 80 000 cases of COVID-19 have been confirmed and most of them had a history of close contact with the epidemic area or with confirmed patients. Major initial symptoms include fever, most of which are high fevers that occur within several days and are not alleviated by routine anti-infective drugs, as well as cough, headache and muscle pain or fatigue 
 <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Other clinical symptoms observed at a lower frequency include elevated troponin levels, diarrhoea, myalgia and myocarditis 
 <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. It should be emphasised that some asymptomatic persons are infected with SARS-CoV-2 
 <xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, therefore the presence of asymptomatic carriers requires due attention. In one study, nearly 20% of patients appeared to have co-morbidities with regard to dysfunction of other organs, primarily renal impairment, and patients with underlying cardiovascular diseases often demonstrated co-morbid heart failure 
 <xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. Patients gradually develop initial symptoms in the cardiovascular system, digestive system and nervous system, which increases the difficulty of diagnosis 
 <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. In this study, the median interval from the start of initial symptoms to significant symptom aggravation such as dyspnoea or the appearance of acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) was 7 days (range 1–20 days), which is consistent with previous reports 
 <xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. According to the newly released pneumonitis diagnosis and treatment plan for novel coronavirus infection, severe patients often have dyspnoea and/or hypoxaemia 1 week after the onset of the illness. Serious cases can quickly progress to ARDS, septic shock, irreformable metabolic acidosis, coagulopathy and multiple organ failure. Nearly 80% of patients have normal or decreased white blood cell counts, and 72.3% have lymphocytopenia 
 <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Lung involvement is present in all cases 
 <xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">[19</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">20]</xref>, with most chest computed tomography (CT) images showing lesions in multiple lung lobes, some of which are dense. Ground-glass opacity co-existing with consolidation shadows or cord-like shadows are observed. Since respiratory support is administered to most patients, oxygen saturation can be maintained above 90% as indicated by pulse oximetry monitoring 
 <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. It is reported that severe and critically ill patients have moderate to low fever, or even without obvious fever. Mild patients show only low fever, mild fatigue and no pneumonia. Judging from the current cases, most patients have a good prognosis, but it is poor for the elderly and those with chronic underlying diseases. Symptoms in children are relatively mild.
</p>
