<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The extrinsic incubation period, which is the time between oral infection and presence of virus in the saliva of vectors, is a major determinant of transmission efficiency [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. We established the kinetics of ZIKV infection, dissemination and transmission in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> by measuring viral RNA in mosquito tissues and live virus in saliva and mosquito organs and tissues and measured viral RNA in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> tissues and live virus in saliva. Our findings support an extrinsic incubation period (EIP) of approximately 10 days in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> under the conditions tested. We found that there were dose-dependent thresholds for infection of salivary glands in both species. Surprisingly, despite the lower transmission percentages observed for 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> compared to 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic>, the estimated threshold for transmission was also lower. The result suggests factors other than disseminated viral titre may be responsible for the transmission percentages observed in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic>. Possible explanations for the lower ZIKV transmission percentages at 14 dpi for 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic>, compared to 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic>, is that EIP is longer in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic>, and/or may be modulated significantly by temperature. This has important public health implications for preparedness, and efficient implementation of mosquito control efforts. A recent study reported that the administration of a second, non-infectious blood meal significantly shortened the EIP of ZIKV-infected 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> by enhancing virus escape from the mosquito midgut [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> may therefore be more competent for ZIKV transmission under field conditions of frequent feeding, suggesting the risk of an outbreak mediated by this vector may be higher than is indicated by our data. Whether this holds true for Australian 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> remains to be determined. Last, we observed ZIKV staining in mosquito ovarian tissue, limited to the follicular epithelium surrounding developing eggs. This may indicate a potential route of infection leading to vertical transmission, which has been observed recently from field specimens collected as larvae [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].
</p>
