<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite the introduction of these initiatives, visual inspection of our data (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="BMJOPEN2015009333F1">figures 1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="BMJOPEN2015009333F2">2</xref>) shows no apparent step change consistent with a sudden change in the regulatory environment (such as the creation of the EMA or implementation of the EU Clinical Trials Directive). This may be expected given the long lead times for planning and conducting clinical trial programmes, though further analysis shows no association between the duration of clinical development and the year when clinical development started (r=0.04, y=−0.16+399.67, p=0.80). However, the impact of regulators can be seen in the shorter development durations seen for HIV drugs, which have previously been reported as receiving Marketing Authorisation without ‘large-scale human clinical trials’,
 <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> though our data suggest this difference is now lessening. This is an example of regulators responding to a public health need and being willing to adopt a different view of the risk-benefit in specific circumstances.
 <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> One current regulatory development applicable to the UK is the MHRA's Early Access to Medicines Scheme, which allows patients with serious conditions to access medicines that have not yet been approved where there is a clear unmet medical need.
 <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> This will not necessarily reduce time to Marketing Authorisation, but may facilitate collection of real-world data to support earlier adoption of innovative new drugs. In this way it has parallels with the EMA's adaptive licensing pilot, but this EU-wide initiative also has the potential to bring forward the date of a drugs initial Marketing Authorisation, allowing first approval in highly selected patient populations based on more limited initial clinical studies.
 <xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> Both these examples are indicative of a wider move towards early dialogue between regulators and commercial developers,
 <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> a move mirrored by health technology assessment (HTA) agencies in Europe, either alone or in parallel with regulators.
 <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
 <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> Early dialogue may or may not lead to a reduction in clinical development durations, but it is likely to be reflected in the design and conduct of late-phase clinical trial programmes.
 <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
 <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> This will have an uncertain effect on clinical trial times if HTA agencies demand longer term patient-related outcomes rather than proxy measures on which to judge value, but it may be expected to speed up the total time to adoption and diffusion of those drugs judged to be most clinically and cost-effective.
</p>
