<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As the terminal UTR sequences could not be determined previously by next generation sequencing [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008166.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], the viral RNA was circularised following the method adapted by Khromykh 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008166.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008166.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Briefly, BgV supernatant from two T175 flasks of C6/36 infected cells was PEG precipitated by adding one part of 40% PEG8000 in TNE (12 mM Tris at pH 8, 120 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA pH8) to four parts of infected cell culture supernatant and spinning on a rotary shaker overnight and centrifuging for one hour at 21,612 g (12,000 rpm; JLA 16.250 rotor Beckman) at 4°C. The precipitated virus pellet was resuspended in 500μL sterile PBS. RNA was extracted from the purified virions using the Macherey Nagel RNA isolation kit following the manufacturer’s instructions. RNA extracts were quantified using Nanodrop (Biolab ND-1000 Spectrophotometer). One microgram of RNA was decapped with tobacco acid pyrophosphatase at 37°C for one hour and circularised with T4 RNA ligase at 4°C overnight. The circularised RNA was reverse transcribed to cDNA with Superscript III (Thermo-Fisher Scientific) with a BgV reverse primer specific for the prM gene (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0008166.s002">S1 Table</xref>). A PCR product containing the joined UTRs was amplified with Phusion High Fidelity DNA polymerase (NEB) in a high-fidelity buffer and Sanger sequenced by the Australian Genome Research Facility (AGRF, Brisbane). The junction site of the end of the 3’ UTR and the start of the 5’ UTR was determined based on consensus established from alignment of flavivirus UTR sequences and confirmed by reverse transcription PCR (RT-PCR) using primers specific for these ends (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0008166.s002">S1 Table</xref>) and SuperScript III One-Step RT-PCR System with Platinum Taq DNA Polymerase (Invitrogen).
</p>
