<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to the mechanistic questions of profound importance, the recent GWAS findings on genetic variation as a predictor of outcome in patients treated for HCV infection will have major practical implications. Several recent GWAS studies have demonstrated remarkable associations between SNPs near or within the region of the IL28B gene, which codes for IFN-lambda-3 (Ge et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2009</xref>; Suppiah et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR165">2009</xref>; Tanaka et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR166">2009</xref>; Rauch et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR143">2010</xref>). These results promise to lead to important mechanistic findings related to IFN responsiveness in this disease and will probably have major contributions for individualized medicine and therapeutic decision making. Ge and colleagues suggest that, in the near future, advance knowledge of the genotype of patients infected with HCV could become an important component of the clinical decision to initiate treatment. These findings may also lead to more individualized treatment regimens with regard to both the chosen medicines and the duration of therapy (Ge et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2009</xref>; Suppiah et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR165">2009</xref>; Tanaka et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR166">2009</xref>; Rauch et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR143">2010</xref>). Moreover, the critical importance of the IL28B gene region in mediating response has emphasized interest in the development of IFN-lambda as a therapeutic agent for patients with CHC (Doyle et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2006</xref>; Pagliaccetti et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">2008</xref>). For instance, the early studies of a pegylated form of IL29 (IFN-lambda-1) have demonstrated promising antiviral activity with the potential benefit of reduced hematologic toxicity, owing to the hepatocyte-specific receptor profile for IFN-lambda (versus IFN-alpha) (Doyle et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2006</xref>; Pagliaccetti et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">2008</xref>).
</p>
