<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">Even though the limited size of the study precludes conclusions on any subtle qualitative differences between regimens, a generally high degree of polyfunctionality was detected in the antigen-specific CD4+ T-cell response in the periphery, and in CD4+ and CD8+ T cells in the lung at the post boost peak response for all three regimens. No non-Adenoviral comparator platform was included in this study, but a similarly high degree of polyfunctionality was observed after heterologous intramuscular electroporation reported above by Grunwald et al.,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>, but not after a homologous intramuscular electroporation DNA/DNA regimen.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup> Whether the induction of strong, polyfunctional antigen-specific T cells with the ability to migrate to the lung may be an inherent quality of Adenoviral vectored vaccines, irrespective of the route of administration remains to be confirmed. Contradicting previously observed insensitivity of the T-cell compartment to respond to repeated homologous administration of Adenoviral vectors,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup> we observed expansion of RSV-F-specific immune responses, including T cells in blood and BAL, irrespective of whether the boost was heterologous (
 <italic>n</italic> = 5) or homologous (
 <italic>n</italic> = 10). Although boost immunization occurred in the presence of vector targeting immunity induced by the prime immunization, as evidenced by the presence of vector neutralizing antibodies (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>), the responses induced by the homologous regimens did not consistently differ in magnitude, quality, or durability compared with the heterologous regimen, indicating that the negative impact of anti-vector immunity on vaccine immunogenicity was limited for these Ad26/Ad35-based vaccine regimens.
</p>
