<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Rabies virus (RABV) is the prototype species of the genus 
 <italic>Lyssavirus</italic> in the family 
 <italic>Rhabdoviridae</italic> and order 
 <italic>Mononegavirales</italic>. Members of this genus are the etiological agent of rabies, an acute, progressive encephalitis that affects mammals, and without proper postexposure prophylaxis results almost invariably in death. RABV is most commonly transmitted to the next host by saliva during the bite of an infected animal. Prevention of rabies through various interventions, including pre-exposure vaccination of domestic animals such as dogs and cats, and postexposure prophylaxis (PEP) in people before clinical onset are highly effective. Pre-exposure prophylaxis in humans can also be indicated in individuals at high risk, such as veterinarians, animal handlers, and laboratory personnel. For PEP, rabies immune globulin is injected around the site of the animal bite, and a regimen of rabies vaccine is administered at a distal site [
 <xref rid="B1-viruses-12-00177" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Despite the reduction of human rabies through canine rabies elimination programs involving elimination of stray dogs and animal vaccination programs, an estimated 59,000 people die annually of rabies from dog bites around the world [
 <xref rid="B2-viruses-12-00177" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. In the United States, an average of two people die annually of rabies, usually transmitted by bats [
 <xref rid="B3-viruses-12-00177" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In some cases, aggressive treatment of the disease has been attempted in an effort to improve patient outcomes [
 <xref rid="B4-viruses-12-00177" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In these cases, various antiviral drugs have been used with poor results [
 <xref rid="B5-viruses-12-00177" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Currently no approved RABV-specific antiviral drug is available. Difficulty in delivering potential antiviral drugs to the central nervous system (CNS) contributes to the lack of effective treatment, and rabies antiviral drugs will most likely be dosed into the cerebrospinal fluid to block viral replication and spread [
 <xref rid="B6-viruses-12-00177" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].
</p>
