<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?OLF?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Microbiol Infect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Microbiol Infect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Clinical Microbiology and Infection</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1198-743X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1469-0691</issn><publisher><publisher-name>European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7506363</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1198-743X(20)30559-0</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2020.09.010</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Letter to the Editor</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Surging publications on the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Guanqiao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Yangzhong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Junyi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Xiaozhen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Qiao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Linqi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1)</label>Tsinghua Clinical Research Institute, School of Medicine, Tsinghua University, Beijing, China</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2)</label>School of Medicine and Vanke School of Public Health, Tsinghua University, Beijing, China</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3)</label>Peking Union Medical College Hospital, Beijing, China</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4)</label>School of Medicine, Tsinghua University, Beijing, China</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author: L. Zhang.</corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>&#x02020;</label><p id="ntpara0010">G. Li and Y. Zhou contributed equally to the work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>22</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>2</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases. Published by Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta><notes><p id="misc0010">Editor: L. Leibovici</p></notes></front><body><p content-type="salutation">To the Editor</p><p id="p0010">Few infectious diseases have posed such tremendous challenges as coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), which had swept across 216 countries or territories by 29 August 2020. In response, an unprecedented upsurge of research has been witnessed [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. To assess the pattern and scale of COVID-19 research, we searched for &#x02018;nCov&#x02019;, &#x02018;COVID-19&#x02019; or &#x02018;SARS-CoV-2&#x02019; in Embase, MEDLINE and Cochrane CENTRAL databases through 31 March 2020 (see Supplementary material, <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix S1</xref>). A total of 1431 out of 3780 publications were included and further manually divided into eight mutually exclusive categories with regards to research topics (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>
a; Supplementary material, <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Table&#x000a0;S1</xref>).<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Analysis of research activities for coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) and severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS). Research publications were classified into eight categories for COVID-19 (a, 1 December 2019 to 31 March 2020) and SARS (b, 1 November 2002 to 31 December 2003), respectively. Detailed study selection process, classification criteria are provided in the Supplementary material (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix S1 and Table S1</xref>).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig.&#x000a0;1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p><p id="p0015">Clinical observational studies appeared at the fastest speed. As of 31 March 2020, the number was 625 (44%). Of note, 70 publications analysed radiographic manifestations and emphasized their diagnostic roles supplementary to nucleic acid testing. These findings translated into guidelines of the appropriate application of imaging in managing patients [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Epidemiological studies ranked second with 210 (15%) publications, describing transmission routes, incubation period and reproduction number. The number of basic research publications grew steadily to 116 (8%). Viral genomic evolution and the structural basis of spike&#x02013;receptor interaction were identified. Interestingly, studies on diagnostic assays, and therapeutic and preventive medications initially followed the pace of basic research, but preceded it since late February, reflecting the high demand of these agents in a pandemic context. Urgent need drove the research into treatment and prevention remedies, including repurposed molecules, investigational drugs and vaccines [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Policy-related analyses reached 95 (7%), covering containment strategies, medical resource allocation and economic impact. Furthermore, patients with pre-existing conditions need special attention during the outbreak, which was addressed in 171 (12%) publications.</p><p id="p0020">Given the rapid spread of COVID-19, many countries joined the global action of research. Generally, research activities correlated with the epidemic from national perspectives (Supplementary material, <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig.&#x000a0;S4</xref>). As the first affected country, China's aggressive public interventions provided evidence for evaluating epidemic responses [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p id="p0025">We also compared the trend of COVID-19 research with that of severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) in 2003 (see <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Supplementary material, Appendix S1 and Fig.&#x000a0;S2</xref>). The patterns of COVID-19 research subjects were generally comparable with those in SARS (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>a,b). The temporal trends in both diseases generally agreed with the way we gain knowledge on novel diseases, and also reflected accessibility of resources to researchers in different disciplines.</p><p id="p0030">However, the volume of COVID-19-related publications increased at a significantly greater speed than that of SARS in all aspects (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>a,b), associated with the extent of pandemic severity and diversification of research tools. As of 29 August 2020, there were more than 60&#x000a0;000 publications on journal or preprint servers [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Studies on therapeutics accumulated dramatically, and results of clinical trial results were published 6&#x000a0;months earlier than those in the SARS epidemic (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>a,b). The initial reaction from China was represented by two remdesivir trials in early February, and quickly expanded to 5000 trials testing antiviral, anti-inflammatory and immunoglobulin therapies on a global scale [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. As of 28 August 2020, at least 45 randomized controlled trials and 19 prospective non-randomized trials have been published [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], and quickly translated into consensus of clinical practice. Notably, based on the results from the international trial of remdesivir from the NIH [<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], the US Food and Drug Administration issued authorization for its emergency use in severe COVID-19. Moreover, 95 policy-related publications for COVID-19 were found, compared to 29 for SARS (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>a,b), which underscored evidence-based public health policy in the modern era. The global spread of COVID-19 brought substantial challenges to other health metrics, especially the management of other medical conditions (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>a,b). In the settings of severe COVID-19 epidemics, health-care services of non-urgent ailments have been disrupted [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The containment strategies, such as social distancing, might negatively influence metabolic health [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p id="p0035">We also identified 1085 COVID-19 papers in preprint platforms (bioRxiv, medRxiv, ChemRxiv and ChinaXiv) using the same search strategies (see Supplementary material, <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix S1 and Fig.&#x000a0;S3</xref>). Despite similarities in most topics, there were 2.2-fold more policy-related studies in preprints than in peer-reviewed counterparts as of late March (see Supplementary material, <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Fig.&#x000a0;5</xref>), which may be explained by the motivations brought by rapid dissemination in preprints and pre-emption obtained by preprint publication for policy research based on open-source data [<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Clinical observational studies were more prominent in peer-reviewed publications, reflecting the accelerated process of peer review in response to COVID-19 [<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. However, worries have been proposed about the quality and reliability of these studies [<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], as exemplified by the retraction of a registry analysis for hydroxycholoroquine due to concerns on veracity 13&#x000a0;days after publication [<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p id="p0040">The outlook of the COVID-19 pandemic is still unclear, and its influence is far-reaching. Continuous research achievements will help to fill the knowledge gap. However, we are left behind in some aspects. For example, funds to support the development of therapeutics and vaccines for SARS coronavirus were reduced when SARS ended [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], leaving us underprepared to cope with COVID-19. Hopefully, reasonable research efforts will persist even after the threat subsides, allowing for better preparedness for the next unexpected yet historically recurring crises.</p><sec id="sec1"><title>Authors' contributions</title><p id="p0045">LZ took responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis. GL and YZ designed the study. GL, YZ, JJ and XL collected the data and independently reviewed the data. QJ cleaned and processed the data. GL and YZ contributed to the statistical analysis. GL, YZ, and JJ drafted the manuscript. All authors contributed to data interpretation, revised the manuscript and approved the final version.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Funding</title><p id="p0050">The authors received no funding for this work.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec3"><title>Transparency declaration</title><p id="p0050d">We declare no competing interests.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cyranoski</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallapaty</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoye</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tollefson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The coronavirus pandemic in five powerful charts</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>579</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>482</fpage><lpage>483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32203366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>China National Health Commission</collab></person-group><chapter-title>Chinese clinical guidance for COVID-19 pneumonia diagnosis and treatment</chapter-title><edition>7th ed.</edition><year>2020</year><publisher-name>China National Health Commission</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://kjfy.meetingchina.org/msite/news/show/cn/3337.html" id="intref0015">http://kjfy.meetingchina.org/msite/news/show/cn/3337.html</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forbes</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Pricing of COVID-19 treatments and coronavirus vaccines</chapter-title><year>2020</year><comment>Available from:</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/joshuacohen/2020/05/11/pricing-of-covid-19-treatments-and-coronavirus-vaccines/#1d591eb72865" id="intref0020">https://www.forbes.com/sites/joshuacohen/2020/05/11/pricing-of-covid-19-treatments-and-coronavirus-vaccines/#1d591eb72865</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of public health interventions with the epidemiology of the COVID-19 outbreak in Wuhan, China</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2020</year><comment>epub ahead of print</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>COVID-19 Open Access Project</collab></person-group><chapter-title>Living evidence on COVID-19</chapter-title><year>2020</year><comment>Available from:</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ispmbern.github.io/covid-19/living-review/" id="intref0025">https://ispmbern.github.io/covid-19/living-review/</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>COVID-Network meta-analysis (NMA)</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Living mapping and living systematic review of Covid-19 studies</article-title><comment>Available from:</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://covid-nma.com/" id="intref0030">https://covid-nma.com/</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beigel</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomashek</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodd</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zingman</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalil</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Remdesivir for the treatment of Covid-19&#x02014;preliminary report</article-title><source>N&#x000a0;Engl J Med</source><year>2020</year><comment>epub ahead of print</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Digitalized adaptation of oncology trials during and after COVID-19</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2020</year><comment>epub ahead of print</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clemmensen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>T.I.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Will the COVID-19 pandemic worsen the obesity epidemic?</article-title><source>Nat Rev Endocrinol</source><volume>16</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>469</fpage><lpage>470</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32641837</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brierley</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Polka</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e1;lfy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preprinting a pandemic: the role of preprints in the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><year>2020</year><comment>epub ahead of print</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palayew</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Norgaard</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Safreed-Harmon</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>L.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazarus</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pandemic publishing poses a new COVID-19 challenge</article-title><source>Nat Hum Behav</source><volume>4</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>666</fpage><lpage>669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32576981</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glasziou</surname><given-names>P.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Waste in COVID-19 research</article-title><source>BMJ</source><volume>369</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>m1847</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32398241</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehra</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruschitzka</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patel AN&#x0003e; Retraction&#x02014;hydroxychloroquine or chloroquine with or without a macrolide for treatment of COVID-19: a multinational registry analysis</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2020</year><comment>epub ahead of print</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of SARS vaccines and therapeutics is still needed</article-title><source>Future Virol</source><volume>8</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32201503</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0060">The following are the Supplementary data to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1"><caption><title>Multimedia component 1</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.docx"><alt-text>Multimedia component 1</alt-text></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc2"><caption><title>Multimedia component 2</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc2.xlsx"><alt-text>Multimedia component 2</alt-text></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Dr Xiaole Xie and Zhenghao Fan for their great supports in data processing.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="appsec2" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="p0065">Supplementary data to this article can be found online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmi.2020.09.010" id="intref0010">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmi.2020.09.010</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>