<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Acute myocarditis, cardiac decompensation, or cardiogenic shock can occur during a cytokine storm. Inflammatory cells in the presence of hypercytokinemia infiltrate the heart. There is a release of troponin and an increase in brain natriuretic peptide (BNP). Inflammatory cytokine storm is accompanied by immunopathological changes in the lungs. Patients infected with SARS-CoV-2 mostly die from Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS) (
 <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). This leads to acute pneumonia and to accumulation of fluid in the lungs, which requires intubation and ventilation. Such a severe clinical picture develops six to seven days after the onset of infection. Unfortunately, 40% of patients with acute respiratory distress syndrome do not survive. At the same time, patients die faster from cytokine storms than from infection. During a cytokine storm, death occurs due to the failure of several organs, which explains such a high mortality. Proinflammatory cytokines such as interleukin 6, interleukin 7, interleukin 8, interleukin 17, interleukin 22, interleukin 1beta, and chemokinases such as CCL2, CCL-5 and CCL3, contribute to the development of ARDS. During the cytokine storm, there is an increase in D-dimer, ferritin, lactate dehydrogenase (LDH), CRP, interleukin 1, interleukin 6, tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF-alpha) and lymphopenia (
 <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). A significant number of people with COVID-19 do not develop a cytokine storm. However, some people have a tendency to develop a cytokine storm, if they possess a specific gene, which allows the immune system to react in a certain way. However, this has not been proven with certainty. This phenomenon of „immune storm“ is not completely new. It has been observed in previous coronavirus-related epidemics, namely SARS (Severe acute respiratory syndrome) in 2003 and MERS (Middle East Respiratory Syndrome) in 2012 (
 <xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). The phenomenon of „immune storm“ can be observed in other viral infections, such as influenza. There are also non-infectious agents that can lead to an „immune storm“, for example after an organ transplantation. The cytokine storm is unwanted and one of the most spectacular moments during treatment with CAR-T cells. This method consists of injecting T lymphocytes that have been genetically modified to fight tumors, leukemia or lymphoma.
</p>
