<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We identified natural infections of Bunyamwera virus and ISFVs in diverse anopheline and culicine mosquito species reared to adults from field-collected larvae, demonstrating that these viruses persist transstadially through development to adult stages from naturally infected immature life stages. Since vertical transmission was first identified of vesicular stomatitis virus by phlebotomine sandflies [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] followed by La Crosse virus in 
 <italic>Aedes triseriatus</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], this mode of maintaining arboviruses within ecosystems has been observed in numerous arboviruses of medical importance circulating in East Africa, including West Nile virus by 
 <italic>Culex</italic> and 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], Ndumu virus [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] by 
 <italic>Cx</italic>. 
 <italic>pipiens</italic>, and Zika [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], dengue [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], chikungunya [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>], and RVF [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] viruses by 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. However, how widespread or important this mode of transmission is in natural ecologies remains poorly understood. While we attribute the naturally occurring virus infections that were transstadially transmitted from immature life stages in this study to vertical transmission from their parents, we cannot completely rule out the possibility that the immature mosquitoes were infected with these viruses from viral contamination in their aquatic environment during early development. However, this mode of transmission if far less likely as past studies indicate that such infection of immature mosquitoes requires unrealistically high viral doses in their aquatic environment [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006949.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>].
</p>
