<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Person‐to‐person spread of SARS‐CoV, MERS‐CoV, and SARS‐CoV‐2 mainly occurs via respiratory droplets produced when an infect person coughs or sneezes.
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref> Fever was the most prevalent symptom that occurred in 86% to 97% SARS‐CoV‐2 infected patients, followed by dry cough (59%‐76%), fatigue (34‐68%), and dyspnea (20%‐40%).
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref> The median time from first symptom to dyspnea was only 5 days.
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref> Apart from acute respiratory syndrome, some other organ dysfunctions, including gastrointestinal symptoms, hepatic dysfunction, splenic atrophy, seizures, and lymphadenopathy have been found in SARS and MERS.
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">16</xref> Since SARS‐CoV‐2 shares the same receptor angiotensin converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) with SARS‐CoV,
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">18</xref> it is reasonable to speculate that these organ dysfunctions may also be found in SARS‐CoV‐2 infected patients. Actually, a retrospective, observational study showed that in 52 critically ill adult patients who were admitted to the intensive care unit (ICU), 15 (29%) had acute kidney injury, 12 (23%) cardiac injury, and 15 (29%) liver dysfunction.
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref> The most severe sequelae after rehabilitation from SARS were femoral head necrosis and pulmonary fibrosis. High‐dose steroid pulse treatment was used to suppress inflammation, which caused subchondral osteonecrosis in about 5% of SARS patients.
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref> The risk of osteonecrosis was 0.6% for patients receiving less than 3 g and 13% for patients receiving more than 3 g prednisolone‐equivalent dose.
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref> In addition, the use of high dose of hydrocortisone or methylprednisolone for an extended duration was shown to be a significant risk factor for osteonecrosis.
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref> In order to suppress inflammation without causing osteonecrosis in SARS‐CoV‐2 infected patients, Chinese National Health Commission recommended that glucocorticoid should be used in a short period (3‐5 days) as appropriate, and the dose should not exceed 1 to 2 mg/kg/d of methylprednisolone.
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref> Moreover, it should be considered that glucocorticoid treatment could delay clearance of viral RNA because of immunosuppression.
</p>
