<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are over 1200 bat species globally and only a small fraction (~15%) have been targeted for viral discovery to date [
 <xref rid="B41-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. That said, pathogen discovery in bats is becoming a widespread activity globally, and this presents an opportunity for researchers to screen specimens for filoviruses while running other routine assays. Global surveillance programs like CDC’s Global Disease Detection centers, or United States Agency for International Development’s (USAID) Emerging Pandemic Threat Program have established laboratory protocols for screening specimens from a diversity of wild mammal hosts. For example, the USAID PREDICT project uses degenerate PCR primers to screen bats, rodents, and primates across multiple (~10–20) viral families including Filoviruses in 20 countries around the world [
 <xref rid="B94-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. Through capacity building in emerging infectious disease “hotspots” globally [
 <xref rid="B120-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>], these efforts have the potential to establish a new baseline for the “unknown” zoonotic pool in wildlife and redraw the biogeographic boundaries of pathogen distribution and host range [
 <xref rid="B94-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>,
 <xref rid="B121-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>]. These global, coordinated efforts may allow us to identify novel viruses that have not yet emerged into human populations and develop prevention strategies to ensure that they do not. Lloviu virus is a good example of this, as it was picked up during wildlife surveillance after a die-off in a bat population [
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and is now part of follow-up studies to better understand its genome [
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], molecular biology, and cell entry [
 <xref rid="B90-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]—in part to be able to predict its potential to spillover and infect humans.
</p>
