<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">26824</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-26824-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Inferring population dynamics of HIV-1 subtype C epidemics in Eastern Africa and Southern Brazil applying different Bayesian phylodynamics approaches</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3172-4867</contrib-id><name><surname>Mir</surname><given-names>Daiana</given-names></name><address><email>daianamir@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4921-7975</contrib-id><name><surname>Gr&#x000e4;f</surname><given-names>Tiago</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Esteves de Matos Almeida</surname><given-names>Sabrina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>Aguinaldo Roberto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5746-0820</contrib-id><name><surname>Delatorre</surname><given-names>Edson</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2724-2793</contrib-id><name><surname>Bello</surname><given-names>Gonzalo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0723 0931</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.418068.3</institution-id><institution>Laborat&#x000f3;rio de AIDS e Imunologia Molecular, Instituto Oswaldo Cruz, Fiocruz, </institution></institution-wrap>Rio de Janeiro, Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2294 473X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8536.8</institution-id><institution>Departamento de Gen&#x000e9;tica, Instituto de Biologia, </institution><institution>Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro, </institution></institution-wrap>Rio de Janeiro, Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0723 4123</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.16463.36</institution-id><institution>KwaZulu-Natal Research Innovation and Sequencing Platform (KRISP), College of Health Sciences, </institution><institution>University of KwaZulu-Natal, </institution></institution-wrap>Durban, South Africa </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.418067.c</institution-id><institution>Centro de Desenvolvimento Cient&#x000ed;fico e Tecnol&#x000f3;gico, Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Estadual de Produ&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o e Pesquisa em Sa&#x000fa;de, </institution></institution-wrap>Porto Alegre, Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2200 7498</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8532.c</institution-id><institution>Programa de P&#x000f3;s-Gradua&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o em Gen&#x000e9;tica e Biologia Molecular, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, </institution></institution-wrap>Porto Alegre, Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0413 0363</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412395.8</institution-id><institution>Instituto de Ci&#x000ea;ncias da Sa&#x000fa;de, Universidade Feevale, </institution></institution-wrap>Novo Hamburgo, Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2188 7235</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411237.2</institution-id><institution>Laborat&#x000f3;rio de Imunologia Aplicada, Departamento de Microbiologia, Imunologia e Parasitologia, </institution><institution>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina, </institution></institution-wrap>Florian&#x000f3;polis, Brazil </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>8</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>8778</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">The subtype C Eastern Africa clade (C<sub>EA</sub>), a particularly successful HIV-1 subtype C lineage, has seeded several sub-epidemics in Eastern African countries and Southern Brazil during the 1960s and 1970s. Here, we characterized the past population dynamics of the major C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemics in Eastern Africa and Brazil by using Bayesian phylodynamic approaches based on coalescent and birth-death models. All phylodynamic models support similar epidemic dynamics and exponential growth rates until roughly the mid-1980s for all the C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemics. Divergent growth patterns, however, were supported afterwards. The Bayesian skygrid coalescent model (BSKG) and the birth-death skyline model (BDSKY) supported longer exponential growth phases than the Bayesian skyline coalescent model (BSKL). The BDSKY model uncovers patterns of a recent decline for the C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemics in Burundi/Rwanda and Tanzania (R<sub>e</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1) and a recent growth for Southern Brazil (R<sub>e</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1); whereas coalescent models infer an epidemic stabilization. To the contrary, the BSKG model captured a decline of Ethiopian C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemic between the mid-1990s and mid-2000s that was not uncovered by the BDSKY model. These results underscore that the joint use of different phylodynamic approaches may yield complementary insights into the past HIV population dynamics.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">The human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1) subtype C accounts for approximately 48% of all people living with HIV, representing the most prevalent HIV-1 subtype in the world<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. The high global prevalence of the C subtype results from its predominance in regions with the highest rates of HIV-1 infection and with large populations, such as Southern and Eastern Africa, India and Southern Brazil<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. The origin of HIV-1 subtype C was recently traced to the Katanga region of the Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC) in the late 1930s<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup> from where it spread independently to Eastern and Southern Africa, leading to a phylogeographic subdivision between the HIV-1 subtype C strains circulating in those two African regions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">The expansion of HIV-1 subtype C inside Eastern Africa gave rise to the C East African clade (C<sub>EA</sub>), whose most probable epicenter of dissemination was in Burundi around the early 1960s. During the 1970s, this country acted as ignition point of several local C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemics in other Eastern African countries<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup> and also in Southern Brazil<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> where the C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemic was fueled from a single founder event<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. The C<sub>EA</sub> clade currently predominates among subtype C strains from Eastern African countries and Brazil, and accounts for almost 100% of subtype C sequences from Burundi and Brazil, 97% from Uganda, 64% from Kenya, 61% from Ethiopia and 49% from Tanzania<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. The evolutionary analyses of the C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemics performed so far mostly address questions about the place and timing of outbreaks onset, focusing on the reconstruction of the geographic dissemination pathways of this viral clade<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Studies on the population dynamics of C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemics, while key to understand their historical epidemic growth trends, epidemic potential and ecological processes shaping their evolution, have been much less frequent<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">Key epidemiological and population parameters, most notably the effective number of infections (<italic>Ne</italic>), the epidemic growth rate (<italic>r</italic>) and the basic (R<sub>0</sub>) and effective (R<sub>e</sub>) reproductive number, can be estimated from viral sequence data by using Bayesian phylodynamic approaches based on coalescent<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> and birth-death<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup> models. These models have very different mathematical grounds as well as particular strengths and limitations. The coalescent is appropriate only if the number of sampled infected individuals is small compared with the size of the total infected population<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>, despite certain robustness to violation of this requirement has been demonstrated<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. The birth-death model, meanwhile, explicitly models the sampling process and can thus be used for sparse or densely sampled viral populations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>, although estimates may be biased if the model of the sampling process is misspecified. The coalescent allows the inference of the R<sub>0</sub> (key epidemiological parameter indicator of increment [R<sub>0</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1], decline [R<sub>0</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1] or stabilization [R<sub>0</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1] in the number of new cases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>) only through modeling the population dynamics under a deterministic assumption, which represents a limitation for populations undergoing complex dynamics<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, and require an independent estimate of the average duration of infectiousness. The birth&#x02013;death model has the advantage of accounting for stochasticity of the demographic process and provides an estimate for R<sub>e</sub> changes over time using only sequence data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. A potential disadvantage of the birth-death model is that credibility intervals grow wider the further we go into the past, which is not the case for the coalescent-based models<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>; although simulation studies showed that the coalescent might not capture the true <italic>r</italic> because of the narrow credibility intervals around the median estimate attributed to its assumption of deterministic changes in the population size<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">The present work aims to shed light on the past population dynamics of the major HIV-1 C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemics established in Burundi, Rwanda, Ethiopia, Tanzania and Brazil by analyzing viral <italic>pol</italic> gene sequences sampled between 1990 and 2014 with Bayesian phylodynamic methods based on coalescent and birth-death models.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Sequence dataset compilation</title><p id="Par6">A reference dataset of HIV-1 subtype C <italic>pol</italic> sequences belonging to the east, southern and central African lineages was selected from a previous study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup> and combined with: 1) more recent east African subtype C <italic>pol</italic> sequences with known sampling dates available in Los Alamos HIV Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hiv.lanl.gov">http://www.hiv.lanl.gov</ext-link>) by August 2017, and 2) subtype C <italic>pol</italic> sequences with known sampling dates isolated from heterosexual populations living in the two southernmost Brazilian states (Rio Grande do Sul and Santa Catarina) previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. The option &#x0201c;One sequence/patient&#x0201d; was selected from Los Alamos HIV database to exclude multiple sequences from the same subject. The subtype assignment of all sequences was confirmed using the REGA HIV-1 subtyping tool v.3.0. Given the two genetically distinct subtype C clades (C and C&#x02019;) co-circulating in Ethiopia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>, linked to subtype C viruses of eastern and southern African origin respectively, putative intrasubtype C/C&#x02019; recombinant sequences (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;99) were identified by Bootscanning using Simplot v3.5.1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup> and removed from further analyses. This resulted in a final dataset of 1,147 HIV-1 subtype C <italic>pol</italic> sequences (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>) covering the complete protease (PR) and the first part of the reverse transcriptase (RT) regions (nucleotides 2,253 to 3,272 relative to HXB2 genome).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Identification of dominant country-specific HIV-1 C<sub>EA</sub> subclades</title><p id="Par7">To identify major country-specific clades within the C<sub>EA</sub> radiation, HIV-1 subtype C <italic>pol</italic> sequences from eastern Africa and southern Brazil were first aligned with reference subtype C sequences belonging to the eastern, southern and central African clades using the CLUSTAL X program<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> and subjected to maximum likelihood (ML) phylogenetic analysis. ML trees were inferred with the PhyML program<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>, using an online web server<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>, under the general time-reversible model of nucleotide substitution plus invariant sites and four discrete gamma rate categories (GTR+I+&#x00393;4) selected with jModeltest program<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> and the subtree pruning and regrafting (SPR) branch-swapping algorithm of heuristic tree search. The reliability of the phylogenies was estimated with the approximate likelihood-ratio test based on a Shimodaira&#x02013;Hasegawa-like procedure (SH-<italic>aLRT</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Basal HIV-1 C<sub>EA</sub> sequences from Burundi and Rwanda and major (n&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;50 sequences) country-specific (&#x0003e;90% of sequences from a single country) monophyletic groups with high support (SH-<italic>aLRT</italic> &#x02265;0.85) nested within the C<sub>EA</sub> clade radiation were selected for demographic analyses. Reference sequences of HIV-1 subtypes A1 and D from the Los Alamos HIV Database were used as outgroups. Final trees were visualized in FigTree v1.4.2.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Estimation of phylodynamic parameters</title><p id="Par8">Epidemiological and evolutionary parameters of the defined C<sub>EA</sub> subclades were estimated via Bayesian Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) phylogenetic inference using coalescent and birth-death tree priors as implemented in BEAST v1.8<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup> and BEAST v.2.4<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup> software packages, respectively. Changes in <italic>Ne</italic> using the coalescent tree prior were first assessed using the non-parametric Bayesian skyline (BSKL)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup> and Bayesian Skygrid (BSKG)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup> models and estimates of the <italic>r</italic> were subsequently obtained using the parametric model that provided the best fit to the demographic signal contained in each dataset. Comparison between demographic models (logistic, exponential, or expansion) was performed using the log marginal likelihood estimation (MLE) based on path sampling (PS) and stepping-stone sampling (SS) methods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. The cumulative number of lineages through time (LTT) was calculated from the combined posterior distribution of sampled coalescent tree topologies by using TRACER v1.6 program<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. A special case of the birth-death tree prior, namely the birth-death skyline (BDSKY) was applied to model viral transmissions through time<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. The sampling rate (&#x003b4;) was set to zero for the period prior to the oldest sample and estimated from the data afterwards. The R<sub>e</sub> was estimated in a piece-wise manner over three different equidistant intervals using a lognormal prior distribution (R<sub>e</sub>: mean&#x02009;=&#x02009;0, standard deviation&#x02009;=&#x02009;1). Bayesian analyses for each transmission clade employed the GTR+I+&#x00393;4 model of nucleotide substitution selected using the jModelTest program<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> and a relaxed uncorrelated lognormal molecular clock model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Because linear regression analysis of root-to-tip distances as function of sampling time obtained by TempEst v1.5<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup> revealed low temporal signal in the datasets, an informative normal prior distribution on the time to the most recent common ancestor (tMRCA) was applied based on previous estimates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. MCMC chains were run for sufficiently long to ensure stationarity (constant mean and variance of trace plots) and good mixing (Effective Sample Size &#x0003e;200) for all parameter estimates, as diagnosed by TRACER v1.6 program<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec7"><title>Identification of major subclades within the HIV-1 C<sub>EA</sub> clade radiation</title><p id="Par9">To obtain a more updated picture of the HIV-1 C<sub>EA</sub> clade radiation, subtype C <italic>pol</italic> sequences from Eastern Africa and Southern Brazil deposited in Los Alamos HIV sequence database between 2013 and 2016 were combined with C<sub>EA</sub>
<italic>pol</italic> sequences from those regions previously characterized<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. The reconstructed ML phylogeny showed that most (79%) subtype C sequences from Eastern Africa and all sequences from Southern Brazil sampled at most recent time (2013&#x02013;2016) branched within the highly supported (SH-<italic>aLRT</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.96) HIV-1 C<sub>EA</sub> clade (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). As expected, sequences from Burundi and Rwanda were highly intermixed among each other and occupied the most basal positions of the C<sub>EA</sub> clade radiation; while sequences from other Eastern African countries and Brazil were nested within Burundian and Rwandan C<sub>EA</sub> sequences.</p><p id="Par10">Most sequences from Kenya and Uganda appeared as sporadic (non-clustered) lineages or clustered in monophyletic subclades of small sizes (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;50) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). All Brazilian sequences and most sequences from Ethiopia (67%) and Tanzania (66%), by contrast, branched within four country-specific C<sub>EA</sub> subclades of large size (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;50) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>) that were more clearly visualized after pruning of non-clustered C<sub>EA</sub> sequences and C<sub>EA</sub> sequences within monophyletic subclades of small sizes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The four identified C<sub>EA</sub> subclades (C<sub>EA/BR</sub>, C<sub>EA/ET-1</sub>, C<sub>EA/ET-2</sub> and C<sub>EA/TZ</sub>) together with sequences from Burundi and Rwanda (C<sub>EA/BI-RW</sub>) comprise 76% (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;616) of all the C<sub>EA</sub> sequences analyzed here; thus confirming the epidemiological relevance of the selected subclades.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>ML phylogenetic tree of HIV-1 C<italic>EA pol</italic> PR/RT sequences (~1,000 nt) from eastern Africa and southern Brazil. Branches are colored according to the geographic origin of sequences as indicated in the legend (upper right). Gray shaded boxes indicate the positions of major C<sub>EA</sub> lineages. Asterisks point to key nodes with high support (SH-<italic>aLRT</italic> &#x0003e;0.85). The tree was rooted using HIV-1 subtypes A1 and D reference sequences and the branch lengths are drawn to scale with the bar at the center indicating nucleotide substitutions per site.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_26824_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e763"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Bayesian population dynamics inference in a coalescent framework</title><p id="Par11">Bayesian MCMC coalescent-based analyses under the BSKL model suggest that all C<sub>EA</sub> subclades presents roughly comparable demographic histories, with an initial phase of fast exponential growth followed by a stabilization of the <italic>Ne</italic> at some time between the late 1970s and the late 1980s that persisted until the most recent sampling date of each of them (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a,e</xref>, <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a,e</xref> and <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). The observed stabilization in the <italic>Ne</italic> of African C<sub>EA</sub> sub-clades occurs before the respective stabilization of the HIV incidence in corresponding countries estimated around the mid-1990s according to the UNAIDS (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d,h</xref> and <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d,h</xref>). The UNAIDS data also supports a significant reduction of the HIV incidence in Burundi/Rwanda, Ethiopia and Tanzania between the mid-1990s and the mid-2000s that was not captured by the BSKL inference. The stabilization of the C<sub>EA/BR</sub>
<italic>Ne</italic> around the early 1990s is consistent with the stabilization of the new HIV cases in Rio Grande do Sul and Santa Catarina at around the same time (considering a lag time of eight years between HIV infection and new AIDS cases reported by the Brazilian AIDS cases databank for those Brazilian states); but fails to capture a recent increase in the number of new HIV cases from 2010 onwards (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4d</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Epidemiological and population dynamics of the C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemics in Ethiopia. Median estimates of the effective number of infections (<italic>Ne</italic>) using the Bayesian skyline or skygrid models (black lines) together with their 95% highest probability density (HPD) intervals (gray areas), co-plotted together with the median <italic>Ne</italic> estimates using the logistic coalescent-based parametric model (blue lines) and its 95% HPD intervals (blue areas). The green dashed lines indicate the time of the last coalescent event reported by the lineages-through-time (LTT) (<bold>a</bold>,<bold>b</bold>,<bold>e</bold>,<bold>f</bold>). Temporal fluctuation of the effective reproductive number (R<sub>e</sub>) of the C<sub>EA/ET-1</sub> and C<sub>EA/ET-2</sub> sub-epidemics estimated using the Bayesian birth-death approach (<bold>c</bold> and <bold>g</bold>). For an easier visualization, the median coalescent-based R<sub>0</sub> estimate (blue dashed lines) inferred for each sub-epidemic and its 95% HPD intervals (blue area) were added. The gray dashed lines indicate R<sub>e</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1 (<bold>c</bold> and <bold>g</bold>). Plots representing the number of new HIV cases in Ethiopia as obtained from UNAIDS website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aidsinfo.unaids.org/">http://aidsinfo.unaids.org/</ext-link> (<bold>d</bold> and <bold>h</bold>). The yellow, pink and gray intervals denote the time spanned for the birth-death-based R<sub>e</sub>-initial, R<sub>e</sub>-middle and R<sub>e</sub>-final estimates of each C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemic.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_26824_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e889"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Epidemiological and population dynamics of the C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemics in Tanzania and Burundi/Rwanda. Median estimates of the effective number of infections (<italic>Ne</italic>) using the Bayesian skyline or skygrid models (black lines) together with their 95% highest probability density (HPD) intervals (gray areas), co-plotted together with the median <italic>Ne</italic> estimates using the logistic coalescent-based parametric model (blue lines) and its 95% HPD intervals (blue areas). The green dashed lines indicate the time of the last coalescent event reported by the lineages-through-time (LTT) (<bold>a</bold>,<bold>b</bold>,<bold>e</bold>,<bold>f</bold>). Temporal fluctuation of the effective reproductive number (R<sub>e</sub>) of the C<sub>EA/TZ</sub> and C<sub>EA/BI-RW</sub> sub-epidemics estimated using the Bayesian birth-death approach (<bold>c</bold> and <bold>g</bold>). For an easier visualization, the median coalescent-based R<sub>0</sub> estimate (blue dashed lines) inferred for each sub-epidemic and its 95% HPD intervals (blue area) were added. The gray dashed lines indicate R<sub>e</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1 (<bold>c</bold> and <bold>g</bold>). Plots representing the number of new HIV cases in Tanzania and Burundi/Rwanda as obtained from UNAIDS website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://aidsinfo.unaids.org/">http://aidsinfo.unaids.org/</ext-link> (<bold>d</bold> and <bold>h</bold>). The yellow, pink and gray intervals denote the time spanned for the birth-death-based R<sub>e</sub>-initial, R<sub>e</sub>-middle and R<sub>e</sub>-final estimates of each C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemic.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_26824_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e972"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Epidemiological and population dynamics of the C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemic in southern Brazil. Median estimates of the effective number of infections (<italic>Ne</italic>) using Bayesian skyline or skygrid models (black lines) together with their 95% highest probability density (HPD) intervals (gray areas), co-plotted together with the median <italic>Ne</italic> estimates using the logistic coalescent-based parametric model (blue lines) and its 95% HPD intervals (blue areas). The green dashed lines indicate the time of the last coalescent event reported by the lineages-through-time (LTT) (<bold>a</bold> and <bold>b</bold>). Temporal fluctuation of the effective reproductive number (R<sub>e</sub>) of the C<sub>EA/BR</sub> sub-epidemic estimated using the Bayesian birth-death approach (<bold>c</bold>). For an easier visualization, the median coalescent-based R<sub>0</sub> estimate (blue dashed line) inferred for the C<sub>EA/BR</sub> subclade and its 95% HPD intervals (blue area) were added. The gray dashed line indicate R<sub>e</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1 (<bold>c</bold>). Plot representing the number of new HIV cases in the Southern Brazilian states of Rio Grande do Sul (RS) and Santa Catarina (SC). AIDS cases reported by the Brazilian AIDS cases databank (SINAN&#x02009;=&#x02009;SIM&#x02009;=&#x02009;SISCEL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.portalsinan.saude.gov.br/dados-epidemiologicos-sinan">http://www.portalsinan.saude.gov.br/dados-epidemiologicos-sinan</ext-link>), minus eight years, was used as an approximation for new HIV infections (solid black line). From 2007 onward, Brazilian Ministry of Health started to report HIV new infections (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aids.gov.br/pt-br/pub/2016/boletim-epidemiologico-de-aids-2016">http://www.aids.gov.br/pt-br/pub/2016/boletim-epidemiologico-de-aids-2016</ext-link>), reprented here as a dashed black line (<bold>d</bold>). The yellow, pink and gray intervals denote the time spanned for the birth-death-based R<sub>e</sub>-initial, R<sub>e</sub>-middle and R<sub>e</sub>-final estimates of the C<sub>EA/BR</sub> sub-epidemic.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_26824_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1045"/></fig></p><p id="Par12">The BSKG demographic reconstructions point to a longer period of exponential growth for all C<sub>EA</sub> subclades that extends up to between the early and the mid-1990s, in agreement with incidence data. For the Ethiopian C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemics, the BSKG points to subsequent decline of the median <italic>Ne</italic> until mid-2000s and a final plateau until 2010, in agreement with epidemiological data (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b,d,f,h</xref>). The median estimated <italic>Ne</italic> for the C<sub>EA/BI-RW,</sub> C<sub>EA/TZ</sub> and C<sub>EA/BR</sub> sub-epidemics reach a plateau that persisted until the most recent sampling time which differs markedly from the HIV incidence pattern (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b,d,f,h</xref> and <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b,d</xref>). The large 95% highest probability density (HPD) interval of the <italic>Ne</italic> estimates inferred by the BSKG model, however, may accommodate different demographic patterns in the latter stages making it difficult to draw solid conclusions on the consistency (or the lack thereof) between these estimates and the HIV incidence temporal pattern.</p><p id="Par13">The logistic growth model was the best-fit parametric model of population growth for all the C<sub>EA</sub> subclades (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). The median <italic>Ne</italic> trajectories obtained by the logistic growth model during the initial exponential phase closely matched the corresponding trajectories obtained with the non-parametric approaches, particularly those obtained with the BSKG (blue line Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a,b,e,f</xref>, <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a,b,e,f</xref> and <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a,f</xref>). The mean R<sub>0</sub> values derived from the logistic growth model using the formula R<sub>0</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>r</italic>D&#x02009;+&#x02009;1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> (where D is average duration of infectiousness herein considered of eight years) was very similar for all C<sub>EA</sub> subclades, ranging between 5.0 and 5.9 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The median <italic>Ne</italic> trajectories of the C<sub>EA/BI-RW</sub>, C<sub>EA/TZ</sub> and C<sub>EA-BR</sub> at the plateau phase obtained with parametric and non-parametric approaches were very similar. As the logistic growth model is unable to capture non-constant trends on recent time period estimates, obviously do not reproduced the declining phase pointed by the BSKG for the C<sub>EA/ET-1</sub> and C<sub>EA/ET-2</sub> sub-clades, however, the parametric and non-parametric models converge to similar median <italic>Ne</italic> values at the late plateau phase.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Evolutionary and demographic parameters estimated for HIV-1 C<sub>EA</sub> subclades.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Clade</th><th>N</th><th>Sampling interval</th><th>Method</th><th>Substitution rate (10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>)</th><th>T<sub>MRCA</sub></th><th>R<sub>0</sub>/Re-initial</th><th>Re-middle</th><th>Re-final</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2">BI-RW</td><td rowspan="2">303</td><td rowspan="2">2002&#x02013;2012</td><td>coalescent (logistic)</td><td>1.5 (1.3&#x02013;1.6)</td><td>1958 (1952&#x02013;1964)</td><td>5.0 (4.2&#x02013;5.8)</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td>birth-death</td><td>1.5 (1.4&#x02013;1.6)</td><td>1957 (1952&#x02013;1962)</td><td>3.8 (1.9 &#x02013;7.1)</td><td>2.3 (1.2&#x02013;3.8)</td><td>0.5 (0.3&#x02013;0.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">ET-1</td><td rowspan="2">63</td><td rowspan="2">2003&#x02013;2011</td><td>coalescent (logistic)</td><td>1.2 (1.1&#x02013;1.4)</td><td>1971 (1969&#x02013;1973)</td><td>5.8 (4.2&#x02013;7.4)</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td>birth-death</td><td>1.3 (1.0&#x02013;1.5)</td><td>1972 (1970&#x02013;1974)</td><td>4.6 (2.0&#x02013;8.8)</td><td>1.6 (0.1&#x02013;3.7)</td><td>1.3 (1.0&#x02013;2.0)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">ET-2</td><td rowspan="2">56</td><td rowspan="2">2003&#x02013;2012</td><td>coalescent (logistic)</td><td>1.1 (0.9&#x02013;1.3)</td><td>1974 (1972&#x02013;1976)</td><td>5.0 (4.2&#x02013;6.6)</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td>birth-death</td><td>1.1 (1.0&#x02013;1.3)</td><td>1974 (1973&#x02013;1976)</td><td>4.3 (1.9&#x02013;8.1)</td><td>2.0 (0.2&#x02013;4.2)</td><td>1.2 (1.0&#x02013;1.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">TZ</td><td rowspan="2">50</td><td rowspan="2">2004&#x02013;2014</td><td>coalescent (logistic)</td><td>1.2 (0.8&#x02013;1.7)</td><td>1974 (1963&#x02013;1984)</td><td>5.8 (3.4&#x02013;8.2)</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td>birth-death</td><td>1.1 (0.9&#x02013;1.3)</td><td>1971 (1966&#x02013;1977)</td><td>4.2 (1.8&#x02013;8.2)</td><td>2.8 (1.2&#x02013;5.4)</td><td>0.3 (0.1 &#x02013;0.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">BR</td><td rowspan="2">144</td><td rowspan="2">1992&#x02013;2014</td><td>coalescent (logistic)</td><td>1.6 (1.2&#x02013;2.0)</td><td>1974 (1966&#x02013;1982)</td><td>5.9 (4.4&#x02013;7.6)</td><td>&#x02014;</td><td>&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td>birth-death</td><td>1.5 (1.3&#x02013;1.7)</td><td>1978 (1974&#x02013;1981)</td><td>4.9 (2.2&#x02013;9.2)</td><td>1.0 (0.2&#x02013;2.1)</td><td>2.4 (1.4&#x02013;3.7)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><bold>*</bold>The 95% credibility intervals for all estimates are indicated inside parenthesis.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Bayesian population dynamics inference under birth-death model</title><p id="Par14">The BDSKY model was applied allowing the R<sub>e</sub> to change in a piece-wise manner over three different time intervals that allow us to estimate the epidemic potential before identification of HIV (first time interval, ~1960&#x02013;1970 to 1980&#x02013;1984) and observe the potential impact of prevention (second time interval, ~1981&#x02013;1985 to 1995&#x02013;1999) or therapy (third time interval, ~1996&#x02013;2000 to 2012&#x02013;2014) measures on epidemic dynamics (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c,g</xref>, <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c,g</xref> and <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref>). The BDSKY model support initial exponential growth dynamics fully consistent with those estimated using coalescent models. Although the mean R<sub>0</sub> values (5.0&#x02013;5.9) were slightly higher than the estimated mean R<sub>e</sub>-initial (3.8&#x02013;4.9), the uncertainty on the R<sub>0</sub> estimates was always contained within the broader 95% HPD intervals of R<sub>e</sub>-initial (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The BDSKY model supports a progressive reduction of the mean R<sub>e</sub> in the second (mean R<sub>e</sub>-initial &#x0003e;mean R<sub>e</sub>-middle) and third (mean R<sub>e</sub>-middle &#x0003e;mean R<sub>e</sub>-final) time intervals for all African subclades. Although the mean R<sub>e</sub> estimates for the Ethiopian clades remained above one during all time intervals, which clearly did not match with the declining and subsequent stabilization of the HIV incidence in Ethiopia from the mid-1990s onwards (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d,h</xref>), those R<sub>e</sub> estimates should be interpreted with caution because the extremely wide 95% HPD intervals (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). For the C<sub>EA/BI-RW</sub> and C<sub>EA/TZ</sub> subclades, the R<sub>e</sub>-middle was above one, while the R<sub>e</sub>-final was below one, in agreement with the increasing HIV incidence in Burundi/Rwanda and Tanzania up to the mid-1990s and the subsequent declining from the mid-1990s onwards (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d,h</xref>). For the C<sub>EA/BR</sub> subclade, the BDSKY model supports a reduction of the mean R<sub>e</sub> in the second interval (R<sub>e</sub>-initial ~1) and a new increase in the third one (R<sub>e</sub>-final &#x0003e;1). This is consistent with the HIV incidence trends in Rio Grande do Sul and Santa Catarina Brazilian states, that supports an epidemic stabilization during the 1990s and a new epidemic increase during the 2000s (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c,d</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par15">In this study, we characterized key features of the epidemic dynamics of major HIV-1 subtype C<sub>EA</sub> lineages circulating in East Africa and Southern Brazil through the use of different phylodynamic frameworks based in coalescent and birth-death process. The different coalescent models capture very similar epidemic dynamics over the earlier decades of the C<sub>EA</sub> lineages dissemination; but point to quite different epidemic dynamics from the mid-1980s onwards.</p><p id="Par16">Both phylodynamic approaches suggest an initial stage of fast exponential growth of all the C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemics during the period of cryptic transmission of HIV in human populations. These initial phases of exponential growth herein inferred correlate with retrospective serological-based studies and simulations that indicated that an explosive epidemic was already sweeping the Eastern African region<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup> by 1981, when the AIDS was first recognized. The exponential growth phase inferred for the Brazilian C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemic during the 1970s and 1980s is also fully consistent with the sharp increase in the number of new HIV cases detected in the southernmost Brazilian states during the 1980s<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. The mean R<sub>0</sub> (5.0&#x02013;5.9) and R<sub>e</sub>-initial (3.8&#x02013;4.9) values here estimated for all C<sub>EA</sub> sub-clades were roughly comparable. The 95% HPD intervals of R<sub>0</sub> were always smaller and contained within the broader 95% HPD intervals of R<sub>e</sub>-initial, consistent with previous empirical and simulated data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. The coalescent-based logistic growth model is expected to provide narrow HPD intervals because it considers a deterministic population trajectory, while the BDSKY model incorporates stochasticity in population size. Additionally, the HPD interval of R<sub>e</sub> estimates from the BDSKY model grows wider the further we go towards the past, that is not the case for the coalescent-based logistic growth model estimates.</p><p id="Par17">Importantly, the mean R<sub>0</sub> and R<sub>e</sub>-initial values inferred for the African C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemics were fully consistent with those estimated through analyses of HIV prevalence rate and life expectancy in Eastern African countries<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. This suggests that both phylodynamic frameworks were able to recover the true early growth rates of HIV-1 C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemics.</p><p id="Par18">Factors like gender inequality<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>, civil and ethnic conflicts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>, conflict-induced displacement, and increasing urbanization<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup> have shaped the early HIV epidemic dynamics across all Eastern African countries, consistent with the similar epidemic growth rates of African C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemics. Notably, the epidemic growth rate inferred for the Brazilian C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemic was very similar to those obtained for the African C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemics despite significantly distinctive history of human conflicts in those regions. The exponential growth phase of the C<sub>EA/BR</sub> sub-epidemic matches with a period in which public health system was unaware about the severity of the epidemic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup> and the C<sub>EA/BR</sub> subclade was efficiently disseminated in Southern Brazil through heterosexual (HET) networks<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>, similar to that observed in Eastern Africa. This suggests that the absence of prevention efforts and the predominant viral transmission through HET route may have been the common driving forces of the early dynamics of the C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemics in Eastern African and Southern Brazil.</p><p id="Par19">The BSKL model supports that African C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemics grew exponentially until between the late 1970s and late 1980s, after which there occurs a plateau in the <italic>Ne</italic> until the most recent sampling time of each of them. The stabilization of the <italic>Ne</italic> trajectories occurs around 10 years before the last coalescent event (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a,b,e,f</xref> and <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a,b,e,f</xref>), thus supporting that the inferred plateau of the <italic>Ne</italic> is not due to a paucity of coalescent events after the early 1990s<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. More important, such stabilization occurred before implementation of prevention campaigns during the 1990s<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup> and introduction of universal access to antiretroviral (ARV) therapy during the 2000s<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup> in Eastern Africa. The overall <italic>Ne</italic> trajectories inferred by the BSKL after the mid-1980s, however, differ markedly from the data of the United Nations Joint Program on HIV/AIDS (UNAIDS)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref></sup> according to which the HIV incidence in Burundi/Rwanda, Ethiopia and Tanzania reached a peak around the mid-1990s (rather than during the 1980s), and was followed by a sharp decline (rather than a plateau) until the mid-2000s, before stabilize.</p><p id="Par20">The overall epidemic dynamics inferred by the BSKG model from the mid-1980s to the mid-1990s are more consistent with the HIV incidence data than those inferred by the BSKL, although some divergences were also detected at later times. The BSKG model points that C<sub>EA</sub> African sub-epidemics grew exponentially until the early/mid-1990s and further supports a declining <italic>Ne</italic> of C<sub>EA/ET</sub> subclades between the mid-1990s and the mid-2000s, consistent with epidemiological data. This model, however, failed to capture a similar decline of <italic>Ne</italic> for the C<sub>EA/BI-RW</sub> and C<sub>EA/TZ</sub> sub-epidemics. These results indicate that the BSKG model can correctly predict epidemic decline in some situations, as demonstrated here for the C<sub>EA/ET</sub> subclades and previously for the CRF02_AG epidemic in Cameroon<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>; but not in others.</p><p id="Par21">Although the BDSKY model also supports a progressive reduction of epidemic growth over time, an R<sub>e</sub> &#x0003e;1 was estimated at the second time interval (that roughly covers the period between early/mid-1980s and mid/late 1990s) for all African C<sub>EA</sub> subclades, consistent with a continuous increase of HIV incidence up to the mid-1990s. The BDSKY model capture an R<sub>e</sub> &#x0003c;1 for the C<sub>EA/BI-RW</sub> and C<sub>EA/TZ</sub> sub-epidemics at the most recent time interval (after the mid-1990s); but supported an R<sub>e</sub> &#x02265;1 for the C<sub>EA/ET</sub> sub-epidemics in the same time interval. These results confirms that the BDSKY model can correctly uncover a signature of a recent declining epidemic not reflected in the coalescent plots, as previously seen in the HIV-1 subtype B epidemic in the UK<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>; but also reveals that it&#x000a0;may fail to capture such trend in some other datasets.</p><p id="Par22">It is interesting to note that&#x000a0;the BSKG failed to capture a decline of <italic>Ne</italic> for the C<sub>EA/BI-RW</sub> and C<sub>EA/TZ</sub> sub-epidemics since the middle-late 1990s onwards, while the BDSKY model failed to capture a R<sub>e</sub> &#x02264;1 for the C<sub>EA/ET</sub> sub-epidemics at the same time interval, suggesting that the performance of different phylodynamics approaches could be affected by different factors. The BSKG model requires strongly informative data to prevent erroneous estimates of <italic>Ne</italic> stabilization as pointed by a recent study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. The lower proportion of HIV-1 subtype C sequences sampled at recent times (since 2008 onwards) in the C<sub>EA/BI-RW</sub> (6%) and C<sub>EA/TZ</sub> (30%) datasets compared with the C<sub>EA/ET</sub> datasets (&#x02265;70%) may have reduce the ability of&#x000a0;this coalescent model to capture changes in <italic>Ne</italic> for the C<sub>EA/BI-RW</sub> and C<sub>EA/TZ</sub> sub-epidemics at most recent times. The BDSKY model could be more robust to the paucity of coalescent events at most recent time; but its performance could be limited by the number of time intervals (changes in R<sub>e</sub>) specified. Increasing the number of R<sub>e</sub>-changes may allow a better fit of&#x000a0;the R<sub>e</sub> trajectories to the&#x000a0;epidemiological data for the C<sub>EA/ET</sub> sub-epidemics. This strategy, however, resulted in a lack of parameter convergence and huge 95% HPD intervals, indicating that accurate R<sub>e</sub> estimations at more time intervals would require a&#x000a0;larger number of C<sub>EA/ET</sub> sequences than those used in&#x000a0;the present study.</p><p id="Par23">The BSKL, BSKG and BDSKY models support quite consistent epidemic dynamics for the C<sub>EA/BR</sub> sub-epidemic until the late 1990s. According to the coalescent models, the <italic>Ne</italic> of the C<sub>EA/BR</sub> subclade growth exponentially until the early (BSKL) or mid-1990s (BSKG) and then reached a plateau. In agreement, the BDSKY model supports an expanding epidemic (R<sub>e</sub> &#x0003e;1) in the first time interval (~ mid-1970s to late 1980s) and a transient epidemic stabilization (R<sub>e</sub> ~ 1) in the second time interval (~ late 1980s to early 2000s). The stabilization of the C<sub>EA/BR</sub> incidence since the early/mid-1990s is in line with the reported trend toward stability of the new HIV cases in Rio Grande do Sul and Santa Catarina states since the mid-1990s<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>, probably due to the implementation of prevention efforts that acted as the driven-force of people&#x02019;s behavioral changes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref></sup>. While coalescent models support a roughly constant <italic>Ne</italic> for the C<sub>EA/BR</sub> sub-epidemic until the most recent sampling time, the BDSKY model uncovers a new epidemic increase (R<sub>e</sub> &#x0003e;1) at the last time interval. This matches with an upward trend of new HIV diagnoses in Rio Grande do Sul and Santa Catarina states since 2007<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>. Such epidemiological changes are probably too recent to be fully captured by coalescent models.</p><p id="Par24">A recent study using BSKG to analyze the population dynamics of the C<sub>EA/BR</sub> sub-epidemic from <italic>pol</italic> and <italic>env</italic> sequences from HET and men having sex with men (MSM) individuals reported a continuous increase in the <italic>Ne</italic> until mid to late 2000&#x02019;s that was associated with the recent expansion of subtype C throughout the MSM group<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Interestingly, universal access to free fully suppressive ARV therapy is available in Brazil since the late 1990s<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup> and an association between ARV treatment availability and increases in sexual risk behavior (and consequent rise in HIV incidence) have been previously reported among MSM from developed countries<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref></sup>. Our BDSKY analyses of sequences from HET individuals support that the recent expansion of the C<sub>EA/BR</sub> sub-epidemic is probably not restricted to a specific group, but also occurred among HET individuals. Increases in sexual risk behavior among HET individuals fully agrees with the sustained increase of HIV<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup> and other sexually transmitted disease observed in Southern Brazil since 2010<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par25">A drawback to consider about the highlighted agreements and disagreements between the available epidemiological data and our phylodynamic modeling is that while the former characterizes the HIV epidemic of each of the countries/regions as a whole, the C<sub>EA</sub> clade herein analyzed is not the only prevalent HIV lineage in all of them<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Then, it is possible that trends in the number of new HIV cases belonging to the C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemics do not fully correspond with those of the overall HIV epidemic. Besides, a more homogeneous and dense sampling of each C<sub>EA</sub> sub-epidemic over time as well as the use of sequence data from multiple genetic loci<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup> and the incorporation of covariates into the demographic inference framework<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup> may improve the performance of phylodynamics methods to recover true population trajectories.</p><p id="Par26">Overall, this study supports that major HIV-1 C<sub>EA</sub> lineages circulating in Eastern Africa and Southern Brazil seem to have had an exponential spread with very similar growth rates until the early/mid-1990s. The overall agreement of the R<sub>0</sub> and R<sub>e</sub>-initial values here estimated from genetic sequences with those previously obtained from classical epidemiological data strengthen the utility of coalescent and the birth-death phylodynamic approaches to infer relevant epidemiological information of HIV epidemics at the earlier stages. Our data supports that introduction of universal access to ARV therapy during the late 1990s and early 2000s coincides with a declining epidemic in Eastern Africa, but with an upward trend of new HIV diagnoses in Southern Brazil. Our results also underscore the importance of the joint use of both coalescent and birth-death phylodynamic approaches for the analyses of HIV population dynamics given its&#x000a0;apparent differential sensitivity for recovering changes in population dynamics at most recent times in different datasets.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec11"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_26824_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary Information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_26824_MOESM2_ESM.csv"><caption><p>Dataset 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_26824_MOESM3_ESM.csv"><caption><p>Dataset 2</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_26824_MOESM4_ESM.csv"><caption><p>Dataset 3</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_26824_MOESM5_ESM.csv"><caption><p>Dataset 4</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_26824_MOESM6_ESM.csv"><caption><p>Dataset 5</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-018-26824-4.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>D.M. was funded by fellowships from &#x0201c;Agencia Nacional de Investigaci&#x000f3;n e Innovaci&#x000f3;n (ANII-Uruguay)&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Coordena&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Aperfei&#x000e7;oamento de Pessoal de N&#x000ed;vel Superior (CAPES-Brazil)&#x0201d;. E.D. was funded by a fellowship from &#x0201c;Programa Nacional de P&#x000f3;s-Doutorado (CAPES-Brazil)&#x0201d;. TG in 2016&#x02013;2017/2 was supported by the VIROGENESIS Project as part of the European Union&#x02019;s Horizon 2020 Research and Innovation Programme under grant agreement 634650 and from a Flagship grant from the Medical Research Council (MRC) of the Republic of South Africa (MRC- RFA-FSP-01-2013/UKZN HIVEPI).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Conceived and design the study: G.B. Collected de data: A.P., D.M., E.D., S.A. and T.G. Performed the experiments: D.M. and T.G. Analyzed the data: D.M., E.D., G.B. and T.G. Wrote the first draft: D.M. and G.B. All authors assisted with the writing and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par27">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hemelaar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouws</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghys</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Osmanov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global trends in molecular epidemiology of HIV-1 during 2000&#x02013;2007</article-title><source>AIDS</source><year>2011</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>689</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/QAD.0b013e328342ff93</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21297424?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21297424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gr&#x000e4;f</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The increasing prevalence of HIV-1 subtype C in Southern Brazil and its dispersion through the continent</article-title><source>Virology</source><year>2013</year><volume>435</volume><fpage>170</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2012.08.048</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22999094?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22999094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faria</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The early spread and epidemic ignition of HIV-1 in human populations</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2014</year><volume>346</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1256739</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25278604?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25278604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic structure in African HIV-1 subtype C revealed by selective sequential pruning</article-title><source>Virology</source><year>2011</year><volume>415</volume><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2011.03.021</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21507449?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21507449</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delatorre</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name><name><surname>Bello</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylodynamics of HIV-1 subtype C epidemic in East Africa</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0041904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delatorre</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tracing the Origin and Northward Dissemination Dynamics of HIV-1 Subtype C in Brazil</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e74072</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074072</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24069269?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24069269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A specific subtype C of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 circulates in Brazil</article-title><source>AIDS</source><year>2003</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00002030-200301030-00004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12478065?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12478065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bello</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Origin and evolutionary history of HIV-1 subtype C in Brazil</article-title><source>AIDS</source><year>2008</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1993</fpage><lpage>2000</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/QAD.0b013e328315e0aa</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18753928?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18753928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fontella</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schrago</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the origin of HIV-1 subtype C in South America</article-title><source>AIDS</source><year>2008</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>2001</fpage><lpage>2011</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/QAD.0b013e3283108f69</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18784462?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18784462</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pillay</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gifford</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>UK</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Collaborative Group on HIV Drug Resistance. The HIV-1 subtype C epidemic in South America is linked to the United Kingdom</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e9311</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009311</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20174561?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20174561</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gr&#x000e4;f</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Contribution of Epidemiological Predictors in Unraveling the Phylogeographic History of HIV-1 Subtype C in Brazil</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>12341</fpage><lpage>12348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.01681-15</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26423943?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26423943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>V&#x000e9;ras</surname><given-names>NMC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Br&#x000ed;gido</surname><given-names>LFDM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Salemi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-resolution phylogenetics and phylogeography of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 subtype C epidemic in South America</article-title><source>J. Gen. Virol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>1698</fpage><lpage>1709</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/vir.0.028951-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21450946?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21450946</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gr&#x000e4;f</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive Characterization of HIV-1 Molecular Epidemiology and Demographic History in the Brazilian Region Most Heavily Affected by AIDS</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>8160</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.00363-16</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27384663?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27384663</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bello</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Short communication: Evidences of recent decline in the expansion rate of the HIV type 1 subtype C and CRF31_BC epidemics in southern Brazil</article-title><source>AIDS Res. Hum. Retroviruses</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1065</fpage><lpage>1069</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/aid.2009.0106</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19895209?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19895209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pybus</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The epidemic behavior of the hepatitis C virus</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2001</year><volume>292</volume><fpage>2323</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1058321</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11423661?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11423661</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Estimating the basic reproductive number from viral sequence data</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msr217</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21890480?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21890480</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Y-X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exact coalescent for the Wright-Fisher model</article-title><source>Theor. Popul. Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>385</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tpb.2005.11.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16426654?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16426654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diekmann</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Heesterbeek</surname><given-names>JAP</given-names></name><name><surname>Metz</surname><given-names>JAJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the definition and the computation of the basic reproduction ratio R 0 in models for infectious diseases in heterogeneous populations</article-title><source>J. Math. Biol.</source><year>1990</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00178324</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2117040?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2117040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratmann</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Koelle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inference for nonlinear epidemiological models using genealogies and time series</article-title><source>PLoS Comput. Biol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e1002136</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002136</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21901082?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21901082</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boskova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonhoeffer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inference of epidemiological dynamics based on simulated phylogenies using birth-death and coalescent models</article-title><source>PLoS Comput. Biol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e1003913</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003913</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25375100?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25375100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhnert</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonhoeffer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Birth-death skyline plot reveals temporal changes of epidemic spread in HIV and hepatitis Cvirus (HCV)</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source><year>2013</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>228</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1207965110</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23248286?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23248286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pollakis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Recombination of HIV Type 1C (C&#x02032;/C&#x02033;) in Ethiopia: Possible Link of EthHIV-1C&#x02032; to Subtype C Sequences from the High-Prevalence Epidemics in India and Southern Africa</article-title><source>AIDS Res. Hum. Retroviruses</source><year>2003</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>999</fpage><lpage>1008</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/088922203322588350</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14678607?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14678607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lole</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Full-length human immunodeficiency virus type 1 genomes from subtype C-infected seroconverters in India, with evidence of intersubtype recombination</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9847317?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9847317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Plewniak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeanmougin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The CLUSTAL X windows interface: Flexible strategies for multiple sequence alignment aided by quality analysis tools</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>4876</fpage><lpage>4882</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/25.24.4876</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9396791?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9396791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>New Algorithms and Methods to Estimate Maximum-Likelihood Phylogenies: Assessing the Performance of PhyML 3.0</article-title><source>Syst. Biol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sysbio/syq010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20525638?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20525638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lethiec</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Duroux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PHYML Online - A web server for fast maximum likelihood-based phylogenetic inference</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>557</fpage><lpage>559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gki352</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>jModelTest: phylogenetic model averaging</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1253</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msn083</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18397919?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18397919</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BEAST: Bayesian evolutionary analysis by sampling trees</article-title><source>BMC Evol. Biol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>214</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2148-7-214</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17996036?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17996036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouckaert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>BEAST 2: a software platform for Bayesian evolutionary analysis</article-title><source>PLoS Comput. Biol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e1003537</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003537</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24722319?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24722319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pybus</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bayesian coalescent inference of past population dynamics from molecular sequences</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1185</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msi103</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15703244?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15703244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improving bayesian population dynamics inference: A coalescent-based model for multiple loci</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mss265</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23180580?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23180580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baele</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improving the accuracy of demographic and molecular clock model comparison while accommodating phylogenetic uncertainty</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>2157</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mss084</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22403239?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22403239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rambaut, A., Suchard, M. &#x00026; Drummond, A. Tracer v1.6. Available at: http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/tracer/ (2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SYW</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relaxed phylogenetics and dating with confidence</article-title><source>PLoS Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e88</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0040088</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16683862?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16683862</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Max Carvalho</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pybus</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring the temporal structure of heterochronous sequences using TempEst (formerly Path-O-Gen)</article-title><source>Virus Evol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>vew007</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ve/vew007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27774300?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27774300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mhalu, F. S. <italic>et al</italic>. Some Aspects on the Epidemiology of AIDS and Infections with the Human Immunodeficiency Virus in the United Republic of Tanzania. In <italic>AIDS and Associated Cancers in Africa 50&#x02013;60 (S. Karger AG</italic>, 10.1159/000415521 (1988).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Serwadda</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Slim Disease: A new disease in Uganda and its association with HTLV-III infection</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1985</year><volume>326</volume><fpage>849</fpage><lpage>852</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(85)90122-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bayley</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HTLV-III serology distinguishes atypical and endemic Kaposi&#x000b4;s sarcoma in Africa</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1985</year><volume>325</volume><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(85)91383-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Melbye</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The natural history of human T lymphotropic virus-III infection: the cause ofAIDS</article-title><source>Br. Med. J.</source><year>1986</year><volume>292</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.292.6512.5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3002536</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jonckheer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cluster of HTLV-III/LAV infection in an African family</article-title><source>Lancet (London, England)</source><year>1985</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>400</fpage><lpage>1</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(85)91423-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stoneburner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Carballo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Saidel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simulation of HIV incidence dynamics in the Rakai population-based cohort, Uganda</article-title><source>AIDS</source><year>1998</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>226</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9468379?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9468379</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Notification Aggregation Information System (SINAN) [in Portuguese]. Available at: http://www.portalsinan.saude.gov.br/dados-epidemiologicos-sinan. (Accessed: 15th November 2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Williams, B. G. &#x00026; Gouws, E. R0 and the elimination of HIV in Africa: Will 90-90-90 be sufficient? <italic>arXiv</italic><bold>1304.3720</bold> Epub, 5&#x02013;7 (2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gender inequality and HIV transmission: a global analysis</article-title><source>J Int AIDS Soc</source><year>2014</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>19035</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7448/IAS.17.1.19035</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24976436?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24976436</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramjee</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Daniels</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Women and HIV in Sub-Saharan Africa</article-title><source>AIDS Res. Ther.</source><year>2013</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>30</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1742-6405-10-30</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24330537?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24330537</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nyindo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complementary factors contributing to the rapid spread of HIV-I in sub-Saharan Africa: a review</article-title><source>East Afr. Med. J.</source><year>2005</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4314/eamj.v82i1.9293</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16122111?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16122111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buv&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishikwabo-Nsarhaza</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutangadura</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The spread and effect of HIV-1 infection in sub-Saharan Africa</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2002</year><volume>359</volume><fpage>2011</fpage><lpage>2017</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(02)08823-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12076570?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12076570</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">UNAIDS. HIV/AIDS and conflict. Available at: http://data.unaids.org/topics/security/fs_conflict_en.pdf. (Accessed: 12th November 2017) (2003).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spiegel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HIV/AIDS among conflict affected and displaced populations: dispelling myths and taking action</article-title><source>Disasters</source><year>2004</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0361-3666.2004.00261.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15344944?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15344944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omare</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanekar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determinants of HIV/AIDS in armed conflict populations</article-title><source>J. Public Health Africa</source><year>2011</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>e9</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Iliffe, J. <italic>The African AIDS epidemic: a history</italic>. (Oxford: James Currey, 2006).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Terminski</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development-Induced Displacement and Resettlement: Theoretical Frameworks and Current Challenges</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2013</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>101</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Vit&#x000f3;ria</surname><given-names>MAA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fighting against AIDS: the Brazilian experience</article-title><source>AIDS</source><year>2002</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>2373</fpage><lpage>2383</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00002030-200212060-00001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12461410?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12461410</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gr&#x000e4;f</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HIV-1 genetic diversity and drug resistance among treatment na&#x000ef;ve patients from Southern Brazil: An association of HIV-1 subtypes with exposure categories</article-title><source>J. Clin. Virol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcv.2011.04.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21622023?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21622023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Silva</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inferring pandemic growth rates from sequence data</article-title><source>J. R. Soc. Interface</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1797</fpage><lpage>1808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsif.2011.0850</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22337627?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22337627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hearst</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Condom promotion for AIDS prevention in the developing world: Is it working?</article-title><source>Stud. Fam. Plann.</source><year>2004</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1728-4465.2004.00004.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15067787?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15067787</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lugalla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Social, cultural and sexual behavioral determinants of observed decline in HIV infection trends: Lessons from the Kagera Region, Tanzania</article-title><source>Soc. Sci. Med.</source><year>2004</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2003.10.033</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15087153?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15087153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ng&#x02019;weshemi</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Changes in male sexual behaviour in response to the AIDS epidemic: evidence from a cohort study in urban Tanzania</article-title><source>AIDS</source><year>1996</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1415</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00002030-199610000-00015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8902072?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8902072</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Macintyre</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sosler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x02018;It&#x02019;s not what you know, but who you knew&#x02019;: examining the relationship between behavior change and AIDS mortality in Africa</article-title><source>AIDS Educ. Prev.</source><year>2001</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1521/aeap.13.2.160.19736</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11398960?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11398960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HIV and TB in Eastern and SouthernAfrica: Evidence for behaviour change and the impact of ART</article-title><source>arXiv</source><year>2014</year><volume>1406.6912</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. Countries offering free access to HIV treatment. 1&#x02013;2 (2005). Available at: http://www.who.int/hiv/countries_freeaccess.pdf. (Accessed: 21st November 2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">&#x02018;3 by 5&#x02019; country information. <italic>WHO</italic> (2011). Available at: http://www.who.int/3by5/countryprofiles/en/. (Accessed: 21st November 2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">United Nations Joint Program on HIV/AIDS (UNAIDS). AIDSinfo. Available at: http://aidsinfo.unaids.org/. (Accessed: 1st December 2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Biek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Suchard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding Past Population Dynamics: Bayesian Coalescent-Based Modeling with Covariates</article-title><source>Syst. Biol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>1041</fpage><lpage>1056</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sysbio/syw050</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27368344?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27368344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Volz, E. M. &#x00026; Didelot, X. Modeling the Growth and Decline of Pathogen Effective Population Size Provides Insight into Epidemic Dynamics and Drivers of Antimicrobial Resistance. <italic>Syst. Biol. e-pub ahead print</italic>. 10.1093/sysbio/syy007 (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berkman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz-Laboy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Paiva</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Critical Analysis of the Brazilian Response to HIV/AIDS: Lessons Learned for Controlling and Mitigating the Epidemic in Developing Countries</article-title><source>Am. J. Public Health</source><year>2005</year><volume>9595</volume><fpage>1162</fpage><lpage>1172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2004.054593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brazilian Ministry of Health. AIDS Epidemiological Bulletin [in Portuguese]. Available at: http://www.aids.gov.br/pt-br/pub/2016/boletim-epidemiologico-de-aids-2016 (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bezemer, D. <italic>et al</italic>. A resurgent HIV-1 epidemic among men who have sex with men in the era of potent antiretroviral therapy. <italic>AIDS</italic> 1071&#x02013;1077 (2008).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Population-based HIV-1 incidence in France, 2003&#x02013;08: a modelling analysis</article-title><source>Lancet Infect. Dis.</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>682</fpage><lpage>687</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(10)70167-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20832367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">The Kirby Institute/Sydney University of New South Wales. HIV, viral hepatitis and sexually transmissible infections in Australia: Annual Surveillance Report. Available at: https://kirby.unsw.edu.au/sites/default/files/kirby/report/SERP_2011-Annual-Surveillance-Report.pdf. (Accessed: 29th November 2017) (2011).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Garnett</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is HIV out of control in the UK? An example of analysing patterns of HIV spreading using incidence-to-prevalence ratios</article-title><source>AIDS</source><year>2006</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1898</fpage><lpage>1901</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.aids.0000244213.23574.fa</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16954735?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16954735</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brazilian Ministry of Health. Syphilis Epidemiological Bulletin [in Portuguese]. Available at: http://www.aids.gov.br/pt-br/pub/2017/boletim-epidemiologico-de-sifilis-2017 (2017).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>