<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>No therapeutics have yet been approved to treat diseases caused by SARS-CoV-2 or other coronaviruses (
 <xref rid="B169" ref-type="bibr">169</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B170" ref-type="bibr">170</xref>). By mid March 2020, WHO launched the global “Solidarity” clinical trial for COVID-19 treatments to assess the effectiveness of four potential therapeutic options, namely remdesivir, lopinavir/ritonavir with and without IFN-β, and chloroquine or hydroxychloroquine (
 <xref rid="B171" ref-type="bibr">171</xref>). Remdesivir, already early suggested to be the most promising compound (
 <xref rid="B172" ref-type="bibr">172</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B173" ref-type="bibr">173</xref>), is a pro-drug of an adenosine nucleotide analog, which upon incorporation in the growing RNA chain potently inhibits RNA-dependent RNA polymerases inducing synthesis arrest (
 <xref rid="B172" ref-type="bibr">172</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B174" ref-type="bibr">174</xref>). Remdesivir has broad antiviral activity against several RNA viruses 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>, including SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="B174" ref-type="bibr">174</xref>–
 <xref rid="B177" ref-type="bibr">177</xref>), and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> against SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV (
 <xref rid="B176" ref-type="bibr">176</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B178" ref-type="bibr">178</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B179" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>). Whereas no significant improvement was observed in an initial trial of 237 patients receiving remdesivir (
 <xref rid="B180" ref-type="bibr">180</xref>), preliminary results from the larger Adaptive Covid-19 Treatment Trial (ACTT) showed that remdesivir significantly shortened the time to recovery in patients with lower airway involvement, and interestingly, another study found no difference between treatment with remdesivir for 5 days compared to 10 days (
 <xref rid="B181" ref-type="bibr">181</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B182" ref-type="bibr">182</xref>). However, importantly, remdesivir did not show major efficacy in patients with severe COVID-19 in the ICU (
 <xref rid="B183" ref-type="bibr">183</xref>), possibly because host responses may be major determinants at that stage, rather than viral replication. Promising results in controlling SARS-CoV-2 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> have also been demonstrated for the protease inhibitor lopinavir/ritonavir, licensed for HIV treatment (
 <xref rid="B184" ref-type="bibr">184</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B185" ref-type="bibr">185</xref>), as well as for chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine presently used in the treatment of malaria and autoimmune diseases (
 <xref rid="B175" ref-type="bibr">175</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B186" ref-type="bibr">186</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B187" ref-type="bibr">187</xref>). However, a randomized trial including 199 COVID-19 patients showed no immediate 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> benefits of lopinavir/ritonavir (
 <xref rid="B188" ref-type="bibr">188</xref>). Similarly, clinical trials on chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine have identified methodological limitations and conflicting results, even suggesting a negative effect of hydroxychloroquine (
 <xref rid="B189" ref-type="bibr">189</xref>–
 <xref rid="B195" ref-type="bibr">195</xref>). In May 2020, a multinational analysis reported the use of hydroxychloroquine or chloroquine, with or without a macrolide, for treatment of COVID-19 comprising data from 671 hospitals in six continents (
 <xref rid="B196" ref-type="bibr">196</xref>). This study failed to show any beneficial effect of the two drugs; moreover, concerns were raised about whether these drugs caused higher in-hospital mortality (
 <xref rid="B197" ref-type="bibr">197</xref>). Notably, the study was retracted shortly after publication, whereas the hydroxychloroquine studies currently continue after evaluation of the safety data by the WHO (
 <xref rid="B198" ref-type="bibr">198</xref>).
</p>
