<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The effectiveness of agents blocking either IL-1 or IL-6, i.e., the receptor-targeted monoclonal antibodies anakinra and tocilizumab, respectively, in the treatment of patients with severe COVID-19 in the ICU have received considerable interest due to the well-established role of these cytokines in immunopathology and association with poor clinical outcome (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). Promising results have been reported for individuals or small groups of COVID-19 patients treated with tocilizumab (
 <xref rid="B203" ref-type="bibr">203</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B204" ref-type="bibr">204</xref>) and anakinra (
 <xref rid="B205" ref-type="bibr">205</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B206" ref-type="bibr">206</xref>), the latter potentially also beneficial in treating COVID-19 related HLH (
 <xref rid="B207" ref-type="bibr">207</xref>). The results of ongoing randomized, controlled clinical trials (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B208" ref-type="bibr">208</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B209" ref-type="bibr">209</xref>) will ultimately determine whether such strategies to dampen immune responses will prove beneficial and safe. So far, no significantly increased tendency to severe COVID-19 was reported in patients receiving these medications (DMARDs) for the treatment of rheumatologic conditions (
 <xref rid="B210" ref-type="bibr">210</xref>). On a more hypothetical basis, the complement system has been suggested as a target for treatment (
 <xref rid="B211" ref-type="bibr">211</xref>). Finally, numerous ongoing studies are investigating additional novel therapeutic strategies (
 <xref rid="B212" ref-type="bibr">212</xref>) and candidate vaccines (
 <xref rid="B213" ref-type="bibr">213</xref>) against SARS-CoV-2. Despite the rapidly evolving number of publications on potential COVID-19 therapeutics, thus far only a very limited number of well-designed clinical trials are available. However, to evaluate the effectiveness and potential adverse effects of future treatments, the results of thorough large-scale, randomized, controlled trials are crucial. Notably, a number of fundamental immunological and virological questions need to be addressed before a vaccine candidate is available. These include aspects related to the mutation rate of the virus, the strength of immunity induced by SARS-CoV-2 and the relative contributions from humoral or cellular immunity, and not least the duration of a protective immune response.
</p>
