<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>WNV is an avian zoonosis, being maintained in nature by transmission among ornithophagic 
 <italic>Culex</italic> mosquitoes and a wide-variety of birds, especially those in the order Passeriformes. Several 
 <italic>Culex</italic> species have been implicated as vectors based mostly on laboratory vector competence studies, including 
 <italic>Culex univittatus, Culex neavei</italic> and perhaps the 
 <italic>Culex pipiens</italic> complex in Africa [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45-viruses-05-02079">45</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46-viruses-05-02079">46</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47-viruses-05-02079">47</xref>], 
 <italic>Cx. pipiens</italic> complex and perhaps 
 <italic>Culex modestus</italic> and 
 <italic>Culex perexiguus</italic> in Europe [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48-viruses-05-02079">48</xref>], 
 <italic>Culex annulirostris</italic> and perhaps the 
 <italic>Cx. pipiens</italic> complex in Australia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49-viruses-05-02079">49</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50-viruses-05-02079">50</xref>], and 
 <italic>Culex bitaeniorhynchus, Culex vishnui, Culex pseudovishnui, Culex tritaeniorhynchus</italic> and 
 <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> in India and Pakistan [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51-viruses-05-02079">51</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52-viruses-05-02079">52</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53-viruses-05-02079">53</xref>]. However, the exact role of these species in virus epidemiology has been confusing due to their frequent blood feeding on large mammals and the limited numbers of isolations made during outbreaks and ecological investigations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54-viruses-05-02079">54</xref>]. A large variety of migratory and resident birds species have been found naturally infected [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2-viruses-05-02079">2</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55-viruses-05-02079">55</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56-viruses-05-02079">56</xref>], but few host competence studies have been conducted to ascertain their importance in transmission. In addition, the apparent repeated introduction of WNV into Europe seems to have resulted in minimal avian mortality, despite the fact that several isolates from outbreaks have contained the NS3 T249P mutation associated with virulence in American Crows in North America (NA) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57-viruses-05-02079">57</xref>]. Interestingly, mortality in southbound migrating White Storks (Ciconiidae) was reported in Israel, and this WNV strain later was associated with wide-spread mortality in domestic geese [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58-viruses-05-02079">58</xref>] and was closely related to the strain that invaded NYC the following year [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40-viruses-05-02079">40</xref>].
</p>
