<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There is a steady increase in the reports of COVID-19 in companion and wild animals around the world. Further studies are required to evaluate the potential of animals (especially companion animals) to serve as an efficient reservoir host that can further alter the dynamics of human-to-human transmission (
 <xref rid="B330" ref-type="bibr">330</xref>). To date, two pet dogs (Hong Kong) and four pet cats (one each from Belgium and Hong Kong, two from the United States) have tested positive for SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="B335" ref-type="bibr">335</xref>). The World Organization for Animal Health (OIE) has confirmed the diagnosis of COVID-19 in both dogs and cats due to human-to-animal transmission (
 <xref rid="B331" ref-type="bibr">331</xref>). The similarity observed in the gene sequence of SARS-CoV-2 from an infected pet owner and his dog further confirms the occurrence of human-to-animal transmission (
 <xref rid="B333" ref-type="bibr">333</xref>). Even though asymptomatic, feline species should be considered a potential transmission route from animals to humans (
 <xref rid="B326" ref-type="bibr">326</xref>). However, currently, there are no reports of SARS-CoV-2 transmission from felines to human beings. Based on the current evidence, we can conclude that cats are susceptible to SARS-CoV-2 and can get infected by human beings. However, evidence of cat-to-human transmission is lacking and requires further studies (
 <xref rid="B332" ref-type="bibr">332</xref>). Rather than waiting for firmer evidence on animal-to-human transmission, necessary preventive measures are advised, as well as following social distancing practices among companion animals of different households (
 <xref rid="B331" ref-type="bibr">331</xref>). One of the leading veterinary diagnostic companies, IDEXX, has conducted large-scale testing for COVID-19 in specimens collected from dogs and cats. However, none of the tests turned out to be positive (
 <xref rid="B334" ref-type="bibr">334</xref>).
</p>
