<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0210">Teicoplanin is a glycopeptide antibiotic produced by the actinomycete 
 <italic>Actinoplanes teichomyceticus</italic> [
 <xref rid="bb0710" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>]. It is currently approved to treat Gram-positive bacterial infections like Staphylococcal infections [
 <xref rid="bb0715" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>]. Teicoplanin has also shown its activity against an array of viruses like the influenza virus, hepatitis C virus, Ebola, HIV, flavivirus and on corona virus-like SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV [
 <xref rid="bb0720" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>]. Teicoplanin inhibits the transpeptidase activities and transglycosylation reaction by nonspecifically binding to the outside layers of the peptidoglycan structure followed by binding to the terminal amino acids which constitute the building blocks of the peptidoglycan cell wall [
 <xref rid="bb0725" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>]. Thus, teicoplanin specifically stops bacterial growth by inhibiting the biosynthesis of the bacterial cell wall [
 <xref rid="bb0730" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>]. Teicoplanin binds to peptidoglycan and inhibits the cell wall lytic enzymes resulting in cell freezing [
 <xref rid="bb0725" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>]. Teicoplanin acts against coronavirus, by inhibiting the genome viral RNA release and thereby preventing the replication of the virus-cell cycle. This inhibition activity is because of teicoplanin acting on the early stage of the viral life cycle by inhibiting the low pH cleavage of viral spike protein by cathepsin L in the late endosome [
 <xref rid="bb0720" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>]. In the case of SARS-CoV-2 teicoplanin acts in the same way by targeting to the cleavage site for cathepsin L present in the spike protein. A study to test the efficacy of teicoplanin on 2019-nCoV showed that teicoplanin efficiently inhibits the entry of the 2019-nCoV spike pseudovirus into the cytoplasm in a dose-dependent manner [
 <xref rid="bb0735" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>]. Teicoplanin is poorly absorbed after oral administration. It has 90% bioavailability upon administering intramuscularly. The protein binding of the drug is 90–95% and it is metabolized in the liver by hydroxylation reaction to give metabolites 1 and 2 [
 <xref rid="bb0740" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>]. The mean volume of distribution at steady state for teicoplanin was found to be 40–70 L. It is eliminated by the renal pathway [
 <xref rid="bb0745" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>]. Hypersensitivity at the site of injection is the major side effect associated with teicoplanin. Other than this it may cause bronchospasm and anaphylactic shock. Teicoplanin can also cause nephrotoxicity and ototoxicity. Tachycardia, fatigue, headache, tremors, diarrhea, and elevation of liver enzymes are the other reported side effects [
 <xref rid="bb0745" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>].
</p>
