<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Different from most of other enveloped viruses using a single Env to mediate viral fusion process, HSV utilize a set of surface glycoproteins including gD, gH/gL, and gB as the core fusion components. Therein gD acts as the receptor-binding protein, gH/gL as the fusion regulator and gB as the class III fusogen (
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Heldwein et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Arii and Kawaguchi, 2018</xref>). Taking HSV-1 as the example, HSV-1 gD (369-amino acids) is a type I membrane glycoprotein with a short cytoplasmic tail and an ectodomain with an immunoglobulin-like core flanked by N- and C-terminal extensions (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Carfi et al., 2001</xref>). As shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5A</xref>, HSV-1 gH is an 838-amino acid type I membrane glycoprotein comprised of a single pass transmembrane domain, a short cytoplasmic tail and an ectodomain (
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Gompels and Minson, 1986</xref>). Its ectodomain can be subdivided into domains H1 (H1A and H1B), H2 and H3, and the N-terminal H1 domain binds gL to form a non-covalent heterodimer (
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Gompels and Minson, 1986</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Chowdary et al., 2010</xref>). Results showed the crystal structure of gH/gL complex does not resemble any other known viral fusogen structure. Therefore, the gB-gH/gL complex is key for fusion and can be inhibited by neutralizing antibody to gH, implying that the gH/gL complex activates gB through direct binding (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Chowdary et al., 2010</xref>). Furthermore, a recent study confirmed the C-terminal domain H3 of HSV-1 is important for interaction with gB (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Bohm et al., 2016</xref>). HSV-1 gB, is a 904-amino acid glycoprotein with an extended rodlike ectodomain, transmembrane domain (TM) and cytoplasmic domain (CP) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5A</xref>). The ectodomain has five distinct parts, domains I–V, and domain IV is fully exposed with neutralizing epitopes on it and possibly interacts with cellular receptors (
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Heldwein et al., 2006</xref>).
</p>
