<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Viral pathogenic factors can be recognized through the pattern recognition receptors (PRRs) in the host cells. The endosomal toll-like receptors (TLRs) that recognize double-strand RNA (dsRNA) in endosomes, and the cytoplasmic receptor family complex form DEAD box, DEAH and the SKI proteins (DExD/H box), RNA helicases, Retinoic-acid inducible gene I (RIG-I) and Melanoma differentiation-associated protein 5 (MDA5)) that recognize intracellular double-strand dsRNA or single-strand viral RNA (ssRNA) [
 <xref rid="B121-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>], are the most important sensors in human cells that are implicated in detecting viral nucleic acids. After viral recognition by these two molecules, the interferon regulatory factors and the NF-kB (Nuclear factor kappa light chain enhancer of activated B cells) transcriptional molecules are activated, and these signaling cascades aid in generating IFN-α/β and inflammatory cytokines to activate the DC for an antiviral response. In the case of DENV, infected cells do not express themselves as a viral ligand sensed by retinoic-acid inducible gene I (RIG-I) and melanoma differentiation-associated protein 5 (MDA5), which is the reason why viral antibody is not detected by RNA sensors and C-type lectin domain family 5 member A (CLEC5A) does not block DENV infection [
 <xref rid="B122-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. Other important molecules such as toll-like receptors (TLR3) also sense dsRNA and can restrict DENV replication in different cell lineages [
 <xref rid="B123-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>,
 <xref rid="B124-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>,
 <xref rid="B125-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. DENV produces excess IFN-I (essential for DENV-induced production) through toll-like receptors 7 (TLR7) in plasmacytoid-DC, which can also restrict DENV replication in different cell lineages, as TLR3 [
 <xref rid="B126-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. Additionally, increasing inflammatory and humoral responses that decrease DENV replication have been found, such as when TLR3 and TLR7/8 agonists administrated into rhesus macaques aided in enhanced antiviral mechanisms during primary DENV infection [
 <xref rid="B127-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>]. Gene expression analysis indicates that RIG-I and MDA5 receptors promote the sensing ability in DENV-infected cells. The infected cells interact with these two receptors and stimulate interferon regulatory factor 3 (IRF-3) and the nuclear factor NF-kB that produces interferon beta (IFN-β) promoters, resulting in impaired replication of DENV. Additionally, DENV with double or single RIG-I/MDA5-deficient fibroblasts triggers both responses [
 <xref rid="B128-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. Furthermore, early detection of antibodies via RNA sensors (for examples RIG-I) enhanced DENV infection by tissue-resident mast cells that produce type IFN-I, along with chemokine ligands (CCL4, 5) and C-X-C motif chemokine ligands 10 (CXCL10) [
 <xref rid="B129-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>]. Consequently, human brain microvascular endothelial cells are infected with DENV, and rapid production of type-I IFN and proinflammatory cytokines were revoked after inhibition of RIG-I. Later, it was found that IFN-β production is induced by RIG-I, MDA5, and TLR3 sensors (major PRRs recognize innate responses to DENV infection), contributing to impairing DENV replication in vitro [
 <xref rid="B130-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>]. Activation of these major pattern recognition receptors (PRRs) by DENV generates a strong type of IFN-I response during human natural infections. Elevated levels of IFN-α for long periods in pediatric patients after the decrement period has also been reported [
 <xref rid="B131-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>]. Extant evidence (experimented upon mice) further indicates that DENV primary infection utilizes the interferon α/β receptor (IFNAR)-dependent (including STAT1-dependent and STAT1-independent) control mechanisms—where the STAT1 (Signal transducer and activator of transcription 1)-dependent mechanism controls the primary steps of infection, while the STAT1-independent mechanism controls the latter antiviral process—aiding virus propagation and disease control. In DENV primary infection, cells typically utilize both mechanisms [
 <xref rid="B132-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>,
 <xref rid="B133-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>]. Anti-CLEC5A blocks DENV by releasing pro-inflammatory cytokines and does not affect IFN-I production in the infected cells [
 <xref rid="B134-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>]. As CLEC5A blocks DENV infections, future studies are necessary to enhance CLEC5A activation.
</p>
