<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the Caribbean, the primary vector of DENV (Flavivirus), CHIKV (Alphavirus) and ZIKV (Flavivirus) is 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> is a tropical and subtropical mosquito species widely distributed around the world, mostly between latitudes 35 °N and 35 °S [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Given the vector distribution, countries located in the tropical and subtropical regions are susceptible to its invasion and spread [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In Curaçao, a Caribbean island within the Kingdom of the Netherlands, all four serotypes of dengue (DENV 1–4) have circulated during the past two decades [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. According to local health authorities, dengue epidemics occur cyclically. CHIKV caused a significant outbreak in 2014–2015, affecting up to 50% of the population (Ministry of Health, Environment and Nature of Curaçao, 2016). In 2016, the introduction of ZIKV caused another major outbreak in the country. The Department of Epidemiology and Research of the Ministry of Health (MoH) reported that since December 2015 up to August 2017, a total of 2314 laboratory-confirmed ZIKV cases were recorded. However, it should be noted that confirmed cases only represent a fraction of those who were infected, as up to 80% of the individuals with ZIKV infection are asymptomatic and not everyone experiencing symptoms, which may be very mild, will visit a health facility [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The MoH estimates that at least 50% of the local population had been infected with ZIKV (I. Gerstenbluth, personal communication). This is comparable to the reported attack rates in French Polynesia (66%) and Yap Island (73%) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].
</p>
