<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Risk communication (RC) refers to the exchange of real-time information, including advice and opinions between experts and individuals facing threats to their health, economic or social well-being [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. It is an essential tool for the prevention and control of diseases because it can supply individuals with the knowledge needed for an optimal decision-making process [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The Health Belief Model (HBM) is one of the most widely used and validated theoretical models to understand the decision-making process and the health-seeking behaviour of individuals [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Core concepts in the HBM are the perceived susceptibility and the perceived severity of the condition, leading to the perceived threat. The perception of threat is integral in the decision-making processes of individuals because it plays an essential role in motivating health behaviour change [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. An essential concept in the HBM that influences the perceived risk and health-seeking behaviour is called “cues to action”. Cues to action refer to strategies that activate readiness. According to a recent study published by Metta et al., individuals’ previous experiences in managing conditions similar to malaria were considered to be cues to action, because their past experiences seem to have informed their self-medication decisions in the context of malaria [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. According to Hochbaum (1958), cues to action could be cultural schemas of individuals or information that individuals receive from media, informal and formal networks [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Cultural schemas are deeply internalised and largely unconscious networks of associations built up over time that facilitate perception, interpretation, and action [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Thus, cultural schemas are frameworks of a specific culture that exist in an individual’s thoughts and have the ability to instigate actions. The cultural schemas are also shaped by the political context, which then influences the relation between the State and the individual/community[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008136.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].
</p>
