<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par74">The incubation period for COVID-19 is approximately 5.1 days. For 97.5% of symptomatic patients, the estimated number of days before symptom onset is 11.5 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. Acute respiratory distress syndrome occurs approximately 8 to 9 days after the incubation period [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. Regarding patients who develop myocardial injury, a median of 18.5 days passed between symptom onset and death [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>].COVID-19 patients with cardiovascular complications typically suffer from acute cardiac injury, arrhythmias, and heart failure [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. According to the National Health Commission of China (NHC), 58% of COVID-19 patients with dire symptoms had hypertension. 44% of these patients suffered from arrhythmia and 25% suffered from heart disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. The NHC stated that 11.8% of patients who died from COVID-19 endured severe heart injury due to high amounts of CTnl or cardiac arrest without having a pre-existing heart condition [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]. Interestingly, the NHC reported that some patients initially showed symptoms such as chest tightness and heart palpitations rather than the common respiratory symptoms suggesting COVID-19 may lead to chronic malady [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. Some patients previously infected by SARS-CoV later developed chronic cardiovascular damage [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. For instance, cardiovascular disorders emerged in 44% of 25 SARS-CoV patients 12 years post-infection. Hyperlipidemia progressed in 68% of patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. SARS-CoV spurred a substantial elevation of free fatty acids, lysophosphatidylcholine, lysophosphatidylethanolamine, and phosphatidylglycerol in the blood serum of these patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>].
</p>
