<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 4.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>RNA binding and exonuclease activities of ERI1 are both required for IAV cycle. (
   <bold>A</bold>) Schematic organization of ERI1. The N-terminal part contains the ‘SAF-box, Acinus and PIAS’ (SAP) domain while the C-terminal part carries the exonuclease activity. (B, C) HEK-293T cells were transfected with Strep-ERI1, Strep-ERI1 mutants (R105A, ΔSAP, D134A+E136A, i.e. ‘no DE’) or Strep-mCherry (as a control) and infected with WSN at an moi of 3 pfu/cell. At 3hpi total RNAs were extracted and the levels of NP mRNAs and vRNAs were determined by strand specific RT-qPCRs 
   <bold>(B)</bold>, or analyzed by immunoblot to assess protein expression levels (
   <bold>C</bold>). The results are expressed as the mean ratios of mRNA/vRNA ± SEM normalized to empty control, in three independent experiments. The significance was tested by one-way ANOVA with Holm-Sidak's multiple comparisons test using GraphPad Prism Software ****
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001). (D, E) HEK-293T cells were infected with WSN at an moi of 3 pfu/cell. At 3 hpi, ERI1 protein (
   <bold>D</bold>) or at 6 hpi, PB2 protein (
   <bold>E</bold>) was purified using anti-ERI1 antibodies (α-ERI1) (D) or anti-PB2 antibodies (α-PB2) (E) or control immunoglobulins (Ctrl IgG). Inputs and α-ERI1, α-PB2 and Ctrl IgG eluates were analyzed by immunoblot to detect ERI1, PB2 and/or NP. Results representative of two (D) and three (E) independent experiments are shown. (
   <bold>F</bold>) HEK-293T cells were transfected with Strep-ERI1 or Step-mCherry and infected 24hpt with WSN at an moi of 3 pfu/cell. At 6hpi, Strep-tagged proteins were purified with sepharose Strep-Tactin beads. Inputs and strep eluates were analyzed by immunoblot to detect PB2, PB1, PA and Strep. Results representative of three independent experiments are shown. (
   <bold>G</bold>) HEK-293T cells were transfected with Strep-ERI1 or Strep-empty and infected with WSN (3 pfu/cell). At 6hpi, Strep-tagged proteins were purified with sepharose Strep-Tactin beads. Complexes bound to the beads were incubated with RNase A (+ RNase) or Rnasin (– RNase) for 1 h. Inputs and Strep-tagged eluates were analyzed by immunoblot to detect ERI1, PB2 and NP. Results representative of three independent experiments are shown. (
   <bold>H</bold>) The levels of NP vRNAs (black bars) and mRNAs (grey bars) co-purified with Strep-ERI1 as described in (B) are expressed as the mean ± SEM of three independent experiments. The background level of detection in Strep-empty eluates was 9.9 × 10
   <sup>2</sup> and 6 × 10
   <sup>3</sup> copies for NP vRNAs and NP mRNAs, respectively. (
   <bold>I</bold>) Viral RNAs co-purified with Strep-ERI1 and Strep-empty (as a control) were expressed as a ratio of the viral RNA quantified in the input. Significance was tested by two-way ANOVA with Sidak's multiple comparisons test using GraphPad Prism Software ****
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="gkaa771fig4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
