<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A limitation of bortezomib is its narrow therapeutic window [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008336.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. In cancer patients, the most significant adverse effect reported is peripheral sensory neuropathy, which is reported in 31% to 55% of patients [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008336.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. It is important to note, however, that bortezomib-induced toxicity is related to accumulated dose, with neuropathy usually surfacing within the first five cycles of treatment, in a treatment plan where each cycle is six weeks long [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008336.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008336.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008336.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008336.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. However, for CHIKV infection, treatment schedules are not expected to last as long, given that the acute phase is resolved within two weeks. Furthermore, altering the route of administration of bortezomib from intravenous to subcutaneous has been found to significantly reduce instances of neuropathy in patients, while retaining similar efficacy [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008336.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In addition, our study has shown that proteasome inhibitors with various functional groups are able to inhibit CHIKV and cause similar changes to viral proteins. This indicates that 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> evaluation of proteasome inhibitors for treatment of CHIKV should not be limited to bortezomib. Rather, the use of newer generation proteasome inhibitors like MLN2238, which has an improved toxicity profile and is administered orally, should also be explored [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008336.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Another option is to chemically modify the structure of the proteasome inhibitor such that it is active only upon cleavage by viral proteases in infected cells. Buckley and colleagues (2011) reported the design and synthesis of a proteasome inhibitor with a large chemical moiety that blocks its entry into the proteasome unless it is cleaved by the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) protease [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008336.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. This steric-capped proteasome inhibitor was able to inhibit human proteasome activity in cell-free assays only when pre-treated with HIV protease. Indeed, a similar method could be employed to limit toxicity of bortezomib and other proteasome inhibitors in the context of CHIKV infection. Extensive optimisations of the modified proteasome inhibitor structure, together with detailed 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> validation would be needed to confirm efficacy.
</p>
