<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Usually, the PK15 porcine kidney cell line is selected to cultivate CSFV 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> in laboratories. The viral titre produced by replication and propagation of CSFV in 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>-cultured cell lines is usually low and does not cause cytopathic effects (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2020-0020_ref_016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Our data in this study indicated that the parent PK15 cell line contains cell populations with different susceptibilities to CSFV infection. After limiting dilution cell cloning, we screened two cell clones from PK15 parent cells, namely, the high-permissive PK15-1A6 and low-permissive PK15-3B1. PK15 cells are established cell lines , besides being susceptible to CSFV, are known to also be to other swine-origin viruses. It is reported that in a PK15 cell culture infected with porcine circovirus 2 (PCV2), about 20% of PK15 cells comprised the group susceptible to the virus (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2020-0020_ref_019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). It is proven that the lower virus titres which are generated from cells infected with CSFV are related to the heterogeneity of the cell line. There are many reports about the proliferation characteristics of CSFV in different cells, but there had been no cell line that could significantly enhance the propagation of CSFV 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> before this research. In this study, we developed a homogeneous PK15 cell line (PK15-1A6) which showed high susceptibility to CSFV infection and could generate CSFV in high titres, and limiting dilution cell cloning was the approach which gave success. According to previous reports, this technique has been employed to generate high- and low-permissive cells to porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome virus from the MA-104 cell line (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2020-0020_ref_007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) and to PCV2 from the PK15 cell line (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2020-0020_ref_019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Our results showed that the high-permissive PK15-1A6 showed higher proliferation ability as determined by the cell number when compared with the parent PK15 cells or the PK15-3B1 clone. Further studies need to be conducted to identify whether the rate of virus replication is correlated with the growth rate of the cell line.
</p>
