<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Hard tick species in the genus 
 <italic>Ixodes</italic> are recognized generally as common vectors of 
 <italic>B. burgdorferi</italic>. 
 <italic>I. scapularis</italic> and 
 <italic>I. pacificus</italic> are known competent vectors in the US, while 
 <italic>I. persulcatus</italic> and 
 <italic>I. ricinus</italic> are the documented vectors in Eurasia (
 <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>–
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>). The pathogen is maintained in the environment by different vertebrate hosts with varying degrees of competence. The main reservoir, the white-footed mouse, 
 <italic>Peromyscus leucopus</italic>, is found in the forests of Eastern North America (
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>). There is an extensive bibliography on the molecular diversity and adaptation of 
 <italic>B. burgdorferi</italic> to its natural environment, as well as on the impact of species diversity in a particular area on reducing LD risk (
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>–
 <xref rid="B118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>). In addition, some of these studies have also considered the effect of climate change on the geographic distribution of 
 <italic>I. scapularis</italic> in addition to its phenology in the US and Canada (
 <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>–
 <xref rid="B121" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>). Although LD in humans is more prevalent in Northeastern US, the lack of detailed studies in Southern US has prevented comparisons, and evaluations of ecological factors responsible for promoting the differential incidence of LD between these regions. Moreover, in some parts of the world the ecology and epidemiology of LD remain to be fully understood. Thus, LD is considered a transboundary zoonotic disease in that it can reach epidemic proportions in regions of the globe regardless of country borders (
 <xref rid="B122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>). This is coupled with the fact that there is unequally distributed knowledge about the ecology of this disease among the regions in which it occurs.
</p>
