<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We estimated the ZIKV reproduction number (
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub>), the average number of secondary infections caused by a single infectious individual in a fully susceptible population, for each Texas county following the method described in Perkins et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The method calculates 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> using a temperature-dependent formulation of the Ross-Macdonald model, where mosquito mortality rate (μ) and extrinsic incubation period of ZIKV (n) are temperature dependent functions; the human-mosquito transmission probability (b = 0.4), number of days of human infectiousness (c/
 <italic>r</italic> = 3.5), and the mosquito biting rate (a = 0.67) are held constant at previously calculated values [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]; and the economic-modulated mosquito-human contact scaling factor (m) is a function of county mosquito abundance and GDP data fit to historic ZIKV seroprevalence data [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. To account for uncertainty in the temperature-dependent functions (the extrinsic incubation period (EIP) and mosquito mortality rate) and in the relationship between economic index and the mosquito-to-human contact rate, Perkins et al. generated functional distributions via 1000 Monte Carlo samples from the underlying parameter distributions. We assume DENV estimates for these temperature-dependent functions, since we lack such data for ZIKV and these Flaviviruses are likely to exhibit similar relationships between temperature and EIP in 
 <italic>Ae. Aegypti</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. We used the resulting distributions to estimate 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> for each county, based on county estimates for the average August temperature, mosquito abundance from Kraemer et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], and GDP [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Our 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> estimates were similar to those reported by Perkins et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] with 95% confidence intervals spanning from 0 to 3.1 (Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S3). Given this uncertainty, and that our primary aim is to demonstrate the risk assessment framework rather than provide accurate estimates of 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> for Texas, we use these estimates to estimate relative county-level transmission risks (by scaling the county 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> estimates from 0 to 1). In each simulation, we assume that a county’s 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> is the product of its relative risk and a chosen maximum 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub>. For our case study, we assume a maximum county-level 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> of 1.5 This is consistent with historical arbovirus activity in Texas (which has never sustained a large arbovirus epidemic) and demonstrates the particular utility of the approach in distinguishing outbreaks from epidemics around the epidemic threshold of 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> = 1.
</p>
