<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Povidone‐iodine (PVP‐I) is a widely used iodine complex carried in a polyvinylpyrrolidone carrier that was developed in the 1950s and is available as a surgical skin prep agent and as a mouthwash.
 <xref rid="hed26200-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref> It has demonstrated both antibacterial and antiviral activities in past studies.
 <xref rid="hed26200-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref> While studies on virucidal activity of PVP‐I have not yet been performed specifically on SARS‐CoV‐2, there have been numerous in vitro studies demonstrating its effectiveness against multiple viruses including related coronaviruses. A 1997 study compared PVP‐I to other antiseptics in inactivating a broad range of both enveloped and nonenveloped viruses (adenovirus, mumps, rotavirus, poliovirus, Coxsackievirus, rhinovirus, herpes simplex virus, rubella, measles, influenza, and HIV) and demonstrated PVP‐I to have the broadest spectrum of antiviral activity among agents tested.
 <xref rid="hed26200-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref> Kariwa et al tested several different commercially available PVP‐I formulations against SARS‐CoV‐1 viral samples (responsible for the SARS epidemic) and found that the viral infectivity was reduced to below detectable levels within 2 minutes of application.
 <xref rid="hed26200-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref> In an industry‐sponsored study, Eggers et al carried out in vitro tests of PVP‐I solutions (1%‐7.5%) against Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS‐CoV; responsible for the MERS epidemic) and found that the viral titer reduction of &gt;99.99% within 15 seconds of application.
 <xref rid="hed26200-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>17</sup>
 </xref> A subsequent study examined a diluted PVP‐I (0.23%) formulation against SARS‐CoV‐1, MERS‐CoV, and influenza A (H1N1) applied for 15 seconds and again found a &gt;99.99% reduction of viral titers.
 <xref rid="hed26200-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref> Despite ample in vitro studies, there are few clinical studies of PVP‐I specifically against viruses. Still, in a small prospective Japanese study of school‐aged children, it was found that cohorts who were encouraged to used PVP‐I gargle had significantly lower rates of absences from school due to the common cold and influenza.
 <xref rid="hed26200-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
