<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par47">The ER is an important location for posttranslational modification, folding, and oligomerization of secretory and cell surface proteins. It is also a main intercellular signal-transducing organelle for responding to environmental changes. Many viruses depend on the extensive membranous network of the ER for their translation, replication, and packaging [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic> family, including the dengue virus (DENV) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], West Nile virus (WNV) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], yellow fever virus (YFV), hepatitis C virus (HCV) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], and Japanese encephalitis virus (JEV) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], depend on the ER for their life cycles and are called endoplasmic reticulum tropic (ER-tropic) viruses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Infection by an ER-tropic virus disrupts the normal ER function, and then ER stress is induced. To alleviate ER stress, the UPR is activated and mainly functions in translational attenuation, protein folding, protein degradation, and cellular apoptosis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. PKR-like ER kinase (PERK), transcription factor 6 (ATF6) and inositol-requiring enzyme 1 (IRE1) are the sensors of the UPR pathway. In unstressed cells, the ER chaperone immunoglobulin heavy-chain-binding protein (BIP) binds to the ER luminal domain of the three sensors. Under the condition of ER stress, however, BIP is dissociated from the three sensors and preferentially binds to misfolded and unfolded proteins. Then, the three response pathways are activated to deal with different ER stress states in a time-dependent manner [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Phosphorylated PERK phosphorylates the α-subunit of eukaryotic translation initiation factor 2 (eIF2α). Phosphorylated eIF2α (phospho-eIF2α) forms a complex with guanine nucleotide exchange factor (eIF2B) and inhibits catalysis of GDP-GTP exchange, thereby leading to the translation attenuation and contradictory expression by activating transcription factor 4 (ATF4). Activated ATF4 upregulates a series of genes related to encoding metabolism and redox regulation and helps cells recover from ER stress. Growth arrest and DNA damage-inducible protein (GADD34), which is regulated by ATF4, interacts with protein phosphatase 1 (PP1) to dephosphorylate eIF2α, thereby acting as a negative feedback loop to restore protein translation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. PERK-mediated eIF2α phosphorylation is triggered in early DENV-2 infection and suppressed in mid and late DENV-2 infection because the inhibition of eIF2α phosphorylation is necessary for viral protein synthesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The RNase activity of phosphorylated IRE1 (phospho-IRE1) has only one substrate, X-box binding protein 1 (XBP1), and removes a 26-nucleotide intron from unspliced 
 <italic>xbp1</italic>mRNA (
 <italic>xbp1u)</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. The spliced 
 <italic>xbp1</italic>mRNA (
 <italic>xbp1s</italic>) results in a frameshift mutation and encodes spliced XBP1 (XBP1s), a transcription factor that binds to the sequences of ER stress response elements (ERSEs) and UPR elements (UPREs), and upregulates the transcription of ER-association degradation (ERAD) proteins, proapoptotic proteins, and some ER chaperones [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. JEV infection activates the IRE1-XBP1 pathway and has a beneficial effect on the activation of the regulated IRE1-dependent decay (RIDD) pathway during the viral life cycle [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Cleaved ATF6 (ATF6n) also can bind to the ERSE and UPRE sequences and upregulate transcription chaperones, foldases, and lipid synthesis genes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. ATF6 is required for efficient WNV replication by maintaining cell viability and modulating the innate immune responses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. In brief, ER is an important location in viral life cycle, and UPR is closely associated with the regulation of viral replication. ZIKV is a flavivirus that its life cycle also closely depends on the extensive membranous network of the ER [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. However, whether ZIKV activates and benefits from ER stress to regulate viral replication needs to be investigated.
</p>
