<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The isobenzofuran-1-(3
 <italic>H</italic>)-ones, 1,2,3-triazolic derivatives, eugenol, and indan-1,3-diones are substances that have been described in the literature as being endowed with antiviral activities [
 <xref rid="pone.0223017.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0223017.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0223017.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Isobenzofuran-1-(3
 <italic>H</italic>) -one derivatives have several biological activities [
 <xref rid="pone.0223017.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0223017.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0223017.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], highlighting antiviral action for HIV[
 <xref rid="pone.0223017.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Indan-1,3-diones derivatives have been specifically associated with antiviral activity. Studies have indicated efficient action of indan-1,3-diones against the enzyme integrase of the HIV-1 virus [
 <xref rid="pone.0223017.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]; against the structure of human papillomavirus (HPV) [
 <xref rid="pone.0223017.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0223017.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]; and also against the Hepatitis C virus (HCV) protease [
 <xref rid="pone.0223017.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], and recently for WNV protease [
 <xref rid="pone.0223017.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Eugenol has been tested against the Herpes virus (HSV), HSV-1 (five viral isolates) and HSV-2 (five viral isolates), providing complete protection against one isolate of each type, HSV-1 and 2, and protection between 16.5% and 87.7% for the remaining isolates [
 <xref rid="pone.0223017.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0223017.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The triazole ring was associated with the molecules due to the antimicrobial activity already described for 1,2,3-triazole compounds, especially studies that demonstrated antiviral action against the Dengue virus [
 <xref rid="pone.0223017.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0223017.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. This fact prompted the authors to evaluate the effect of the compounds presenting general structures (
 <bold>I</bold>), (
 <bold>II</bold>) and (
 <bold>III</bold>) on the NS2-NB3 WNV protease.
</p>
