<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An alternative strategy proposed to combat AMR infection is based on the use of monoclonal antibodies. The main modes of action of anti-bacterial antibodies are based on the neutralization of virulence factor activities and inhibition of complement-mediated bacterial lysis. An important aspect is that the efficacy of monoclonal antibodies is dependent upon the expression level and the degree of sequence conservation of the corresponding target epitope. Hence, the ideal epitope should be highly conserved in structure and to be easily accessible for antibody binding. This is the case of monoclonal antibodies against bacterial toxins approved for clinical use which include two antibodies against anthrax (
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>) and one targeting the toxin B of 
 <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic>, approved for the prevention of recurrent infections in high-risk patients (
 <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>). As described above, the new technologies could allow the analysis of immune response and the identification of human monoclonal antibodies naturally produced by infected or vaccinated human donors. This will guide the design of novel and highly immunogenic antigens and antigen derived peptides. Analyzing the Ab-Ag complex, it would be possible to design powerful antigen molecules with high neutralization activity as in the case of the RSV preF antigen (
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>). The outstanding power of these new technologies is boosting our ability to identify, design and stabilize antigens in a very short time frame and consequently starts clinical trials immediately after (
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>). Effective medical treatments are urgently needed to address major global threats, and in this context, monoclonal antibodies represent a unique valuable weapon. In developing human monoclonal antibodies careful attention should be paid to evaluate possible reactions with human tissue at early preclinical stages. Reactions can be limited by using fully human monoclonal antibodies and by an accurate selection of the targeted epitopes.
</p>
