<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The reproduction number (R
 <sub>0</sub>) of COVID-19 infection was earlier estimated to be in the range of 1.4 to 2.5 (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>); recently, it was estimated to be 2.24 to 3.58 (
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>). Compared to its coronavirus predecessors, COVID-19 has an R
 <sub>0</sub> value that is greater than that of MERS (R
 <sub>0</sub> &lt; 1) (
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>) but less than that of SARS (R
 <sub>0</sub> value of 2 to 5) (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>). Still, to prevent further spread of disease at mass gatherings, functions remain canceled in the affected cities, and persons are asked to work from home (
 <xref rid="B232" ref-type="bibr">232</xref>). Hence, it is a relief that the current outbreak of COVID-19 infection can be brought under control with the adoption of strategic preventive and control measures along with the early isolation of subsequent cases in the coming days. Studies also report that since air traffic between China and African countries increased many times over in the decade after the SARS outbreak, African countries need to be vigilant to prevent the spread of novel coronavirus in Africa (
 <xref rid="B225" ref-type="bibr">225</xref>). Due to fear of virus spread, Wuhan City was completely shut down (
 <xref rid="B233" ref-type="bibr">233</xref>). The immediate control of the ongoing COVID-19 outbreaks appears a mammoth task, especially for developing countries, due to their inability to allocate quarantine stations that could screen infected individuals’ movements (
 <xref rid="B234" ref-type="bibr">234</xref>). Such underdeveloped countries should divert their resources and energy to enforcing the primary level of preventive measures, like controlling the entry of individuals from China or countries where the disease has flared up, isolating the infected individuals, and quarantining individuals with suspected infection. Most of the sub-Saharan African countries have a fragile health system that can be crippled in the event of an outbreak. Effective management of COVID-19 would be difficult for low-income countries due to their inability to respond rapidly due to the lack of an efficient health care system (
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>). Controlling the imported cases is critical in preventing the spread of COVID-19 to other countries that have not reported the disease until now. The possibility of an imported case of COVID-19 leading to sustained human-to-human transmission was estimated to be 0.41. This can be reduced to a value of 0.012 by decreasing the mean time from the onset of symptoms to hospitalization and can only be made possible by using intense disease surveillance systems (
 <xref rid="B235" ref-type="bibr">235</xref>). The silent importations of infected individuals (before the manifestation of clinical signs) also contributed significantly to the spread of disease across the major cities of the world. Even though the travel ban was implemented in Wuhan (
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>), infected persons who traveled out of the city just before the imposition of the ban might have remained undetected and resulted in local outbreaks (
 <xref rid="B236" ref-type="bibr">236</xref>). Emerging novel diseases like COVID-19 are difficult to contain within the country of origin, since globalization has led to a world without borders. Hence, international collaboration plays a vital role in preventing the further spread of this virus across the globe (
 <xref rid="B237" ref-type="bibr">237</xref>).
</p>
