<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">Firstly, all brain regions available were screened with our usual IHC protocols for the presence of BoAstV-CH13/NeuroS1 (using hyperimmune serum CH13-ORF2-con) and BoAstV-CH15/OvAstV-CH16 (using hyperimmune serum CH15-ORF2-var). Secondly, samples were tested with other hyperimmune sera: one specific for BoAstV-CH13/NeuroS1 (CH13-23917) and one for BoAstV-CH15/OvAstV-CH16 (CH15-ORF2-var). The generation procedures for hyperimmune sera CH13-ORF2-con, CH15-ORF2-var and CH15-ORF2-con are described elsewhere [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Polyclonal antibodies CH13-23917 were obtained by immunizing rabbits with a short polypeptide derived from the capsid protein precursor sequence of our BoAstV-CH13/NeuroS1 index case [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] (ID 45564; amino acids 60–73 of the capsid protein gene of Bovine astrovirus CH13, GenBank accession no. NC_024498.1). The immunization and subsequent affinity purification of the hyperimmune serum were performed at BioGenes GmbH (Berlin, Germany). Regarding the IHC method, tissue sections were first deparaffinised, rehydrated, and endogenous peroxidase activity was blocked in a solution of 3% H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> in methanol. They were then microwave cooked in Dako Target Retrieval Solution, pH 9 (Dako Denmark A/S, Glostrup, Denmark) for antibodies CH13-ORF2-con and CH13-23917, or Dako Target Retrieval Solution, Citrate pH 6 (Dako Denmark A/S, Glostrup, Denmark) for antibodies CH15-ORF2-var and CH15-ORF2-con. Blocking was performed with 10% Goat Serum (Normal) (Dako Denmark A/S, Glostrup, Denmark) in phosphate-buffer saline with 0.5% Tween (PBS-T). The samples were incubated with each primary antibody CH13-ORF2-con (diluted 1:100 in PBS-T), CH13-23917 (diluted 1:50 in PBS-T), CH15-ORF2-var (diluted 1:50 in PBS-T) and CH15-ORF2-con (diluted 1:50 in PBS-T) overnight at 4 °C. Finally, detection was carried out with Dako REAL Detection System (Dako Denmark A/S, Glostrup, Denmark), following the manufacturer’s instructions.
</p>
