<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Over a span of many years, numerous experiments were dedicated to ASFV stability. As far back as 1921, Montgomery (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) demonstrated that ASFV is extremely resistant to high temperatures, putrefaction and desiccation. Much later, Coggins (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) evidenced high ASFV resistance to selected chemical (trypsin and EDTA) and physical treatments (freezing/thawing and ultrasonic waves). In the same study he successfully collected viable virus after 1 h incubation at 56°C and one week at 37°C. Plowright and Parker (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>) in 1967 showed that storing at 4°C preserves infectivity of viraemic blood for at least 75 weeks and of virus-spiked medium without Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> or Mg
 <sup>2+</sup> for 61 weeks. At 37°C, medium containing ASFV remained infectious for 11–22 days, but at 60°C it was only for 30 min. It was also shown that the virus is stable over a wide pH range (from pH 3.9 to 13.4) for seven days (in serum-supplemented media) (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Another study concerning ASFV resistance to temperature was conducted more recently, and partially confirmed previous results. It was shown that the virus was stable at 4, 22, and 40°C and lost only less than 10
 <sup>1</sup> 50% haemadsorption doses (HAD
 <sub>50</sub>)/mL during 24 h incubation in EMEM. At 50°C, only a small fraction of virus remained infectious, and at 60°C no infectious virions could be detected after only 15 min (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). In summary, ASFV in tissues can survive deep freezing (−70°C) for many years without significant loss of titre, but at −20°C it systematically loses its titre, nevertheless remaining viable for at least 105 weeks (2 years) (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2019-0058_ref_042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). At 4°C it is also very stable when contained in medium; it remains infectious for at least 61 weeks (1 year and 2 months). In higher temperatures ASFV is inactivated relatively quickly. At 37°C traces of viable virus could be found after 22 days, at 56°C after 1 h, but at 60°C no longer than after 15 min.
</p>
