<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>COVID-19 is a systemic disease that affects a wide spectrum of tissues and cell types. Liver cells and bile duct cells express ACE2. However, the ACE2 expression of bile duct cells is much higher than that of liver cells, but comparable to that of alveolar type 2 cells in the lung. Efforts to isolate the virus from the liver have not succeeded. In patients surveyed so far, liver biochemistry findings are common, and transaminases are elevated in 14–53% of cases.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr28-2050640620920157" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
 </sup> In more severe cases, research evidenced a possible correlation between disease severity and higher frequency of elevated transaminases.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr16-2050640620920157" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
 </sup> Though elevated liver transaminases suggest that hepatic dysfunction is common, serum Gamma-glutamyl transferase (GGT) is elevated in 54%, while elevated alkaline phosphatase levels is rare.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr28-2050640620920157" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
 </sup> In a large cohort of Chinese patients, bilirubin was elevated in 10% of cases. However, fatality as a result of liver failure has not been reported so far. Liver injury in severe COVID-19 patients was significantly higher than that in mild patients.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr16-2050640620920157" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
 </sup> At this point, a better picture of the impact of COVID-19 infection in patients, with a pre-existing liver disease or on immunosuppression starts to emerge. So far, the data suggest that patients with a pre-existing liver disease (such as chronic hepatitis B infection or liver cirrhosis) do not have an additional risk. Current research could not evidence that COVID-19 causes a more severe disease in immunosuppressed patients, such as liver-transplant patients or patients treated with immunosuppressants (like those with auto-immune hepatitis). The Bergamo experience (in which approximately 700 children received a liver transplant, three in the last two months) showed that, among about 200 transplant recipients, none has developed clinical pulmonary disease, despite three testing positive for SARS-CoV-2.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr29-2050640620920157" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
 </sup> Considering their immunocompromised status, more intensive surveillance or individually tailored therapeutic approaches is needed for severe patients with COVID-19, with pre-existing conditions such as advanced liver disease. This is particularly important for the elderly with other comorbidities.
</p>
