<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The association between bruxism and psychological aspects has been documented,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> - 
  <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>
 </sup> although the intensity of sleep bruxism has not been associated to self-reported stress, depression, TMD or TMD-related pain.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> - 
  <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
 </sup> A recent systematic review, however, reported that some specific symptoms of the anxiety disorders spectrum might have association to probable sleep bruxism.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>
 </sup> Awake bruxism, in contrast, has psychosocial factors such as anxiety, stress and difficulty in identifying and describing feelings as important as somatic causes in its occurrence and maintenance.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
 </sup> Patients with high levels of stress are almost 6 times more likely to report awake bruxism.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>
 </sup> Sustained muscle contraction of head and neck is also related to a required body posture associated to fight-or-flight response. Therefore, muscle contraction in awake bruxism could be part of the defense behavior associated with anxiety and stress.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
 </sup> The anxiety-related processes occur in the CNS and involves interactions among prefrontal cortex, limbic, paralimbic structures (amygdala, insula, anterior cingulate gyrus) and motor regions of the brain stem that leads to motor and physiological responses not only to stress, but also increased alertness and attention.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
 </sup> Under non-stress conditions, the prefrontal cortex (PFC) regions regulate behavior, thought and emotion, including inhibition of inappropriate motor responses. However, in stressful conditions, the amygdala activates pathways in the hypothalamus and brainstem and impairs PFC regulation.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
