<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0020">Various research groups have analyzed the epidemiological and clinical characteristics of gastrointestinal disorders in patients with COVID-19. The percentage of patients with gastrointestinal disorders (as evidenced by vomiting, nausea, and/or diarrhea) varies depending on the study. In China, Jin and colleagues enrolled 651 patients on admission, i.e., before treatment with antiviral or antibiotic drugs, which might have biased the analysis (
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Jin et al., 2020</xref>). Interestingly, 11.4% of COVID-19 patients had at least one gastrointestinal tract symptom, the most common being diarrhea (in 5% to 8% of patients). In the study by Jin and colleagues, the intestinal disorders lasted a median of 4 days and appeared to precede the respiratory symptoms. Gastrointestinal symptoms were more frequent in severe/critical cases of COVID-19 (23%) than in mild COVID-19 (8%) (
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Jin et al., 2020</xref>). In other studies performed in China and Hong Kong, the proportion of COVID-19 patients (n total = 254, 59, 204, 58, 138, and 1,099, respectively) who developed gastrointestinal disorders was 26%, 25.4%, 18.6%, 11%, 13.7%, and 8.7%, respectively (
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2020b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Cheung et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Pan et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2020c</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Guan et al., 2020</xref>). Other studies (of 40 COVID-19 patients in Europe and 278 and 318 COVID-19 patients in the United States) reported that 55%, 35%, and 61% of the patients, respectively, displayed gastrointestinal signs and symptoms (
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Effenberger et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Nobel et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Redd et al., 2020</xref>). Importantly, meta-analyses of studies totaling 4,243, 6,686, and 10,890 patients found that the pooled prevalence of gastrointestinal symptoms was 17.6%, 15%, and 10%, respectively (
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Cheung et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Mao et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Sultan et al., 2020</xref>). SARS-CoV-2 infection triggers an inflammatory response in the gut, as evidenced by elevated fecal levels of calprotectin (a marker protein expressed mainly by neutrophils) (
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Effenberger et al., 2020</xref>). Lin and colleagues also observed that although the presence of SARS-CoV-2 in the stool does not correlate with gastrointestinal symptoms, the presence of SARS-CoV-2 in intestinal tissue is generally associated with severe gastrointestinal symptoms (
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2020</xref>). The use of human small intestinal organoids will be instrumental in better analyzing the modalities of enterocyte infection and its impact on the inflammatory response. Furthermore, it will be interesting in the future to determine the consequences of pre-existing digestive diseases (i.e., inflammatory bowel disease) on gastrointestinal disorders caused by SARS-CoV-2 and on the severity of COVID-19.
</p>
