<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The results presented here further reveal that subtype C most likely emerged in the mining city of Mbuji-Mayi, and spread significantly faster than subtype A1 and D throughout Central and East Africa. The spatial origins in Mbuji-Mayi are consistent with recent reports suggesting complex mosaic forms related to subtype C in this city [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007976.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. These results further suggest that the earliest dispersal events of subtype C (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1007976.s019">S7 Fig</xref>) occurred in a mining region [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007976.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] that includes Mbuji-Mayi (e.g. diamond mining; Kasai region) and Lubumbashi (e.g. Copperbelt; Katanga). The latter is the largest city in southern DRC, and due to its railway connections to other African neighbouring countries, this region may have acted as a stepping stone for the larger epidemics in southern Africa. Railway networks in Uganda, Rwanda, Burundi, and Tanzania were among the earliest in sub-Saharan Africa [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007976.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. In addition, truck drivers, who often travel long-distance and are known to be at a higher risk of HIV infection than the general population [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007976.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007976.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], and populations living in the vicinity of highways, have also been shown to be at higher risk of acquiring HIV [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007976.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Road traffic around 1960 was highest in the northern highway connecting Mombasa to Kampala by Lake Victoria, and lower along the southern highway connecting Dar es Salaam to Mwanza, in southern Lake Victoria [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007976.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. These connectivity patterns agree with the strongly supported virus lineage migration events we observe along the northern highway. Moreover, we estimated that the epidemic wavefront of subtype C travelled faster compared to other co-circulating lineages. These findings were robust to the type of model-based phylogeographic reconstruction. Our posterior estimates are directly comparable among subtypes because sequences were sampled across the same geographic range. However, we note that these estimates are dependent of the scale of sampling [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007976.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and it may be more problematic to compare these spatial invasion rates to HIV-1 datasets collated from different geographic regions and sampling regimes.
</p>
