<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par67">
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par68">After global eradication of rinderpest, we may succeed in eradicating PPR, a serious disease of small ruminants, caused by a morbillivirus similar to rinderpest virus by 2030 following the OIE pathway and timeline. Similarly, with concerted efforts, adequate vaccine production and funding support, it should be possible to eradicate FMD from India by 2040 adopting the OIE Progressive Control Pathway (PCOP) with significant economic and trade dividends. Presently, India is in the Stage 3 of FAO’s COP for the control of FMD (Anonymous 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2017–18</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par69">Strengthening of the disease diagnostic laboratories at the national, regional and state level with state-of-the-art facilities having desired biosafety and containment facilities of BSL-2/BSL-3 status depending on the type of bioagent being handled is warranted on priority. Other viral diseases, namely, CSF, sheep pox, goat pox, fowl pox and rabies, may also be included in national eradication programmes as potent vaccines are available against these.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par70">As India has long porous land borders with the neighbouring countries all around, there is always threat of transboundary diseases. Ideally disease control/eradication programmes should be taken in network mode involving all the neighbouring SAARC/ASEAN countries. A venture fund should be created by the participating countries for routine programmes to meet emergency situations in the face of disease outbreaks.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par71">Farmers need to be updated on useful livestock technologies, best practices and innovations in animal health, nutrition and management. This will require strengthening of extension services for livestock, poultry and fishery in PPP mode using modern ICT tools.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par72">A comprehensive livestock health policy should be developed at the national and state level.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par73">Capacity building for developing cold chain; testing the quality of vaccines, medicines, mineral mixture and residues in livestock feed; and production of disease-free semen, chicks, and fingerlings.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par74">The success story of rinderpest eradication and FMD-CP needs to be replicated for PPR, classical swine fever, HS, brucellosis and other dreadful diseases of livestock and poultry.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par75">A state-level 
    <bold>zoonoses coordination committee</bold> with subcommittees at the district level should be constituted under the umbrella of the Department of Animal Husbandry GoI to bring about close association among veterinarians, medical professionals, wildlife experts and other related departments focusing on the ‘One World, One Health’ concept for efficient handling of the newly emerging and re-emerging deadly viral and other infectious diseases having zoonotic significance.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
