<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pbio.3000673.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.3000673.g003</object-id>
 <label>Fig 3</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Timescaled phylogenetic tree of BTV-8 samples collected during the European outbreaks between 2006 and 2018.</title>
  <p>Maximum clade credibility time-calibrated phylogenetic tree generated in BEAST. The tree is scaled in years, with the final sampling date being October 2018. Clades with posterior support of 0.9 or higher are indicated by a white circle. Samples from the first and second outbreaks are shown as purple and orange circles, respectively. The branches are coloured accordingly to their median evolutionary rate across the posterior (see heatmap within the figure). The long branch leading from the first outbreak to the second (in dark purple) shows the slowest evolutionary rate on the maximum clade credibility tree. The inset shows the posterior distribution of the normalised rank of the evolutionary rate of the long branch relative the other branches in the tree, as estimated from the lognormal relaxed clock. Relative to the rest of the tree, values close to 0 represent slow evolution, values close to 1 represent fast evolution, and 0.5 represents the median branch–specific evolutionary rate on the tree. This analysis reveals an unusually slow evolution of BTV-8 between outbreaks. See the Methods section for the specifics of this calculation. Note that an identical tree with labels corresponding to the individual samples is shown as 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.3000673.s005">S2 Fig</xref>. The tree is available in 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.3000673.s003">S3 Data</xref> as MCC.tree; other presented data can be extracted using code in 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.3000673.s001">S1 Data</xref> from the trees in 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.3000673.s003">S3 Data</xref> as AllGMRF_reduced.trees. BTV-8, bluetongue virus serotype 8.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pbio.3000673.g003" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
