<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As reviewed above, laboratory vector competence experiments using artificial bloodmeals often lead to the conclusion that very high titers are needed to infect mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="B140-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>]. However, a substantial body of evidence across multiple arboviral families/orders (
 <italic>Flaviviridae, Togaviridae</italic>, and Bunyavirales) indicates that artificial bloodmeals are less infectious compared to bloodmeals taken from a viremic animal at equivalent titers [
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B138-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>,
 <xref rid="B140-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>,
 <xref rid="B141-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">141</xref>,
 <xref rid="B142-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>,
 <xref rid="B143-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>,
 <xref rid="B144-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>]. Artificial bloodmeal methods vary widely among laboratories, but the vast majority are conducted utilizing either hanging blood drops, pledgets (cotton soaked in blood/virus mixtures), or membrane feeding systems [
 <xref rid="B144-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>], although the former two have seen less use in recent years. Membrane systems consist of heated (generally 37 °C) reservoirs filled with a blood and virus mixture [
 <xref rid="B145-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>]. Additional sources of variation include the membranes overlaying the reservoirs, which include animal skin, sausage casing, or laboratory films based on collagen or that are completely artificial [
 <xref rid="B145-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>,
 <xref rid="B146-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>], as well as the kind of blood utilized (animal versus human, whole blood versus washed erythrocytes, defibrinated or anticoagulated) [
 <xref rid="B146-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>,
 <xref rid="B147-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>,
 <xref rid="B148-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>]. The effect on vector competence of the type of membrane overlaying blood reservoirs does not appear to be an active area of research, other than the effect on feeding efficiency [
 <xref rid="B146-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>]. Surprisingly, there has also been scant attention to the effects of anticoagulants on vector competence results, and the few studies that have been conducted used different virus/mosquito combinations. Knox et al. noted that DENV-4 lost significant titers over the course of an hour in an artificial membrane feeder when using lithium heparin-treated rabbit blood, necessitating the use of sodium citrate [
 <xref rid="B149-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>]. Surprisingly, such a finding was not corroborated within the same study in the context of DENV-2, illustrating that anticoagulant effects may be highly species-specific and possibly even virus strain-specific. Mahmood et al. found no significant differences in the feeding efficiency or infection rates of 
 <italic>Cx. tarsalis</italic> with WEEV in either heparinized or defibrinated rabbit or chicken blood [
 <xref rid="B146-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>]. These limited findings indicate the potential benefit to the vector competence field of further anticoagulant studies to determine the effects on feeding efficiency and arbovirus infectivity. Another source of variance in vector competence assessments is the source of blood used. Among the more widely used blood sources are sheep, human, bovine, chicken, and rabbit [
 <xref rid="B150-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>,
 <xref rid="B151-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">151</xref>]. Although humans, chickens, and sheep are ecologically relevant with respect to some mosquito-borne arboviruses (e.g., DENV/ZIKV/CHIV, WNV/WEEV, RVFV), many studies utilize blood derived from vertebrates that are irrelevant to the mosquito species or arbovirus in question. As with many variables discussed here, the exact role played by blood source on the outcome experimental infections is largely unknown. When examined in the context of the presence/absence of anticoagulants, and the various bloodmeal compositions (e.g., washed erythrocytes versus whole blood), the potential variation from lab to lab becomes potentially enormous, illustrating the need for further research on an improved standardization of methods for vector competence research. 
</p>
