<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Always keep in mind that the main goal during this pandemic is to protect yourself and your patient, preserve all health services to stop its spread, and prevent the health system from being compromised. It is safer to divide patients who attend eye clinics or have ophthalmology complaints into three groups: low risk, medium risk, and high risk (Table 
 <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Ophthalmology clinics that see patients should be equipped with screening stations before entry to the waiting area and must take a detailed history about any respiratory illnesses, fever, recent return from high-risk areas, or contact with family members recently back from one of the countries battling a COVID-19 outbreak [
 <xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. This way, every patient can be classified as low, medium, or high risk. This should be coupled with nurse-directed triage protocols to determine if an appointment is necessary or if the patient can reschedule and be sent home to ensure safe triage and isolation of patients presenting with COVID-19 symptoms or other respiratory infections. Those at low risk can be attended to with standard precautions. Medium-risk patients with non-urgent ophthalmic problems should be asked to return home and reschedule their appointment [
 <xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. High-risk patients with a non-urgent ophthalmic problem should be sent to the emergency room (ER) immediately and local health authorities notified. Medium-risk patients with urgent ophthalmic problems should be put in the examination lane immediately in order to decrease the time spent at the clinic. The patient, the ophthalmologist, and all health care personnel should wear surgical masks, gowns, gloves, and eye protection. In case of any planned procedure that results in an aerosolized virus, an N95 mask should be worn. High-risk or COVID-19 positive patients with urgent ophthalmic problems can be seen but after following local hospital guidelines and precautions for treating patients with COVID-19 or that of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) such as using an N95 mask, eye protection, and gowns (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="FIG1">1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Standard precautions for every patient should be followed, including using a breath shield during a slit-lamp exam or any clear plastic barrier to block the transfer of breaths between the patient and the doctor (2). Ophthalmologists should tell their patients that they will speak as little as possible during the slit-lamp examination and request that the patients also refrain from talking. They should always use protection for the mouth, nose, and eyes when caring for patients potentially infected with COVID-19. They should also keep the waiting room as empty as possible and advise seated patients to remain at least two meters (around 6 feet) from one another [
 <xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. As much as is prudent, they should reduce the visits of the most vulnerable patients. Patients with or suspected to have COVID-19 should be cared for in a single-person room with the door closed. Limited points of entry to the facility is strongly recommended too.
</p>
