<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Before opening a routine clinic, checklist criteria that aim at safe opening should be available. Complying with local governmental guidance, these guidelines should be closely reviewed and followed. Making a plan and pre-opening planning will be critically important to the success of your practice reopening, including an assessment of your personal protective equipment (PPE) needs and alternatives such as cloth masks, eye protection, and others [
 <xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Evaluate the clinics to determine what kinds of surfaces and materials make up that area, as most surfaces just need normal, routine cleaning; however, frequently touched surfaces like doorknobs will need to be cleaned with soap and water and then disinfected using United States Environmental Protection Agency (EPA)-approved disinfectant. If a disinfectant is unavailable, you can use one-third cup of bleach added to 1 gallon of water or 70% alcohol solutions to disinfect. Make sure all slit-lamps are equipped with a breath shield (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="FIG2">2</xref>). It is better that staff who do not need to be physically present in the office stay at home and work remotely. Even more, consider bringing employees back in stages, at different parts of the day, or working on alternative days. Start with a few outpatients visits a day and work on a modified schedule to avoid high volume or density. Unless necessary, ask patients to attend alone, keep the waiting room as empty as possible, and advise seated patients to remain at least two meters (around 6 feet) from one another, consider another option to wait in the clinic by asking patients to wait in their car or outside and text or calling when the appointment is ready. Remove magazines, brochures, remote controls, and other shared items from waiting and exam rooms. Follow U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) guidance, which requires all individuals who visit the office to wear a cloth face covering. This should be explained to patients and other visitors before they arrive at the clinic. Prioritize seniors above 60 years, those with chronic diseases like diabetes mellitus, and patients on chemotherapy to be seen and leave the clinic early. The availability of screening stations before entry to the waiting area should also continue to pick up any suspected cases and then deal with them as high-risk patients.
</p>
