<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Due to the shortage of kits and false negative rate of RT-PCR, the Hubei Province, China temporarily used CT scans as a clinical diagnosis for COVID-19.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47">47</xref>
 </sup> Chest CT scans are non-invasive and involve taking many X-ray measurements at different angles across a patient’s chest to produce cross-sectional images.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48">48</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref49">49</xref>
 </sup> The images are analyzed by radiologists to look for abnormal features that can lead to a diagnosis.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48">48</xref>
 </sup> The imaging features of COVID-19 are diverse and depend on the stage of infection after the onset of symptoms. For example, Bernheim 
 <italic>et al</italic>. saw more frequent normal CT findings (56%) in the early stages of the disease (0–2 days)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref50">50</xref>
 </sup> with a maximum lung involvement peaking at around 10 days after the onset of symptoms.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref51">51</xref>
 </sup> The most common hallmark features of COVID-19 include bilateral and peripheral ground-glass opacities (areas of hazy opacity)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref52">52</xref>
 </sup> and consolidations of the lungs (fluid or solid material in compressible lung tissue).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref50">50</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref51">51</xref>
 </sup> De Wever 
 <italic>et al</italic>. found that ground-glass opacities are most prominent 0–4 days after symptom onset. As a COVID-19 infection progresses, in addition to ground-glass opacities, crazy-paving patterns (
 <italic>i</italic>.
 <italic>e</italic>., irregular-shaped paved stone pattern) develop,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref51">51</xref>
 </sup> followed by increasing consolidation of the lungs.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref50">50</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref51">51</xref>
 </sup> Based on these imaging features, several retrospective studies have shown that CT scans have a higher sensitivity (86–98%) and improved false negative rates compared to RT-PCR.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref53">53</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref54">54</xref>
 </sup> The main caveat of using CT for COVID-19 is that the specificity is low (25%) because the imaging features overlap with other viral pneumonia.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
