<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0455">Advanced countries, such as in Europe, have more and more smog because of an unexpected temperature inversion, which traps polluting emissions from the city near ground-level mainly in winter season. The ambient pollution mixes with moisture in the air to form a thick fog that affects the health of people in the city (
 <xref rid="bb0725" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">Bell et al., 2004</xref>). The exposure to pollutants, such as airborne particulate matter and ozone, generates respiratory and cardiovascular diseases with increases in mortality and hospital admissions (cf., 
 <xref rid="bb0470" ref-type="bibr">Langrish and Mills, 2014</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bb0745" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al. (2020)</xref> analyze the effect of heavy aerosol pollution in northern China-(characterized by high PM
 <sub>2.5</sub> concentrations in a wide geographical area)- that impacts on environmental ecology, climate change and public health (cf., 
 <xref rid="bb0510" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2017</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0515" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0415" ref-type="bibr">Jin et al., 2017</xref>). The biological components of air pollutants and bio aerosols also include bacteria, viruses, pollens, fungi, and animal/plant fragments (
 <xref rid="bb0240" ref-type="bibr">Després et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0315" ref-type="bibr">Fröohlich-Nowoisky et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0680" ref-type="bibr">Smets et al., 2016</xref>). Studies show that during heavy aerosol pollution in Beijing (China), 50%–70% of bacterial aerosols are in sub micrometer particles, 0.56–1 mm (
 <xref rid="bb0835" ref-type="bibr">T. Zhang et al., 2019</xref>; cf., 
 <xref rid="bb0830" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2016</xref>). As bacteria size typically ranges from 0.5 to 2.0 mm (
 <xref rid="bb0240" ref-type="bibr">Després et al., 2012</xref>), they can form clumps or attach to particles and transport regionally between terrestrial, aquatic, atmospheric and artificial ecosystems (
 <xref rid="bb0680" ref-type="bibr">Smets et al., 2016</xref>). Moreover, because of regional bio aerosol transportation, harmful microbial components and bacterial aerosols have dangerous implications on human health and also plantation (cf., 
 <xref rid="bb0710" ref-type="bibr">Van Leuken et al., 2016</xref>). Harmful bio aerosol components (including pathogens, antibiotic-resistant bacteria and endotoxins) can cause severe respiratory and cardiovascular diseases in society (
 <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">Charmi et al., 2018</xref>). In fact, the concentration of microbes, pathogens and toxic components significantly increases during polluted days, compared to no polluted days (
 <xref rid="bb0515" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2018</xref>). In addition, airborne bacterial community structure changes with pollutant concentration, which may be related to bacterial sources and multiplication in the air (
 <xref rid="bb0835" ref-type="bibr">T. Zhang et al., 2019</xref>). Studies also indicate that microbial community composition and bioactivity are significantly affected by particle concentration (
 <xref rid="bb0515" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2018</xref>). To put it differently, the atmospheric particulate matter harbors more microbes during polluted days than sunny or clean days (
 <xref rid="bb0740" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al., 2016</xref>). These studies can explain one of the driving factors of higher diffusion of COVID-19 in the industrialized regions of Nord Italy, rather than in other part of Italy (
 <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="t0025" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="t0030" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). In fact, viable bio aerosol particles and high microbial concentration in particulate matter play their non-negligible role during air pollution and transmission dynamics of viral infectivity (
 <xref rid="bb0835" ref-type="bibr">T. Zhang et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb2015" ref-type="bibr">Morawska and Cao, 2020</xref>). For instance, studies on airborne bacteria in PM
 <sub>2.5</sub> from the Beijing-Tianjin-Hebei regions in China reveal that air pollutants are main factors in shaping bacterial community structure (
 <xref rid="bb0325" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2017</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bb0805" ref-type="bibr">Xie et al. (2018)</xref> indicate that total bacteria concentration is higher in moderately polluted air rather than in clean or heavily polluted air. 
 <xref rid="bb0515" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al. (2018)</xref> argue that bacterial concentration is low in heavily pollution of PM
 <sub>2.5</sub> and PM
 <sub>10</sub>, whereas the pathogenic bacteria concentration is very high in heavy and moderate pollution. 
 <xref rid="bb0685" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al. (2018)</xref> study bacterial community during low and high particulate matter (PM) pollution and find out that predominant species vary with PM concentration. In general, bio aerosol concentrations are influenced by complex factors, such as emission sources, terrain, meteorological conditions and other climate factors (
 <xref rid="bb0825" ref-type="bibr">Zhai et al., 2018</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bb0745" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al. (2020)</xref> investigate the differences between inland and coastal cities in China (Jinan and Weihai, respectively) to explain the influence of topography, meteorological conditions and geophysical factors on bio aerosol. Results suggest that from clean days to high polluted days, bacterial community structure is influenced by bacterial adaptation to pollutants, chemical composition of pollutants and meteorological conditions (cf., 
 <xref rid="bb0685" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2018</xref>). Moreover, certain bacteria from Proteobacteria and Deinococcus-Thermus have high tolerance towards environmental stresses and can adapt to extreme environments. As a matter of fact, bacilli can survive to harsh environments by forming spores. Moreover, certain bacteria with protective mechanisms can survive in highly polluted environments, while other bacteria cannot withstand such extreme conditions. In particular, bacteria survive in the atmosphere adapting to ultraviolet exposure, reduced nutrient availability, desiccation, extreme temperatures and other factors. In short, in the presence of accumulated airborne pollutants, more microorganisms might be attached to particulate matter. Thus, in heavy or severe air pollution, highly toxic pollutants in PM
 <sub>2.5</sub> and PM
 <sub>10</sub> may inhibit microbial growth. Numerous studies also indicate that the combination between meteorological conditions and air pollution creates an appropriate environment for microbial community structure and abundance, and diffusion of viral infectivity (cf., 
 <xref rid="bb0425" ref-type="bibr">Jones and Harrison, 2004</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bb0850" ref-type="bibr">Zhong et al. (2018)</xref> argue that static meteorological conditions may explain the increase of PM
 <sub>2.5</sub>. In general, bacterial communities during aerosol pollution are influenced by bacterial adaptive mechanisms, particle composition, and meteorological conditions. The particles could also act as carriers, which have complex adsorption and toxicity effects on bacteria (
 <xref rid="bb0745" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al., 2020</xref>). Certain particle components are also available as nutrition for bacteria and the toxic effect dominates in heavy pollution. The bacterial adaptability towards airborne pollutants can cause bacterial survival or death for different species. 
 <xref rid="bb0360" ref-type="bibr">Groulx et al. (2018)</xref> argue that microorganisms, such as bacteria and fungi in addition to other biological matter like endotoxins and spores, commingle with particulate matter air pollutants. Hence, microorganisms may be influenced by interactions with ambient particles leading to the inhibition or enhancement of viability (e.g., tolerance to variation in seasonality, temperature, humidity, etc.). Moreover, 
 <xref rid="bb0360" ref-type="bibr">Groulx et al. (2018)</xref> claim that in the case of microbial agents of communicable disease, such as viruses, the potential interactions with pollution may have public health implications. 
 <xref rid="bb0360" ref-type="bibr">Groulx et al. (2018, p. 1106)</xref> describe an experimental platform to investigate the implications of viral infectivity changes:
 <disp-quote>
  <p>Preliminary evidence suggests that the interactions between airborne viruses and airborne fine particulate matter influence viral stability and infectivity ….. The development of a platform to study interactions between artificial bio aerosols and concentrated ambient particles provides an opportunity to investigate the direction, magnitude and mechanistic basis of these effects, and to study their health implications.… The interactions of PM
   <sub>2.5</sub> with Φ6 bacteriophages decreased viral infectivity compared to treatment with HEPA
   <xref rid="fn0015" ref-type="fn">2</xref>-filtered air alone; By contrast, ΦX174, a non-enveloped virus, displayed increased infectivity when treated with PM
   <sub>2.5</sub> particles relative to controls treated only with HEPA-filtered air.
  </p>
 </disp-quote>
</p>
