<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0465">Other studies have reported associations between air pollution and reduced lung function, increased hospital admissions, increased respiratory symptoms and high asthma medication use (
 <xref rid="bb0675" ref-type="bibr">Simoni et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0400" ref-type="bibr">Jalaludin et al., 2004</xref>). In this context, the interaction between climate factors, air pollution and increased morbidity and mortality of people and children from respiratory diseases is a main health issue in society (
 <xref rid="bb0210" ref-type="bibr">Darrow et al., 2014</xref>). Asthma is a disease associated with exposure to traffic-related air pollution and tobacco smoking (
 <xref rid="bb0495" ref-type="bibr">Liao et al., 2011</xref>). Many studies show that exposure to traffic-related outdoor air pollutants (e.g., PM
 <sub>10</sub> with an aerodynamic diameter ≤ 10 μm, nitrogen dioxide NO
 <sub>2</sub>, carbon monoxide CO, sulfur dioxide SO
 <sub>2</sub>, and ozone O
 <sub>3</sub>) increases the risk of asthma or asthma-like symptoms (
 <xref rid="bb0665" ref-type="bibr">Shankardass et al., 2009</xref>). Especially, high levels of PM
 <sub>10</sub> increases cough, lower respiratory disorders and lower peak expiratory flow (
 <xref rid="bb0735" ref-type="bibr">Ward and Ayres, 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0570" ref-type="bibr">Nel, 2005</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bb0750" ref-type="bibr">Weinmayr et al. (2010)</xref> provide strong evidence that PM
 <sub>10</sub> may be an aggravating factor of asthma in children. Furthermore, asthma symptoms are exacerbated by air pollutants, such as diesel exhaust, PM
 <sub>10</sub>, NO
 <sub>2</sub>, SO
 <sub>2</sub>, O
 <sub>3</sub> and respiratory virus, such as adenovirus, influenza, parainfluenza and respiratory syncytial virus (
 <xref rid="bb0410" ref-type="bibr">Jaspers et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0550" ref-type="bibr">Murdoch and Jennings, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0555" ref-type="bibr">Murphy et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0790" ref-type="bibr">Wong et al., 2009</xref>). The study by 
 <xref rid="bb0495" ref-type="bibr">Liao et al. (2011)</xref> confirms that exacerbations of asthma have been associated with bacterial and viral respiratory tract infections and air pollution. Some studies focus on the effect of meteorology and air pollution on acute viral respiratory infections and viral bronchiolitis (a disease linked to seasonal changes in respiratory viruses) in the first years of life (
 <xref rid="bb0575" ref-type="bibr">Nenna et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0660" ref-type="bibr">Ségala et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0715" ref-type="bibr">Vandini et al., 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0720" ref-type="bibr">Vandini et al., 2015</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">Carugno et al. (2018)</xref> analyze respiratory syncytial virus (RSV), the primary cause of acute lower respiratory infections in children: bronchiolitis. Results suggest that seasonal weather conditions and concentration of air pollutants seem to influence RSV-related bronchiolitis epidemics in Italian urban areas. In fact, airborne particulate matter may influence the children's immune system and foster the spread of RSV infection. This study also shows a correlation between short- and medium-term PM
 <sub>10</sub> exposures and increased risk of hospitalization because of RSV bronchiolitis among infants. In short, manifold environmental factors-(such as air pollution levels, circulation of respiratory viruses and colder temperatures)-induce longer periods of time spent indoors with higher opportunities for diffusion of infections between people. In fact, high diffusion of COVID-19 in North Italy is in winter period (February–March 2020). Studies also show that air pollution is higher during winter months and it has been associated with increased hospitalizations for respiratory diseases and other disorders (
 <xref rid="bb0455" ref-type="bibr">Ko et al., 2007a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0535" ref-type="bibr">Medina-Ramón et al., 2006</xref>). Moreover, oscillations in temperature and humidity may lead to changes in the respiratory epithelium, which increase susceptibility to infections (
 <xref rid="bb0235" ref-type="bibr">Deal et al., 1980</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bb0550" ref-type="bibr">Murdoch and Jennings (2009)</xref> correlate the incidence rate of invasive pneumococcal disease (IPD) with fluctuations in respiratory virus activity and environmental factors in New Zealand, showing how incidence rates of IPD are associated with the increased activity of some respiratory viruses and air pollution. Another side effect of air pollution exposure is the high incidence of mumps. In fact, 
 <xref rid="bb0370" ref-type="bibr">Hao et al. (2019)</xref> show that exposure to NO
 <sub>2</sub> and SO
 <sub>2</sub> is significantly associated with higher risk of developing mumps. Instead, 
 <xref rid="bb0815" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al. (2020)</xref> show that the exposure of people to SO
 <sub>2</sub>, NO
 <sub>2</sub>, O
 <sub>3</sub>, PM
 <sub>10</sub> and PM
 <sub>2.5</sub> is associated with hand, foot, and mouth diseases. Moreover, the effect of air pollution in the cold season is higher than in the warm season. 
 <xref rid="bb0670" ref-type="bibr">Shepherd and Mullins (2019)</xref> analyze the relationship between arthritis diagnosis in those over 50 and exposure to extreme air pollution in utero or infancy. In particular, this study links early-life air pollution exposure to later-life arthritis diagnoses, and suggests a particularly strong link for Rheumatoid arthritis.
 <xref rid="fn0020" ref-type="fn">3</xref>
 <xref rid="bb0670" ref-type="bibr">Shepherd and Mullins (2019)</xref> also argue that exposure to smog and air pollution in the first year of life is associated with a higher incidence of arthritis later in life. Overall, then, these studies suggest complex relationships between people, meteorological conditions, air pollution and viral infectivity over time and space.
</p>
