<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?OLF?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int. J. Infect. Dis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Infectious Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1201-9712</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1878-3511</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of International Society for Infectious Diseases.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7313512</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S1201-9712(20)30507-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2020.06.072</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>COVID-19 and routine childhood immunization in Africa: leveraging systems thinking and implementation science to improve immunization system performance</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0005"><name><surname>Adamu</surname><given-names>Abdu A</given-names></name><email>abdu.adamu@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor0005" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0010"><name><surname>Jalo</surname><given-names>Rabiu I</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0015"><name><surname>Habonimana</surname><given-names>Desire</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0020" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0020"><name><surname>Wiysonge</surname><given-names>Charles S</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff0025" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0005"><label>a</label>Cochrane South Africa, South African Medical Research Council, Francie van Zijl Drive, Parrowvallei, Tygerberg, 7505, Cape Town, South Africa</aff><aff id="aff0010"><label>b</label>Division of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, Department of Global Health, Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences, Stellenbosch University, Francie van Zijl Drive, Parrowvallei, Tygerberg, 7505, Cape Town, South Africa</aff><aff id="aff0015"><label>c</label>Department of Community Medicine, Bayero University/Aminu Kano Teaching Hospital, Zaria Road, Kano State, Nigeria</aff><aff id="aff0020"><label>d</label>Research and Innovation Unit, Department of Community Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, University of Burundi, Bujumbura, Burundi</aff><aff id="aff0025"><label>e</label>School of Public Health and Family Medicine, University of Cape Town, Observatory, 7925, Cape Town, South Africa</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor0005"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author at: Division of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, Department of Global Health, Stellenbosch University, South Africa. <email>abdu.adamu@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>24</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>18</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0005"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="lis0005"><list-item id="lsti0005"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0005">One of the routine health services that is at high risk of being disrupted by coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) in Africa is childhood immunization.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0010">Experiences from previous outbreaks on the continent indicates that any disruption of immunization services can result in epidemics of childhood vaccine-preventable diseases which will invariably increase child mortality.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0015">Contextualized strategies are needed to mitigate the impact of COVID-19 on access and utilization of immunization services.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0020">Using systems thinking can advance the understanding of the interaction between COVID-19 and immunization by explicitly elucidating the non-linear and dynamic relationships that exist between all elements of the system.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0025"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0025">Implementation science models can be used to fast-track the use of evidence-based innovations to re-design local systems such that it enhances access and utilization of immunization services despite COVID-19 outbreak.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><abstract id="abs0010"><p>One of the routine health services that is being disrupted by coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) in Africa is childhood immunization. This is because the immunization system relies on functioning health facilities and stable communities to be effective. Its disruption increases the risk of epidemics of vaccine-preventable diseases which can increase child mortality. Therefore, policymakers must quickly identify robust and context-specific strategies to rapidly scale-up routine immunization in order to mitigate the impact of COVID-19 on their national immunization performance. To achieve this, we propose a paradigm shift towards systems thinking and use of implementation science in immunization decision making. Systems thinking can inform a more nuanced and holistic understanding of the interrelationship that between COVID-19, its control strategies and childhood immunization. Tools like causal loop diagrams can be used to explicitly illustrate the systems structure by identifying the feedback loops. Once mapped and leverage points for interventions have been identified, implementation science can be used to guide the rapid uptake and utilization of multifaceted evidence-based innovations in complex practice settings. As Africa re-strategize for the post-2020 era, these emerging fields can contribute significantly in accelerating progress towards universal access to vaccines for all children on the continent despite COVID-19.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>