<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>CVA21, a member of the Picornaviridae family, is a nonenveloped ssRNA enterovirus enclosed in an icosahedral capsid. Two major subgroups, A and B, have been characterized in murine models [
 <xref rid="B151-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">151</xref>]. Subgroup A contains 23 serotypes, with their main impact on skeletal muscles, while subgroup B contains six serotypes affecting a broad range of tissue types [
 <xref rid="B149-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>]. Their clinical significance in humans reflects their responsibility for mild upper respiratory tract infections spread by aerosol transmission [
 <xref rid="B152-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>]. The oncolytic CVA21 is commercially available as CAVATAK™ based on the wild-type Kuykendall strain [
 <xref rid="B153-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>]. Modelling of the attachment mechanisms and cell internalization has indicated that other group A serotypes may have similar oncolytic potential [
 <xref rid="B154-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">154</xref>]. The CVA21 infection is characterized by attachment to the intracellular adhesion molecule-1 (ICAM-1), the primary receptor for attachment, and to the decay-accelerating factor (DAF), the secondary receptor for attachment [
 <xref rid="B155-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>]. ICAM-1 is a viral receptor common for the Picornaviridae family. Although DAF is expressed on almost all cells, its primary role is regulation of complement responses [
 <xref rid="B155-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>]. Since the attachment of CVA21 to DAF is not sufficient for host cell infection, DAF is considered to act as a membrane receptor, which accumulates the virus at the cell surface and optimizes viral entry via ICAM-1 [
 <xref rid="B156-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>]. The discovery of CVA21 and its lysis of cancer cells was mainly achieved through research conducted on ICAM-1 and DAF receptors, and comparisons between various cancer cell lines and nonmalignant tissues. It has also been shown for melanoma as well as multiple myeloma, malignant glioma, breast, colon, endometrial and pancreatic cancer cell lines [
 <xref rid="B157-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>,
 <xref rid="B158-biomedicines-08-00060" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>]. 
</p>
