<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this paper, we reported on molecular dynamics simulations of the main protease (Mpro), whose crystal structures have been released. We compared the Mpro for SARS-CoV-2 with a highly similar SARS-CoV protein. In spite of a high level of sequence similarity between these two homologous proteins, their active sites showed major differences in both shape and size, indicating that repurposing SARS drugs for COVID-19 may be futile. Furthermore, a detailed analysis of the binding pocket’s conformational changes during simulation time indicated its flexibility and plasticity, which dashes hope for rapid and reliable drug design. Moreover, our findings show the presence of a flexible C44-P52 loop regulating the access to the binding site pocket. A successful inhibitor may need to have an ability to relocate the loop from the entrance to bind to the catalytic pocket. However, mutations leading to changes in the amino acid sequence of the C44-P52 loop, although not affecting the folding of the protein, may result in the putative inhibitors’ inability to access the binding pocket and provide a probable development of drug resistance. To avoid this situation in which the future evolution of the Mpros can undermine all our efforts, we should focus on key functional residues or those whose further mutation will destabilise the protein (e.g., P39, R40, P52, G143, G146, or L167). Alternatively, we would suggest targeting the region between II and III domains, which contributes to the dimer formation. Our results provide the basis for drug design efforts aimed at this important protein target as part of the multifaceted global effort to eradicate COVID-19. In view of the presented challenges to finding a potent drug targeting Mpro, in our opinion, the most successful strategy would be to screen a large database of compounds with diverse structures involving or designing inhibitors de novo using a fragment-based approach. Both of these strategies, unfortunately, take much longer than a currently preferred approach based on repurposing existing FDA-approved compounds and hence should be pursued as a long-term plan of preparedness for future outbreaks of COVID epidemics involving this and other strains of the virus.</p>
