<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although immunization with Dengvaxia has shown no advantageous results in naïve individuals, long-term follow-up studies have demonstrated that the vaccine is effective in DENV-immune recipients. One possible explanation for this seemingly contradictory result is the presence of higher titers of anti-E antibodies that have undergone affinity/avidity maturation in individuals from the latter group. This is further borne out by the fact that all non-structural viral proteins in Dengvaxia belong to YFV, and thus immunization of DENV-immune individuals with this vaccine is expected to produce very low levels of cell-mediated immune recall. The protective effect of Dengvaxia on DENV-positive vaccinees is, therefore, supposed to rely almost exclusively on the humoral immune response, though this hypothesis remains to be thoroughly verified. This raises the interesting question of whether an inactivated virus vaccine might protect DENV-immune individuals better than live-attenuated Dengvaxia—the answer is probably yes. Since inactivated viruses are adjuvanted and presented to the immune system in the same manner as subunit vaccines, memory B-cells will recognize their target epitopes in the surface of inactivated viruses and turn into plasmatic cells producing protective neutralizing antibodies. From this perspective, Dengvaxia should represent an inferior alternative to an inactivated virus or subunit vaccine, because its replication inside the cells does not stimulate the development of an anti-DENV cell-mediated immune response and thus, any other vaccine candidate expressing DENV-specific B and T-cell epitopes could in theory be engineered to present them to the immune system in a more efficient manner. All said, however, there is something Sanofi Pasteur has definitely taught us, and it is that a prime-boost strategy might represent a promising alternative for the development of anti-DENV vaccines, priming, for instance, with LATV and boosting with subunit vaccines. Boosting doses, of course, are required to maintain protective levels of neutralizing antibodies, and the time between doses would have to be worked out.</p>
