<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Indeed, these anthropogenic changes to habitat are also contributing to a second biological crisis: an increase in the rate of emerging and re-emerging infectious diseases (EIDs) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6-viruses-03-00379">6</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7-viruses-03-00379">7</xref>]. Of these EIDs, 75% are 
 <bold>zoonotic</bold> (see 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1-viruses-03-00379">Table 1</xref> for a definition) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8-viruses-03-00379">8</xref>] and 37% are RNA viruses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9-viruses-03-00379">9</xref>]. The high mutation rate of RNA viruses coupled with their ability to recombine and reassort allows for a rapid rate of evolution. In turn, this makes them highly adaptable and thus able to both exploit the new hosts and habitats afforded by a changing environment, as well as to develop resistance to treatments [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10-viruses-03-00379">10</xref>]. Examples of zoonotic RNA viruses which have emerged relatively recently include SARS coronavirus (SARS CoV), West Nile virus (WNV), Chikungunya virus, the 2009 influenza A (H1N1) and human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1) and 2 (HIV-2). Cumulatively, these ailments have claimed hundreds of millions of human lives and cost the global economy hundreds of billions of US dollars. Among all viruses, HIV-1 causes the greatest amount of human mortality [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11-viruses-03-00379">11</xref>] and its immunosuppressive nature is facilitating the resurgence of “old” pathogens (
 <italic>i.e.</italic>, tuberculosis) in human populations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12-viruses-03-00379">12</xref>]. It is possible that the emergence of HIV is also encouraging cross-species transmission and that these disease threats may have a severe, negative impact on wild animal populations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13-viruses-03-00379">13</xref>]. A multi-disciplinary approach will be necessary to combat the crises of extinction and disease emergence because human, ecosystem and animal health are inextricably linked. In recent years, great advances have been made in virology and disease ecology, particularly towards elucidating the mechanisms behind the emergence and evolution of zoonotic viruses. Thus, it is important to review and consider how advances in virology and disease ecology complement each other.
</p>
