<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza A viruses (IAVs) are members of the Orthomyxoviridae family of RNA viruses and are capable of infecting a wide array of species. IAV is classified into different subtypes dependent on two viral glycoproteins, hemagglutinin (HA) and neuraminidase (NA) [
 <xref rid="B1-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Avian species such as waterfowl are the natural host reservoir of IAVs where 16 HA subtypes and 9 NA subtypes have been observed to circulate; in addition, two subtypes H17N10 and H18N11 have been observed in bats [
 <xref rid="B2-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Currently only a few subtypes, H1N1 and H3N2, have maintained substantial transmission within the human population and are among the leading causes of respiratory infections annually. While seasonal epidemics caused by IAVs are a significant global health burden, IAVs also have the potential to cause pandemic outbreaks. Most strains of IAV are specifically adapted to one host species, but genomic reassortment between human and avian viruses has previously led to pandemic outbreaks. Pandemics occur when antigenically distinct viruses, to which the human population has no preexisting immunity, emerge and quickly spread. The natural avian reservoir of IAV is a major source of antigenically distinct viruses which can potentially cause pandemic outbreaks. Direct adaptation of avian IAVs to humans or the genomic assortment of human and avian IAV genes can lead to the introduction of these antigenically distinct viruses to the human population. Within the last century, four IAV pandemics have occurred: the H1N1 Spanish flu (1918), the H2N2 Asian flu (1957), the H3N2 Hong Kong flu (1968), and the H1N1 swine flu (2009). Genomic sequencing of the viruses behind these outbreaks has definitively linked avian IAVs to each pandemic. More recently, sporadic zoonotic infections in humans with highly pathogenic avian IAVs, such as H5N1 and H7N9, have been observed. While there is little evidence of human to human transmission, the adaptation of these antigenically novel viruses to humans is a mounting health concern as they may lead to the next pandemic outbreak. In order to cross the species barrier, these avian IAVs need to acquire adaptive mutations in certain viral genes [
 <xref rid="B4-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Some of these genes include the viral glycoproteins HA and NA which mediate viral entry and release, respectively [
 <xref rid="B4-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Additionally, activity of the viral RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (vRdRp) has been identified as a significant factor regulating the host adaptation of avian IAVs to mammals. 
</p>
