<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>K18-hACE2 transgenic mice express hACE2, with regulation by the human cytokeratin 18 (K18) promoter. Specifically, these mice contain 2.5 kb of the K18 genomic sequence, including the promoter, the first intron, and a translation-promoting sequence. Expression of hACE2 is mainly observed in the epithelium of the respiratory tract, which shows a higher incidence of SARS-CoV-2 infection, and in the epithelium of other organs, including the liver, kidneys, and gastrointestinal tract (
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>). K18-hACE2 mice infected with SARS-CoV-2 show weight loss and viral replication in the lungs, as in humans. Furthermore, they show the typical histopathological findings of interstitial pneumonia with lymphocytic and monocytic infiltration into the alveolar interstitium and an accumulation of macrophages in the alveolar cavities. Alveolar and bronchial epithelial cells show presence of viral antigens; this is not observed in wild-type (WT) mice with SARS-CoV-2 infection. Furthermore, these mice show other pathological changes, such as vasculitis, degeneration, and necrosis of extrapulmonary organs and presence of the viral antigen in the brain (
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>). Bao et al. (
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>) recently studied the pathogenicity of SARS-CoV-2 virus in hACE2-expressing ICR transgenic mice and WT mice. This model may be useful in research into drug treatments for COVID-19. Israelow et al. (
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>) developed an hACE2-adeno-associated virus 9 (AAV) murine model, which was subsequently intranasally infected with SARS-CoV-2. They studied the presence of coronavirus infection, the inflammatory response in the lungs, the presence of neutralizing antibodies, and the type I interferon signaling pathway. The authors reported that this model would be very useful for understanding questions related to infection, replication, and pathogenesis of SARS-CoV-2 and for testing therapeutic strategies.
</p>
