<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0065">In the present study, 166 countries with confirmed cases as of March 27, 2020 were included. Descriptive analyses were performed for all the data. A log-linear GAM was used to analyze the associations between meteorological factors (temperature and relative humidity) and daily new cases and daily new deaths of COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">Samet et al., 2000</xref>). First, the basic models were constructed, including meteorological factors (temperature and relative humidity). Second, the variables were controlled to adjust for regional variation, including wind speed, median age of the population, GHSI, and country. Third, the day-of-week and the penalized smoothing spline functions were incorporated to control the time trend and cycle. The core GAM equation was as follows:
 <disp-formula id="fo0015">
  <math id="M3" altimg="si3.svg">
   <mo mathvariant="italic">log</mo>
   <mfenced close=")" open="(">
    <msub>
     <mi>Y</mi>
     <mi>t</mi>
    </msub>
   </mfenced>
   <mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mo>
   <mi>α</mi>
   <mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mo>
   <mi>β</mi>
   <msub>
    <mi>X</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
   </msub>
   <mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mo>
   <mi mathvariant="italic">Wind</mi>
   <mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mo>
   <mi mathvariant="italic">Country</mi>
   <mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mo>
   <mi mathvariant="italic">Median</mi>
   <mo>.</mo>
   <mi mathvariant="italic">Age</mi>
   <mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mo>
   <mi mathvariant="italic">GHSI</mi>
   <mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mo>
   <mi mathvariant="italic">DOW</mi>
   <mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mo>
   <mi>s</mi>
   <mfenced close=")" open="(">
    <mrow>
     <mi mathvariant="italic">Time</mi>
     <mo>，</mo>
     <mi mathvariant="italic">df</mi>
    </mrow>
   </mfenced>
  </math>
 </disp-formula>where 
 <italic>t</italic> is the day of the observation. Considering that the number of daily new cases or daily new deaths in some countries is 0, 
 <italic>Y</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>t</italic>
 </sub> is the number of daily new cases or daily new deaths on day 
 <italic>t</italic> plus one. 
 <italic>α</italic> is the intercept; 
 <italic>β</italic> is the regression coefficient; 
 <italic>X</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>t</italic>
 </sub> is the weather variables on day 
 <italic>t</italic>; 
 <italic>Wind</italic> is the wind speed; 
 <italic>Country</italic> is a categorical variable for country; 
 <italic>Median.Age</italic> is the median age of each countries' population; 
 <italic>GHSI</italic> is the Global Health Security Index; 
 <italic>DOW</italic> is a categorical variable indicating the date of the week; 
 <italic>s()</italic> refers to the smoother, which is based on the penalized smoothing spline; 
 <italic>Time</italic> is the date of the observation; 
 <italic>df</italic> is the degree of freedom.
</p>
