<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Commensurate with its role in transmission in Africa, the western Pacific and South America, we have demonstrated that a Townsville, Australia, population of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> is susceptible to infection and can transmit ZIKV. Transmission rates were higher than those recently reported for Brazilian and Senegalese strains of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> that were exposed to Asian and African lineages of ZIKV, respectively, but lower than those for a Singapore strain infected with MR 766 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004959.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0004959.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. However, comparison of experimental vector competence outcomes between different laboratories should be viewed with caution due to differences in mosquito strain, virus strain, mosquito feeding method and virus assay used to analyze samples [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004959.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Regardless, we have confirmed that highly infected 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> could be a potential source of transmission of ZIKV in Australia. Although 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> was prevalent in eastern Australia during the first half of the 20
 <sup>th</sup> century, the distribution of this species is currently restricted to urban areas of northern Queensland [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004959.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Therefore, should the virus be introduced, this is the region that is most at risk of ZIKV transmission. However, if the distribution of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> expanded, or if 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic>, another potential vector [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004959.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], invaded the Australian mainland, then the ZIKV receptive zone would need to be redefined. This highlights the importance of surveillance for these container-inhabiting species to ensure that any expansion of these species is recognized and elimination programs initiated.
</p>
