<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the beginning of the West Africa Ebola epidemic, there existed no approved specific treatments or vaccines for the infection. Clinical interventions consisted of supportive care, including fluid and electrolyte management, analgesia, support of blood pressure, management of coagulopathy, treatment of secondary infections, and a case-by-case management of other complications [
 <xref rid="B11-vaccines-08-00038" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-vaccines-08-00038" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Medical treatments that had been proposed had not undergone clinical trials in Ebola virus-infected populations or at all [
 <xref rid="B6-vaccines-08-00038" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Experimental vaccines were in the very early stages of development, and just a few had entered Phase I safety and immunogenicity trials. As the epidemic progressed and the fatalities increased, numerous proposals for clinical trials were submitted to the WHO Research Ethics Review Committee (WHO-ERC), the committee that evaluated and approved proposed potential clinical investigations including new and amended protocols for experimental interventional (drug, vaccine) and observational studies [
 <xref rid="B44-vaccines-08-00038" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. From August 2014 to April 2016, WHO-ERC evaluated 24 new EVD-protocols and 22 amendments, all of which excluded pregnant and lactating women and infants under 1 year of age. The proposed clinical trials for two promising antiviral drugs—brincidofovir and favipiravir—also excluded women who were pregnant for a variety of reasons (potential embryotoxicity for brincidofover and lack of insurance coverage for favipiravir) [
 <xref rid="B13-vaccines-08-00038" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The WHO-ERC recognized that excluding pregnant women and their infants from drug and vaccine clinical trials undermined ethical principles of justice—fairness, equity and maximization of benefit, and that it would deny them the potential life-saving benefits from what was believed to be an almost universally fatal infection [
 <xref rid="B13-vaccines-08-00038" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Because of this, the WHO-ERC systematically requested amendments to these protocols in order to include pregnant women and children. Despite their efforts as well as those of the Médecins Sans Frontières (MSF) Ethics Review Board and Inserm Institutional Review Board to have the applicants reconsider their exclusion of pregnant women, the necessity for rapid implementation of field trials had priority over the delays that would have been encountered in pursuing revision of the protocols to include pregnant women. The West Africa Ebola epidemic included many “firsts” for an Ebola epidemic—it was also the first time that a vaccine was fielded for preventative use for this infection. The rVSV-ZEBOV vaccine had been developed by the Canadian National Microbiology Laboratory, licensed to NewLink Genetics, and subsequently sublicensed to Merck, which has been the manufacturer and partner in ongoing research, licensure, and compassionate use efforts [
 <xref rid="B39-vaccines-08-00038" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-vaccines-08-00038" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. rVSV-ZW+EBOV is a live-attenuated vector vaccine using recombinant vesicular stomatitis virus to encode the glycoprotein of the Ebola Zaire strain. During its clinical testing conducted during the epidemic, an open-label, cluster-randomized ring vaccination trial (Ebola ça suffit!) of rVSV-ZEBOV in Guinea and Sierra Leone showed protective effects in non-pregnant adults. The WHO-ERC and Data Safety Monitoring Board requested that pregnant women receive the vaccine. Despite this, 42 pregnant women were denied participation in the trial [
 <xref rid="B6-vaccines-08-00038" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-vaccines-08-00038" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. During the West Africa epidemic, the rVSV-ZEBOV vaccine underwent extensive clinical study including multiple Phase I–III human clinical trials in non-pregnant persons to evaluate the safety and efficacy of the vaccine. But by the close of the epidemic, pregnant women, their fetuses and newborns had been systematically excluded from all vaccine clinical trials [
 <xref rid="B5-vaccines-08-00038" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].
</p>
