<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since the beginning of December 2019, the novel SARS-CoV-2 outbreak is spreading globally posing critical challenges for the medical community [
 <xref rid="B1-vaccines-08-00224" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. So far Covid-19 seems to be more contagious and more deadly than most strains of seasonal influenza. In fact, without containment measures, the basic reproduction number (R
 <sub>0</sub>) of SARS-CoV-2 has been estimated in the range of 2.2 and 5.7, meaning one case may infect between two and five other persons, while for seasonal influenza this number is reportedly around 1.3 [
 <xref rid="B2-vaccines-08-00224" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-vaccines-08-00224" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Fatality rates for Covid-19 differ significantly in magnitude across countries. Discrepancies most likely depend, among other factors, on the frequency of asymptomatic or mildly symptomatic patients as well as on the testing strategy adopted in different settings, which may result in a significant proportion of undiagnosed cases. An accurate estimate of the overall infection fatality is still very difficult to calculate. Recent estimates based on aggregate data from China adjusted for demography and under-ascertainment bias suggest that the overall case fatality rate of Covid-19 could be close to 1.38% [
 <xref rid="B4-vaccines-08-00224" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. However, taking into account the ratio of asymptomatic cases support infection fatality ratios hovering 0.4–0.7% [
 <xref rid="B5-vaccines-08-00224" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. These figures are lower than that of Severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) and Middle East respiratory syndrome (MERS), which had case fatality rates around 10% and 36% respectively [
 <xref rid="B6-vaccines-08-00224" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], yet they seem to exceed those of most severe influenza strains, which have case fatality rates averaging 0.1%. The reasons why some patients progress to severe disease while others only manifest with mild or no symptoms remain to be elucidated. Beside the direct cytopathic effect of the virus, the host hyper-inflammatory response has clearly emerged as a key factor in determining disease severity and mortality.
</p>
