<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat.1008517.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1008517.g003</object-id>
 <label>Fig 3</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Epitope mapping studies to identify groups of mAbs recognizing similar major antigenic sites.</title>
  <p>
   <bold>(A)</bold> An Octet RED96 instrument (Pall FortéBio) was used to perform epitope binning studies using competition binding. RRV-86 was used as a capture antibody and was immobilized onto Fc-specific anti-human IgG biosensors for 2 min. After measuring the baseline signal, the biosensor tips were immersed into wells containing RRV VLPs for two minutes. After another baseline measurement, biosensors then were transferred to wells containing a first mAb at a concentration of 100 μg/mL for 5 min, before immersion in a solution containing a second mAb, also at a concentration of 100 μg/mL for 5 min. The percent competition of the second mAb in the presence of the first mAb was determined by comparing the maximal signal of binding for the second mAb in the presence of the first antibody to the maximal signal of the second mAb in the absence of competition. Competition was defined by reduction of the maximal binding score to &lt;25% of un-competed binding (black boxes). A non-competing mAb was identified when maximal binding was &gt;50% of un-competed binding (white boxes). A 25 to 50% reduction in maximal binding was considered intermediate competition (gray boxes). Some values are negative due to slight dissociation of the first antibody in the presence of the second. The colored boxes denote two overlapping asymmetrical competition groups. The blue dotted boxes highlight antibody self-competition. 
   <bold>(B)</bold> Residues corresponding to mAbs in each competition group as determined through alanine scanning mutagenesis mapped onto the CHIKV E1/E2 trimer of heterodimers (PDB 3N42). Space-filling models for loss-of-binding residues in competition group 1 are shown in red, and loss-of-binding residues for competition group 2 in orange. A top view of the trimer is shown (left) as well as a side view (right).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1008517.g003" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
