<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>All raw files were analyzed using the Proteome Discoverer 2.1 software (Thermo Fisher Scientific). A search for fragmentation spectra was performed using the MASCOT search engine (Matrix Science, London, UK; Version 2.2) embedded in Proteome Discoverer against the Uniprot Canidae protein sequence database (released in November 2016, 31,596 sequences). Several search parameters were used: (1) monoisotopic mass; (2) trypsin as the cleavage enzyme; (3) two missed cleavages; (4) TMT labeling; (5) cysteine carbamidomethylation as fixed modifications; (6) peptide charges of 2+, 3+, and 4+; and (7) methionine oxidation. The mass tolerance was set to 20 ppm for precursor ions and to 0.1 Da for the fragment ions. Peptide spectral matches were filtered to a 1% false discovery rate. The relative quantitative analysis of the sample proteins was based on TMT reporter ion ratios from all unique peptides representing each protein. This analysis was performed using Proteome Discoverer (version 2.1). The relative peak intensities of the TMT reporter ions released in each of the MS/MS spectra were used. The final ratios obtained from the relative protein quantifications were normalized based on the median average protein quantification ratio. Only unique peptides obtained with a confidence percentage of &gt;95% were included in the ratio ≥1.20, or ≤0.8333-fold cutoff value was used to identify upregulated and downregulated proteins with 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05. The mass spectrometry proteomic data have been deposited to the ProteomeXchange Consortium via the PRIDE partner repository with the dataset identifier PXD lycorine (accession number 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://proteomecentral.proteomexchange.org/cgi/GetDataset?ID=PXD012936" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">PXD012936</ext-link>). Protein-protein interaction (PPI) analysis of DEP proteins STRING (Search Tool for the Retrieval of Interacting Genes/Proteins) version 11.0 was employed in this study for the potential PPI analysis of the DEPs proteins (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://string-db.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://string-db.org/</ext-link>) (
 <xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr">Szklarczyk et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Shannon et al., 2003</xref>). The parameter for confidence score was set to 0.4, and the yield PPI results were visualized by Cytoscape software (
 <xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Shannon et al., 2003</xref>). The light blue nodes indicated upregulated-proteins and the light green nodes indicated downregulated-proteins. The edge thickness was proportional to the combined score of the proteins.
</p>
