<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Acquisition of the raw data was performed using MassLynx software version 4.1 (Waters Corp., MA, USA) and raw data were converted into the Analysis Base File (ABF) format by the Reifycs ABF Converter software (
 <uri xlink:href="https://www.reifycs.com/AbfConverter/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.reifycs.com/AbfConverter/</uri>) [
 <xref rid="B16-ijms-20-05952" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The ABF data were then processed to generate a usable data matrix including annotation lipid name, accurate mass, retention time, and the corresponding intensity of unique MS features by the MS-DIAL software (
 <uri xlink:href="http://prime.psc.riken.jp/Metabolomics_Software/MS-DIAL/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://prime.psc.riken.jp/Metabolomics_Software/MS-DIAL/</uri>) [
 <xref rid="B16-ijms-20-05952" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-ijms-20-05952" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The data matrix was then exported as a .csv file for statistical analysis. MetaboAnalyst 3.0 (
 <uri xlink:href="http://www.metaboanalyst.ca" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.metaboanalyst.ca</uri>) and SIMCA-P V12.0 (Umetrics, Umeå, Sweden) were used for univariate and multivariate analysis, respectively [
 <xref rid="B40-ijms-20-05952" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. For univariate analysis, the statistical significance of the features was determined by comparing the mock-infected and virus-infected groups using the Student’s t-test and the fold changes. Adjust 
 <italic>p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05, fold change &gt;1.25 or &lt;0.8 were used as the criteria for selecting significant features. For multivariate analysis, the features were first subjected to Pareto scaling, followed by orthogonal partial least squares discriminant analysis (OPLS-DA) to find important variables with discriminative power. Variable importance in projection (VIP) score &gt;1 was used as a criterion for significant lipid features selection. The R2X/R2Y and Q2, which represented the X/Y variables explanation rate and the predicted ability of the OPLS-DA model, respectively, were calculated using the SIMCA-P software [
 <xref rid="B41-ijms-20-05952" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].
</p>
