<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005">
 <label>Table 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Summary of reviewed papers looking at the impact of COVID-19 infections and diabetes mellitus.</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th>Date, Title of paper, Authors</th>
    <th>Study type</th>
    <th>Aim of the study</th>
    <th>Outcomes</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td>January 30th, 2020
     <break/>Chen N, Zhou M, Dong X, Qu J, Gong F, Han Y, et al. Epidemiological and clinical characteristics of 99 cases of 2019 novel coronavirus pneumonia in Wuhan China: a descriptive study. Lancet 2020;395(10223):507–513 
     <xref rid="b0220" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>
    </td>
    <td>Original article.
     <break/>
     <break/>Retrospective single centre study of 99 patients admitted from 1st to 20th January 2020, including adult cases of COVID-19 confirmed by RT-PCR.
    </td>
    <td>To clarify the epidemiological and clinical characteristics of 2019-nCoV pneumonia.</td>
    <td>Comorbidity is a worsening predicting factor: 51% had chronicle medical disease of whom 24% had diabetes mellitus.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>February 24th, 2020
     <break/>Wu Z, McGoogan JM. Characteristics of and important lesson from the Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak in China: summary of a report of 72,314 cases from the Chinese center for disease control and prevention. J Am Med Ass 2020 Feb24. doi.org/https://doi.org//10.1001/jama.2020.2648 
     <xref rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>
    </td>
    <td>Opinion article, viewpoint.
     <break/>Among a total of 72.314 cases, the overall case-fatality rate (CFR) was 2.3%.
    </td>
    <td>To summarize
     <break/>key findings from Chinese cases of COVID-19 epidemic.
    </td>
    <td>Comorbidities including diabetes increase the risk of adverse outcome in COVID-19 infection.
     <break/>
     <break/>CFR was elevated among those with diabetes: 7.3%.
     <break/>No deaths occurred in the group aged 0–9 years.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>March 10th, 2020
     <break/>Gupta R, Ghosh A, Singh AK, Misra A. Clinical considerations for patients with diabetes in times of COVID-19 epidemic. Diabetes Metab Syndr 2020;14:211–12 
     <xref rid="b0325" ref-type="bibr">[65]</xref>
     <break/>
    </td>
    <td>Clinical considerations.</td>
    <td>To increase the knowledge on SARS-CoV-2 infection’s management in patients with diabetes.</td>
    <td>Diabetic patients have an increased risk of infection with SARS-CoV-2. Comorbidities and older age worsen the prognosis.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>March 28th, 2020
     <break/>Fadini GP, Morieri ML, Longato E, Avogaro A. Prevalence and impact of diabetes among people infected with SARS-CoV-2. JEI 2020; htpps://doi.org/https://doi.org//10.1007/s-40618-020-01236- 
     <xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>
    </td>
    <td>Letter to the Editor.</td>
    <td>To report the results of a meta-analysis and of local data, showing the prevalence of diabetes among adults with COVID-19</td>
    <td>Diabetes does not increase the risk of SARS-CoV-2 infection but can worsen the outcome of COVID-19. The rate ratio of diabetes among patients with adverse disease course was 2.26 in China and 1.75 at the University Hospital of Padua (Italy).</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>March 31st, 2020
     <break/>
     <break/>Guo W, Li M, Dong Y, Zhou H, Zhang Z, Tian C, et al. Diabetes is a risk factor for the progression and prognosis of COVID-19. Diabetes Metab Res Rev 2020;e3319.
    </td>
    <td>Research article.
     <break/>
     <break/>Retrospective study on 174 adult patients, admitted from 10th to 29th February 2020.
    </td>
    <td>To define whether diabetes influences COVID-19 infection.</td>
    <td>Diabetes is a risk factor for rapid progression and bad prognosis of COVID-19 pneumonia.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>March 31st, 2020
     <break/>Muniyappa R, Gubbi S. Perspective: COVID-19 pandemic, coronaviruses, and diabetes mellitus. Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab 2020 May 1; 318(5): E736–E741 
     <xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>
    </td>
    <td>Research article.
     <break/>
     <break/>Pathophysiology study.
    </td>
    <td>To summarize clinical features and natural course of COVID-19, its pathophysiology and the potential mechanisms by which diabetes modulates the host-viral interaction and host immune responses.</td>
    <td>Importance of identification of clinical and biochemical parameters using multiomics approaches, that predict severity of COVID-19 in patients with diabetes.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>April 17th, 2020
     <break/>Garg SK, Rodbard D, Hirsch IB, Forlenza GP. Managing new-onset type 1 diabetes during the COVID-19 pandemic: Challenges and opportunities. Diab Technol Therap 2020;22(6):1–9. 
     <xref rid="b0330" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref>
    </td>
    <td>Original article</td>
    <td>To define the role of telemedicine in type 1 diabetes management</td>
    <td>Telemedicine in an effective approach for the management of new-onset type 1 diabetes particularly during COVID-19 pandemia</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
