<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This study provides new insights into the high CFR and dynamics of A/H1N1pdm09 in India. Using the most comprehensive A/H1N1pdm09 HA sequence dataset annotated with associated temporal and spatial metadata available from India, our analysis has uncovered possible genetic explanations for the apparent high CFR of A/H1N1pdm09 observed there. Case fatality ratios aim to measure the individual risk of death among infected cases and are frequently used as a proxy for disease severity within populations [
 <xref rid="B48-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. In India, yearly CFR for A/H1N1pdm09 have ranged from 3.6% to 23.3%, which is orders of magnitude higher than observed in other countries (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00791-f001">Figure 1</xref>b). The true CFR is certainly lower due to case under-ascertainment [
 <xref rid="B48-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. For example, in states with more than 100 reported deaths, the upper CFR range from 2009 to 2017 drops to 18.2% [
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In order to roughly determine the degree of possible case ascertainment issues affecting CFR estimates in India, we used demographic reconstruction methods to infer the effective viral population size (N
 <sub>e</sub>) of A/H1N1pdm09 through time. In contrast to official case counts which show little activity in the three years from 2012 to 2014 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00791-f001">Figure 1</xref>b) we infer sizable A/H1N1pdm09 epidemics in India occurring almost yearly (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00791-f001">Figure 1</xref>a). This suggests a high degree of case under-ascertainment during those years. Likely explanations for this include the widespread circulation of mild or subclinical strains or increasing population immunity to drifted but antigenically indistinguishable strains. In the absence of any significant changes to surveillance and reporting guidelines however, the magnitude of cases and deaths therefore detected in 2015 and 2017 suggests the emergence of antigenically novel A/H1N1pdm09 viruses. The acute magnitude and severity of the 2015 season in particular was reflected extensively in the Indian media at the time [
 <xref rid="B49-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], and largely affected younger and middle-aged persons under 65 years and involved the deaths of healthy people [
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Clinicians working in intensive care reported severe clinical manifestations and extensive ulceration of the trachea-bronchial tree on bronchoscopy (personal correspondence, clinician round table). This is in contrast to other countries where post-pandemic A/H1N1pdm09-predominate seasons have been relatively mild [
 <xref rid="B52-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>].
</p>
