<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In our study we provide possible genetic explanations for the circulation of a severe A/H1N1pdm09 virus in India which has yet to be articulated in the literature. We provide evidence of increased positive selection within the antigenic sites of HA (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00791-f002">Figure 2</xref>) among Indian A/H1N1pdm09 strains relative to globally circulating strains that could explain the severity of recent epidemics observed there (
 <xref rid="viruses-11-00791-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Progressive selection at HA antigenic sites (i.e., antigenic drift) is principally responsible for the seasonal emergence of influenza A epidemics worldwide [
 <xref rid="B54-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], and higher rates of selection at antigenic sites are known to drive the increased frequency and severity of A/H3N2 epidemics [
 <xref rid="B56-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Residue changes within the four antigenic sites of A/H1N1pdm09 HA (Sa, Sb, Ca and Cb) continue to be detected worldwide [
 <xref rid="B57-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] including S185T [
 <xref rid="B58-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] detected in our study (
 <xref rid="viruses-11-00791-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>; Sb domain). Residue change S185T was observed in the majority of our extant Indian sample (
 <italic>n</italic> = 473/643; 77.2%). Increased selection at position 186 however has not previously been reported. Residue changes at this position have been observed overseas among cases with severe disease concurrent with other residue changes also detected in our study (
 <xref rid="viruses-11-00791-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) such as S185T and D222N/G [
 <xref rid="B61-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Outside of typical determinates associated with excess influenza mortality such as reduced access to health care in India [
 <xref rid="B6-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], selection at these sites together provide possible genetic explanations for the unusual severity of recent epidemics in India. At site 186 particularly, the equivalent position in A/H3N2 viruses (position 189) is one of seven key positions within HA capable of generating antigenically novel variants from a single residue change [
 <xref rid="B65-viruses-11-00791" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Therefore, residue changes at this site, such as A186T, may constitute a new antigenic determinate of A/H1N1pdm09 severity. This could have substantial public health implications for future epidemic prevention, control, and response within India, but also for risk prediction around the world. However, the low frequency of residue changes at position 186 in our sample (
 <italic>n</italic> = 8/613; 1.31%) mean these mutations might also be sporadic. Yet, the robust evidence for increased selection relative to internationally circulating A/H1N1pdm09 viruses (
 <xref rid="viruses-11-00791-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) suggests an unusual situation could be occurring in India which warrants further investigation. Future studies such as haemagglutinin inhibition (HI) assays will be necessary to provide empirical evidence of the potential antigenic implications of residue changes at position 186 in A/H1N1pdm09 rather than position 189 in A/H3N2.
</p>
