<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par52">Based on the success of humanized mAbs in the clinic, a key discovery technology to obtain fully human mAbs (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref>) was developed in 1990 by Sir Gregory P. Winter [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. This technique was based on phage display, wherein diverse exogenous genes are incorporated into filamentous bacteriophages to compose a library. The library proteins are then presented on the phage surface as fusions with a phage coat protein, allowing the selection of specific binders and affinity characteristics. The phage display technique was first introduced by George P. Smith [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] and comprises a powerful method for the rapid identification of peptides or antibody fragments, such as single chain fragment variable (scFv) or Fab, that bind a variety of target molecules (proteins, cell-surface glycans and receptors) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref>). The Nobel Prize in Chemistry 2018 was awarded to George P. Smith and Sir Gregory P. Winter. George Smith developed phage-displayed peptides, which can be used to evolve new proteins [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Gregory P. Winter was able to apply the phage-displayed antibody library to the discovery and isolation of antibodies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Phage display technology has also been used for antibody maturation by site-directed mutagenesis of CDR and affinity selection. Based on these techniques, the first fully human therapeutic antibody, adalimumab (Humira), an anti-tumor necrosis factor α (TNFα) human antibody [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], was approved in 2002 by the US FDA for rheumatoid arthritis (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Until now, nine human antibody drugs generated by phage display have been approved by the US FDA (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). 
</p>
