<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">At present, the treatment is mostly symptomatic and supportive, though anti-inflammatory and antiviral treatment have been employed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Several efforts are underway to make vaccines for this deadly disease, COVID-19, however, it will take approximately 18 months, as estimated by WHO to achieve this goal [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Currently, there is no promising and definitive treatment available around the world. The supportive treatment for complicated patients includes invasive mechanical ventilation, continuous renal replacement therapy (CRRT), and even extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Currently, there are several clinically approved antiviral drugs under consideration to find effective treatments targeting viral entry and replications. These include an oral drug called EIDD-2801, anti-malarial drug hydroxychloroquine, remdesivir -a failed Ebola drug, and kaletra which is a combination of HIV drug lopinavir and ritonavir [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Not just anti-viral drugs, but immunosuppressants like sarilumab and tocilizumab are also being tested for the patients, where not only the virus but the patient’s immune overreaction worsens the situation ultimately killing them [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Furthermore, dexamethasone which is a generic steroid widely used to reduce inflammation is the latest in the fray and is emerging as another lifesaving drug in this pandemic [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Plasma Therapy has also given some hope for severely ill patients where it has been reported to improve their survival rate [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Moreover, several studies have shown a shorter hospital stay and lower mortality rates in patients treated with convalescent plasma. Despite these drug modalities under consideration, the question remains the same: Do we have a definitive treatment available for this infection?
</p>
