<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Infectious diseases are the largest cause of human mortality worldwide, leading to over 13 million deaths a year [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007111.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Respiratory diseases alone account for a large fraction of these infections—CDC reports that the buden of illness during 2017-18 influenza season was high in the United States, with an estimated 48.8 million illnesses and 959,000 hospitalizations [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007111.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], higher than any season since the 2009 pandemic. Therefore, controlling the spread of infectious diseases, especially influenza, remains an important priority for local, state, and federal governments in the US and countries worldwide. Pharmaceutical interventions (PI) such as the use of prophylactic vaccinations and anti-viral drugs remain one of the most effective methods for controlling the spread of infectious diseases, e.g., [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007111.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007111.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. However, these interventions are constrained by limited resource supply and the high logistics cost of delivering them over a large geographical region. These limitations have been an actively studied topic in public health policy research. The primary objective here is to devise allocation and distribution strategies to improve the overall effectiveness of the limited supply of vaccines. In this paper, we denote this problem as V
 <sc>acc</sc>I
 <sc>nt</sc>D
 <sc>esign</sc>. Most of the existing literature has focused on identifying whom to allocate the vaccines to, based on age and disease risk [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007111.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007111.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, it is widely understood that seasonal influenza exhibits typical spatial trends [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007111.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Further, the vaccine allocation problem is temporally constrained by the production and availability schedule, while most prior studies on epidemic interventions have primarily focused on static allocation before the start of the epidemic [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007111.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Thus the when and where aspects of allocation become equally, if not more, relevant. In [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007111.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], the authors studied vaccine allocation and distribution during the 2009 H1N1 pandemic and found that for many states, the vaccines arrived far too late to be useful. While the authors define possible alternatives for the pro-rata vaccine distribution using axiomatic Operations Research (OR) models, in this paper, we adopt a simulation optimization approach, by using a mechanistic model of influenza spread across the US.
</p>
