<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">Viral polymerase complex is a promising target for the development of anti-influenza drugs, because transcription and replication are critical steps for virus propagation. Moreover, the viral polymerase complex acts by a specific molecular mechanism for viral transcription and replication. The viral polymerase complex is a heterotrimer composed of three subunits: PA, PB1 and PB2. At the initiation of viral mRNA transcription, influenza viral polymerase cannot synthesize the 5′-cap structure of mRNA that is necessary for translation and uses a unique ‘cap-snatching’ mechanism to ‘steal’ the cap structure of mRNA from host mRNAs.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup> Host-cell pre-mRNA is bound to the PB2 subunit via its 5′-cap structure and can be cleaved at nucleotide 10–13 by the endonuclease activity of the PA subunit. Using this capped fragment as a primer, the viral polymerase complex synthesizes viral mRNA. These processes have been targeted in the development of anti-influenza drugs and two inhibitors, VX-787 (pimodivir) and S-033188, are under phase 2 and 3 clinical trials, respectively. VX-787 is a PB2 inhibitor that binds to the cap-binding pocket in PB2.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup> The molecule 3-pyrimidineazainodole, VRT-0761704, was identified as a lead compound for anti-influenza virus activities by phenotypic screening, and the target of this compound was determined to be the PB2 subunit. Based on structural information for the PB2-m
 <sup>7</sup>GTP and PB2-VRT-0761704 complex, VX-787 was synthesized. VX-787 represents an orally bioavailable compound that is only effective for influenza A virus, not influenza B virus. S-03318 specifically inhibits the endonuclease activity of PA and thus prevents the cleavage of host pre-mRNAs. S-03318 is effective for both influenza A and influenza B virus infections.
</p>
