<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To date, a total of 4,434,653 confirmed cases and 302,169 deaths are reported from the SARS-COV-2 epidemic, which indicates that the current viral treatment is not satisfactory, and more diverse studies are needed for the incorporation of various natural and FDA approved compounds for the effective treatment of SARS-COV-2. Further, our existing capacity for treating zoonotic coronavirus infections is still in the trial, and the available resources seem very limited to fight this life-threatening hazard. Although extensive research efforts have been initiated during 2003 and 2012 outbreaks of SARS and MERS-CoV, respectively, however, no effective drugs so far have been synthesized, nor the matter may be taken seriously to prevent the future pandemics of zoonotic coronavirus. Drug repositioning is a ‘universal strategy’ for neglected diseases due to reduced number of clinical trial steps required could reduce the time and cost of the medicine to reach the market, existing pharmaceutical supply chains could facilitate the ‘formulation and distribution’ of the drug, the known possibility of combining with other drugs could enable more efficient treatment, Repositioning could encourage the development of ‘new modes of action for old drugs and new types of medicines, eliminating ‘activation obstacles’ from early stages of study could allow the project to progress rapidly towards disease-oriented development (Pushpakom et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). One of the primary reasons why no prototype coronavirus inhibitor has progressed to the (early) preclinical stage so far is due to the transient nature of this epidemic. Like the SARS virus 17 years ago, the new SARS-CoV-2, and the new evolving coronaviruses that may continue to pose a threat to global public health in the future. Hence, discovering broad-spectrum inhibitors that can reduce the symptoms of human coronavirus infection remains a formidable subject of study. Considering the time-consuming process of designing and documenting antiviral medications, proven therapies for certain diseases may be the only fastest therapeutic choice for emerging infectious diseases. The prescription has ample experience and dosage for most of those medications that have been formulated, and their health and ADME properties are well known.
</p>
