<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In early studies, Rosen detected minimal VT of DENV among 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] but more recent reports have provided consistent evidence of VT in field-collected 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], although significant variations in the frequency of VT have been noted among strains of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> infected with different DENV serotypes and genotypes [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. DENV have been detected in field-collected larvae [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] and field caught adult male mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The detection of DENV infected male mosquitoes suggests that males could play a role in the maintenance of DENV in nature [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Few studies have addressed the role of male mosquitoes in DENV transmission dynamics and only one study focused on VNT of DENV in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] by determining VNT by males that were artificially injected with virus. In this context, we tested VT and VNT of DENV2 in a genetically diverse laboratory strain (GDLS) of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> derived from mosquito populations collected in Chiapas, Mexico [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Initially, we investigated whether VT in GDLS was more efficient in the first or second gonotrophic cycle (E1 and E2). We clearly observed that orally infected GDLS mosquitoes vertically transmitted DENV2 to their F1 progeny during the second gonotrophic cycle (E2) and VT increased if a second blood meal was given 10 or 21 days post infection. Significantly, the MFIR determined by either RT-semi-nested-PCR (RT-N-PCR) or IFA was 8–10 fold higher than previously reported for flaviviruses [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006754.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. We detected DENV2 in ovarian tissues and oocytes of infected females suggesting VT can occur by TOT. The present study also demonstrated that males acquiring DENV2 by the VT route were capable of transmitting the virus to un-infected virgin GDLS females during mating. Our results suggest that VT and VNT of DENV in mosquito populations are potential mechanisms for virus maintenance during inter-epidemic periods.
</p>
