<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The findings we report come, however, with several important caveats. The most obvious is that ours was a before–after, single-site trial lacking independent replicates, which limits the strength of the evidence we present. To partly mitigate this limitation, we estimated intervention effects using detailed 12-mo baseline data, and accounted for dwelling-level repeated measures, weather conditions, and unequal sampling effort using GLMMs. The size, sign, and consistency of effect estimates—which fully align with expectations based on mosquito biology and previous reports of PPF effects [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]—reinforce our confidence in the outcome of our analyses. In addition, that our findings are consistent with results from a neighborhood in a different city [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] suggests that PPF dissemination effects might be replicable elsewhere. Control results might however depend on the local availability of alternative breeding sites, which we did not measure. The impact of the intervention could thus be reduced in places where competing larval habitats are widespread enough to distract egg-laying females away from DSs. A second key limitation is that our SBS data are difficult to interpret in terms of true adult mosquito density or abundance [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. While this should not greatly affect our estimates of 
 <italic>relative</italic> change in juvenile catch and adult emergence, it calls for a cautious reading of our 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> results. Even if our complementary analyses using three times as many emerging females as observed are reassuring, we regard our 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> estimates as explicit, plausible hypotheses to be tested in future trials—ideally, cluster-randomized trials with replicate intervention and control sites and including a blind prospective assessment of arboviral infection incidence [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Finally, we note that we did not have the means to measure PPF in our SBSs, and therefore lack direct evidence of PPF dissemination. However, we did not record any extreme weather event or vector control intervention that could account for our observations. Further, alternative GLMMs investigating dissemination intensity/quality (coded as a 1-mo-lagged 0–4 variable; see 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec008">Methods</xref>) suggested “dose-dependent” effects—with, for instance, a 57.1% (95% CI 54.3%–59.8%) reduction in monthly adult 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> emergence for each unit increase in dissemination intensity/quality (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1002213.s005">S4 Fig</xref>). In sum, we are confident that the striking changes in mosquito demographics we report were real and were a direct consequence of our intervention. The caveats discussed above call, however, for a cautious interpretation of our results, particularly regarding virus transmission—which we did not measure empirically.
</p>
