<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One additional asset of our approach is that it may easily be combined with other interventions, traditional or novel, in integrated mosquito control strategies. For example, control agents and community members could focus on treating or destroying large, conspicuous, and accessible breeding sites, while mosquitoes disseminate PPF to the small, cryptic, and inaccessible larval habitats often used by 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> spp. The community could engage in DS maintenance with support from local health agents; this would empower communities and may enhance acceptability while reducing costs. During outbreaks, indoor insecticide spraying could synergize PPF dissemination to quickly block transmission; in sites with effective early warning systems, spatially targeted interventions could be deployed as soon as the first cases of infection (in humans, vectors, or sentinel hosts) are detected. In general, flexible PPF dissemination strategies can be designed to suit particular needs in time and space. For example, focally deploying DSs at high densities could protect people in transmission-prone places such as hospitals, schools, stadiums, markets, churches, cemeteries, hotels, or prisons. Specific dissemination schemes in airports, bus/train stations, or ports (even on ships) might help limit man-mediated 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> spread. Mosquito-disseminated PPF also holds promise for sites without mosquito-borne disease transmission but where mosquito bites cause skin lesions, allergies, distress, or economic losses (e.g., by affecting tourism). We also note that the 95%–98% reduction in adult 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> emergence we recorded (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed.1002213.g005">Fig 5</xref>) could allow PPF dissemination to contribute to strategies based on the release of sterile, transgenic, or 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-transinfected mosquitoes, which require a high enough ratio of modified to wild mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>–
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. The scale of mosquito releases (and associated costs including those of mass rearing) could be considerably reduced after a pulse of mosquito-disseminated PPF crashes local wild populations. Finally, we stress that combining PPF with products or tactics with different modes of action [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002213.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] would help reduce the odds of selecting resistant mosquitoes—a concern we also plan to address by testing larvicides other than PPF in experimental dissemination trials.
</p>
