<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0020">Of the known viruses that infect humans, about 80% perpetuate naturally in nonhuman “reservoirs,” largely farm mammals and poultry and, to a lesser extent, in wild animals and arthropods. It is estimated that zoonotic infectious agents constitute about 60% of the known human pathogens and up to 75% of “emerging” human pathogens. The knowledge of such zoonosis and the diversity of these viruses in their known reservoirs are limited. Also the data on some of the domestic mammals harboring dozens of virus species is limited, and there is insufficient knowledge about the wild animals that are estimated to host thousands of virus species (
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Keusch et al., 2009</xref>). Emerging human viruses, such as novel influenza strains, human (h)CoV, Hendra virus, Nipah virus, and several others, are all linked to zoonosis. Recently, the deadly outbreak of MERS-CoV was linked to its zoonotic origin because of its close genetic homology to bat CoV, but not to any other known hCoV (
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Kilpatrick and Randolph, 2012</xref>). Current data shows that bats harbor the greatest diversity of CoVs, which vary from species to species and region to region. The Lyssaviruses of Rhabdoviridae are zoonotic human pathogens that cause fatal encephalitic disease. In addition, European bat lyssavirus type-1/-2, Bokeloh bat lyssavirus (
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Wolfe et al., 2007</xref>), and Australian bat lyssaviruses have been implicated in human fatalities. Rabies virus, the Archetypal lyssavirus, is historically one of the most dreaded viruses, with zoonotic potential in dogs, cats, and ferrets, and includes other domestic and wild mammals. Globally, several mammalian species, including the deer mouse, rice rat, and cotton rat, are recognized as potential reservoir of HTNV. In China, the HTNV and Seoul virus are zoonotically linked to the striped field mouse and the Norway rat, respectively. Also in China, the Fugong virus, a novel HTNV, has recently been identified in small oriental voles. HTNVs have also been detected in shrews and bats, but their link to human illness remains to be established. Moreover, in addition to humans and pigs, there is a growing chain of mammalian hosts for the hepatitis E virus (HEV) that includes deer, boar, mongoose, rabbit, rat, goat, camel, bat, ferret, moose, etc. Likewise, the highly prevalent Torque teno virus, of the newly established virus family, Anelloviridae, also infects pigs, cows, sheep, cats, dogs, and chickens. Arboviruses, such as dengue virus, chikungunya virus (CHIKV), ZIKV, and West Nile virus (WNV), are the arthropod-borne viruses that have reemerged in many tropical and subtropical regions in the last two decades (
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Taylor et al., 2001</xref>). Notably, ZIKV was known as a neglected tropical disease confined to Africa and Asia until an outbreak was reported in 2007 on Yap Island and in 2013/2014 on islands in the Pacific, thus expanding its geographical territory. The WNV remains the most important mosquito-borne encephalitis pathogen in North America, involving 
 <italic>Culex</italic> sp. and the American Robin in its transmission cycle. Since its emergence in the West in 1999, it has undergone adaptive genetic changes as it spreads throughout North America (
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Woolhouse and Antia 2008</xref>). Furthermore, Crimean–Congo hemorrhagic fever virus (CCHFV) is considered to be one of the major emerging diseases spreading to and within the European nations, following the expanding distribution of anthropophilic ticks. Every year, &gt;1000 cases of CCHFV, due to human-to-human transmission, are reported in southeastern Europe, including Turkey. SFTSV, a previously unidentified tick-borne bunyavirus, has recently emerged in China with fatality rates as high as 30% (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Anderson and Tong, 2010</xref>) (
 <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 4.1</xref> ).
</p>
