<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">As part of social distancing requirements in many settings, routine HIV care is being offered via telemedicine [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. For women who may not have disclosed their HIV status to their partners, this form of care provision, although necessary during these times, may not be a feasible option for many women living with HIV. Virtual care provides greater opportunity for disclosing women’s HIV status, reduces women’s ability to disclose experiences of violence to providers for fear of their abuser overhearing, thus increasing their risk of further experiences of violence [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Our previous research has found that among a sample of women living with HIV in British Columbia, Canada, 59% experienced some form of IPV in their lifetime, of those only 12.4% sought violence support [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. More recent data from the Canadian HIV Women’s Sexual and Reproductive Health Cohort Study (CHIWOS), showed 80% of participants reported experiencing violence as an adult, 42% of whom reported seeking help for violence. Among CHIWOS participants who reported seeking help, the most commonly accessed form of help to cope with violence was through health care providers [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. In other low-income settings, where telemedicine is unlikely to occur, women living with HIV may still struggle to access medication, as their normal collection points, often far from their communities, are no longer accessible, and male partner surveillance of their movement may have increased. As the health care system, and HIV care, may be the first line of violence support for many women living with HIV, during these unprecedented times, it is especially important that HIV care providers take a women-centred trauma-aware approach, which is led by the needs and priorities of their patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. This can help to ensure privacy and address concerns regarding limited mobility and access to medication.
</p>
