<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Twenty years after its introduction, West Nile virus (WNV, 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic>: 
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic>) continues to be the leading cause of arboviral disease in the continental United States (US) [
 <xref rid="B1-pathogens-09-00048" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. WNV was first isolated in 1937 from the blood of a woman in the West Nile district of Uganda [
 <xref rid="B2-pathogens-09-00048" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. During the 1950s, the virus was isolated from birds, mosquitoes and people in Egypt [
 <xref rid="B3-pathogens-09-00048" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-pathogens-09-00048" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The virus continued to present primarily as recurrent epidemics of mild febrile disease in Africa, the Middle East and Europe [
 <xref rid="B5-pathogens-09-00048" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. However, the disease phenotype was drastically different during outbreaks in the United States, Romania, Russia and Israel, which occurred in the late 1990s and early 2000s [
 <xref rid="B6-pathogens-09-00048" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-pathogens-09-00048" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In the United States, about 1 in 150 clinical patients developed neuroinvasive disease, characterized by meningitis, encephalitis, and/or poliomyelitis [
 <xref rid="B8-pathogens-09-00048" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-pathogens-09-00048" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Of those with neuroinvasive disease, 9% experienced mortality [
 <xref rid="B10-pathogens-09-00048" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The US outbreak represented the first known introduction of WNV to the Western hemisphere. Outbreaks during the late 1990s in Israel and eastern Europe were also characterized by higher rates of fatal neuroinvasive disease [
 <xref rid="B11-pathogens-09-00048" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-pathogens-09-00048" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Given that these outbreaks occurred in disparate locations, phylogenetic analysis was performed to assess the degree of relatedness between the virus isolates. The strain introduced into the United States (NY99) had greater than 99.8% nucleotide homology to virus isolated from the brain of a goose in Israel from 1998 and human Israeli cases in 1999 [
 <xref rid="B13-pathogens-09-00048" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-pathogens-09-00048" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Isolates from the US also held similar relatedness to isolates from Romania [
 <xref rid="B13-pathogens-09-00048" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-pathogens-09-00048" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. It is surmised that these closely related viruses were able to cause disease in these distant locations as a result of globalization. Following its arrival in the United States, the virus showed remarkable adaptability to a new environment, quickly spread and is now endemic.
</p>
