<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par121">IV infection also induces ER stress and generates ROS in inflamed tissues [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">129</xref>]. IVs induce proteasome-dependent ER-associated degradation through the inositol-requiring enzyme 1/x-box binding protein 1 (IRE1/XBP1) signaling pathway and commitment to downregulation of SOD1, thus allowing ROS accumulation. ROS-mediated JNK or the IRE1-mediated JNK1 contributes to the control of IV infection and propagation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">129</xref>]. H1N1 PR8 infection of mouse tracheal epithelial cells increased the ER-stress-related ATF6 and the ER chaperone Erp57 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130">130</xref>]. IV infection induces caspase 12 to commit to apoptosis, as well as the production of TGF-β in IV-infected cells in a JNK1-dependent manner [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130">130</xref>]. H1N1-infected mice exhibit induction of parenchymal lung inflammation, alveolar epithelial metaplasia, and ER stress. A lung epigenetic/transcriptome analysis demonstrated that mir-155 null mice recovered from IV infection and exhibited decreased lung inflammation and ER stress [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR131">131</xref>]. Protein disulfide isomerase 3 (PDIA3) interacts with IAV-HA, and this interaction is critical for the efficient oxidative folding of HA 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>. PDIA3 is upregulated in IAV-infected mouse or human lung epithelial cells and interacts with IAV-HA directly. Treatment with a PDI inhibitor, LOC14, inhibited PDIA3 enzyme activity in lung epithelial cells, followed by the reduction of intradisulfide bond and subsequent oligomerization (maturation) of HA in both H1N1- and H3N2-infected lung epithelial cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">132</xref>]. IAV-mediated autophagy and unfolded protein response are connected to apoptosis in chronic stresses to regulate cellular homeostasis via CHOP and Beclin-1 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133">133</xref>].
</p>
