<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Regarding purine biosynthesis inhibitors, ribavirin and mycophenolic acid (MPA) are inhibitors of inosine-5′-monophosphate (IMP) dehydrogenase (IMPDH), which is a key enzyme of the purine biosynthesis pathway. These inhibitors have been successfully used as clinical antiviral or immunosuppressant agents for decades. Both have antiviral activities against viruses such as HCV, hepatitis E virus (HEV), MERS-CoV, dengue virus, yellow fever, hepatitis B virus, West Nile virus (WNV), Chikungunya virus (CHIKV), and IAV [
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-10-00211" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-10-00211" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-10-00211" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-10-00211" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-10-00211" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-10-00211" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-viruses-10-00211" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], majorly through the inhibition of the purine biosynthesis pathway, with the antiviral activity against HCV and HEV shown to involve the stimulation of ISGs [
 <xref rid="B10-viruses-10-00211" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-viruses-10-00211" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. For the antiviral activity of ribavirin against HCV, ribavirin specifically induced the expression of IRF7, IRF9, and ISG15 mRNAs, which are known to be important for anti-HCV immune responses [
 <xref rid="B6-viruses-10-00211" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. ISG activation occurred through an undefined mechanism that was different from the classical IFN signaling, intracellular dsRNA sensing pathway, Toll-like receptor and nuclear factor B pathways. More importantly, ribavirin-induced ISG activation and antiviral activity were suppressed using supplemented guanosine, a natural analog of ribavirin, suggesting IMPDH inhibition-mediated ISG activation as an alternative innate immunity pathway. Like ribavirin, MPA remarkably induced the expression of several ISGs, including IRF1, IRF9, ISG15, IFI6, IRF7, CXCL10, IFIT2, and IFITM3 mRNAs in naïve or HEV-infected Huh-7 cells, and the induction of ISGs was at least partially abrogated by the use of supplemented guanosine [
 <xref rid="B10-viruses-10-00211" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Mechanistically, the induction of ISGs by MPA was independent of the classical JAK/STAT system, which is similar to that observed with ribavirin [
 <xref rid="B30-viruses-10-00211" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Similar results were obtained with several IMPDH1 or IMPDH2 inhibitors, with various affinities, that were custom-designed and synthesized [
 <xref rid="B10-viruses-10-00211" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].
</p>
