<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>With regard to conservation of T cell-specific immunological determinants among flavivirus serocomplexes, the YVF lost the highest amount of 100% conserved T cell epitopes (see 
 <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). This is in accordance with the highest genetic distance of YFV serocomplex with regard to other flavivirus serocomplexes (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). An important explanation for the epidemiology of flaviviruses may arise from this observation. For example, vaccination against YFV in Brazil is not currently related to protection against DENV and ZIKV epidemics. However, DENV and JEV serocomplexes share most of epitopes identified in this work. It seems immunity to DENV precludes viruses of JEV serocomplex of circulating in South America. Recent studies showed evidences of cross-protective immunity between DENV and JEV serocomplexes (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). The same does not occur in Central America, Africa and Asia. Interestingly, Central America and South Africa present a low population coverage of the selected T cell epitopes. Nevertheless, population coverage of class-I HLA specific epitopes presented in this work does not seem to explain the whole scenario. For example, the population of United States is 88% covered by the set of epitopes, but there is co-circulation of DENV and JEV serocomplexes in that country. In addition, most of regions in Africa and Asia, which have also a high population coverage of our set of epitopes, present co-circulation of DENV and JEV serocomplexes. The explanation for this is probably related to class-II HLA restricted epitopes, from which only two were selected according to our criteria. Such epitopes did not present a high conservation among all serocomplexes and probably confer cross-protection in specific combinations of viruses and serocomplexes, as previously described (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). It was recently shown that cross-reactive epitopes can promote recall from a pool of flavivirus serocomplex cross-reactive memory CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). However, such epitopes are not enough conserved in order to induce cross-protection among all serocomplexes.
</p>
