<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Third-generation sequencing is based on sequencing single molecules in real-time without the need for clonal amplification, thus shortening DNA preparation time and giving long reads of several kilobases (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">Goodwin et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B247" ref-type="bibr">van Dijk et al., 2018</xref>). Long reads are more appropriate for genome sequencing, genotyping, and detecting recombination. However, third-generation sequencing needs further improvement since error rates are still much higher than in second-generation sequencing. Several techniques are being developed by different companies such as single-molecule real-time (SMRT) and nanopore sequencing. SMRT sequencing uses a flow cell with millions of individual picolitre wells with transparent bottoms (zero-mode waveguides) with a DNA polymerase fixed. Incorporation on each single-molecule template per well is continuously visualized with a laser and camera system that records the color and duration of emitted light, as the labeled nucleotide momentarily pauses during incorporation at the bottom of the wells. Nanopore sequencing is based on translocating the DNA or RNA through a nanopore (in membrane proteins or synthetic materials such as silicon nitride and aluminum oxide), where an ionic current pass by setting a voltage. The DNA passing through the nanopore changes the current depending on the shape, size and length of the DNA sequence. Nanopore sequencing has several advantages such as the relatively low cost compared to other HTS technologies, high mobility due to the sequencer small size and rapid sample processing, without the need for reverse transcription for RNA viruses (
 <xref rid="B124" ref-type="bibr">Kiselev et al., 2020</xref>). This technology has been recently used to detect some plant viruses, such as plum pox virus (PPV) and tomato yellow leaf curl virus (TYLCV), and discover new plant viruses (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Bronzato Badial et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Chalupowicz et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B166" ref-type="bibr">Naito et al., 2019</xref>).
</p>
