<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">Introducing pharmaceutical nanotechnology into the field of natural medicine is useful and promising. New strategies for the delivery of poorly soluble phytochemicals and plant extracts allow improved pharmacokinetic and clinical outcomes. Commonly used approached such as phytosomes, nanoparticles, hydrogels, microspheres, transferosomes and ethosomes, self-microemulsifying drug delivery systems (SMEDDS), and self-nanoemulsifying drug delivery systems (SNEDDS) have been applied for the delivery of antiviral plant agents (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). These antiviral technologies may be preferred over older phytochemical drug formulations due to enhanced solubility and oral absorption, systemic bioavailability, safety, delayed metabolism, and better overall antiviral activity. Yet, very few papers have been published on the topic of antiviral herbal drug delivery, so we wish to display several successful attempts of improving the delivery of phytodrugs with known antiviral activity. Qian et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>] attempted to design a self-nanoemulsifying drug delivery system (SNEDDS) to allow greater apparent solubility and oral bioavailability (&lt; 10%) of myricetin. Overall, four formulations were prepared, F04 (Capryol 90/Cremophor RH 40/PEG 400 in a 4:3:3 ratio), F08 (Capryol 90/Cremophor RH 40/1,2-propanediol 4:3:3), F13 (Capryol 90/Cremophor EL/Transcutol HP 4:3:3), and F15 (Capryol 90/Cremophor RH 40/Transcutol HP 2:7:1), and the solubility of myricetin in different excipients was studied. The optimized formulations underwent evaluation of release (dissolution), Caco-2 cell cytotoxicity and intestinal permeability studies 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>, following by 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> pharmacokinetics of myricetin-SNEDDS. Three of the four chosen formulations exhibited acceptable cell viability (&gt; 90%), while the fourth formulation was slightly cell-toxic, probably because of high nonionic surfactant content (70%). 
 <italic>In vitro</italic> drug release testing demonstrated that myricetin alone had limited dissolution of 51% after an hour, whereas drug release for all SNEDDS formulations was over 90% after 1 min. Single-pass intestinal perfusion (SPIP) method in rats showed that in the duodenum, the primary absorption site of myricetin, the effective permeability coefficient was significantly higher (1.2–2.2-fold, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in all SNEDDS formulations relative to free myricetin, via inhibition of myricetin efflux by nonionic surfactants in SNEDDS (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). In animal models, the myricetin-loaded SNEDDS formulations exhibited higher plasma myricetin concentrations in all time points compared to the free myricetin. Formulation No. 13 in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> had higher intestinal permeability, but showed lower bioavailability attributed to poor lymphatic transport—a main absorption mechanism of myricetin. Formulation No. 4 and 8, on the other hand, achieved small particle size, required for lymphatic transport (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).
</p>
