<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>West Nile virus (WNV) is a single-stranded RNA virus which belongs to the family Flaviviridae, genus Flavivirus. This family includes several important human arthropod-borne pathogens, such as dengue (DENV), Zika (ZIKV), tick-borne encephalitis (TBEV), Yellow fever (YFV) or Japanese encephalitis (JEV) viruses.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0001">1</xref>
 </sup> WNV circulates in birds and is transmitted by many different mosquito species. These can infect other animals including horses and humans, which, although dead-end hosts, can develop disease symptoms. In humans, most infections remain asymptomatic or may lead to mild fever or headache.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0002">2</xref>
 </sup> Mainly older or immunocompromised individuals are at risk for more severe forms of WNV-induced disease, which occur in up to 1% of the infections.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0002">2</xref>
 </sup> Symptoms include high fever, but also neurological complications like encephalitis or meningitis. Fatality rates reach 10% among the severe cases.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0003">3</xref>
 </sup> Since its first description in 1937 WNV has caused several outbreaks in Africa, Asia and South Eastern Europe.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0004">4</xref>
 </sup> In 1999 the virus received much of public attention when its introduction into the USA was detected, which was followed by a rapid spread over the entire American continent. In the following years, thousands of people needed to be hospitalized, and more than 1,500 fatalities have been recorded until today. In addition, WNV led to countless severe infections among horses and caused the decline of local bird populations.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0005">5</xref>,
  <xref rid="CIT0006">6</xref>
 </sup> WNV outbreaks occur in unpredictable magnitude and localization. In Europe, a peak in WNV circulation was experienced in 2018, in total, 1,503 cases were counted. In addition to countries such as Italy and Greece, where WNV is endemic already for several years, the virus was detected for the first time in Germany.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0007">7</xref>,
  <xref rid="CIT0008">8</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
