<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par100">Plasma therapy may be used to harvest antibodies from individuals who have been exposed to the SARS-Cov-2 to treat COVID-19 patients with pulmonary, neural, or cardiovascular dysfunctions. The transplanted antibodies may bind to SP or ACE2 sites, preventing the coronavirus from fusing with the cell membrane and injecting its viral genome. By blocking this crucial entry point, inflammatory symptoms and infections significantly decreased compared to patients without antibodies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>]. This occurs due to the correlation between inflammatory symptoms and infections and the expression of ACE2. If no blockage is present, the virus binds to pulmonary ACE2 and transfers its viral genome into the cell, causing cell death [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>]. The increased cell mortality and loss of ACE2 expression stimulate inflammatory and immune activity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>]. Inflammatory response and overreaction of the immune system to the increased infection and cell death would further cause pulmonary damage, possibly worsening respiratory distress, post-viral infection, and severe acute respiratory failure [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>]. Conversely, blocking ACE2 or viral SP with antibodies would preserve ACE2 expression and lower cell mortality, decreasing inflammatory symptoms and infections. Viral infections may also damage neural and cardiovascular cells, decreasing ACE2 expression in the brain and heart, respectively [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>]. Similar to pulmonary damage, neural and cardiovascular cell mortality induces inflammatory activity, further causing structural damage and cognitive and cardiovascular dysfunctions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>]. On the other hand, blocking ACE2 or SP via antibodies prevents cell death from viral infection, which consequently preserves ACE2 expression and increases anti-inflammatory activity.
</p>
