<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par103">Both clinical studies presented findings that parallel previous discoveries from earlier pandemics and studies regarding convalescent plasma treatment. Earlier treatment after exposure to SARS-CoV-2 was more effective compared to later treatments [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>]. As seen in previous studies, inflammatory activity decreased and normal pulmonary and respiratory functions returned after convalescent plasma therapy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>]. Additionally, plasma therapy does not present any detrimental or adverse reactions to patients even when administered large dosages [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>]. These results suggest that plasma therapy is safe and effective for COVID-19 patients, especially when treated early. However, some limitations are present in the two clinical trials. Both clinical trials had a small number of subjects. Furthermore, some patients received other sources of standard care while also receiving plasma therapy, such as antiviral treatment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>]. Indeed, this opens the possibility of antiviral treatment contributing to the recovery of the patients. However, this also raises uncertainty regarding the true therapeutic effects of plasma therapy in human subjects. Additionally, some patients were treated much later after exposure to SARS-CoV-2 compared to other patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>]. For patients who received plasma treatment late, it is difficult to determine whether their recovery was due to convalescent plasma or natural recovery. The varying times of treatment along with limited human trials limit the potential of convalescent plasma infusion. Future clinical studies should increase the number of test subjects and apply plasma therapy as early as the first onset of symptoms.
</p>
