<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The Influenza virus belongs to the 
 <italic>Orthomyxoviridae</italic> family and causes respiratory infections in about 20% of the global population every year. The 1918 flu pandemic was caused by Influenza A subtype H1N1 and killed 50 million people around the world [
 <xref rid="B93-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. The Asian Influenza caused by Influenza A subtype H2N2 occurred in 1957 and the Hong Kong Influenza caused by Influenza A subtype H3N2 took place in 1968 and made far fewer victims than the 1918 Spanish flu. About 70 people died in Asia in 2004–2005 due to the H5N1 strain of avian flu [
 <xref rid="B93-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. The 2009 flu pandemic (swine flu) was the second pandemic involving a strain of Influenza A virus. It was classified as Influenza A H1N1 2009 and the genetic material originated from three different species: human, avian and swine [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B94-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. The chemotherapy or prophylaxis of Influenza infections comprises agents blocking the Influenza A virus M2 proton-selective ion channel (amantadine, rimantadine) and neuraminidase inhibitors (zanamivir, oseltamivir, laninamivir, peramivir) [
 <xref rid="B1-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B93-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. Both classes can induce virus resistance and therefore there is an urgent need to develop new antiviral agents with novel mechanisms of action. An alternative concept has recently emerged and it is based on the idea of designing new molecules targeting host cell factors that are hijacked by the virus during its replication. Host-targeting antivirals are an alternative strategy for addressing host structures involved in the virus life cycle. This type of inhibitors could exhibit a significantly greater barrier for selecting drug-resistant viruses and, in addition, display broad-spectrum antiviral activity when interacting with a cellular target common to several viruses. The host factor-directed antiviral therapy is recently studied. This is increasingly recognized as a relevant approach to combat viral resistance and provides broad-spectrum antiviral agents [
 <xref rid="B95-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>,
 <xref rid="B96-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>].
</p>
