<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0010">
 <label>Table 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Lessons learned from SARS and COVID-19.</p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text id="at0065">Table 2</alt-text>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th align="left"/>
    <th align="left">SARS</th>
    <th align="left">COVID-19</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Lesson 1</td>
    <td align="left">Enhanced monitoring of wildlife sources.</td>
    <td align="left">Closing wildlife markets, forbidding wildlife trade, and prohibiting wildlife consumption as food.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Lesson 2</td>
    <td align="left">Unrestricted sharing of information.
     <break/>Travel restrictions partly.
    </td>
    <td align="left">International cooperation.
     <break/>Unrestricted, accurate, timely and effective information dissemination.
     <break/>Travel restrictions; Community, city, and even national lockdown.
     <break/>Increased viral transmission due to human mobility and quick and convenient public transportation.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Lesson 3</td>
    <td align="left">Building up an epidemic reporting system network.</td>
    <td align="left">Rapid responses: National and local government measures; Rapid mobilization of healthcare personnel to treat patients; Developing guidelines to control viral transmission; Cloud computing and big data to control the epidemic.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Lesson 4</td>
    <td align="left">Reducing viral transmission:
     <break/>Isolation of suspect cases;
     <break/>Regular disinfection;
     <break/>Wearing of masks and washing of hands.
    </td>
    <td align="left">Rigorous infection control:
     <break/>Aggressive quarantine; Regular disinfection;
     <break/>Wearing masks correctly; Effective hand washing; Minimal social contact.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Lesson 5</td>
    <td align="left">The importance of rapid testing and isolation.</td>
    <td align="left">Early testing, early reporting, early isolation, early diagnosis, early treatment.
     <break/>Although CT examination is important for identifying suspected cases, it does not replace accurate diagnosis with nucleic acid testing kits.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Lesson 6</td>
    <td align="left">Urgent construction of a temporary hospital.</td>
    <td align="left">Reassignment of medical facilities: Flexible use of public facilities for temporary hospitals.
     <break/>Differentiated patient admittance: Existing hospitals for patients with severe or critical disease; Mobile, field, or temporary medical facilities for patients with mild or moderate disease.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Lesson 7</td>
    <td align="left">Corticosteroids was used to treat patients with severe disease.</td>
    <td align="left">Integral medicine: Multidisciplinary and multiorgan treatment. Critical care medicine is crucial for patients with severe or critical disease.
     <break/>Oxygen supplementation and mechanical ventilation are key to treatment of patients with severe or critical disease.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Lesson 8</td>
    <td align="left">TCM was effective in treating SARS and reduced complications due to corticosteroid use.
     <break/>Building a number of TCM hospitals nationwide and developing TCM.
    </td>
    <td align="left">Defining the importance of TCM and reintegrated treatment with TCM and Western medicine.
     <break/>TCM was effective in decreasing mortality, suppressing progression to severe disease, and curing mild or moderate cases.
     <break/>Shaping a protocol to use a batch of effective TCM formulas.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Lesson 9</td>
    <td align="left">There is no FDA-approved vaccine for SARS.</td>
    <td align="left">Accelerating the development of vaccines.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Lesson 10</td>
    <td colspan="2" align="left">Virus has no borders.
     <break/>Viral infection occurs regardless of socioeconomic status.
     <break/>Human life is not simply a number.
     <break/>Medical personnel are the backbone fighting against COVID-19 and SARS by saving patients' lives and providing recommendations for epidemic control.
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn>
   <p>SARS: Severe acute respiratory syndrome; COVID-19: Coronavirus disease 2019; CT: Computed tomography; TCM: Traditional Chinese medicine; FDA: Food and Drug Administration.</p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
