<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A retrospective analysis of all reported cases of APM occurring from 1939 to 1972 was undertaken. The data were derived from several sources. First, a review was conducted on available published studies, which appeared since 1935. The major source of these studies was obtained from the epidemiological publications of the League of Nations Health Organization, the World Health Organization, and other studies.[
 <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
 <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
 <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
 <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>
 <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
 <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
 <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
 <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>
 <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
 <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] To track the occurrence of APM in Trinidad both before and after the 1972 epidemic, data were obtained from the Annual Statistical Reports published by the Ministry of Health, from 1972 to 2000. In compliance with the regional polio elimination strategies, Latin American and Caribbean (LAC) countries must report and investigate all cases of acute flaccid paralysis (AFP) in children aged &lt;15 years. AFP is formally defined in LAC as any flaccid paralysis with acute onset for any reason other than severe trauma.[
 <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
 <xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] The LAC countries also use standardized definitions for polio and clinical and laboratory criteria for the disease's differential diagnosis. A stool specimen is required to test for poliovirus.[
 <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
 <xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
 <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] Simple univariate statistics were used. We report mainly counts of disease occurrence and deaths and were applicable rates.
</p>
