<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The bat neuraminidases (NAs) are structurally similar to classical NAs but lack conserved amino acids for SA binding or cleavage (Li et al., 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Zhu et al., 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Moreover, unlike classical NAs, they display no enzymatic activity (Garcia-Sastre, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Carnell et al., 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), have a dispensable role in viral entry (Hoffmann et al., 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Maruyama et al., 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Giotis et al., 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) and their function is not yet elucidated. Recent studies demonstrated that the passage of reverse-genetics-generated H18N11 virus in cell cultures, accumulates mutations in the N11 protein that increase virus titers in culture and may enhance organ tropism 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> (Zhong et al., 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Ciminski et al. demonstrated by utilizing a chimeric bat influenza virus (PR8-H18N11) that viruses encoding the full-length N11 protein exhibited a growth advantage over viruses that encode a truncated protein version and also showed that N11 is essential for viral transmission (Ciminski et al., 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2019b</xref>). Another study showed that the N10 protein facilitates heterosubtypic (H5 and H7) influenza hemagglutinin-bearing pseudotype release in the absence of another source of neuraminidase, indicating a possible role of N10 in viral release (Carnell et al., 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). It has been proposed that N11 downregulates MHC-II, thereby facilitating virion release but mechanistic data for such function is as yet missing (Ciminski et al., 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2019b</xref>). There is no evidence that a functional balance exists between bat HAs and NAs although it is possible that the proteins coordinate their actions. Despite the recent progress in our understanding, the exact function of bat NAs remains an enticing mystery.
</p>
