<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Based on the best hits of the BLASTx search, the following sequences of RNA-dependent RNA polymerases (RdRp) from the reference virus genomes of the family Reoviridae, listed by their Genbank numbers, were chosen for phylogenetic analysis: AF291684, AF389452, AF389463, MH085099, MH0850100, MH0850101, DQ087277, KJ191105, KM978416, KM978427, KM978428, KM978429, KP217035, KR704195, KX509952, KX884614, MF161423 and KX884635. Alignment was conducted in Mafft software online [
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-11-00147" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] and analyzed by the identity matrix tool of BioEdit 7.0.5.3 software [
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-11-00147" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Detailed information of the strains chosen are listed in 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-viruses-11-00147">Supplementary Table S1</xref>. A maximum likelihood (ML) tree was constructed using PhyML software [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-11-00147" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Branch support values of the ML tree were assessed using the approximate likelihood ratio test (aLRT). The General Time Reversible (GTR) model and gamma distribution were selected according to the Bayesian information criterion (BIC) implemented in the jModeltest software [
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-11-00147" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The evolutionary history was inferred by using the Maximum Likelihood method and the General Time Reversible model. Estimated GTR frequencies were A:0.3434, G:0.1692, T:0.1988, C:0.2886, and the transition rates were AC:1.3930, AG:2.5688, AT:1.1758, CG:1.3281, CT:2.9047, GT:1.0000. A discrete Gamma distribution was used to model evolutionary rate differences among sites (five categories (+G, parameter = 1.6232)). Selection of the best-fit nucleotide model was performed using the Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC). The lowest BIC scores model that was considered to describe the substitution pattern the best was GTR + gamma distribution (BIC score; 113841.75). The tree with the highest log likelihood (−56589.22) is shown. Initial tree(s) for the heuristic search were obtained automatically by applying Neighbor-Joining algorithms to an instantaneous matrix of pairwise distances estimated using the Maximum Likelihood (ML) approach, and then selecting the topology with the superior log likelihood value. The tree is drawn to scale, with branch lengths measured in the number of substitutions per site. This analysis involved 25 nucleotide sequences. There was a total of 5389 positions in the final dataset.
</p>
