<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The identification of a stable mutator phenotype and possible dedicated RNA-dependent RNA-proofreading complex is significant for several reasons. The availability of the M-ExoN and S-ExoN mutant viruses constitutes a unique system to directly study the impact of profoundly decreased replication fidelity and increased diversity on replication and pathogenesis of RNA viruses. The use of both traditional di-deoxy (Sanger) and ultradeep (Solexa) sequencing in conjunction with virus passage and persistent infection will allow establishment of new models for understanding the range and limitations on diversity and mutational load and will aid in developing tool sets for evaluating, comparing and annotating sequence diversity across RNA virus genomes. Massive sequence annotation and analysis during different stages of acute infection (intracellular, virion), as well as over time (passage, persistent infection) will allow mapping of genetic regions highly tolerant or resistant to change and to define potential epistatic interaction networks not predictable by other approaches as well as conserved across the Coronaviridae. Passage and sequencing of ExoN mutator viruses also will provide a system to rapidly generate extensive libraries of individual mutations and complete mutation sets across the genome that can be tested in individual coding or regulatory domains for effects on immune response, host range and virulence. Such studies of ExoN-generated decreased fidelity and increased diversity also represent two potentially broadly applicable strategies for live vaccine design that simultaneously attenuate and prevent reversion to virulence. Finally, the mutator viruses and studies of ExoN mutant revertants will result in important insights into the evolutionary mechanisms by which the Nidovirales acquired (or lost) the capacity for RNA proofreading, and will allow testing of the limitations of size and complexity of RNA as a replicating molecule. As such, ExoN should be considered as a high impact research target for protecting the public health against future emerging CoV diseases.</p>
