<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The size and spatial heterogeneity of the DF epidemics were probably associated with numerous UVs widely distributed across the study region with developed public transportation (e.g., many bus stops), good economic status, and a dense population. Previous studies across the entire joint Guangzhou-Foshan (GF) area have found that spatially clustered DF cases in this region are associated with its higher land urbanization level, population size, road density, and economic level (GDP per capita) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007350.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007350.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Our study found that this central region typically featured by not only impervious surfaces (including NCL and UVs) but also spatially differentiated DF epidemics on the 1 km × 1 km grid scale. Meanwhile, there was higher density of DF cases and incidence rates in UV areas than in NCL areas, and the DF epidemic was significantly positively associated with UVs’ acreage both at the grid scale and the UV level. There are two possible reasons for this. First, UVs, as a type of informal urban settlement, provide 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> mosquitoes with a suitable environment for survival and breeding, featuring slightly lower land surface temperature than NCL areas [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007350.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], especially in the summer months. Second, the denser population in UVs and its flowing traits were two core impetuses of UVs’ influences on the DF epidemic. In particular, UVs have a high density of low-cost accommodation rented by migrant workers from local house owners, which provided local citizens with a steady source of revenue and resulted in a large floating population [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007350.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007350.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. This increases the probability of being bitten by mosquito vectors, causing rapid transmission of this disease. DF is also more frequent within a specific 200–300 m radius around UVs, which is probably determined by the mosquitoes’ maximum flying range of approximately 300 m [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007350.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007350.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Thus, it can be seen that widely distributed UVs have an important influence on the DF epidemic, not only within the specific UV areas but also within their surrounding zones, crucially associated with the severity and obvious spatial disparities in DF incidence across the central region in Guangzhou City. We cautiously suggest that both UVs and their surrounding zones should receive considerable focus during DF epidemics.
</p>
