<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Use of generalized additive models has revealed that associations between DF infection and GDP were nonlinear at the township level across the Pearl River Delta [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007350.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Our earlier investigation found that GDP had a weak but spatially differentiated correlation with DF infection across the GF area [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007350.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. We found similar in this study, employing GWR models at a fine spatial scale (1 km × 1 km) and taking three spatially differentiated variables (UVs and bus stops as special influencing factors, as well as GDP) into consideration. GDP had a clear protective effect in the west zones (including in Liwan, most of Yuexiu, and west Haizhu) where there were more serious DF epidemics and larger areas of UV. This effect is likely related to the UVs in these areas being surrounded by NCL, with a higher economic status and the better promotion of public health services (e.g., education and publicity about hygiene) in these well-developed zones. On the contrary, GDP tended to be a risk factor for DF transmission in the east zones (i.e., most of Tianhe and northeast Haizhu) where there were relatively small DF outbreaks and many construction sites (categorized as unused land in this study), especially in the district of Tianhe, which is experiencing rapid economic development and urban construction. However, whether the positive correlation between GDP and DF incidence rates was related to the wide distribution of unused land needs further investigation. Nevertheless, our findings are sufficiently reasonable and detailed to infer that the influence of economic status on DF transmission was spatially differentiated. We advise that the protective influences of GDP on DF infection in Liwan and Yuexiu districts are further investigated to explore how its protective effects can be expanded to Tianhe and Haizhu districts with their growing economies.
</p>
