<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">The emergence of influenza viruses resistant to anti-influenza drugs is a threat to global public health. The Korea Centers for Disease Control and Prevention operates the Korea Influenza and Respiratory Viruses Surveillance System (KINRESS) to monitor epidemics of influenza and Severe Acute Respiratory Infection (SARI) to identify mutated influenza viruses affecting drug resistance, pathogenesis, and transmission.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p id="Par2">Oropharyngeal swab samples were collected from KINRESS and SARI during the 2018–2019 season. The specimens confirmed influenza virus using real-time RT-PCR on inoculated MDCK cells. HA and NA sequences of the influenza viruses were analyzed for phylogeny and mutations. Neuraminidase inhibition and hemagglutination inhibition assays were utilized to characterize the isolates.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p id="Par3">Two A(H1N1)pdm09 isolates harboring an H275Y substitution in the neuraminidase sequence were detected in patients with acute hematologic cancer. They had prolonged respiratory symptoms, with the virus present in the respiratory tract despite oseltamivir and peramivir treatment. Through the neuraminidase inhibition assay, both viruses were found to be resistant to oseltamivir and peramivir, but not to zanamivir. Although hemagglutinin and neuraminidase phylogenetic analyses suggested that the 2 A(H1N1)pdm09 isolates were not identical, their antigenicity was similar to that of the 2018–19 influenza vaccine virus.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p id="Par4">Our data indicate the utility of monitoring influenza-infected immunocompromised patients in general hospitals for the early detection of emerging neuraminidase inhibitor-resistant viruses and maintaining continuous laboratory surveillance of patients with influenza-like illness in sentinel clinics to monitor the spread of such new variants. Finally, characterization of the virus can inform the risk assessment for future epidemics and pandemics caused by drug-resistant influenza viruses.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
