<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The increasing incidence, severity and size of EBOD outbreaks highlight the importance of developing and standardizing diagnostic tools for EBOD rapid diagnosis and post-epidemic surveillance. The most devastating EBOD outbreak to date, the West African outbreak, prompted the development of diagnostic assays that can address limited laboratory infrastructure, resources and personnel in affected areas and fulfill requirements for point-of-care (POC) rapid diagnostic tests (RDTs), including real-time reverse-transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) based on Cepheid GeneXpert technology [
 <xref rid="B15-viruses-11-00678" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-11-00678" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and antigen detection lateral flow immunoassays [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-11-00678" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-11-00678" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. While Ebola virus (EBOV) POC and RDTs molecular and virological methods have been successfully developed and evaluated, serological diagnosis, disease serosurveillance and control programs and monitoring of the immune responses in vaccines remain a challenging subject due to unavailability of validated serological assays. Collection of diagnostic specimens after viral clearance and inappropriate transportation methods and storage conditions may negatively impact molecular assays [
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-11-00678" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-11-00678" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] making serology testing an important tool in the public health response to outbreaks occurring in remote locations where limited resources are available. Serological tests such as enzyme-linked immunosorbent assays (ELISA) are used for the detection of antibody responses to antigens associated with filovirus infection or vaccination. Establishment of such assays is dependent on the production of high quality immunoreagents [
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-11-00678" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Recombinant antigen technology offers the advantage of development and production under biosafety level two conditions.
</p>
