<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The efficiency of virus seed transmission was estimated as per cent of infected seeds that gave rise to infected progeny per plant. Accordingly, we measured virus seed transmission to seedlings. For each replicate, 100 seeds were washed in a 10% household bleach solution (4% active chlorine) to ensure that any viral infection that occurred was not simply the result of virus presence on the seed coat, but rather the result of embryonic infection. Seeds were kept in this solution for 5 min and washed three time in sterile distilled water. Then, seeds were placed in Petri dishes containing Murashige and Skoog medium, stratified for three days at 4 °C, and germinated in a growth chamber at 22 °C, under 16 h light (intensity: 120–150 mol s/m
 <sup>2</sup>). Following [
 <xref rid="B67-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], fifteen days post-stratification seedlings were pooled in groups of three for a total of 33 groups per replicate. These groups were tested for TuMV or CMV via qRT-PCR as above. Since we knew the proportion of samples that tested negative, we used a Poisson distribution to estimate the probability that more than one seedling would test positive in the same sample. Per cent of virus-infected seeds (
 <italic>ST</italic>) was then estimated using the expression reported by [
 <xref rid="B68-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm1">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mi>p</mi>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mn>1</mn>
     <mo>−</mo>
     <msup>
      <mrow>
       <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
       <mrow>
        <mn>1</mn>
        <mo>−</mo>
        <mfrac>
         <mi>y</mi>
         <mi>n</mi>
        </mfrac>
       </mrow>
       <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
      </mrow>
      <mfrac>
       <mn>1</mn>
       <mi>k</mi>
      </mfrac>
     </msup>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>, where 
 <italic>p</italic> is the probability of virus transmission by a single seed, 
 <italic>y</italic> is the number of positive samples, 
 <italic>n</italic> is the total number of samples assayed (
 <italic>n</italic> = 33), and 
 <italic>k</italic> is the number of seedlings per sample (
 <italic>k</italic> = 3).
</p>
