<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A socioscope survey conducted by Samuel G. and colleagues, in 2018 [
 <xref rid="B22-ijerph-17-06341" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], studied the importance of knowledge in order to face epidemics and pandemics, particularly Zika virus outbreak disasters. Zika virus (ZIKV) is a single-stranded RNA virus of the Flaviviridae family, transmitted primarily through the bite of an infected Aedes species mosquito. The first large outbreak of the Zika virus occurred on the island of Yap in 2007, when an estimated 73% of the population contracted the virus. Another epidemic flood appeared in Brazil in 2015. However, Zika virus had already been discovered and isolated in 1947 [
 <xref rid="B23-ijerph-17-06341" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. In this socioscope survey, there were 224 participants with a mean age of 33 (SD ± 11.6), 77% female and 24% of them pregnant. The majority of the sample (98%; 213/217) were unable to identify all of the symptoms associated with acute Zika virus infection and all modes of transmission (97%; 213/219). The most concerning aspect of Zika virus for 46% of the sample (91/200) was the risk of disabilities to babies, and risk of sexual transmission (25%; 49/200). Most participants (80%; 165/207) believe that Zika virus was an important issue in their community, a quarter (25%; 51/201) of all participants and 36% (16/45) of pregnant participants thought that a person who had Zika virus, and their family, would face stigmatization. Similarly, 30.2% (63/197) of all, and 46% (20/44) of pregnant participants indicated that if a woman had a baby with microcephaly or another disability, she would be stigmatized because of the child. The results suggest that while the majority of participants heard of Zika prior to this survey, there are gaps in knowledge and information regarding multiple aspects of the Zika virus, including transmission risks, prevention methods, and symptoms. Following these arguments, the population can be harmed by the disease itself, but also by stigmatization and discrimination, enforced by prejudice and low levels of knowledge. In fact, other research noticed a powerful relation between knowledge and stigmatization (i.e., Milin et al., 2016 [
 <xref rid="B24-ijerph-17-06341" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], in their studies on mental illness and stigma, and Herek et al., 2005 [
 <xref rid="B25-ijerph-17-06341" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] in “HIV-Related Stigma and Knowledge in the United States”). Raising awareness of the risks coming from chronic, epidemic, or mental illness, and from new infectious diseases, will help promote social recommended treatment regimens and lower levels of discrimination (i.e., [
 <xref rid="B26-ijerph-17-06341" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-17-06341" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]).
</p>
