<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>China and Italy first, and subsequently many other countries in the world, have currently closed all schools, from primary nurseries to universities. This choice was based on the concern for aggregation and not on scientific evidence of a child-to-child transmission. Further information on transmission dynamics are needed, as well as a good understanding of the real burden of SARS-CoV-2 infection in children, in order to improve our screening practices. Children in high-burden areas should be tested and results correlated with their recent medical history as well as with infectious status of close contacts, in order to understand how and how long they shed the virus. Moreover, the better knowledge of the pediatric SARS-CoV-2 infection can clarify the underlying mechanisms that lead children to develop paucysymptomatic disease; this, in turn, can help researchers in findings novel therapeutic strategies against viral infections in general, and COVID-19 in particular. Recenlty, Spanish researchers evaluated a large series of children evaluated in 30 tertiary hospitals during the first 2 weeks of the epidemic in Spain (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Although they found that only 41 of the 4,695 confirmed cases (0.8%) were children younger than 18 years of age, they only tested those evaluated in hospitals. This is an important limitation since most children are expected to be asymptomatic or have mild symptoms (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), and to know the real burden of pediatric COVID-19 and how this influences the SARS-CoV-2 diffusion, we need to test children in the community, in both high and low SARS-CoV-2 burden settings and compare results. Importantly, children should be tested with both nasopharyngeal and rectal swab, since authors state that pharyngeal and nasal swab sensitivity is as low as 32–63% (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). More importantly, serological studies are necessary to understand the real burden of pediatric COVID-19. We need to know that and stop neglecting and not considering children, this will really help in understanding epidemics in general (not only the current one) and knowledge gained will help to better manage the next one, which will come soon or later.
</p>
