<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0265">To develop nonpeptidic inhibitors that interact with the P1, P2 and P4 sites of 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup>, a new series of serine derivatives were designed by Kenichi Akaji et al. based on the tetrapeptide aldehyde Ac-Thr-Val-Cha-His-H (
 <bold>60</bold>, IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 98 nM) and Bai’s bis-cinnamoyl inhibitor (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 10.6 μM) [
 <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. First, imidazole, cyclohexyl, and hydroxyl groups, which were previously reported in the literature and exhibit potent biological activity, were linked to L-serine for the design of serine derivatives (
 <bold>61.62</bold>), as shown in 
 <xref rid="fig16" ref-type="fig">Fig. 16</xref> . However, compared with peptide inhibitor 
 <bold>83</bold>, these optimized groups did not provide good coverage of the substrate-recognition pocket of 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> (PDB code: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:3AW1" id="intref0025" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">3AW1</ext-link>), and the different binding modes of peptide inhibitors and non-peptide inhibitors with 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup>s lead to changes in the interactions between these groups and the corresponding pocket [
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. It was hypothesised that the cyclohexyl group would occupy the S2 pocket of 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup>, but contrary to the expectations, molecular mechanics calculations and docking simulations indicated that the cyclohexyl group of serine derivatives (
 <bold>61, 62</bold>) must occupy the S1 pocket of 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup>. Thus, the imidazole and hydroxyl groups of 
 <bold>61</bold> and 
 <bold>62</bold>, which are expected to interact with the S1 and S4 pockets, were not effective and thereby reduced the interaction between the inhibitor and 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup>. In addition, Bai’s inhibitor 
 <bold>63</bold> is located deep insides the S′1, S1 and S2 pockets and exhibits appropriate cinnamoyl functionalities [
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Therefore, benzoyl and aniline groups were used to molecularly dock with serine derivatives to obtain 
 <bold>64</bold>. In addition, reasonable structural transformations of the serine derivative and hybrids constructed with other functionalities were investigated. Virtual screening using GOLD software indicated that 
 <italic>N</italic>-cinnamoyl derivatives with benzoate, such as 
 <bold>64</bold> and 
 <bold>65</bold>, are suitable substructures.
</p>
