<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>High-throughput sequencing-based viral metagenomics is a powerful tool to explore known and unknown viruses existing in host animals. Recently, it has been successfully used to detect viruses in bats in North America, Africa and Asia [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], where the viromes of one frugivorous bat species, 
 <italic>E. helvum</italic> in Africa, and several insectivorous bats were described. From our metagenomic study of paramyxovirus-positive bat samples, full-length viral genomic sequences were unable to be assembled from the clean reads. This result is similar with that of previous studies and may be due to the low quantity of the virus within samples, the short reads, and the lack of known reference sequences [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Previous studies demonstrated that protein-based comparisons are more effective than those based on nucleotides, and thus BLASTx usually identifies more suspect-viral sequences than BLASTn [
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Among the viral contigs, most of the bacterioviruses detected in this study are enterobacterial phages, suggesting the similarity between the intestinal bacterial population of bats and that of humans. Five contigs are highly similar to Moloney Murine Leukemia Virus (M-MLV), which may have resulted from contamination of RT reagents and also have been detected in previous virome analysis of insectivorous bats in China [
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Many contigs are closed to bat retrovirues, which were identified by previous studies [
 <xref rid="B38-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Furthermore, we found that many viral contigs showed equivalent or higher identity with Fowlpox virus (FPV) more than Reticuloendotheliosis virus (REV). As a prototypical member of 
 <italic>Avipoxvirus</italic>, FPV only infects non-mammalian hosts [
 <xref rid="B49-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], and there is no previous data available to indicate that bats are natural reservoirs or vectors of FPV. Previous studies show that REVs derive directly from mammalian retroviruses and integrate into FPV genomes, which become endogenous in the genome of larger and more complex DNA viruses [
 <xref rid="B50-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Thus, these FPV-like contigs were deemed as REVs and classified into unknown gammaretroviruses temporarily, and the source of FPV-like contigs in this study should be explored further.
</p>
