<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our sequence analysis indicates that majority of the vertebrate viral sequences were distinct from those previously identified in bats and were often diverse within the viral family. The novel viruses identified were classified into two viral families, 
 <italic>Retroviridae</italic> and 
 <italic>Polyomaviridae</italic>, which were also detected in previous studies [
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Retroviruses have both endogenous and exogenous forms in nature, comparing the results from this study with previous studies, metagenomic virome analysis indicated that retroviruses are the most common viral sequences found in bats, especially in 
 <italic>Hipposideridae</italic> [
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. This finding may be due to the frequent integration of retroviral genomic material into host genomes, rather than an indication of viral infection. Interestingly, the Illumina screening did not detect paramyxovirus nucleic acid, which had been detected by RT-PCR, suggesting that these viruses may be present in samples in relatively small amounts and below the sensitivity of Illumina detection. These findings highlight an important limitation of high throughput sequencing as a tool for virome characterization. Furthermore, the limited size or number of contigs generated by Illumina sequencing may necessitate follow-up with conventional PCR assays in order to obtain enough sequence to perform meaningful phylogenetic analyses [
 <xref rid="B6-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The sensitivity of high-throughput sequencing to detect viral nucleic acid is also limited if samples are not properly filtered and treated to remove host genome and other non-target nucleic acid and enrich for viral sequences. Host nucleic acid are typically present in significantly higher abundance relative to viral nucleic acid and can create background noise in the results [
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-06-02138" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. As the cost of high-throughput sequencing decreases and methods of sample preparation improve to optimize results, Illumina sequencing can be an effective tool for characterizing virus diversity in host organisms. Bats represent a massively diverse group of mammals, and as a group they have been increasingly identified as natural reservoirs for virus families such as paramyxoviruses, coronaviruses, and retroviruses, that contain zoonotic members. Emerging zoonotic bat-borne viruses, such as SARS coronavirus; Nipah and Hendra virus; and Marburg and Ebola virus; illustrate that bat viruses are capable of infecting people through various routes of transmission and in various contexts such as through domestic animals, food-borne routes, or the wildlife trade. Understanding the underlying diversity of viruses within common bat species and the types of interactions they have with people, wildlife and livestock in China may provide further insight into the risk of viral spillover, and may ultimately allow for interventions that reduce the risk of outbreaks.
</p>
