<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To date, most of the published quantitative analyses of interactions rely on statistical association between incident cases of influenza-like illness (ILI) and other infections based on regression and correlation analyses [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. A major methodological challenge of detecting interactions is that significant correlation between epidemics of two pathogens in surveillance data may result from either a true biological direct or indirect interaction or may be confounding as a result of the two pathogens sharing common ecological conditions (e.g., cold weather). Regression models describe simple functional links between, for example, the incidence time series, onset or peak time, or epidemic magnitude or severity. Despite their apparently simple formulation, they rely on strong statistical assumptions on the shape of the data and the association [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. Regression models are also used to calculate correlations between reported time series at different time lags. When properly controlled for confounding variables, they have proved very useful tools to detect signals of associations. Other methods have been proposed through the deployment of seasonal autoregressive integrated moving average (SARIMA) models to analyse time series [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>], Granger causality [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref093" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>], or seasonality patterns [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref094" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. However, these models do not formalize the transmission process or biological mechanism of interaction, so the interaction mechanism cannot be determined nor the strength of interaction quantified. Furthermore, this lack of mechanistic formulation prevents easily interpretable predictions that are required to support public health decision-making.
</p>
