<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="f0010">
 <label>Fig. 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>NS1-treatment of dermal fibroblasts and microvascular endothelial cells enhances synthesis and alters organization of hyaluronan, promoting adhesion of macrophages
   <italic>.</italic>
  </p>
  <p>
   <bold>(a-b)</bold> RNA was prepared from human dermal fibroblast 
   <bold>(a)</bold> and proliferative microvascular endothelial 
   <bold>(b)</bold> cultures treated or not with NS1 (3 μg/ml) for 24 h, and reversed transcribed to cDNA; real-time PCR was run using primers for 
   <italic>HAS1,2,3, HYAL1,2</italic> and 
   <italic>CD44</italic> (
   <italic>n</italic> = 3). 
   <bold>(c)</bold> Analysis of hyaluronan content in conditioned media of fibroblasts (upper panel) and endothelial cells (lower panel) treated or not with NS1 (n = 3). 
   <bold>(d-g)</bold> Immunofluorescence of untreated and NS1-treated fibroblasts 
   <bold>(d and f)</bold> and endothelial cells 
   <bold>(e and g)</bold>, exposed to PMA-activated THP-1 human monocyte-derived macrophage-like cells 
   <bold>(f and g)</bold> or not 
   <bold>(d and e)</bold>, were fixed with 3.7% formaldehyde and stained for hyaluronan (green) or CD44 (red); hyaluronan-rich cable-like structures (arrows) and dot-like structures (arrowheads) are depicted. Representative THP-1 cells among several THP-1 cells are marked by black triangles 
   <bold>(f and g)</bold>. See also Fig. S3. 
   <bold>(h and i)</bold> Fibroblasts 
   <bold>(h)</bold> and endothelial cells 
   <bold>(i)</bold> were treated with 3 μg/ml NS1 protein for 24 h, or not, in the absence or presence of Hermes1 (50 μg/ml) antibodies. Then 200,000 PMA-activated THP-1 human monocyte-derived macrophage-like cells (round cells) were co-cultured with fibroblasts and endothelial cells for 20 min, where after non-adherent cells were removed and adherent cells were stained. Ten randomly taken fields (20×) were obtained and the bound THP-1 cells were counted. Quantification of four independent experiments is depicted. In 
   <bold>(a-c)</bold> and 
   <bold>(h-i)</bold>, * 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; .05. In 
   <bold>(d-g)</bold>, scale bars, 10 μm.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text id="al0010">Fig. 2</alt-text>
 <graphic xlink:href="gr2" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
