<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Humanized mice have provided the opportunity to study HIV entry and infection, virology, latency, and disease progression. They are good and convenient models for testing prophylactic drugs and anti-HIV antibodies. HIV infection, replication, and pathogenesis can be studied 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> using Hu-PBL-SCID mice. Human disease pathogenesis can be studied using HSCs-engrafted and BLT models. BLT models can be infected with either CCR5 or CXCR4-tropic HIV strains to study HIV mutations and how they escape from the CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T-cell response [
 <xref rid="B43-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. NOD-SCID BLT humanized mice were used to study cell-to-cell transmission and retroviral spread 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>; their results provided new insights and novel approaches for blocking the spread of viruses [
 <xref rid="B47-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. NOD-SCID BLT models have been helpful in understanding the utility of ART in decreasing the transmission of HIV from infected individuals to their partners. Studies of HIV-infected NSG-BLT mice revealed that ART significantly suppresses HIV in cervico-vaginal secretions and restores the CD4
 <sup>+</sup> and CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T-cell numbers [
 <xref rid="B48-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. A rapid rebound of viremia was also demonstrated when ART was discontinued in NSG-BLT mice [
 <xref rid="B48-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Despite the many other uses of BLT-humanized mice, the development of GVHD in these mice limited their use for HIV cure studies until the development of C57BL/6 
 <italic>Rag2
  <sup>−</sup>/
  <sup>−</sup>γc 
  <sup>−/−</sup>CD47
  <sup>−/−</sup>
 </italic> triple knockout (TKO)-BLT mice. Lavender et al. [
 <xref rid="B49-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] reported that, in TKO-BLT mice, HIV-1 latency can be maintained over unlimited periods when the mice are on ART, and quick viral recovery occurs following therapy removal. Compared to other BLT models, TKO-BLT mice offer a sufficient time to investigate the effects of extended periods of ART (15–18 weeks) on the latent reservoir and it delays in recrudescence in HIV-1 cure studies [
 <xref rid="B49-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. 
</p>
