<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Advancement in the technology and understanding of the usage of animal models has enabled researchers to explore the establishment of stable, integrated, and non-productive states of HIV infection in individual cells, termed HIV latency; this latency has been the primary barrier to the development of an HIV cure, and is the most studied aspect of the virus. Brooks et al. [
 <xref rid="B51-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] used SCID-hu thy/lv mice to demonstrate HIV latency by injecting HIV into human thymic organoids that develop in these animals. Following the above model and strategy, different studies have reported reconstituting many types of tissues in different humanized mice (human thymus and liver mice (Thy/Liv mice); human CD34+ HSCs (huCD34 mice), or both BLT mice). NOD/ SCID (NS), NOD/SCID IL2rgc
 <sup>−/−</sup> (NSG), or NOD/Rag1
 <sup>−/−</sup> IL2rgc 
 <sup>−/−</sup> (NRG)). A humanized mice model reconstituted with different tissues and organs appears to be an ideal model to study the effect of ART on systemic HIV infection [
 <xref rid="B52-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Upon ART treatment, huCD34 and BLT humanized mice (
 <xref rid="viruses-11-00252-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>) tissues reconstituted with human hematopoietic lineages resulted in the repression of viral replication, reduction in plasma viral RNA (vRNA) below the detection limit, and maintainence or preservation of the CD4+ T-cell counts [
 <xref rid="B45-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. However, ART could not absolutely remove HIV infection, and the presence of latent viruses has been demonstrated in huCD34-NSG humanized mouse models [
 <xref rid="B46-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. The newer generation of T-cell-only mice (TOM) or myeloid-only mice (MOM), developed by reconstituting specific hematopoietic cell lineages, allows investigators to study the individual contribution of T-cells or macrophages to HIV persistence 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. NSG-hu thy/liv mice were generated by implanting human fetal thymus and liver tissues under the kidney capsule. They are scientifically reconstituted with T-cells alone and not with any other lymphoid lineages like monocytes/macrophages, B cells, or DCs. These mice were susceptible to HIV-1 infection and did not develop any signs of GVHD. Following combination ART, HIV latent reservoirs and resting CD4+ T-cells were observed [
 <xref rid="B58-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. This clearly indicates that TOM humanized models can be used to study HIV latency. In addition to studies with these models, there are reports suggesting that macrophages can serve as HIV-1 reservoirs [
 <xref rid="B58-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. ART treatment of HIV-infected MOM mice suggested that the half-life of the infected macrophages from MOM mice is shorter than that of infected T-cells in BLT mice [
 <xref rid="B60-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. The seemingly unlimited ability to transplant human immune cells into immunodeficient mice has led to the development of a wide array of techniques and assays. One prominent example is the 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> viral outgrowth assay that quantifies the latent HIV reservoir. This assay not only validates the results of 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> latent viral detection, but also quantifies the viral content with a greater sensitivity [
 <xref rid="B61-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Improvements with humanized mice are endless. Satheesan et al. [
 <xref rid="B63-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] used a human HSC-engrafted NSG humanized model (hu-NSG) to investigate and demonstrate HIV latency 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. They demonstrated the ability of HIV-infected human cells from HIV-infected hu–NSG mice on combinatorial antiretroviral therapy (cART) to act as a latent HIV reservoir. This model is an attractive alternative to humanized BLT mice and SCID-hu-thy/liv mice, which require the surgical manipulation and reconstitution of immune cells and tissues models to study HIV latency and latent T-cell reservoirs [
 <xref rid="B63-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Thus, mice models have immensely contributed to the improved understanding of HIV pathogenesis, persistence, prophylactic and therapeutic intervention; they could be a vital tool in the eradication of HIV.
</p>
