<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The high mortality rate of EBOV infection underscores the urgent need for an effective EBOV vaccine. A number of EBOV vaccine approaches have been explored in past studies, many of these vaccine strategies have been shown to be able to protect vaccinated animals against lethal EBOV challenge in small laboratory animal models with various efficacies (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Marzi and Feldmann, 2014</xref>). Moreover, promising results have also been obtained with viral vector-based vaccine strategies in the NHP model for protection against lethal EBOV challenge, which include recombinant adenovirus replicons (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Sullivan et al., 2006</xref>), VSV (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Jones et al., 2005</xref>), parainfluenza virus (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Bukreyev et al., 2007</xref>), Rabies virus (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Blaney et al., 2013</xref>), VRP (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Herbert et al., 2013</xref>), as well as a replication defective EBOV (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Marzi et al., 2015</xref>) vaccines. In addition to viral vector-based vaccines, EBOV virus-like particles (VLPs) and other protein-based subunit vaccines have been shown to induce protective immune responses against lethal EBOV infection of NHPs (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Warfield et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Swenson et al., 2008</xref>). Of these, recombinant adenovirus replicons and recombinant VSV based vaccines have been evaluated in a number of Phase I clinical trials and shown to be safe and immunogenic (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Ewer et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Regules et al., 2017</xref>). More recently, a Phase III clinical trial was conducted in Guinea with a the recombinant VSV-based vaccine that expresses EBOV GP, and this vaccine was found to be highly effective in preventing EBOV infection of people with high risks to EBOV infections (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Henao-Restrepo et al., 2015</xref>). The success of the recombinant VSV/EBOV vaccine in the Phase III trial showed that an effective vaccine can control the EBOV epidemics. Nonetheless, the efficacy of viral vector-based EBOV vaccines may be hampered by the pre-existing immunity in the affected area to these viral vectors. Further, immunization by such vaccines may also induce strong immune responses against the vector and therefore dampen their ability to induce immune responses in boosting immunizations for achieving durable protection or in subsequent vaccination of high risk personnel against another filovirus in future outbreaks. Thus, development of vaccine strategies to overcome the limitations of viral vector-based vaccines is still in need.
</p>
