<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">Among the proposed mechanisms of myocardial and lung injury caused by SARS-CoV-2, there is a “cytokine storm” triggered by an imbalanced response by type 1 and type 2 T helper (Th) cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. The Notch pathway plays a major role during the differentiation and the activity of innate and adaptive immune cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Dll4/Notch signalling is an important inducer of M1 macrophage polarisation and experiments in vitro and in vivo have shown that inhibition of the Notch by GSI or by anti-Dll4 antibodies leads to a dampening of the inflammation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. In macrophages, Notch1 directly binds to interleukin (IL)-6 promoter in response to interferon (IFN)-γ and positively regulates IL-6 production [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. It is important to underline that IL-6, in turn, increases the expression of the Notch ligand Dll1, thus amplifying the Notch signalling and establishing a positive feedback loop that promotes the further production of IL-6 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. In Th cells, Notch signalling triggered by Dll1,4 ligands promotes the production of inflammatory Th1/Th17 cytokines, whereas Jagged1 suppresses IL-6-induced Th17 activation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>] (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). A multicentre randomised controlled trial to test a monoclonal antibody against the IL-6 receptor (tocilizumab, Roche) in patients with COVID-19 pneumonia and elevated IL-6 has been conducted in China with promising results (ChiCTR2000029765). Based on these results, a phase II clinical trial to test the efficacy of tocilizumab in 330 Italian patients with COVID-19 pneumonia has been approved by the Italian Medicines Agency (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.agenziafarmaco.gov.it/en" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.agenziafarmaco.gov.it/en</ext-link>) and a phase III clinical trial enrolling 330 patients globally has been announced in the US (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.roche.com/media/releases/med-cor-2020-03-19.htm" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.roche.com/media/releases/med-cor-2020-03-19.htm</ext-link>). In addition, other strategies have been attempted to reduce the cytokine storm. CytoSorb is an extracorporeal cytokine adsorber and, according to the manufacturers, over 65 patients with severe COVID-19 have been treated with CytoSorb in China, Italy and Germany (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cytosorb-therapy.com/en/covid-19" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://cytosorb-therapy.com/en/covid-19</ext-link>). However, data on the effectiveness of this approach are not yet available. 
</p>
