<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Viruses</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Viruses</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">viruses</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Viruses</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1999-4915</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v11050449</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">viruses-11-00449</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Structure and Hierarchy of Influenza Virus Models Revealed by Reaction Network Analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>Stephan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-viruses-11-00449">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-viruses-11-00449">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7090-8717</contrib-id><name><surname>H&#x000f6;lzer</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-viruses-11-00449">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4-viruses-11-00449">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6375-6441</contrib-id><name><surname>Lamkiewicz</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-viruses-11-00449">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4-viruses-11-00449">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9909-8068</contrib-id><name><surname>di Fenizio</surname><given-names>Pietro Speroni</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-viruses-11-00449">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6550-378X</contrib-id><name><surname>Al Hwaeer</surname><given-names>Hassan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af5-viruses-11-00449">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marz</surname><given-names>Manja</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-viruses-11-00449">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4-viruses-11-00449">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>Stefan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af6-viruses-11-00449">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2541-6745</contrib-id><name><surname>Dittrich</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-viruses-11-00449">2</xref><xref rid="c1-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7773-0122</contrib-id><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>Bashar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4-viruses-11-00449">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af6-viruses-11-00449">6</xref><xref rid="c1-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-viruses-11-00449"><label>1</label>Ernst-Abbe University of Applied Sciences Jena, Carl-Zeiss-Promenade 2, 07745 Jena, Germany; <email>stephan.peter@eah-jena.de</email></aff><aff id="af2-viruses-11-00449"><label>2</label>Bio Systems Analysis Group, Department of Mathematics and Computer Science, University of Jena, Ernst-Abbe-Platz 2, 07743 Jena, Germany; <email>pietros@gmail.com</email></aff><aff id="af3-viruses-11-00449"><label>3</label>RNA Bioinformatics and High-Throughput Analysis, Friedrich Schiller University Jena, Leutragraben 1, 07743 Jena, Germany; <email>martin.hoelzer@uni-jena.de</email> (M.H.); <email>Kevin.Lamkiewicz@uni-jena.de</email> (K.L.); <email>manja@uni-jena.de</email> (M.M.)</aff><aff id="af4-viruses-11-00449"><label>4</label>European Virus Bioinformatics Center, Leutragraben 1, 07743 Jena, Germany</aff><aff id="af5-viruses-11-00449"><label>5</label>Mathematics and Computer Applications Department, Al-Nahrain University, Al-Jadriya, Baghdad 10072, Iraq; <email>hassan1167@yahoo.com</email></aff><aff id="af6-viruses-11-00449"><label>6</label>Chair of Bioinformatics, Matthias-Schleiden-Institute, University of Jena, Ernst-Abbe-Platz 2, 07743 Jena, Germany; <email>stefan.schu@uni-jena.de</email></aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-viruses-11-00449"><label>*</label>Correspondence: <email>peter.dittrich@uni-jena.de</email> (P.D.); <email>bashar.ibrahim@uni-jena.de</email> (B.I.); Tel.: +49-3641-9-49585 (P.D. &#x00026; B.I.)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>449</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2019 by the authors.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>Licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland. This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY) license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Influenza A virus is recognized today as one of the most challenging viruses that threatens both human and animal health worldwide. Understanding the control mechanisms of influenza infection and dynamics is crucial and could result in effective future treatment strategies. Many kinetic models based on differential equations have been developed in recent decades to capture viral dynamics within a host. These models differ in their complexity in terms of number of species elements and number of reactions. Here, we present a new approach to understanding the overall structure of twelve influenza A virus infection models and their relationship to each other. To this end, we apply chemical organization theory to obtain a hierarchical decomposition of the models into chemical organizations. The decomposition is based on the model structure (reaction rules) but is independent of kinetic details such as rate constants. We found different types of model structures ranging from two to eight organizations. Furthermore, the model&#x02019;s organizations imply a partial order among models entailing a hierarchy of model, revealing a high model diversity with respect to their long-term behavior. Our methods and results can be helpful in model development and model integration, also beyond the influenza area.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>chemical organization theory</kwd><kwd>influenza A</kwd><kwd>virus dynamics modeling</kwd><kwd>complex networks analysis</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-viruses-11-00449"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Influenza is an infectious respiratory disease, annually infecting 5&#x02013;15% of the human population and causing epidemics that result in 3&#x02013;5 million severe cases with 300,000&#x02013;500,000 deaths each year [<xref rid="B1-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The annual recurrence of epidemics is caused by the continuous alteration of seasonal influenza viruses, which enables them to efficiently escape the immune system even due to previous infections or vaccinations [<xref rid="B2-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The major burden of disease in humans is caused by seasonal influenza A (IAV) and influenza B viruses, causing symptoms varying from mild respiratory disease characterized by fever, sore throat, headache and muscle pain to severe and in some cases lethal pneumonia and secondary bacterial infections [<xref rid="B3-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>The long-term spread of influenza viruses in the human population and the acute nature of influenza virus epidemics is driven by the global movement of these viruses. Differences in seasonal epidemics caused by influenza viruses are mainly driven by differences in the rates of virus evolution. The single-stranded RNA segments of influenza viruses, which are located inside the virus particle (or virion), evolve rapidly and thus can escape the host&#x02019;s immune response very efficiently.</p><p>Several ordinary differential equations (ODEs) models have been developed to provide insight into within-host dynamics of influenza A virus infections (for reviews, see [<xref rid="B4-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B5-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="B6-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B8-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]). These models work in a time scale of days and describe the concentration dynamics of target cells, immune system components, viral load, and sometimes co-infecting pathogens. The models differ in terms of complexity and state space dimensions, which are between 3 and 15 for the models examined here. While the low-dimensional models can be analyzed completely and in a straightforward way (e.g., by calculating their fixed points and stability analysis), the characterization of the entire behavioral spectrum of complex models is more difficult (see for example [<xref rid="B9-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]).</p><p>Here, we present an approach to understand the overall structure of these models that allows them to be related to each other in a simple way. To this end, we apply chemical organization theory [<xref rid="B10-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B11-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] to obtain a hierarchical decomposition of each model into chemical organizations. A chemical organization is a sub-set of species (i.e., dimensions or model components, like, uninfected cells or viruses) that cannot generate any other species (property of closure) and that can self-maintain its own species, i.e., any species consumed by a process within the organization can be regenerated by a process within the organization. The organizations of an ODE model are rigorously related to its long-term dynamics in the following way: Given a stationary state of the ODE model, the set of species with strictly positive concentrations must be an organization [<xref rid="B10-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The same is true for all practically relevant periodic and chaotic attractors [<xref rid="B12-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Note that the advantage of this approach is that decomposition into organizations is based solely on the model structure (i.e., reaction rules) and thus is independent of kinetic details, like rate constants. The relation between measured data, ODE model, and organizations is depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f001">Figure 1</xref>.</p><p>By applying the method to twelve models of influenza A virus infection, we found different types of model structures ranging from two to eight organizations. Furthermore, the models&#x02019; organizations imply a partial order among models. The resulting hierarchy of models can help to select a suitable model for certain data or serve as a framework for further model development.</p><p>We provide reaction network files for all models and a software tool for computing their organizations (<uri xlink:href="https://github.com/stephanpeter/orgsflu">https://github.com/stephanpeter/orgsflu</uri>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-viruses-11-00449"><title>2. Materials and Methods: Procedure for the Organizational Analysis</title><p>To illustrate our method, we follow a basic ODE model of influenza dynamics, namely the target cell limited model by Baccam et al. [<xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], called Baccam Model in the following. Note that we refer throughout this paper to a model by the first author&#x02019;s name of the respective publication.</p><p>The Baccam Model is based on in vivo experimental data and contains three variables: the number of susceptible and uninfected target (epithelial) cells <italic>T</italic>, the number of infected cells <italic>I</italic>, and the number of infectious-viral titer <italic>V</italic>. The dynamical behavior of the variables is given by the ODEs shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f002">Figure 2</xref>a. That is, target cells become infected and thus converted to infected cells at a rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm1"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, infected cells die spontaneously at rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm2"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, virus proliferates at a rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm3"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and dies at a rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm4"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The parameters <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm5"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm6"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic>p</italic> and <italic>c</italic> are, as usual, positive real numbers (cf. [<xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] for actual values).</p><p>Throughout this paper, the following coloring scheme for particular classes of species is used to improve readability:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><styled-content style="color: #0000FF">Uninfected (target) cells or those resistant/refractory to infection are marked in blue, e.g., <italic>T</italic></styled-content>.</p></list-item><list-item><p><styled-content style="color: #FE2E9A">Infected cells, partially or latently infected cells, and viruses are marked in magenta, e.g., <italic>I</italic> and <italic>V</italic></styled-content>.</p></list-item><list-item><p><styled-content style="color: #01DF01">Species belonging to the active immune response are marked in green</styled-content>. It is worth noting that the first two models analyzed in this paper [<xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="B14-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] do not explicitly have immune system components.</p></list-item><list-item><p><styled-content style="color: #FE9A2E">Bacterial co-infection species are marked in orange</styled-content>. These species are only occurring in Smith&#x02019;s model [<xref rid="B15-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><p>Text referring to any other species is marked in black, e.g., transient target cell states, passive immune system, or dead cells.</p></list-item></list></p><p>For simplicity, the models&#x02019; variable names also denote the related <italic>species</italic>. For example, <italic>V</italic> denominates not only the number of viruses in the ODE model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f002">Figure 2</xref>a), but also the virus itself (e.g., <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f002">Figure 2</xref>b).</p><sec id="sec2dot1-viruses-11-00449"><title>2.1. Deriving the Reaction Network from the ODE System</title><p>In a first step, we need to obtain the reaction network underlying the ODE model. A reaction represents, for example, a cell infection by a virus, the generation of new viruses from an infected cell or the spontaneous death of a cell. The reaction rules can be derived from the ODEs in a straightforward way [<xref rid="B16-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. This step can also be performed by an online tool presented by Soliman and colleagues [<xref rid="B16-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Note that in modeling one first creates the network and then derives the ODEs. For our analysis, we have to take the other direction.</p><p>For this purpose, we have to investigate the kinetic terms (kinetic laws) of the ODE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f002">Figure 2</xref>a):<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>The term <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm7"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the reaction <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm8"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, which in turn denotes the transformation of an uninfected target cell <italic>T</italic> to an infected cell <italic>I</italic> catalysed by the virus <italic>V</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The terms <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm9"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm10"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represent reactions <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm11"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02205;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm12"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02205;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> which are the outflow of infected cells <italic>I</italic> resp. virus <italic>V</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The term <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm13"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the reaction <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm14"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> which is the production of viruses <italic>V</italic> catalysed by infected cells <italic>I</italic>.</p></list-item></list>
The set of species <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm15"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">S</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> together with the set of reactions <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm16"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> constitute the so-called <italic>reaction network</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm17"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> associated with the model. The set of reactions together with their kinetic parameters are depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f002">Figure 2</xref>c. Note that for clarity we use different types of underlining to highlight certain recurring kinetic terms in the ODE:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><underline>Single underline</underline> for the transformation of uninfected cells into infected ones by the action of viruses.</p></list-item><list-item><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm800"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mtext>Double underline</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="true">=</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>&#x000a0;for kinetic terms involving interferon.</p></list-item></list></p><p>We call the species on the left-hand side (LHS) of a reaction <italic>R support</italic> of <italic>R</italic> and write <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm18"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, e.g., <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm19"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f002">Figure 2</xref>d). Analogously, we call the set of species occurring on the right-hand side (RHS) of a reaction <italic>R products</italic> of <italic>R</italic> and denominate this set by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm20"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, e.g., <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm21"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p>Furthermore, let us recall the <italic>stoichiometric matrix</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm22"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">N</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of a reaction network [<xref rid="B17-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The element <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm23"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in the <italic>i</italic>-th line and <italic>j</italic>-th column of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm24"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> denotes the net-production of the <italic>i</italic>-th species in reaction <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm25"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The net-production <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm26"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the difference between the number of occurrences (stoichiometric coefficient) of species <italic>i</italic> in the RHS of reaction <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm27"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> minus the number of occurrences of species <italic>i</italic> in the LHS of reaction <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm28"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. For example, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm29"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>21</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> because the second species (<italic>I</italic>) appears in the first <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm30"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> once as a reactant in the support of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm31"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (LHS) but does not appear in <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm32"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as a product (RHS). For our example in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f002">Figure 2</xref>, the stoichiometric matrix becomes:<disp-formula id="FD1-viruses-11-00449"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="mm33"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">N</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="sec2dot2-viruses-11-00449"><title>2.2. Computing the Organizations from the Reaction Network</title><p>From the reaction network, we can compute the (chemical) <italic>organizations</italic> of the model. Each organization is a subset of species that is <italic>closed</italic> and <italic>self-maintaining</italic> [<xref rid="B10-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B18-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In the following, let <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm34"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02286;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> be a subset of species and <italic>n</italic> be the total number of reactions of the reaction network (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm35"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in our example).</p><p>We call <italic>S <bold>closed</bold></italic> if and only if all reactions <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm36"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm37"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02286;</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> fulfill <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm38"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02286;</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> too [<xref rid="B10-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B18-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. This means that the products of a reaction <italic>R</italic> with support in <italic>S</italic> are also in <italic>S</italic>. In other words, no species outside of <italic>S</italic> can be produced by the reactions &#x0201c;running on&#x0201d; <italic>S</italic>. As an example, we assume <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm39"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The reactions with support in <italic>S</italic> are <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm40"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm41"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. However, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm42"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> produces species <italic>V</italic>, which is not in <italic>S</italic>. Thus, <italic>S</italic> is not closed.</p><p>We call a vector <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm43"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">v</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">R</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<italic>flux vector for S</italic> if and only if it fulfills
<disp-formula id="FD2-viruses-11-00449"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="mm44"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">v</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="" open="{" close=""><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>if</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4.pt"/><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02286;</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>if</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4.pt"/><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02288;</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
Thus, all flux vectors for <italic>S</italic> have in common that those components are strictly positive which correspond to reactions that can run on <italic>S</italic>, while all other entries are zero. As an example, consider <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm45"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> again. We know that the reactions <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm46"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm47"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> can "run on" it, i.e., they have support in <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm48"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Thus, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm49"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">v</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> or <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm50"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are example flux vectors for <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm51"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p>We call <italic>S <bold>self-maintaining</bold></italic> if and only if there exists (at least one) flux vector <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm52"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">v</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">R</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for <italic>S</italic> that fulfills
<disp-formula id="FD3-viruses-11-00449"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="mm53"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">N</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000b7;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">v</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="bold">0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
i.e., <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm54"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">N</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000b7;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">v</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for all <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm55"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02026;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <italic>n</italic> is again the total number of reactions [<xref rid="B10-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="B19-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B20-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="B21-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Roughly speaking, if <italic>S</italic> is self-maintaining, it has the potential to sustain the amount of its species above a certain level. Our example set <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm56"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is not self-maintaining because <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm57"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">N</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000b7;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">v</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for all flux vectors for <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm58"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. That is, species number 2 (the infected cells <italic>I</italic>) can not be maintained by this set.</p><p>As mentioned in the beginning of this section, we call <italic>S</italic> an <italic>organization</italic> if and only if it is both closed and self-maintaining. Clearly <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm59"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is not an organization, as it has neither of these properties. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f002">Figure 2</xref>d, the so-called <italic>Hasse diagram</italic> of organizations of this model can be seen. In it, two organizations are linked by a line if the lower one is a subset of the upper one and there is no organization in between. The Hasse diagram for the Baccam Model contains only the two organizations <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm60"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02205;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm61"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f002">Figure 2</xref>d). The superscript &#x0201c;B&#x0201d; stands for Baccam Model and with the subscripts we refer to the organizations within a model. The organization <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm62"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represents an organism without any influenza A virus infection. Note that there is no organization with all species, i.e., representing the infected body.</p></sec><sec id="sec2dot3-viruses-11-00449"><title>2.3. The Role Organizations Play in the Dynamics</title><p>Given a fixed point <italic>x</italic> of an ODE describing a reaction system, the set of species with strictly positive concentrations in <italic>x</italic> is an organization. This is shown in [<xref rid="B10-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. This in turn means that, if a subset of species is not an organization, then the system does not have a fixed point with exactly the chosen subset of species. This is not only true for fixed points but also for other attractors [<xref rid="B12-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Attractors are those states that a system approaches in the long-run and once reached never leaves anymore. Besides converging towards a fixed point, the long-term behavior can be also periodic oscillations or chaotic trajectories. In particular, it was shown that the long-term behavior of the system always tends at least to one organization [<xref rid="B12-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Thus, organizations rule the long-term behavior of such dynamical reaction system. Note that the case of a system tending towards a fixed point is included in this statement as a special case. For example, the <italic>simulation</italic> results of the Baccam model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f002">Figure 2</xref>a and Ref. [<xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]) suggest that after about two to three days the species begin to decay to finally arrive in an organization namely the empty set.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec3-viruses-11-00449"><title>3. Results and Discussion</title><p>In the literature, there exist several mathematical models of IAV dynamics that are derived from experimental data, reviewed in Refs. [<xref rid="B4-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B5-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="B6-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]). These models differ in their complexity, e.g., the number of reactions and the number of species, depending on the available experimental data used for parameter fitting and questions to be answered. For example, models can include eclipse phases, an innate immune response, or an adaptive immune response.</p><p>After having exemplified our method in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec2-viruses-11-00449">Section 2</xref> by an analysis of the basic target cell limited model by Baccam et al. [<xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], we present now the full analysis for eleven additional more detailed influenza models of IAV dynamics, with up to 15 variables (species) and 45 reactions (cf. <xref rid="viruses-11-00449-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> for an overview at the end). Note that for our analysis we abstract from kinetic details, that is, the organizations are independent of particular settings of parameter values.</p><sec id="sec3dot1-viruses-11-00449"><title>3.1. Target Cell Limited Model by Miao et al. (Miao Model, M, 2010)</title><p>The models by Miao et al. [<xref rid="B14-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] are designed to fit experimental in vivo data from mice [<xref rid="B6-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The first one ([<xref rid="B14-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-11-00449">1</xref>)) depends on measured time-series. The second one ([<xref rid="B14-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD2-viruses-11-00449">2</xref>)) is a simplified version of the first one, neglecting the terms depending on those time-series and still leading to a good fit within the first five days after infection [<xref rid="B14-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Thus, we analyze this second model (Miao Model).</p><p>Compared to the basic Baccam Model, the Miao Model (Figure 3a) has the same three variables (named differently) and one additional reaction, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm63"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. This reaction represents the self-replication of target cells <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm64"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> taking place at a rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm65"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The full set of reactions can be found in the <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-viruses-11-00449">Appendix A</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f0A2">Figure A2</xref>).</p><p>In the Hasse diagram of organizations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f003">Figure 3</xref>b), a new &#x0201c;full&#x0201d; organization <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm66"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> appears, which contains all three species. Thus, organization <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm67"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> reflects the slight difference between the two models: in the Baccam Model, uninfected target cells <italic>T</italic> are only the susceptible ones and can not increase in number, but in the Miao Model uninfected cells <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm68"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are reproduced repeatedly by the organism. Thus, in the Baccam Model, infection is limited inherently by the limited number of uninfected target cells, while in the Miao Model the limitation of an infection in time and number of infected cells and viruses depends on other mechanisms:</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot2-viruses-11-00449"><title>3.2. Target Cell Limited Model with Delayed Virus Production (Baccam II Model, Ba2, 2006)</title><p>The Baccam II Model [<xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="B22-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] contains one more species than the Baccam Model presented in the methods section above. That is, there are now <italic>two</italic> types of infected cells: those which do not yet produce viruses <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm69"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and those which actively produce viruses <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm70"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. In addition, there is only one new reaction, which transforms infected cells of type <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm71"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> into type <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm72"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> at rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm73"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f004">Figure 4</xref>a). However, the Hasse diagram of organizations remains the same when compared with the basic Baccam Model [<xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot3-viruses-11-00449"><title>3.3. Innate and (Simple) Adaptive Immune Response (Pawelek Model, P, 2012)</title><p>The Pawelek Model [<xref rid="B23-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] contains 11 parameters and was designed to fit in vivo experimental data of horses [<xref rid="B6-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The model has five variables and nine reactions. Like the basic Baccam Model, it contains uninfected target cells (<italic>T</italic>), infected cells (<italic>I</italic>), and viruses (<italic>V</italic>). Furthermore, there are two new species: interferon (<italic>F</italic>) and uninfected cells that are refractory to infections (<italic>R</italic>) because of the antiviral effect induced by interferons.</p><p>Investigating the reaction network (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f0A4">Figure A4</xref> in the <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-viruses-11-00449">Appendix A</xref>) derived from the differential equations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f005">Figure 5</xref>a), we can see that, like in the basic Baccam Model, self-replication of uninfected cells <italic>T</italic> is missing. However, due to the two new species <italic>R</italic> and <italic>F</italic>, we have five new reactions, which are neither included in the Baccam Model nor in the Miao Model. One of these five reactions is the spontaneous decay of interferon <italic>F</italic> at a rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm74"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The other four new reactions describe interactions between different species:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>The rate term <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm75"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003d5;</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the transformation of uninfected target cells to refractory cells catalysed by interferon.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The reverse shift back from refractory to simple uninfected cells is represented by the term <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm76"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Furthermore, infected cells are deleted by the action of interferon at a rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm77"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003ba;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Interferon is produced in the presence of infected cells at a rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm78"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></list-item></list></p><p>Even though we have more species and more reactions, we get the same small pattern of organizations as in the basic Baccam Model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f005">Figure 5</xref>b). Both models have in common that there is no self-replication of target cells. This might be one reason for the missing of other and bigger organizations which could contain species related to infection and/or immune response. This in turn means that, like the Baccam Model, this model implicitly treats infections and immune responses as phenomena that can only appear in a limited (transient) time span. The Hasse diagram of organizations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f005">Figure 5</xref>b) tells us that the system necessarily tends towards a state of healthiness, which is represented by the organizations <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm79"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm80"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, showing absence of infection and immune response.</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot4-viruses-11-00449"><title>3.4. A Model Including Bacterial Co-Infection (Smith Model, Sm, 2016)</title><p>The Smith Model [<xref rid="B15-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] contains 15 parameters and compared to experimental in vivo data from mice. It has five variables and 12 reactions. Like in the previous models, we have susceptible target cells (<italic>T</italic>) and viruses (<italic>V</italic>). Note that <italic>T</italic> is only consumed in this model but not produced. Contrarily to previous models, we have two kinds of infected cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm81"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm82"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) here as well as bacteria (<italic>P</italic>). Bacteria <italic>P</italic> represent <italic>bacterial co-infection</italic> during or after virus infection. Infection is modeled as a transformation of susceptible target cells <italic>T</italic> into infected cells <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm83"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> catalyzed by viruses <italic>V</italic> (see underlined terms in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f006">Figure 6</xref>a). Infected cells <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm84"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in turn spontaneously transform into <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm85"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> at rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm86"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Only infected cells <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm87"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> produce viruses <italic>V</italic> at a rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm88"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Furthermore, infected cells <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm89"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> produce viruses <italic>V</italic> together with bacteria <italic>P</italic>. Bacteria <italic>P</italic> are self-replicating (rate term <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm90"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). Viruses <italic>V</italic> are the only species influencing bacteria <italic>P</italic>.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f006">Figure 6</xref>b shows the Hasse diagram of organizations. The smallest one is the empty set. The biggest one is <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm91"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, which contains susceptible target cells <italic>T</italic> and bacteria <italic>P</italic>. It represents an organism without viral but with bacterial infection. Between those two extreme organizations, we find <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm92"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm93"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE9A2E">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Thus, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm94"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the healthy organism without any infection. <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm95"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE9A2E">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> could mark the state after a viral-bacterial co-infection: after viral infection and because of the death of all target cells as well as all viruses only bacteria remain.</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot5-viruses-11-00449"><title>3.5. Innate and Adaptive Immune Response (Handel Model, Ha, 2009)</title><p>The Handel Model [<xref rid="B24-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] contains eight parameters and was designed to fit experimental in vivo data from mice [<xref rid="B6-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B25-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. It has seven variables (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f007">Figure 7</xref>) and only 12 reactions (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f007">Figure 7</xref>a):<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><italic>Infection</italic> is catalyzed by viruses <italic>V</italic> and transforms uninfected cells <italic>U</italic> to latently infected cells <italic>E</italic> and viruses <italic>V</italic> are consumed thereby. Latently infected cells <italic>E</italic> transform into infected cells <italic>I</italic> autonomously, which in turn transform into dead cells <italic>D</italic> autonomously too. Finally, the transformation of dead cells <italic>D</italic> into non-infected cells <italic>U</italic> closes the <italic>circle</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The <italic>remaining three species V</italic>, <italic>F</italic> and <italic>X</italic> form an almost totally separate <italic>subsystem</italic> since the only interaction with the four species from the "circle" mentioned above is the catalysis of the infection by viruses <italic>V</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The <italic>interactions within the subsystem</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm96"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> consisting of viruses <italic>V</italic> and immune responses <italic>F</italic> and <italic>X</italic> are as follows:
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>&#x02013;</label><p>Viruses <italic>V</italic> catalyze the proliferation of <italic>F</italic> and <italic>X</italic>. In the Hernandez model, proliferation of interferon <italic>F</italic> is catalyzed by infected cells instead of viruses.</p></list-item><list-item><label>&#x02013;</label><p>There is no direct interaction between innate immune response <italic>F</italic> and adaptive immune response <italic>X</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><label>&#x02013;</label><p>The adaptive immune response <italic>X</italic> deletes viruses directly. Innate immune response <italic>F</italic> inhibits the self-replication of the viruses which is represented by the denominator of the fraction <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm97"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003ba;</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">F</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. We ignore the inhibition because whether the rate is zero or not is independent of <italic>F</italic>.</p></list-item></list></p></list-item></list>
The Hasse diagram <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f007">Figure 7</xref>b shows five organizations. For the first time, it contains the empty set as well as the set of all species at the same time. Between these extremes, we find <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm98"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">U</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> representing the healthy organism. The Baccam, Miao, and Pawelek models exhibit the same organization. Structurally, the Hasse diagram of the Handel Model is very similar to that of the Smith Model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f006">Figure 6</xref>b). The first reveals an autonomy of the adaptive immune response <italic>X</italic>, whereas the latter does this same for bacteria <italic>P</italic>.</p><sec><title>Temporal Dynamics</title><p>For the Handel Model, we perform dynamical simulation in order to show how the organizational hierarchy helps also to understand transient short-term behavior. We start at <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm99"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>20</mml:mn><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with an uninfected state, i.e., <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm100"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>9</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> uninfected cells. After 20 days, at <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm101"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, we add <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm102"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> virus particles. The resulting seven-dimensional trajectory in state space is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f008">Figure 8</xref>. Projecting this trajectory to organizations results in a more abstract view of the dynamics, shown as a dashed curved arrow in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f007">Figure 7</xref>b. The system starts in organization <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm103"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (uninfected organization), moves after adding virus particles at <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm104"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> into organization <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm105"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (infected organization with immune response), and drops after 37 days into organization <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm106"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (immune response active, virus absent).</p><p>The projection of a state <italic>x</italic> to an organization <italic>O</italic> follows the procedure suggested by Dittrich and Speroni d.F. [<xref rid="B10-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]: First, we generate a set <italic>S</italic> of those species whose concentration is greater than a particular threshold (here: <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm107"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). Then, we generate the closure of this set by adding all species that can be produced from the set. Finally, we take the largest organization <italic>O</italic> that is a subset of that closure. For example: At <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm108"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> by adding viruses to the system, we have <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm109"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, whose closure is the set of all species, which is also an organization, here; thus, the state at <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm110"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is projected to organization <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm111"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. At <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm112"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>60</mml:mn><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, we have <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm113"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, whose closure is again <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm114"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and the largest organization contained is <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm115"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Thus, as can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f008">Figure 8</xref>, the system state is projected to organization <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm116"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, in which it stays for <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm117"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mn>37</mml:mn><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3dot6-viruses-11-00449"><title>3.6. Innate Immune Response and Resistance to Infection (Hernandez Model, He, 2012)</title><p>The 13 parameters of the Hernandez Model [<xref rid="B26-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] were fitted to data from many different sources. The model contains seven variables and 16 reactions (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f009">Figure 9</xref>). The species refer to viruses (<italic>V</italic>), interferon (<italic>F</italic>) and natural killer cells (<italic>K</italic>) as well as four types of respiratory tract epithelial cells: healthy/uninfected (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm118"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), partially infected (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm119"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), infected (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm120"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and resistant to infection (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm121"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). Compared to the Pawelek Model, there are two qualitatively new species: partially infected cells <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm122"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and killers <italic>K</italic>.</p><p>Next, we state some remarks about the reactions:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>There is an <italic>infection</italic> reaction catalyzed by viruses like in all previous models but with one difference: during infection, healthy cells <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm123"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> first transform to <italic>partially infected</italic> cells <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm124"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and only after that they transform spontaneously to infected cells <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm125"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> at a rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm126"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Interferon</italic> catalyzes the transformation of healthy cells to resistant cells <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm127"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, like in the Pawelek Model. However, in the Pawelek Model, interferon removes infected cells. Here, interferon&#x02019;s production is catalyzed by infected cells <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm128"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> at a rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm129"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. There is no further influence of interferon on any other species.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Infected cells are removed by natural <italic>killers K</italic>, which also delete partially infected cells in this model. The production of <italic>killers K</italic> is catalyzed by infected cells <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm130"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> at a rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm131"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003a6;</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Note that here we have an constant <italic>inflow of healthy cells</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm132"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> at a rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm133"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (first differential equation). Thus, healthy cells cannot converge to zero.</p></list-item></list>
The Hasse diagram of organizations consists only of two organizations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f009">Figure 9</xref>b). For the first time, the empty set is not an organization because the empty set is not closed due to a constant inflow of healthy cells <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm134"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and killers <italic>K</italic>, represented by the reaction <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm135"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02205;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm136"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02205;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, respectively. The smallest organization <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm137"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> can be regarded as a state of healthiness. Contrarily, the second organization <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm138"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> contains all species (as in the Miao Model) and therefore can be interpreted as the infected organism exhibiting immune response to infection.</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot7-viruses-11-00449"><title>3.7. A Model with More Detailed Immune Response (Cao Model, C, 2015)</title><p>The Cao Model [<xref rid="B27-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] consists of 20 parameters and has been derived by referring to experimental data from ferrets. The model has seven variables and 26 reactions. Like in most of the previous models, we have (uninfected) target cells (<italic>T</italic>), infected cells (<italic>I</italic>), viruses (<italic>V</italic>), resistant cells (<italic>R</italic>), and interferon (<italic>F</italic>). Furthermore, there are B cells <italic>B</italic> and antibodies <italic>A</italic>.</p><p>According to the ODE shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f010">Figure 10</xref>a, <italic>B cells</italic> are only influenced by viruses: viruses support the production of B cells (rate term <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm139"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), but the more B cells that are present, the more of them are destroyed by viruses again (term: <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm140"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). B cells influence only one other species, namely antibodies <italic>B</italic>, which they produce. <italic>Antibodies A</italic> influence only one other species, namely viruses, which are destroyed by this reaction at rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm141"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Antibodies in turn are influenced by B cells positively and by viruses negatively.</p><p>There are three organizations in this model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f010">Figure 10</xref>b): the empty set, the healthy organism without any infection and without any immune response (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm142"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">T</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and the organization <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm143"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> containing all species.</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot8-viruses-11-00449"><title>3.8. Innate Immune Response and Eclipse Phase (Saenz Model, Sa, 2010)</title><p>The Saenz Model [<xref rid="B28-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] requires 12 parameters and was designed to fit experimental in vivo data from horses [<xref rid="B6-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The model contains eight variables and 12 reactions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f011">Figure 11</xref>a). There are no adaptive immune response, no dead cells, and no natural killer cells. However, the model contains viruses <italic>V</italic> and interferon <italic>F</italic>. There is an eclipse phase (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm144"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm145"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) here as well as prerefractory and refractory cells. In particular, epithelial cells are represented by six species: susceptible (<italic>T</italic>), eclipse phases (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm146"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<italic>and</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm147"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), infectious (<italic>I</italic>), prerefractory (<italic>W</italic>), and refractory (<italic>R</italic>). Thus, the new features are the inclusion of two eclipse phases and three steps for the transformation of uninfected cells to refractory cells.</p><p>The Hasse diagram of organizations is composed by four organizations: <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm148"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>: the empty set; <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm149"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">T</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>: representing a healthy organism; <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm150"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">R</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>: there is no consuming reaction for refractory cells <italic>R</italic>; <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm151"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">T</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">R</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>: also representing a healthy organism that contains refractory cells maybe as the remains of a previous infection.</p><p>The Hasse diagram is very similar to that from of the Handel Model. There are only two differences:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>The &#x0201c;full&#x0201d; organization is missing here. For sure, one of the reasons is that there is no reaction producing susceptible cells <italic>T</italic>. Thus, when viruses <italic>V</italic> or interferon <italic>F</italic> are present susceptible cells <italic>T</italic> can not survive and the &#x0201c;full&#x0201d; organization neither.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Adaptive immune response is replaced by refractory cells in the organizations here.</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="sec3dot9-viruses-11-00449"><title>3.9. Focusing on Innate and Adaptive Immunity (Hancioglu Model, Hcg, 2007)</title><p>The Hancioglu Model [<xref rid="B29-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] contains 28 parameters, 10 variables, and 44 reactions. It has not been mathematically fitted to data but has been designed to meet specific general criteria [<xref rid="B6-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The ODEs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f012">Figure 12</xref>a) describe the dynamics of the following 10 species: viruses (<italic>V</italic>), healthy cells (<italic>H</italic>), infected cells (<italic>I</italic>), interferon (<italic>F</italic>) and resistant cells (<italic>R</italic>). The remaining species are new: antigen presenting cells (<italic>M</italic>), effector cells (<italic>E</italic>), plasma cells (<italic>P</italic>) antibodies (<italic>A</italic>) and antigenic distance (<italic>S</italic>). There are no species for an eclipse phase in this model.</p><p>Looking at the reaction network (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f0A8">Figure A8</xref>), we can see again a reaction for <italic>infection</italic>, i.e., the transformation of healthy cells <italic>H</italic> into infected cells <italic>I</italic> catalyzed by viruses <italic>V</italic> at a rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm152"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (single underlined in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f012">Figure 12</xref>a). Furthermore, <italic>interferon F</italic> is produced catalytically by antigen presenting <italic>M</italic> and infected cells <italic>I</italic>, decays spontaneously at a rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm153"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and is additionally removed when converting healthy cells <italic>H</italic> into resistant cells <italic>R</italic> by the reaction <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm154"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02192;</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> at rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm155"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (double underlined in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f012">Figure 12</xref>a).</p><p>The Hancioglu Model has three organizations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f012">Figure 12</xref>b):<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>The smallest one is <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm156"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, which contains all the species responsible for the <italic>immune response</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm157"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a subset of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm158"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, which additionally contains species <italic>H</italic> and <italic>R</italic>, representing the healthy organism without infection but with the immune response turned on.</p></list-item><list-item><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm159"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the &#x0201c;full&#x0201d; organization containing all the species of the models and thus representing the organism with infection and immune response.</p></list-item></list>
Thus, all the organizations represent meaningful states of the organism. However, there is no organization that only consists of healthy cells without any infection and immune response. Note that almost all the previous models except for Hernandez have such an organization.</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot10-viruses-11-00449"><title>3.10. Model with Delay Differential Equations (Bocharov Model, Bo, 1994)</title><p>The Bocharov Model [<xref rid="B30-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] contains 49 parameters and was designed to fit experimental in vivo data from humans [<xref rid="B6-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. It includes 10 variables and 51 reactions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f0A9">Figure A9</xref>). Only here and in the Lee Model (below) we have differential equations with <italic>delay</italic>, i.e., some rates depend on variable values from the past (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f013">Figure 13</xref>a). Because the delay does not matter in a steady-state, we can also neglect the delay when analyzing the chemical organizations of a delay differential equation model.</p><p>Note that this is by far the oldest model analyzed here. The names of the variables are a bit particular when compared to those of the previously analyzed models. As in all the other models, we have viruses <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm160"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and infected cells <italic>C</italic>. Furthermore, there are destroyed epithelial cells <italic>m</italic> as in the Handel Model. All other species belong to the immune response. Note that only in this model there is no state variable for uninfected, healthy cells. Bocharov et al. represent these healthy cells implicitly by subtracting the amounts of infected-cells <italic>C</italic> and destroyed epithelial cells <italic>m</italic> from the initial total amount of target epithelial cells <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm161"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Since all the other models analyzed here have a related variable, we inserted the variable <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm162"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for uninfected cells together with its ODE to make the model comparable to the others.</p><p>Due to the fact that the majority of the species belongs to the immune response, this is the case for most of the reactions too. These species of the immune response form exactly the organization <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm163"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, only macrophages <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm164"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are missing.</p><p>Similarly to the Hancioglus model, the smallest organization <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm165"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is an organization with immune response but without infection (<italic>C</italic>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm166"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). There is only one further organization that contains only one more species than <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm167"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, namely uninfected cells <italic>U</italic>. This organization we already found in three of the previous models. However, for the first time, there is no bigger organization in this model. Thus, virus infection is necessarily transient.</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot11-viruses-11-00449"><title>3.11. Complex Dual-Compartment Model (Lee Model, L, 2009)</title><p>The Lee Model [<xref rid="B9-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] is the most complex model considered here. It contains 48 parameters and was designed with respect to experimental in vivo data from mice [<xref rid="B6-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. It has 15 variables and 37 reactions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f0A10">Figure A10</xref>). Like in the Bocharov Model, Lee et al. apply delay differential equations.</p><p>Note that this model is the only one analyzed here that distinguishes between <italic>lung compartment</italic> and <italic>lymphatic compartment</italic>. There is one species representing uninfected (healthy) cells <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm168"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">E</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">p</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and three species for modelling <italic>infection</italic>: <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm169"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathcolor="#FE2E9A"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">E</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">P</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm170"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathcolor="#FE2E9A"><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">D</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and viruses <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm171"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The remaining species belong to the <italic>immune response</italic>, colored black when naive to infection, while colored green when activated for infection.</p><p>Note that we write a species in the <italic>organizations</italic> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f014">Figure 14</xref>b in bold text, if it is &#x0201c;new&#x0201d;, that is, not contained in neither of its subset organizations. The Hasse diagram contains eight organizations. The smallest one is <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm172"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mstyle mathcolor="#0000FF"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">E</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">P</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">D</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and contains exactly the uninfected cells as well as the naive part of the immune response. The biggest organization contains all species. Between these two &#x0201c;extreme&#x0201d; organizations are six further organizations containing different parts of the activated part of the immune response.</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot12-viruses-11-00449"><title>3.12. Hierarchy of Influenza A Virus Models</title><p>In order to construct a hierarchical map of all investigated models, we characterize a model by a signature of organizations, which is a set of organization types. For example, the signature of the Handel Model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f007">Figure 7</xref>b) is the set <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm173"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02205;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">X</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">X</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">X</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. An organization type like <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm174"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">X</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> means that there is at least one organization that contains uninfected (target) cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm175"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) <italic>and</italic> species of the active immune response <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm176"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The deviation of the signatures for all models is shown in <xref rid="viruses-11-00449-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Note that we ignore species colored black. We include the empty set <italic>&#x02205;</italic> because this distinguishes models without any inflow from those that possess an inflow of some species.</p><p>Now, we can obtain a partial order among models by defining that a model A is smaller or equal to another model B (A &#x02264; B), if the signature of A is a subset of the signature of model B. For example, the Hernandez Model is smaller than the Lee Model because <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm177"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">X</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">X</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">X</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02286;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">X</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">X</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">X</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. This partial order among models leads to a hierarchical map of models, which is visualized by a Hasse-diagram in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f015">Figure 15</xref>. Note that a model A that is smaller than a model B according to this partial order can possess more species and reactions than B.</p><p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f015">Figure 15</xref>, we can see that all models have organizations with uninfected, healthy cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm178"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). There are models that furthermore have infection (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm179"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and/or immune response (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm180"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) in their organizations. There are exactly two models (Hancioglu and Hernandez Model) with immune response in all their organizations which means that these models implicitly assume immune response to be active all the time. Among the models neglecting immune response are those which have infection (Miao Model) or bacteria (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm181"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE9A2E">X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) (Smith Model) in their organizations and also those that do not (Baccam and Baccam II Model). For models involving immune response, the situation is more complex. There are those that only have healthy cells in their organizations (Pawelek and Saenz Models). This means that these models implicitly exclude infection and immune response from the long run and thus treat them as transient phenomena a priori. The Bocharov Model is the only one that exhibits only healthy cells and immune response in its organizations but no infection. The remaining five models include all kinds of species (except for bacteria of course) in their organizations.</p><p>By looking at the hierarchy of models, it becomes evident that there is space for more models. Above the Smith and Handel Model, there could be one in which virus infection as well as bacterial coinfection can be simultaneously persistent (&#x0201c;fully persistent models&#x0201d; denote such hypothetical models in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f015">Figure 15</xref>). Another extreme case would be a &#x0201c;fully-transient model&#x0201d; in which we have only transient dynamics and all species would finally tend to zero. Such a model would be the smallest one in our partial order of models (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f015">Figure 15</xref>).</p><p>The derived hierarchical map of models might be used to choose the most appropriate model for a particular domain and data set: The model should contain at least one organization for each set of species that were experimentally observed to survive in the long run. If there are several models with such organizations, the one with the smallest organizations might be chosen to provide maximum efficiency in modeling. <xref rid="viruses-11-00449-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> as well as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f015">Figure 15</xref> might guide the selection process, complementing established quantitative selection methods, such as those using the area under the viral load curve [<xref rid="B31-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec4-viruses-11-00449"><title>4. Conclusions</title><p>By analyzing twelve published IAV immune system models, we have shown that we can compute, independently of quantitative kinetic data like rate constants or kinetic laws, all chemical organizations of a typical IAV model, which provides a hierarchical decomposition of the model and an overview of its potential long-term behavior.</p><p>It turned out that the derived organizations are meaningful with respect to the model&#x02019;s domain. That is, the composition of species inside an organization can be related to a particular state of the organism, like &#x0201c;healthy&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;infected&#x0201d;, or &#x0201c;virus controlled by active immune response&#x0201d;, and it is possible to annotate organizations accordingly.</p><p>By deriving an organizational signature from a model&#x02019;s organizations, we obtained a novel classification scheme and a hierarchy of models with respect to their qualitative long-term behavior. Although the classification via organizational signature is quite coarse-grained, the analysis revealed still a high diversity of models. That is, the models have different potentiality with respect to which variables persist in the long turn and which vanish. Furthermore, the hierarchy map of models contains various empty territories, suggesting space for potential future models.</p><p>We envision as a practical use that our method and results can help to select the right model for a particular situation, to relate other models to the present ones, to obtain an overview of the potential long-term dynamics of complex models, and to support model development, for example, by providing a rapid consistency check. Note that measured long-term as well as transient data can be explained with respect to organizations, by defining a projection from a system state to an organization, as demonstrated for the Handel model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f007">Figure 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f008">Figure 8</xref>).</p><p>In addition, our approach is not limited to IAV models, but can be directly applied to other viruses in the same way since their dynamics are similarly modeled by ODEs [<xref rid="B32-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Furthermore, our approach is open to include other dynamically relevant components like treatment and vaccination strategies. Another task for future work would be to study the transient virus immune system in more detail, for example, by mapping the basin of attraction of each organization or by systematically analyzing the transition dynamics in-between organizations [<xref rid="B33-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="B34-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].</p></sec></body><back><notes><title>Author Contributions</title><p>S.P. performed the implementation and computations. S.P., P.D. and B.I. analyzed the results with the help of M.H. and K.L. S.P., P.D., and B.I. completed the analysis and final conclusions. S.P., P.D. and B.I. wrote the paper with critical input from M.H., K.L., P.S.d.F., H.A.H., M.M. and S.S. P.D. and B.I. supervised the project and conceived the study. All authors reviewed and approved the final version of the paper.</p></notes><notes><title>Funding</title><p>S.P. and P.D. acknowledge funding from the Zeiss Foundation, project &#x0201c;Eine virtuelle Werkstatt f&#x000fc;r die Digitalisierung in den Wissenschaften&#x0201d; (Durchbr&#x000fc;che 2018). B.I. and StS acknowledge funding by the German Research Foundation (DFG) within the Collaborative Research Center (CRC) 1127 ChemBioSys (SFB 1127, Project C07) and M.H. within the CRC 1076 AquaDiva (Project A06). K.L. acknowledges the funding by the Bundesministerium f&#x000fc;r Bildung und Forschung (BMBF) (Project 03ZZ0820A).</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest</p></notes><app-group><app id="app1-viruses-11-00449"><title>Appendix A</title><p>Here you find the sets of reactions for all example models presented in this paper. Written in brackets behind each reaction is its corresponding term from the differential equations:</p><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f0A1" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Figure A1</label><caption><p>Reactions of Baccam model [<xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g0A1"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f0A2" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Figure A2</label><caption><p>Reactions of Miao model [<xref rid="B14-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g0A2"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f0A3" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Figure A3</label><caption><p>Reactions of Baccam model [<xref rid="B14-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] with delayed virus production.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g0A3"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f0A4" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Figure A4</label><caption><p>Reactions of Pawelek model [<xref rid="B23-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g0A4"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f0A5" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Figure A5</label><caption><p>Reactions of Handel model [<xref rid="B24-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g0A5"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f0A6" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Figure A6</label><caption><p>Reactions of Hernandez model [<xref rid="B26-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g0A6"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f0A7" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Figure A7</label><caption><p>Reactions of Saenz model [<xref rid="B28-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g0A7"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f0A8" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Figure A8</label><caption><p>Reactions of Hancioglu model [<xref rid="B29-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g0A8"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f0A9" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Figure A9</label><caption><p>Reactions of Bocharov model [<xref rid="B30-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g0A9"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f0A10" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>Figure A10</label><caption><p>Reactions of Lee model [<xref rid="B9-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g0A10"/></fig></app></app-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1-viruses-11-00449"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>St&#x000f6;hr</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influenza&#x02014;WHO cares</article-title><source>Lancet Infect. Dis.</source><year>2002</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>517</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(02)00366-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12206966</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2-viruses-11-00449"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petrova</surname><given-names>V.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The evolution of seasonal influenza viruses</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro.2017.118</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29081496?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29081496</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3-viruses-11-00449"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krammer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fouchier</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peiris</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kedzierska</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doherty</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palese</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Treanor</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Influenza</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Dis. Prim.</source><year>2018</year><volume>4</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41572-018-0002-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29955068?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29955068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4-viruses-11-00449"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perelson</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influenza A virus infection kinetics: Quantitative data and models</article-title><source>Wiley Interdiscip. Rev. Syst. Biol. Med.</source><year>2011</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>445</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wsbm.129</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21197654?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21197654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5-viruses-11-00449"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beauchemin</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Handel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review of mathematical models of influenza A infections within a host or cell culture: Lessons learned and challenges ahead</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><issue>Suppl. 1</issue><fpage>S7</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-11-S1-S7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21356136?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21356136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6-viruses-11-00449"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dobrovolny</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamal</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rayner</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beauchemin</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing mathematical models of influenza infections using features of the immune response</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e57088</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0057088</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23468916?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23468916</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7-viruses-11-00449"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boianelli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>V.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebensen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilk</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stegemann-Koniszewski</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruder</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toapanta</surname><given-names>F.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Modeling Influenza Virus Infection: A Roadmap for Influenza Research</article-title><source>Viruses</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>5274</fpage><lpage>5304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v7102875</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26473911?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26473911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8-viruses-11-00449"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Handel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beauchemin</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Progress and trends in mathematical modelling of influenza A virus infections</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Syst. Biol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coisb.2018.08.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9-viruses-11-00449"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Topham</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollenbaugh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Treanor</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosmann</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holden-Wiltse</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Simulation and prediction of the adaptive immune response to influenza A virus infection</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>7151</fpage><lpage>7165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.00098-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19439465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10-viruses-11-00449"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dittrich</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Speroni di Fenizio</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical Organization Theory</article-title><source>Bull. Math. Biol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>1199</fpage><lpage>1231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11538-006-9130-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17415616</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11-viruses-11-00449"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsumaru</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Centler</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>di Fenizio</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dittrich</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical organization theory applied to virus dynamics</article-title><source>IT-Inf. Technol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>154</fpage><lpage>160</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12-viruses-11-00449"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dittrich</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the Relation between Organizations and Limit Sets in Chemical Reaction Systems</article-title><source>Adv. Complex Syst.</source><year>2011</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1142/S0219525911002895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13-viruses-11-00449"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baccam</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beauchemin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Macken</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayden</surname><given-names>F.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perelson</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinetics of influenza A virus infection in humans</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>7590</fpage><lpage>7599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.01623-05</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16840338</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14-viruses-11-00449"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollenbaugh</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zand</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holden-Wiltse</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosmann</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perelson</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Topham</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantifying the early immune response and adaptive immune response kinetics in mice infected with influenza A virus</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>6687</fpage><lpage>6698</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.00266-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20410284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15-viruses-11-00449"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Critical, Nonlinear Threshold Dictates Bacterial Invasion and Initial Kinetics During Influenza</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>38703</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep38703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27974820</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16-viruses-11-00449"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soliman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heiner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A unique transformation from ordinary differential equations to reaction networks</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e14284</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0014284</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21203560?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21203560</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17-viruses-11-00449"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><source>The Regulation of Cellular Systems</source><publisher-name>Springer Science &#x00026; Business Media</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin, Germany</publisher-loc><year>2012</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18-viruses-11-00449"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fontana</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buss</surname><given-names>L.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x0201c;The arrival of the fittest&#x0201d;: Toward a theory of biological organization</article-title><source>Bull. Math. Biol.</source><year>1994</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>64</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19-viruses-11-00449"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kreyssig</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wozar</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veloz</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dittrich</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of small particle numbers on long-term behaviour in discrete biochemical systems</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2014</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu453</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25161236?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25161236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20-viruses-11-00449"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toward a systems-level view of mitotic checkpoints</article-title><source>Prog. Biophys. Mol. Biol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbiomolbio.2015.02.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25722206</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21-viruses-11-00449"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kreyssig</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Escuela</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynaert</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Veloz</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dittrich</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cycles and the qualitative evolution of chemical systems</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e45772</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0045772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23071525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22-viruses-11-00449"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moquin</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernhauerova</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influenza virus infection model with density dependence supports biphasic viral decay</article-title><source>Front. Microbiol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1554</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.01554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30042759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23-viruses-11-00449"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pawelek</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huynh</surname><given-names>G.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinlivan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cullinane</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rong</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perelson</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling within-host dynamics of influenza virus infection including immune responses</article-title><source>PLoS Comput. Biol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e1002588</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002588</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22761567?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22761567</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24-viruses-11-00449"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Handel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Longini</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name><surname>Antia</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards a quantitative understanding of the within-host dynamics of influenza A infections</article-title><source>J. R. Soc. Interface</source><year>2009</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsif.2009.0067</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19474085?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19474085</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25-viruses-11-00449"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Handel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Longini</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name><surname>Antia</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neuraminidase inhibitor resistance in influenza: Assessing the danger of its generation and spread</article-title><source>PLoS Comput. Biol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>e240</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.0030240</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18069885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26-viruses-11-00449"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hernandez-Vargas</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer-Hermann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Innate immune system dynamics to influenza virus</article-title><source>IFAC Proc. Vol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>260</fpage><lpage>265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3182/20120829-3-HU-2029.00029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27-viruses-11-00449"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heffernan</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrie</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carolan</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guarnaccia</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelso</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>I.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>McVernon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Innate Immunity and the Inter-exposure Interval Determine the Dynamics of Secondary Influenza Virus Infection and Explain Observed Viral Hierarchies</article-title><source>PLoS Comput. Biol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e1004334</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004334</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26284917?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26284917</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28-viruses-11-00449"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saenz</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinlivan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elton</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Macrae</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blunden</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mumford</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Digard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cullinane</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grenfell</surname><given-names>B.T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dynamics of influenza virus infection and pathology</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>3974</fpage><lpage>3983</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.02078-09</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20130053?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20130053</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29-viruses-11-00449"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hancioglu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Swigon</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clermont</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A dynamical model of human immune response to influenza A virus infection</article-title><source>J. Theor. Biol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>246</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtbi.2006.12.015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17266989?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17266989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30-viruses-11-00449"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bocharov</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Romanyukha</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mathematical model of antiviral immune response. III. Influenza A virus infection</article-title><source>J. Theor. Biol.</source><year>1994</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jtbi.1994.1074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7516024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31-viruses-11-00449"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCaw</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mechanisms for within-host influenza virus control affect model-based assessment and prediction of antiviral treatment</article-title><source>Viruses</source><year>2017</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>197</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v9080197</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32-viruses-11-00449"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zitzmann</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaderali</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mathematical Analysis of Viral Replication Dynamics and Antiviral Treatment Strategies: From Basic Models to Age-Based Multi-Scale Modeling</article-title><source>Front. Microbiol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1546</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.01546</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30050523?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30050523</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33-viruses-11-00449"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dittrich</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Organisation-Oriented Coarse Graining and Refinement of Stochastic Reaction Networks</article-title><source>IEEE/ACM Trans. Comput. Biol. Bioinform.</source><year>2018</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1152</fpage><lpage>1166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TCBB.2018.2804395</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29994367?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29994367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34-viruses-11-00449"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henze</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Puljiz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamaleson</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huwald</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haslegrave</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>di Fenizio</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Good</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multi-scale stochastic organization-oriented coarse-graining exemplified on the human mitotic checkpoint</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>3902</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-40648-w</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30846816?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30846816</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Relation between measured data, ordinary differential equations (ODE) model, and hierarchy of organizations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g001"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The <bold>Baccam Model</bold> [<xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] with three variables: uninfected (susceptible) target cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm182"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), infected cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm183"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and infectious-viral titer (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm184"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g002"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The <bold>Miao Model</bold> [<xref rid="B14-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] with three variables: uninfected target cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm185"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">E</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">P</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), productively infected cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm186"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">E</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">P</mml:mi><mml:mo mathcolor="#FE2E9A">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and free infectious influenza viruses (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm187"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g003"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The <bold>Baccam II Model</bold> [<xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] with delayed virus production and four variables: uninfected (susceptible) target cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm188"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), infected cells not yet producing virus (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm189"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">I</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), infected cells actively producing virus (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm190"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">I</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and infectious-viral titer (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm191"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g004"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>The <bold>Pawelek Model</bold> [<xref rid="B23-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] with five variables: (uninfected) target cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm192"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), productively infected cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm193"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), uninfected cells refractory to infections (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm194"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), free viruses (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm195"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and interferon (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm196"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">F</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g005"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>The <bold>Smith Model</bold> [<xref rid="B15-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] with five variables: susceptible target cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm197"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), two classes of infected cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm198"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">I</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm199"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">I</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), free viruses (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm200"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), and bacteria (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm201"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE9A2E">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g006"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>The <bold>Handel model</bold> [<xref rid="B24-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] with seven variables: uninfected cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm202"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">U</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), latently infected cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm203"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), productively infected cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm204"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), dead cells (<italic>D</italic>), free viruses (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm205"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), innate immune response (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm206"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">F</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and adaptive immune response (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm207"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). The dotted arrows denote the projection of the dynamics shown in Figure 8.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g007"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Temporal dynamics of the Handel model. By projecting the seven-dimensional trajectory to organizations (dotted arrows in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00449-f007">Figure 7</xref>b) we find three phases: (Phase 1) Until day number 0, there are solely <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm208"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>9</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> uninfected cells <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm209"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">U</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in the system represented by the organization <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm210"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">U</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. (Phase 2) At day 0, <bold>infection</bold> is simulated by adding <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm211"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> virus particles to the system. The resulting state <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm212"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">U</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">V</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is projected to organization <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm213"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (all species). (Phase 3) Lastly, at day t = 37d past infection the system settles in the final organization, namely <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm214"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">U</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, which is generated by the set <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm215"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">U</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (see text). The values of the model parameters are (from [<xref rid="B24-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]): <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm216"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.25</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm217"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm218"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm219"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm220"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm221"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003ba;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.8</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm222"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm223"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>7.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm224"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm225"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm226"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm227"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.7</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm228"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Note that the number of uninfected cells <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm229"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">U</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is not constant after infection as it may seem from the figure. In fact, after infection, the number of uninfected cells first decreases and than rises again [<xref rid="B24-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g008"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f009" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>The <bold>Hernandez Model</bold> [<xref rid="B26-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] with seven variables: healthy cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm230"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">U</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">H</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), partially infected cell (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm231"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">U</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">E</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), infected cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm232"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">U</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), cells resistant to infection (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm233"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">U</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">R</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), virus particles (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm234"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), interferon (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm235"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">F</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and natural killers (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm236"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">K</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g009"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f010" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>The <bold>Cao Model</bold> [<xref rid="B27-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] with seven variables: target cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm237"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), infected cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm238"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), viruses (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm239"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), resistant cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm240"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), interferon (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm241"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">F</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), B cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm242"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), and antibodies (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm243"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g010"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f011" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>The <bold>Saenz Model</bold> [<xref rid="B28-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] with eight variables: Epithelial cells in one of the states: susceptible (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm244"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), eclipse phase (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm245"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">E</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm246"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), prerefractory (<italic>W</italic>), refractory (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm247"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and infectious (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm248"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). The further variables are: virus cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm249"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and interferon (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm250"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">F</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g011"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f012" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 12</label><caption><p>The <bold>Hancioglu Model</bold> [<xref rid="B29-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] with 10 variables: viral load (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm251"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), healthy cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm252"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), infected cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm253"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), antigen presenting cells (<italic>M</italic>), interferon (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm254"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">F</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), resistant cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm255"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), effector cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm256"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), plasma cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm257"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), antibodies (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm258"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and antigenic distance (<italic>S</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g012"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f013" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 13</label><caption><p>The <bold>Bocharov Model</bold> [<xref rid="B30-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] with 10 variables: infective IAV particles (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm259"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">V</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), IAV-infected cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm260"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), destroyed epithelial cells (<italic>m</italic>), stimulated macrophages (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm261"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">M</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">V</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), activated helper T cells providing proliferation of cytotoxic T cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm262"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">H</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">E</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), activated helper T cells providing proliferation and differentiation of B cells B (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm263"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">H</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">B</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), activated CTL (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm264"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), B cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm265"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), plasma cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm266"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), antibodies to IAV (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm267"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">F</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), and uninfected epithelial cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm268"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">U</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). Note that, for clarity, we have added <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm269"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">U</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as a state variable, which is only implicitly represented as <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm270"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">U</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">C</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in the original model by Bocharov et al.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g013"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f014" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 14</label><caption><p>The <bold>Lee model</bold> [<xref rid="B9-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] which contains 15 variables: uninfected epithelial cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm271"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">E</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">P</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), infected epithelial cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm272"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">E</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">P</mml:mi><mml:mo mathcolor="#FE2E9A">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), virus titer (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm273"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm274"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), immature dendritic cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm275"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), virus-loaded dendritic cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm276"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#FE2E9A">D</mml:mi><mml:mo mathcolor="#FE2E9A">*</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), mature dendritic cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm277"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">D</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">M</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), naive CD4+ T cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm278"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), effector CD4+ T cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm279"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">H</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">E</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), naive CD8+ T cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm280"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), effector CD8+ T cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm281"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">T</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">E</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), naive B cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm282"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), activated B cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm283"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">B</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), short-lived plasma (antibody-secreting) B cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm284"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">P</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">S</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), long-lived plasma (antibody-secreting) B cells (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm285"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">P</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">L</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and antiviral antibody titer (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm286"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). Note that here we have colored green only those species representing the <styled-content style="color: #01DF01">immune system when activated.</styled-content>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g014a"/><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g014b"/></fig><fig id="viruses-11-00449-f015" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 15</label><caption><p>Hasse-diagram of the hierarchy of IAV models with respect to their long-term behaviour. In brackets (), we added the number of species of each model. Underneath (marked by colors) the kinds of species contained in the organizations belonging to each model. The meaning of the four colors is as follows: Species belonging to the healthy state of the organism are colored <styled-content style="color: #0000FF">blue</styled-content>, those belonging to the immune response are colored <styled-content style="color: #01DF01">green</styled-content>, those belonging to infection like infected cells and viruses are colored <styled-content style="color: #FE2E9A">magenta</styled-content>, and bacteria from bacterial co-infection are colored <styled-content style="color: #FE9A2E">orange</styled-content>. Horizontally, the diagram consists of four lines. The models in the lowest line contain organizations with exactly two different kinds of species (colors) (including the empty set). In the second line above, there are three different combinations of species (colors) to be found in each model. There is only one model in each of the highest two lines: The Smith model [<xref rid="B4-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] is the only one with bacteria and contains four different combinations of colors. In the Handel Model, there are even five different combinations of colors out of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm287"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>16</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> possible combinations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00449-g015"/></fig><table-wrap id="viruses-11-00449-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">viruses-11-00449-t001_Table 1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Overview of all models and organization types contained. An organization type like <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm288"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#0000FF">X</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold" mathcolor="#01DF01">X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> denotes the type of species contained in an organization, according to our coloring scheme. The set of organization types of a model is called its signature.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of<break/>Variables</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of<break/>Reactions</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of<break/>Organizations</th><th colspan="4" align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1">Organizations &#x00026; Signature</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">Baccam [<xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]<break/>2006</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">
<italic>2</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm289"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02205;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm600"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">Miao [<xref rid="B14-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]<break/>2010</td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">
<italic>3</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm290"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02205;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm599"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm700"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #FE2E9A">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">Baccam II [<xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]<break/>2006</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">
<italic>2</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm291"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02205;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm610"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">Pawelek [<xref rid="B23-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]<break/>2012</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">
<italic>2</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm292"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02205;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm595"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">Smith [<xref rid="B15-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]<break/>2016</td><td rowspan="4" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="4" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="4" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">
<italic>4</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm293"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02205;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm580"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm581"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #FE9A2E">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm582"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #FE9A2E">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">Handel [<xref rid="B24-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]<break/>2010</td><td rowspan="5" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="5" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="5" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">
<italic>5</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm294"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02205;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm570"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm571"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #01DF01">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm573"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #01DF01">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm574"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #01DF01">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #FE2E9A">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">Hernandez [<xref rid="B26-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]<break/>2012</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">
<italic>2</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm295"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #01DF01">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm560"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #01DF01">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #FE2E9A">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">Cao [<xref rid="B27-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]<break/>2015</td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">
<italic>3</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm298"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02205;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm701"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm702"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #01DF01">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #FE2E9A">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">Saenz [<xref rid="B28-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]<break/>2010</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">
<italic>4</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm299"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02205;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm705"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm708"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm710"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">Hancioglu [<xref rid="B29-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]<break/>2007</td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">44</td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">
<italic>3</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm300"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #01DF01">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm720"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #01DF01">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm721"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #01DF01">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #FE2E9A">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">Bocharov [<xref rid="B30-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]<break/>1994</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">45</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">
<italic>2</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm302"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #01DF01">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm725"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #01DF01">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">Lee [<xref rid="B9-viruses-11-00449" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]<break/>2009</td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">37</td><td rowspan="3" align="center" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">
<italic>8</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm304"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm726"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm730"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm732"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm731"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm735"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #01DF01">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm738"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm740"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #0000FF">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #01DF01">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<styled-content style="color: #FE2E9A">
<bold>X</bold>
</styled-content>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>