<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We show that while BFDV remained detectable in a nest box for up to several months, as predicted in several studies which assumed extended persistence of BFDV outside of the host (
 <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Eastwood et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Peters et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Raidal &amp; Peters, 2018</xref>), it was less likely to be detected after the breeding season (only one nest box had a BFDV-positive nest swab after the breeding season). Additionally, we did not close off the nest boxes after the nestlings had fledged. It is therefore possible that BFDV-positive birds accessed the nest boxes after breeding, which may have contributed to nest swabs testing BFDV-positive after the breeding season. As we only tested swabs collected directly after the breeding season, i.e., two to three months after birds occupying the boxes tested BFDV-positive, and not later in the year, we cannot exclude that BFDV can be present for a longer time period than reported here. However, the lack of BFDV detection (threshold
 <sub>36</sub>) in all boxes (boxes occupied by BFDV-positive birds during the breeding season, and both sets of control boxes) before the breeding season and the very low prevalence of BFDV in nesting material two to three months after the breeding season suggests that at least in our study system, it is unlikely that BFDV persists in the nest box up until the next breeding season. We detected BFDV on nest swabs with a qPCR assay, which is a well-established and very accurate method for the detection of BFDV-infected birds, which detects short fragments of viral DNA (
 <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Eastwood et al., 2015</xref>). Most qPCR positives, at least those ones derived from blood samples, represent active infection with viable virus as confirmed by sequencing (
 <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Eastwood et al., 2014</xref>), but some could be non-active remnant viral DNA (
 <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Eastwood et al., 2019</xref>). As we could not pick up viral DNA fragments with qPCR before or, in most cases, after the breeding season, it seems unlikely that intact, infectious viral particles persist in nest boxes outside of the breeding season. Future studies could consider testing nest swabs with an HA assay (
 <xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr">Raidal, Sabine &amp; Cross, 1993</xref>), to elucidate whether BFDV-positive results indeed represent contamination of the nest box with viable, infectious antigen.
</p>
