<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although we show that JE-CVax immunization resulted in complete protection against YFV-induced disease, there were variations in the actual levels of anti-YFV nAbs after YFV challenge. In some animals, no nAbs were detected against YFV after YFV-17D-challenge. This lack of YFV nAb indicates that JE-CVax possibly conferred sterilizing immunity in these mice. Since such protection cannot be explained by nAb against the YFV-prM/E, it may be accredited to non-nAbs (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>) and/or adaptive cellular immunity (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Some correlation between anti-NS1 antibody levels and the dose of JE-CVax needed to cause protection was observed (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2B</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">C</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS1">Fig. S1A</xref>), and serum from JE-CVax-vaccinated mice was found to induce an ADCC response against YFV-17D (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS3">Fig. S3</xref>). In addition, in our model both CD4
 <sup>+</sup> and CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells seem (in a likely association with anti-NS1 antibodies) to be involved in JE-CVax-mediated protection against YFV (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4E</xref>). Previously, only humoral immunity and CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T (but not CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T) cells have been implied to be sufficient and required for protection against YFV (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), with a strong emphasis on nAb as a historically established immunological correlate of protection for YFV (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) and for flaviviruses (such as JEV) in general (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). nAbs possibly block viral spread, whereas cellular immunity efficiently eliminates intracellular viruses either directly or targeted by non-nAbs toward infected cells in an Fc-dependent manner (for example, via ADCC toward cells expressing YFV NS1 on their surfaces) (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Indeed, YF-induced CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells have been shown to act as a “backup defense” system in the absence of nAbs and to participate in viral clearance in particular from the central nervous system (CNS) in mice (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Moreover, strong CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cell responses are also detected in the response to human vaccines (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). As we show here, immunization of AG129 and C57BL/6 mice with JE-CVax elicited protective polyfunctional YFV antigen-specific CD4
 <sup>+</sup> and CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cell responses (expressing the Th1-type cytokines TNF-α and IFN-γ), which is in line with a previous study with a chimeric Japanese encephalitis/dengue virus 2 vaccine (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Previously, clinical studies with humans also demonstrated that vaccination with CYD-TDV/Dengvaxia elicits cell-mediated immunity directed against YFV nonstructural proteins (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). Our comparative 
 <italic>in silico</italic> analysis indicated that the YFV-17D backbone is more immunogenic in humans than in mice and provides a hint that CTL responses should be at least as effective in humans as in mice. Likewise, several HLA-binding YFV-17D peptides thus predicted have recently also been confirmed experimentally using human-derived T cells and vaccinated human volunteers (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>) (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS10">Fig. S10</xref>). Collectively, our data suggest that JE-CVax-mediated vigorous protection against lethal YFV challenge depends on the combined effects of several effector principles, including both the humoral and cellular immune responses, yet definitely other than nAbs.
</p>
