<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0060">The occurrence of confirmed local cases of COVID-19 in Mexico has been analyzed taking into account the weather and climate of each of 31 states and the capital during the phase 1 of the epidemic progress. The evolution of COVID-19 was analyzed through in the number of LCPC rather than TCPC or ICPC. Neither ICPC nor deceases described the environmental effect on transmission in phase 1. COVID-19 local spread was strongly associated with both the climate and daily environmental conditions due to during phase 1 the transmission occurred freely without contention strategy influences. Thus, the regional climate in each Mexico's state has a central role in the initial local SARS-CoV-2 transmission. TCPC (i.e. ICPC+LCPC) associates positively with daily average air temperature. High temperature and high evaporation in tropical climates are the best-combined predictors as a disadvantaged condition for SARS-CoV-2 survival. Daily incidence of COVID-19 increased slowly in states belonging to tropical cluster. Template condition promotes the highest LCPC observed. Temperature and evaporation were negatively associated with the LCPC without statistical significance. Regional climate was statistically significantly associated with LCPC and LTR. Dry and temperate cold climates are the more suitable environmental conditions for transmission. The tropical climate (mean temperature around 25.95 °C and mean precipitation around 8.74 mm) delayed the regional onset. However, the regional onset in dry climates emerged earlier as consequence of the lower temperatures and higher precipitations (20.57 °C and 20.87 mm respectively) than the observed in the tropical climate. The fastest regional onsets were observed in tempered climates with the lowest temperatures and precipitations registered (19.65 °C and 8.48 mm respectively). Therefore, the regional climate was strongly associated with initial COVID-19 local contagion during the phase 1 being the tempered regions (as Tlaxcala, Guanajuato, Jalisco, among others) more vulnerable than the dry (as Aguascalientes, Sinaloa, Queretaro, among others) or tropical areas (as Veracruz, Guerrero, Chiapas, among others). Any attempt related to evaluate the effect of outdoor environmental factors on the spread, transmission or virus survival should take into account both the phase of the epidemic evolution and the effective active period of the virus since regional onset on communitarian transmission.</p>
