<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par36">Now, the above-described abilities of CQ or HCQ to function as anti-viral and immunomodulatory agent highlight the rationale for usage of CQ or its derivate as both prophylactic and therapeutic agents in clinically admissible concentrations (Shah et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2020</xref>). A small randomized clinical trial conducted in China with 100 patients showed that CQ had superior effects in inhibiting exacerbation of pneumonia, improving lung-imaging findings, promoting a virus-negative conversion and shortening the disease course when compared to a control drug (Jie et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2020</xref>; Gao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2020</xref>) Another clinical trial in Marseille, France reported by Gautret et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2020</xref>) demonstrated that HCQ has efficacy in increasing viral clearance. In that non-randomized trial (
 <italic>n</italic> = 36) conducted, HCQ alone and in combination with azithromycin antibiotic effectively cleared viral nasopharyngeal carriage as evidenced by the gold standard PCR (polymerase chain reaction) test (versus control). The virus clearance at day 6 post-inclusion HCQ vs. control was 70.0% versus 12.5%, respectively (
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.001). A higher virus clearance effect was seen with a combinational therapy of azithromycin and CQ. This combinational therapy was effective because azithromycin is an anti-viral agent that has shown efficacy against Zika and Ebola viruses (Gautret et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2020</xref>). However, all clinical results did not show the same picture. In a randomized study from China, patients with mild to moderate cases of COVID-19 did not show recovery rates when treated with HCQ (Gao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2020</xref>). Likewise, another study conducted in France with 11 hospitalized cases also failed to confirm anti-viral activity of HCQ when administered with an azithromycin (Yazdany and Kim 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2020</xref>). A reason for the discrepancy in effect as noted among these clinical trials could be the dosage of CQ or HCQ selected; a higher dose of CQ or HCQ may be imparting untoward implications, especially if not monitored. The current doses tested may be with respect to the anti-malarial effects of CQ and HCQ when the body encounters a deadly pathogen of plasmodium genus or even with respect to the other viral infections that it was tested with. Since CQ is effective at blocking viral entry, it would have better effects as a prophylactic or for patients with mild symptoms. We also see that trials were conducted during the different stages of the pandemic; at severe stages, perhaps, a different therapeutic regimen is required. Upon further mutations with time (that is seen in the different stages of a pandemic), the adherence propensity of the virus towards host cells may change (increased) that CQ or HQ alone may not be not alone sufficient as an anti-viral therapy. At the same time, a toxicity profile of CQ or HCQ in combination with azithromycin versus azithromycin and CQ or HCQ should be conducted to rule out the toxicity arising from combinational therapy (Gautret et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2020</xref>). Additional research to carry out research on CQ and HCQ is emphasized because unlike other drugs, apart from the ability to block viral infection, these drugs also have immunomodulatory effects which is very much useful for countering the initiation of the cytokine storm seen in COVID-19 patients (Conti et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2020</xref>). Although this review focuses on the beneficial effects of CQ, we do not overlook some of the precautions as evidenced from clinical studies (van den Broek et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2020</xref>). During the course of the prophylactic or therapeutic regimen involving CQ or HCQ, frequent monitoring of hematological parameters (RBC, WBC and platelet counts), measurement of serum electrolytes, blood glucose (owing to the hypoglycemic potential of HCQ), liver function test, kidney function test and electrocardiography are warranted at time intervals to rule out any toxicity. Combinational therapy of CQ with any other allopathic drug be it azithromycin, lopinavir/ritonavir and remdesivir is warranted only after testing in in vitro model systems and pre-clinical trials. Clinical experience has shown that chloroquine is well absorbed in the body and distributes widely in the system. It has an apparent and terminal half-life of 1.6 days and 2 weeks, respectively (Smit et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2020</xref>). The drug is metabolized by cytochrome P450 and renal clearance is responsible for one-third of total clearance of chloroquine (Smit et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2020</xref>). So with lower dose, it is probable that chloroquine can be used safely for an acute virus infection. But some of the potential side effects of HCQ and CQ, such as retinopathy, vomiting, diarrhea and increased risk of arrhythmia, should be also taken into account (Conti et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2020</xref>) and we presume that these may be countered by a combinational therapy wherein the beneficial effect of CQ may be retained and the toxicity of CQ may be alleviated. Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> gives framework of some of the research work published using CQ or HCQ with suggested drug doses for treatment regimen of COVID 19.
</p>
