<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0045">An effective ZIKV vaccine continues to be actively sought [
 <xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>]. These initiatives exploit multiple strategies and platforms for ZIKV vaccine development. Of the many potential vaccine platforms available, we have been interested in particulate vaccines because of the advantages they offer in terms of safety and immunogenicity. In previous work, we found that DENV-80E proteins, when expressed in the absence of the prM proteins, in 
 <italic>P. pastoris</italic>, exhibit the capacity to self-assemble into NPs 
 <xref rid="bib0043" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0044" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0046" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. An interesting observation was that these DENV-80E NPs, which were highly immunogenic, displayed EDIII prominently, based on DENV EDIII-specific mAb-probing analyses, as well as the predominantly EDIII-focused nAbs they consistently elicited. From a vaccine perspective, this is important, as anti-EDIII antibodies are not only potent neutralisers of virus infectivity, but are also type-specific and inherently appear to lack ADE potential. This prompted us to question if ZIKV-80E when expressed in 
 <italic>P. pastoris</italic>, would assemble into ZIKV EDIII-displaying NPs with similar attributes. The elimination of the prM protein from the vaccine candidate may also be advantageous. Though it is not known if ZIKV prM antibodies may have a role in ADE, like their DENV counterparts, this cannot be entirely ruled out given that pups born to ZIKV-immune mice 
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref> and macaques pre-infected with ZIKV 
 <xref rid="bib0061" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref> manifest signs of ADE of DENV infection. Thus, it is preferable to eliminate prM from vaccine design.
</p>
