<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0415">The arthralgias are polyarticular, symmetric, and predominantly affect the small joints of the hands, wrists, ankles, and feet (see 
 <xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 36.2.1</xref>) with lesser involvement of larger joints. During the acute phase, joint pain can be incapacitating. Patients with milder articular manifestations are usually symptom free within a few weeks, but more severe cases require months or years to resolve entirely.
 <xref rid="bib2.10" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref> One study indicated that one third of patients had chronic joint symptoms that persisted for at least 9 months.
 <xref rid="bib2.11" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref> Cutaneous manifestations are typical with many patients. This is usually a maculopapular rash, but bullous lesions can occur in infants. The trunk and limbs are most commonly involved, but the face, palms, and soles may also show lesions. During the acute phase, some patients will have headache, but it is not usually severe, and retro-orbital pain, commonly found in dengue infections, rarely occurs. Conjunctival redness is present in some cases. Pregnant women can pass the virus to their infant, most commonly during the intrapartum phase. The Reunion South Hospital Group observed 84 pregnant women who had laboratory-confirmed CHIK infection. In 88% of these women (all involving infections relatively distant from delivery), the newborns appeared asymptomatic. Conversely, 10 newborns developed disease soon after birth (4 with meningoencephalitis and 3 with intravascular coagulation) and required intensive care support.
 <xref rid="bib2.12" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref> Severe cases of CHIK, including neurologic complications, myocarditis, or nephritis, can occur, most commonly in the elderly, newborns, and immunocompromised individuals.
 <xref rid="bib2.13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib2.14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> CHIK outbreaks typically result in several hundred or thousands of cases, but deaths are rarely encountered.
</p>
