<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The HA glycoprotein is composed of two subunits, the globular surface subunit HA1 and the stalk-like transmembrane subunit HA2. The HA protein of influenza viruses is initially synthesized as a single polypeptide precursor (HA0), which is cleaved into HA1 and HA2 subunits by cellular proteases. The sequence of the cleavage site determines by which cellular proteases HA0 can be cleaved. The highly pathogenic phenotype of some H5 and H7 viruses is the result of the introduction of a multibasic cleavage site (MBCS) in HA and directly correlates with the high lethality of avian influenza viruses in poultry, primarily as a consequence of systemic virus replication in these hosts. HPAI H5N1 virus can also cause severe and/or fatal disease in a wide range of mammalian species, but the association between HA cleavability and systemic virus replication is less straightforward for influenza viruses in mammals as compared to poultry. Removal of the MBCS from HA of an HPAI H5N1 virus resulted in a virus that caused only respiratory tract infection in mice, in contrast to the systemic replication of the HPAI H5N1 virus, indicating that the MBCS was a major virulence factor in mice.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">52</xref>
 </sup> However, experimental infection of non-human primates with HPAI H5N1 virus caused respiratory tract disease only with no evidence of systemic virus replication.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">53</xref>
 </sup> Recent studies showed that the MBCS in an HPAI H5N1 virus was important for systemic spread in ferrets, since deletion of the MBCS from HPAI H5N1 virus resulted in replication that was restricted to the respiratory tract.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">54</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">55</xref>
 </sup> However, insertion of an MBCS in a human H3N2 virus did not result in systemic spread in ferrets.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">56</xref>
 </sup> The increased tissue tropism and virulence of HPAI H5N1 virus in mammals is most likely caused by multiple factors, among which the MBCS is essential. However, the presence of appropriate receptors for virus attachment, presence of the proper proteases in host cells and local innate immune responses also influence the ability of influenza virus to replicate systemically.
</p>
