<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cardiotonic steroids digoxin and digitoxin have been suggested to offer a new strategy to target and suppress HAdV. Historically, these drugs have been used to treat heart failure for over 200 years. More recently, they have also shown efficacy in cancer treatments, in that treated patients demonstrated a lesser chance of relapse.
 <xref rid="CIT0088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref> Hartley et al first noted its potential antiviral benefit, noting its efficacy against HAdV and herpesviruses.
 <xref rid="CIT0089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref> This is due to the drugs inhibiting Na+/K+ ATPase on the cell surface, which leads to increased intracellular levels of NA+ and, subsequently, Ca++. Na+/K+ ATPase is an important cell signaling molecule, where binding with digoxin or digitoxin initiates multiple signaling cascades, influencing gene expression. These drugs also alter RNA splicing, which is necessary to HAdV replication. Preliminary data supports a concentration-dependent reduction in the number of infected cells and no apparent damage. Although there is known toxicity, particularly with long-term use of digoxin, the antiviral uses of cardiotonic steroids would be short term, negating the associated systemic complications. As such, these drugs seem to be efficacious against HAdV serotypes A-D and serve as potential treatment therapies for the treatment and prophylaxis of EKC.
 <xref rid="CIT0088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref> Thus, repurposing of these cardiotonic steroids as an antiviral agent for short-term treatment of adenoviral keratoconjunctivitis as well as a prophylactic for use in individuals in close contact with patients with epidemic keratoconjunctivitis.
 <xref rid="CIT0088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref> Furthermore, Marrugal-Lorenzo et al reported that mifepristone, a synthetic steroid drug, possesses anti-adenoviral properties via its interference with viral entry into the nucleus. As such, it could be repurposed for treating adenoviral infections.
 <xref rid="CIT0090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>
</p>
