<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our analysis of the dynamics of NS1 expression showed an MOI-dependent expression of this important innate immune antagonist protein in infected cells. Similarly, we found that the levels of all IAV genes per infected cell were more elevated when cells were exposed to a high MOI than to a low MOI, most likely due to differences in the numbers of cells being initially infected with multiple virions. Under physiological conditions, the first round of infection of the respiratory epithelia by IAV would be mediated by a few virus particles, so probably infected host cells receive only one infectious virus. This is consistent with the very low number of viruses shown to be responsible for initation of infection in ferrets (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>) and humans (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). However, as infection progresses, infection of neighboring cells is likely mediated by more than one virus originating from the infected cells, with lower numbers of viruses reaching cells farther away from the initially infected cells. Thus, we expect to find both single-virus- and multiple-virus-infected cells during human IAV infections. Interestingly, as found by a correlation analysis of the viral genes versus a panel of innate immune genes, NS shows a consistent negative correlation with the transcription of most of the innate immune genes. This negative correlation is clearly more enhanced in cells infected with multiple viruses (high MOI) than in those infected with single viruses (low MOI), suggesting that the number of virions that infect each individual cell has important consequences for the ability of the virus to counteract the innate immune response in that cell (see model in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref>). Therefore, our results suggest that viral IFN antagonism might be less effective during the initial stages of infection in the context of humans infected with a virus, when cells are impacted by single virus particles. During viral infection, the concentration of viral particles released grows exponentially, reaching levels up to 10
 <sup>5</sup> to 10
 <sup>7</sup> 50% tissue culture infective doses (TCID
 <sub>50</sub>)/ml (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). At this level of replication in the respiratory tract tissue, it is highly probable that many cells get infected with multiple viruses, which would enhance the ability of IAV to suppress the innate immune response 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> and at the same time favor the reassortment of IAV genes, an important evolutionary force for IAV.
</p>
