<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>NS1 has multiple functions to antagonize the cellular response. One of the best characterized is its ability to inhibit virus sensing by RIGI, either by sequestering dsRNA or by direct interaction with RIGI or TRIM25 (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). Related to this, we found IFNB1, all type III IFNs, and other cytokines and chemokines among the genes that correlated negatively with the levels of NS at the high MOI. However, we found that gene expression was affected at a general level, suggesting a global inhibition of the transcription of the innate immune genes. Also, when we compared the gene expression profiles in infected versus bystander cells, we found a group of genes, presumably induced in a paracrine manner, that were expressed at lower levels in infected than in bystander cells, probably due to virus transcriptional antagonism. While a combination of viral factors could be responsible for this global shutoff of host transcription, our data suggest that NS1 might be associated with this phenomenon. There is evidence in the literature that IAV infection results in reduced host transcription and mRNA processing by inhibiting the host RNA polymerase II (Pol II) function (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>). Related to this, a recent study found that several strains of IAV elicit global deregulation of Poll II transcription termination by impairing 3′-end cleavage and termination, and this effect was dependent on NS1 expression (
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>). These studies could partially explain the global negative correlation that we found between viral genes and cellular genes. NS1 interactome studies have identified multiple additional interactions of NS1 with nuclear proteins (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>), which could also have a global effect on cellular transcription. In addition, another study that used a combination of modeling and experimental research found that ISGs are specifically suppressed in IAV-infected dendritic cells through the inhibition of multiple transcription factors (
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>). The second viral gene that showed the strongest negative correlation with host genes in our analysis was PA. Interestingly, in addition to encoding one subunit of the IAV polymerase, it has a second open reading frame accessed by ribosomal frameshifting that results in the expression of the protein known as PA-X (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). PA-X inhibits transcription of cellular genes by selectively targeting host Pol II transcribed mRNAs (
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>). Therefore, it is possible that the global negative correlation is a consequence of the expression of NS1 and PA-X in infected cells. Further investigation will determine if this effect is similar for other IAV strains or if it is strain specific, which will shed light into possible unknown mechanisms for virus-mediated host transcription inhibition.
</p>
