<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Continued transmission during winter provides an alternate means of virus persistence at both northern and southern latitudes. At temperate latitudes where mosquitoes are inactive throughout the cold winter months, WNV has been detected repeatedly in dead birds. In upstate NY WNV transmission was found to continue at a communal American Crow roost by bird-to-bird transmission, possibly through fecal-oral contamination (feces under the roost were positive), preening (ectoparasites tested positive), and/or cannibalism of carcasses (dead birds were positive) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B132-viruses-05-02079">132</xref>]. Bird species positive during winter frequently have been corvids or raptors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B133-viruses-05-02079">133</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B134-viruses-05-02079">134</xref>] that may have been infected orally, perhaps by eating acute or chronically infected birds. After WNV became established at southern latitudes in the USA, infected birds and mosquitoes were collected throughout the winter months in southern California (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-05-02079-f004">Figure 4</xref>) and Texas [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B135-viruses-05-02079">135</xref>], and sentinel chickens in Florida were found to seroconvert to WNV and SLEV throughout the year (
 <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.doh.state.fl.us/Environment/medicine/arboviral/surveillance.htm" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.doh.state.fl.us/Environment/medicine/arboviral/surveillance.htm</uri>). Although difficult to separate from patterns of progressive vernal warming at increasing northern latitudes, northbound migrants appear to acquire WNV infections during migration at southern temperate latitudes and then transport virus northward during spring. For example, northbound birds collected along the Pacific flyway in the Central Valley of California had higher infection rates than those collected at stop-over points along the Salton Sea near Mexico [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B108-viruses-05-02079">108</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B136-viruses-05-02079">136</xref>]. Similar findings were reported for the Mississippi and Atlantic flyways for WNV [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B107-viruses-05-02079">107</xref>] and other arboviruses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B137-viruses-05-02079">137</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B138-viruses-05-02079">138</xref>].
</p>
