<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In general, a virus entry to the host cell comprises a series of fundamental interactions; (i) binding to a target host cell via cellular receptors; (ii) fusing the envelope with a cellular membrane; and (iii) forking over its genetic material inside the cell (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). The process of viral genomic delivery of nucleic acids into the host cell is highly dependent upon binding specificity to receptors, proteolytic activation, and endocytosis efficiency (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Coronaviruses demonstrate a great degree of plasticity regarding the entry pathways, which can occur at the plasma membrane or through the endocytic pathway (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). The entry to the host cell process of SARS-CoV-2 is regulated by Glycosylated spike (S) fusion protein and host receptor known as ACE2. The S proteins is capable of significant structural rearrangement thus, play a crucial role in fusing the viral membrane with the host cell membrane (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). This fusion process sparks off with binding of the S1 subunit to ACE2 and is linked with the accessibility of receptor determined by hinge-like conformational movements of the receptor-binding domain (RBD) of S1. Thus, RBD can transiently hide or expose the determinants of receptor binding through receptor-inaccessible state or receptor-accessible state, respectively (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Once the virus has entered to the host cell, the replication-transcription complex (RTC) is organized in double-membrane vesicles to initiate transcription of polyprotein 1a/1ab (pp1a/pp1ab). These pp1a/pp1ab proteins encode chymotrypsin-like protease (3CLpro), main protease (Mpro), and papain-like proteases for the production of non-structural proteins (nsps) (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Trans-membrane helical segments in the ORF1ab region encodes for nsp2 and nsp3 (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). The structural proteins and nsps play a role in the pathogenicity of SARS-CoV-2 by blocking the innate immune response and assembly and release of newly synthesized virions (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>).
</p>
