<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Maximum phylogenetic information would be obtained by studying whole DENV genomes. However, available DENV whole genomes from Asia have insufficient coverage through time and space for reliable analysis, and most available sequences comprise partial or complete coding E gene sequences. In order to generate a data set with both acceptable phylogenetic diversity and spatiotemporal sampling, we used DENV E gene sequences in subsequent analyses. DENV (DENV-1 to DENV-3) envelope (E) gene sequences with known collection dates and locations of sampling in Asia were collected from GenBank. DENV-4 was not included in this study because too few samples were available (only 64 sequences from 11 countries; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005694.g001">Fig 1</xref>). The remaining strains comprised a total of 2,202 sequences sampled between 1956 and 2015, from 20 distinct countries or geographic regions (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005694.g001">Fig 1</xref>). Sequences were grouped by serotype and aligned separately using MAFFT [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005694.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Recombination was inspected using the methods implemented in RDP3 and SimPlot [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005694.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. After removing duplicate and recombinant strains, the final data set contained 1,272 DENV-1 sequences, 628 DENV-2 sequences and 302 DENV-3 sequences. In the complete sequence dataset, some countries, such as Vietnam, Cambodia, Thailand, and Singapore, were over-represented. In order to control for possible bias from uneven sampling, we randomly subsampled the complete sequence datasets by location and sampling time. At most 10 sequences were sampled per country and per year in order to create a more equitable spatio-temporal sampling distribution. After sub-sampling, the total number of sequences analyzed here was 327 for DENV-1, 357 for DENV-2, and 202 for DENV-3, sampled over a total of 59 years (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0005694.s001">S1 Fig</xref>). Details of the sequences in each data set, including information on the year of isolation, sampling location, and accession numbers, are provided in Supplementary Information (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0005694.s007">S1 Table</xref>).
</p>
