<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Numerous nucleoside analogues have recently been explored as antiviral agents against ZIKV [
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-11-00365" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-11-00365" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-11-00365" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-11-00365" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-11-00365" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-11-00365" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. However, many of these compounds were tested in either cell-free systems or using cells that are not clinically relevant for the disease (such as Vero cells). Further, sofosbuvir is the only FDA approved inhibitor tested against ZIKV thus far in ProTide form. In addition, recent work by our group and others has suggested that sofosbuvir and ProTides in general have differential activity depending on the cell line used, which may be linked to the cell-specific metabolism of ProTides [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-11-00365" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-11-00365" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In this work, we chemically synthesized a library of 13 ProTides and tested them for activity against ZIKV in human neural stem cells, a disease-specific cell model of infection. Interestingly, the activity of 2′-
 <italic>C</italic>-modified aryloxyl phosphoramidate ProTides was strongly biased towards uridylate derivatives, with only modest activity observed for the 2′-
 <italic>C</italic>-modified adenylate and cytidylate aryloxyl phosphoramidate ProTides we tested. Changing the aryloxyl phosphoramidate masking group to a 2-(methylthio)ethyl phosphoramidate abolished the activity of the 2′-
 <italic>C</italic>-methyluridine ProTide, a representative hit from our library. In a head-to-head comparison between the 2′-
 <italic>C</italic>-methyluridine aryloxyl phosphoramidate ProTide and sofosbuvir, better suppression of viral titers was observed for the former compound. In addition, better protection from ZIKV-induced cytopathic effect was observed for the 2′-
 <italic>C</italic>-methyluridine aryloxyl phosphoramidate ProTide over sofosbuvir in a highly ZIKV-susceptible stem cell model of infection with strong phenotypic changes during ZIKV infection. These results represent the first broad study of nucleoside analogue ProTides against ZIKV.
</p>
