<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <bold>
  <italic>Plaque reduction neutralisation test (PRNT).</italic>
 </bold> The PRNT procedure for determining the titre of RSV neutralising antibodies has been described previously 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
 </sup>. The method incorporated a step in which serum samples were incubated at 56°C in a water bath for 30 minutes to inactivate complement cascade proteins. Each serum sample was repeatedly diluted 2-fold over ten consecutive dilutions and mixed with an equal volume of 50 plaque forming units (pfu) of RSV A2 virus (RSVA2 and Hep2 cells were a kind donation from Dr. Patricia Cane while she worked at the Health Protection Agency, UK). The virus-serum mixture (50µl per well) was dispensed over a confluent monolayer of Hep2 cells in a 96 well culture plate, incubated at 37°C for 1 hour and then underwent 4-hour cycles of rotation on an angled (about 30°) rotating platform (about 40 rev/minute) for 10 minutes and incubation in a 37°C CO 
 <sub>2</sub> incubator for 30 minutes. The plate was then incubated for 48 hours in a 37°C CO 
 <sub>2</sub> incubator. Fixation of cells was done by the addition of 100µl of fixation reagent (30% methanol+70% acetone). Plaques were detected by addition of a primary antibody (RSV F protein mouse monoclonal-BIO-RAD, Catalogue# MCA490) solution diluted 1:500 in PBS with 2 hours incubation at 37°C, followed by an addition of a 100µl/well of an anti-mouse HRP-conjugated secondary antibody (170-5047 Immun-Star Goat Anti-Mouse (GAM)- IgG (H/L) polyclonal antibody HRP–BIORAD) solution diluted 1:1000 in Phosphate Buffered Saline (PBS) with 1 hour incubation at room temperature. After each step, plates were washed manually three times using 200µl/well PBS buffer. Plaques were visualised by addition of 100µl/well detection reagent. This consisted of 16 µl of hydrogen peroxide and 0.6ml of 3-amino-9-ethlycarbazole 3.3mg/ml solution (20mg 3-amino-9-ethlycarbazole tablet were dissolved in 6.06ml of dimethyl sulphoxide (DMSO) to give a 3.3mg/ml solution) to 10ml of 20mM sodium acetate solution (pH 5.0-5.5). Reading and counting of the brown-stained RSV micro-plaques was done using an ELISpot reader (Autoimmun Diagnostika GmbH, Germany).
</p>
