<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <bold>
  <italic>Crude RSV lysate IgG ELISA (Crude ELISA).</italic>
 </bold> Blood samples were tested for antibody concentration with an IgG based ELISA method using crude virus extract from lab-adapted RSV A2 culture following a local standard operating procedure 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>
 </sup>. The crude virus RSV lysate preparation, optimal dilutions for RSV-A2 antigen, the serum dilutions and generation of a standard curve from a pooled adult serum were determined by a checkerboard titration as previously described 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
  <xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
 </sup>. In every run, one half of the 96 well plate (column 1-6) was coated with 50µl/well of RSV lysate (antigen), while the other half (column 7-12) was coated with 50µl/well of mock lysate (mock). The mock consisted of Hep2 cells without RSV virus prepared using same procedure as that of the RSV lysate. Plates were incubated overnight at 37°C, then blocked for 1 hour with 200µl/well of 5% skimmed milk at 37°C. Blocking buffer was flicked off. Diluted serum samples 100µl/well were dispensed to both the antigen and mock sides of the plate. The plates were washed 4 times with 200µl/well of 0.05% Tween 20 in PBS (PBS-T) using an ELISA plate washer. A secondary antibody [polyclonal antibody to human IgG heavy chains (Goat anti human IgG HRP antibody-KPL, Catalogue# 074-1002) (100µl/well) diluted 1:1000 in PBS buffer was added to each well and incubated for 1 hour at room temperature. The reaction was developed using 50µl/well of Ortho-Phenylenediamine dihydrochloride (OPD, Catalogue# P8412-100TAB, Sigma-Aldrich) solution as substrate (prepared just before use in the ratio 1mg of OPD in 1 ml of PBS and 1ul of hydrogen peroxide). The intensity of colour developed was read at 490nm using an ELISA reader (SYNERGY 4, BioTeK). All samples were run in duplicate to monitor reproducibility of results and variability arising from pipetting. Positive and negative controls were run on every plate and plotted on a graph over time to check for antigen deterioration of the standards or coating antigen. The OD values of the mock were subtracted from the OD values of the antigen lysate to give the final OD value of the serum sample. OD values of the standard serum dilutions were assigned arbitrary unit (AU) values. Serum samples were assigned arbitrary units of RSV specific IgG by comparison against a standard curve generated from the pooled adult serum (serum standard) tested in each ELISA plate.
</p>
