<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A recent study screened 83 chemical structures from TCM compounds and found that theaflavin (ZINC3978446) has a low idock score (−9.11 kcal·mol
 <sup>−1</sup>) and binding energy (−8.8 kcal·mol
 <sup>−1</sup>) in the catalytic pocket of SARS‐CoV‐2 RdRP. The results from the protein‐ligand interaction profiler (PLIP) showed that theaflavin can form extra π‐cation interactions and hydrogen bonds with the catalytic pocket (at the site of Asp452, Lys545, Arg555, Thr556, Tyr619, Lys621, Cys622, Asp623, Arg624, and Asp760) of SARS‐CoV‐2 RdRp (Lung et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0063" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>), which indicated that theaflavin should be recognized as a lead compound for developing promising anti‐SARS‐CoV‐2 drugs. Moreover, an in silico integrative model of absorption, distribution, metabolism, and excretion (ADME) was used to screen promising ingredients or compounds from TCM for directly inhibiting SARS‐CoV‐2 (Zhang, Pomplun, et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0112" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Of the screened compounds, 13 (including kaempferol, moupinamide, and dihydrotanshinone I) that are components of TCMs were found to have potential anti‐SARS‐CoV‐2 activity related to similar possible targets, including PLpro, 3CLpro, and S protein. Furthermore, 125 TCMs were found to contain two or more of these 13 compounds, and 26 (such as Forsythiae fructus, Coptidis rhizome, and Mori cortex) of them are classically catalogued as treating viral respiratory infections. In addition, network pharmacology analysis predicted that these 26 TCMs have general roles, including regulating viral infection, immune/inflammation reactions, and the hypoxia response in vivo (Zhang, Wu, et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0111" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). The results of this approach showed that many ingredients or compounds of TCMs could be considered lead compounds for developing promising anti‐SARS‐CoV‐2 drugs. Therefore, researchers should also concentrate a certain effort on screening, discovery, and development of promising TCM compounds and extracts for the treatment of SARS‐CoV‐2.
</p>
