<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Emerging pathogen sample types, sample processing, and development of their specific extraction methods for MS-based technologies are challenging but critically important. In COVID-19, saliva, nasopharyngeal swabs (NS), gargle solution, sputum, bronchoalveolar lavage fluid (BLF), and exhaled breath condensate (EBC) can be utilized for detection of SARS-CoV-2 particles. As SARS-CoV-2 spreads via respiratory droplets, both BLF and EBC could be more appropriate biospecimens for COVID-19 diagnosis.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref99">99</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref102">102</xref>
 </sup> Inparticular, EBC with or without COVID-19 patients could be promising for SARS-CoV-2 detection. Saliva or NS or gargle solution sampling is recommended for early diagnosis; in contrast, sputum or BLF sampling should be used for detecting and monitoring COVID-19 as the lower respiratory tract yields higher viral load with disease severity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref102">102</xref>
 </sup> Urine, plasma, serum, and PBMCs from COVID-19 patients and diverse cellular models with viral infection or drug treatment can be used to interpret the molecular mechanism for diagnosis of COVID-19. During COVID-19 specimen handling, an MS lab should follow proper PPE rules, processing of inactivated virus or its containing specimens should be conducted in at least BSL-2 cabinet, and samples should only be stored in a proper designated freezer. Inactivation of SARS-CoV-2 or its containing materials is a major challenge in emerging pathogen sample preparation. However, different chemicals such as acetone, acetone/methanol, methanol/chloroform, UV at 254 nm, heat treatment of 65 °C or greater, alkaline (pH &gt; 12) or acidic (pH &lt; 3) conditions, or formalin can be used to inactivate coronavirus in controlled laboratories at biosafety level 3 (BSL3).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref103">103</xref>
 </sup> A multiomics sample preparation technique should be explored for integrated omics analysis of COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>
 </xref>). Interestingly, MPLEx (metabolite, protein, and lipid extraction) was developed for emerging pathogen including SARS corona virus to partition a single sample into three distinct parts (metabolites, proteins, and lipids) while simultaneously inactivating the virus by solubilizing and disrupting the viral envelope and denaturing viral proteins.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref27">27</xref>
 </sup> Notably, COVID-19 MS coalition of MS laboratories has been established and working since the beginning of this pandemic to provide guidance and protocols on MS technologies-based sample collection, processing, extraction, data collection, and analysis to reduce the harm caused by the SARS-CoV-2 virus pandemic. As COVID-19 continues to grow, MS-based multiomics methods should be developed to study disease prognosis, assess biomarkers for diagnosis and treatment, understand the impact of infective particles in the environment, and evaluate the response of vaccine and therapeutics.
</p>
