<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The lungs are the organs most affected by SARS‐CoV‐2 because the virus accesses host cells via the enzyme angiotensin‐converting enzyme (ACE) 2, which is most abundant in type II alveolar cells. Yet, glial cells and neurons of the central nervous system (CNS) have been reported to express ACE 2, rendering the brain a potential target of the virus [
 <xref rid="ene14257-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">6</xref>]. Knowledge about the transneuronal transport of SARS‐CoV through the olfactory bulb supports this hypothesis [
 <xref rid="ene14257-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">7</xref>]. However, whether the viral invasion of the olfactory bulbs is the neurobiological background for smell and taste disorders reported by infected patients remains to be elucidated [
 <xref rid="ene14257-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">8</xref>]. There is a report about a 56‐year‐old male in China who developed COVID‐19 and in whom the virus was detected in the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) [
 <xref rid="ene14257-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref>]. There are no clinical details outlined beyond the information that this patient recovered and was discharged from hospital. Of note, examination of SARS‐CoV‐2 in CSF is not a routine examination and may not be consistently available. The concern that patients with neuroinvasive disease and atypical CNS manifestations are likely to be just a matter of time is supported by a case of COVID‐19 associated acute necrotizing encephalopathy [
 <xref rid="ene14257-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref>]. The study of the mechanism leading to neuroaxonal injury, which may involve both direct viral damage and bystander inflammation, is critical for the development of treatment strategies. Whether ACE inhibitors, which are widely used for the treatment of hypertension, suppress the adaptive immune system and the subsequent antiviral response to SARD‐CoV‐2 is another unsolved question [
 <xref rid="ene14257-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">11</xref>].
</p>
