<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As mentioned above, two envelope glycoproteins, HA and NA, are on the surface of the influenza virion. HA is originally translated as the HA0 precursor, about 560 amino acids (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>). Subsequently, it undergoes proteolytic cleavage and glycosylation to form a heterodimerized trimer composed of three HA1 and three HA2 subunits, and approximately 350–400 trimers are found on the surface of a virion (
 <xref rid="B134" ref-type="bibr">Skehel and Wiley, 2000</xref>). On the surface of HA1 globular head, it is the RBS (residues 116–261), composed of a β-barrel motif and α-helices, which resembles a shallow pocket. The key receptor binding residues are highly conserved among different HA subtypes (
 <xref rid="B122" ref-type="bibr">Priyadarzini et al., 2012</xref>). The C-terminus of HA2 subunit is the conserved stem, which is the target of multiple neutralizing antibodies (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Ekiert et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B139" ref-type="bibr">Sui et al., 2009</xref>). As shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>, to initiate the entry process, the RBS on HA attaches the virus to cell surface receptors that contain terminal sialic-acid residues, which triggers the virion entering an endosome via endocytosis (
 <xref rid="B141" ref-type="bibr">Sun and Whittaker, 2013</xref>). The acidic environment in the endosome induces conformational change of HA, enabling the exposure of the fusion peptide on the N-terminus of HA2. Subsequently, the fusion peptide inserts into the endosomal membrane with the C-terminal transmembrane domain (TMD) anchoring HA2 in the viral envelope, to create a pre-hairpin conformation (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Bullough et al., 1994</xref>). Afterward, the HA2 subunit fold back on itself to form a hairpin that brings the two membranes closer. The hairpin further collapses into a six-helix bundle, which enables the formation of the lipid stalk and the subsequent fusion of the two membranes (
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Harrison, 2008</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>).
</p>
