<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0480">Distantly related viruses, with no discernible nucleotide or amino acid sequence identity, can sometimes be grouped on the basis of the three-dimensional structures of viral proteins. The evolutionary trace (ET) clustering method combines phylogenetic partition of sequences with structural information (
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Chakravarty et al., 2005</xref>), and it may help in identifying functionally relevant domains shared by divergent isolates in particular highly variable capsid and surface viral proteins. ET can be applied to proteins and nucleic acids, and its clustering features may reveal conserved structures that are overlooked when all sequences are compared together. As explained in Chapter 1, the great diversity of amino acid sequences recorded among viral structural proteins (several URL links in 
 <xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 7.3</xref>) are actually reduced to a limited number of morphotypes at the structural level. In another approach, the probabilities of equivalence between pairs of residues in viral proteins are converted into evolutionary distances (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Bamford et al., 2005</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib112" ref-type="bibr">Ravantti et al., 2013</xref>). The structure-based classification has grouped the coat protein of icosahedral viruses in separate classes, each of which, interestingly, embraces different domains of life (Archaea, Bacteria, and Eukarya) (
 <xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">McTavish et al., 2017</xref>). A lineage of structurally related viruses includes tailed bacteriophages and the herpesviruses, suggesting that parts of the genomes of complex viruses may have a very ancient origin. They might have belonged to viruses that infected primitive cells before the latter diverged into the domains of life that we identify in our biosphere (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Bamford et al., 2005</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib149" ref-type="bibr">Villarreal, 2005</xref>) (compare with models of virus origins in Chapter 1).
</p>
