<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par45">It was found that dietary supplementation of chromium picolinate (1500 ppb) and chromium NPs (1000 ppb) improved the performance and antibody titers against avian influenza and infectious bronchitis heat stress conditions (36 °C) in broilers (Hajializadeh et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2017</xref>). Serum samples collected from immunized chickens with formulation consisting of plasmid encoding HA gene of AIV, (A/Ck/Malaysia/5858/04 (H5N1)), formulated using biosynthesized AgNPs (4–18 nm) and PEG showed rapidly increasing antibody responses against H5 on day 14 after immunization and single oral administration of this formulation resulted in the induction of both the antibody and cell-mediated immune responses as well as enhanced cytokine production (Jazayeri et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">2012</xref>). A vaccine formulation consisting of ion channel membrane matrix protein 2 of the extracellular domain of influenza A conjugated to AuNPs with CpG oligodeoxynucleotide as a soluble adjuvant, which was delivered intranasally in mice, resulted in lung B cell activation and robust serum anti-M2e IgG response, with stimulation of both IgG1 and IgG2a subtypes. Lethal challenge of vaccinated mice with A/California/04/2009 (H1N1pdm) pandemic strain, A/Victoria/3/75 (H3N2), and the highly pathogenic AIV A/Vietnam/1203/2004 (H5N1) resulted in 100, 92, and 100% protection (Tao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR216">2017</xref>). Considering a very important role of mucosal immunity in the antiviral immune response, AgNPs biofabricated using 
 <italic>Cinnamomum cassia</italic> extract showed enhanced antiviral activity against highly pathogenic AIV subtype H7N3, when incubated with the virus prior to infection as well as introduced to cells after infection, whereby the tested concentrations of extract and AgNPs (up to 500 μg/mL) were found to be nontoxic to Vero cells (Fatima et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2016</xref>). For complexity, it is necessary to mention (as was discussed above) that Fujimori et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2012</xref>) described antiviral activity of CuI NPs against influenza A virus of swine origin H1N1.
</p>
