<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par48">Vaccination of chickens with nonencapsulated AIV combined with PLGA-encapsulated CpG oligodeoxynucleotides, CpG 2007, resulted in qualitatively and quantitatively augmented antibody responses manifested as a reduction in virus shedding compared to the encapsulated AIV combined with PLGA-encapsulated CpG 2007 formulation (Singh et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR204">2016a</xref>). Similarly, nonencapsulated CpG 2007 in inactivated AIV vaccines administered by the intramuscular route generated higher antibody responses compared to the CpG 2007 encapsulated in PLGA, while PLGA-encapsulated CpG 2007 in AIV vaccines administered by the aerosol route elicited higher mucosal responses compared to nonencapsulated CpG 2007 (Singh et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR203">2016b</xref>). Seok et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR194">2017</xref>) designed an intradermal pH1N1 DNA vaccine delivery platform using microneedles coated with a polyplex-containing PLGA/polyethyleneimine NPs inducing a greater humoral immune response due to rapid dissolution of the coated polyplex in porcine skin (within 5 min) than that observed at intramuscular polyplex delivery or naked pH1N1 DNA vaccine delivery by a dry-coated microneedles. Consequently, intradermal delivery of DNA vaccines within a cationic polyplex coated on microneedles has potential in skin immunizations. Polyanhydride NPs encapsulating subunit proteins can enhance humoral and cell-mediated immunity and provide protection upon lethal challenge. A robust immunogen, recombinant H5 hemagglutinin trimer (H5
 <sub>3</sub>) encapsulated into polyanhydride NPs used to immunizing mice induced high neutralizing antibody titers and enhanced CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cell recall responses in mice and H5
 <sub>3</sub>-based polyanhydride nanovaccine induced protective immunity against a low-pathogenic H5N1 viral challenge (Ross et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR188">2015</xref>). Similarly, intranasal delivery of nanovaccine consisting of inactivated SwIV encapsulated in polyanhydride NPs enhanced antigen-specific cellular immune response in pigs, with promise to induce cross-protective immunity (Dhakal et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2017a</xref>), and inactivated SwIV encapsulated in PLGA NPs (200–300 nm diameter) administered via intranasal route reduced the clinical disease and induced cross-protective cell-mediated immune response in a pig model as well (Dhakal et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2017b</xref>).
</p>
