<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Once planted at the beginning of a season, plants are harvested at rate 
 <italic>h</italic>. Additional plants may be replanted at rate 
 <italic>μ</italic>, with material obtained from the grower’s own field, through trade with the owner of another field (
 <italic>q</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub> = 1), or from a clean-seed system (
 <italic>q</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub> = 0). When cuttings are not obtained from the grower’s own field, the proportion of cuttings in field 
 <italic>i</italic> obtained from every field 
 <italic>j</italic> is given by 
 <italic>τ</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>ij</italic>
 </sub>, so that 
 <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005654.e002">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1005654.e002.jpg" id="pcbi.1005654.e002g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M2">
    <mrow>
     <mstyle displaystyle="false">
      <msubsup>
       <mo>∑</mo>
       <mrow>
        <mi>j</mi>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mn>1</mn>
       </mrow>
       <mrow>
        <mi>N</mi>
       </mrow>
      </msubsup>
     </mstyle>
     <mrow>
      <msub>
       <mrow>
        <mi>τ</mi>
       </mrow>
       <mrow>
        <mi>i</mi>
        <mi>j</mi>
       </mrow>
      </msub>
     </mrow>
    </mrow>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mn>1</mn>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </inline-formula>. In the absence of a comprehensive set of empirical data, we assume that trade networks can be generated through a dispersal kernel describing the probability of planting material movement between fields. For a grower at field 
 <italic>i</italic> trading with neighbours, each neighbouring field 
 <italic>j</italic> is ranked according to 
 <inline-formula id="pcbi.1005654.e003">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1005654.e003.jpg" id="pcbi.1005654.e003g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M3">
    <msub>
     <mrow>
      <mi>ρ</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mi>i</mi>
      <mi>j</mi>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mi>r</mi>
    <msup>
     <mrow>
      <mi>e</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mfrac>
       <mrow>
        <mo>−</mo>
        <msub>
         <mrow>
          <mi>d</mi>
         </mrow>
         <mrow>
          <mi>i</mi>
          <mi>j</mi>
         </mrow>
        </msub>
       </mrow>
       <mrow>
        <msub>
         <mrow>
          <mi>d</mi>
         </mrow>
         <mrow>
          <mi>m</mi>
          <mi>a</mi>
          <mi>x</mi>
         </mrow>
        </msub>
       </mrow>
      </mfrac>
     </mrow>
    </msup>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </inline-formula> for 
 <italic>d</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>max</italic>
 </sub> the maximum distance between any two fields and random variable 
 <italic>r</italic> ∈ [0,1] taken for simplicity from a uniform distribution, where grower 
 <italic>i</italic> trades with a random number of the highest ranked neighbours from a uniform distribution up to a given maximum. We note that the dispersal kernel implicit in the ranking does not qualitatively affect our results. Dispersal based on both an exploratory data set and a fat-tailed dispersal kernel, resulting in more frequent long-distance transactions, yield similar results. This is likely due to the fact that all assumed trade acts over a significantly larger scale than whitefly dispersal, in part due to the field density. See 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1005654.s003">S3 Appendix</xref> for different trade dispersal assumptions. The level of infection in the material obtained from field 
 <italic>j</italic> is determined by 
 <italic>P</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>j</italic>
 </sub> and 
 <italic>C</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>j</italic>
 </sub>, the total number of uninfected and infected plants respectively harvested from field 
 <italic>j</italic> in the previous season. Latently infected harvested plants may also have sufficiently low viral load as to undergo reversion at rate 
 <italic>η</italic>, although no data yet exist for this parameter and we assume it to be zero. In this way, the proportion of infected cuttings replanted depends on whether or not the grower is using a clean-seed system, and the incidence of infection in material that the grower has collected both from her own and her neighbour’s fields. Plants may additionally be infected through contact with infectious vectors, which infect uninfected plants at density-dependent rate 
 <italic>β</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>p</italic>
 </sub>. Once infected, latently infected plants progress to a fully infectious state at rate 
 <italic>γ</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>p</italic>
 </sub>, when they may be removed by roguing at rate 
 <italic>g</italic>.
</p>
