<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Saliphenylhalamide (SaliPhe), a viral entry blocker which targets vacuolar ATPase and prevents the acidification of endosomes, also inhibits ZIKV replication in human retinal pigment epithelial (RPE) cells, which are natural targets for ZIKV infection [
 <xref rid="B102-pharmaceuticals-12-00101" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>] with an EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 1 μM [
 <xref rid="B103-pharmaceuticals-12-00101" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. Similarly, obatoclax mesylate, also known as GX15-070, is an experimental drug for the treatment of different types of cancer. This drug is an inhibitor of the Bcl-2 family of proteins that targets cellular Mcl-1 and inhibits endocytosis, thus inducing apoptosis. Obatoclax mesylate displays an EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 0.3 μM against ZIKV. Niclosamide is an FDA-approved drug, formerly designated in pregnancy category B, that has been used for more than 50 years showing acceptable safety. It has been broadly used in the treatment of intestinal helminthiasis. This drug blocks the acidification of endosomes, using a mechanism that has not yet been fully elucidated [
 <xref rid="B104-pharmaceuticals-12-00101" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. In glioblastoma SNB-19 cells, the EC
 <sub>50</sub> against ZIKV was 0.37 μM based on the measurement of intracellular viral RNA [
 <xref rid="B105-pharmaceuticals-12-00101" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. PHA-690509, is an investigational cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor which inhibited ZIKV infection with an EC
 <sub>50</sub> value of 1.72 μM [
 <xref rid="B105-pharmaceuticals-12-00101" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. This drug was detected by Xu et al. as part of a large drug repurposing screen for ZIKV. The authors measured ZIKV-induced caspase-3 activity and cell viability from over 6000 approved drugs and drug candidate compounds using human neural cells. This study led to the identification of small molecules that either protect against cell death in multiple neural cell types or inhibit ZIKV replication. Among them, seliciclib (a purine analog) and RGB-286147 inhibited ZIKV infection at sub-micromolar concentrations [
 <xref rid="B105-pharmaceuticals-12-00101" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. 
</p>
