<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">Currently, microbial secondary metabolites are well established to contain many compounds with structural and chemical diversity. Professor Umezawa 
 <italic>et al.</italic> postulated that certain compounds among them may target enzyme reactions and started to search for enzyme inhibitors from a microbial fermentation broth in 1965. This pioneering work has contributed to various biochemical advances and to therapeutic approaches for certain diseases. For example, in the field of virus research, leupeptin, an inhibitor of serine and cysteine proteases from 
 <italic>Streptomyces roseus</italic>,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup> has been shown to prevent glycoprotein-mediated entry of Marburg virus, suggesting the role of unknown host proteases in glycoprotein activation.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup> Antipain and elastatinal, inhibitors of serine and cysteine proteases from 
 <italic>Actinomycetes</italic>,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup> were used to inhibit poliovirus 2A protease.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup> Notably, pepstatin, an aspartic proteinase inhibitor isolated from several species of 
 <italic>Streptomyces</italic>,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup> made a significant contribution to the development of a key class of anti-HIV drugs in highly active antiretroviral therapy. HIV proteinase processes viral polyproteins to generate mature proteins and is essential for the virus life cycle. The acetyl-derivative of pepstatin has been reported to be highly effective against HIV protease through a transition state mimic, which led to the rational design of peptide-based protease inhibitors.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup> Furthermore, siastatin B, an analog of sialic acid, was isolated from 
 <italic>Streptomyces verticillus</italic> var. 
 <italic>quantum</italic> as a sialidase inhibitor.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup> Although siastatin B showed no effect on the sialidase activity of influenza virus neuraminidase (NA), its epimeric analog significantly inhibited this enzymatic activity and virus propagation i
 <italic>n vitro</italic>, as described below.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup> Together, IMC has identified many microbial products with antiviral activities, some of which have played prominent roles as a unique pharmacophores for antiviral drugs.
</p>
