<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Soon after, it was demonstrated that bi (1995) and then triple (1996) antiretroviral therapy in HIV-infected adults allows efficient and lasting inhibition of viral replication, followed by a major immunological and clinical benefit [
 <xref rid="CIT0018">18</xref>]. The close link between the level of viral replication and the risk of transmission to the child logically justified applying such therapeutic escalation to pregnant women; the infection rate steadily dropped to near zero with the use of three molecules, with an undetectable viral load at delivery (
 <xref rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>). Although there is an overall transmission rate of less than 1%, there is still a significant risk gradient depending on the duration of treatment during pregnancy (
 <xref rid="T0001">Table 1</xref>). Treatment started before pregnancy, with undetectable viral replication up to birth, is even associated with a zero risk of transmission, a finding now validated in several cohorts totaling several thousand women [
 <xref rid="CIT0019">19</xref>]. These extraordinary results – unimaginable in the darkest hours of the epidemic – have completely overshadowed the interest in planned cesareans and demonstrated to be effective before the era of antiretroviral combinations. They also made it possible to abandon intensification during labor, initially proposed in the form of a continuous infusion of zidovudine. The post-natal phase, administered to newborns, is currently maintained, although it is not known whether it is necessary if the mother was properly treated during pregnancy. In 2019, the preventive strategy in previously untreated women is still empirically based on a combination comprising two nucleoside analogs and a third molecule of one of the other classes: antiprotease, non-nucleoside reverse-transcriptase inhibitor, or integrase strand-transfer inhibitor. Alternatives have been proposed if there is resistance or intolerance (rare) to one or more of these molecules [
 <xref rid="CIT0020">20</xref>–
 <xref rid="CIT0022">22</xref>]. In a pragmatic approach, the general recommendation for women who have been effectively treated before pregnancy is to maintain the same treatment. This sometimes leads to the continuation of new molecules during pregnancy for which the toxicity data are still limited or virtually zero. The recent warning about dolutegravir (see below), the latest generation molecule, calls for caution in a context in which maximum preventive efficacy can be obtained with older molecules [
 <xref rid="CIT0023">23</xref>]. In contrast, intensification strategies are proposed if the mother has been insufficiently treated: the addition of a fourth molecule at the end of pregnancy, performance of a cesarean section before labor, perfusion of zidovudine, or intensification of the treatment of the newborn with bi or even triple therapy [
 <xref rid="CIT0024">24</xref>]. These various measures make it possible to drastically reduce the transmission rate, even if there was insufficient treatment during pregnancy. Such prevention requires proactive attention from the medical teams: the earliest possible screening for maternal infection, optimization of the choice of maternal treatment depending on possible prior resistance, assistance in taking the medication, reactivity if there is an insufficient virological result, and anticipation of the choice of treatment for the newborn. The WHO and most countries issue regularly updated guidelines that should be consulted before prescribing antiretrovirals to pregnant women and newborns [
 <xref rid="CIT0020">20</xref>–
 <xref rid="CIT0022">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0025">25</xref>] (
 <xref rid="T0002">Table 2</xref>). Beyond purely therapeutic considerations, there is also the social and administrative vulnerability of many women living with HIV that can alter the overall prevention strategy. Maternal seroconversion during pregnancy after the initial negative screening is still one of the causes of failure, and it is necessary to be aware of the need to repeat the screen if a woman is considered to have a potentially high risk of infection during pregnancy. 
</p>
