<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 1.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Pattern of immune mediators from a Zika virus (ZIKV) patient cohort in Campinas, Brazil, during the acute phase of disease. 
   <italic>A, B</italic>, Acute-phase patient samples were grouped according to ZIKV polymerase chain reaction (PCR) status (12 patients ZIKV PCR negative [Neg] and 83 ZIKV PCR positive (Pos). 
   <italic>C, D,</italic> clinical observation during hospitalization (11 patients with neurological complications [Neuro] and 84 without [Non]). Levels of immune mediators (proinflammatory cytokines, anti-inflammatory cytokines, chemokines, and growth and other factors) during acute ZIKV infection were analyzed and presented in heat maps of normalized scores. In the heat \-map presentation, the immune mediator concentrations were scaled between 0 and 1 for each measured immune mediator, and the average scaled value was then computed for each group. Selected immune mediators are depicted as Tukey box plots. One-way analyses of variance were conducted on the logarithmically transformed concentrations with Bonferroni-corrected post hoc 
   <italic>t</italic> tests; results were corrected for multiple testing using the method of Benjamini and Hochberg. *
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; .05; †
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01; ‡
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; .001. Abbreviations: BDNF, brain-derived neurotrophic factor; bNGF, beta-nerve growth factor; EGF, epidermal growth factor; FGF-2, basic fibroblast growth factor; GM-CSF, granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor; GRO-α, chemokine (C-X-C motif) ligand 1; HGF, hepatocyte growth factor; IFN, interferon; IL-1α (etc), interleukin 1α (etc); IP-10, interferon gamma-induced protein 10; LIF, leukemia inhibitory factor, MCP, monocyte chemoattractant protein; MIP, macrophage inflammatory protein; PDGF-BB, platelet-derived growth factor; PIGF, placental growth factor; RANTES, regulated on activation, normal T-expressed, and presumably secreted; SCF, stem cell factor; SDF, stromal cell-derived factor 1α; TNF, tumor necrosis factor; VEGF, vascular endothelial growth factor.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="jix26101" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
