<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<boxed-text id="B1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
 <label>Box 1</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Inclusion/exclusion criteria</title>
 </caption>
 <sec>
  <title>Inclusion criteria</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>Adults, male or female. Females must be postmenopausal defined as 12 consecutive months without menstruation.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Diagnosis based on NIA diagnostic criteria: probable AD with CDR=1, or CDR=0.5 (questionable dementia) with biomarker evidence of AD either by amyloid PET scan or CSF evidence of AD as defined by a positive Aβ, tau and phospho-tau protein profile. This criterion applies to patients with these results already available prior to recruitment, and these tests are not required or done as part of screening.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Folstein MMSE score of 18–28 (inclusive) out of 30.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>A family member or other individual who is in contact with the patient and consents to serve as informant during the study.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Patient retains capacity to consent for him/herself or retains the capacity to identify a surrogate/caregiver who will consent on his/her behalf.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>At screening, patients must test positive for serum antibodies to HSV1 or HSV2 (IgG or IgM). If the test is rated ‘equivocal’, blood will be drawn again within 6 weeks for a repeat test. If the test is equivocal or positive, the patient will be eligible.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Use of cholinesterase inhibitors and memantine is permitted. Doses of these medications need to be stable for at least 1 month prior to study entry. Psychotropic medications (other than benzodiazepines prescribed at a dose equivalent of 2 mg lorazepam daily or higher) and other medications prescribed for medical reasons will be permitted throughout the trial.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Exclusion criteria</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>Caregiver is unwilling or unable, in the opinion of the study physician, to comply with study instructions.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Patient has dementia predominantly of the non-Alzheimer’s type, including vascular dementia, frontotemporal dementia, Lewy body dementia, substance-induced dementia.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Modified Hachinski scale score greater than 4.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Current clinical diagnosis of schizophrenia, schizoaffective disorder, other psychosis, bipolar disorder or current major depression by Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 5th Edition (DSM-5) criteria. Prior history of major depression will not be exclusionary because 25% of older adults have a lifetime history of major depression.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Active suicidal intent or plan based on clinical assessment.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Current or recent (past 6 months) alcohol or substance use disorder (DSM-5 criteria).</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Current diagnosis of other major neurological disorders, including Parkinson’s disease, multiple sclerosis, Huntington’s disease and amyotrophic lateral sclerosis.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Clinical stroke with residual neurological deficits. MRI findings of cerebrovascular disease (small infarcts, lacunes, periventricular disease) in the absence of clinical stroke with residual neurological deficits will not lead to exclusion.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Acute, severe, unstable medical illness. For cancer, patients with active illness or metastases in the last 12 months will be excluded, but past history of successfully treated cancer will not lead to exclusion.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Sitting blood pressure &gt;160/100 mm Hg.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Renal failure as determined by an estimated GFR &lt;44 mL/min/1.73 m
     <sup>2</sup>.
    </p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Serum vitamin B12 levels below the normal range.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Patients with thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura/haemolytic uremic syndrome will be excluded (specific exclusion for valacyclovir as per FDA package insert).</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Use of benzodiapezines in lorazepam equivalent doses equal to or greater than 2 mg daily.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>For patients consenting to LP (estimated 33% of sample), this procedure will be conducted if there is no lower spinal malformation or specific contraindication to LP such as taking prescription anticoagulants.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Metal implants and pacemaker that are not deemed to be compatible by MRI staff, and claustrophobia to the degree that the patient refuses MRI.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Radiation exposure in the prior 12 months that is above the permitted threshold. This will be determined by the study physician and PET Center Centre staff based on questionnaires and medical records.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Severe vision or hearing impairment that would prevent the participant from providing a valid performance on neuropsychological testing.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Olfaction component: current upper respiratory infection (patient tested as soon as this improves), current smoker &gt;1 pack daily (past smoking has been shown not to affect UPSIT scores, UPSIT score &lt;12/40 (10 out of 40 is scored by chance in this multiple-choice test) indicating congenital anosmia. Patients excluded from the olfaction component participate in the main protocol and all other study procedures.</p>
    <p>Aβ, amyloid beta-protein; AD, Alzheimer’s disease; CDR, Clinical Dementia Rating; CSF, cerebrospinal fluid; FDA, Food and Drug Administration; GFR, glomerular filtration rate; HSV1, herpes simplex virus-1; LP, lumbar puncture; MMSE, Mini Mental Status Examination; NIA, National Institute on Ageing; PET, positron emission tomography; TSH, thyroid stimulating hormone; UPSIT, University of Pennsylvania Smell Identification Test.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
</boxed-text>
