<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The viral outbreak of CoVID-19, declared as a global pandemic, continues to overwhelm the healthcare system with increasing number of patients presenting with clinical symptoms of this coronavirus. This increasing rate of incidence of this contagion presents with its own challenges, burdening healthcare institutions, global economy, impacting the physical and mental health of people worldwide. Although several strategies have been adopted to mitigate the effects of this viral outbreak, the rural population has been largely ignored, despite the high risks of morbidity and mortality among this population. This review aims to provide a clinical insight into the outbreak of CoVID-19, outlining the pathogenesis, transmission dynamics, and clinical characteristics of the patients tested positive for this virus (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-17-04279-f001">Figure 1</xref>). Although the development of a SARS-CoV-2-specific vaccines is still under clinical trials, this review discusses pharmacological and non-pharmacological interventions that are widely being used by healthcare professionals to manage the symptoms and combat the impact of the virus on patients. Finally, this review provides an outline of the challenges and implications of CoVID-19 in a rural population, given that a large percentage of the population in a rural setting are frail subjects with pre-existing comorbidities, individuals with obesity, and individuals having a smoking history, who are at higher risk of mortality. Considering the age stratification, pre-existing co-morbidities such as obesity, smoking status along with limited healthcare access, resources, and health literacy, the rural population might be at a significant risk. Because of the dynamic nature of the pandemic, a conceptual framework is required for current and post-pandemic stages of CoVID-19, inclusive of strategies to mitigate the risks of this contagion in the rural population.
</p>
