<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>H9N2 viruses are fairly regularly isolated from humans, with the first reported human cases concerning two children, in Hong Kong in 1999, who exhibited flu-like symptoms. Retrospectively, several H9N2 infections on the Chinese mainland were also found to have occurred in 1998 [
 <xref rid="B115-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>,
 <xref rid="B116-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>]. Subsequent human infections have been reported from Egypt, Bangladesh, Pakistan and Oman [
 <xref rid="B117-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B120-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>]. Human H9N2 infections are generally mild and there has only been a single reported death due to the virus, likely due to an underlying health condition [
 <xref rid="B121-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>]. Human H9N2 cases are more often isolated during periods where other more pathogenic zoonotic influenza viruses are being surveyed for. Many H9N2 cases have been found recently in China, most likely due to the ongoing screening for zoonotic H7N9, and in Egypt and Bangladesh due to ongoing screening for zoonotic H5N1 infections (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00620-f002">Figure 2</xref>a) [
 <xref rid="B42-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]. As of June 2019, there have been a total of 59 laboratory-confirmed human H9N2 infections with over half of those being recorded since 2015 (see 
 <xref rid="viruses-11-00620-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00620-f002">Figure 2</xref>a). The majority of those with confirmed infections were young children (39 of 56 cases were aged 8 years or below, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00620-f002">Figure 2</xref>b), the median age of infection was 4-years-old, while the mean age was 14. Both sexes appeared to get infected at similar rates (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00620-f002">Figure 2</xref>b). This age and sex distribution is in stark contrast to that of the first wave of H7N9, which predominantly infected the elderly and males, and H5N1 viruses, which infected mostly young adults [
 <xref rid="B122-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>,
 <xref rid="B123-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>]. In the majority of infections, contact with poultry was confirmed as the likely source (29 with confirmed poultry exposure compared to 11 without any known poultry exposure, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00620-f002">Figure 2</xref>c). However, unlike H7N9, there are still no confirmed reports of human-to-human transmission of H9N2 viruses [
 <xref rid="B124-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]. Virus sequencing show that all human H9N2 isolates contain HA genes from the G1-W, G1-E or BJ94 lineages with virus isolates highly related to local poultry isolates [
 <xref rid="B5-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,
 <xref rid="B115-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>].
</p>
