<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A prerequisite for plant‐made mAbs to be competitive alternatives of those made in mammalian cells is their robust production in plants. While mAb production in mammalian cell culture is highly efficient, production costs are immense ($80 000–160 000/kg protein; Shevitz 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="pbi13194-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>) and, in many cases, unaffordable to people in many parts of the world. In contrast, production of plant‐derived proteins does not require expensive cell‐culture facilities, bioreactors, or tissue culture media and production can be scaled up for commercial manufacture without prohibitive capital investments (Chen and Davis, 
 <xref rid="pbi13194-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Tuse 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="pbi13194-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Indeed, recent case studies have confirmed that 
 <italic>N. benthamiana</italic>‐based platforms can substantially reduce the upstream production cost of biologics to as low as $1.00–2.00 per kilogram of protein (Tuse 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="pbi13194-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Our results indicated that both WTpCHKVmab and ∆XFpCHKVmab accumulated in 
 <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves to levels comparable to other mAbs produced in plants with non‐optimized codons (Chen and Lai, 
 <xref rid="pbi13194-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2014b</xref>). Under optimized conditions, however, mAbs can be produced up to 0.8–4.8 mg/g LFW, a commercially feasible level for mAb manufacturing (Bendandi 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="pbi13194-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Lai 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="pbi13194-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). Our results also showed that WTpCHKVmab and ∆XFpCHKVmab were readily extracted and purified from leaves with a scalable process that is compliant to current Good Manufacturing Practice (cGMP) regulations (Lai and Chen, 
 <xref rid="pbi13194-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Lai 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="pbi13194-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). In fact, biotechnology companies, such as Fraunhofer IME, already have a cGMP manufacturing licence for plant‐produced mAbs (Ma 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="pbi13194-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) and can easily adopt the downstream process we developed here for the future manufacturing of CHKVmabs. Together, these results indicate that similar to CHIKV vaccine development (Cardona‐Ospina 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="pbi13194-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Salazar‐Gonzalez 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="pbi13194-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>), the 
 <italic>N. benthamiana</italic>‐based plant system has the potential to produce anti‐CHIKV mAbs with favourable yield and cost, which will markedly increase the affordability of mAb‐based CHIKV drugs to people in the developing world, where the majority of CHIKV cases occurs.
</p>
