<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Receptor binding is one of the major determinants of tissue tropism and host range for CoVs. A study showed that CoVs utilize existing cell surface enzymes as their binding receptors, such as the ACE2 receptor for SARS‐CoV and the dipeptidyl peptidase 4 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/ObjectDisplayForward?objectId=1612" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">DPP4</ext-link>) receptor for MERS‐CoV (Fung &amp; Liu, 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). Recently, a study found that SARS‐CoV‐2 can enter into the same set of cell lines as SARS‐CoV, suggesting that they have a similar receptor, ACE2. The results of sequence analysis showed that some but not all SARS‐CoV‐2 clusters can use ACE2 for host cell entry (Cao, Li et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). According to receptor binding motif (RBM) analysis, the majority of amino acid residues essential for ACE2 binding were retained in the S protein of SARS‐CoV‐2, which was consistent with a previous conclusion that the virus used ACE2 for host cell entry (Yan et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0106" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). In agreement with these findings, SARS‐CoV‐2 uses ACE2 for cellular entry, similar to SARS‐CoV. Therefore, targeting ACE2 can prevent the replication of SARS‐CoV‐2, which can be regarded as a potential therapeutic strategy that needs to be studied in depth. A recent hypothesis proposed that ACE inhibitors (ACEIs), such as 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/LigandDisplayForward?ligandId=5158" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">captopril</ext-link> and 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/LigandDisplayForward?ligandId=6322" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">enalapril</ext-link>, or angiotensin 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/ObjectDisplayForward?objectId=34" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">AT
  <sub>1</sub> receptor
 </ext-link> antagonists, including 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/LigandDisplayForward?ligandId=590" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">losartan</ext-link> and 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/LigandDisplayForward?ligandId=3937" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">valsartan</ext-link>, might be beneficial for those patients who experienced pneumonia induced by SARS‐CoV‐2 (Sun, et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0089" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). However, unfortunately, this is just a plausible speculation without basic or clinical research verification. At present, researchers envision administering a type of antibody that could bind to the host cell membrane ACE2 protein, thus preventing the entry and subsequent infection by SARS‐CoV‐2. This promising intervention strategy was shown to significantly block viral entry and replication in experiments, but additional tests are needed to identify any anti‐SARS‐CoV‐2 infection effects (Li et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). Alternatively, people could simply develop a single chain variable fragment (scFv) that binds to the ACE2 protein to inhibit its binding with SARS‐CoV‐2. In addition, VHH domains or nanobodies from camelids are two possible choices for consideration as well (Desmyter et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). A potentially more promising strategy was proposed by a researcher, who claimed that an antibody‐like molecule could be created that would bind to the virus itself rather than protecting host cells against infection. Based on this strategy, researchers proposed using clinical‐grade soluble human ACE2 (hrsACE2) to bind the S protein of SARS‐CoV‐2, thereby neutralizing the virus. Experiments using SARS‐CoV indicated that this strategy is quite promising and it would be feasible to inhibit SARS‐CoV‐2 infection of cells, including Vero‐E6 cells, human capillary organoids, and human kidney organoids, using the hrsACE2, in a dose‐dependent manner (Vanessa, 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0092" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). As ACE2 is already a valuable therapeutic target and hrsACE2 shows good therapeutic properties in vitro, it may be valuable to fuse hrsACE2 to an immunoadhesin to form an immunoglobulin‐Fc domain to prolong the availability of the circulating molecule and boost immune system functions to fight SARS‐CoV‐2 infection. This research offers solid evidence that hrsACE2‐immunoglobulin‐Fc may similarly suppress SARS‐CoV‐2 both in vitro and potentially in patients (Kruse, 
 <xref rid="bph15092-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Overall, the therapeutic strategies outlined above indicated that ACE2 must be a potential therapeutic target in the treatment of SARS‐CoV‐2. Meanwhile, an ACE2 antibody, ACE2‐scFv, ACE2 nanobody, and ACE2‐Fc may be promising anti‐SARS‐CoV‐2 drugs after animal testing and clinical trials.
</p>
