<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The fact that after 90 years of massive efforts, there is still no efficient therapy or comprehensive vaccination, combined with the many questions regarding influenza pathology that are still open, has motivated investigators to try new, in some cases seemingly irrelevant, experimental models. Indeed, models such as single-cell organisms (yeast), or invertebrates, such as 
 <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> (
 <italic>Drosophila</italic>) and aquatic vertebrates, such as zebrafish, appear to be not legitimate for studying a human-infecting virus. They do provide, nevertheless, advantages, which have contributed to our understanding of important aspects of viral-host interactions and viral replication [
 <xref rid="B10-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Some of these advantages are unique to these systems and are derived from the fact that they are lower organisms in the evolutionary tree and consequently much simpler relative to mammals. An advantage that is derived from this simplicity is the widespread use of these organisms in basic biological research, which has led to the generation of sophisticated technology, libraries, mutants and information about the system, which are readily available. Some of these systems are also permissive for efficient and rapid genetic screens and for drug screening. The need for genetic screens and other large-scale approaches is essential to identify the numerous effects of the virus on host systems, achieved through close functional and structural connections with the biochemical machinery of the host. In addition to the simple animal models, another less used system in influenza research is that of primary human tissue cultures [
 <xref rid="B12-pharmaceuticals-12-00147" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The relevance of such cells is obvious and they may replace some of the many studies that use cell lines of dogs and mice, and the human cell lines derived from cancerous cells. A further advantage of using primary cultures is that they can be isolated from patients and can be used for studying the disease at an individual level.
</p>
