<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">Adoptive transfer of antigen-specific T cells has been developed for the treatment of cancers, autoimmunity, and viral infections including hepatitis B virus (HBV), hepatitis C virus (HCV), and cytomegalovirus (CMV) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. In this approach, anti-viral-specific T cell clones are generated, expanded, and purified in vitro [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. It is shown that engineered SARS-specific CD8+ T cells had normal activity and function and may be a potential therapeutic tool for SARS infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Recently, it has been indicated that the number of CD8+ T cells decreased dramatically and the ratio of CD4+/CD8+ T cells increased during the SARS-CoV-2 infection. This decrease in the number of CD8+ lymphocytes has been correlated with the disease severity and clinical outcome [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. It has also indicated that CD8+ T cells and the CD4+/CD8+ ratio decreased and increased respectively after the treatment. It seems that CD8+ T cells play an important role in COVID-19 and could be a potential biomarker of the disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Due to these findings, adoptive transfer of COVID-19-specific CD8+ T cells may be an effective treatment strategy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. NK cells are innate immune cells that play a crucial role in host immune response after viral infections [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. Preprinted studies indicated that NK cell population decreased remarkably during the disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. It has been indicated that during SARS-CoV-2 infection, increased amount of IL-6 inflammatory cytokine had negative correlation with the number of NK cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Thus, it is assumed that adoptive transfer of NK cells may have an effective therapeutic approach. Therefore, recently, an ongoing phase I clinical trial has been registered in which NK cell therapy in combination with conventional therapies for COVID-19 patients was proposed (NCT04280224). Altogether, it seems that cell-mediated immunity plays an important role in host immune response against SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>].
</p>
