<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Translational epidemiology requires causal chain model in addressing epidemics and pandemics, which should be based on the social determinants of health (SDH), such as the conditions in environments in which people live, learn, work, worship, age and play. Specifically, these conditions reflect the availability of resources in addressing quality education, economic stability, health and healthcare needs, safe neighborhood and built environment, as well as social and community context [
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-17-04322" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. These attributes of SDH reflect the social gradient in health, implying impaired health outcomes for the socially disadvantaged such as low socio-economic status (SES) relative to the socially advantaged (wealth, income, high education). Available data on pandemic history, such as H7N9 implicate poverty, inequity, and SDH in infectious disease transmission and the associated burden of morbidity and mortality [
 <xref rid="B10-ijerph-17-04322" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The 2009 H1N1 influenza pandemic observed differential mortalities by socio-demographic [
 <xref rid="B10-ijerph-17-04322" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] as well as substantial geographic variation [
 <xref rid="B11-ijerph-17-04322" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] and population density [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-17-04322" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In addition, the H1N1 pandemic observed an increased rate of hospitalization among the poor and those residing in poor neighborhoods as well as racial/ethnic minorities in the US [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-17-04322" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Observed in the 1918–1920 flu pandemic mortality was low SES as per-head income associated with healthcare access, care utilization, nutritional status and comorbidities [
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-17-04322" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. A study on the flu pandemic in 1918 in Chicago observed significant disparities in transmission and mortality associated with socio-demographics namely population density, illiteracy, unemployment, and age. Specifically, in relation to illiteracy, the multivariable model after controlling for population density, homeownership, employment and age, showed a 32.2% increased mortality risk for every 10% increase in illiteracy [
 <xref rid="B15-ijerph-17-04322" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].
</p>
