<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Nucleic acid alignments based on amino acid code were done in Mega4 (www.megasoftware.net). Gap-free coding nucleotide sequence alignments were generated containing the novel viruses as well as reference strains, using the complete deletion option in which any site containing gaps was deleted from the data set (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S3</xref> for a list of all reference strains with isolation years, host and GenBank accession number). The data set used for inference of 
 <italic>Paramyxovviridae</italic> phylogenies comprised 559 nucleotide (nt). An additional analysis was done for only those rubulaviruses for which only a shorter 217 nt fragment could be amplified (see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2a</xref>, note that 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref> includes only rubulaviruses with complete 559 nt coverage). Bayesian phylogenies were calculated with MrBayes V3.2
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b56">56</xref> using amino acid sequences (WAG+G model) and nucleotide sequences (GTR+I+G model). Both analyses yielded identical topologies (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref>). Convergence of chains was confirmed by the PSRF statistic in MrBayes
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b57">57</xref>, as well as by visual inspection of individual traces using TRACER from the BEAST package
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b58">58</xref>. Outgroups were Rabies virus (GenBank, NC_001542) for phylogenies, including the complete family 
 <italic>Paramyxoviridae</italic>, Newcastle Disease virus for phylogenies of the genus 
 <italic>Rubulavirus</italic> (GenBank, NC_002617) and Human Parainfluenzavirus 1 (GenBank, NC_003461) for the genera 
 <italic>Henipa</italic>- and 
 <italic>Morbillivirus</italic>. In parallel to the Bayesian analyses, maximum likelihood algorithms (WAG+G substitution model, 5 gamma categories and 1,000 bootstrap replicates) were applied using PhyML V3.0
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b59">59</xref>. Trees were visualised with FigTree V1.3.1 from the BEAST package
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b58">58</xref>.
</p>
