<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Viral hepatitis is a liver inflammation responsible for about 171,000 deaths every year in the European Region. Patients may have an acute form as a recent infection, with relatively rapid onset or a chronic form. There are five main hepatitis viruses (HAV, HBV, HCV, HDV and HEV) with different ways of transmission and different impact on human health [
 <xref rid="B97-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. While HAV or HEV infection is usually mild, with most people recovering quickly and completely, infection with HBV, HCV or HDV often leads to chronic infections and progressive liver damage with the development of cirrhosis and liver cancer [
 <xref rid="B97-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. There are about 15 million people living with chronic HBV infection and about 14 million with HCV infection in the European Region [
 <xref rid="B97-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. Safe and effective vaccines for the prevention of HBV infection have been available since the 1990s. These vaccines also provide protection from HDV infection. Unfortunately, the HCV vaccine has not yet been developed [
 <xref rid="B97-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,
 <xref rid="B98-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. Many patients infected with HBV are adults born before the hepatitis B vaccine became available in the 1990s. In these cases, drug treatment is the only option [
 <xref rid="B98-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. Several nucleoside and non-nucleoside derivatives with anti-HBV (e.g., adefovir, entecavir, lamivudine, telbivudine, tenofovir) or anti-HCV activity (e.g., boceprevir, grazoprevir, elbasvir, ledipasvir, sofosbuvir, telaprevir) are in use [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B99-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>] and chronic infections with HBV and HCV can be currently controlled or even cured. Due to the costs of antiviral drugs for chronic hepatitis, access to treatment is a major obstacle in many countries and finding new, less expensive antiviral drugs is a necessity [
 <xref rid="B97-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>].
</p>
