<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Boender 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref rid="ppat.1002094-Boender1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref> have previously performed a spatial analysis of inter-farm transmission using epidemiological data from the HPAI H7N7 epidemic. They showed that risk of transmission decreased with inter-farm distance and they could map higher-risk areas for the spread of the virus. However, the epidemiological data did not permit the resolution of the pathways of transmission between farms. Our results show that the analysis of viral genetic data can complement epidemiological studies, allowing notably the identification of clusters of infections and of specific farm-to-farm transmission events. The geographical position of the farms associated with the transmission clusters identified from the phylogenetic analyses is indicated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1002094-g001">Figure 1</xref>. Most of the farms of Cluster I are located geographically close to one another, suggesting that inter-farm virus transmission during the epidemic was at least partially caused by short distance air-borne movements of virus particles 
 <xref rid="ppat.1002094-Lebarbenchon1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. However, farms of cluster III showed a combination of aggregated and dispersed geographical location, whereas Cluster II and Cluster III were more dispersed within the Gelderland area. It is possible that such transmission between farms separated by 5–15 km occurred naturally, as avian influenza viruses could persist for long periods in the environment (e.g. water or feather) 
 <xref rid="ppat.1002094-Yamamoto1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1002094-DomanskaBlicharz1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. The poultry production system with its professional contacts could also have favoured virus spread during the epidemic. Notably, some operations of farms, such as egg collection, were resumed during the epidemic and may have played a role in virus transmission 
 <xref rid="ppat.1002094-Thomas1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. We estimated that the H7N7 virus was present in poultry maybe weeks before the first outbreak, so it is possible that the virus spread via a network of contacts formed by normal poultry operations across the Gelderland area before the implementation of the transport ban. Also, it has been recently shown that many humans involved in the control of the epidemic were infected by H7N7 in farms they visited 
 <xref rid="ppat.1002094-BosMarian1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. Thus, H7N7 virus might have been transmitted between farms by infected people or by human-mediated mechanical transport. Analyzing the sequence of virus isolated from infected humans and the movements of people involved in control activities could help to determine whether human-mediated transport played a role in the inter-farm transmissions.
</p>
