<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para70">WHO has acknowledged the efforts made by the Chinese Government to investigate and contain the outbreak.
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>17</sup>
 </xref> For example, authorities rapidly initiated the first measures to isolate Wuhan, which were then extended to the whole Hubei province, stranding 35 million residents during the heavy-travel Chinese Spring Festival holidays. At the same time, the two new-built hospitals in Wuhan have been put into use, with 2600 beds for the confirmed and suspected patients with pneumonia. The decision makers also extended the holiday period and postponed school openings. Additionally, at least 68 medical teams, including more than 8000 physicians and nurses, from other provinces and cities went to the most affected Hubei province to fight against the disease side by side with the local medical staff.
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref> The Chinese Government has initiated at least 13 research programmes as an emergency measure to study the different aspects of the outbreak such as the diagnosis, treatment, and prevention of 2019-nCoV-associated disease.
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref> Novel therapeutic approaches, including treatment with allogeneic mesenchymal stem cells, are expected to progress to clinical trials involving patients with 2019-nCoV infection in a critical condition when the projects meet both ethical requirements and the principle of informed consent (eg, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04252118" id="interrefs40" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04252118</ext-link>). Furthermore, therapeutic drugs, protective equipment, and charitable funds from inside and outside of China are transported to the epidemic area to support the response. All these measures are aimed to maximise prevention and minimise the occurrence of new infections, which will help the in-time diagnosis and treatment of patients and protect the healthy population against viral infection not only in China but also in the rest of the world. China also faces other challenges, including asymptomatic carriers with 2019-nCoV might be a new potential source of infection; there will be a huge increase in people returning from trips after the Chinese Spring Festival vacation; and it may be difficult to control the outbreak due to the lack of adequate medical resources in epidemic communities and rural areas of Hubei province.
</p>
