<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This was a qualitative study comprised of six focus group discussions (FGDs) conducted in June 2017. A focus group discussion guide was developed and applied by our research team (see Appendix A), all proficient or native Spanish speakers, and included a local coordinator from Iquitos to facilitate and ensure cultural understanding. Two of the co-authors (VPS and ACM) have been conducting dengue research in Iquitos for ~35 years combined, including a dengue knowledge, attitudes, and practices survey and FGDs exploring various aspects of dengue transmission and control in the context of Iquitos [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006708.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006708.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006708.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006708.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The FGD guide was developed by local experts in our research team and focused on qualitatively exploring themes that are common in knowledge, attitudes, and practices (KAP) surveys regarding Zika virus [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006708.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006708.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The main topics explored in the FGDs were: 1) knowledge of Zika transmission, symptoms, and treatment, 2) attitudes regarding Zika, including perceived risk for and severity of Zika, and 3) common preventative practices (e.g., use of repellents or condoms), and health messages received in the community regarding Zika. Because dengue and Zika viruses share a common vector and have similar symptoms, participants were also probed to compare characteristics of Zika and dengue fever symptoms and 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> vector control campaigns in general. The Health Belief Model (HBM) was used to inform the focus group discussion guide, specifically the themes surrounding attitudes towards Zika, by focusing on perceived risk and severity; perceived risk represents a person’s perceived susceptibility of experiencing Zika virus, while perceived severity refers to the beliefs a person holds concerning the seriousness of Zika virus [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006708.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].
</p>
