<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Starting from the experience of SARS outbreak management, with the attempt to control the infection, the market was immediately closed and decontaminated the first of January, 2020. Furthermore, with the increasing of human cases, quarantine of infected or potentially infected individual was adopted, and safety guidelines were issued and publicized to the general population to reduce the chances of infection. The picture of an emerging, rapidly evolving situation quickly appeared, with information increasing day by day (Table 
 <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Unfortunately, the number of cases increased at a high rate, and by the 7th of February 31 503 lab-confirmed cases were confirmed with 638 deaths (ECDC 
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">2020a</xref>). The virus moved also outside China and human cases were detected in other Countries of Asia (221), and in different continents, such as Europe (31), America (19) and Oceania (15) (ECDC 
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">2020b</xref>). The epidemiological data allowed to estimate a transmission rate of 1.4–2.5, similar to the one observed at the beginning of the SARS outbreak and of the novel influenza virus A(H1N1)pdm09 (Read 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Clinical information suggested that severe symptoms and death are frequent in elderly, in people with comorbidity, and that infection involve mainly adults (Huang 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Li 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Data obtained from familiar outbreaks and confirmed cases reported outside of China supported the human to human transmission (Chan 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; ECDC 
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">2020c</xref>). Although it has been suggested that 2019-nCoV can be transmitted by asymptomatic patients (Rothe 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>), a clear cut demonstration is still missing. This aspect is crucial for its impact on the efficacy of virus control strategies (Kupferschmidt 
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>).
</p>
