<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par85">
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par86">Surface plasmon resonance or SPR aptasensors, which by evaluating the change of refractivity of a material bound on a surface, measures the resonance of free electrons in the metal films [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>]. Typically, the capturing aptamer is immobilized on a metal surface. As the virus binds to the aptamer, the thickness of the metal surface changes, resulting in the alteration of the refractive index. Quantification can be carried out by monitoring the difference in the angle or intensity of light after the virus is bound to the aptamer. The advantages of this method are miniaturization, automation, and absence of labelling [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>]. This method has been used for the detection of avian influenza virus (AIV) H5N1 [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>, 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>], and HIV-1 Tat protein [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par87">Calorimetric-based aptasensors use a shift in color to detect a virus. This shift can be seen by the naked eye, or it will require a spectrophotometer. These types of aptasensors are cheap, simple, usually portable, and have been used in many applications [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>]. They fall into different groups, for example, nanomaterial-based calorimetric aptasensors [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>, 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>] can use a nanomaterial as support for the aptamer or as a part of the transducer to create the signal with their assistance. Another type is the enzyme-linked aptamer assays (ELAA) which have the same base as ELISA, but use aptamers instead of antibodies as the bio-receptor or the transducer [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>]. This type has been used to detect H5N1 [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>], Zika virus [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref>], and others [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">106</xref>]. Lastly, aptamers have been used to modify lateral flow assay (LFA) for virus detection [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par88">Fluorescent aptasensors, which can be categorized into aptasesnors that respond with fluorescent intensity [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">108</xref>], or the ones that respond with fluorescence polarization [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">109</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par89">Others such as SERS based [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">110</xref>] and CL aptasensors [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">111</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
