<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A human challenge study had previously reported that viable virus could be found in the faeces four days before onset of the icteric phase of disease (i.e. jaundice) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006807.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. We therefore assumed that patients become infectious one week before the icteric phase of disease. A prior for the mean infectious period was derived from a study of faecal shedding in 11 patients with sporadic acute HEV infection acquired in Bangladesh, Vietnam, Nepal, and Japan (
 <xref rid="pntd.0006807.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006807.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]; this study found that viable HEV could be recovered from faecal samples up until 2–5 weeks after hepatitis onset. We also performed sensitivity analyses where we based this prior on duration of faecal shedding from the single patient with HEV genotype 1 in this study. The prior distribution for the latent period was based on a single observation from the same study where there was a delay of 34 days between inoculation and viable HEV in faeces. Faecal shedding of HEV in asymptomatically infected people is known to occur [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006807.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]; we assumed no difference in faecal viral shedding between symptomatic and asymptomatic individuals. We used seroprevalence data to derive an informative prior for the proportion of infections that are reported (
 <xref rid="pntd.0006807.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). By default we assumed no immunity to HEV in the IDP camp populations prior to first reported case, consistent with the absence of reports of previous HEV epidemics in Kitgum district and serological data [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006807.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. We performed multiple sensitivity analyses, considering models with: i) a different prior for the infectious period; ii) camp-specific transmission rates affected by a water and sanitation intervention (Models 2a and 2b); iii) different assumptions about the distribution of the latent and infectious periods (Models 3–5); and iv) allowing for between 10% and 30% of the population to be initially immune to HEV infection, prior to the start of the outbreak. All the above models assumed nothing about the relative importance of different modes of transmission and are consistent with both transmission mediated by a contaminated environment (though without long-term virus persistence in this environment) and direct person-to-person spread. We also compared our findings with those from a model (Model 6) explicitly accounting for a second mode of transmission, an unobserved environmental reservoir of HEV where virus may persist for longer time periods. We performed an extensive sensitivity analysis by running this model under 25 different prior assumptions representing combinations of five different assumptions about the relative importance of this environmental reservoir in the early stages of an epidemic and five different assumptions about persistence of viable virus in the environment.
</p>
