<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Antibody repertoire analysis can be used to directly incorporate host immune response for vaccine design. It combines sequence analysis with structural modeling and machine learning to predict and analyze all the antibody affinity and specificities that can be produced by an individual, which can be a valuable tool for quantitative evaluation of vaccine-induced immune responses [
 <xref rid="B30-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Though it is currently used to characterize broadly neutralizing antibody (bnAb) lineages, with the development of next-generation sequencing (NGS) technologies and systems biology, the analysis of antibody repertoire encoded by B cells in the blood or lymphoid organs can be used to understand humoral immune responses and to identify antibodies specific for antigens of interest in animal models and human vaccine trials [
 <xref rid="B30-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B87-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>,
 <xref rid="B88-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. The antibody NGS can have impact on the rational vaccine design by decoding the human immune responses and delineating B and T cell antigen receptors [
 <xref rid="B90-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>,
 <xref rid="B91-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. This approach has been well developed in HIV-1 to identify hypervariants and evolution on neutralization and binding to bnAbs [
 <xref rid="B92-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>,
 <xref rid="B93-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>] and explore the antibody lineage via phylogenetic modeling [
 <xref rid="B89-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>,
 <xref rid="B94-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. These technologies and bioinformatics tools can be applied to influenza virus vaccine design with creating library of antibody repertoire by NGS. The library then can be used in computational approaches to quantitatively measure the immune responses and further to predict the effects of vaccine candidates without completely relying on costly animal tests. 
</p>
