<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0190">According to Ayurveda, on the basis of predominance of dosha, every person has their own different constituent, and every season and the place have their identical role over the person’s 
 <italic>Prakriti</italic>. According to Ayurveda, 
 <italic>Tikshna</italic> properties can stimulate the urinary system thus increasing urine, and can cause sweating [
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. As these drugs have 
 <italic>Laghu</italic> and 
 <italic>Tikshna</italic> properties, they can cause 
 <italic>Srotoshodhana</italic>, thus can increase urination and defecation in higher doses. Due to 
 <italic>Usna Virya</italic>, it can cause 
 <italic>Pitta Vriddhi Lakshan</italic> like hyperacidity, hot or burning sensation, excessive sweating, fatigue, loss of taste and sleep disturbances. Ginger is contraindicated in the summer and autumn season. It is mentioned that 
 <italic>Chandraprabhavati</italic>, which contains 
 <italic>Sunthi, Marich</italic> and 
 <italic>Dalchini</italic>, clears fluid and 
 <italic>Kapha</italic> from 
 <italic>Mutravaha Srotas</italic> and 
 <italic>Ambuvaha Srotas</italic>; this excess of fluid can cause cystitis, burning, and painful urination. There may be too high content of sugar and albumin in the urine [
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>].These drugs seemed to increase 
 <italic>Pitta</italic>, tend to have some adverse effects such as headache, sleepiness, mild diarrhea, etc. Also, there may be hypo or hyper immune sensitivity of this formulation or occurrence of chemical incompatibility due to many chemical constituents [
 <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Though the maximum use of each herbs traditionally for a long time ensures that these herbs are safe but it is essential to determine dosage of PHF for adults and pediatrics in the form of bodyweight or dosage per kg and according to severity of disease, the person’s 
 <italic>Prakriti</italic> and his/her residing climate and region. Thus, this formulation must be evaluated using scientific methods to understand bioactive compounds responsible, their mechanism of action, and ways to regulate the activity of these compounds on COVID-19 related immunological factors. Toxicological studies and clinical trials must be done before its extensive usage.
</p>
