<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para240">The idea of a biobank network to accelerate test development and evaluation is not new. The diagnostics research group in the UNICEF/UNDP/World Bank/WHO Special Programme for Research and Training in Tropical Diseases (TDR) developed different systems of biobanking well-characterised specimens to facilitate and accelerate diagnostic development and evaluation for TDR priority diseases. Because the use of patient specimens for the development of diagnostic tests that companies could potentially make a profit from is a sensitive issue, TDR developed a set of guiding principles for its specimen banks. These principles specify that it is important to have: (1) equitable access to specimens and pathogen strains by both public and private test developers; (2) transparency of all processes; (3) ethics and respect for national laws, especially with regards to the export of samples and the need for informed consent for specimen collection and storage in accordance with the International Ethical Guidelines for Health-related Research Involving Humans prepared by the Council for International Organizations of Medical Sciences in collaboration with the WHO; (4) country ownership, whereby each country retains the ownership of the specimens and the evaluation data generated at each site but must agree to share these data across the network; and (5) fairness in compliance with the Nagoya Protocol on Access to Genetic Resources and the Fair and Equitable Sharing of Benefits Arising from their Utilization to the Convention on Biological Diversity, such as negotiated prices for countries that have contributed to test development and evaluation.
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref> To ensure the quality of specimens used in test development and evaluation, we selected biobanking sites using a set of quality criteria (
 <xref rid="box1" ref-type="boxed-text">panel 1</xref> ).
 <boxed-text id="box1">
  <label>Panel 1</label>
  <caption>
   <title>Criteria for selection of biobank network sites</title>
  </caption>
  <p id="para10">
   <list list-type="simple" id="celist10">
    <list-item id="celistitem10">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="para20">Accreditation from the International Organization for Standardization or a laboratory compliant with the Good Clinical Laboratory Practice</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="celistitem20">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="para30">Access to appropriate specimens, including specimens from control groups, and from time-series studies if possible (multiple specimens from a single individual)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="celistitem30">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="para40">Proficiency of laboratory staff in doing reference standard testing to characterise specimens, demonstrated through participation in External Quality Assessment programmes</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="celistitem40">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="para50">Robust data management system</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="celistitem50">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="para60">Robust archiving facilities, including appropriate conditions of storage such as freezers with monitored alarms</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="celistitem60">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="para70">Mechanism for timely ethics approval for specimen collection with informed consent and for the use of left-over clinical specimens for research</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
 </boxed-text>
</p>
