<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The relatively high genetic variability associated with the HVR2 was confirmed by the alignment of the predicted amino acid sequences of strains from both RSV subgroups. Of significance was the observed changes in the potential N-linked glycosylation sites, which can alter the antigenic characteristics of the viral surface protein by masking of specific epitopes from the host immunity (
 <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Collins &amp; Graham, 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Garcia-Beato et al., 1996</xref>). Thus, mutations leading to novel glycosylation sites on viral surface glycoproteins may enable immune evasion. Glycosylation site at N237 was found to be highly conserved in all ON1 strains examined in this study. In contrast, only some NA1 strains possessed N237. A gain in glycosylation at N318 was also observed for some NA1 and ON1. One reason in which NA1 in our study demonstrated more heterogeneity at positions 251 and 318 than in other studies may be attributed to our multiple years of surveillance and larger sample size. The observed variations in the potential N-linked glycosylation sites tend to be genotype-specific, and coincidentally most of the positively selected sites in the G protein were in close proximity to and, in some cases, overlapped with, predicted glycosylation motifs (i.e., at amino acid positions 237 and 274). This suggests that positive selection based on N-linked glycosylation sites may play an important role in driving viral diversity (
 <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Do et al., 2015</xref>) as was shown with residue 274, which is located within an antigenic site and is under positive selection (
 <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Eshaghi et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Cane, 1997</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Malasao et al., 2015</xref>). In summary, understanding the genetic variability in the RSV G gene is important in evaluating its evolving pathogenicity and transmission potential.
</p>
