<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para2260">Alcohol is responsible for a small but important proportion of deaths due to liver disease in Singapore. According to the GHE 2015 dataset, alcohol consumption accounted for 4·9% of all deaths due to cirrhosis and other chronic liver diseases, and for 10·8% of all deaths due to liver cancer (
 <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>).
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> According to 2016 WHO estimates, age-standardised deaths from cirrhosis in adult Singaporean men and women were 4·4 and 2·4 per 100 000 individuals per year, respectively, and 30·3% (in men) and 34·9% (in women) of these were attributable to alcohol cosnumption.
 <xref rid="bib165" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>165</sup>
 </xref> The 2010 Singapore Burden of Disease survey reported that, in patients admitted for hospital treatment with liver cirrhosis in 1991–2010, 27·6% of cases were alcohol-related and 68·5% were non-alcohol-related.
 <xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>90</sup>
 </xref> A study of 564 patients with liver cirrhosis treated in a major public hospital in Singapore showed that 11·2% of these patients were admitted because of alcohol-related liver disease.
 <xref rid="bib180" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>180</sup>
 </xref> Consequently, alcohol-related liver disease can be considered a small but important cause of liver cirrhosis. In 2016, WHO's estimates of total alcohol consumption per capita in Singaporean adults aged at least 15 years was 2·0 L of pure alcohol (3·3 L in men and 0·8 L in women) and total alcohol consumption per capita in this age group for drinkers only was 2·9 L of pure alcohol (4·0 L in men and 1·4 L in women). Overall, 6·7% of Singaporean adults aged at least 15 years (3·1% of men and 10·2% of women) never consume alcohol throughout their lives. The prevalence of heavy episodic drinking in 2016 for drinkers only (≥15 years) was 42·9% (57·4% in men and 23·5% in women).
 <xref rid="bib165" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>165</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
