<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">Similarly, the use of nanomaterials can build antimicrobial properties in textiles used in PPE. This strategy has been used to prevent the growth of microorganisms in clothes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>]. The surfaces modified by nanoscale biocides, such as quaternary ammonium or quaternary phosphonium salts, polymers or peptides, can control microorganisms through oxidation of the microbial membrane [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>]. One of the best examples of how nanotechnology can improve personal protection is the production of facemasks. Traditional facemasks have a gap between the fibres, averaging 10–30 µm, that is inadequate for avoiding virus contact, and the reduction of this gap between the fibres cause a reduction of breath and increases of both temperature and pressure, making it uncomfortable for the user [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>]. Many frontline healthcare workers have been suffering from skin damage due to the continuous use of facemasks [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]. The use of nanomaterials, such as nanofibers (composition not mentioned), can reduce breathing resistance and drop the pressure to provide wearing comfort, but at the same time protect against small particles (&lt; 50 nm) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>]. This provides much better protection than traditional surgical facemasks, which do not offer protection against particles 10–80 nm in size. For example, N95/FFP2 facemasks can only protect against particles 100–300 nm in size [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Another strategy also used to increase the personal protection of facemasks is the modification of the textile surface. The use of nanoparticles, such as copper and silver, provide antimicrobial activity and can be included in different types of fibres or materials, such as cotton, polyalkene, polyester, polyamide, polyaramide and cellulose-based polymers [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>]. Park et al. showed that silver nanoparticles (in the form of a silica hybrid composite) can be used in filters or membranes. The nanoparticles can inactivate influenza virus due to its interaction with the membrane of the virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. Fudzhimori et al. have described a technology-based on monovalent copper compound and/or iodide fine nanoparticles for antimicrobial textile products. The system can inactivate influenza virus and has potential against different viruses, such as human coronavirus or SARS-CoV [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>].
</p>
