<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <boxed-text id="box001" position="float" orientation="portrait">
  <label>Box 1.</label>
  <caption>
   <p>Glossary</p>
  </caption>
  <p>
   <list list-type="simple">
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Association index (AI):</bold> test statistic used as a means of quantifying phylogeny-trait associations i.e. given a discrete character for each tip of a phylogenetic tree, are more closely related taxa likely to share the same trait values than is expected by chance alone. Avoids the issue of lack of independence due to shared ancestry (Wang 
      <italic>et al.</italic>
      <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref80">2001</xref>).
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Metapopulation:</bold> concept describing the persistence of a species in a spatially heterogeneous environment as a balance between colonisation and extinction in loosely coupled subpopulations or ‘patches’ with different within and between-patch dynamics, which can be applied to infectious diseases (Grenfell and Harwood, 1997)
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Most recent common ancestor (MRCA):</bold> most recent individual from which all taxa in the group are directly descended.
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Oral rabies vaccination (ORV):</bold> distribution of oral rabies vaccine baits as a strategy to control the spread of wildlife rabies. Used as a control measure for wildlife rabies in North America, and Europe.
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Phylogeography:</bold> combines phylogenetics and biogeography to describe the contemporary pattern of an organism's geographic spread according to gene genealogies.
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>R</bold>
      <sub>
       <bold>0</bold>
      </sub>
      <bold>(basic reproductive number):</bold> the average number of secondary cases derived from a single infectious individual in an entirely susceptible population (Anderson and May, 1991).
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Superspreader:</bold> an individual causing a disproportionately high number of secondary cases, compared to the mean (represented by R
      <sub>0</sub>), depicted in the long tail of a frequency distribution of secondary cases (Lloyd-Smith 
      <italic>et al</italic>. 
      <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref49">2005</xref>).
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Surfing mutation model:</bold> genetic variants at the front of an advancing wave of infection are swept to high frequencies during an epidemic peak, resulting in long-term dominance of colonising genetic lineages (Excoffier and Ray, 
      <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">2008</xref>, Klopfstein 
      <italic>et al.</italic> 2006).
     </p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
 </boxed-text>
</p>
