<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Indonesia, the world’s fourth most populous country, provides an important context in which to explore the potential benefits of offering HIV partner services in prisons. Indonesia was one of the first Asian countries to develop a national HIV/AIDS strategy to prevent, diagnose, and treat HIV in prisons [
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Most of Indonesia’s ~260,000 prisoners are male [
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] and 6%-8% are people who inject drugs (PWID) [
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. HIV prevalence in male prisoners is 1.1% [
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], but higher in specialized narcotic prisons (6.5%-7.2%) where many PWID are incarcerated [
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Implementing the National Strategy has brought progress and challenges. Under Indonesian national guidelines, antiretroviral therapy (ART) is recommended for all PLHIV, including those in prison, regardless of CD4
 <sup>+</sup> cell count [
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Recent evidence suggests that a substantial proportion of PLHIV in prison are individuals who were first diagnosed and initiated treatment within prison [
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Nevertheless, HIV stigma and lack of information about the benefits of ART may contribute to low levels of ART adherence in prisons [
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], and mortality remains high among PLHIV within prison and after release [
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Likewise, harm reduction initiatives in prisons, including condom and needle-syringe distribution, and methadone treatment for opioid use disorder have achieved only modest diffusion [
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], despite ample evidence of HIV risk behaviors in prison [
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].
</p>
