<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Immunization of pigs with recombinant BoHV-4 induced good antibody responses against the NiV glycoproteins. Antigen-specific antibodies appeared earlier than those induced by the ALVAC NiV G vector and comparable titers were obtained by 42 dpv. This was also reflected in the comparison of the NiV neutralizing antibody titers between the BoHV-4-A-CMV-NiV-GΔTK and ALVAC NiV G groups. In line with previous studies comparing delivery of NiV F and G using the same vector system [
 <xref rid="B26-vaccines-08-00115" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], the BoHV-4 NiV F vector stimulated lower titers of neutralizing antibodies as assessed by a pseudotype and classical VNT. However, the NiV F immunized pig sera was the only group which demonstrated a significant inhibition of NiV glycoprotein mediated cell fusion, which models a natural route of NiV dissemination [
 <xref rid="B76-vaccines-08-00115" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>,
 <xref rid="B77-vaccines-08-00115" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Despite a high degree of conservation between the F and G protein sequences between NiV-M and NiV-B, neutralizing antibody responses appeared strongest against the homologous virus (NiV-M), suggesting the presence of both strain specific and cross-neutralizing epitopes. At the amino acid level, 98.4% sequence identity can be seen between the F protein of NiV-M and NiV-B; whereas for the G protein, the homology at the amino acid level is 95.5% [
 <xref rid="B7-vaccines-08-00115" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The high homology between F proteins could explain the similarity seen in mVNT results of BoHV-4-A-CMV-NiV-FΔTK immunized pigs between NiV strains. Furthermore, the reduction in mVNT from NiV-M to NiV-B from pigs immunized with BoHV-4-A-CMV-NiV-FΔTK and ALVAC NiV G could be attributed to the differences in sequence homology between strains. As all vaccine are based on NiV-M, it was expected to have stronger responses against the homologous virus. Low cross-neutralizing antibody titers were observed against HeV, which were surprisingly low given the cross species identify of F (98%) and G (79%) and published cross-protection between HeV sG-based vaccine and NiV.
</p>
