<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are several strengths of the current study. Our data collection process was comprehensive, and we were able to adjust the VF risk for multiple significant covariates. Despite these strengths, there were also some limitations that should be noted. First, we did not have individual viral exposure data. Second, it employed an ecological study design. As such, it was not possible to examine the exact exposure history of each individual. In addition, the community burden of viral infections is substantially underestimated in surveillance data, as most patients with EV or influenza do not seek medical care. However, because the underreporting is unlikely to vary over time, there is no evidence that this would substantially bias our results. Furthermore, the EV incidence was on a monthly basis, and an option could have been to interpolate the EV data as weekly incidences. However, the data points for EV were too scarce to obtain reliable incidence estimates. Third, there is a concern for recall bias regarding the symptoms prior to event. Patients were questioned about their symptoms during the admission to hospital. However, we have previously found that cases experience less angina within the last 12 months compared with controls.[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] Fourth, even though data were prospectively collected, we performed retrospective analyses. Fifth, patients who died outside of hospitals were not included, and the results may not be generalizable to patients who do not survive to reach the hospital. Lastly, although the strength of this study is the completeness of data via link between clinical data (the Eastern Danish Heart Registry) and Danish nationwide registries the validity of our data depends largely on the accuracy of coding. It has been documented that the coding of risk factors has high validity and specificity in the Danish National Patient Registry.[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]
</p>
