<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As in most countries of Central and South America [
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-11-00764" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], all four DENV serotypes have circulated in Panama. However, co-circulation of all serotypes in Panama was only documented for a two year period in 1998–2000, in contrast to other countries of the Americas, where it is more common to have all four serotypes in co-circulation [
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-11-00764" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Patterns of dengue serotype replacement in Panama are similar to other countries in the region [
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-11-00764" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-11-00764" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and seem to follow a cyclic pattern of re-introduction every 4 to 5 years, as in Costa Rica [
 <xref rid="B37-viruses-11-00764" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] and Trinidad and Tobago [
 <xref rid="B68-viruses-11-00764" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], with a predominant serotype dominating for 2–3 years [
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-11-00764" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. However, in Panama over the past 25 years, only one genotype per serotype appears to dominate transmission, contrasting with the co-circulation and replacement of genotypes described in Central and South America [
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-11-00764" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-11-00764" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-11-00764" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-11-00764" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-11-00764" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-11-00764" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-viruses-11-00764" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-viruses-11-00764" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Co-circulation and replacement of different clades within a genotype was clearly observed in Panama and was similar to what has been described elsewhere in Central and South America. Often when a serotype has re-emerged, circulating strains belong in a new cluster and/or lineage compared to strains that circulated previously, consistent with a pattern of intense diversification (“boom and bust” period) followed by lineage extinction (“pruning” period) and clade replacement. 
</p>
