<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Not surprisingly, then, popular culture has often tended to present epidemics as a foreign invasion (
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>2</italic>
 </xref>,
 <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>21</italic>
 </xref>), especially given the moral associations often drawn between disease and social and cultural phenomena through metaphors such as corruption, decay, and pollution (
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>11</italic>
 </xref>). For example, in the Sherlock Holmes story 
 <italic>The Giant Rat of Sumatra</italic> (not penned by Conan Doyle), Professor Moriarty prepares to import plague to Britain by acquiring infected rats from Southeast Asia (
 <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>5</italic>
 </xref>). Accordingly, in some recent Hollywood films, the direction of disease movement is typically east to west, or at least from developing to developed countries, and plays on common stereotypes, including concepts of orientalization and othering (
 <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>4</italic>
 </xref>,
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>22</italic>
 </xref>). The film 
 <italic>Contagion</italic> (2011, Steven Soderbergh), although widely lauded for its accurate depiction of the mechanisms of disease transmission and epidemiology, can be seen to neatly fit within Wald’s outbreak narrative framework, in which a pathogen is brought into the developed world after contact with migrants and visitors from lesser developed areas (
 <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>4</italic>
 </xref>,
 <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>6</italic>
 </xref>). Evie Kendal noted that the virus that hit the United States in 
 <italic>Outbreak</italic> (1995, Wolfgang Petersen) was thought to have originated in Africa, whereas in 
 <italic>Contagion</italic> and 
 <italic>The Crazies</italic> (1973, George Romero), the disease originates in Asia (
 <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>4</italic>
 </xref>).
</p>
