<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">The mechanisms of the ‘cytokine storm’ and how they contribute to fatalities reported for COVID-19 are still under investigation. Currently, it is believed that SARS-CoV-2 dampens antiviral interferon responses, which results in uncontrolled viral replication. For the other coronaviruses, SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV, the response to viral infection by type I IFN is suppressed. The influx of neutrophils and monocytes/macrophages results in hyperproduction of pro-inflammatory cytokines [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">118</xref>]. In a study of 41 patients hospitalized with COVID-19, high levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines were found, including IL-2, IL-7, G-CSF, IP-10, MCP-1, MIP-1A, and TNF-α, in the most severe cases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119">119</xref>]. This overproduction of a large number of pro-inflammatory cytokines dubbed a 'cytokine storm,' begins a cascade of events that is hard to stop. For instance, the cytokine storm can initiate viral sepsis and inflammatory-induced lung injury, which leads to other complications including pneumonitis. While ‘cytokine storms’ can overwhelm people of any age, some scientists believe that this phenomenon may explain why otherwise healthy young people died during the 1918 Spanish flu pandemic and more recently during the SARS, MERS, and H1N1 epidemics. One of the most frequently studied organisms known to cause cytokine storms is influenza a virus, particularly the pandemic subtypes. It has been shown that the H1N1 strain responsible for the 1918 pandemic induced higher levels of pro-inflammatory immune cells and cytokines in the lungs than the seasonal influenza viruses. This contributed to its high virulence and may account for the unusually high mortality rate seen among young adults during the outbreak [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120">120</xref>]. Severe influenza infections caused by highly virulent subtypes such H1N1 and H5N1 are characterized by over induction of the pro-inflammatory cytokines TNF-α, IL-1β, IL-6, IL-8, and monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 (MCP-1) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121">121</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">122</xref>], which eventually results in multiple organ dysfunction and failure and increased vascular hyperpermeability [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">122</xref>].
</p>
