<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8">Another 'multi-headed beast' sweeping its tracks is the hepatitis C virus (HCV). HCV is a positive-sense single-stranded RNA virus of the Flaviviridae family [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Although the zoonotic origins of HCV in humans remain unclear, recent and direct cross-species transmission from horses to dogs appears plausible [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Highly diverse HCV-related viruses have also been detected in bats and rodents [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], in cattle [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], and in black-and-white colobus monkeys [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. There is good news in the form of direct-acting antivirals (DAA) against the hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection, which have been shown to achieve a complete cure in &gt; 95% of cases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. It has been suggested that DAA have the potential to eliminate an infection that affects more than 71 million individuals worldwide [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. This is particularly important because many individuals do not seek treatment for constant hepatitis C because they are unaware that they are infected. Sadly, it is often a long time after the initial infection, when hepatitis C has precipitated serious health issues, that these individuals look for help. It is estimated that only 5% of HCV cases worldwide are diagnosed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. This is one reason that the development of vaccines that protect against persistent HCV infection remain a public health priority. Without access to vaccines that can limit viral transmission, even the broad use of highly effective DAA is unlikely to achieve HCV elimination. In addition, DAA treatment does not protect against reinfection, further underscoring the need for an effective vaccine [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Current preclinical and clinical trials are being carried out for two vaccines that target either the antibody or the T cell response. The next generation of vaccines is likely to involve a combination of these two strategies. The first vaccine contains a recombinant form of the virus envelope glycoproteins gpE1 and gpE2, aimed at inducing neutralizing antibodies and CD4 helper T cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. The second vaccine is vector-based and encodes nonstructural (NS) proteins of the virus (NS3-NS5) using chimpanzee adenovirus priming and a modified vaccinia Ankara (MVA) boost. These represent two of the most promising strategies: production of broadly neutralizing antibodies (bNAb) to neutralize the infectivity of the virus and generation of potent virus-specific CD4 and CD8 T cells to eliminate infected hepatocytes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. Multiple studies of HCV in humans and chimpanzees have provided strong evidence for the kinetic association between spontaneous viral clearance and the induction of a broad, sustained group of HCV-specific CD4 and CD8 T cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. As it turns out, these T cells are polyfunctional, producing multiple cytokines and effector functions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. For instance, as the infection is being cleared, virus-specific T cells develop a memory T cell phenotype that upregulates cell surface expression of the IL-7 receptor CD127 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. If the virus persists, CD8 T cells that recognize intact epitopes (i.e., epitopes that have not mutated) become exhausted and express exhaustion markers such as programmed death 1 (PD1), T-cell immunoglobulin and mucin domain-containing-3 (Tim-3), cytotoxic T-lymphocyte protein 4 (CTLA4), 2B4, CD160, KLRG1, T-cell immunoreceptor with Ig and ITIM domains (TIGIT), and CD39 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. There is an increasing amount of evidence that the specificity and potency of the early antibody response can influence the acute infection outcome and that neutralizing antibodies seem to play a part in controlling HCV during chronic infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. In particular, it is worth noting the data from studies showing that bNAb isolated from chronically infected and spontaneously resolved individuals have the capacity to block infectivity in mouse models of HCV infection, further emphasizing the important protective effect of the antibody response [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>].
</p>
