<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our global transcriptomic approach revealed the up-regulation of Siglec-1, as part of an ISG-signature enhanced in macrophages exposed to a TB-associated microenvironment. Although pulmonary active TB has been characterized as an IFN-I-driven disease (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Berry et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">McNab et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Moreira-Teixeira et al., 2018</xref>), there are no report in the literature about a role for Siglec-1 in TB or in Mtb co-infection with retroviruses. Expression of Siglec-1 is restricted to myeloid cells except circulating monocytes (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Crocker et al., 2007</xref>), and is enhanced by IFN-I (
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Puryear et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Rempel et al., 2008</xref>) and during HIV-1 infection (
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Pino et al., 2015</xref>). In addition, human alveolar macrophages are distinguished from lung interstitial macrophages by Siglec-1 expression (
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Yu et al., 2016</xref>). In this study, we determined that IFN-I present in TB-associated environment is responsible for Siglec-1 overexpression in human macrophages, which resembled that obtained in HIV-1-infected cells. While we saw a modest induction of Siglec-1 in macrophages upon IL-10 treatment, its depletion from the TB-associated microenvironment had no effect on Siglec-1 expression. This could be explained by the fact that IL-10 induces the autocrine production of IFN-I (
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Ziegler-Heitbrock et al., 2003</xref>) to indirectly modulate Siglec-1 expression in M(IL-10) macrophages, which then contributes to the exacerbation of HIV-1 infection as we previously reported (
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Souriant et al., 2019</xref>). In the context of the most closely related lentivirus to HIV, namely SIV, we not only confirmed the presence of Siglec-1
 <sup>+</sup> alveolar macrophages in SIV-infected NHP, but also reported the high abundance of these cells in active TB and in co-infected NHP groups, when compared to healthy ones. Importantly, we associated the high abundance of Siglec-1
 <sup>+</sup> leukocytes with the increase NHP pathological scores, and it correlated positively to the detection of pSTAT1
 <sup>+</sup> macrophage nuclei in histological staining of serial sections of lung biopsies from co-infected NHP. This is in line with a recent report on the presence of IFN-I, IFNAR and different ISG in alveolar and lung interstitial tissue from NHP with active TB (
 <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Mattila, 2019</xref>), and with the fact that the in vivo expression of Siglec-1 is up-regulated early in myeloid cells after SIV infection and maintained thereafter in the pathogenic NHP model (
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Jaroenpool et al., 2007</xref>). In TB-SIV co-infection, we hypothesized that IFN-I is not exerting the expected antiviral effect, but instead is concomitant with chronic immune activation and attenuated by the high expression of Siglec-1 in myeloid cells, as recently proposed in the HIV-1 context (
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Akiyama et al., 2017</xref>). Altogether, these findings uncover the IFN-I/STAT1/Siglec-1 axis as a mechanism established by Mtb to exacerbate HIV-1 infection in myeloid cells, and call for the need to further investigate this signaling pathway in TB pathogenesis.
</p>
