<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Beside classical ELISA‐based and NT assays specific anti‐HA influenza antibodies, there are newer assays with increased precision and sensitivity, such as the XMAP (x = analyte MAP = Multi‐analite profiling) technology adapted for Luminex‐based IgA assays.
 <xref rid="irv12664-bib-0079" ref-type="ref">79</xref>, 
 <xref rid="irv12664-bib-0080" ref-type="ref">80</xref> The XMAP technology is a serological method that can be applied to measure multiple proteins or antibodies in a single‐well reaction with high accuracy and reproducibility. The Luminex XMAP technology is based on the combination of different well‐established techniques such as flow cytometry, carboxylated microspheres, laser, and traditional chemistry. Briefly, specific nano‐magnetic beads can be coated with different purified proteins arising from the same pathogen or from different ones and then incubated with serum samples. Using specific biotinylated secondary antibody, the presence of antigen‐specific antibodies in sera can be easily measured and quantified by a dedicated detection system (Luminex). Wang et al
 <xref rid="irv12664-bib-0081" ref-type="ref">81</xref> applied this novel method for the simultaneous detection of antibodies against the Newcastle disease and avian influenza virus and have shown that the Luminex XMAP‐based assay has been up to 1024 times more sensitive for avian influenza virus antibody detection compared to the conventional ELISA assay. The minimal volume of sample required, the cost reduction for multiple detection in comparison with the classical methods, and the possibility to perform a rapid multiplexing in a single reaction are additional advantages of this new technology. However, these new generations of serological assays are not standardized and require further studies for the generation of validated and reproducible results. Currently, only the ELISA is a reliable and valuable approach to determine sIgA in various biological samples.
</p>
