<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In any discussion of vector competence, delineating the differences vis-a-vis vectorial capacity is critical. Vector competence is disproportionately overrepresented in the modern literature, and is simply defined as the ability for a given vector to acquire and subsequently transmit a pathogen [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] (summarized in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00867-f001">Figure 1</xref>). For mosquito-borne arboviruses, the virus is initially imbibed by an adult female from a viremic host (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00867-f001">Figure 1</xref>, step 1). The first major hurdle the virus faces is the midgut infection barrier (MIB), in which the virus must infect the epithelial cells of the midgut, overcoming digestive proteolytic enzymes, RNA interference (RNAi), effects of the luminal and sometimes internal microbiota, the formation of the peritrophic matrix, as well the physical barrier represented by the midgut epithelium itself [
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00867-f001">Figure 1</xref>, step 2). From this point, the virus must undergo replication in the midgut epithelial cells, be shed from its basolateral aspect, and traverse the basal lamina into the hemolymph (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00867-f001">Figure 1</xref>, step 3). Failure of the virus to escape or disseminate from an infected midgut is called the midgut escape barrier (MEB). During this stage of the infectious process, the virus may infect and replicate in secondary tissues such as the fat body, hemocytes, nerves, and muscles (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00867-f001">Figure 1</xref>, step 4), although such infection of secondary tissues may not be strictly required. The salivary gland infection barrier (SGIB) represents the next step in the progression of vector competence, and can be considered an extension of dissemination from the midgut (disseminated infection). The basal lamina surrounding this organ must first be traversed (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00867-f001">Figure 1</xref>, step 5). Upon infection of the salivary gland acinar cells of a competent vector, the virus is subsequently shed from the acinar cells into apical cavities, such that it is inoculated with saliva into subsequent hosts upon blood feeding (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00867-f001">Figure 1</xref>, step 6). The time period between oral exposure to the virus and the presence of virus in the saliva is known as the extrinsic incubation period, or EIP. Although rare, reports do exist in which a virus that is capable of infecting salivary glands is incapable of being shed efficiently into saliva [
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], indicating the existence of a salivary gland escape barrier [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] (SGEB). Generally, the presence of virus in the saliva extends for the life of the mosquito. In the laboratory settings, vector competence is most synonymous with transmission efficiency (viral deposition in saliva), although competence and refractoriness are often estimated based on midgut infection and dissemination into the hemocoel, assuming the lack of salivary gland barriers, which are relatively rare.
</p>
