<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> shows the visualization of the MCC tree in FigTree, with internal nodes annotated according to the posterior ancestral location state probabilities within the MCC tree file. As expected, one can observe that posterior support for the preferred ancestral location decreases from the observed tips toward the root, in other words the further we go back in time, the more uncertain the inferred location states become. All of the information required to make the FigTree visualization in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> is contained within a NEXUS file, containing all of the ancestral trait annotations, which we use as the (only) input for the FigTree (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). The standard Newick file format itself does not contain such trait annotations but remains in popular use for storing phylogenetic trees and is hence supported by most (if not all) phylogenetic visualization packages. In general however, Newick and other older formats (e.g., NEXUS) offer limited expressiveness for storing and visualizing annotated phylogenetic trees and associated data, which has lead to extensions for this format being proposed [e.g., the extended Newick format; (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>)]. FigTree allows users to upload annotation information for the sequences in the analyzed alignment in the form of a simple tab-delimited text file, and a parsimony approach can be used to infer the most parsimonious state reconstruction for the internal nodes from those provided for the tips. iTOL (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) is another application that can take an MCC tree as its input file and allows annotating branches and nodes of the phylogenetic tree using descriptions provided through the use of simple text files in which custom visualization options can easily be declared (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). iTOL is even suited for showing very large trees (with more than 10,000 leaves) with Webkit-based browsers—such as Chromium/Google Chrome, Opera and Safari—offering the best performance.
</p>
