<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="RSIF20110223F1" position="float">
 <label>Figure 1.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>(
   <italic>a</italic>) Epidemiological data from the entire outbreak region, (
   <italic>b</italic>) the index farm and (
   <italic>c</italic>) evidence of agricultural intensification. (
   <italic>a</italic>) Symptomatic Nipah virus cases in Malaysia and Singapore, January 1997–April 1999; data are from the Center for Disease Control and Prevention's 
   <italic>Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Reports</italic> [
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSIF20110223C7">7</xref>,
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSIF20110223C8">8</xref>], records from the Department of Veterinary Services and the Ministry of Health, Malaysia [
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSIF20110223C16">16</xref>]. Further information on case numbers can be found in the electronic supplementary material. (
   <italic>b</italic>) Detection of Nipah virus-induced pre-weaning mortality in the three breeding sections on the index farm. To investigate the timing of Nipah-induced mortality in the three breeding sections, we define a piglet mortality index (PMI) that compares the observed mortality for each litter with expected mortality (based on the number of piglets born and the time from farrow to wean). Here we present average PMI values through time, shown as quantiles of the values observed during the parametrization period; raw litter-level PMI values are shown in the electronic supplementary material. The presence of Nipah virus is suggested when pre-weaning mortality of piglets is significantly greater than expected, and we infer the presence of Nipah virus when significant excess mortality is observed in multiple litters during the same time period or coincident with human cases. The binned PMI values show that significant mortality peaks occurred in the Breeding Nucleus and Breeding section 2 during the time period of the first cluster of human cases in early 1997; individual litters in Breeding section 1 also showed elevated mortality during this time period (electronic supplementary material). Piglet mortality then returned to baseline levels until approximately July 1997, corresponding to the time of the next observed human cases, around which time the virus is likely to have been reintroduced from the flying fox reservoir. Model output analysed in the same manner as the piglet mortality data from the index farm is shown in the electronic supplementary material. (i) Breeding Nucleus; (ii) Breeding section 1; (iii) Breeding section 2. (
   <italic>c</italic>) Commercial production of mangoes and domestic pigs in Malaysia, 1961–2005. The drop in both mango (dashed lines) and pig production (solid line) between 1998 and 1999 is because of the depopulation and closing of pig farms in areas infected with Nipah virus. Mangoes on these farms were not harvested and many of the orchards have since been abandoned or converted to other crops. Data are from the Food and Agricultural Organization's Agricultural Production database.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="rsif20110223-g1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
