<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="RSIF20110223F2" position="float">
 <label>Figure 2.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Deterministic model results illustrating Nipah virus dynamics in the growing section of the index farm. Individuals are characterized as belonging to one of five states: susceptible (S), immune—maternal antibodies (A), immune—recovered from infection (R), exposed (E) and infectious (I). The top panels illustrate the infection/immunity profile of the growing section following (
   <italic>a</italic>) initial introduction of the virus and (
   <italic>b</italic>) subsequent introduction. The population profile is normalized by the capacity of the growing section (see the electronic supplementary material). The qualitative difference in infection dynamics results primarily from the prevalence of maternal antibodies in the young pig population. (
   <italic>c</italic>,
   <italic>d</italic>) Following the initial introduction of the virus (
   <italic>c</italic>), the rate of replenishment of the susceptible population in the growing section (solid blue line) declines, as many individuals are immune, having been infected while in the breeding sections. The rate at which individuals are infected (green line) declines in consequence. When the virus is reintroduced (
   <italic>d</italic>), many individuals entering the growing section have maternal antibodies. Loss of maternal antibodies after entry into the growing section provides a source of susceptibles independent of the presence of infection (blue line), allowing the virus to persist. Infection dynamics are qualitatively similar for a wide range of transmission parameters. The results shown were produced using the following combination of transmission parameters: 
   <italic>ɛ</italic> = 0.5, 
   <italic>σ</italic> = 0.01 and 
   <italic>R</italic>
   <sub>0</sub> = 10. Analogous results for introduction into a vaccinated population are shown in the electronic supplementary material.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="rsif20110223-g2" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
