<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This is the largest cohort of IKK2 deficiency reported in the Saudi population. In general, the clinical features of our patients were not different from previously reported cases. Susceptibility to a wide range of infections caused by opportunistic and non-opportunistic organisms were commonality. The generalized maculopapular rash, hepatosplenomegaly, chorioretinitis, and CNS complications in our patients are probably related to the chronic CMV and disseminated BCG infections. All reported patients succumbed to their disease during infancy unless they had successful HSCT (
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). On average, the degree of lymphopenia was more profound in our patients (420–2,680/mm
 <sup>3</sup>) compared to others (1,520–11,850/mm
 <sup>3</sup>) (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Interestingly, all our patients had delayed umbilical cord separation [normal separation occurs in 1–2 weeks (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>)] Patient V:6, who died in infancy from a febrile illness before diagnosis and the identification of the genetic defect in the family, was also reported to have had delayed separation of the umbilical cord. None of the reported patients with IKK2 deficiency had delayed cord separation except one from Saudi Arabia, but with a different mutation (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>–
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). No neutrophil chemotaxis or adhesion assay was done for the patients. Delayed cord separation was reported in conditions that affect neutrophil number and/or compromise their function including leukocyte adhesion defects as well as MyD88 and IRAK4 deficiency, which are upstream to the NF-κB activation pathway (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). This feature may be a clue to IKK2 deficiency in patients with combined immunodeficiency. The mechanism by which 
 <italic>IKBKB</italic> mutation may predispose to delayed cord separation is not clear. It has been reported that neutrophil infiltration was prominent during the cord separation process in healthy babies, and a defect in neutrophil chemotaxis and adhesion was illustrated in cases of leukocyte adhesion deficiency (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Since all IKK2 deficiency patients in the literature did not exhibit delayed cord separation except one Saudi patient with a different mutation, it is likely that this feature is a result of a complex interaction between the 
 <italic>IKBKB</italic> defect and other modifier genes.
</p>
