<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Findings in blood do not necessarily explain the events occurring in tissues directly affected by the infection, thus studies in bronchoalveolar lavage fluids (BALF) are very relevant (
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Xiong et al. (
 <xref rid="B127" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>) used RNA-seq to study BALFs and peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) transcriptome from three COVID-19 patients (unfortunately their clinical conditions were not reported) and from three healthy subjects. The BALF cells in these patients expressed 9,609 genes, 679 of which were up-regulated and 325 down-regulated, as opposed to controls. In PBMC, 15,726 genes were expressed, with 707 up-regulated and 316 down-regulated. BALF cells from patients showed a differential expression of genes related to viral invasion and replication (viral RNA was detected in BALFs of all three patients) such as membrane-associated proteins, endoplasmic reticulum, and viral transcription. In contrast, PBMCs showed increased expression of genes related to complement activation, immunoglobulins, and B cell-mediated responses, while some genes corresponded to the acute inflammatory response. The down-regulated genes in patients' BALF were mostly related to activation of the immune response. Comparison of the cytokine genes showed that in BALFs the genes for IL-10, CCL2/MCP-1 (together with its CCR2 receptor), CXCL10/IP-10, CCL3/MIP-1A (together with its CCR5 receptor), and CCL4/MIP1B were differentially up-regulated. Another relevant finding was that in PBMC, genes related to autophagy, apotopsis, and p53 pathways were up-regulated, a finding that could be related to the lymphopenia detected in the three patients. Interestingly, IL-6 transcripts were not increased in PBMCs, although the patients had high plasma levels of such cytokine, suggesting that circulating IL-6 could have been produced in the lungs, either by alveolar epithelial cells or by recruited inflammatory cells.
</p>
