<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat.1007706.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007706.g005</object-id>
 <label>Fig 5</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Requirements of DRs for CHIKV-Cbn and CHIKV-LR replication in mosquito and mammalian cells.</title>
  <p>
   <bold>(A)</bold> Top, schematic representation of the 3’UTR corresponding to recombinant CHIKV-Cbn. DR copies are represented with colored blocks and DR deletions are indicated with light grey blocks. Middle and bottom, immunofluorescence (left) and growth kinetics (right) of recombinant viruses compared to the parental CHIKV-Cbn (WT) performed in C6/36 cells and BHK cells, respectively. Error bars represent standard deviations from the mean, n = 3. Data were analyzed by two-way ANOVA with Bonferroni´s test using PRISM5 (GraphPad Software). Compared to the WT: p&lt;0.001 for Δ(1+2)abb’ at 24h and 32h, Δ(1+2)ab at 24h and 32h, Δ3a at 24h; and p&lt;0.05 for Δ3a at 32h. A representative agarose gel for PCR amplification of the 3'UTRs of individual clones is shown for Cbn Δ(1+2)abb’ population after 10 days post-transfection in C6/36 cells. DNA ladder (M) was used as reference. The sizes of DNA bands in the ladder (in base pairs) are indicated on the right. 
   <bold>(B)</bold> Top, schematic representation of the 3’UTR corresponding to recombinant CHIKV-LR. DR copies are represented with colored blocks and DR deletions are indicated with light grey blocks. Left and right panels, immunofluorescence and growth kinetics of a recombinant virus carrying the deletion of both DR1 and DR2 copies (Δ1abΔ2ab) compared with the parental CHIKV-LR (WT) performed in C6/36 cells and BHK cells, respectively. Titer values are the mean +/- SD, n = 3. Data were analyzed by two-way ANOVA with Bonferroni´s test using PRISM5 (GraphPad Software). Compared to the WT, p&lt;0.001 for Δ1abΔ2ab at 24h and 32h.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1007706.g005" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
