<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0335">Nutritional modulation of the immune system is also associated with reduction or delayed onset of immune-mediated chronic diseases. Several micronutrients and dietary components have been shown to play specific roles in the development and maintenance of an effective immune system. For example, arginine is necessary for the nitric oxide generation by macrophages, and vitamin A and zinc are known regulators of cell division. Vitamin E is both an antioxidant (
 <xref rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr">Lee and Han, 2018</xref>) and protein kinase C activity inhibitor (
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Childs et al., 2019</xref>). Dietary and supplementation interventions enriching the gut microbiome, such as the use of probiotics and prebiotics (
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Hill et al., 2014</xref>), may be needed to help enhancing or restoring a healthy gut microbiome. In addition, diets lacking vegetables may decrease the diversity of nutrients reaching the gut microbiome. This in turn alters epithelial integrity resulting in increased permeability or ‘leaky gut’, allowing immune cells within the gut-associated lymphoid tissue to be directly exposed to intraluminal nutrients or elements of the gut microbiota. A great example of altered gut permeability induced by micronutrient status is that of vitamin D. Specifically, vitamin D-deficient diets are found to be responsible for increased epithelial permeability due to dysfunctioning tight junctions, resulting in both acute and chronic gut inflammation (
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Bischoff et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib147" ref-type="bibr">Sassi et al., 2018</xref>). Optimal probiotic bacterial composition has been shown to effectively reduce inflammation, characterized by reduction of proinflammatory Th1 and Th17 cytokines, such as IL-17 and IFN-γ, and concomitant increases in the levels of inflammation-resolving cytokine, such as IL-10 (
 <xref rid="bib146" ref-type="bibr">Santiago-Lopez et al., 2018</xref>). On the other hand, prebiotics can be used not only as substrates for bacterial metabolism but also to enhance barrier function. The unparalleled importance of natural and well-balanced diets has been also highlighted vis-à-vis infant formula consumptions. It is well established that breastfeeding affords passive immunity to the infant via transfer of antibodies, growth factors, and cytokines to the offspring (
 <xref rid="bib158" ref-type="bibr">Torres-Castro et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib133" ref-type="bibr">Plaza-Diaz et al., 2018</xref>). Breastmilk is also enriched with microbiota thatpromote the maturation of gut-associated lymphoid tissue (
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Donovan and Comstock, 2016</xref>), playing a key role in development of the immune system during thymus maturation, particularly for T cell function. In breastfed infants, complementary feeding with prebiotics for optimal microbiome maintenance has been proposed (
 <xref rid="bib107" ref-type="bibr">McKeen et al., 2019</xref>).
</p>
