<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">Antiviral drugs such as rupintrivir may have an immune-modulatory effect in experimentally induced allergic asthma with subsequent RV infection. We infected lung slices of house-dust mite (HDM)-sensitized asthmatic mice ex vivo with human rhinovirus (RV) and investigated the effect of the antiviral drug rupintrivir on RV-induced cytokine response in lung tissue of HDM-sensitized mice ex vivo.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p id="Par2">Mice were sensitized with HDM. Precision-cut lung slices (PCLS) were prepared from HDM-sensitized or non-sensitized mice. Lung slices were infected ex vivo with RV or RV together with rupintrivir. Modulation of immune responses was evaluated by cytokine secretion 48 h post infection.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p id="Par3">In vivo HDM sensitization resulted in a T
   <sub>H</sub>-2/T
   <sub>H</sub>-17-dominated cytokine response that persisted in PCLS ex vivo. RV infection of PCLS from non-sensitized mice resulted in the induction of an antiviral and pro-inflammatory immune response, as indicated by the secretion of IFN-α, IFN-β, IFN-γ, TNF-α, MCP-1, IP-10, IL-10, and IL-17A. In contrast, PCLS from HDM-sensitized mice showed an attenuated antiviral response, but exaggerated IL-4, IL-6, and IL-10 secretion upon infection. Rupintrivir inhibited exaggerated pro-inflammatory cytokine IL-6 and T
   <sub>H</sub>-2 cytokine IL-4 in HDM-sensitized mice.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p id="Par4">In summary, this study demonstrates that treatment with rupintrivir influences virus-induced IL-4 and IL-6 cytokine release under experimental conditions ex vivo.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Electronic supplementary material</title>
  <p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12931-019-1175-y) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
