<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24">The analysis of data for scientific purposes requires objectivity. This cannot be achieved without considering the falsifiability of models
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. Here, we presented views that are very different from those of previous studies. The discrepancies were generated by differences in the methodologies, because many of the data analysed were common among studies. Here, we wish to show that our study has better falsifiability
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup>. A sequence matrix is essentially composed of multivariate data with a large number of dimensions
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup>. Previous studies used tree-based models (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) which can handle only a single dimension
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>; such tree models have to ignore the real data structure. The understanding of clusters requires advanced judgement calls; hence, it may fail easily and the comparison of the results of different segments or types is difficult. In contrast, PCA does not have limitations regarding the shape of presentations or the number of dimensions; thus, it has better objectivity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup>. For instance, the attributions of clusters presented in Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1C</xref> and 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref> should not cause confusion. Moreover, the assumption that “the relationship among samples should be a tree-like structure” cannot be verified. Our analyses are free from such assumptions. One of the major differences observed was the direct shift from avian to swine or human viruses. Although these shifts were thought to explain the 1918
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup> and 2009
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup> pandemic viruses, the segments of avian viruses were separated from any swine or human segments, even those that were thought to be close to the source (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>, A, orange)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, it is difficult to estimate such direct shifts. In fact, the cluster called “triple reassortant” disappeared (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2S</xref>); this class was detected as a pandemic swine H3N2 virus
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup> and also presented some clusters of H1N1
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>. Although avian viruses might be the origin of the H1 viruses, they might have a limited capacity to infect swine or humans, and vice versa. Among the samples studied here, there was only one example of such transmittance, which may have occurred from humans to turkeys (NCBI taxonomy ID: 1848980) in contrast to the occasional transmittance observed between humans and swine (Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1C</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4A,B</xref>). The three groups, R, M, and U, may have branched out from the origin to achieve better infectivity in swine or humans (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). The 1943 human strain may represent an earlier process of branching out (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). Swine may be the origin of the 1918 pandemic virus, i.e., the 1930 swine strain may be a derivative of this group of viruses.
</p>
