<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">Indeed, modern drug delivery technologies are numerous, and tailoring the most appropriate formulation to the medicinal phytochemical in question is not just a matter of trial and error; rather, the physicochemical properties of the specific natural drug substance determine the delivery issues that the formulator may face, and the excipients that can be used to overcome these challenges [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR157">157</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR158">158</xref>]. Among the physicochemical properties of importance are log P (a measure of the drug’s lipophilicity) and melting point. These parameters will determine the likelihood of the active substance to precipitate in the gastrointestinal lumen, in which case the use of amorphous formulations may be preferred over other oral carriers. Additional important physicochemical properties include the drug’s chemical structure and molecular weight; using previously successful formulations to deliver drugs with similar chemical structure may be a wise approach. Also, generally speaking, higher molecular weight substances may be better incorporated into lipid-based drug delivery systems [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR159">159</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR161">161</xref>]. It should be noted that some solubility-enabling formulations may simultaneously decrease the drug’s permeability, and overall absorption may be unimproved. This solubility-permeability interplay was shown for formulations based on cyclodextrins [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR162">162</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR164">164</xref>], surfactants [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR165">165</xref>], cosolvents [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR166">166</xref>], and hydrotropes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR167">167</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR168">168</xref>]. In amorphous solid dispersions (ASD), on the other hand, the solubility increases (via supersaturation) with unchanged permeability, and thus, ASD may be preferred over other carrier systems, given supersaturation can be achieved and maintained for sufficient time [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR169">169</xref>].
</p>
