<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Travellers have been mainly implicated in giving wings to SARS-CoV-2 for its worldwide spread [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. COVID-19 is spreading rapidly and crossing borders too. It has been stated that most of the affected patients in China worked at or lived in the Huanan seafood wholesale market, where live animals like snakes, bats, birds, marmots, and other wildlife farm animals were sold [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Wuhan was considered a hotspot for emerging infectious diseases. The news of numerous cases of pneumonia was reported from December 31, 2019, with unknown aetiology in Wuhan, China [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], which was thought to be SARS-CoV (an epidemic which originated in China as well in 2002). Finally, it was confirmed that the SARS-CoV-2 virus, too, belongs to the family of viruses that include the common cold, and viruses of SARS and MERS [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. The available yet limited epidemiological and clinical data for SARS-CoV-2 suggest that the disease spectrum and transmission efficiency of this virus differ from those reported for SARS-CoV [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Apart from implications of SARS-CoV-2 to have its origin from bats and pangolins and then documented to affect humans leading to mainly respiratory infection and also to cause multiple system infection, the virus infection has also been reported from few animals such as cats, dogs, tiger, lion and mink [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Infected patients develop symptoms of high fever, dyspnea, pneumonia, chest pain, dry cough, myalgia and diarrhoea as clinical signs of the disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] and few other non-respiratory illness symptoms too [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>].
</p>
