<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">CRISPR/Cas13d is an RNA-guided, RNA-targeting CRISPR system.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup> To cleave the 2019-nCov (SARS-CoV-2) RNA genome, a Cas13d protein and guide RNAs-containing spacer sequences specifically complementary to the virus RNA genome are used (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>). One advantage of the CRISPR/Cas13d system is its flexibility with respect to designing guide RNAs, because the RNA-targeting cleavage activity of Cas13d does not depend on the presence of specific adjacent sequences such as the NGG motif for the DNA-editing effector, Cas9.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup> This unique feature of the system meets the requirement for rapid development of guide RNAs to target different virus variants that evolve and may escape traditional drugs. In total, we have designed 10,333 guide RNAs to specifically target 10 peptide-coding regions of the 2019-nCov (SARS-CoV-2) virus RNA genome, without affecting the human transcriptome (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>). Due to its desirable safety profile, adeno-associated virus (AAV) can serve as a vehicle to deliver the Cas13d effector to patients infected with 2019-nCov (SARS-CoV-2). The small size of the Cas13d effector makes it suitable for an ‘all-in-one’ AAV delivery with a guide-RNA array (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1e</xref>). Up to three guide RNAs targeting different peptide-encoding regions of 2019-nCov (SARS-CoV-2) RNA genome can be packaged into one AAV vector (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1e</xref>), making the system more efficient for virus clearance and resistance prevention. The expression of Cas13d can be driven by tissue-specific promoters to achieve precise treatment of infected organs. Additionally, AAV has serotypes highly specific to the lung, the main organ infected by 2019-nCov (SARS-CoV-2), and thus can be exploited for targeted delivery of the CRISPR system. A similar strategy is applicable to other types of RNA viruses.
</p>
