<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p> Below are specific comments as they relate to the reported study: 
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>It is difficult to understand the justification for including the mouse component of the work. The final sentence of the introduction is misleading. As it reads, it indicates that mice were used to demonstrate transmission (i.e. that mosquitoes actually fed on mice which were then monitored for evidence of infection). However, mice (along with mosquitoes) were used to indicate whether saliva collected using an in vitro method contained infectious virus and not to demonstrate transmission directly. If mice had been used to demonstrate transmission directly, then this would have added greatly to the novelty and significance of the study by demonstrating that transmission is affected in an animal model and not just using in vitro assessment of transmission (which is what almost all other studies do).</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>The actual number of saliva samples tested was relatively low, so interpretation of the findings with regards to transmission blocking should be undertaken with caution, especially when extrapolating to the field.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>“Pluripotency” is not really an appropriate descriptive term in this context.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>The background in the abstract needs to mention that there is an efficacious vaccine and then state issues with its widespread roll-out (i.e. supply, logistics etc.). This provides a segue into why 
    <italic>Wolbachia</italic> may be appropriate for YFV control.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Also in the abstract (5 
    <sup>th</sup> line): 
    <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> is still the main (urban) vector, not “used to be”.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Introduction: In lines 3 and 4 of paragraph 2, it is important to emphasise that 
    <italic>Haemagogus </italic>and 
    <italic>Sabethes</italic> are important sylvan vectors in South America. Africa has a different suite of sylvan vectors. Also, insert a comma after 
    <italic>Sabethes</italic>, as the way it currently reads, it sounds as though they are all urban vectors.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Also in this paragraph (lines 9-12), state that there was (thankfully) no evidence of urban transmission during these outbreaks.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Line 10 of paragraph 3: Need a segue into the 
    <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-based control. Something like “ 
    <italic>Wolbachia</italic> is being deployed to limit arbovirus transmission…”. Then describe what 
    <italic>Wolbachia</italic> actually is.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Methods: Need to be consistent on whether it is PCR or RT PCR.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Methods: Please provide references for the IFA and qRT-PCR in regard to the virus isolation.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Methods: In the first paragraph of the mosquito saliva transmission assays (line 9), state whether saliva was from individual mosquitoes or from pools of saliva.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Methods: Viral detection on (in) infected mosquitoes and mice: 
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p>Remove “infected” from this heading, as it is not known whether mosquitoes are infected until they are tested.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p>Also, line 1 of first paragraph: qPCR detects viral RNA.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p>What was the justification for using inoculation of mosquitoes and mice to demonstrate transmission? Why not a cell culture based system?</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p>In terms of the mice, is there evidence that the strain used was highly susceptible to YFV infection? Why was this strain of mice used?</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>In terms of the multiplex assay, can some data be supplied regarding the relative efficiencies of each of the components of the assay? How does sensitivity compare to singleplex assays? What were the limits of detection, especially for detection of YFV?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>More information on the quantification of 
    <italic>Wolbachia</italic> and YFV would be beneficial, especially with respect to the RPS 17 sequence and why it was included.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Results: The authors state that there “was no significant difference between infection rates resulting from the human or primate virus isolates.”. Please provide the statistical test used to compare rates and provide significance levels. Please provide statistical tests to show that infection rates were indeed significantly different between 
    <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-positive and -negative mosquitoes.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Results: Paragraph 2, lines 9-11 – this is speculation or if there is previously published work on this it should be provided – in the discussion.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Figure 3: 
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p>Were only the head and thorax of YFV-infected mosquitoes tested for 
       <italic>Wolbachia</italic> density? One would think not, given they are 
       <italic>Wolbachia</italic> infected. Clarify.
      </p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p>Line 4, the sentence staring with (B) needs to state that these were the YFV copy numbers from the start.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p>In the last sentence, what does the significance level refer to?</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p>Was this absolute or relative quantification of YFV RNA? Clarify.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Results: The number of saliva samples from WT and wMel+ was 8 for each of the viruses (primate and human). Why was such a relatively low number (especially of the WT) of saliva samples tested? In Figure 3, there was a much larger number of mosquitoes tested. Was transmission not attempted with these mosquitoes? The number of saliva samples tested really was very low compared to what could and should have been tested (especially by mosquito injection, where there shouldn’t really be any limitation to the number of samples processed).</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Figure 4: The legend and figures are the wrong way around. Do Figures 4A and 4C actually refer to wMel+ infected saliva?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>The discussion needs to consider some important factors: 
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p>What are the possible mechanisms causing the 
       <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-mediated virus inhibition? This is pertinent in this case, because the effect of subsequent blood meals was examined.
      </p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p>
       <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-based control strategies are undoubtedly promising tools for control of 
       <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> transmitted viruses. However, the authors should discuss any potential issues that could arise with 
       <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-based approaches in the future.
      </p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
