<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="brief-report"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JACC Cardiovasc Interv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JACC Cardiovasc Interv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Jacc. Cardiovascular Interventions</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1936-8798</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1876-7605</issn><publisher><publisher-name>by the American College of Cardiology Foundation. Published by Elsevier.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S1936-8798(20)30879-7</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcin.2020.04.006</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Spontaneous Coronary Artery Dissection in a Patient With COVID-19</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Courand</surname><given-names>Pierre-Yves</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><email>pycourand@hotmail.com</email><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://twitter.com/bpy_courand">b@py_courand</ext-link><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Harbaoui</surname><given-names>Brahim</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Bonnet</surname><given-names>Marc</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Lantelme</surname><given-names>Pierre</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>University of Lyon, CREATIS UMR5220, INSERM U1044, INSA-15, Lyon, France</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Cardiology Department, H&#x000f4;pital Croix-Rousse, Hospices Civils de Lyon, Lyon, France</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Cardiology Department, H&#x000f4;pital Lyon Sud, Hospices Civils de Lyon, Lyon, France</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Pierre-Yves Courand, H&#x000f4;pital de la Croix-Rousse, Cardiology, Grande Rue de la Croix-Rousse, Lyon, Rhone-Alpes 69004, France. <email>pycourand@hotmail.com</email><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://twitter.com/bpy_courand">b@py_courand</ext-link></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>8</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>e107</fpage><lpage>e108</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 by the American College of Cardiology Foundation. Published by Elsevier.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>American College of Cardiology Foundation</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Key Words</title><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>OCT</kwd><kwd>spontaneous coronary artery dissection</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="p0010">Severe acute respiratory syndrome-coronavirus-2, which causes coronavirus-2019 (COVID-19), has&#x000a0;reached a pandemic level. Cardiac injury,&#x000a0;defined as&#x000a0;an elevated high-sensitivity cardiac&#x000a0;troponin I (hs-TnI), has been reported during&#x000a0;COVID-19; it is associated with an increased risk of mortality (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Several underlying mechanisms are possible: COV-2 myocarditis, acute coronary syndrome type 1 associated with plaque rupture (systemic proinflammatory stimulation and hypercoagulability), or type 2 (mainly related to oxygen mismatch) (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). All these etiologies require a specific diagnosis and appropriate management.</p><p id="p0015">A 55-year-old man with a medical history of peripheral artery disease was admitted to our hospital for cough and febrile dyspnea with suspected COVID-19. The polymerase chain reaction was positive, and the computed tomography scan demonstrated bilateral crazy paving. Forty-eight h after admission, he complained of chest pain. His 12-lead electrocardiogram demonstrated inverted T waves in the inferior leads. Hs-TnI was at 355&#x000a0;ng/l, then 570&#x000a0;ng/l 3&#x000a0;h later (normal values &#x0003c;7 ng/l). Transthoracic echocardiography showed a left ventricular ejection fraction at 60% without wall motion abnormalities, no diastolic dysfunction, and a mild mitral regurgitation. Coronary angiogram performed via radial approach demonstrated a chronic total occlusion of the posterior descending artery with epicardial collateral from the left anterior descending artery (Rentrop 3) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1A</xref>
). In the mid-right coronary artery, a spontaneous dissecting coronary hematoma was observed with an intimal tear (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figures&#x000a0;1B and 1C</xref>). Flow grade was Thrombolysis In Myocardial Infarction (TIMI) 3 in the posterolateral artery. Optical coherence tomography (OCT) was performed in the right coronary artery and confirmed the spontaneous dissecting coronary hematoma with&#x000a0;an intimal rupture (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figures&#x000a0;1D to 1F</xref>). A&#x000a0;conservative&#x000a0;management was decided. Patient was transferred to the medical department with&#x000a0;treatment with aspirin, statins, and beta-blockers. A subsequent control coronary angiogram is planned.<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Coronary Angiography and OCT of the Dissection</p><p><bold>(A)</bold> Coronary angiogram of the left anterior descending artery with epicardial collateral to the posterior descending artery <bold>(black arrow)</bold>. <bold>(B and C)</bold> Total chronic occlusion of the posterior descending artery <bold>(black arrow)</bold>, and suspected intimal tear in the mid right coronary artery <bold>(white arrows)</bold>. <bold>(D, E, and F)</bold> Optical coherence tomography (OCT) on the proximal <bold>(D)</bold>, middle <bold>(E)</bold>, and distal <bold>(F)</bold> part of the dissection (<bold>asterisks</bold> indicate the false lumen, <bold>white arrows</bold> show intimal rupture).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p><p id="p0020">Coronary artery dissection may be related to intraplaque hemorrhage resulting in an intra-adventitial hematoma, spreading longitudinally along the coronary artery, dissecting the tunicae (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Lessons from the previous coronavirus and influenza epidemics suggest that viral infections can trigger acute coronary syndrome primarily owing to a combination of a significant systemic inflammatory response plus localized vascular inflammation at the arterial plaque level (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Herein, we report the first case of spontaneous coronary artery dissection in a patient with COVID-19 infection. In this pandemic period, almost all the physicians&#x02019; attention is captured by the symptoms of COVID-19. This report&#x000a0;shows that true acute coronary syndrome can&#x000a0;occur in this setting and should be appropriately&#x000a0;characterized. Whether specific mechanisms are triggered by this virus requires further scrutiny.</p></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cardiac injury in patients with corona virus disease 2019 Association of cardiac injury with mortality in hospitalized patients with COVID-19 in Wuhan</article-title><source>JAMA Cardiol</source><year>2020 Mar 25</year><comment>[E-pub ahead of print]</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madjid</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Safavi-Naeini</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vardeny</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential effects of coronaviruses on the cardiovascular system: a review</article-title><source>JAMA&#x000a0;Cardiol</source><year>2020 Mar 27</year><comment>[E-pub ahead of print]</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saw</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancini</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphries</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contemporary review on spontaneous coronary artery dissection</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Am Coll Cardiol</source><volume>68</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27417009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kwong</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campitelli</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute myocardial infarction after laboratory-confirmed influenza infection</article-title><source>N&#x000a0;Engl J Med</source><volume>378</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>353</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29365305</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn id="d33e267"><p id="ntpara0010">The authors have reported that they have no relationships relevant to the contents of this paper to disclose.</p></fn><fn id="d33e270"><p id="ntpara740040">The authors attest they are in compliance with human studies committees and animal welfare regulations of the authors&#x02019; institutions and Food and Drug Administration guidelines, including patient consent where appropriate. For more information, visit the <italic>JACC: Cardiovascular Interventions</italic><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://interventions.onlinejacc.org/content/instructions-authors" id="interref03010">author instructions page</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>