<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is expected that majority of people who recover from COVID-19 will not have long-term consequences. However, COVID-19 is a multi-organ disease commonly affecting the lung, heart, kidney, digestive tract, and nervous system, with unclear situation regarding long-term consequences [
 <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Survivors of the severe COVID-19 disease were reported to have changes in their lungs, similar to those observed in SARS, marked by the diminished pulmonary capacity [
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Important lessons on long term outcomes for patients who contracted COVID-19 are still to be learned, but in order to adapt to the global situation, we believe it is paramount to draw parallels with the epidemics of SARS (severe acute respiratory syndrome) and MERS (Middle East Respiratory Syndrome). A recent study showed that approximately 20% of COVID-19 patients suffered from cardiac injuries [
 <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Studies of SARS and MERS reported high occurrence of hypertension, persistent tachycardia and myocarditis in convalescent patients. A study on 121 patients who were infected with SARS showed that hypertension occurred in over half of all the patients, while 71.9% of them developed persistent tachycardia [
 <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. One the other hand, it has been shown that MERS causes myocarditis, most likely by the direct viral infection; the same was implied for COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Acute kidney injury and proteinuria were also reported in COVID-19 patients, suggesting direct cellular damage of the kidney tissue [
 <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. By comparison, COVID-19 patients who were treated in the ICU, particularly those who were mechanically ventilated, were reported to suffer from “post-intensive care syndrome”, most likely because the lack of oxygen in blood [
 <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. All these reports suggest that COVID-19 infection might be regarded as higher risk than it was initially believed. This is of paramount importance in football activities, knowing that career development requires a lot of time and effort invested into prevention of injury, disease, disability and even death [
 <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The sport community finds itself facing uncharted territories in both the wake and the aftermath of this pandemic. Therefore, we firmly believe that coordinated, well-communicated and transparent action is of utmost importance if we want the return to regular activities be safe for all stakeholders.
</p>
