<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para20">During the epidemic, rapid and robust research is important to help guide clinical practices and public health policies. Zhu and colleagues sampled bronchoalveolar-lavage fluid from three patients and used next-generation sequencing and PCR to characterise the virus, and they identified the pathogen of this outbreak as a novel coronavirus that falls within the subgenus Sarbecovirus of the genus Betacoronavirus and confirmed the cytopathic effects (structural changes in host cells) of this virus.
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> Their achievement not only improves methods of diagnosis confirmation in clinics but also promotes the study of the underlying mechanisms of viral infection.
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>2</sup>
 </xref> Subsequently, collaborations between Chinese and international scientists have rapidly unmasked some additional virological features of 2019-nCoV. A specific viral nucleic acid assay using RT-PCR was quickly developed for the diagnosis of 2019-nCoV infection.
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Additionally, human angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 has been shown to be the putative receptor for the entry into host cells by use of bioinformatic prediction methods and in-vitro testing.
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Furthermore, bats are speculated to be the original host of this zoonotic virus, but whether an intermediate host facilitated the viral infection in humans is still unknown.
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref> Lastly, evidence of person-to-person transmission is accumulating,
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> with an estimated R
 <sub>0</sub> of 2·2 (95% CI 1·4–3·9),
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref> and the assessment of the full extent of this mode of transmission is urgently needed.
</p>
