<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This approach included: (a) listening to the caller's feelings, emphasizing the caller's strengths (Hootz, Mykota, &amp; Fauchoux, 
 <xref rid="da23073-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>) and focusing on the “Why now?” of the call. The social readjustment rating scale (Holmes &amp; Rahe, 
 <xref rid="da23073-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">1967</xref>) is a useful list of 43 common precipitants of a crisis; (b) understanding the meanings of the stressors, in the context of the caller's life. (c) Uncovering the 6‐week timeline of events that led up to the call, see Figure S2, a 6‐week timeline. (d) Developing an ecological map (Greene, 
 <xref rid="da23073-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). This is a representation (Feinstein &amp; Snavely, 
 <xref rid="da23073-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) which includes the caller's complete family genogram, network of other helpers (e.g., physicians, faith‐based support, neighbors, friends), and community and national resources, see Figure S3. The ecological map is used to help view and determine what people or resources are available, interested and competent to help a caller. (e) It is essential to focus on one major problem, progress to a list of contributing problems, prioritized these in order of urgency, and link each problem to a specific solution. A wheel and spoke diagram depicts this process (Feinstein &amp; Collins, 
 <xref rid="da23073-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; see Figure S4). (f) In addition, using problem‐solving therapy (Haley, 
 <xref rid="da23073-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">1987</xref>) integrated with crisis intervention is important to discover maladaptive coping styles and encourage adaptive problem‐solving (Feinstein &amp; Collins, 
 <xref rid="da23073-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; see Table S1). (g) We also utilized a 12‐step crisis resolution strategy as a guide for crisis counselors which can also be used as a self‐help strategy by callers' after the initial hotline contact (see Table S2).
</p>
