<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>At the beginning of the epidemic, nucleic acid testing was considered the gold standard for the diagnosis of novel coronavirus pneumonia. However, previous data show that the success rate of nucleic acid testing is not high; moreover, there have recently been strict restrictions imposed on the conditions for the collection of specimens. To avoid these limitations and improve the accuracy of the test, the sixth version of the new coronavirus pneumonia diagnosis and treatment plan (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nhc.gov.cn/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.nhc.gov.cn/</ext-link>) states that, in addition to upper respiratory tract and blood samples, stool samples can also be used for diagnosis, if they are positive. It is hoped that these types of amendments will improve the sensitivity of nucleic acid detection and allow a more accurate diagnosis. At present, the approaches used for the detection of novel coronavirus pneumonia are divided into 2 categories: direct detection and indirect detection. Direct detection comprises the detection of the nucleic acids of the novel coronavirus [
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] using RT-PCR or sequencing of the viral gene, which is highly homologous to known novel coronavirus [
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In contrast, antibody and antigen tests are indirect detection tests [
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Although antibody detection has advantages in terms of convenience and speed, it is not currently able to replace the method of nucleic acid detection. Although computed tomography detection can be used as an auxiliary method to achieve full coverage, it cannot completely distinguish between novel coronavirus pneumonia and other pneumonias owing to the diverse manifestations of the pneumonia caused by the novel coronavirus [
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].
</p>
