<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig0010">
 <label>Fig. 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>A cartoon depiction of the predicted effects of ‘attract and deter’ versus ‘retain’ virally-induced plant phenotypes on transmission of non-persistently aphid-vectored viruses. 
   <bold>(A)</bold> The outputs of epidemiological modelling by 
   <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">Donnelly et al. (2019)</xref> support the idea that a virally-induced ‘attract and deter’ plant phenotype will engender relatively rapid local spread of virus (upper panel), whereas induction of a ‘retain’ phenotype (lower panel), will not. However, they also predict virus transmission promoted by the ‘attract and deter’ phenotype will be self-limiting since aphids will reproduce less if not settled and be exposed to increased risks of predation as they travel between plants, leading to decreased vector density. 
   <bold>(B)</bold> It is predicted that a virally-induced ‘retain’ plant phenotype resulting from increased nutritional quality or decreased resistance to aphid colonisation will encourage aphids to settle, reproduce and become crowded (
   <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">Donnelly et al., 2019</xref>). Crowding induces increased production of winged (alate) aphids (
   <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Braendle et al., 2006</xref>). 
   <bold>(C)</bold> The modelling of 
   <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">Donnelly et al. (2019)</xref> predicts that enhanced production of alates on plants expressing a virally-induced ‘retain’ phenotype will result in longer-distance transmission. Although this enhancement in virus transmission may take longer to occur than that driven by the ‘attract and deter’ virally-induced plant phenotype, it was suggested that it may be more effective in launching epidemics (
   <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">Donnelly et al., 2019</xref>).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text id="at0010">Fig. 2</alt-text>
 <graphic xlink:href="gr2" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
