<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza virus is a major cause of severe and acute respiratory tract infections. Complications of influenza virus infection can result in viral pneumonia, secondary bacterial pneumonia, encephalopathy in infants, or sinusitis, which may lead to increased mortality, especially among people in high-risk groups [
 <xref rid="pone.0200761.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0200761.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Global spread of influenza virus affects up to 10% of the world’s population annually and accounts for more than 15 million cases of infection. There are about 15,000 hospitalizations in one influenza season in Japan alone [
 <xref rid="pone.0200761.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0200761.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Seasonal influenza epidemics that are attributed to influenza A virus (IAV) subtypes of H1N1pdm (new H1N1 that emerged during the influenza pandemic of 2009) and H3N2 in addition to influenza B virus (IBV) occur every year despite the global availability of influenza vaccines. There is a possibility that a new subtype of influenza virus will infect humans and trigger a pandemic that may cause serious health problems with social and economic impacts. Since the first reported case of human infection with avian IAV (H7N9) in 2013, the number of patients with H7N9 infection has been increasing, especially in China [
 <xref rid="pone.0200761.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. This suggests the pandemic potential of new subtypes of human IAV that originated in avian IAV. Furthermore, if a highly pathogenic avian H5N1 influenza virus spreads throughout the world, it could cause catastrophic pandemics due to its high mortality rate of approximately 60% [
 <xref rid="pone.0200761.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Therefore, disease control with anti-influenza agents is of great importance for the prevention of potential pandemics. On the other hand, epidemic influenza infection, which is highly contagious, show rapid progression of symptoms, and has the potential to induce encephalopathy, especially in infants, should also be diagnosed at an early stage of disease onset and then appropriate medication with anti-influenza agents should be initiated as soon as possible [
 <xref rid="pone.0200761.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0200761.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].
</p>
