<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Three classes of antiviral drugs have been shown to be effective against influenza virus infection: M2 ion channel blocker, neuraminidase inhibitor (NAI), and viral RNA polymerase inhibitor [
 <xref rid="pone.0200761.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0200761.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. M2 ion channel blockers (amantadine and rimantadine) exhibit antiviral activity against IAV alone by inhibiting proton channel activity of viral M2 protein that is essential for the uncoating process of viral internal proteins during viral cell entry [
 <xref rid="pone.0200761.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Since the majority of seasonal influenza viruses have already acquired resistance against M2 ion channel blockers, the use of these drugs for treatment of current IAV is no longer recommended [
 <xref rid="pone.0200761.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. NAIs target sialidase activity of viral neuraminidase, which plays an essential role at the release stage of progeny virus from the cellular surface. NAIs suppress virus replication by inhibiting sialidase activity of neuraminidase proteins of both IAV and IBV [
 <xref rid="pone.0200761.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Four NAIs, oseltamivir (OV), peramivir (PV), zanamivir (ZV), and laninamivir (LV), have been developed and their efficacy against influenza infection has been evaluated [
 <xref rid="pone.0200761.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0200761.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0200761.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The first influenza viral RNA polymerase inhibitor, favipiravir, has been found to have potent and selective inhibitory activity against influenza virus through direct interference in replication of the viral RNA genome [
 <xref rid="pone.0200761.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In Japan, favipiravir has already been approved, but its use is permitted only when pandemic influenza viruses that are resistant to all of the conventional antiviral drugs have become prevalent. In the USA and Europe, favipiravir has been undergoing phase 3 clinical trials [
 <xref rid="pone.0200761.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Therefore, NAIs are 
 <italic>de facto</italic> standard anti-influenza drugs for treatment of influenza patients.
</p>
