<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>On the basis of these considerations, we propose four main suggestions towards the development of PLP inhibitors with the potential to treat COVID-19. The first is to consolidate our knowledge on the structure and function of SARS-CoV2 PLP in order to highlight its role in pathogenesis and facilitate drug design. Secondly, we claim that the PLPs effects may be strongly interconnected between all their enzymatic activities. Antagonizing one of these functions alone may be less effective than inhibiting the function of the whole protein. Thus, we suggest developing and testing molecules with such capability [
 <xref rid="B67-ijms-21-03492" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], rather than focusing on each of the PLPs’ functions alone [
 <xref rid="B57-ijms-21-03492" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. However, since the PLP protease activity seems to be critical for virus replication, inhibiting at least this activity could be effective. Third, the number and the specificity of in vivo PLP inhibition models must be increased. Lastly, given the importance of a new coronavirus-specific drug in the fight against the current pandemic, the hypothesis of testing the proposed drugs in COVID-19 should not be underestimated. In detail:
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>Drugs reviewed in the past [
    <xref rid="B69-ijms-21-03492" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>] and novel plant derivatives should progress to the next step in pharmacological development, hopefully being evaluated in vitro against SARS-CoV2 and, subsequently, in animal models;
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Recently proposed SARS-CoV2 PLP inhibitors [
    <xref rid="B3-ijms-21-03492" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] and other drugs proposed in our review should also undergo further evaluations;
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Effects of dietary integration with plant compounds such as polyphenols on COVID-19 prevention should be investigated clinically, in order to demonstrate if this can be a relatively safe and effective health measure;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>A clinical study on the effects of high levels of cystatin C (as uremia) on the outcome of patients with COVID-19 should be performed. Trialing the exogenous administration of this peptide, i.e. via aerosol, may then be considered in humans;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>A similar strategy should be used for thiopurine analogs and disulfiram. However, the evaluation of thiopurine analogs may need to be retrospective and their administration reasoned cautiously. Disulfiram may be tested more safely, paying attention to its pharmacological interactions and any alcohol consumption.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
