<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0035">Microorganisms are a leading cause of human fatalities as they account for 17%–25% of the total number of deaths worldwide (
 <xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr">Fauci et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0320" ref-type="bibr">Muehlenbein, 2016</xref>). Two thirds of EID have zoonotic origins (
 <xref rid="bb0460" ref-type="bibr">Taylor et al., 2001</xref>) with a proven wildlife origin for 71.8% of them (
 <xref rid="bb0220" ref-type="bibr">Jones et al., 2008</xref>). Not only wildlife zoonotic diseases represent the most significant threat to global health but the number of events of EID is accelerating at an unprecedented rate since the last decades (
 <xref rid="bb0220" ref-type="bibr">Jones et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">Cutler et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0315" ref-type="bibr">Morse et al., 2012</xref>). Although our understanding of the underlying mechanisms that contribute to the emergence of pathogenic agents from wildlife to humans remains rudimentary (
 <xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">Allen et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0355" ref-type="bibr">Olival et al., 2017</xref>), the human-wildlife interface and the frequency with which humans are exposed to pathogens are critical in this process (
 <xref rid="bb0365" ref-type="bibr">Pike et al., 2010</xref>). Various factors such as land use change, extraction of natural resources, animal production systems, modern transportation, global trade, and drug usage in human and veterinary medicines, all play a role in cross-species transmission and spread of zoonotic diseases from animals to humans (
 <xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">Bengis et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0385" ref-type="bibr">Rimoin et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0230" ref-type="bibr">Karesh et al., 2012</xref>). The international wildlife trade, including bushmeat and exotic pet trade, are major factors that contribute to such disease transmission (
 <xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">Chomel et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0225" ref-type="bibr">Karesh et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0230" ref-type="bibr">Karesh et al., 2012</xref>). This is especially true for non-human primate species with which humans share close phylogenetic relationships and have the weakest species barriers (
 <xref rid="bb0525" ref-type="bibr">Wolfe et al., 2007</xref>). Although primate species represent only 0.5% of all vertebrates, they act as reservoirs for 20% of the diseases that affect humans (
 <xref rid="bb0525" ref-type="bibr">Wolfe et al., 2007</xref>). The hunting and the butchering of non-human primates led to the major pandemic of HIV (
 <xref rid="bb0365" ref-type="bibr">Pike et al., 2010</xref>) which contributed to the deaths of 35 million people worldwide (
 <xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">Bell and Bedford, 2017</xref>). Retroviruses such as human T-cell lymphotropic (HTLV) virus and simian foamy virus (SFV) have emerged into human populations because of the primate bushmeat trade (
 <xref rid="bb0510" ref-type="bibr">Wolfe et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0515" ref-type="bibr">Wolfe et al., 2005a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0360" ref-type="bibr">Peeters and Delaporte, 2012</xref>). HTLV-1 is now a global epidemic affecting 22 million people and causing life-threatening and incurable diseases (
 <xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">Edlich et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0515" ref-type="bibr">Wolfe et al., 2005a</xref>). More generally, high level of contacts with a wide range of wild species fosters the emergence of zoonotic diseases in human populations. Several of the last Ebola outbreaks in Africa were due to the handling of dead animals and contacts with bat guano (
 <xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">Bengis et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0260" ref-type="bibr">Leroy et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0210" ref-type="bibr">Jacobsen et al., 2016</xref>). The 2014 Ebola epidemic in West Africa was responsible for 27,000 reported cases including more than 11,000 deaths (
 <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">Carroll et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0320" ref-type="bibr">Muehlenbein, 2016</xref>) although Ebola virus can be way more virulent depending on the strains (e.g., up to 90% of recorded mortalities: 
 <xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr">Feldmann and Geisbert, 2011</xref>). Ebola virus disease was also reported in countries such as USA, Spain, UK and Italy (
 <xref rid="bb0280" ref-type="bibr">Mann et al., 2015</xref>). The emergence of the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV-1) in 2002–2003 was associated with the international trade of civets and bats (
 <xref rid="bb0500" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0225" ref-type="bibr">Karesh et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">Cui et al., 2019</xref>). Monkeypox virus, which causes fatal illness in humans in up to 10% of cases (
 <xref rid="bb0530" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2016</xref>), occurred in the USA because of the importation of naturally-infected wild African rodents from Ghana to supply the wildlife pet trade (
 <xref rid="bb0225" ref-type="bibr">Karesh et al., 2007</xref>). In 2004, two crested hawk-eagles illegally smuggled from Thailand to Belgium that were seized at the airport, turned out to be positive for the highly pathogenic avian influenza H5N1 (
 <xref rid="bb0495" ref-type="bibr">Van Borm et al., 2005</xref>). Similarly, passerines imported from Asia to the UK in 2005 were also carrying H5N1 (
 <xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr">Dudley, 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0225" ref-type="bibr">Karesh et al., 2007</xref>). H5N1 is highly lethal for wild and domestic birds but it also threats humans due to potential cross-species transmissions and subsequent reassortment that could lead to a devastating pandemic (
 <xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">Ferguson et al., 2004</xref>). Birds are also responsible for psittacosis, a bacterial infection caused by 
 <italic>Chlamydia psittaci</italic> and that can lead to severe pneumonia in humans, potentially fatal if left untreated (
 <xref rid="bb0425" ref-type="bibr">Smith et al., 2011</xref>). The severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) outbreak in 2019–2020 originated probably from pangolin sold on wet markets in China (
 <xref rid="bb0545" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2020</xref>). About 10 months following the first discovered case of SARS-CoV-2, the virus has affected roughly 30 million persons worldwide and caused 940,000 deaths. These few examples demonstrate that the multiplication of human-wildlife contacts plays a primary role in pathogens' exchange and that leaving the illegal wildlife trade in its current state equals accepting the fact that other EID will likely becoming devastating threats to humans in the near future.
</p>
