<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The sexually transmitted HPV is responsible for genital tract and oropharyngeal infections as a precursor to causing oncological disease affecting the cervix, vagina, vulva, penis, anal tract, and pharynx in both men and women. Cervical cancer is the fourth most common cancer globally, with 528,000 new cases annually and peak incidence in young women aged 25–34 years (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Ferlay et al., 2012</xref>). The HPV serotypes 16 and 18 carry a high-risk for cervical cancer (
 <xref rid="B117" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2018</xref>) and vaccination against these specific serotypes has been available since 2006 through bivalent (16 and 18), quadrivalent (6, 11, 16, and 18), and nonavalent (6, 11, 16, 18, 31, 33, 45, 52, 58) vaccines, which are now available to individuals from the age of 9 years (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Gupta et al., 2017</xref>). A vaccination program started in the United Kingdom in 2008, and at the time of writing over 10.5 million doses had been given to girls (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">Public Health England, 2018</xref>), with the aim of preventing primary infection with HPV. The vaccine coverage was 83.8% for 13–14 year old girls in England in 2017/18 (
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">Public Health England, 2019</xref>). In July 2018, the vaccine was approved for use in boys (
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">Public Health England, 2019</xref>). After a decade of use, there has been an observed decline in the genital infections caused by serotypes 16 and 18 (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">Public Health England, 2018</xref>), with further time needed to observe the fall in cervical cancer incidence. However, the incidence of pre-invasive cervical diseases has been reduced by 79–89% in Scottish women over 20 who were vaccinated with bivalent HPV vaccine when aged 12–13 years, with evidence of herd protection (
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">Palmer et al., 2019</xref>), offering a promising outlook for the reduction of cervical cancer in the future. An additional benefit of HPV vaccines, is their impact on neonatal morbidity and mortality, through the reduction in surgical treatment of cervical neoplasias, and the related preterm births and complications (
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">Soergel et al., 2012</xref>).
</p>
