<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27">ZIKV belongs to the family 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic>, genus 
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic>, and it is closely related to other mosquito-borne flaviviruses such as dengue (DENV), West Nile (WNV), and Japanese encephalitis viruses (JEV) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. ZIKV has a positive-sense, single stranded RNA (+ ssRNA) genome of approximately 11 kb in length and a single open reading frame (ORF) flanked by two untranslated regions (UTRs) at both the 5′ and 3′ termini. The single ORF encodes for a polyprotein that, upon cleavage, gives rise to 3 structural (capsid [C], precursor of membrane [prM], and envelope [E] proteins) and 7 non-structural proteins (NS1, NS2A, NS2B, NS3, NS4A, NS4B, and NS5) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. ZIKV strains can be phylogenetically grouped into two distinct phylogenetic lineages (African and Asian lineages) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Similarly to other flaviviruses, ZIKV is primarily transmitted by 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> species of mosquitoes, including the urban and suburban mosquito species 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>A. albopictus,</italic> also implicated in the transmission of DENV and alphaviruses such as Chikungunya virus (CHIKV) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Even though urban and suburban transmission cycles involve human-mosquito-human transmission, the sylvatic transmission cycle apparently involves non-human primates as the main viral reservoir [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. In addition, ZIKV can be transmitted from the mother to the developing fetus during pregnancy or to the infant during the peripartum [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Most importantly, the virus can be transmitted during sexual intercourse via semen or vaginal secretions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Also, ZIKV can be potentially transmitted by blood transfusions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], and transmission through transfusion of a platelet concentrate has been recently reported in Brazil [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].
</p>
