<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28">Although the vast majority of infected individuals (approximately 80%) remain asymptomatic, ZIKV can cause a wide range of clinical manifestations ranging from a mild, acute febrile illness to severe neurologic disease (i.e. Guillain-Barré syndrome), and devastating congenital anomalies including microcephaly, ocular malformations, and other neurologic defects [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. However, in adult individuals where clinical manifestations do occur they are usually mild, self-limiting, and non-specific associated with an acute febrile illness characterized by low-grade (~38 °C) and short-term (2–7 days) fever, fatigue, rash, arthralgia, myalgia, headache, and conjunctivitis. These clinical signs are indistinguishable from those induced by many other flaviviral or alphaviral infections. Hence, laboratory diagnosis of ZIKV is mandatory to confirm the clinical diagnosis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Therefore, the availability of rapid, reliable, and relatively low cost diagnostic tools is of utmost importance for ZIKV control and management. Currently, clinical diagnosis of ZIKV infection relies on serological assays for the detection of antibodies (including rapid lateral-flow immunochromatographic assays, IgM capture enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay [MAC-ELISA], and plaque reduction neutralization test [PRNT]) and molecular-based assays for the detection of viral nucleic acids (conventional or quantitative, real-time reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction [RT-qPCR]) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Serological assays do not offer a suitable specificity due to the extensive antibody cross-reactivity with other flaviviruses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. In contrast, molecular-based assays for detection of ZIKV RNA (e.g. RT-qPCR) are high throughput, sensitive, and highly specific. Several conventional and RT-qPCR assays have been described [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. To date, there are two ZIKV RT-qPCR assays validated by the Center for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC; Atlanta, GA, USA) which target the prM and E genes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], and an NS2B-specific RT-qPCR assay recently developed by the Pan American Health Organization (PAHO) in response to the ZIKV outbreak in South America which intends to replace the CDC-validated ZIKV prM RT-qPCR assay of lower sensitivity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. However, the use of RT-qPCR assays as diagnostic tests requires centralized laboratory facilities, trained personnel, expensive equipment, and extended turnaround times associated with sample transportation over large distances. Consequently, RT-qPCR assays are not suitable for use within clinical settings in rural areas or may not be available in areas with poor resources including developing countries where ZIKV is spreading at an accelerated rate. Therefore, the socio-economic gap implies that a significant number of suspected cases do not have access to appropriate testing. For these reasons, point-of-need (PON) molecular detection tools for easy, rapid, reliable, inexpensive, and on-site ZIKV testing can not only significantly improve the quality of the health care system in vulnerable areas, but also ensure rapid testing in blood banks and provide enhanced field surveillance of ZIKV transmission with an overall impact of major significance on public health. To date, only three potential PON, molecular-based assays to detect ZIKV RNA have been developed, although not extensively evaluated on target diagnostic specimens [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>].
</p>
