<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">Still, more can be done. We propose a 12-item Infodemic Response Checklist (IRC) as a comprehensive tool to overcome the challenges posed by infodemics (Supplemental Fig. 1). Officials responsible for health communication strategies and media policies can adopt several measures to overcome the COVID-19 infodemic, communicate valid information, and protect the global community against any future info/pandemics.
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par21">Provide more exposure and airtime for medical professionals, scientists, and public health personnel to provide authentic, useful, and transparent information for the public.</p>
   <p id="Par22">Direct and effective communication between scientists and the public on global concerns is essential to allay fear and prevent erroneous assumptions. While the role of scientific journals and institutions is important for dissemination of evidence-based science, scientists and medical professionals are uniquely positioned to empower people with facts through interviews, op-eds, podcasts, blogs, and social media [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. CNN and Facebook, for example, collaborated to host a global town hall during the outbreak, during which medical doctors and psychologists participated from the studio or via skype to answer people’s questions. Dr. Anthony Fauci, director of the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases in the United States, has taken a leading role in the White House Coronavirus Task Force, participating in interviews, town hall meetings, and engaging journalists in person during daily press briefings.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par23">Promote websites of public health organizations via search engines.</p>
   <p id="Par24">Engines like Google and Yahoo must promote websites of official public health organizations to those seeking information on preventive measures on the internet. A recent study assessing health information about COVID-19 prevention on the internet revealed substantial differences regarding recommendations to wear masks or wash hands among websites of different countries affected by COVID-19 [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Searches of keywords that relate to the infodemic must prioritize public health websites and list them prominently where viewers will see them at the start of a search.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par25">Verify the accounts of public health personnel on popular social media platforms.</p>
   <p id="Par26">Media platforms like Twitter and Facebook, where the public indulges heavily in social interaction must verify the accounts of those appearing to be medical professionals. This will make it easier for the public to know whether the claimed source is verified and authentic or not.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par27">Promote the posts of public health and medical professionals.</p>
   <p id="Par28">In times of crises, social media platforms can sponsor posts of health officers to make sure that the public exposure and understanding is guided by reliable sources and authentic information.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par29">Monitor engagement on social media platforms to control the messages being delivered.</p>
   <p id="Par30">During the Zika virus outbreak in 2016, a cross-sectional survey of public information officers at local public health departments across the United States revealed that monitoring social media resulted in higher satisfaction with crisis management [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Thus, social media technology companies must closely review content shared on their platforms during pandemics to ensure false information does not promote harmful perceptions or practices.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par31">Establish programs that help people cope with stress and address their mental health concerns.</p>
   <p id="Par32">The media has a huge role to play in addressing the mental health aspect of the pandemic. Sick individuals may suffer from stress, anxiety, and fear. Quarantine and self-isolation may have severe psychological consequences and lead to difficulties in concentration, increased intake of alcohol, tobacco, and other drugs [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Lack of public knowledge on the virus can promote social stigma against individuals infected or suspected to be infected by the virus [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Furthermore, closure of medical clinics and postponement of medical appointments and elective procedures can worsen chronic health conditions. Acknowledging these conditions and guiding the public on how to manage and contain them via broadcasting media programs or social media posts is essential to promote health and well-being.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par33">Adopt an empathic style of communication to grab public attention and address health concerns.</p>
   <p id="Par34">Empathy in communication is critical for managing public anxiety and promoting behavioral compliance with public health guidelines. In China, online users generally had low engagement with posts relevant to COVID-19 from government agencies. Public posts that attracted more engagement, were more personal, showed empathy to affected people, and expressed worry about the epidemic [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Merely sharing updated information and policies may be insufficient to capture public interest in official communications.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par35">Promote dialogue to understand people’s perceptions and the motives behind their practices.</p>
   <p id="Par36">Communication through town hall meetings and debate circles can address concerns raised and hesitancy to adhere to health measures [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Such communication can further strengthen societal adhesion and unity.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par37">Share personal experiences on social media to combat misinformation.</p>
   <p id="Par38">Promoting stories of people who have been affected by the disease can have a major impact on people’s perception of the pandemic. To increase public confidence in HPV vaccines, Danish public health officials emphasized the risk of disease and promoted stories about people who had lost wives and mothers to cervical cancer. Ireland’s social media efforts used similar tactics to rebuild HPV-vaccine confidence; numbers for 2018 showed an increase of 6% for vaccine uptake from 2017 [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Adopting a similar strategy for COVID-19 is important.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par39">Direct health communication strategies towards minority populations and people of different classes, races, and ethnicities.</p>
   <p id="Par40">In the United States, health professionals estimated that about a third of COVID-19 fatalities are African Americans, even though African Americans constituted only 14% percent of the COVID-19 cases [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Based on media reporting, in New York, African Americans died at twice the rate of their white peers; Latinos in the city were also falling to the virus at a much higher rate than white or Asian New Yorkers [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Media companies must design health awareness campaigns for influencers and role models of different racial and ethnic backgrounds to present to the public. This ensures that people who share similar race or ethnicity feel relevant and thus become aware of the reality of the pandemic and the importance of prevention strategies and governmental efforts. In addition, governments and health officials need to direct health communication campaigns at highlighting the lack of access to healthcare facilities and services that certain populations might suffer from to drive corrective governmental health policies.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par41">Develop educational material and speed the share of evidence-based science to address existing wrong perceptions, correct behaviors, and promote healthy practices.</p>
   <p id="Par42">During outbreaks, people struggle with uncertainty and look for sources to fill their needs for information. Unfortunately, ordinary citizens and communication systems do not operate at the same pace as the scientific method, which often takes time to provide evidence-based results. As such, false information that are usually marginally believable lead to wrong conclusions and fake news reports [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Public health officials need to be faster in filling the public void for information and in directing conventional and social media platforms to better comprehend what to be reported and how data should be portrayed. When conventional media provides evidence-based information to the general public, it will eventually be picked up on social media [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], which will facilitate its rapid widespread among the public. This will ensure that the people will act effectively to control the disease and mitigate its impact. Awareness campaigns do not always achieve their desired impact because public health officials craft messages based on what they want to promote, without addressing existing perceptions.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par43">Increase investment in the research and development of health communication to explore and understand strategic ways of targeting different populations.</p>
   <p id="Par44">Health communication is a rising field in different parts of the world [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Investing in the field is important to understand the psychological influences that affect the individual efforts in following guidelines and seeking the right information. In addition, more research will be important to learn which health communication strategies will prove effective–through trials that assess communal perceptions of health communication and awareness campaigns.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
