<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Here, we have described the direct impact of synonymous substitutions on YFV replicative phenotype both 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. As previously described with TBEV (
 <xref rid="vey021-B15" ref-type="bibr">De Fabritus et al. 2015</xref>), the level of re-encoding necessary to observe viral attenuation 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> was lower than that required to obtain an observable decrease in replicative fitness 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>. As further suggested by supplementary, basic, growth curve experiments (data not shown), all re-encoded strains with only one re-encoded fragment (101–350 mutations) maintained a replicative phenotype close to that of the parental 
 <italic>Asibi</italic> strain 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>. Only YFV rTs4, that included an additional re-encoded fragment (741 mutations in total), showed a severe reduction in replicative fitness 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>. Previous works on Poliovirus, Echovirus, RSV, Influenza, HIV, CHIKV, DENV, and Marek’s disease virus (
 <xref rid="vey021-B10" ref-type="bibr">Burns et al. 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B58" ref-type="bibr">Mueller et al. 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B46" ref-type="bibr">Martrus et al. 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B60" ref-type="bibr">Nougairede et al. 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B3" ref-type="bibr">Atkinson et al. 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B41" ref-type="bibr">Le Nouen et al. 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B68" ref-type="bibr">Shen et al. 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vey021-B14" ref-type="bibr">Conrad et al. 2018</xref>) brought evidence that the effect of synonymous mutations may vary according to the location within the viral sequence. Hence, a control, 
 <italic>Asibi</italic>-derived virus including only the additional re-encoded fragment (388 mutations in the NS5) was produced. Contrarily to the viruses re-encoded in the NS2-3-4 region, it showed a decrease in replicative fitness during competition experiments (outcompeted by the wild-type virus at passage no. 10). As three consensus non-synonymous mutations (associated to major variants) arose in the viral sequence during the production of this virus, it is not possible to associate the 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> phenotype to the re-encoding in the NS5 protein rather than to the additional, consensus, non-synonymous mutations. However, this suggests that in the case of YFV, re-encoding may have a greater effect in the polymerase gene than in other non-structural proteins. In contrast with the 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> results, we observed a broad range of levels of attenuation among all the strains that were tested in hamsters (101–350 mutations). While the least attenuated viruses showed no observable loss of replicative fitness and retained a degree of lethality, the most attenuated viruses displayed a complete loss of lethality, together with a ten-fold reduction in viral loads in the liver and significant alleviation of weight loss. We did not produce nor test a hamster-adapted version of the rTs4 strain because such a heavily re-encoded virus would have been unlikely to achieve infection 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>.
</p>
