<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There is good evidence that in the wild PUUV-prevalences in bank voles are age-dependent (Bernshtein et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">1999</xref>; Escutenaire et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">2002</xref>). The age of bank voles is commonly estimated using bodyweight as a proxy as the basis for weight class categories, e.g., juvenile, subadult, and adult (Escutenaire et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">2002</xref>; Kallio et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">2007</xref>). Another method applied for age determination of voles is by assessing the development of the molars (Bernshtein et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">1999</xref>; Olsson et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B118">2002</xref>). As described for France, age-dependency of virus prevalence in the rodents may be indicative for a horizontal transmission of PUUV in the rodent host (Tersago et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B158">2011b</xref>). An explanation for this might be that adult rodents will have been exposed to viruses longer than young ones and on more occasions. Another theory discusses that older male rodents may suffer from immunosuppression due to high levels of stress hormones, which are associated with breeding, making them more vulnerable to infections (Deter et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">2008a</xref>). That sexually mature rodents may be at higher risk for infection due to fighting rituals, mating, and generally close social behavior was already mentioned (Escutenaire et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">2002</xref>). Moreover, juvenile rodents will have benefited from maternal antibodies during the first 3 months of their live and therefore less often been infected during suckling (Kallio et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">2006b</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">2010</xref>). Findings in Lower Bavaria affirm these observations. In the large part older animals are infected with PUUV. The odds of the tested bank voles being PUUV seropositive constantly increased with each unit increase of the rodents’ bodyweights (Thoma, personal communication). By implication, given the horizontal transmission and as indicated by the respective chapters in this paper climatic and environmental factors may have a benefit on the survival and aging of rodent populations and on population density. Together, increasing rodent population densities may lead to increased rodent contacts, which may foster the transmissibility of the virus, resulting in higher prevalences, and eventually driving and influencing hantavirus epidemics.
</p>
