<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In recent years, a large number of rapidly-spreading viral outbreaks have placed considerable demands on healthcare infrastructure, sparking global concern.
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> The emergence of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) in 2002,
 <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> the H1N1 influenza pandemic in 2009,
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>–
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> pandemics of the H5N1 and H5N7 strains of influenza A virus (IAV),
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> and the devastating Ebola and Zika virus epidemics of 2014 and 2015 illustrate the severity of these outbreaks.
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Among these viruses, avian influenza virus H5N1 has attracted a great deal of attention due to its rapid spread and high pathogenicity worldwide.
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> The leading cause of death in infected patients is diffuse alveolar damage and hemorrhage in the lungs, which is caused by overactive inflammatory responses.
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> Overproduction of inflammatory cytokines in H5N1-infected mice and humans, referred to as a cytokine storm, has been identified as the main cause of death associated with this virus.
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> Vaccination remains the most effective preventive measure against influenza viruses. Nevertheless, vaccination effectiveness is decreasing as new variants arise through antigenic drifts or shifts.
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Although some antiviral drugs such as zanamivir (Relenza) and oseltamivir (Tamiflu) are currently in use, the increasing emergence of drug-resistant strains affects their clinical application.
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Therefore, development of novel broad-spectrum prophylactic and therapeutic agents against IAV is urgently needed.
</p>
