<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par48">Regarding nCovid-19 and its similarity in transmission to SARS-CoV, recent studies have also demonstrated that transmission occurs via the receptor angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. This may indicate why SARS-CoV-2 has often led to severe and in many cases fatal respiratory tract infections, like its two SAR-CoV predecessors. Since the SARS-CoV epidemic of 2002 was also known to use the ACE2 receptor to infect humans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. Bronchoalveolar lavage fluid taken from nCovid-19 patients have shown that ACE2 is widely distributed in the lower respiratory tracts of humans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Furthermore, the virion S-glycoproteins expressed on the surface of coronaviruses adhere to ACE2 receptors on human cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. This location provides a target for uncovering the mechanistic insights into the severity of the disease and how this region has assisted in the zoonosis of SARS-CoV-2 specifically. Additionally, mutations in the genomic structure of SARS-CoV-2 also might elucidate on the aggressiveness and pathogenicity of the viruses, which may in turn help to explain why some strains are evolutionarily much more virulent and contagious. Angeletti et al. have described mutations in the endosome-associated-protein-like domain of the nsp2 and nsp3 proteins, the former possibly accounting for the high virulence and contagion, while the latter suggesting a mechanism that differentiates nCovid-19 from SARS-CoV [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. Our studies build on this knowledge and assist to begin to identify the sub-clinical causes for the virulence and unique pandemic pattern of this outbreak by identifying the evolving mutations from region to region. Additionally, previous studies by Pachetti et al. have reported novel recurrent mutations of the SARS-Cov-2, and our study corroborates these mutations in South America and Africa regions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].
</p>
