<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Due to high error rates of RNA replication, RNA viruses exist as quasispecies, defined as “ensembles of related genotypes”.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref> There is evidence that evolutionary selection targets RNA virus quasispecies populations rather than individual variants,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref> and that cooperative interactions between variants influences RNA virus pathogenesis. Cell culture passage of a mumps vaccine strain associated with meningitis resulted in reduced neurovirulence that correlated with heterogeneity at specific positions in multiple viral genes.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref> For West Nile virus, increased genetic heterogeneity after mosquito cell passage correlated with growth fitness in those cells.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref> Another study provided evidence suggesting that innate immunity can limit poliovirus pathogenesis by restricting viral diversity during transit to vulnerable tissues such as brain.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref> Despite the clear linkage between replication fidelity and pathogenesis, and although numerous studies support high mutation rates of RNA viruses, the range of genetic variability tolerated by specific viruses is not well understood. A four-fold increase in mutation frequency of poliovirus through chemical mutagenesis reduced infectivity by 95%.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref> In contrast, a 2-to-3-fold decrease in mutation frequency (3Dpol-G64S) reduced the capacity of the mutant poliovirus to compete with WT virus in direct competition assays in culture and in mice and resulted in highly attenuated viruses with restricted tissue tropism in mice.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref> Vesicular stomatitis virus (VSV) likely has a narrow tolerance for alteration in replication fidelity, based on the finding that mutations from chemical mutagenesis at two defined single-nucleotide positions in VSV genomes could be only moderately increased (2–3-fold) without abolishing infectivity.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref> Underscoring the contribution of diversity to pathogenesis, modulation of replication fidelity is a new and promising approach for engineering live-attenuated RNA virus vaccines. Poliovirus RdRp mutants with restricted genetic diversity elicit a protective immune response in mice comparable to the Sabin type 1 vaccine strain but have superior genetic stability since increased replication fidelity minimizes reversion to virulence.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref> Although constitutively low replication fidelity (m = 10
 <sup>−4</sup> to 10
 <sup>−5</sup> substitutions per nt per round of replication) is thought to be a key determinant of RNA virus quasispecies diversity, adaptation and virulence, the tolerated range of increased or decreased fidelity has appeared to be constrained to less than 4-fold. This is in sharp contrast to DNA genomes of bacteria such as 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> that may have profoundly greater fidelity (10
 <sup>−9</sup> to 10
 <sup>−11</sup> substitutions per gene per round of replication) but may tolerate up to 1,000 fold differences in replication fidelity in viable mutator phenotype bacteria.
</p>
