<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To perform viral competition assays, we generated a genetically marked clone of CHIKV AF15561 using sight- directed mutagenesis (Forward Primer: 
 <named-content content-type="sequence">5′-ctaaactaaaggggcccaaagcagcagcgctgt-3′</named-content>; Reverse Primer: 
 <named-content content-type="sequence">5′-acagcgctgctgctttgggcccctttagtttag-3′</named-content>) to introduce a silent mutation that generates an ApaI restriction site in nsP4, as described previously (
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2013</xref>). For in vitro competition experiments, C6/36 cells were seeded in 24-well dishes and inoculated in triplicate at an MOI of 1 PFU/cell with a 1:1 ratio of CHIKV AF15561-ApaI and CHIKV AF15561 or CHIKV AF15561-ApaI and CHIKV AF15561 E2 K200R. Following a 1 hr adsorption, virus inoculum was removed, cells were washed, and fresh media was added. At 24 hpi, 1/10
 <sup>th</sup> of the supernatant was passaged onto a new well of cells, and this was repeated for a total of five passages. RNA was extracted from the supernatant, and cDNA was generated as described above for CHIKV quantification. For in vivo competition experiments, 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> mosquitoes were microinjected intrathoracically with 138 PFU of a 1:1 mixture of CHIKV AF15561-ApaI and CHIKV AF15561 or CHIKV AF15561-ApaI and CHIKV AF15561 E2 K200R. At seven dpi, mosquito bodies and saliva were collected and processed as described above and frozen at −80°C. RNA was extracted from 50 µL of each sample using the Mag-Bind Viral DNA/RNA 96 kit (Omega Bio-Tek) on the KingFisher Flex Magnetic Particle Processor (Thermo Fisher Scientific) following the manufacturer’s instructions. cDNA was generated as described above for CHIKV quantification. Relative amounts of each virus in samples were evaluated as described previously (
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2013</xref>). In brief, cDNA was subjected to PCR using forward primer (
 <named-content content-type="sequence">5′-atatctagacatggtgga-3′</named-content>) and reverse primer (
 <named-content content-type="sequence">5′- tatcaaaggaggctatgtc-3′</named-content>) to amplify the region of nsP4 (6106–6794) containing the ApaI site. PCR products were digested with equal amounts of ApaI and PspOMI (isoschizomers) at room temperature for 30 min, and at 37°C for 4 hr. Complete digestion was confirmed using control PCR products amplified from cDNA plasmid clones of CHIKV AF15561 WT or CHIKV AF15561-ApaI. Digested products were run on a 1% TAE gel, stained with ethidium bromide (Sigma), and imaged using Syngene G:Box. The percent band intensity was quantified using Syngene GeneTools.
</p>
