<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29">MERS-CoV has also evolved a mechanism to escape the host cell immune system. When host sensors initiate signaling pathways, transcription of type I IFN genes begins, and the type I IFN response, which is an essential component of antiviral innate immunity, is initiated.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>
 </sup> IFN activates the transcription of numerous IFN-stimulated genes (ISGs) and synthesizes 2′,5′-oligoadenylate (2-5A), which causes RNase L activation.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>
 </sup> Activated RNase L can cleave both viral and host ssRNA, leading to translation stagnation and apoptosis and limiting virus replication and transmission in vitro and in vivo.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>
 </sup> However, the MERS-CoV protein NS4b has phosphodiesterase activity and antagonizes RNase L via enzymatic degradation, leading to inference with IFN signaling. Although NS4b is mainly expressed in the nucleus, the expression level of the NS4b protein in the cytoplasm is sufficient to prevent activation of RNase L.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>
 </sup> In addition, the MERS-CoV M, ORF4a, ORF4b, and ORF5 proteins are reported to be strong IFN antagonists, among which the ORF4a, ORF4b, and ORF5 proteins inhibit both type I IFN induction
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>
 </sup> and NF-κB signaling pathways, which are similar to the type I IFN signaling pathway,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>
 </sup> providing a possible mechanism for MERS-CoV evasion of innate immunity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
