<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Lopinavir
 <italic>/</italic>Ritonavir (LPV/r) is a coformulation of two structurally related protease inhibitor antiretroviral agents primarily used for treatment of HIV-1 infection in adults and children over 2 years of age. LPV/r reduces the replication of SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV in vitro [
 <xref rid="B107-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>,
 <xref rid="B108-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>] by inhibiting viral proteases including 3CLpro or PLpro [
 <xref rid="B108-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. Ritonavir is used in combination with Lopinavir to increase LPV half-life by inhibiting Cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) [
 <xref rid="B109-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. A study of six patients with confirmed COVID-19 infection in Korea and China showed a significant decrease in SARS-CoV-2 viral load and clinical improvement after administration of LPV/r [
 <xref rid="B110-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,
 <xref rid="B111-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. However, concomitant drug therapies, variation in starting time of therapy, different levels of illness severity, and the lack of a control group reinforces the need for caution when interpreting such results [
 <xref rid="B80-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>,
 <xref rid="B110-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,
 <xref rid="B111-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. In another study in Singapore the efficacy of LPV/r was evaluated on five patients with COVID-19 who required supplemental oxygen. Three of them improved within 3 days, while two experienced progressive respiratory failure. [
 <xref rid="B112-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. On the other hand, in a retrospective cohort study among 29 hospitalized patients who received LPV/r and were discharged, no differences in viral shedding duration was noted [
 <xref rid="B113-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. Similarly, Cao et al. reported a clinical trial including 199 patients with SARS-CoV-2 infection, which showed that LPV/r was not associated with clinical improvement [
 <xref rid="B114-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. However, the low efficacy of LPV/r in this study might be attributed to the advanced pneumonia in treated patients coupled with a lack of knowledge about the exact concentrations required to inhibit viral replication [
 <xref rid="B115-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>]. So far 10 ongoing clinical trials have been registered from China, Korea, Thailand and Hong Kong to evaluate efficacy of LPV/r for the treatment of COVID-19, either alone or in combination with other antivirals including ribavirin, interferon beta-1b or Chinese traditional medicine [
 <xref rid="B103-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. It is important to note that LPV/r has significant drug interactions including the risk of cardiac arrhythmia due to QT- prolongation [
 <xref rid="B116-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>]. Cao et al. documented multiple side effects of LPV/r including gastrointestinal adverse events (i.e., anorexia, nausea, abdominal discomfort, or diarrhea) as well as acute gastritis, hepatic injury risk, pancreatitis, more severe cutaneous eruptions, and QT prolongation, and the potential for multiple drug interactions [
 <xref rid="B114-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. The European Society of Intensive Care Medicine (ESICM) and the Society of Critical Care Medicine (SCCM) have recommended against the routine use of LPV/r in critically ill COVID-19 patients [
 <xref rid="B117-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]. The National Institutes of Health (NIH) guidelines recommend against the use of Lopinavir/ritonavir as a clinical benefit has not been demonstrated in patients with COVID-19, due to unfavorable pharmacodynamics and a lack of clinical trials [
 <xref rid="B2-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].
</p>
