<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The coevolution of HLA and KIR has been proved by several population studies worldwide, and different KIR–HLA pair correlations were identified in different populations. In 2006, Single et al. studied the distribution of KIR and its HLA ligands in 30 populations worldwide and observed that a balancing selection acted on the negative correlation between 
 <italic>KIR3DS1</italic> and 
 <italic>HLA-Bw4-80I</italic> pairs [
 <xref rid="B30-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In 2013, Hollenbach et al. compared KIR–HLA pairs in 105 populations worldwide and revealed a significant correlation between 
 <italic>KIR2DL3</italic> and 
 <italic>HLA-C</italic> ligands. However, the correlation for 
 <italic>KIR3DL1</italic> and 
 <italic>HLA-Bw4</italic> pairs was not significant [
 <xref rid="B39-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. In the Italian population, a correlation between 
 <italic>KIR</italic> and 
 <italic>HLA-C</italic> ligands was not observed; instead, a correlation between 
 <italic>KIR3DL1</italic> and 
 <italic>HLA-Bw4</italic> ligands, as well as 
 <italic>KIR3DL2</italic> and 
 <italic>HLA-A3</italic> and 
 <italic>HLA-A11</italic> ligands, was observed [
 <xref rid="B40-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. In the present study, the observed frequencies for 
 <italic>KIR2DL3</italic> and 
 <italic>HLA-C1</italic> ligands showed a correlation (r = 0.637, 
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.035) that agreed with Hollenbach et al.’s study, as well as Gendzekhadze’s study in the Yucpa og South Amerindian [
 <xref rid="B4-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The association of 
 <italic>KIR2DL3</italic> and 
 <italic>HLA-C1</italic> has also been investigated regarding the Hepatitis C virus and Malaria infection [
 <xref rid="B41-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. In Hirayasu et al.’s study, they found 
 <italic>KIR2DL3+HLA-C1</italic>, but no other KIR–HLA pairs were associated with cerebral malaria, and the frequency of combination was significant lower in malaria high-endemic populations. This result suggested that natural selection has reduced the 
 <italic>KIR2DL3+HLA-C1</italic> frequencies in malaria high-endemic populations to favor the development of malaria [
 <xref rid="B41-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Thus, KIR–HLA coevolution may be driven by microbial pathogens, resulting in specific distributions of KIR–HLA pairs in different populations.
</p>
