<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par41">Bacterial pneumonia is characterized by alveolar pneumonia (lobar pneumonia) and bronchopneumonia (lobular pneumonia). The manifestations of alveolar pneumonia include alveolar consolidation, which can be found in the cases of pneumococcus infection, pneumobacillus infection, and legionella infection. The lesions involve singular or multiple lung lobes. Chest X-ray demonstrates lobar or partial lobe occupied consolidation opacity with high even density with internal bronchial shadow containing air. The lesions at different locations have different radiological demonstrations. The intrapulmonary lesions are mostly absorbed within 2 weeks. In addition to the abovementioned pathogenic bacterial infections, bronchial pneumonia can also be caused by 
 <italic>Haemophilus influenzae</italic>, 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, and Gram-negative bacillus. Bronchial pneumonia commonly occurs in infants and young children, the elderly, and extremely weak patients. Chest X-ray demonstrates enhanced and thickened pulmonary markings, blurry nodular shadows in diameters of 6–8 mm, or blurry flakes of shadows in diameters of 10–25 mm. And relatively larger patches of uneven shadows with poorly defined boundaries are the result of overlapped multiple lobular alveolitic shadows (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">21.3</xref>). Bronchial blockage by mucus can be demonstrated as lobular atelectasis or focal emphysema in the lesion area. Bronchial blockage can result in a small triangular atelectasis. The lesions are mostly located in the medial zone of both lower lungs, with more posterior lobar lesions than anterior lobar lesions. They are distributed along the bronchial branches, with unobstructed bronchi in the pulmonary segment and lobe. Congestion, edema, and inflammatory exudates of the terminal bronchial mucosa can cause obstructive emphysema, with manifestations of increased transparency of both lung fields, expanded thorax, widened intercostal space, and flat low diaphragm.
</p>
