<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par26">Wolfe et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] identified five stages leading to endemic human disease, where a pathogen restricted to infecting animals may be transformed into a human pathogen. The first stage is when a pathogen is present in animals but has not yet been detected in humans under natural conditions; the second is when a pathogen has been transmitted from animals to humans, but there is no evidence of human-human transmission (e.g., tetanus, rabies); the third is when a pathogen can undergo only a few cycles of secondary transmission between humans and shortly die out, where a subsequent wave will require the involvement of animal hosts (e.g., Ebola virus, Marburg virus, monkeypox virus); the fourth is when a pathogen undergoes long sequences of secondary transmission between humans without the involvement of animal hosts (many vector-borne diseases, e.g., dengue virus, yellow fever virus, cholera, influenza A, typhus); and the fifth is when a pathogen previously restricted to animals later evolves into an exclusively human pathogen (e.g., smallpox, measles, syphilis, falciparum malaria, rubella, mumps, hepatitis B, tuberculosis, AIDS) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Consequently, the passage from one stage to another depends on the host-pathogen-environment interconnection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The emergence of infection is influenced by the interconnecting domains of determinants such as physical and environmental factors; ecological factors; genetic and biological factors; and social, political, and economic factors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Therefore, these determinants may influence the emergence and spread of infectious diseases. According to Chareonsook et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], human demographic changes and behavior, travel and commerce, ecological changes, technology and industry, microbial adaptation and change, and the breakdown of public health measures are sufficient factors for the emergence and spread of infectious diseases. Subsequently, Lederberg et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] identified additional factors such as human vulnerability, economic development, land use, lack of political will, poverty and social inequality, war and famine, and intent to harm.
</p>
