<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The viremia-dissemination equation was equal to 0.098*(Log
 <sub>10</sub> viremia) −0.268 and the viremia-transmission rate of a mosquito with a disseminated infection equation was equal to 0.056*(Log
 <sub>10</sub> viremia)−0.0155 (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0003163.s001">Figure S1</xref>, A and B; 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0003163.s002">Table S1</xref>). Both equations show a positive relationship for dissemination (N = 27; R
 <sup>2</sup> = 0.28; p = 0.0049) and transmission (N = 27; R
 <sup>2</sup> = 0.13; p = 0.07) as viremic dose increases. For each mosquito species we generated a linear equation and the y-intercept was adjusted for each mosquito species based on the difference between the experimentally observed rate and what the standardized equations described above (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0003163.s001">Figure S1</xref>, A and B) would predict at a specific viremic dose. This adjusted y-intercept and the standardized slopes from 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0003163.s001">Figure S1</xref>, A and B (Dissemination m = 0.098, Transmission m = 0.056) were utilized to create two unique linear equations for each mosquito species: one to calculate dissemination rate and one to calculate transmission rate with respect to viremic dose for each vector species. By solving for y when x = log
 <sub>10</sub> 7.5 PFU/ml we were able to estimate dissemination and transmission rates at an exposure viremia of 10
 <sup>7.5</sup> PFU/ml for each mosquito species (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0003163-t001">Table 1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0003163.s002">Table S1</xref>). When there were multiple data points for a mosquito species the averages of exposure viremia and the observed experimental transmission data were used to calculate the two linear equations for vector competence standardization.
</p>
