<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par77">Animal disease surveillance is critical for the welfare and sustainability of healthy livestock productivity systems of any country, as the threat of infectious diseases is large as well as diverse and dynamic. Preparedness and combating the prevailing emerging, re-emerging and transboundary diseases require sound monitoring and precision detection systems that are flexible and adaptable under field conditions. There is also an international obligation for OIE reportable diseases of high importance from the point of view of trading in animals and animal products harbouring potent infectious agents/pathogens by all member countries of WTO. It is the right time to apply developed diagnostics and molecular detection tools at the field stage to ensure fast detection and confirmation of pathogens capable of causing diseases in humans and animals. This must be accompanied by national-level disease surveillance, monitoring and networking to enable an early warning system for infectious diseases based on forecasting (Saminathan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2016</xref>). Due priority is also required for application of new vaccines, developing vaccine delivery systems and adopting prudent vaccination programmes and immunomodulatory and effective therapeutic modalities, which would help in devising timely prevention and control strategies against viral and other infectious diseases. Besides these, good management and standard biosecurity measures/practices and appropriate hygienic and zoo-sanitary and quarantine measures should be observed. Moreover, on-the-spot control and checking the spread of pathogens and adequate trade restrictions as envisaged under the SPS agreement of WTO also need to be followed. A holistic vision is required for timely implementation of these concepts and strategies along with strengthening of various multidimensional research and development programmes backed with appropriate funding resources. These measures will greatly help minimize disease incidences and outbreaks and lessen economic burdens due to infectious animal diseases and boost livestock and poultry health, reproduction and production to strengthen sustainable growth of livestock and poultry industry. Reduction in pandemic threats and public health concerns eventually lead to improvement in the socioeconomic status and welfare of the society at large.
</p>
