<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat.1006770.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1006770.g004</object-id>
 <label>Fig 4</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Example model outputs showing effect of synergistic and competitive interaction.</title>
  <p>
   <xref ref-type="boxed-text" rid="ppat.1006770.box003">Box 3</xref> gives details on the model that produces these epidemic trajectories. (A) In the baseline enhancing scenario, an endemic bacterial pathogen (blue) occurs at 5% prevalence. An influenza epidemic occurs with no interaction, and the bacterial prevalence does not change. If the presence of influenza coinfection increases bacterial transmissibility by 4-fold (
   <italic>σ</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>1</italic>
   </sub> = 4), then there is a transient rise in bacterial prevalence. If there is also an increase in influenza transmissibility during coinfection (
   <italic>σ</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>1</italic>
   </sub> = 4 and 
   <italic>σ</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>2</italic>
   </sub> = 2), then there is also a higher and earlier influenza peak as a result of coinfection. (B) In the baseline competition scenario, the second epidemic pathogen is introduced later than influenza. The two pathogens have the same transmission characteristics (same 
   <italic>γ</italic>, same β). If there is only a 50% chance of infection with pathogen 2 when individuals are infected with pathogen 1 (
   <italic>δ</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>1</italic>
   </sub> = 0.5), then the epidemic trajectory of pathogen 2 is lower and later. If competition is even stronger (
   <italic>δ</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>1</italic>
   </sub> = 0.1) so there is a 90% reduction in chance of coinfection, the profile of pathogen 2 is even further separated from pathogen 1. Computer code generating these trajectories is given in 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1006770.s004">S1 Code</xref>.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1006770.g004" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
