<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p> Washing hands is the first line of defence against viruses such as coronavirus. Fear of the public for COVID-19 has significantly contributed towards maintaining the personal hygiene of the individuals. Practicing good hygienic measures in hospitals, schools and other public places, could drastically reduce the spread and thereby eliminate new cases.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
 </sup> Governments and other organizations have succeeded in promoting the universal safety precautions such as washing hands, covering nose and mouth while coughing and sneezing, use of sanitizers, use of face masks, avoiding contact of fingers with mouth, nose and eyes, and social distancing techniques to a remarkable extent. Several cities and states across the world are currently short of hand sanitizers and face masks, which shows the public’s interest in acquiring the universal precautions to a remarkable extent.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
 </sup> Furthermore, in many countries, efforts are in place to demonstrate proper handwashing and mask usage techniques. Social distancing is a sage practice and an obvious action to be followed during outbreaks for preventing the spread of disease by confining the interaction of individuals and groups.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
 </sup> Unfortunately, in China, social distancing measures were not in place until it was too late; as a result, hospitals were filled to capacity, and a rapid transmission was observed, which had led to a steep spike in newer infections. As a result, with the goal of flattening the curve, the Chinese health authorities have implemented non-pharmacological measures such as social distancing, which showed a significant impact in limiting the spread.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
 </sup> A recent modelling study has predicted that if social distancing measures were implemented one week, two weeks and three weeks earlier in China, it could have reduced the number of new cases by 66%, 86%, and 95%, respectively.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
 </sup> Furthermore, a 
 <italic>New York Times</italic> model for the USA has suggested that aggressive social distancing measures could reduce COVID-19 cases from a possible peak of 9 million to 513000 and cumulative deaths from 982000 to 51000 over the next few months.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
 </sup> Similarly, by adopting the community mitigation measures such as social distancing, countries like South Korea, which experienced a severe outbreak in its initial days, is now remarkably declining its epidemic curve. 
</p>
