<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Nitrogen-containing heterocycles are widely distributed in nature and are essential in vegetal and animal metabolism. They are found in nucleic acids, vitamins, antibiotics, alkaloids, etc. [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In addition, nitrogen-containing heterocycles are important targets for medicinal chemistry, as they are found in more than half of the commercially available drugs and can also act as versatile intermediates in the synthesis of complex products that exhibit outstanding biological activities [
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Most of the nitrogen-containing heterocyclic compounds exhibit better biological activity than non-nitrogen compounds [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Currently, there are approximately 90 drugs approved for use in the treatment of nine human viral infections caused by human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis B virus (HBV), hepatitis C virus (HCV), herpes simplex virus (HSV), Influenza virus, human cytomegalovirus (HCMV), varicella-zoster virus (VZV), respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) and human papillomavirus [
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Most of these drugs (e.g., acyclovir, cidofovir, idoxuridine, nevirapine, pleconaril, ribavirin, etc.) are nitrogen heterocycle molecules [
 <xref rid="B3-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-25-00942" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].
</p>
