<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0218226.s001">
 <label>S1 File</label>
 <caption>
  <p>
   <bold>Table A:</bold> Characteristics of the subtype B population in the PT-naive cohort between 2001 and 2014. Missing data was less than 5%, the exception were variables with an asterisk. CD4 count, risk of transmission and continent of origin were excluded from the multivariate analyses given the amount of missing data. Abbreviations: IQR: interquartile range, n: sample, TDR: transmitted drug resistance, % percentage.
  </p>
  <p>
   <bold>Table B:</bold> Characteristics of the subtype G population in the PT-naive cohort between 2001 and 2014. Missing data was less than 5%, the exception were variables with an asterisk. CD4 count, risk of transmission and continent of origin were excluded from the multivariate analyses given the amount of missing data. Abbreviations: IQR: interquartile range, n: sample, TDR: transmitted drug resistance, % percentage.
  </p>
  <p>
   <bold>Table C:</bold> Characteristics of the “pure” subtype G population in the PT-naive cohort between 2001 and 2014. Missing data was less than 5%, the exception were variables with an asterisk. CD4 count, risk of transmission and continent of origin were excluded from the multivariate analyses given the amount of missing data. Abbreviations: IQR: interquartile range, n: sample, TDR: transmitted drug resistance, % percentage.
  </p>
  <p>
   <bold>Table D:</bold>Table D. Characteristics of the transmission clusters (TCs) in the PT-naive cohort and in the PT-naive cohort with TDR for the “pure” subtype G. Abbreviations: IQR: interquartile range, n: sample, NS: No significant, TCs: Transmission clusters TDR: transmitted drug resistance, % percentage.
  </p>
  <p>(DOCX)</p>
 </caption>
 <media xlink:href="pone.0218226.s001.docx" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <caption>
   <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
  </caption>
 </media>
</supplementary-material>
