<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig3">
 <label>Fig. 3</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Erucic acid inhibits NF-κB and p38 MAPK signaling after IAV infection. (A) A549 cells were infected with A/PR8/34(H1N1) (MOI = 0.1) and incubated with or without erucic acid for 24 h prior to Western blot analysis. Phosphorylated and total NF-κB (p65), MAPKs and AKT were detected with specific antibodies; GAPDH served as loading control. Data are presented as the mean ± standard error of the mean, representative of three independent experiments. ∗
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, ∗∗
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. IAV-infected. (B) Analysis of NF-κB transcription activity. NF-κB-luc reporter plasmid was transfected into 293 cells and cells were inoculated with A/PR8/34(H1N1) (MOI = 0.1) for 2 h prior to 24 h treatment with different concentrations of erucic acid. Cells were assayed for luciferase activity. Data are presented as the mean ± standard error of the mean, representative of three independent experiments. ∗
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, ∗∗
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. IAV-infected. (C) Combination of p38 MAPK and NF-κB inhibitors, and erucic acid treatment reduced viral polymerase activity. IAV minigenome-based reporter system-transfected cells were treated with or without p38 MAPK of NF-κB inhibitors. For the combined treatment cells were incubated with erucic acid for further 24 h and assessed using the dual-luciferase reporter assay system. Data are presented as the mean ± standard error of the mean, representative of three independent experiments. ∗
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, ∗∗
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 and ∗∗∗
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001 vs. untreated cells; 
   <sup>#</sup>
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs. BAY11-7082-treated (column 2); 
   <sup>§</sup>
   <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs. SB203580-treated (column 4).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text id="alttext0030">Fig. 3</alt-text>
 <graphic xlink:href="gr3" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
