<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par143">The pathophysiology of IV infection is related, at least in part, with the imbalance between oxidation and antioxidation systems, as well as with the state of AhR activation (
 <bold>Fig.</bold>
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">
  <bold>3</bold>
 </xref>). In this review, we presented several examples of the effect of the IV–host interactions on the intracellular redox and ROS states. Based on this knowledge, several potential therapeutics for the treatment or prevention of IV infection are presented (
 <bold>Tables</bold>
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">
  <bold>1</bold>
 </xref>
 <bold>and</bold>
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">
  <bold>2</bold>
 </xref>). Heaton et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR256">256</xref>] reported a CRISPR activation screening that aimed to identify a pan-avian IV-inhibitor host factor; those authors isolated the glycosyltransferase B4GALNT2, which can modify glycans containing α-2,3-linked sialic acids. However, most of these proposed therapeutic strategies require validation using animal models of IV infection and human clinical trials. Although many studies have uncovered the multifaceted roles of the cellular redox system and of ROS activity in IV-infection-induced lung inflammation and injury, several questions remain unanswered that are important for illustrating the precise IV–host interaction and that await further investigation. For example, both oxidative stress and virus replication result in chromatin remodeling, which largely affects gene expression, including that of Nrf2- and AhR-regulated genes, and determines the outcome of the virus–host interaction. Understanding the precise crosstalk between multiple chromatin modifiers, such as histone acetyltransferases/deacetylases and methyltransferases/demethylases, and the transcription factors Nrf2 and AhR upon IV infection is required to predict the consequences of viral infection accurately. Accordingly, a more specific and effective intervention for IV infection may be developed by targeting either ROS homeostasis or chromatin modifiers [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR257">257</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR258">258</xref>]. In conclusion, this review presents the notion that, in addition to viral components, the therapeutic treatment of IV infection may be achieved by targeting virus-induced ROS and redox-associated cellular responses, which may suppress IV propagation and reduce adverse inflammation in the host. 
</p>
