<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0065">This model diversification has required the application of new inference methods, whether completely novel or borrowed from other fields and adapted to epidemiological studies. Developments in statistical methods applied to infectious diseases in this period include accounting for the incubation period to infer transmission from disease data (
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">Donnelly et al., 2003</xref>), using data augmentation to account for asymptomatic/undetected transmission (
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Cauchemez et al., 2006</xref>) and likelihood-free parameter estimation (
 <xref rid="bib0215" ref-type="bibr">Toni et al., 2009</xref>). Fortunately, advances in computational capabilities, as well as advances in tools and software packages available have allowed for these developments. Infectious disease modellers now require skills in coding (often in several languages) and statistical inference, as well as an ability to manipulate and solve equations. However, with increasing model complexity, statistical inference becomes challenging and sometimes a distraction from the objectives of the analysis (ie. to capture the dynamics of infection through a population). Fortunately, shortcuts have been made increasingly available, such as packages to borrow inference from elsewhere and approximating the full likelihood, which has been helped by the sharing of code to complement equations within the papers. The increasing use of R and python software by researchers has also been transformational, as the software is relatively accessible and the use of libraries of additional code and wrappers to use other languages enable a rapid progression to carry out infectious disease modelling. To this end, several of the papers within this Special Edition make use of R libraries and various wrappers that port other languages into R (
 <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Auzenbergs et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Chatzilena et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">Funk and King, 2020</xref>), making modelling more accessible.
</p>
