<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">In view of the promising characteristics of carotenoids, more attention has recently been given to discovering novel natural safe sources of carotenoids with an effective impact on human diseases (cancer and viral hepatitis). In our study, the concentration of 
 <italic>Natrialba</italic> sp M6 pigment extract up to 0.79 mg/ml did not demonstrate any hemolysis effect but at 4.699 mg/ml caused hemolysis by 50%. Furthermore, the 
 <italic>Natrialba</italic> sp. M6 pigment extract was safer than the standard anticancer drug 5-FU against normal human cells, where the EC
 <sub>100</sub> of the studied pigment was 9-fold that of 5-FU. This extracted pigment also revealed potent antiproliferative and apoptotic activity against colon, breast, liver and cervical cancer cells. Previous study, in line with our findings, reported the antiproliferative effect of haloarchaeal carotenoids of 
 <italic>Halogeometricum limi</italic> and 
 <italic>Haloplanus vescus</italic> on the HepG-2 cell line at dose &gt;45 µg/ml
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>. This indicates that our pigment of 
 <italic>Natrialba</italic> sp. M6 strain exhibited a higher anticancer effect, causing 50% death in all four cancer cell lines at doses &lt;39 µg/ml, compared to the above-mentioned pigments. Cellular apoptosis occurs via activation of the proteolytic caspase cascade. Caspase 3 is the most important executor of endonuclease-mediated DNA fragmentation, and the formation of apoptotic bodies eventually leads to rapid irreversible cell death. The surface of these apoptotic bodies is characterized by the presence of phosphatidylserine as a ligand of phagocytes. Hence, annexin V (recombinant phosphatidylserine-binding protein) can be used for the quantification of apoptosis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. In the current study, annexin V-stained apoptotic populations were &gt;48% of the tested pigment-treated human cancer cell lines (Caco-2, MCF-7, HepG-2, HeLa), whereas 5-FU-treated cancer cells resulted in significantly smaller annexin V-stained apoptotic ppulations (31.37–38.01%). Moreover, the caspase-dependent apoptotic impact of the extracted pigment for stimulating cancer cell death was declared by their higher relative % of caspase activation than 5-FU 
 <bold>(</bold>Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5D</xref>
 <bold>)</bold>. Recent literature reported that supernatant metabolites of 
 <italic>H. salinarum</italic> IBRC M10715 and red pigment-producing HDZK-BYSB107 were able to induce apoptosis in prostate cells via upregulation of caspase 3
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
