<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The rubella virus (RV) was not only the first human teratogen identified, and as such the first human pathogenic virus that has been classified as a teratogen, it is still one of the most efficient teratogenic viruses. A teratogen is defined as a physical, chemical, or infectious agent associated with physical or functional birth defects, including growth retardation and pregnancy loss, that result from abnormal embryonal or fetal development (
 <uri xlink:href="www.embryo.asu.edu/handle/10776/7510" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.embryo.asu.edu/handle/10776/7510</uri>). Historically, malformations associated with congenital RV infection, as first described by Sir Norman Gregg in 1941, have formed our current concept of teratogenicity [
 <xref rid="B1-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In 1959, Wilson postulated the six principles of teratology, which are still valid today (embryo.asu.edu/handle/10776/7893). The second principle describes that susceptibility to teratogenesis depends on the developmental stage at the time point of exposure to the teratogen. Thus, our understanding of teratogenic mechanisms caused by agents such as RV is strictly dependent on our knowledge of human development, which has undergone some paradigm shifts in recent years. The first paradigm that has been challenged is the all-or-none hypothesis. It states that exposure to embryotoxic or teratogenic agents before organogenesis either does not affect embryonal development at all or results in embryonic death. However, cell death as a requirement for this hypothesis is not a general consequence of exposure to these agents. Instead, their mode of action and the associated congenital malformations are rather developmental stage-specific [
 <xref rid="B2-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Another paradigm shift refers to our view of pregnancies as a state of immune suppression. This is now replaced by our new understanding of the placenta and decidua as immunologically active organs [
 <xref rid="B3-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The elicited antiviral immune response mechanisms include interferon (IFN) signaling as a very efficient first line of defense against pathogenic viruses. The decidua as the maternal compartment of this embryo/fetal-maternal-interface results from morphogenetic restructuring of the endometrium as the inner lining of the uterine wall. Moreover, pregnant women have the capacity to elicit a solid immune response [
 <xref rid="B3-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], and the fetus itself is not entirely dependent on maternal immune functions. On the contrary, the maternal antiviral countermeasures are supported by the fetal immune response. This was revealed by a mouse model for the congenital Zika virus (ZIKV) infection based on the heterozygous knock-out of the type I IFN receptor, IFNAR, as a result of the crossing of IFNAR
 <sup>-/-</sup> female mice with wild-type males [
 <xref rid="B4-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Thus, in pregnant dams, IFNAR
 <sup>-/+</sup> fetal cells in the placenta were facing IFNAR
 <sup>-/-</sup> cells in maternal tissue. In comparison to their homozygous (IFNAR
 <sup>-/-</sup>) counterparts, the placental damage caused by ZIKV infection was reduced. Moreover, these heterozygote (IFNAR
 <sup>-/+</sup>) pups were partially protected from high viral burden, especially in the brain [
 <xref rid="B4-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. This leads to the third paradigm shift, the contribution of the IFN system to the protection of embryonal development. Compared to somatic cells, IFN signaling components are attenuated in embryonal and induced pluripotent stem cells (ESCs and iPSCs, respectively) as a cell culture model for early human development [
 <xref rid="B5-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The generation of iPSCs, through transfer of a cocktail of four pluripotency factors into human dermal fibroblasts using retroviral vectors as an ESC-counterpart with less ethical constraints, has changed developmental biology tremendously [
 <xref rid="B6-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The attenuation of the innate immune response in pluripotent stem cells appears to be due to the severe consequences IFN-associated inflammation could have for embryonal development. These negative effects would outweigh its beneficial antiviral activity. An engineered type I IFN response impaired, not only the morphology and pluripotency of iPSCs, but also their endodermal differentiation capacity [
 <xref rid="B7-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Thus, other mechanisms of protection against vertically transmitted pathogens appear to be in place during the very early phase of embryogenesis. One protective mechanism is provided by the intrinsic expression of a subset of IFN-stimulated genes (ISGs) including members of the interferon-induced transmembrane (IFITM) family at high levels, which in somatic cells are only expressed at the basal level and require IFN for their activation [
 <xref rid="B5-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. This highlights that our concept of human embryogenesis, and as such of congenital virus infections as initiated in 1941 by Sir Norman Gregg on malformations associated with maternal RV infections [
 <xref rid="B1-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], is in a constant state of flux. Both research areas, developmental biology and congenital virology, could mutually enrich each other. Not only does the analysis toolbox for virus-associated teratogenic alterations during embryonal development continuously advance, but teratogenic virus infections could also be used for the validation of these newly established models for embryonal development. The well-characterized symptoms associated with congenital virus infections can be correlated to developmental pathways and signaling circuits, and vice versa. Transplacental transmission, the crosstalk at the embryo/fetal-maternal compartment, and the mode of impairment of early embryonal development, remain ill-defined, not only for RV. Although there are already a number of recent reviews on RV and its associated teratogenicity, which is strictly human specific, the potential value of RV for the analysis of congenital virus infections in pluripotent stem cell-based models for the early steps of human development has not yet been discussed. These models offer insights into so far inaccessible processes during very early embryonal development and, thus, complement animal models and overcome some of their limitations. The need for validating these models for congenital virology research is reflected by the constant threat posed by emerging viruses. The recent ZIKV outbreak has shown how even a virus that has been circulating in the human population for decades could evolve and cause congenital malformations. Moreover, new human pathogens are discovered each year, some of which could affect human embryonal development. We will discuss the role that RV, as an archetypic teratogenic virus, could play in addressing future research questions on congenital virus infections. The first highlighted aspect is the placenta as an efficient barrier against virus transmission from the mother to the embryo or fetus; the so-called vertical transmission. Thereafter, we will compare the clinical symptoms and epidemiology of congenital rubella to other viruses with teratogenic impact during first trimester infection, namely human cytomegalovirus (HCMV) and ZIKV. Finally, the knowledge obtained from pluripotent stem cell-based cell culture models for the associated developmental steps of human embryogenesis will be discussed. This includes, not only the promises, but also the limitations that are associated with the use of these models.
</p>
