<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During IAV infection, the transient decrease in Ly6C
 <sup>high</sup> monocytes in the BM and their concomitant increase in the blood is consistent with the known recruitment of inflammatory monocytes in the lungs of IAV-infected mice [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Importantly, our analysis of the Ly6C
 <sup>high</sup> monocytes’ phenotype and cytokine production highlighted the presence of a mixed regulatory/inflammatory population in the BM of infected animals. Monocyte function is in general shaped by local signals in the tissue where the cells are recruited. A recent study demonstrated that monocytes can also be pre-emptively educated during their development in the BM [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Additional studies will be required to establish whether monocyte progenitor cells can be programmed in the BM for regulatory functions during IAV infection. In parallel with the changes in Ly6C
 <sup>high</sup> monocytes, we showed for the first time that an acute respiratory infection could lead to a drastic decrease in the numbers of BM and blood patrolling Ly6C
 <sup>low/-</sup> monocytes. This finding is in line with the reported recruitment of Ly6C
 <sup>low/-</sup> monocytes to the lungs of IAV-infected mice [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Lung Ly6C
 <sup>low/-</sup> monocytes can be switched towards an inflammatory phenotype, a process controlled by type I IFNs [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. The changes in Ly6C
 <sup>low/-</sup> monocyte homeostasis in the BM during IAV infection could also be due to increased generation of inflammatory Ly6C
 <sup>high</sup> monocytes at the expense of patrolling Ly6C
 <sup>low/-</sup> monocytes. Both hypotheses are not mutually exclusive.
</p>
