<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par42">Persons living in Woliso town do not have distance barriers to access to the Woliso hospital. The probability of severe disease after measles infection was therefore computed as the fraction of measles patients from Woliso town that have been hospitalized for two nights or more among all measles infections estimated by the transmission model for this spatial unit. For severe cases, we indicate here those cases that from a clinical point of view are physiologically unstable and require supportive care (fluid resuscitation, oxygen, etc.) that can be provided only inside a well-resourced hospital. The resulting probability of developing severe measles illness 
 <italic>p</italic>
 <sup>
  <italic>s</italic>
 </sup> was used in combination with the estimated number of measles infections at different kebeles and woredas 
 <italic>c</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub> to estimate the potential number of severe cases occurring at different distances from the hospital as 
 <italic>p</italic>
 <sup>
  <italic>s</italic>
 </sup>
 <italic>c</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub>. For each considered spatial unit 
 <italic>i</italic>, missed severe cases were computed as the difference between the estimated number of severe cases and the number of patients recorded at the hospital, namely 
 <inline-formula id="IEq2">
  <alternatives>
   <tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$ {m}_i^s={p}^s{c}_i-{h}_i $$\end{document}</tex-math>
   <math id="M10" display="inline">
    <msubsup>
     <mi>m</mi>
     <mi>i</mi>
     <mi>s</mi>
    </msubsup>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <msup>
     <mi>p</mi>
     <mi>s</mi>
    </msup>
    <msub>
     <mi>c</mi>
     <mi>i</mi>
    </msub>
    <mo>−</mo>
    <msub>
     <mi>h</mi>
     <mi>i</mi>
    </msub>
   </math>
   <inline-graphic xlink:href="12916_2018_1171_Article_IEq2.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </alternatives>
 </inline-formula>. Missed severe cases were considered untreated and counted as additional deaths. The overall number of deaths caused by measles was estimated as the sum of missed deaths and measles deaths observed among hospital admitted patients. Averted deaths due to hospital treatment were estimated by considering all severe cases 
 <italic>p</italic>
 <sup>
  <italic>s</italic>
 </sup>
 <italic>c</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub> as counterfactual deaths that would have occurred in the absence of adequate treatment.
</p>
