<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Lancet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Lancet</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Lancet (London, England)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0140-6736</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1474-547X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7194526</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S0140-6736(20)30739-X</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30739-X</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>COVID-19 gives the lie to global health expertise</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au10"><name><surname>Dalglish</surname><given-names>Sarah L</given-names></name><email>sdalgli1@jhu.edu</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of International Health, Johns Hopkins School of Public Health, Baltimore, MD 21205, USA</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Institute for Global Health, University College London, London, UK</aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub" iso-8601-date="2020-04-17"><season>11-17 April</season><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>395</volume><issue>10231</issue><fpage>1189</fpage><lpage>1189</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Elsevier Ltd</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p id="para10">As the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak began spreading in Europe and the USA, a chart started circulating online showing ratings from the 2019 Global Health Security <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ghsindex.org" id="interrefs10">Index</ext-link>, an assessment of 195 countries' capacity to face infectious disease outbreaks, compiled by the US-based Nuclear Threat Initiative and the Johns Hopkins School of Public Health's Center for Health Security. The USA was ranked first, and the UK second; South Korea was ranked ninth, and China 51st; most African countries were at the bottom of the ranking.</p><p id="para20">Things look different now. The US and UK Governments have provided among the world's worst responses to the pandemic, with sheer lies and incompetence from the former, and near-criminal delays and obfuscation from the latter. Neither country has widespread testing available, as strongly recommended by WHO, alongside treatment and robust contact tracing.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> In neither country do health workers have adequate access to personal protective equipment; nor are there nearly enough hospital beds to accommodate the onslaught of patients. Even worse, by refusing to ease sanctions against Iran, Venezuela, and Cuba, the US has crippled the ability of other countries to respond, continuing to block medical supplies and other humanitarian aid.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</p><p id="para30">Meanwhile, Asian countries, including China, South Korea, Singapore, and Taiwan, have provided rapid, effective, and often innovative responses, thanks in part to their recent experience with outbreaks of Middle East respiratory syndrome in 2015 and the 2002&#x02013;03 severe acute respiratory syndrome epidemic. China has convened hundreds of foreign officials to share lessons, and dispatched experts, masks and other supplies to Italy and other affected countries. Cuba has also sent doctors to help with the response, and welcomed sick cruise ship passengers refused entry by the USA.</p><p id="para40">Although it is too early to assess the strength of the COVID-19 response in Africa, African countries, despite limited resources, have also adopted measures worth imitating, such as simplified triage strategies<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> and proactive screening (Uganda), handwashing stations at transport hubs (Rwanda), WhatsApp chatbots providing reliable information and rapid testing diagnostics (Senegal), and volunteer-staffed call centres and celebrity campaigns to promote responsible actions during the pandemic (Nigeria). Yet relatively little has been heard on the global stage about these efforts or from African veterans of the Ebola epidemics in west Africa and central Africa, even though COVID-19 appears to spread in similar ways&#x02014;through family clusters.</p><p id="para50">Is preparedness in the eye of the beholder? COVID-19 is giving the lie to prevailing notions of expertise and solidarity. The global health model is based in large part on technical assistance and capacity building by the US, the UK, and other rich countries, whose response has been sclerotic and delayed at best. A recent report by Global Health 50/50 showed that 85% of global organisations working in health have headquarters in Europe and North America; two-thirds are headquartered in Switzerland, the UK, and the USA.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> More than 80% of global health leaders are nationals of high-income countries, and half are nationals of the UK and the USA.</p><p id="para60">Global health will never be the same after COVID-19&#x02014;it cannot be. The pandemic has given the lie to the notion that expertise is concentrated in, or at least best channelled by, legacy powers and historically rich states. We must move quickly, for our own security, beyond the rhetoric of equality to the reality of a more democratic, more multipolar, more networked, and more distributed understanding and operation of global health.</p><p id="para70">Conversations about how to do so, although just beginning, are long overdue.</p><p id="para70a">
<fig id="f10"><graphic xlink:href="fx1_lrg"/><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Gallo Images/Getty Images</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions></fig>
</p></body><back><ref-list id="bibl10"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>WHO</collab></person-group><chapter-title>Critical preparedness, readiness and response actions for COVID-19</chapter-title><year>2020</year><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Economists demand Trump immediately lift Iran, Cuba, and Venezuela sanctions that are &#x02018;feeding the coronavirus epidemic&#x02019;</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.commondreams.org/news/2020/03/19/economists-demand-trump-immediately-lift-iran-cuba-and-venezuela-sanctions-are" id="interrefs20">https://www.commondreams.org/news/2020/03/19/economists-demand-trump-immediately-lift-iran-cuba-and-venezuela-sanctions-are</ext-link><year>March 19 2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ayebare</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Flick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Okware</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bodo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamorde</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adoption of COVID-19 triage strategies for low-income settings</article-title><source>Lancet Resp Med</source><year>2020</year><comment>published online March 11.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(20)30114-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Global Health 50/50</collab></person-group><article-title>The Global Health 50/50 Report 2020: power, privilege and priorities</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://globalhealth5050.org/2020report/" id="interrefs40">https://globalhealth5050.org/2020report/</ext-link><year>March, 2020</year></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack><p>I declare no competing interests.</p></ack></back></article>