<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Delayed diagnosis and treatment of HIV, HBV, HCV, and syphilis can lead to severe complications and sequelae including liver cirrhosis, cancer, opportunistic infections, and death [
 <xref rid="B37-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. On the contrary, timely diagnoses and treatment of these co-infections can offset a faster disease progression, reduce transmission to sexual partners and children [
 <xref rid="B40-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], and will cumulatively decrease HIV, HBV, HCV, and syphilis epidemics. Hence, it is an important public health issue to assess the rate of these infections in a timely manner among the population. Unfortunately, like HIV-infection, there are no symptoms at the beginning of the infection, and the asymptomatic features of these infections favor their quiet spread. In the absence of knowledge of these diseases, diagnosis, and treatment, they are efficiently spread among vulnerable populations who present risk behaviors [
 <xref rid="B43-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. According to the results of the first CD4+ T-cell test, the time interval between HIV infection and diagnosis was estimated. It was estimated that 66.8% of HIV-infected patients had been infected with HIV for more than 3 years, and 25.2% had reached more than 8 years. Meanwhile, the source of HIV-infected patients was mainly passive detection such as “pre-operative testing” and “other patient detection”, which was much higher than the active detection method such as voluntary counseling and testing (VCT), indicating that HIV-infected patients were found late [
 <xref rid="B45-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. This is consistent with previous experimental results. Because of similar routes of transmission and risk factors, we speculate that HBV, HCV, and syphilis infection among HIV-positive individuals of this study were found late too, as even they were not aware of their infection status at all when they were diagnosed with HIV. The average infection time of ≥50 years old was significantly higher than that of &lt;50 years old group (
 <italic>t</italic> = 4.500, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01). Only 13.6% of HIV-infected individuals ≥50 years old were diagnosed with recent HIV infection by Limiting antigen avidity enzyme immunoassay (LAg-avidity EIA). The data indicates that late diagnosis is more severe in the elderly population. The phenomenon is likely multifactorial. Subjects ≥50 years old usually do not perceive themselves at risk of HIV infection [
 <xref rid="B46-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Further, shyness and lack of knowledge on how to get a HIV test may cause late detection and late diagnosis [
 <xref rid="B47-ijerph-17-01990" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], and indicate that current sexual health services should be adjusted to better meet their needs.
</p>
