<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">Aptamers are produced through an in vitro procedure, which specifically isolates aptamers for a target of interest and involves repetitive selection-amplification rounds, termed as SELEX [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. The main advantage of this procedure is to select aptamers, as nucleic acid-based affinity ligands, without any prior knowledge of the target. One of the modified SELEX procedures is the Cell-SELEX, which is used to discover specific aptamers against a whole cell (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). In other words, cells are considered as the target in selection process [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. An oligonucleotide library consists of 10
 <sup>12</sup> to 10
 <sup>16</sup> distinct sequences. The random region of library is usually 40–100 bases long, flanked by constant primer sequences at both ends, facilitating PCR amplification [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. The separation of the target-bound sequences from unbound ones via an affinity-based partitioning method and the amplification of the bound sequences by PCR are the important phases of SELEX method. Then, amplified sequences are converted into single strand forms and single stranded oligonucleotides enter the next cycle of SELEX, same as the previous round. The selection cycles are repeated several times to achieve high-affinity sequences in an enriched pool. The identity of DNA pool individuals is determined by cloning and then, sequencing [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] or by next generation sequencing techniques [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Several negative selection cycles are developed through a SELEX process to reduce the nonspecific bound oligonucleotides, to enhance the specificity of evolved pool. This type of SELEX has been extensively applied to develop aptamers against bacteria or other pathogenic cells. Low diversity of the DNA library sequence, PCR reagent contamination, contamination of the eluted sequences from the target cells, strong non-specific binding, low frequency of target molecules on the cells and the change in a cellular state can affect negatively the enrichment of the aptamer sequences [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. 
</p>
