<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Vector competence refers to the inherent capacity of an invertebrate host to become infected and ultimately transmit a given pathogen. For mosquito-borne viruses, this requires infection of the epithelial cells of the mosquito midgut following blood meal acquisition and digestion, efficient replication of the pathogen in the gut, traversing of the basal lamina of the midgut to enter the hemocoel, infection of/replication in the salivary glands, and sufficient accumulation of infectious particles in saliva for transmission to competent hosts [
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Numerous studies have documented highly significant effects of adult holding temperature on vector competence for zoonotic arboviruses of interest (
 <xref rid="viruses-11-01013-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>; [
 <xref rid="B30-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]). Increases in environmental temperature increase viral replication rates in ectothermic hosts, and because viral dissemination is directly correlated to viral load [
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], temperature increases should generally result in shorter extrinsic incubation periods (EIPs) and increased overall transmissibility. While this is largely the case, the magnitude of this effect is variable and dependent on the virus species, virus strain, dose, mosquito species, and mosquito population (
 <xref rid="viruses-11-01013-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>; [
 <xref rid="B30-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]). Kilpatrick et al. [
 <xref rid="B37-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] demonstrated an accelerated EIP for the WNV02 genotype strains relative to NY99 genotype strains which was magnified at higher temperatures, yet similar studies by Danforth et al. [
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] with distinct mosquito populations and strains measured no strain-specific effect of temperature. Additionally, while replication and subsequently EIP is generally accelerated, the effect on susceptibility is more variable and similarly species-dependent. For instance, studies with Rift Valley fever virus (RVFV) found increased infectivity at increased temperatures for 
 <italic>Cx. pipiens</italic> [
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] but no difference in infectivity at higher temperatures in 
 <italic>Ae. fowleri</italic> [
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. There is also likely a thermal limit to the correlation between competence and temperature that is virus and mosquito-specific and independent from effects on mosquito fitness (addressed below). For instance, Vogels et al. found increased competence from 18 to 23 °C in Dutch and Italian populations of 
 <italic>Cx. pipiens</italic>, yet further increases from 23 to 28 °C only increased competence in Italian 
 <italic>Cx. pipiens</italic> [
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. While there are limited studies that demonstrate decreased competence above a thermal limit with zoonotic arboviruses [
 <xref rid="B33-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], this is likely a result of experimental design (most studies have utilized maximum temperatures of between 28–32 °C). Although this review does not focus on arboviruses which utilize humans as amplifying hosts, more extensive studies assessing thermal limits and the role of interactions between mosquito genotype, viral genotype and temperature have been completed with dengue, chikungunya and Zika viruses [
 <xref rid="B52-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. A recent study by Tesla et al. which studied Zika virus competence at a temperature range from 16.0–38.0 °C found that competence was maximized at 30.6 °C with significant declines above 34.0°C, and EIP accelerated up to 36.4 °C, followed by a steep decline [
 <xref rid="B54-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. These relationships are likely to be highly variable with different virus strains and mosquito populations. In fact, the influence of mosquito genetics could at times supersede the generic effects of rising temperatures, even at relatively low temperatures, as has been shown by increased transmission of dengue and chikungunya at lower temperatures in some mosquito populations [
 <xref rid="B53-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Given the specificity of these interactions, future studies with enzootic arbovirus should focus on establishing the relationship of temperature to competence in individual populations with circulating viral genotypes. In addition, a more thorough understanding of the mechanistic basis for population and strain-specific interactions with temperature could significantly increase our capacity to utilize genetic surveillance to predict regional impacts of climate change on arbovirus transmission.
</p>
