<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The differentiation of DCs and monocytes in the BM is tightly controlled by growth factors, cytokines and transcription factors (for reviews [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]). Acute microbial infections induce a host phenomenon known as emergency myelopoiesis, which maintains the supply of myeloid cells (particularly monocytes) to the infected tissues. For example, systemic bacterial infection with 
 <italic>Ehrlichia muris</italic>, 
 <italic>Yersinia Enterocolitica</italic> or 
 <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> modulates myeloid progenitors in the BM, promotes myeloid cell differentiation, and thus contributes to host defences [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Systemic viral infections can also trigger myelopoiesis in the BM [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. There is also evidence to suggest that local (i.e. non-systemic) infections can also indirectly affect BM myelopoiesis. For instance, intestinal infection with 
 <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> can act remotely to reprogram myeloid progenitors in the BM - leading to profound changes in monocyte functions [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Respiratory viral infections also trigger myeloid cell production in the BM, which influences lung immunity and contributes to viral clearance [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. This emergency response to systemic or local infection is mediated by inflammatory mediators (
 <italic>e</italic>.
 <italic>g</italic>. type I and II interferons (IFN)) produced systemically [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] or locally in the BM [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007360.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].
</p>
