<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par64">Serum antibodies have long been used in the treatment of many diseases caused by viruses, such as poliomyelitis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR138">138</xref>], measles [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR139">139</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140">140</xref>], mumps [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR141">141</xref>], and influenza [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR142">142</xref>]. A meta-analysis showed that the administration of serum from recovered patients to infected patients during the H1N1 influenza pandemic resulted in reduced mortality rates [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR143">143</xref>]. Although the efficacy of this type of treatment was observed to be dependent on the viral pathogen, it has been employed in numerous viral outbreaks that claimed the lives of millions of people. Nevertheless, it is noteworthy that antibodies were studied and used at that time before any information was available about virus serotypes and clinical studies were approved. The use of serum antibodies has increased in the wake of recent viral outbreaks. They were employed in the treatment of patients during the H1N1 influenza pandemic, where they led to a decrease in the respiratory distress and fatality rates in critically ill patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR144">144</xref>]. Convalescent serum was also experimented with during the Ebola pandemic in 2013. Its use reduced mortality in infected patients compared to those undergoing routine treatment, as observed in a study conducted in Africa during the Ebola outbreak [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR145">145</xref>]. Furthermore, evidence from studies conducted during various viral outbreaks worldwide suggests that treatment with sera from convalescent patients can improve survival [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR146">146</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR149">149</xref>]. Although every virus is unique, the information gained from these studies is potentially applicable for combating the COVID-19 pandemic.
</p>
