<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0055">Why the children are less affected is still not very clear but following may be the contributing factors. Children are made to stay at home and usually well cared for. The exposure to sick is less, that in turn implying that viral load may be less to begin with. Ciaglia et al in their review have elaborated upon the higher circulating levels of ACE 2 in children and asserted that it could offer protection by means of buffering effects and severe infection in elderly could possibly occur due to immunesenescence.
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>28</sup>
 </xref> It is also speculated that children are less sensitive to COVID-19 infection because the maturity and function (e.g., binding ability) of ACE2 in children may be lower than that in adults.
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref> Furthermore, children's immune systems are in developing stage and may respond to challenges differently from adult immune systems. The Immature respiratory tract and immune system in children contributes to severe illness in case of other viral respiratory diseases like influenza or respiratory syntial virus
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>29</sup>
 </xref> but conflicting reports are there in case of COVID 19. Children may have some peculiar mechanisms which regulate the interaction between the immune system and respiratory machinery. This may be the contributing mechanism for milder COVID 19 disease in children. It may be possible that lung infiltrates may have a protective role in paediatric SARS-CoV-2 infection, similar to lymphocytes participating in inducible bronchus-associated lymphoid structure development after respiratory insult.
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>30</sup>
 </xref> There is also heightened procoagulant activity suggested by elevated D-Dimer levels in children similar to adults.
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
