<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previously, it was believed that avian influenza viruses may not cause the next influenza pandemic directly, as pigs were considered a necessary intermediate host to facilitate reassortment between avian, swine and human influenza viruses. In addition, pigs were thought to serve as a critical host for initial mammalian adaptation. However, the role of pigs as mixing vessel for avian and human influenza viruses may not be unique, as humans can be infected with avian influenza viruses directly from an avian reservoir. Reassortment of the H5N1 virus with contemporary human influenza viruses did not easily yield an airborne-transmissible virus between mammals.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib116">116</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib117">117</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib118">118</xref>
 </sup> However, more recently, it was shown that several reassortant H5N1 virus variants were transmitted via the airborne route between guinea pigs.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">16</xref>
 </sup> This H5 virus, which revealed dual specificity for avian and human receptors, required the PA and NS genes of the A(H1N1)pdm09 virus to acquire airborne transmissibility between guinea pigs. In addition, the NP, M and NA genes from A(H1N1)pdm09 virus were important to enhance airborne transmissibility between mammals. These results appear to be in contrast to the study of Imai 
 <italic>et al.</italic>,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref>
 </sup> in which a reassortant virus with a mutant H5 HA with human receptor specificity in a A(H1N1)pdm09 virus backbone failed to transmit via the airborne route between ferrets. This difference may be explained by the use of different lineages of H5 HAs. In addition, it is unclear how the guinea pig and ferret models compare with respect to H5 virus transmission studies. However, as mentioned above, the avian-human reassortant influenza virus in the study of Imai 
 <italic>et al.</italic> transmitted via the airborne route after passaging in ferrets, when a few additional genetic changes in HA were acquired. These two studies thus demonstrated that different airborne-transmissible H5N1 strains can emerge upon reassortment between human and avian influenza viruses, as was previously also shown for avian H9N2 virus.
</p>
