<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29">A recent study in which single gene segments of the 1918 virus were replaced with those from a recent human H1N1 influenza virus, work in one of our laboratories (T.M.T. and colleagues)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>
 </sup> has revealed that the HA, NA and polymerase PB1 genes are important for virulence and replication in the mouse system; however, the fully virulent phenotype is observed only with the completely reconstructed virus (
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>; T.M.T., J.K.T. and colleagues)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>
 </sup>. The demonstrated role of the HA and PB1 genes in replication efficiency and virulence is particularly interesting because both genes were transferred by reassortment from an avian virus to the then-circulating human influenza virus, to generate the 1957 and 1968 pandemic strains. The acquisition of an avian influenza PB1 gene by reassortment might result in increased transcriptional activity of the RNA-dependent RNA polymerase and increased virus replication efficiency of a new pandemic strain
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>
 </sup>. The HA and its binding preference for particular sialic acid (SA)-terminated glycans has also been implicated in efficient transmission of the 1918 virus in ferrets (T.M.T. 
 <italic>et al</italic>.)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>
 </sup>. It has been generally suspected that a switch in receptor-binding preference that confers efficient transmission among humans would be a necessary step for avian influenza viruses in the generation of a pandemic virus. Notably, we (T.M.T. and colleagues) have found that mutation of two amino acid residues (D190E, D225G) in the HA, which was previously identified as sufficient to switch the receptor-binding preference of parental 1918 HA (α2,6 SA receptor preference) to the avian α2,3 SA receptor preference
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>
 </sup>, prevented transmission among ferrets without affecting the replication efficiency of the rescued 1918 virus
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>
 </sup>. These findings suggest that changes in receptor binding of avian influenza viruses could potentially move them one step closer to a pandemic phenotype.
</p>
