<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>IAV cause severe respiratory tract infections, which are associated with lung inflammation, excessive ROS production from NOX2 oxidase and significant lung pathology.
 <xref rid="resp13524-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="resp13524-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="resp13524-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="resp13524-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="resp13524-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="resp13524-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="resp13524-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">15</xref> The spatial restrictions of ROS strongly suggest that their site of production governs their site of action. Indeed, we have recently identified endosomes as key sites of ROS generation during influenza virus infections.
 <xref rid="resp13524-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="resp13524-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">16</xref> To this end, we custom‐modified the NOX2 oxidase peptide inhibitor gp91ds‐TAT to target these subcellular compartments and tested the therapeutic potential of localized NOX2 oxidase inhibition. Importantly, this novel endosome‐targeted inhibitor of NOX2 oxidase reduced the severity of various clinical outcomes associated with a low pathogenic IAV infection.
 <xref rid="resp13524-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref> This was characterized by a reduction in airway inflammation, lung injury and oxidative stress. In the present study, we utilized a high dose of the highly pathogenic IAV, that is PR8, and tested whether this endosome NOX2 oxidase targeting system had the capacity to reduce lung pathogenesis. Airway and lung parenchymal inflammation are important pathological characteristics of influenza virus infections, particularly those due to highly pathogenic strains, such as PR8. In the present study, PR8 infection caused significant changes to lung morphology characterized by extensive alveolitis, peribronchiolar inflammation and infiltrating inflammatory cells, together with airway epithelial denudation and perivascular inflammation. Strikingly, Cgp91ds‐TAT treatment attenuated all of these key parameters with marked reductions in alveolitis, suggesting that endosome ROS is a major contributor to the deleterious parenchymal inflammation observed during infections with highly pathogenic IAV.
</p>
