<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32">A full sagittal section was mounted of one dichorionic fetus from dam 1, and frontal and coronal sections of the singleton dam 2 pregnancy were formalin-fixed and paraffin-embedded. Sections were H&amp;E stained to assess for localized inflammation, as well as to visualize and identify tissues within the fields. Serial sections of all marmoset tissues were further probed for ZIKV viral genome using RNAscope ZIKV probes (Advanced Cell Diagnostic, Inc.) for both + (stable) and − (active replicating) RNA strands to determine subcellular localization of viral establishment and active replication. Probing utilized established methodologies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>. Briefly, 4 µM sections were deparaffinized and subjected to antigen retrieval as per manufacturer’s instructions (RNAscope 2.5 HD Detection Kit, ACD). A previously designed probe set of complementary oligos against either strand, covalently bound to adapter sequences was then applied
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>. The ZIKV sequence specific probe sets consisted of 87 probe pairs requiring hybridization of adjacent matching genome sites for adapter probe hybridization and amplification. DAB signal was generated after a series of amplification probes as per manufacturer’s instructions. Placenta were also stained with 4G2 antibody against flavivirus protein E (Millipore) as previously described
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup>. Vero cells (Green monkey kidney epithelial) infected with contemporaneous ZIKV were used as a positive control. Cells were infected with first passage ZIKV HN16 (GenBank: KX928077.1) isolated from traveler returning to the USA from Honduras. Following 6 days of 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> infection and replication, scraped cells were formalin fixed in a syringe, then paraffin embedded. Bright field slides were examined under low and medium power using a Nikon Eclipse 90i microscope (Nikon Instruments, Melville, NY, USA). Minor adjustment for contrast and background levels were made using NIS Elements Viewer 4.20 (Nikon) and Adobe Photoshop CC.
</p>
