<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Hemaglutination inhibition experiments gave the same trends as the BLI assay, but effects were smaller. A difference was seen in the degree of inhibition and multivalency effects. Overall the data are consistent with a bivalent chelating binding mode.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref6">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48">48</xref>
 </sup> As such this is the first example of a nonmacromolecular compound to demonstrate this and indicates that with additional optimization a therapeutic avenue is within reach. Compounds 
 <bold>14</bold> and 
 <bold>12</bold> were tested in infection inhibition assays and cell killing inhibition assays. In both of these cases inhibition is clearly observed, and the order of potency is consistent with that from the BLI assay. Furthermore, no toxicity was observed for these compounds. In the BLI assay it was remarkable that no effect of the NA inhibitor oseltamivir carboxylate was observed. Furthermore, in the infection inhibition assay no NA inhibitor was added, yet full inhibition was observed. Others
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref>
 </sup> have seen a similar nonresponse to NA blocking before and explained it with (1) the tight inhibitor binding to HA, resulting in less availability for NA, (2) weak inherent NA activity, especially on the α-2,6 isomers, and (3) a lower presence of NA compared to HA. For medical application of this type of NA inhibiting compound the introduction of an S-linked sialic acid, as previously reported,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref49">49</xref>
 </sup> is nevertheless recommended to ensure sialic acid cleavage from the inhibitor by NA does not happen. In agreement herewith, 
 <bold>15</bold> showed a synergistic effect with NA inhibitor OC. Low nanomolar concentrations of either reagent had no major effect, but the combination greatly reduced infections. This result supports the notion of a combination therapy, as practiced for HIV. The multivalent approach as described here may not be limited to IAV but can likely be extended to other systems as previously shown for adenovirus.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref50">50</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
