<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The complexity of MIEP regulation further amplifies when considering transcription in the chromatin or “epigenetic” context. The MIEP may undergo limited DNA methylation, especially in systems for transgene expression, and the major IE gene exhibits CpG dinucleotide suppression [
 <xref rid="B97-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,
 <xref rid="B98-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,
 <xref rid="B99-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>,
 <xref rid="B100-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>,
 <xref rid="B101-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>]. Beyond these observations, there is little evidence that MIEP activity or IE transcription are regulated by DNA methylation following HCMV or MCMV infection [
 <xref rid="B102-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>,
 <xref rid="B103-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>,
 <xref rid="B104-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. Nuclear HCMV genomes form nucleosomes, octamers of core histones H2A, H2B, H3 and H4 wrapped with just under 150 bp of DNA, resembling host chromatin structure [
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B105-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Consequently, the chromatin of HCMV and other DNA viruses that replicate in the nucleus is subject to regulation by nucleosome occupancy, histone composition and post-translational histone modification [
 <xref rid="B106-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>,
 <xref rid="B107-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>,
 <xref rid="B108-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. Nucleosome occupancy on the MIEP is believed to be low during productive infection, but likely increases during establishment of latency based on findings from the mouse model and by analogy to other herpesviruses [
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B105-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>,
 <xref rid="B109-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. Numerous studies have shown correlations between activating or repressive histone modifications associated with the major IE gene and the levels of viral gene expression. For example, association of the MIEP with H3K4me2, H3K4me3, H3K9/14ac, H3S10ph or H4Kac has been linked to high levels of IE (or transgene) transcription and productive infection or reactivation from latency [
 <xref rid="B72-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B110-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,
 <xref rid="B111-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>,
 <xref rid="B112-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>,
 <xref rid="B113-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>,
 <xref rid="B114-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>,
 <xref rid="B115-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>,
 <xref rid="B116-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B120-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>]. By contrast, the presence of H3K9me2, H3K9me3 or H3K27me3 at the MIEP generally correlates with low levels of IE transcription and either latent or the onset (pre-IE phase) of productive infection [
 <xref rid="B110-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,
 <xref rid="B111-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>,
 <xref rid="B112-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>,
 <xref rid="B115-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>,
 <xref rid="B116-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00110-f001">Figure 1</xref>). In agreement with these observations, histone modifying enzymes and enzyme complexes including histone acetyltransferases (e.g., KAT6A/MOZ), histone deacetylases (e.g., HDAC1, HDAC3), histone methyltransferases (e.g., EHMT2/G9A, EZH2, SETDB1, SUV39H1), histone demethylases (e.g., KDM1A/LSD1, KDM4A/JMJD2, KDM6B/JMJD3) and histone kinases (e.g., MSK family) have all been implicated in regulating transcription from the MIEP [
 <xref rid="B72-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B120-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>,
 <xref rid="B121-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>,
 <xref rid="B122-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>,
 <xref rid="B123-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>,
 <xref rid="B124-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>,
 <xref rid="B125-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>,
 <xref rid="B126-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>,
 <xref rid="B127-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>,
 <xref rid="B128-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>,
 <xref rid="B129-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00110-f001">Figure 1</xref>). The histone modifying proteins are typically recruited by transcription factors bound to the MIEP including cAMP responsive element binding protein 1 (CREB1), ETS2 repressor factor (ERF) and Ying Yang 1 transcription factor (YY1). In turn, chromatin modifications lead to the recruitment of further activators or repressors that may affect IE expression making for a complex hierarchy of transcriptional regulation [
 <xref rid="B107-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>,
 <xref rid="B130-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>,
 <xref rid="B131-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>].
</p>
