<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Expression of the major IE gene also varies with the activity of cellular signalling pathways that connect the extra- and intracellular environment to the nucleosomes and transcription factors associated with the HCMV genome including the MIEP. The virus has been shown to activate, rewire or inhibit numerous of these signalling pathways. HCMV infection triggers both pathways considered to be proviral as well as pathways linked to innate immune responses resulting in the production of proinflammatory and antiviral cytokines. In fact, many signalling pathways appear to exhibit both pro- and antiviral potential, and the net effect on the virus depends on various factors including cell type and stage of infection. Binding of HCMV to receptor proteins on the cell surface initiates the first wave of signalling. The virus engages various cellular entry receptors, several of which activate similar pathways relevant to the IE phase of infection [
 <xref rid="B145-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>,
 <xref rid="B146-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>,
 <xref rid="B147-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>,
 <xref rid="B148-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>,
 <xref rid="B149-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>]. In particular, epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR), platelet-derived growth factor receptor alpha and integrins independently trigger the phosphatidylinositol 3-phosphate and protein kinase B (PI3K/AKT) pathway [
 <xref rid="B150-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>,
 <xref rid="B151-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">151</xref>,
 <xref rid="B152-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>]. The PI3K/AKT pathway is central to many cellular properties including motility, proliferation and survival [
 <xref rid="B153-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>,
 <xref rid="B154-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">154</xref>,
 <xref rid="B155-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>]. Transient induction of this pathway triggered by receptor signalling appears to be followed by more sustained activation involving the viral major IE proteins [
 <xref rid="B156-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>,
 <xref rid="B157-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>,
 <xref rid="B158-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>,
 <xref rid="B159-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>]. Initial PI3K/AKT activation is required for efficient viral entry as well as optimal replication in fibroblasts and establishment of latency in monocytes [
 <xref rid="B156-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>,
 <xref rid="B158-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>,
 <xref rid="B160-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>,
 <xref rid="B161-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>,
 <xref rid="B162-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>,
 <xref rid="B163-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">163</xref>]. However, at later times during infection inhibition of EGFR or PI3K seems to favour viral replication and reactivation from latency suggesting a negative regulatory role at this point [
 <xref rid="B164-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>,
 <xref rid="B165-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>,
 <xref rid="B166-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">166</xref>,
 <xref rid="B167-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>]. Besides PI3K/AKT signalling, various other kinase pathways are known to be activated very early during HCMV infection. These pathways include mitogen-activated kinase (MAPK) signalling both via extracellular signal-regulated kinase (ERK) 1 and 2 including RAF1 (MAPKKK upstream of ERK) as well as via p38 MAPK [
 <xref rid="B168-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">168</xref>,
 <xref rid="B169-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">169</xref>,
 <xref rid="B170-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">170</xref>,
 <xref rid="B171-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">171</xref>,
 <xref rid="B172-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">172</xref>]. Other kinases thought to be involved in the IE phase of HCMV infection include adenosine monophosphate-activated protein kinase (AMPK) [
 <xref rid="B173-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">173</xref>], hematopoietic cell kinase (a src family kinase) [
 <xref rid="B174-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">174</xref>], cyclin-dependent kinases (CDKs) [
 <xref rid="B175-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">175</xref>], protein kinase A [
 <xref rid="B176-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">176</xref>] and mitogen and stress activated kinase (MSK) [
 <xref rid="B128-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. The activation of kinase signalling pathways in the initial infection phase comes with multiple, mostly beneficial consequences for the virus including major IE gene activation. For example, ERK mediates induction of major IE gene expression via binding of CREB to the MIEP and recruitment of MSK. In turn, MSK-mediated histone H3 phosphorylation promotes histone demethylation and the subsequent exit of HCMV from latency [
 <xref rid="B128-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. One of the most crucial transcription factors linked to the PI3K/AKT, MAPK and other signalling pathways relevant to HCMV infection is nuclear factor kappa B (NF-κΒ). Canonical NF-κΒ activation requires degradation of inhibitor of NF-κΒ (IκΒ), which depends on phosphorylation by a three-subunit IκΒ kinase (IKK). IKK-mediated phosphorylation of IκΒ is triggered as early as five minutes after exposure of cells to HCMV particles resulting in activation of preformed NF-κΒ [
 <xref rid="B177-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">177</xref>,
 <xref rid="B178-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">178</xref>]. This first phase of the NF-κΒ response to HCMV infection may facilitate IE expression via binding sites in the proximal enhancer of the MIEP (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00110-f001">Figure 1</xref>). However, the requirement of NF-κΒ for efficient IE expression varies widely with cell type, virus strain and other conditions of infection [
 <xref rid="B179-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>,
 <xref rid="B180-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">180</xref>,
 <xref rid="B181-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">181</xref>,
 <xref rid="B182-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">182</xref>]. A second phase of NF-κΒ activation due to initiation of NF-κΒ transcription allows for continued expression throughout infection. While NF-κΒ activation benefits HCMV replication, at least under certain conditions, it also comes with adverse effects for the virus. NF-κΒ, along with IFN regulator factor 3 (IRF3), binds to promoters and stimulates transcription of numerous cytokine and chemokine genes. Some of these genes encode antiviral proteins including type I IFNs. HCMV gene products including tegument proteins (e.g., pUL35, pUL82/pp71, pUL83/pp65) and IE proteins as well as non-coding RNAs target the IFN response and other signalling pathways, adding an additional layer of complexity. Targeting of host cell signalling by HCMV will be discussed below in the context of IE proteins (see 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot4-viruses-12-00110">Section 3.4</xref>), but is otherwise beyond the scope of this review. For a comprehensive and detailed account of this topic, the reader is referred to several other recent reviews [
 <xref rid="B183-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">183</xref>,
 <xref rid="B184-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">184</xref>,
 <xref rid="B185-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">185</xref>].
</p>
