<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To design accurate probes or primers for a given virus, the first step is to get a picture of the genetic variation and structure by gathering as many nucleotide sequences as possible from isolates of that virus and from genetically related viruses. Sequences of specific genomic regions or complete genomes can be determined from purified or cloned PCR products or by HTS from viral samples and retrieved from databases like GenBank (
 <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</uri>). The genetic diversity and structure can be estimated easily with the MEGA X software (
 <xref rid="B129" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al., 2018</xref>), after alignment with the algorithm CLUSTALW (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">Higgins et al., 1994</xref>) implemented in MEGA. Nucleotide diversity is the mean distance (proportion of nucleotide differences) between sequence pairs and can be considered as a measure of the genetic variation within a virus population. In this case, p-distance should be used instead of nucleotide substitution models as this analysis is aimed to know the actual genetic differences for application in diagnostic and not the evolutionary changes that occurred. The genetic structure can be visualized with phylogenetic trees, which can be inferred with different methods, such as Neighbor-Joining, Maximum Likelihood and Maximum Parsimony. As an illustration, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">
  <bold>Figure 2</bold>
 </xref> shows the nucleotide diversity and the phylogenetic relationships of randomly selected worldwide isolates of cucumber green mottle mosaic virus (CGMMV) and grapevine leafroll-associated virus 2 (GLRaV-2). The nucleotide diversity of GLRaV-2 is higher, so it is more challenging to develop an accurate detection method for GLRaV-2 than for CGMMV. Since the viral population of GLRaV-2 is structured in eight groups or clades, at least one isolate per clade should be considered to develop detection and disease control procedures for this virus.
</p>
