<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza‐like illnesses in dogs and cats, apparently acquired from either horses or, less commonly, humans, have been reported for centuries during epidemics and equine epizootics,
 <xref rid="b1" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="b62" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>62</sup>
 </xref> probably representing in most instances occasional “dead‐end” host transmission. Apparent canine influenza was reported, for example, during the 1675–1676, the 1760, and the 1767 epidemics/equine epizootics,
 <xref rid="b1" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="b43" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>43</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="b57" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>57</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="b59" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>59</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="b61" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>61</sup>
 </xref> and substantial outbreaks of possible influenza in dogs were seen during the 1782 pandemic, anecdotally associated with transmission to parrots,
 <xref rid="b75" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>75</sup>
 </xref> and the Australian epidemic of 1851–1852.
 <xref rid="b76" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>76</sup>
 </xref> Similar canine and feline illnesses and deaths were reported frequently in the 1872 equine panzootic as well and have more recently been reported in the 2009 H1N1 pandemic. Influenza cases and deaths in racing greyhounds have been recognized for over a century (
 <italic>The San Francisco Call</italic>, 11 November 1901; 
 <xref rid="f5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>). Equine H3N8 viruses have recently become stably adapted to dogs
 <xref rid="b77" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>77</sup>
 </xref> and are now evolving in dogs by antigenic drift,
 <xref rid="b78" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>78</sup>
 </xref> establishing another extra‐avian IAV reservoir. Different lineages of this virus are now spreading internationally,
 <xref rid="b79" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>79</sup>
 </xref> a situation without recognized precedent in the historical literature. Other species such as large cats, ferrets, minks, seals, and other mammals have also occasionally been infected.
</p>
