<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Compounds that inhibit IE2 function have been identified and offer promise as a potential new class of HCMV inhibitors (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00110-f002">Figure 2</xref>). IE2 has been targeted, as it is an essential multifunctional protein that regulates critical events in HCMV replication including transactivation of early and late genes and auto-regulation of the MIEP. IE2 has also been linked to broad dysregulation of host gene expression affecting cell cycle progression, immunomodulation and pathogenesis (see 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot1-viruses-12-00110">Section 3.1</xref>). The first compound demonstrated to directly inhibit IE2 function was WC5, a 6-aminoquinolone derivative [
 <xref rid="B374-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">374</xref>]. WC5 was tested based on evidence that compounds within this chemical group exhibit antiviral activity against HIV-1 by inhibiting Tat transactivation [
 <xref rid="B375-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">375</xref>,
 <xref rid="B376-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">376</xref>]. WC5 specifically inhibits HCMV but not a selection of other herpesviruses [
 <xref rid="B376-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">376</xref>,
 <xref rid="B377-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">377</xref>]. In addition to IE, early and late gene expression profiles, which suggest inhibition of IE2 function, WC5 has been shown to directly inhibit IE2′s transactivating activity via a cell-based assay in which an EGFP reporter gene was placed under the control of IE2-dependent early gene promoters [
 <xref rid="B374-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">374</xref>]. In these assays, WC5 significantly inhibited IE2-mediated transcriptional activation of early gene promoters UL54 and UL112/113. A minimal region of the UL54 promoter composed of a 150-bp segment upstream of the transcriptional start site has been demonstrated to be sufficient to mediate the inhibitory activity of WC5 [
 <xref rid="B378-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">378</xref>]. Within this 150-bp segment is the IR-1 signal (8-bp inverted repeat element 1), a 
 <italic>cis</italic>-acting sequence with an established role in IE2-dependent transactivation, yet the IR-1 signal has been shown not to be required for WC5′s inhibitory activity [
 <xref rid="B378-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">378</xref>]. In addition, two key protein interactions, IE2 dimerization and its interaction with TBP, known to be involved in IE2-dependent transactivation of viral promoters have also been discounted as WC5′s target [
 <xref rid="B378-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">378</xref>]. Intriguingly, WC5′s activity appears to be specifically confined to the regulation of HCMV promoters, as the compound exhibits no effect on a variety of cellular promoters regulated either by IE2 protein interactions or a direct IE2 interaction with promoter DNA [
 <xref rid="B378-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">378</xref>]. In addition to inhibiting IE2 transactivation of viral promoters, a second mechanism of action by which WC5 inhibits a different IE2 function has been identified [
 <xref rid="B378-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">378</xref>]. WC5 specifically disrupts IE2′s direct interaction with the crs within the MIEP (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00110-f001">Figure 1</xref>). Disruption of the IE2-crs interaction abolishes IE2′s auto-repression of its own promoter, a function essential for viral replication. Although WC5 has been demonstrated to inhibit two IE2 functions, transactivation of viral early and late genes and MIEP auto-regulation, the exact molecular mechanisms require further elucidation.
</p>
