<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">Until now, one YFV serotype and seven genotypes have been described in Africa and South America. In Africa, five genotypes are described, named West Africa I, West Africa II, East Africa, East/Central Africa, and Angola [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. In Africa, there are three transmission cycles: (
 <italic>i</italic>) the sylvatic cycle is reported in the rainforest, involving NHP and sylvatic 
 <italic>Aedes africanus</italic>, (
 <italic>ii</italic>) the intermediate cycle in the forest-savanna ecotone has peridomestic anthropophilic 
 <italic>Aedes spp.</italic> (such as 
 <italic>A. furcifer</italic>, 
 <italic>A. taylori</italic>, 
 <italic>A. luteocephalus</italic>, and 
 <italic>A. simpsoni</italic>) as vectors, and (
 <italic>iii</italic>) the urban cycle has 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Aedes bromeliae</italic> as vectors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. In South America, YFV is endemic in the Amazon Basin (Brazil, Peru, Bolivia, Colombia, Ecuador, Venezuela, French Guiana, Suriname, and Guyana) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] and the sylvatic cycle involves various species of NHP and mosquitoes primarily belonging to the genera 
 <italic>Haemagogus and Sabethes</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. YFV South American I and II genotypes are derived from the West African genotype [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. South American I is the predominant YFV genotype in Brazil, possessing five distinct lineages 1A-1E [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Until the middle of the 1990s, the old lineages (1A, 1B, and 1C) co-circulated in South America but were then replaced by the modern ones, 1D and 1E [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Lineage 1E is responsible for the recent YF outbreaks in Brazil (2016 to 2019), and it was probably originated from YF endemic areas in North Brazil [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Genomic analyses of YFV causing the recent outbreaks revealed unique mutations leading to nine amino acid substitutions in the deduced polyprotein (eight substitutions in highly conserved positions of non-structural proteins 3 and 5, which form the replication complex of YFV). Those amino acid substitutions have not been previously described for YFV, and the impacts of those changes in viral fitness should be investigated [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].
</p>
