<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>Context:</title>
  <p>To systematically evaluate the effects of hepatoprotective agents, when delivered either alone or in combination with other antiviral or non-antiviral drugs in patients with hepatitis B and hepatic fibrosis.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Objectives:</title>
  <p>The current randomized controlled clinical trials aimed to evaluate the efficacy of combinations of antiviral and non-antiviral hepatoprotective agents on indexes of liver function and liver fibrosis in patients with hepatitis B.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Data Sources:</title>
  <p>Published literatures in Chinese and English on hepatoprotective treatment strategies for chronic hepatitis B and liver fibrosis were searched in three databases and randomized controlled clinical trials were selected. </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Study Selection:</title>
  <p>Data were extracted according to a variety of inclusion and exclusion criteria. Meta-analysis was employed to analyze the data.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results:</title>
  <p>A total of 22 randomized controlled trials encompassing 1,714 cases were considered in the meta-analysis. The obtained results indicated that the combination of antiviral drug and hepatoprotective agent was better than antiviral drug alone to improve liver function. Similarly, regarding liver fibrosis, using two different hepatoprotective agents was better than using one agent. The normalization rates of Aminotransferase (ALT) and total Bilirubin (TBil) were improved 25.7% by two hepatoprotective agents compared to the single agent. Acetylcysteine was superior to ursodeoxycholic acid or silibinin to reduce ALT. Ursodeoxycholic acid was superior to acetylcysteine or silibinin to reduce TBIL.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusions:</title>
  <p>Hepatoprotective agents combined with antiviral drugs can significantly improve liver function and liver fibrosis parameters in patients with hepatitis B.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
