<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Essential oils extracted from plants belonging to the 
 <italic>Labiatae</italic> and 
 <italic>Verbenaceae</italic> families have also been shown to have antiviral activity against HSV. Vero cells incubated with HSV and plant-extracted essential oils for 48–72 h significantly reduced HSV-1 and HSV-2 viral titers. Interestingly, their mechanisms of action were found to be related to the pre-infective stages (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Brand et al., 2016</xref>). Another study that also assessed essentials oils, but extracted from 
 <italic>Glechon spathulata</italic> and 
 <italic>Glechon marifolia</italic> identified antiviral activity against HSV-1, which was effective after the infection of Vero cells (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) (
 <xref rid="B193" ref-type="bibr">Venturi et al., 2015</xref>). Eucalyptus essential oils are used to treat symptoms during cough and bronchitis, in numerous presentations, such as ointments, liniments, in oral form and in vapor baths as inhalants (
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">Kaur et al., 2013</xref>). The main components of the essential oils from the Eucalyptus species are cineole and alpha-pinene (
 <xref rid="B168" ref-type="bibr">Sebei et al., 2015</xref>). One study evaluated the Australian tea tree oil and Eucalyptus oil over HSV and reported antiviral activity against both, HSV-1 and HSV-2. Treatments before, during or post-infection determined that these compounds had virucidal activity affecting the virus before or during adsorption, before the virus had entered the cells (
 <xref rid="B166" ref-type="bibr">Schnitzler et al., 2001</xref>). Ethanolic extracts from the leaves of 
 <italic>E. camaldulensis</italic> were shown to inhibit HSV-1 and HSV-2 infection when the extracts were added to Vero cells during- and post-infection. Additionally, in this study a synergistic effect between acyclovir and the ethanolic extracts was reported in cell cultures (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Abu-Jafar and Mahmoud, 2017</xref>). In another study, researchers reported 24 new metabolites in the leaves of 
 <italic>E. sideroxylon</italic> and four new metabolites within the genus 
 <italic>Eucalyptus</italic> that have antiviral activity using an ultra-performance liquid chromatography coupled to photodiode-array and electrospray ionization mass spectrometer (UPLC/PDA/ESI-qTOF-MS). Within the antiviral activities detected, there were compounds that also inhibited hepatitis A, coxsackie and adenoviruses, besides HSV-1 and HSV-2. Interestingly, the highest antiviral activity was observed against HSV-2, with the antiviral effect acting pre-treatment (virucidal), thus inhibiting virus entry and subsequent infection processes, while the antiviral effect against HSV-1 was only observed when the extract was incubated with the virus previous to the cell infection (
 <xref rid="B137" ref-type="bibr">Okba et al., 2017</xref>). In addition, twelve compounds isolated from the leaves and twigs of 
 <italic>E. globulus</italic> were found to have antiviral activity against HSV-1 and HSV-2. In this study, Tereticornate A was identified to have the greatest activity against HSV-1, which was higher than acyclovir. Cypellocarpin C displayed the strongest antiviral activity against HSV-2, greater than that observed for acyclovir (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Brezáni et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
