<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Natural or experimental PPRV infection has now been shown to induce clinical disease affecting camels (Khalafalla et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Kwiatek et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Zakian et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0068" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) and unusual hosts such as pigs (Nawathe and Taylor 
 <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">1979</xref>; Schulz et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Subsequent to the occurrence of likely spill-over events, such evidence indicates the potential of the virus to affect a wide range of hosts, particularly in disease-endemic regions. Such spill-over events are most likely to occur as a result of interactions between PPRV-infected small ruminants and other susceptible hosts during epidemic or endemic conditions and may act as a foundation for further inter-species transmission, particularly in livestock-dense endemic regions. PPRV has previously been reported in other species, such as populations of several species of wild mountain goat (genus 
 <italic>Capra</italic>), and is most likely due to spill-over from domestic small ruminants (Abubakar et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Thus, the viral-host jumps are not uncommon for PPRV and associated with provoking hurdles in disease eradication worldwide. Similar findings of viral transmissions have previously been reported from infected sheep and goats to wild ungulates in Saudi Arabia (Frölich et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). Recently, PPRV has been reported from the four-horned antelope (
 <italic>Tetracerus quadricornis</italic>), an endangered bovid species of India. During the outbreak, 20 animals died and this was attributed to PPRV lineage IV (Jaisree et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Further investigations are needed to ascertain the status of PPRV among endangered animals like the four-horned antelope or Chowsingha. In these scenarios, direct or indirect contact with infected domestic small ruminants may transmit the virus to other hosts. Together this evidence further substantiates the assumption that, while living in close proximity to each other, particularly in a developing country setting, there are several chances for cross-species transmission, either from small ruminants to large ruminants or to unusual hosts (Lembo et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Mahapatra et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Schulz et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). With reference to the genetic makeup, the viral strains responsible for infection, in both small and large ruminants, exhibit a marked genetic relatedness (Rahman et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Despite these facts, the potential transmission of PPRV, and factors involved in disease epidemiology among domestic small and large ruminants and unusual host populations in disease-endemic regions, are largely unknown.
</p>
