<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Strains of EV-A71 are frequently characterized into genogroups based on the sequence of the VP1, which represents the major epitope determinant and binding properties of the viral particles [
 <xref rid="B72-ijms-20-05201" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Currently, there are six genogroups from A to F [
 <xref rid="B73-ijms-20-05201" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], and genogroups B and C are further subdivided into B0 to B5 and C1 to C5, respectively (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-20-05201-f004">Figure 4</xref>). The genogroup A contains the prototype EV-A71, and genogroups D, E and F contain a single strain each. The high strain diversity in EV-A71 is attributed to a high evolutionary rate, ca. 4 × 10
 <sup>−3</sup> substitutions per site per year estimated on the VP1 [
 <xref rid="B74-ijms-20-05201" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]; such a high mutation rate is due to the lack of a proofread mechanism in the viral RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp) with overall mutation rates of 10
 <sup>−3</sup> to 10
 <sup>−5</sup> mutations per copied nucleotide per replication cycle [
 <xref rid="B75-ijms-20-05201" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Additionally, despite recombination events in the capsid-encoding region are considered infrequent due to structural and functional constraints, the effects of recombination in EV-A71 are considered source of diversity among strains and genogroups [
 <xref rid="B73-ijms-20-05201" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="B76-ijms-20-05201" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>,
 <xref rid="B77-ijms-20-05201" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. The VP1 divergence and the evolutionary forces modeling a growing diversity of EV-A71 are important factors to consider in the development and deployment of vaccines [
 <xref rid="B75-ijms-20-05201" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] It is noteworthy that the capsid region exhibits low recombination rates, while the 5′UTR-VP4 junction and P2 have been shown to represent recombination boundary hotspots [
 <xref rid="B77-ijms-20-05201" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>].
</p>
