<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Generally, the FGD participants presented little knowledge on the sexual transmission route of Zika and the use of condoms to prevent Zika transmission, despite the evidence of viral presence in semen and vaginal secretions and the ability to sexually transmit the virus [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006708.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006708.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006708.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. That said, there was one participant that stated that she was avoiding unprotected sex during pregnancy for this reason. In contrast, a qualitative study in Brazil found that women were adapting their family planning due to the Zika outbreak, as encouraged by health services [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006708.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. This change in family planning practice may well be due to the first-hand experiences participants in Brazil had with the neurological effects of the Zika virus. Using condoms during sex, however, is easier said than done: respondents acknowledged available condom resources, but commented that their partners (and men in general) did not like using condoms and needed to be persuaded. Similarly, in another qualitative study about Zika and reproductive decision-making in Iquitos found couples associate condoms with risk, and are not used within committed relationships [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006708.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The woman’s responsibility for preventing sexual transmission of Zika and men’s aversion to using condoms was also mentioned in a qualitative study in Brazil examining the effect of the Zika virus on family planning practices [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006708.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Moreover, in previous studies regarding sexual health in Iquitos, researchers described liberal social norms for sex and marriage [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006708.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], but insufficient sexual education in secondary schools [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006708.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. One programmatic implication from these findings would be to increase the understanding of the importance of condom use and its role in preventing Zika transmission via sex, at least during an outbreak. Moreover, promoting condom education could have other benefits, including reducing transmission of sexually transmitted infections and preventing unwanted pregnancies—but both men and women need to see this value. Condom use would serve various purposes, since most participants commented that they did not want any more pregnancies.
</p>
