<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Future health education programs within this region could focus on addressing the fatalism expressed regarding the acquisition of Zika. Other studies which have examined feelings of fatalism suggested that future research and interventions should focus on agency and self-efficacy within specific cultural contexts if they are to address how feelings of fatalism affect care-seeking behaviors [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006708.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006708.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Another way of empowering communities is through participation in health campaigns. One example would be through peer education, in which people are not objects or recipients of educational projects, but participants in this process, who are able to identify their problems and solutions [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006708.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006708.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]; for example, involving volunteer community members in health promotion initiatives and clean up activities. Our findings suggest that women in these communities are receptive to health education and have expressed a desire to acquire more information regarding Zika. Anecdotally, following completion of the groups many women asked if there would be more FGDs in the future, and were enthusiastic to participate, share their knowledge, and learn more. Research in the Iquitos community has found that people are willing to spend time and money—albeit limited—on controlling vectors to prevent diseases: people report sprinkling and/or mopping petroleum or creoline daily on their floors to try to keep mosquitoes away [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006708.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. That said, the main preventive practice for Zika is vector control, and beyond large scale fumigation and larviciding done by the regional health authorities, community members are limited to controlling breeding sites in a rainforest—and for many, this may seem like a futile task—since personal insect repellents and household insecticide sprays are too expensive for most.
</p>
