<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In our study, small epidemics remained largely unnoticed in certain syndrome TS, especially when the mean baseline count, and the background noise were high (e.g., syndrome TS extracted from AMD). Adjusting the alarm threshold is a strategy for increasing sensitivity, but it increases the number of false alarms. Increasing the number of false alarms is a problem when monitoring several syndrome TS at the same time, as surveillance systems monitoring multiple syndromic TS have been reported to intrinsically suffer from a lack of specificity (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). An alternative approach to improve detection performance is to split large syndrome TS into smaller sub-TS or, in other words, to change the level of TS clustering. If syndrome TS are sufficiently large, splitting them into sub-TS can reduce the background noise in the sub-TS. This will increase the ratio of “epidemic cases” to “baseline cases,” and potentially improve detection performance. But only if the epidemic cases are not expected to be split among the sub-TS. For example, when geographical information is available, hierarchical time series approaches (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) or other spatiotemporal methods [see for example (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>)] could be used to improve detection performance as epidemics of transmissible diseases are supposed to start in a localized geographical area. When the epidemic is expected to be split among the sub-TS (e.g., when splitting a syndrome TS according to the production type and when all production types are susceptible to the disease), the benefit of splitting the data may be reduced. Splitting the data into different sub-TS should be carefully discussed as the benefit in terms of improved detection performance may not always offset the extra effort needed to properly monitor additional TS. Monitoring syndrome TS with low counts also has disadvantages. There is an increased risk of producing excessive numbers of false positive alarms (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>), especially when the mean count per time unit is ≤ 5 (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>).
</p>
