<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0035">As a nucleoside analog, remdesivir acts as an RdRp inhibitor, targeting the viral genome replication process. The RdRp is the protein complex CoVs use to replicate their RNA-based genomes. After the host metabolizes remdesivir into active NTP, the metabolite competes with adenosine triphosphate (ATP; the natural nucleotide normally used in this process) for incorporation into the nascent RNA strand [
 <xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The incorporation of this substitute into the new strand results in premature termination of RNA synthesis, halting the growth of the RNA strand after a few more nucleotides are added. Although CoVs have a proofreading process that is able to detect and remove other nucleoside analogs, rendering them resistant to many of these drugs, remdesivir seems to outpace this viral proofreading activity, thus maintaining antiviral activity [
 <xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Unsurprisingly, Agostini et al. reported that a mutant murine hepatitis virus (MHV) devoid of proofreading ability was more sensitive to remdesivir [
 <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The opposite is also possible—that mutations that improve proofreading or otherwise increase fidelity of the base-pairing process may result in remdesivir resistance [
 <xref rid="bb0165" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In fact, Agostini et al. also induced mutations in MHV (through passage in remdesivir) that conferred strong resistance against the drug, but these mutated strains were outcompeted by wild-type MHV in coinfected cell cultures that were not exposed to remdesivir [
 <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. How well this experiment would represent a situation in which a resistance mutation developed naturally, though, is unclear. Nonetheless, some evidence suggests that remdesivir could have an additional mechanism of action that has yet to be discovered, which, if true, may allow for partial antiviral activity to continue despite viral mutations that enhance replication fidelity [
 <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>].
</p>
