<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>When considering the wind speed, negative correlations were observed between all three entomological indices of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> and current month average wind speed and these correlations were significant in Akbar Town study area. The negative correlations may be explained by the difficulties in finding breeding places as well as hosts for dengue vector mosquitoes due to suppressing of mosquito flights at higher wind speed. However, non-significant positive correlation was observed in HI and BI of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> with current month wind speed in Akbar Town and 3
 <sup>rd</sup> Kurana study area. The reason may be attributed to the indoor resting of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> mosquitoes. Since the 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> mosquitoes are resting indoors, they can find a host easily for their blood feedings. Further, the 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> mosquitoes are reluctant to fly long distances and they prefer artificial breeding containers close to their resting household. In the entomological survey, many potential artificial breeding places were identified and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> mosquitoes can find better breeding container with the aid of wind speed. Meantime, positive correlations were observed between HI and BI of both the species with two months previous average wind speed and it was significant in 3
 <sup>rd</sup> Kurana study area for both the species and Eriyawetiya study area for 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic>. These positive correlations may be explained by migration of dengue vector mosquitoes by air waves and wind. Even though the movements of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> was greatly affected by human activities, previous studies have mentioned that the wind currents may also advances the movements of large populations of mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="pone.0231408.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. These positive correlations at lag 2 and 3 months of wind speed suggested that the possibility of movement of dengue vector mosquitoes from another area to study areas and emphasized areas of attention that has to be paid intensively during future vector control programmes [
 <xref rid="pone.0231408.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].
</p>
