<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0035">Factors that contribute to the inflammatory and immune response include the nitric oxide/reactive oxygen species (NO/ROS) ratio, the activation of M1 macrophages and red blood cell (RBC) damage. A normal NO/ROS balance is crucial for normal vascular function. NO is an endothelium-derived relaxing factor that plays key roles in vascular signaling, regulation of blood flow and host defense [
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. ROS, such as superoxide, also serve as host defense and are induced during stress, such as viral infection [
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. An excess of ROS, such as in viral overload, activates M1 macrophages, recruits neutrophils and enhances production of peroxynitrite in conjunction with NO in a potent response to the invading virus, with the collateral damage of endothelial dysfunction, permeable vessels and lipid membrane peroxidation [
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. M1 macrophages produce a large amount of highly reactive nitrogen- and oxygen-derived molecular species and proinflammatory cytokines, such as interleukin (IL)-2, IL-6, IL-8, interferon (IFN)-α/β and tumor necrosis factor (TNF)- α, that neutralize invading organisms but also compound the vascular damage [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Furthermore, inflammation-induced platelet activation, which can be lessened by NO, can lead to increased coagulation, an important reported consequence of the disease [
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Lippi and Mattiuzzi recently reported evidence of SARS-CoV-2 disrupting hemoglobin in RBCs [
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], likely triggering significant oxidative stress. Subsequent hemolysis can result in anemia, but more importantly it can exacerbate the inflammatory process. Cell-free hemoglobin scavenges modulators of coagulation, such as endothelial NO, while released proinflammatory heme and iron can activate platelets [
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Enhanced clotting and sluggish blood flow result in systemic hypoxia in oxygen-sensitive organs such as the kidneys [
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Repolarization of the M1 population back to M2, promoted by NO, stops the proinflammatory insult to the tissues and initiates repair processes and clearance of debris. Unchecked M1 macrophage response creates an inflammatory cascade and cytokine storm that result in a buildup of cellular debris and edema due to the leaky vasculature, presenting in the lungs as ARDS [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].
</p>
