<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0040">Additional processes that enhance the progression toward an inflammatory cascade include the renin angiotensin system (RAS) and reoxygenation/reperfusion. Observations that SARS-CoV-2 uses ACE2 as the receptor binding domain for its spike (S) protein, with higher affinity than measured with SARS-CoV-1, have led to postulations about the role of the RAS in the novel virus's pathophysiology [
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>]. The genes for viral entry and for ACE2 expression are highly enriched in nasal epithelium, implying a significant role for ACE2 in infectivity and the course of infection [
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. ACE and ACE2 serve opposing physiological functions. After ACE cleaves angiotensin (AT) I to angiotensin II, ATII binds its receptor to constrict blood vessels. ACE2 inactivates ATII and generates angiotensin 1-7 and promotes endothelial production of NO, both potent vasodilators and inhibitors of ACE [
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Conversely, ACE inhibits NO production, promoting ROS and inflammation. The binding of SARS-CoV-2's spike protein to ACE2 likely downregulates it and contributes to unchecked downstream effects of ACE, including increased vascular permeability and decreased anti-inflammatory mediators such as NO. This mechanism of dysregulation of the NO/ROS balance has been detailed with SARS-CoV-1 and translates to a potential area for intervention in the current pandemic [
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Hypoxia/Reoxygenation (H/R) and ischemia/reperfusion (I/R) both initiate the proinflammatory cycle through ROS- and heparinase-mediated degradation of the glycocalyx and endothelial lining [
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>]. In the setting of blood flow stagnation and microvascular emboli, ventilation and rapid restoration of blood flow to sites that were hypoxic and ischemic may contribute to pathogenesis of ARDS. Anti-inflammatory molecules such as 
 <italic>N-</italic>acetylcysteine can potentially attenuate cellular damage by ROS [
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], and restoring NO/ROS balance may reduce cellular damage by reoxygenation and reperfusion.
</p>
