<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para2640">The National Programme for Hepatitis Prevention and Control was launched in 2005, after which provincial implementation units were also set up.
 <xref rid="bib272" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>272</sup>
 </xref> The Programme focused on screening and treatment for HCV infection and did not establish laboratory-based viral hepatitis surveillance. At the time, hepatitis surveillance in Pakistan was syndromic, not providing laboratory confirmation of infection or information on the type of virus, and not collecting information on risk factors. In 2009, to monitor the effectiveness of the Programme's activities and guide the implementation of evidence-based preventative interventions, the Pakistan Field Epidemiology and Laboratory Training Programme (under the akistani Centres for Disease Control and Prevention and the Ministry of Health) launched a hepatitis sentinel-site surveillance system (
 <xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">appendix p 3</xref>). The sites were located in five public tertiary care hospitals in four provincial headquarters (Lahore, Peshawar, Karachi, and Quetta) and in Islamabad. To engage Sindh province to implement strategies, the United States Agency for International Development further supported the Pakistani Centres for Disease Control and Prevention toward expansion of the surveillance sites.
 <xref rid="bib273" ref-type="bibr">273</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib274" ref-type="bibr">274</xref> A National Hepatitis Strategic Framework for viral hepatitis (2017–21)
 <xref rid="bib274" ref-type="bibr">274</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib275" ref-type="bibr">275</xref> has been launched to eliminate viral hepatitis C by 2030, reduce hepatitis B and C by 10% reduction by 2021, and reduce new cases of hepatitis B, C, and D by 30% by 2021. So far, the measures implemented by the Government of Pakistan include HBV vaccination for children and adults and providing antiviral therapy for patients with HBV and HCV through various programmes and public awareness campaigns. The national essential medicines list, subsidised by the government, includes antiviral therapy for HBV (interferon alpha, pegylated interferon, entecavir, tenofovir, and lamuvidine) and HCV (interferon alpha, pegylated interferon, ribavirin, sofosbuvir, daclatasvir, and velpatsavir).
</p>
