<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para2780">Encouraging weight loss is a central aim of Healthy Japan 21, a series of 10-year public-health goals devised at the start of the millennium (
 <xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">table 5</xref>).
 <xref rid="bib297" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>297</sup>
 </xref> This reduction of overweight is to be achieved through public education campaigns on healthy eating and increased physical activity.
 <xref rid="bib298" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>298</sup>
 </xref> Japan's school lunches programme has helped to slow the rise of child obesity in Japan. Lunches tend to be planned by a nutritionist, include locally grown and fresh ingredients, and tend to be dominated by rice, vegetables, soups, and fish. Childhood obesity has increased in Japan since the 1970s, but that increase has happened more slowly than in other economically developed countries. The Government has established healthy waistline thresholds for adults aged 40–74 years with the metabo law, which came into effect in 2008, and these are measured at annual checkups.
 <xref rid="bib298" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>298</sup>
 </xref> The threshold for men is 33·5 inches or less and women, it is 35·4 inches. People who exceed those norms are required to attend counselling and support sessions. Companies are required to measure the waistlines of at least 80% of their employees along with their families, and of retired employees. Furthermore, at the time of introduction, companies were required to help 10% of those who were above the thresholds to lose weight by 2012, and 25% by 2015. Companies and local governments that failed to meet specific targets were liable for financial penalties, potentially as high as $19 million.
 <xref rid="bib298" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>298</sup>
 </xref> The targets have not been updated, but companies are now required to increase their contributions to their welfare fund by 10% if they do not perform well. Men and women who exceed the waistline measurement threshold during their annual medical examinations are enrolled in diet programmes, fitness classes, or are asked to see a doctor. The long-term effectiveness of this controversial stringent approach are yet to be clarified.
 <xref rid="bib299" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>299</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
