<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para2860">In Australia, a universal hepatitis B vaccination programme for all infants was introduced in 2000.
 <xref rid="bib306" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>306</sup>
 </xref> It was preceded by various programmes implemented in the late 1980s that targeted individuals at increased risk of HBV infection. Catch-up vaccination programmes against hepatitis B for adolescents have been implemented at different times, settings, and jurisdictions since 1997.
 <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>71</sup>
 </xref> However, health inequity between Indigenous and non-Indigenous Australians regarding HBV infection is still substantial. Vaccination coverage of Indigenous Australian adults needs to be increased through a state-funded vaccination catch-up programme. In 2017, an estimated 149 746 people living with chronic hepatitis B in Australia had been diagnosed, representing 68% of the total estimated population living with chronic hepatitis B and a modest increase from the 63% estimate in 2011.
 <xref rid="bib307" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>307</sup>
 </xref> The first National Hepatitis B Strategy 2010–13
 <xref rid="bib308" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>308</sup>
 </xref> sought to reduce disease transmission and the morbidity and mortality associated with hepatitis B. Furthermore, the introduction of highly effective HBV antiviral therapy in Australia with entecavir in 2005 and tenofovir in 2007 was accompanied by considerable increases in treatment uptake. During 2017, 19 358 people were administered drugs for hepatitis B, representing 8·7% of those estimated to be living with chronic hepatitis B. Modeled trends between 2011 and 2017 show an ongoing modest increase (average 0·93% per year) in this proportion.
 <xref rid="bib307" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>307</sup>
 </xref> At the population-level, only a few people with chronic HBV infections (possibly 10–15%) would be recommended for treatment on the basis of national and international consensus guidelines.
 <xref rid="bib309" ref-type="bibr">309</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib310" ref-type="bibr">310</xref> These vaccination efforts are collectively reflected in the fact that Australia was recognised by WHO as meeting the regional control target of hepatitis B, which is a prevalence of less than 1% in children younger than 5 years.
 <xref rid="bib311" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>311</sup>
 </xref> Australia implemented its Third National Hepatitis B Strategy for 2018–22 to achieve and maintain 95% vaccination coverage against hepatitis B in infants, increase the proportion of diagnosed people with chronic hepatitis B infection to 80%, increase the proportion of those receiving care to 50% and those receiving antiviral treatment to 20%, and reduce mortality related to chronic hepatitis B by 30%.
 <xref rid="bib312" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>312</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
