<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para2940">A Childhood Obesity Plan was launched in New Zealand in October, 2015, with three focus areas comprising 22 initiatives (
 <xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">table 5</xref>).
 <xref rid="bib326" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>326</sup>
 </xref> These initiatives either expanded on already existing recommendations or were new, such as targeted interventions for obese individuals, increased support for people at risk of becoming obese, and broad approaches to make healthier choices easier for all New Zealanders. The focus of the plan is on food, the environment, and physical activity at each life stage, starting from pregnancy. The plan brings together initiatives across government agencies, the private sector, communities, schools, families, and 
 <italic>whānau</italic> (Māori for extended family or community co-inhabiting an area as an economic unit). There have been many initiatives that encourage healthy eating, physical activity, and adequate sleep, such as Eating and Activity Guidelines for New Zealand Adults,
 <xref rid="bib327" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>327</sup>
 </xref> Physical Activity guidelines,
 <xref rid="bib328" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>328</sup>
 </xref> Clinical Guidelines for Weight Management for Adults,
 <xref rid="bib329" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>329</sup>
 </xref> Clinical Guidelines for Weight Management for Children and Young People,
 <xref rid="bib330" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>330</sup>
 </xref> Fruit in Schools,
 <xref rid="bib331" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>331</sup>
 </xref> Green Prescriptions,
 <xref rid="bib332" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>332</sup>
 </xref> and Active Families.
 <xref rid="bib333" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>333</sup>
 </xref> The Fruit in Schools programme provides a piece of fruit each day to children from communities with low socioeconomic status. The Green Prescriptions initiative provides individual support for increased physical activity after a referral from a general practitioner or a practice. The Active Families initiative comprises community-based health initiatives designed to increase physical activity and improve nutrition in children and young people aged 5–18 years and in their 
 <italic>whānau</italic>.
 <xref rid="bib325" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>325</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
