<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>RVFV is single-stranded segmented RNA belongs to the genus Phlebovirus, family Phenuiviridae of order Bunyavirales. The family Phenuiviridae includes 4 genera: Phlebovirus, Goukovirus, Phasivirus, and Tenuivirus [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The RVF virus is enveloped with ribonucleocapside core, is spherical or pleomorphic in shape, 80–120 nm in diameter with surface glycoprotein projections of 5–10 nm, and embedded in a lipid bilayer envelope [
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The RVF virus contains a thick linear viral ribonucleocapsid of 2–2.5 nm in diameter, 200–300 nm in length and displays helical symmetry [
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The RVF virus genome contains a single strand tripartite with L, M and S-segments [
 <xref rid="B3-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] as previously shown in Ikegami and Makino [
 <xref rid="B4-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00139-f001">Figure 1</xref>); The large segment (L-segment) of RVFV has a single open reading frame (ORF) in the viral complementary sense coding region for L-protein (viral polymerase) [
 <xref rid="B5-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The M-segment encodes two envelope glycoproteins, Gn and Gc, and two uncharacterized polypeptides (one expressed by himself (NSm1), and the other one in combination with Gn (NSm2)) [
 <xref rid="B3-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The S-segment of RVFV has a unique ambisense coding strategy [
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. It contains two ORF; one encodes the nucleoprotein in the 3’ half of viral complementary sense molecule and the other encodes non-structural 
 <italic>NSs</italic> protein in the 5’ half of viral sense RNA. The two ORFs are responsible for evading the host immune system, and they are separated by a short C-rich intergenic region. [
 <xref rid="B7-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].
</p>
