<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <title>Abstract</title>
 <p>Viral hepatitis is caused by different etiological agents with distinct epidemiological, clinical, and laboratory characteristics accounting for significant worldwide morbidity and mortality. Since 1996, the Brazilian Department of Sexually Transmitted Infections (STIs), Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS) and Viral Hepatitis (DIAHV) in collaboration with the Ministry of Defense has been conducting periodic serosurveys of conscripts enlisted for the Brazilian army to assess STI prevalence and obtain data on knowledge and risk factors pertaining to STIs. This article aims to present the hepatitis B (hepatitis B surface antigen - HBsAg) and C (anti-HCV) seroprevalence estimates and risk factors as per the 8th edition of the Conscript Survey performed in 2016.</p>
 <p>This cross-sectional study was conducted among conscripts across Brazil aged 17 to 22 years from August to December 2016. It included a self-reported questionnaire and blood testing for syphilis, human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), and hepatitis B and C.</p>
 <p>In total 38,247 conscripts were enrolled; after applying exclusion criteria, 37,282 conscripts were included. The estimated HBsAg and anti-HCV prevalence rates were 0.22% and 0.28%, respectively. Higher HBsAg and anti-HCV prevalence rates were observed in the North Region (0.49%) and in the Central-west Region (0.65%), respectively. Regarding hepatitis B vaccination, 23.5% (
  <italic>n</italic> = 8412) of the individuals reported being unvaccinated and 47.4% (
  <italic>n</italic> = 16,970) did not know if they had been vaccinated. Among the anti-HCV positive conscripts, 53% (
  <italic>n</italic> = 51, 0.56%, 
  <italic>P</italic> = .049) reported that they had never had sexual intercourse. Regarding self-reported STI status, most of the positive anti-HCV (
  <italic>n</italic> = 100, 0.29%, 
  <italic>P</italic> &lt; .01) and positive HBsAg (
  <italic>n</italic> = 76, 0.22%, 
  <italic>P</italic> = .205) conscripts reported not having a STI. From those who tested positive for HBsAg, 89% (
  <italic>n</italic> = 42, 0.28%, 
  <italic>P</italic> = .005) reported not making consistent use of condoms with steady partners.
 </p>
 <p>Our data suggest a low prevalence of hepatitis B virus (HBV) and hepatitis C virus (HCV) infections among Brazilian young men, and relatively low rates of self-reported HBV immunization. History of STIs, higher number of partners, inconsistent use of condoms, and lack of awareness of routes of transmission were significantly associated with HBV and HCV infections. To achieve the World Health Organization's goal of viral hepatitis elimination, access to hepatitis information, testing, and surveillance need to be improved.</p>
</abstract>
