<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0095">Pneumonia appears to be the most frequent manifestation of SARS-CoV-2 infection, characterized primarily by fever, cough, dyspnea, and bilateral infiltrates on chest imaging (
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Khan et al., 2020a</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. (2020c)</xref>, observed fever (88.5%), cough (68.6%), myalgia or fatigue (35.8%), expectoration (28.2%), and dyspnea (21.9%) as the main clinical manifestations in COVID-19 patients (n = 1994). They also reported less common symptoms including headache or dizziness (12.1%), diarrhea (4.8%), and nausea or vomiting (3.9%). Furthermore, laboratory tests indicated the presence of lymphocytopenia (64.5%) and an elevation in CRP (44.3%), LDH (28.3%), and leukocytopenia (29.4%). In the same study, 
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. (2020d)</xref>, found that lymphocytopenia, eosinophil cytopenia, and leukopenia were observed in 10 COVID-19 patients. In another study on 29 COVID-19 patients, 
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Meng et al. (2020)</xref> observed decreased white blood cell count (79.3%), decreased lymphocyte count (68.9%), increased levels of hs-CRP (93.1%), and normal level of procalcitonin. Similarly, serum LDH was found increased (68.9%) while albumin was decreased (51.7%) in this study. Overall, these indications suggest that LDH and High-sensitivity C-reactive Protein (
 <italic>α</italic>-HBDH) could be reliable biomarkers for investigating COVID-19. Moreover, by investigating 140 COVID-19 patients, 
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al. (2020b)</xref>, reported eosinopenia and lymphopenia as potential diagnostic factors for the disease while asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) are unlikely to be the risk factors. Older age and underlying health conditions including cardiovascular problems, hypertension, diabetes, and pulmonary aberrations were found to be associated with the development of severe symptoms in COVID-19 infected patients.
</p>
