<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Effective antiviral-COVID-19 candidates are essential for reducing disease severity, viral load and transmission, thus helping to prevent the coronavirus outbreaks. There are several drugs against SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV tested in animals, and infected viral cell in lab and proteins vaccines (Graham et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). These investigations are in progress but it requires months to years to develop the vaccines for COVID-19. So far, the infected virus patient’s population is growing rapidly. The organized effort of the computational community is becoming very essential to infer about the structural characteristics of the virion with and without the interaction of drug molecules that may help to experimental/clinical scientist identify effective inhibitor using in vitro studies. Both the computational and experimental outcomes in terms of novel drugs should be recommended a new drug to test in vivo experiments that may be suitable for the disease patient. Following fundamental knowledge of research is required by using computer simulations 1. To elucidate the role of E-protein ion channel activity in virus pathogenesis by study the E-protein ion conductivity with the manipulation of COVID-19 genome. 2. To identify inhibitor block the E-protein ion channel activity as well as inhibits COVID-19 RNA polymerase. 3. To study the energetic binding affinity of COVID-19 M
 <sup>pro</sup> with each inhibitor of ritonavir, lopinavir, Azithromycin, hydroxychloroquine, N3, ribavirin and new inhibitors based on free energy calculations. 4. To investigate the structural properties, flexibility, conformational changes of the COVID-19 M
 <sup>pro</sup>, and study interaction pattern between virus and membrane, virus and inhibitor. 5. To monitor the thermodynamics (virus-water interaction) properties of COVID-19 M
 <sup>pro</sup> in the presence/absence of the antiviral inhibitor. 6. To develop an effective drug targeting to inhibit the contacts between N-protein and single positive RNA strand in order to stop viral replication and transcription. 7. To characterize mechanical profile and energetic affinities between Spike (S) protein and angiotensin converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) in order to device novel targeted molecular treatment which can aid vaccine developments.
</p>
