<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to antiviral therapy, a new treatment strategy having a significant impact on clinical outcomes is utmost required. Immunomodulatory therapy to downregulate the cytokine storm may provide great benefit to the treatment of COVID-19. Recently, researchers focused on targeting specific molecular markers involved in inflammatory cytokines-receptors interactions, their correlation in health and disease and drugs in use that can activate or block their actions. A higher concentration of cytokines has been found in the plasma from COVID-19 patients in ICU compared with the ones from non-ICU COVID-19 patients, suggesting that the cytokine storm could be linked to the severity of the disease [
 <xref rid="B113-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. Corticosteroids are among the most commonly used drugs for immunomodulatory therapy of infectious diseases. However, the use of corticosteroids in the treatment of COVID-19 can cause host immune suppression and delay of viral clearance. A recent study on 201 patients with ARDS showed that treatment with methylprednisolone decreased the risk of death (hazard ratio 0.38, 95% confidence interval 0.20–0.72). These findings indicate that using corticosteroids does not influence viral clearance time, length of hospital stays or duration of symptoms in patients with mild COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="B181-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">181</xref>]. Thus, the use of corticosteroids is considered beneficial in severe cases of COVID-19 (especially in patients with ARDS), but not in mild cases. Accordingly, a recent retrospective study showed the potential benefits from low-dose corticosteroids treatment in a subset of critically SARS-CoV-2 patients [
 <xref rid="B182-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">182</xref>]; these data are in contrast with NHC guidelines that highlight that systematic use of corticosteroids is not recommended for these cases, due to their immunosuppressive effects. However, administration of corticosteroids has been indicated for specific reasons such as exacerbation of asthma or chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), septic shock or severe acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS). Further studies are required to find out how and when it is appropriate the use of corticosteroids for COVID-19, as there are no available data on the benefits of corticosteroid treatment in SARS-CoV or MERS infection [
 <xref rid="B183-ijerph-17-05648" ref-type="bibr">183</xref>].
</p>
