<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Trees were simulated using MASTER (version 5.0.2 [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005868.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]) under a susceptible-infected-removed (SIR) model of an epidemic, as described in previous work [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005868.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In brief, transmissions occur between infected (
 <italic>I</italic>) and susceptible individuals (
 <italic>S</italic>) at a rate 
 <italic>βSI</italic>. Individuals are removed from 
 <italic>I</italic> due to mortality at a rate 
 <italic>μ</italic> or by becoming sampled at a rate 
 <italic>ψ</italic>. The population is structured into two subpopulations with constant migration between like compartments (
 <italic>S</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> ↔ 
 <italic>S</italic>
 <sub>1</sub>, 
 <italic>I</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> ↔ 
 <italic>I</italic>
 <sub>1</sub>) at a rate 
 <italic>m</italic>. The two subpopulations comprised 
 <italic>S</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> + 
 <italic>I</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> = 9000 and 
 <italic>S</italic>
 <sub>1</sub> + 
 <italic>I</italic>
 <sub>1</sub> = 1000 individuals, respectively. Each epidemic was seeded by a single infected individual in the majority subpopulation (
 <italic>I</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> = 1 at time 0). We simulated 100 replicate trees under three different scenarios where rates of transmission (
 <italic>β</italic>
 <sub>1</sub>) and sampling (
 <italic>ψ</italic>
 <sub>1</sub>) were varied in the minority subpopulation as follows: (1) a faster sampling rate (
 <italic>ψ</italic>
 <sub>1</sub> &gt; 
 <italic>ψ</italic>
 <sub>0</sub>); (2) a faster transmission rate (
 <italic>β</italic>
 <sub>1</sub> &gt; 
 <italic>β</italic>
 <sub>0</sub>); or (3) both faster sampling and transmission rates relative to the majority subpopulation. Hence, our model contained two sets of rate classes for each subpopulation. The underlying assumption is that samples from the minority subpopulation should be assigned to clusters. Infected individuals were removed due to mortality at a constant rate 
 <italic>μ</italic>. The end condition for each simulation was for the tree to reach 1000 terminal branches (tips), which were subsequently filtered for tips corresponding to sampled individuals. As a result, the final number of tips was stochastic and slightly less than 1000. The simulation outputs were serialized to files in the Newick tree specification format and parsed using regular expressions in a Python script to transfer node attributes from comment strings to node labels.
</p>
