<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is well established that birds infected with avian influenza are infectious for approximately a week (range 6–10 days), during which they continuously shed vast concentrations of viral particles in their feces 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000346-Webster1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000346-Stallknecht1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000346-Brown1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. These virions are then ingested by susceptible birds, completing the fecal/oral transmission route 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000346-Stallknecht2" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000346-Hinshaw1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. However, attempts to recover the patterns of periodicity and persistence in avian influenza epidemics in waterfowl from simple modeling principles using only this essentially direct transmission mechanism are unsuccessful (see, for example, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1000346.s001">Text S1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s4">Discussion</xref>). We propose that the missing ingredient in direct transmission models is the additional indirect contribution made to transmission by the ingestion of infectious virions that persist in the environment. It has been demonstrated, for example, that the avian influenza strain H2N4 (A/Blue-winged teal/TX/421717/01) can persist for extended periods in the environment, with an estimated one log decay time of 490 days in water at temperature 4°C, pH 7.2, salinity 0 ppt 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000346-Stallknecht1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000346-Stallknecht3" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. Additionally, these persistent virions are known to be infectious 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000346-Stallknecht1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000346-Stallknecht3" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000346-Brown2" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, arguing for a potentially significant epidemiological contribution by environmental transmission.
</p>
