<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Viruses</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Viruses</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">viruses</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Viruses</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1999-4915</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5923494</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v10040200</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">viruses-10-00200</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Accounting for Space &#x02014; Quantification of Cell-To-Cell Transmission Kinetics Using Virus Dynamics Models</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kumberger</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Durso-Cain</surname><given-names>Karina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-viruses-10-00200">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-viruses-10-00200">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Uprichard</surname><given-names>Susan L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-viruses-10-00200">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-viruses-10-00200">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dahari</surname><given-names>Harel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-viruses-10-00200">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1198-6632</contrib-id><name><surname>Graw</surname><given-names>Frederik</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref><xref rid="c1-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-viruses-10-00200"><label>1</label>Center for Modeling and Simulation in the Biosciences, BioQuant-Center, Heidelberg University, 69120 Heidelberg, Germany; <email>peter.kumberger@bioquant.uni-heidelberg.de</email></aff><aff id="af2-viruses-10-00200"><label>2</label>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Loyola University Medical Center, Maywood, IL 60153, USA; <email>kdurso@luc.edu</email> (K.D.-C.), <email>suprichard@luc.edu</email> (S.L.U.)</aff><aff id="af3-viruses-10-00200"><label>3</label>The Program for Experimental and Theoretical Modeling, Division of Hepatology, Department of Medicine, Loyola University Medical Center, Maywood, IL 60153, USA; <email>hdahari@luc.edu</email></aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-viruses-10-00200"><label>*</label>Correspondence: <email>frederik.graw@bioquant.uni-heidelberg.de</email>; Tel.: +49-6221-54-51309</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>200</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2018 by the authors.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>Licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland. This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY) license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Mathematical models based on ordinary differential equations (ODE) that describe the population dynamics of viruses and infected cells have been an essential tool to characterize and quantify viral infection dynamics. Although an important aspect of viral infection is the dynamics of viral spread, which includes transmission by cell-free virions and direct cell-to-cell transmission, models used so far ignored cell-to-cell transmission completely, or accounted for this process by simple mass-action kinetics between infected and uninfected cells. In this study, we show that the simple mass-action approach falls short when describing viral spread in a spatially-defined environment. Using simulated data, we present a model extension that allows correct quantification of cell-to-cell transmission dynamics within a monolayer of cells. By considering the decreasing proportion of cells that can contribute to cell-to-cell spread with progressing infection, our extension accounts for the transmission dynamics on a single cell level while still remaining applicable to standard population-based experimental measurements. While the ability to infer the proportion of cells infected by either of the transmission modes depends on the viral diffusion rate, the improved estimates obtained using our novel approach emphasize the need to correctly account for spatial aspects when analyzing viral spread.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>cell-to-cell transmission</kwd><kwd>virus dynamics</kwd><kwd>mathematical modeling</kwd><kwd>spatial effects</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1-viruses-10-00200"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>The way a pathogen spreads within a host has important implications for the successful establishment and maintenance of an infection, as well as the identification of therapeutic targets. Being&#x000a0;cellular parasites, viruses have evolved different mechanisms to invade their corresponding target cells in order to replicate and spread infection. In general, these mechanisms can be categorized by two main modes of viral transmission, i.e., (i) cell-free (CF) spread by diffusing viral particles and (ii) direct cell-to-cell (CC) transmission between infected and uninfected cells [<xref rid="B1-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. While cell-free diffusion of viral particles allows the infection of distant cells, direct cell-to-cell transmission leads to local spread, avoids complex entry processes and is thought to have the potential to shield the virus from neutralizing antibodies and other antiviral clearance mechanisms [<xref rid="B2-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B3-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Therefore, the latter transmission mode is usually thought to be more efficient in spreading infection [<xref rid="B4-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B5-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In addition, CC is assumed to play an important role in the establishment of persistent infections and therapy failure [<xref rid="B2-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B6-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The importance and contribution of each of the transmission modes to viral spread still has to be determined in detail. However, to address this question, a reliable quantification of the individual transmission kinetics is needed.</p><p>Mathematical models have been an essential tool to analyze experimental data to assess viral infection dynamics. They have allowed the quantification of viral kinetics and identification of potential antiviral therapies (reviewed in [<xref rid="B8-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="B9-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B10-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]). These virus dynamics models are usually based on systems of ordinary differential equations (ODE) describing the change in concentrations of target and infected cells, as&#x000a0;well as the viral load over time. The earliest models, including the so-called standard model of virus dynamics [<xref rid="B8-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], concentrated on cell-free transmission describing the spread of infection by a contact process between virions and target cells [<xref rid="B11-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="B12-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Mathematically, this transmission was formulated by simple mass-action kinetics. While these models provided first estimates of viral infection kinetics and cellular turnover dynamics, they ignored the process of cell-to-cell transmission. With increasing awareness of the importance of cell-to-cell transmission for infection dynamics, revised models appeared that additionally accounted for this transmission mode by extending the standard model of virus dynamics [<xref rid="B13-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="B14-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="B15-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B16-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="B17-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. These&#x000a0;new models considered different specific aspects of cell-associated transmission, including the possibility to transfer multiple viral strains simultaneously [<xref rid="B16-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="B17-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], as well as considering a time-delay for viral production [<xref rid="B13-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. However, all these models described cell-to-cell transmission by allowing target cells to get infected proportional to the concentration of infected cells and assumed that target and infected cells are well mixed. This assumption is especially violated for viral spread among stationary cells, e.g.,&#x000a0;within solid tissue environments. As the infection progresses, infected cells successively become surrounded by other infected cells, hindering cells in the center of infected foci from contributing to cell-to-cell transmission. Such foci of infected cells have been observed, for example, in HCV-infected liver tissue [<xref rid="B18-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B19-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B20-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Thus, previous models relying on the mass-action assumption overestimate the fraction of infected cells contributing to cell-to-cell transmission and lead to an inappropriate quantification of the infection dynamics. There have been several approaches to improve these quantifications for various pathogens by using probabilistic [<xref rid="B21-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and spatially explicit modeling frameworks, such as agent-based models [<xref rid="B22-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="B23-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. However, especially the latter approach is difficult to be directly fit to experimental data. Therefore, finding an extension for the standard model of virus dynamics that appropriately accounts for cell-to-cell transmission would help to improve current analyses of viral spread.</p><p>To this end, we developed an agent-based model (ABM) to simulate viral replication and spread in a monolayer of cells. The simulated data allowed us to reveal the deficiencies of standard virus dynamics models when analyzing viral spread by cell-to-cell transmission. Based on these analyses, we developed an extension for the standard model of virus dynamics to allow for an appropriate quantification of the infection kinetics due to cell-to-cell transmission. Our novel approach adjusts for the decreasing proportion of infected cells contributing to cell-to-cell spread with progressing infection, which is especially important for viral transmission among stationary cells. In contrast to current models, our&#x000a0;proposed model provides a more accurate quantification of the underlying infection dynamics. As&#x000a0;such, our extension provides a means to account for viral transmission dynamics on a single cell level within the context of a model that remains applicable to common population-based experimental measurements that are used to quantify rates characterizing viral infection and spread. Additionally, we&#x000a0;tested the ability of our novel method in comparison to previous approaches to infer the contribution of each of the transmission modes to infection spread and found that reliable approximations of these contributions depend on the diffusion rates of cell-free virus, with our novel approach leading to more appropriate estimates. Thus, our analysis provides an improved understanding of how to reliably quantify cell-to-cell transmission dynamics for various viruses spreading within solid tissue-environments.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-viruses-10-00200"><title>2. Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec2dot1-viruses-10-00200"><title>2.1. The Standard Model of Viral Dynamics</title><p>The standard model of virus dynamics describes the coupled dynamics of the concentration of target cells, <italic>T</italic>, infected cells, <italic>I</italic>, and the extracellular viral load, <italic>V</italic> [<xref rid="B8-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In general, target cells are assumed to get infected at rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm1"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> proportional to the viral concentration <italic>V</italic> and have an average lifetime of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm2"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Infected cells produce new virions with a viral production rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm3"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and are lost with rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm4"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, while free virions are cleared with rate <italic>c</italic>. Previous model extensions accounted for cell-to-cell transmission by including an additional infection term, also allowing target cells to get infected at a rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm5"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> proportional to the concentration of infected cells [<xref rid="B13-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="B14-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="B15-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Hereby, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm6"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> describes the rate of cell-to-cell transmission. In summary, the basic model accounting for both transmission modes is then described by the following system of ordinary differential equations:<disp-formula id="FD1-viruses-10-00200"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="mm7"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>As we will later introduce different extensions and sub-models of this standard model, <xref ref-type="table" rid="viruses-10-00200-t001">Table 1</xref> provides an overview of all the different models used in the current study.</p></sec><sec id="sec2dot2-viruses-10-00200"><title>2.2. Simulating Viral Spread in a 2D Agent-Based Model</title><p>We developed and simulated spread of a positive-strand RNA virus within a monolayer of cells in vitro using an agent-based modeling approach. Cells were distributed on a two-dimensional lattice with each node denoting a single cell. We assume that each cell has a hexagonal shape with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm8"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> direct neighbors and the total hexagonal shaped grid comprising 24,031 cells in total (90 cells per side).</p><p>A sketch of the different processes considered in the agent-based model is depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f001">Figure 1</xref>A. Cells are stationary and can be either infected or uninfected. Upon infection of a cell, intracellular viral replication is modeled by an ordinary differential equation describing the accumulation of positive-strand RNA, <italic>R</italic>. We assume density dependent replication with a maximal replication rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm9"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and a carrying capacity of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm10"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>cap</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for each cell. Positive-strand RNA is degraded with rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm11"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and exported from the cell with an export rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm12"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> contributing to the extracellular viral concentration, <italic>V</italic>. However, only a fraction of the intracellular viral RNA, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm13"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>inf</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, is assumed to be infectious. Thus, the intracellular replication of positive-strand RNA in an infected cell at site <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm14"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and its export is described by the following system of ordinary differential equations:<disp-formula id="FD2-viruses-10-00200"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="mm15"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>cap</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>inf</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Extracellular virus is capable of diffusing through the lattice with diffusion modeled as seen in [<xref rid="B24-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] assuming that the viral concentration at grid site <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm16"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> changes from time step <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm17"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm18"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> by:<disp-formula id="FD3-viruses-10-00200"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="mm19"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x003a9;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
with <italic>k</italic> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm20"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x003a9;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> denoting the number and set of neighboring grid sites, respectively, and <italic>m</italic> the fraction of viral particles that are assumed to diffuse. An uninfected cell can get infected by cell-free transmission at each time-step with probability <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm21"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> dependent on the extracellular viral concentration at the corresponding grid site, <italic>V</italic>, and a scaling factor <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm22"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, i.e., <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm23"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Cell-to-cell transmission is considered by the direct transmission of intracellular viral RNA from an infected cell to its uninfected neighbor and occurs with probability <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm24"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> dependent on the intracellular concentration of infectious viral RNA within the infected cell, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm25"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>inf</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and a scaling factor <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm26"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Upon successful infection, the concentration of intracellular viral RNA within the infecting cell is reduced due to transfer of viral material into the target cell and the novel infected cell starts viral replication with one single viral RNA. Initial viral load for cells infected through cell-free infection is also one viral RNA. Intracellular viral replication is parameterized by fitting Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD2-viruses-10-00200">2</xref>) to experimental data on the spread of HCV within in vitro cultures that measured the intracellular RNA per cell and the extracellular viral load over time [<xref rid="B25-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The estimated parameter values considered within the simulation are shown in <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-viruses-10-00200">Table S1</xref> and the resulting time courses of the concentrations for intracellular RNA, <italic>R</italic>, and extracellular infectious virus, <italic>V</italic>, for one infected cell are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f001">Figure 1</xref>B.</p><p>Resembling previous experimental protocols [<xref rid="B21-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], our ABM-simulated infection is initialized by choosing a number of cells at random that are infected with probability <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm27"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>init</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> during the first 17&#x000a0;h of a simulation. Hereby, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm28"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>init</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is defined by:<disp-formula id="FD4-viruses-10-00200"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="mm29"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>init</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>17</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm30"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> denoting the expected total number of infected cells during initialization, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm31"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the rate at which the inoculum used for infection looses its infectivity. At 17 h post infection, the total extracellular virus concentration is reset to zero, representing the change of media.</p><p>The simulated cell culture system was run for 10 days and the number of infected cells, as well as the viral concentration at indicated time points was noted. The appropriateness of different population-based modeling approaches to infer the underlying parameters characterizing both transmission modes was determined by fitting these models to the simulated ABM-data. The&#x000a0;probabilities for cell-free, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm32"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and cell-to-cell transmission, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm33"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, were varied between simulations to consider different contributions of each of the two transmission modes to infection spread. An example of a simulation of the agent-based model about 3 days after the initiation of infection assuming a scaling factor <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm34"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>28</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:msup><mml:mi>min</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:msup><mml:mi>virus</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm35"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.82</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:msup><mml:mi>min</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:msup><mml:mi>RNA</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f001">Figure 1</xref>C. The model was implemented in the <monospace>C++</monospace> programming language.</p></sec><sec id="sec2dot3-viruses-10-00200"><title>2.3. Parameter Estimation</title><p>The different mathematical models describing the spread of infection, e.g., Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref>), were fitted to the simulated data using the optim-function in the <italic>R</italic>-language of statistical computing [<xref rid="B26-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Parameters characterizing the infection dynamics were determined maximizing the log-likelihood function given by:<disp-formula id="FD5-viruses-10-00200"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="mm36"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:munderover><mml:msup><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>ln</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi>with</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="FD6-viruses-10-00200"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="mm37"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>me</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>and</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mspace width="4pt"/></mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Hereby, <italic>n</italic> determines the number of different simulations, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm38"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the measured concentration of infected cells or the viral concentration at sampling time point <italic>t</italic> for simulation <italic>j</italic>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm39"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the empirical variation across all simulations, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm40"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the corresponding model prediction with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm41"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x02026;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Furthermore, we assume a constant absolute measurement error, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm42"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>me</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, that was additionally estimated. When the extracellular viral concentration and the number of infected cells were considered in the fit, a relative measurement error was assumed. Parameter identifiability was assessed using a profile likelihood approach [<xref rid="B27-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], which was also used to calculate the 95%-confidence intervals.</p><p>Model performance was compared using the corrected Akaike information criterion (AICc) [<xref rid="B28-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] calculated by:
<disp-formula><mml:math id="mm43"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>AICc</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="script">L</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm44"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">L</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>max</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> defines the maximal value of the log likelihood function, <italic>k</italic> the number of model parameters and <italic>n</italic> the number of data points the model is fitted to. Differences between models were evaluated by the <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm45"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>AICc</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with the difference always calculated compared to the best performing model with the lowest AICc-value within the corresponding situation.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3-viruses-10-00200"><title>3. Results</title><sec id="sec3dot1-viruses-10-00200"><title>3.1. Standard Models of Virus Dynamics Are Insufficient to Describe Cell-To-Cell Transmission Dynamics among Stationary Cells</title><p>The standard model of virus dynamics has been extensively used to analyze time courses of infection. It describes the dynamics of the concentration of target cells, <italic>T</italic>, infected cells, <italic>I</italic>, and the extracellular viral load, <italic>V</italic>, accounting for the infection processes and viral turnover [<xref rid="B8-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f002">Figure 2</xref>A and Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref>) in the Materials and Methods for a detailed description of the model). In this model, the two infection processes of CF- and CC-transmission are generally described by mass-action kinetics dependent on the viral concentration, <italic>V</italic>, and the concentration of infected cells, <italic>I</italic>. Examining the latter term addressing cell-to-cell transmission in more detail, it becomes clear that all infected cells are assumed to always contribute to CC-transmission. However, this assumption is most likely violated for viral spread within spatially defined environments, especially for viral spread among stationary cells, as, e.g., in solid tissues.</p><p>To test the ability of the basic model defined in Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref>) to describe cell-to-cell transmission dynamics among stationary cells, we used an agent-based model (ABM) simulating viral spread in a 2D monolayer of cells. The ABM assumes cells to be distributed in a hexagonal grid, i.e., with each cell having six different neighbors, and accounts for intracellular viral replication and intercellular viral spread (see the Materials and Methods for a detailed explanation). For simplicity, proliferation and death of infected and uninfected cells were neglected. To concentrate on the dynamics of cell-to-cell transmission, we first studied infection spread by cell-to-cell transmission starting with a single infected and assuming unlimited target cell numbers. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f002">Figure 2</xref>B shows the increase in the total number of infected cells averaged over 100 individual ABM simulations that were evaluated every 24 h for 10 days. Fitting a model that assumes standard mass-action kinetics to describe cell-to-cell transmission (CC-model, Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref>) with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm46"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) to these data, we find that it is incapable of providing a reasonable representation of the infection dynamics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f002">Figure 2</xref>B, with reduced Chi-squared-statistics <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm47"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1096</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> indicating poor fit considering the standard deviation of the data). Such a model fails to explain the observed decreasing growth rate of a focus of infected cells over time. Thus, simple mass-action kinetics as it has been used previously [<xref rid="B11-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="B13-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="B14-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] seems to be inappropriate when describing viral spread by cell-to-cell transmission among stationary cells.</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot2-viruses-10-00200"><title>3.2. Improved Description of Cell-To-Cell Transmission Dynamics Accounting for Spatial Effects</title><p>Our ABM-simulated data indicate a non-constant growth rate for foci of infected cells by cell-to-cell transmission among stationary cells. To better understand the dynamics of focus growth by cell-to-cell transmission over time, we consider a virus only capable of spreading by cell-to-cell transmission. Newly-infected cells can only appear next to already infected cells leading to large foci of infected cells. The larger a focus gets, the larger the proportion of cells that are completely surrounded by other infected cells and, hence, can no longer contribute to cell-to-cell transmission (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f003">Figure 3</xref>A). Thus, the previously assumed proportionality between successful cell-to-cell transmissions and the concentration of infected cells (Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref>)) might not hold true and needs to be adapted.</p><p>To this end, we derived a correction term <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm48"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> that adjusts the infection term <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm49"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for the decreasing proportion of cells contributing to cell-to-cell transmission during the progression of infection. Following a single focus of infected cells in a 2D layer of stationary cells and assuming radial focus growth, i.e., all cells in a certain radius around the focus-founding cell are infected before the next expansion phase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f003">Figure 3</xref>A), the proportion of cells able to contribute to cell-to-cell transmission, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm50"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, can be calculated by the ratio between the number of cells in the perimeter of the focus and the total focus size,
<disp-formula><mml:math id="mm51"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>#</mml:mo><mml:mi>cells</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>in</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>perimeter</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>of</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>focus</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>#</mml:mo><mml:mi>cells</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>in</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>focus</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The number of cells in the perimeter depends on the assumed number of neighbors per cell, <italic>k</italic>, and the radius of infection, i.e., the expansion phase, <italic>n</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f003">Figure 3</xref>A). Initially, having only one infected cell, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm52"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as the perimeter equals the whole focus size. After the first expansion phase, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm53"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, the number of cells in the perimeter is equivalent to the total number of neighbors of a cell, i.e., <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm54"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. After the second and third expansion phase, the number of cells in the perimeter doubles and triples, respectively, while the total focus size grows slightly faster (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f003">Figure 3</xref>A). In general, the proportion of cells in a focus contributing to cell-to-cell transmission (CC contributors) after completion of expansion phase <italic>n</italic> and dependent on the assumed number of neighbors, <italic>k</italic>, is determined by:<disp-formula id="FD7-viruses-10-00200"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="mm55"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="10pt"/><mml:mi>for</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Similarly, the total number of infected cells in a focus is calculated by:<disp-formula id="FD8-viruses-10-00200"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="mm56"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>By solving Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD8-viruses-10-00200">8</xref>) for <italic>n</italic> and substituting in Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD7-viruses-10-00200">7</xref>), we obtain:<disp-formula id="FD9-viruses-10-00200"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="mm57"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
as a continuous function of the assumed number of neighbors per cell and the number of infected cells in the focus (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f003">Figure 3</xref>B, dashed red line).</p><p>Obviously, Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD9-viruses-10-00200">9</xref>) only holds true if <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm58"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Otherwise, all infected cells in the focus can still contribute to cell-to-cell transmission as not all neighbors of the founder cell are infected (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f003">Figure 3</xref>A). To allow for a better approximation of the proportion of contributors for small foci sizes, we define <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm59"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm60"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. In order to obtain a smooth function for <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm61"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> dependent on the number of infected cells, we define a connection term <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm62"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm63"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm64"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">R</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, to connect the proportion of contributors for small focus sizes, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm65"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, with the general function for larger focus sizes obtained in Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD7-viruses-10-00200">7</xref>) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f003">Figure 3</xref>B and <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-viruses-10-00200">Supplementary Material Text S1</xref> for a detailed derivation of the connection term <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm66"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). Hereby, the parameter <italic>z</italic> defines the number of infected cells over which the transition between full contributors and ringlike focus growth is used. Thus, the final adjustment term <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm67"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for a single focus comprising <italic>I</italic> infected cells is then given by:<disp-formula id="FD10-viruses-10-00200"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="mm68"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="" open="{" close=""><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>for</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>for</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>for</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm69"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm70"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are functions of the parameters <italic>z</italic> and <italic>k</italic> and define coefficients of the polynomial for <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm71"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ensuring the smoothness of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm72"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (see <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-viruses-10-00200">Text S1</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f003">Figure 3</xref>C shows the development of the proportion of CC contributors for different numbers of neighbors per cell dependent on the focus size, <italic>I</italic>. Note that the adjustment term described in Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD10-viruses-10-00200">10</xref>) is valid for a continuous variable <italic>I</italic>, e.g., <italic>I</italic> representing the concentration of infected cells. To approximate the proportion of cells contributing to cell-to-cell transmission in a culture comprising several foci, <italic>I</italic> can be replaced by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm73"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003d5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <italic>I</italic> defines the total number of infected cells and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm74"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003d5;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the number of different foci at the beginning.</p><p>With the definition of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm75"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, an adjusted model for cell-to-cell transmission dynamics that extends Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref>) is then defined by:<disp-formula id="FD11-viruses-10-00200"><label>(11)</label><mml:math id="mm76"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>As we always neglect cellular turnover in our simulations to focus on the effect of the spatial conditions on the transmission processes, cell death is neglected in the following, meaning <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm77"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> throughout the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot3-viruses-10-00200"><title>3.3. Adjusted Model Provides Improved Description of Cell-To-Cell Transmission Dynamics for Individual Focus Growth</title><p>To test the ability of our adjusted model to describe individual focus growth by cell-to-cell transmission, we fit it to the same simulated data. The adjusted model (aCC-model, Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11-viruses-10-00200">11</xref>) with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm78"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, see also <xref ref-type="table" rid="viruses-10-00200-t001">Table 1</xref>) provides a visibly better description of the growth dynamics than the standard CC-model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f004">Figure 4</xref>A). Model fits are significantly improved (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm79"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>AICc</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>823.1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> compared to <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm80"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>AICc</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>29.2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for the CC- and aCC-model, respectively) and with the adjusted cell-to-cell transmission rate, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm81"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, we are able to explain the decreasing growth rate of a focus over time.</p><p>Estimates for the transmission rate characterizing cell-to-cell spread using the aCC-model are roughly 1.5-times larger than for the CC-model (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm82"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.49</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>cell</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.47</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.50</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> aCC-model vs. <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm83"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.04</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>cell</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm84"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.00</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.07</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> CC-model, <xref ref-type="table" rid="viruses-10-00200-t002">Table 2</xref>). Profile likelihood analysis indicates that all parameters are identifiable based on the given data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f004">Figure 4</xref>A, insert and <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-viruses-10-00200">Figure S1</xref>).</p><p>To more closely resemble the simulated scenario, we also considered a model that additionally incorporated a time-delay for the concentration of infected cells mediating cell-to-cell transmission, i.e., accounting for the time that cells need to become infectious. To this end, the term <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm85"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> describing cell-to-cell transmission in the aCC-model is replaced by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm86"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm87"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> defining the considered time-delay. This revised aCC-d<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm88"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-model further improves model predictions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f004">Figure 4</xref>B and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm89"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>AICc</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>29.2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> compared to the aCC-model, <xref ref-type="table" rid="viruses-10-00200-t002">Table 2</xref>). However, including a time-delay on the standard-model, i.e., CC-d<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm90"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, does not improve model predictions substantially (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm91"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>AICc</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>810.9</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> compared to aCC-d<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm92"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), indicating that the additional consideration of an eclipse phase does not explain all the dynamics observed in the data.</p><p>To validate our theoretically derived adjustment term <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm93"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, we compared the predicted proportion of cells contributing to cell-to-cell transmission (CC contributors) to the proportions inferred from the individual ABM simulations. We found that the aCC-model predicts a slightly higher proportion of CC contributors dependent on the focus size than observed in the simulations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f004">Figure 4</xref>C, green line). However, the aCC-model with an additional time-delay in the concentration of infected cells contributing to CC (aCC-d<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm94"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-model) leads to nice agreement in the predicted and observed proportions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f004">Figure 4</xref>C, red-dotted line).</p><p>In summary, our adjusted model is a more appropriate approach than previous models with simple mass-action kinetics when describing individual focus growth among stationary cells. In addition, it provides a good approximation of the proportion of cells capable of contributing to cell-to-cell transmission.</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot4-viruses-10-00200"><title>3.4. Determining Cell-To-Cell Transmission Dynamics across Multiple Foci</title><p>Data from in vitro experiments usually comprise the simultaneous growth of multiple foci with measurements of viral load and infected cells obtained on a population level. Here, heterogeneity in the time at which individual foci are initiated, as well as processes such as merging of foci (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f005">Figure 5</xref>A) might violate the assumptions used for the derivation of the adjustment term <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm95"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p>To evaluate the appropriateness of our adjusted model to correctly infer cell-to-cell transmission dynamics given the simultaneous growth of multiple foci, we used our agent-based model to simulate viral spread assays that allow the initiation of multiple foci. According to previous experimental conditions [<xref rid="B21-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B29-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="B30-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], we consider a monolayer of cells in which infection is randomly initiated during a time period of 17 h. After this initial infection period, the extracellular virus concentration is set to zero and cell-free infection is turned off, resembling the removal of medium and the addition of antibodies targeting the viral envelope in the experiment [<xref rid="B21-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B29-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="B30-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Infection is then assumed to progress solely by cell-to-cell transmission. As before, the total number of infected cells in the simulations is sampled every 24 h (see the Materials and Methods for a detailed description of the ABM). To compare the CC- and aCC-model in their ability to describe cell-to-cell transmission dynamics, we separate the two processes of initiation of infection and subsequent focus growth. Therefore, only the data after the end of the initial infection period are considered for the analysis, i.e., taking the number of infected cells 17 h post infection as initial condition.</p><p>Again, we observed that our aCC-model performs better than the CC-model that relies on the well-mixed assumption between target and infected cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f005">Figure 5</xref>B and <xref ref-type="table" rid="viruses-10-00200-t002">Table 2</xref>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm96"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>AIC</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>92.88</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). In this more complex scenario, a model not accounting for a decreasing growth rate with progression of infection still fails to describe the decelerated infection dynamics. As already observed for a single focus, using the adjusted model (aCC) leads to approximately a 1.5-fold increase in the estimates for the cell-to-cell transmission rate (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm97"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.13</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>cell</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm98"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.07</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.18</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> CC-model, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm99"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.72</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>cell</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm100"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.70</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.74</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> aCC-model, <xref ref-type="table" rid="viruses-10-00200-t002">Table 2</xref>). In addition, we found that estimates of the cell-to-cell transmission rate for the aCC-model are robust even if the assumed neighbor-distribution, <italic>k</italic>, deviates to some extent from the correct distribution (see <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-viruses-10-00200">Supplementary Material Table S2</xref>). Extending our adjusted aCC-model to additionally account for the time a cell needs to become infectious (aCC-<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm101"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) does not improve model fits as we estimate a delay of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm102"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02248;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. This is expected as, in contrast to the scenario starting with a single infected cell, there are already some infectious cells present after the end of the initiation period. Therefore, an additional time-delay can be neglected and we will concentrate on the aCC-model for the underlying scenario.</p><p>To confirm the suitability of the adjustment term <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm103"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in such a complex scenario, we compared the proportion of CC contributors among all foci of infected cells inferred from the ABM simulations to the proportion predicted by our model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f005">Figure 5</xref>C). Here, the adjustment seems to provide a worse prediction for the proportion of CC contributors than compared to single focus growth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f004">Figure 4</xref>C). Especially for later time points with multiple infected cells, we seem to overestimate the proportion of cells contributing to infection spread. However, the discrepancy between the proportion of CC contributors in the ABM simulations and the predicted proportion by our aCC-model is due to an uneven comparison of both terms. For the ABM, the average increase in infected cells per time step, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm104"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>ABM</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, can be described by:<disp-formula id="FD12-viruses-10-00200"><label>(12)</label><mml:math id="mm105"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>ABM</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002dc;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002dc;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>with</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>end</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>start</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002dc;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>start</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>end</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002dc;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Here, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm106"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>start</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm107"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>end</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represent the start and end time of the simulation run, respectively, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm108"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the approximated average concentration of viral particles in the cells contributing to cell-to-cell transmission. The term <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm109"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002dc;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> defines the infectivity per intracellular viral particle, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm110"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the proportion of infected cells contributing to cell-to-cell transmission by accounting for the availability of uninfected target cells in their neighborhood.</p><p>On the other hand, the increase in infected cells in our aCC-model (Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11-viruses-10-00200">11</xref>) with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm111"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) is given by:<disp-formula id="FD13-viruses-10-00200"><label>(13)</label><mml:math id="mm112"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>ODE</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Both equations, Equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD12-viruses-10-00200">12</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD13-viruses-10-00200">13</xref>), describe the same increase, i.e., <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm113"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>ABM</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>ODE</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f005">Figure 5</xref>D) with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm114"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002dc;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Hereby, the proportion of contributors in Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD13-viruses-10-00200">13</xref>), <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm115"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, needs to be corrected for the proportion of target cells that are still available (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f005">Figure 5</xref>C, dashed green line). This is already implicitly considered in the corresponding term <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm116"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002dc;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for the ABM. Thus, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm117"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x002dc;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> corresponds to <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm118"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm119"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> describes the proportion of available target cells at time <italic>t</italic> with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm120"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> defining the total number of target cells at the start of the infection dynamics. In summary, although heterogeneous growth of multiple foci and merging of foci violate the assumptions used to derive the adjustment term <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm121"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, the term still provides a reliable approximation of the proportion of cells contributing to focus growth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f005">Figure 5</xref>C) if corrected for the available proportion of target cells. Therefore, our extended aCC-model provides a better description of the observed infection dynamics than standard models when analyzing viral spread by cell-to-cell transmission among stationary cells.</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot5-viruses-10-00200"><title>3.5. Using Population Dynamics Models to Disentangle Combined Transmission Dynamics</title><p>So far, we have only considered the spread of infection by cell-to-cell transmission and showed that the adjusted CC model (aCC) provides a good description of the underlying dynamics. However, during infection, both transmission modes most likely occur simultaneously. This leads to the question to which extent population dynamics models, as described by Equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11-viruses-10-00200">11</xref>), are generally able to disentangle the contribution of each of the transmission modes to viral spread. To this end, we simulated infection dynamics allowing for simultaneous occurrence of cell-free and cell-to-cell transmission in our agent-based model. Hereby, infected cells produce virions that are exported to the extracellular space and diffuse through the simulated space before infecting other cells (see the Materials and Methods). Sampling the number of infected cells and the extracellular viral load at various time points, we then determined the ability of the different ODE models (Equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11-viruses-10-00200">11</xref>)) to predict the proportion of cells infected by either cell-free (CF proportion) or cell-to-cell transmission as observed in the ABM-simulations.</p><p>In the first step, we considered a scenario with virions diffusing slowly through the extracellular environment, i.e., considering a low viral diffusion rate. For simplicity, we again neglected cell proliferation and cell death within the ABM-simulations. As before, we observe that our adjusted model considering both transmission modes (aCCF-model, Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11-viruses-10-00200">11</xref>) with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm122"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) provides a substantially better description of the observed dynamics than the standard model (CCF-model, Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref>) with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm123"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f006">Figure 6</xref>A, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm124"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>AICc</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>60</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="viruses-10-00200-t003">Table 3</xref>). Based on the estimates for <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm125"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm126"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, the CCF-model also predicts that all cells are infected by only one of the two transmission modes. In contrast, the aCCF-model indicates an increasing proportion of cells infected by cell-free transmission, which is comparable to the observations in the simulated data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f006">Figure 6</xref>B). However, at later time points, the CF proportion is generally underestimated which indicates an underestimation of the corresponding transmission rate, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm127"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Thus, while the standard model is incapable of inferring the contribution of each of the two transmission modes to infection spread, our adjusted model provides appropriate approximations, although it underestimates the CF proportion at later time points.</p><p>Identifying the contribution of each of the transmission modes to viral spread could potentially be facilitated if one of the transmission rates is already known, or if it can be quantified based on separate experiments. Assuming that cell-to-cell transmission can be blocked, we simulated infection spread in our ABM only allowing for cell-free transmission. Fitting the standard model of virus dynamics (CF-model, Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref>), <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm128"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) to these data, we observe that a correct quantification of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm129"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is impaired under conditions in which the extracellular virus diffuses slowly (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f006">Figure 6</xref>C). Specifically, in cases of low viral diffusion rates infection tends to spread locally, causing a model assuming mass-action kinetics for infection spread to provide a poor description of the dynamics. This could already be seen for local spread by cell-to-cell transmission (e.g., <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f004">Figure 4</xref>A). However, given fast viral diffusion rates (&#x0223c;1.7 <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm130"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>m<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm131"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>s<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm132"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> resembling those observed for HIV-sized virions diffusing in water [<xref rid="B31-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-viruses-10-00200">Table S1</xref>), which are roughly 165-times faster than assumed before, a model describing cell-free transmission by mass-action kinetics would provide a reasonable description of the observed dynamics as the system approaches a well-mixed situation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f006">Figure 6</xref>C). Thus, a separate quantification of the rate of cell-free transmission is only appropriate in case of fast viral diffusion rates allowing far-range viral spread.</p><p>We therefore tested if the simultaneous analysis of simulated data from systems considering either only cell-free or both transmission modes in case of fast viral diffusion allows us to disentangle the contribution of each of the two transmission modes to infection spread. We found that both models, CCF and aCCF, provide reasonable descriptions of the dynamics for infected cells and extracellular virus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f006">Figure 6</xref>D,E). Furthermore, both models lead to similar estimates for the cell-free and cell-to-cell transmission rates, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm133"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm134"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f006">Figure 6</xref>F and <xref ref-type="table" rid="viruses-10-00200-t003">Table 3</xref>). In this scenario, there is no indication for the necessity of an adjustment term that corrects for a decreasing frequency of CC contributors (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm135"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>AICc</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>9.5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="viruses-10-00200-t003">Table 3</xref>). Due to a fast viral diffusion, many new foci are initiated during the time course of infection, which in turn leads to small average focus sizes. Despite their ability to describe the infection kinetics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f006">Figure 6</xref>F), both models slightly overestimate the proportion of cells infected by cell-free virus, although capturing the general dynamics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f006">Figure 6</xref>D,E).</p><p>In summary, population dynamics models are able to provide a rough approximation for the proportion of cells infected by either of the transmission modes if viral diffusion rates allow for far-range viral spread, and in case one of the transmission kinetics can be quantified separately. In the case of high viral diffusion, there is generally no evidence for using the adjusted aCCF-model. However, if CF infection tends to spread locally, i.e., if viral diffusion rates are low, using the adjusted model aCCF-model is recommended as it provides far better approximations than the previously used CCF-model.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4-viruses-10-00200"><title>4. Discussion</title><p>Direct cell-to-cell transmission of viral material between infected and uninfected cells has been found to play an important role for various viruses, including hepatitis C virus, influenza and HIV-1 (reviewed in [<xref rid="B1-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]). As cell-to-cell transmission is thought to have the potential to shield the virus from host neutralizing antibodies and other viral clearance mechanisms [<xref rid="B2-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B3-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B21-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B32-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], it has been estimated that this route of transmission is much more efficient than cell-free viral spread [<xref rid="B4-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B5-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. However, to reliably infer the contribution of this transmission mode for the spread of infection, appropriate mathematical models that analyze the infection dynamics are essential.</p><p>In the current study we show that standard population-based approaches fall short to explain viral spread within spatially defined environments given cell-associated viral spread. In particular for stationary cells, ODE models relying on mass-action kinetics to describe spread of infection by cell-to-cell (CC) transmission do not explain the observed dynamics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f002">Figure 2</xref>B). This can be explained by the fact that such models assume that all infected cells are capable of contributing to cell-to-cell spread while the actual proportion is decreasing with increasing focus sizes. Spatial effects limit the proportion of contributors as soon as infected cells are completely surrounded by other infected cells. Models not accounting for this loss underestimate the actual transmission kinetics by overestimating the population of cells driving the spread of infection. Extending previous virus dynamics models by adding a newly developed adjustment term that accounts for this decreasing proportion of CC contributors over time, we were able to correctly describe the underlying dynamics. This novel approach provides more appropriate estimates for the kinetics of cell-to-cell transmission among stationary cells, with estimates for the cell-to-cell transmission rates being roughly 1.5-times larger than estimates relying on the uncorrected models. In this scenario, estimates based on mathematical models that rely on mass-action kinetics only provide a lower bound for the transmission kinetics as they tend to overestimate the cell population contributing to infection. To what extent this also applies for cell-to-cell transmission among motile target cells still has to be investigated. However, it has already been shown that the assumption of a well-mixed situation has to be taken with care if cell-cell interactions take time, and if multiple cells interact simultaneously [<xref rid="B33-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="B34-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="B35-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. With the observed importance and assumed efficiency of a direct viral transmission pathway between infected and uninfected cells for several viruses, it is more important than ever to correctly account for this mode of transmission when analyzing viral spread.</p><p>As appropriate experimental methods to distinguish between cells infected by either route of transmission are lacking, mathematical models currently represent a feasible alternative strategy to estimate the contribution of each of the transmission modes to viral spread. However, disentangling the contribution of cell-free and cell-to-cell transmission to viral spread by population dynamics models in case of their simultaneous occurrence is generally challenging (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f006">Figure 6</xref>). Our analysis based on simulated data indicates that our extended ODE model provides a better approximation for the proportion of cells infected by each transmission mode compared to previous approaches, when cell-free virus tends to spread locally (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f006">Figure 6</xref>B). However, an underestimation of the proportion of cells infected by cell-free transmission at later time points is still observed, and is to be expected. Specifically, when viral diffusion rates are low growth patterns are more likely to resemble those relying on cell-to-cell transmission dynamics causing the contribution of cell-free transmission to be underestimated as it cannot be reliably separated from growth of foci by cell-to-cell transmission. Analysis of data from experiments where either cell-free [<xref rid="B21-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] or cell-to-cell transmission [<xref rid="B14-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] is inhibited can be used to quantify one of the transmission kinetics separately. This additional information clearly improves the quantification of the contribution of each of the transmission modes to viral spread. Hereby, the kinetics of cell-free transmission can only be reliably estimated by population-dynamics models if viral diffusion rates allow for far-range viral spread leading to non-local growth patterns. However, even with such prior-knowledge biased estimates can still be obtained as the mean-field approximations by ODE models can only insufficiently account for the effects both transmission modes have on each other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f006">Figure 6</xref>F).</p><p>For simplicity, our analysis explicitly concentrated on the viral transmission dynamics and neglected infected cell death and the turnover of uninfected target cells in the simulated data and analysis. As such, our approach could be especially relevant for non-cytopathic viruses, such as hepatitis B and C virus, where cell death can be ignored until effective immune responses are induced [<xref rid="B36-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="B37-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. To which extent target cell turnover, as well as recovery of tissue could affect the dynamics and, thus, the appropriateness of our extension term, remains to be investigated. However, several theoretical studies including target cell dynamics already revealed the limitations of modeling approaches using simple mass-action kinetics in case of spatial effects [<xref rid="B24-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="B38-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. In ecological and epidemiological studies, it has also been shown that the consideration of space for contact-dependent infection spread has important implications on the epidemiological and evolutionary dynamics [<xref rid="B39-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="B40-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Spatial separation of the susceptible population can lead to delayed and more reduced infection kinetics, as well as a higher likelihood of epidemics to go extinct [<xref rid="B39-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. A number of different modeling frameworks have been developed that study infection spread within populations and that have also been used to determine the effect of space in the context of viral spread within tissues. These modeling frameworks include meta-population models [<xref rid="B24-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], pairwise-approximation or spatial moment equations [<xref rid="B41-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], models based on partial differential equations [<xref rid="B31-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], and even sophisticated agent-based models and cellular automata [<xref rid="B22-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="B23-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. However, these studies mainly concentrated on the qualitative behavior of the systems due to the general difficulty of fitting them to experimental data. Nevertheless, they already revealed differences in the infection dynamics in comparison to non-spatial models and limitations for their assumptions [<xref rid="B24-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="B38-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="B42-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Thus, especially in the context of experimental systems of increasing complexity that mimic natural tissue structures [<xref rid="B43-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="B44-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="B45-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], reliably accounting for space will be important when analyzing viral spread.</p><p>Our novel approach represents a first step towards an improved quantification of cell-to-cell transmission dynamics within complex environments using ODE-based virus dynamics models. It is especially relevant for viruses spreading within solid tissues, such as hepatitis C virus within the liver [<xref rid="B18-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B20-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] or influenza spreading in lung epithelial tissue [<xref rid="B23-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Most importantly, the extended model formalism allows for consideration of viral spread on the cellular level, while remaining applicable to the standard population-based experimental data typically available for analysis (e.g., [<xref rid="B14-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]). While individual cell-based approaches, such as agent-based models as presented here and elsewhere [<xref rid="B22-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="B46-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], allow a more detailed description and analysis of the transmission kinetics, the complex data required to utilize such models is less often available, and the computational complexity of the models themselves can be limiting. In combination with the advances in computational methods that allow parameter estimation for such sophisticated models [<xref rid="B47-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], these approaches could enhance the possibility to infer the kinetics and contribution of each of the transmission modes to viral spread for different pathogens and, thus, could provide necessary information for the development of potent antiviral strategies.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>Peter Kumberger and Frederik Graw were funded by the Center for Modeling and Simulation in the Biosciences (BIOMS). The research was supported in part by the U.S. National Institute of Health (NIH) Grant R01-AI078881 (Susan L. Uprichard and Harel Dahari). We acknowledge financial support by Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft within the funding program Open Access Publishing, by the Baden-W&#x000fc;rttemberg Ministry of Science, Research and the Arts and by Ruprecht-Karls-Universit&#x000e4;t Heidelberg. The funders had no role in the design of the study; in the collection, analysis or interpretation of data; in the writing of the manuscript; nor in the decision to publish the results.</p></ack><app-group><app id="app1-viruses-10-00200"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><p>The following are available online at <uri xlink:href="http://www.mdpi.com/1999-4915/10/4/200/s1">http://www.mdpi.com/1999-4915/10/4/200/s1</uri>: Figure S1: Profile likelihood analysis for parameter estimates considering single focus growth, Table S1: Parameters used for simulating viral spread in the agent-based model, Table S2: Estimates for the aCC-model given multiple foci using different fixed values for the assumed number of neighbors per cell, <italic>k</italic>, Text S1: Mathematical derivation of a continuous adjustment term for cells contributing to cell-to-cell transmission.</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="viruses-10-00200-s001"><media xlink:href="viruses-10-00200-s001.zip"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></app></app-group><notes><title>Author Contributions</title><p>F.G. conceived of and designed the study. P.K. and F.G. performed the analysis and developed the methods. P.K., S.L.U., H.D. and F.G. analyzed the data. K.D. and S.L.U. contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools. P.K., S.L.U., H.D. and F.G. wrote the paper.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></notes><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><p>The following abbreviations are used in this manuscript:</p><array orientation="portrait"><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell-to-cell</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CF</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell-free</td></tr></tbody></array></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1-viruses-10-00200"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sattentau</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Avoiding the void: Cell-to-cell spread of human viruses</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>815</fpage><lpage>826</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro1972</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18923409?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18923409</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2-viruses-10-00200"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sigal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balazs</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekel</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Milo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baltimore</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell-to-cell spread of HIV permits ongoing replication despite antiretroviral therapy</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2011</year><volume>477</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10347</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21849975?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21849975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3-viruses-10-00200"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brimacombe</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grove</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meredith</surname><given-names>L.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Syder</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Timpe</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumert</surname><given-names>T.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tellinghuisen</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neutralizing antibody-resistant hepatitis C virus cell-to-cell transmission</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>596</fpage><lpage>605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.01592-10</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20962076?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20962076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4-viruses-10-00200"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubner</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spinelli</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predominant mode of human immunodeficiency virus transfer between T cells is mediated by sustained Env-dependent neutralization-resistant virological synapses</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>12582</fpage><lpage>12595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.00381-07</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17728240?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17728240</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5-viruses-10-00200"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orenstein</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimitrov</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell-to-cell spread of HIV-1 occurs within minutes and may not involve the participation of virus particles</article-title><source>Virology</source><year>1992</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>712</fpage><lpage>724</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0042-6822(92)90038-Q</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1370739</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6-viruses-10-00200"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abela</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berlinger</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schanz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynell</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunthard</surname><given-names>H.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rusert</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trkola</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell-cell transmission enables HIV-1 to evade inhibition by potent CD4bs directed antibodies</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog.</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e1002634</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002634</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22496655?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22496655</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7-viruses-10-00200"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barretto</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sainz</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uprichard</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determining the involvement and therapeutic implications of host cellular factors in hepatitis C virus cell-to-cell spread</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>5050</fpage><lpage>5061</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.03241-13</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24554660?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24554660</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8-viruses-10-00200"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perelson</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modelling viral and immune system dynamics</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Immunol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri700</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11905835?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11905835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9-viruses-10-00200"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Canini</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perelson</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Viral kinetic modeling: State of the art</article-title><source>J. Pharmacokinet. Pharmacodyn.</source><year>2014</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10928-014-9363-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24961742?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24961742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10-viruses-10-00200"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graw</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perelson</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling Viral Spread</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Virol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>555</fpage><lpage>572</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-virology-110615-042249</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27618637?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27618637</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11-viruses-10-00200"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perelson</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>A.U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Markowitz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>D.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HIV-1 dynamics in vivo: Virion clearance rate, infected cell life-span, and viral generation time</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>1582</fpage><lpage>1586</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.271.5255.1582</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8599114?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8599114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12-viruses-10-00200"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>A.U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>N.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahari</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gretch</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiley</surname><given-names>T.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Layden</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perelson</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis C viral dynamics in vivo and the antiviral efficacy of interferon-alpha therapy</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1998</year><volume>282</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.282.5386.103</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9756471?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9756471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13-viruses-10-00200"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Culshaw</surname><given-names>R.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A mathematical model of cell-to-cell spread of HIV-1 that includes a time delay</article-title><source>J. Math. Biol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>425</fpage><lpage>444</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00285-002-0191-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12750834?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12750834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14-viruses-10-00200"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwami</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakaoka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mammano</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clavel</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Inaba</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Misawa</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aihara</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koyanagi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cell-to-cell infection by HIV contributes over half of virus infection</article-title><source>eLife</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e08150</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.08150</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26441404?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26441404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15-viruses-10-00200"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Groppelli</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellegrino</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borrow</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chain</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jolly</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hybrid spreading mechanisms and T cell activation shape the dynamics of HIV-1 infection</article-title><source>PLoS Comput. Biol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e1004179</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004179</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25837979?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25837979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16-viruses-10-00200"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Komarova</surname><given-names>N.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>D.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wodarz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synaptic transmission and the susceptibility of HIV infection to anti-viral drugs</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>2103</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep02103</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23811684?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23811684</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17-viruses-10-00200"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Komarova</surname><given-names>N.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wodarz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Virus dynamics in the presence of synaptic transmission</article-title><source>Math. Biosci.</source><year>2013</year><volume>242</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mbs.2013.01.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23357287?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23357287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18-viruses-10-00200"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kandathil</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Graw</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>H.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Torbenson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perelson</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balagopal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of laser capture microdissection to map hepatitis C virus-positive hepatocytes in human liver</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2013</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>1404</fpage><lpage>1413</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2013.08.034</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23973767?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23973767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19-viruses-10-00200"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graw</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balagopal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kandathil</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perelson</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inferring viral dynamics in chronically HCV infected patients from the spatial distribution of infected hepatocytes</article-title><source>PLoS Comput. Biol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e1003934</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003934</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25393308?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25393308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20-viruses-10-00200"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wieland</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Makowska</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campana</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calabrese</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dill</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chisari</surname><given-names>F.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heim</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simultaneous detection of hepatitis C virus and interferon stimulated gene expression in infected human liver</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><year>2014</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>2121</fpage><lpage>2130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.26770</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24122862?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24122862</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21-viruses-10-00200"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graw</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>D.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perelson</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uprichard</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahari</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantification of Hepatitis C Virus Cell-to-Cell Spread Using a Stochastic Modeling Approach</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>6551</fpage><lpage>6561</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.00016-15</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25833046?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25833046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22-viruses-10-00200"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beauchemin</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perelson</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Agent-based modeling of host-pathogen systems: The successes and challenges</article-title><source>Inform. Sci.</source><year>2009</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>1379</fpage><lpage>1389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ins.2008.11.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23-viruses-10-00200"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beauchemin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Samuel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuszynski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple cellular automaton model for influenza A viral infections</article-title><source>J. Theor. Biol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>232</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtbi.2004.08.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15530492?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15530492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24-viruses-10-00200"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>V.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonhoeffer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Killingback</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial models of virus-immune dynamics</article-title><source>J. Theor. Biol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>233</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtbi.2004.10.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15619362?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15619362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25-viruses-10-00200"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aunins</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramanya</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uprichard</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perelson</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intracellular hepatitis C modeling predicts infection dynamics and viral protein mechanisms</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><year>2018</year><comment>in press</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.02098-17</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29563295?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29563295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26-viruses-10-00200"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>R Core Team</collab></person-group><source>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</source><publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27-viruses-10-00200"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raue</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreutz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maiwald</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachmann</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klingm&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural and practical identifiability analysis of partially observed dynamical models by exploiting the profile likelihood</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1923</fpage><lpage>1929</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp358</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19505944?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28-viruses-10-00200"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burnham</surname><given-names>K.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Model Selection and Multinomal Inference: A Practical Information-Theoretic Approach</source><edition>2nd ed.</edition><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc><year>2002</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29-viruses-10-00200"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sabahi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahari</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corcoran</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamora</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garry</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uprichard</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The rate of hepatitis C virus infection initiation in vitro is directly related to particle density</article-title><source>Virology</source><year>2010</year><volume>407</volume><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2010.07.026</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20800257?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20800257</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30-viruses-10-00200"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barretto</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uprichard</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis C virus Cell-to-cell Spread Assay</article-title><source>Bio-Protocol</source><year>2014</year><volume>4</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21769/BioProtoc.1365</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29104884?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29104884</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31-viruses-10-00200"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strain</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richman</surname><given-names>D.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatiotemporal dynamics of HIV propagation</article-title><source>J. Theor. Biol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>218</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jtbi.2002.3055</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12297072?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12297072</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32-viruses-10-00200"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reh</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Magnus</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schanz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uhr</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rusert</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trkola</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Capacity of Broadly Neutralizing Antibodies to Inhibit HIV-1 Cell-Cell Transmission Is Strain- and Epitope-Dependent</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog.</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e1004966</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1004966</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26158270?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26158270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33-viruses-10-00200"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graw</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Regoes</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigating CTL Mediated Killing with a 3D Cellular Automaton</article-title><source>PLOS Comput. Biol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000466</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19696876?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19696876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34-viruses-10-00200"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gadhamsetty</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mar&#x000e9;e</surname><given-names>A.F.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beltman</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Boer</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A General Functional Response of Cytotoxic T Lymphocyte-Mediated Killing of Target Cells</article-title><source>Biophys. J.</source><year>2017</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>1780</fpage><lpage>1791</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpj.2014.01.048</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24739177?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24739177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35-viruses-10-00200"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pilyugin</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Antia</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling immune responses with handling time</article-title><source>Bull. Math. Biol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>869</fpage><lpage>890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bulm.2000.0181</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11016088?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11016088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36-viruses-10-00200"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dahari</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Major</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mihalik</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perelson</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feinstone</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>A.U.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mathematical modeling of primary hepatitis C infection: Noncytolytic clearance and early blockage of virion production</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2005</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>1056</fpage><lpage>1066</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2005.01.049</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15825086?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15825086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37-viruses-10-00200"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Serti</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Block</surname><given-names>P.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chayama</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehermann</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatitis B virus evades innate immunity of hepatocytes but activates cytokine production by macrophages</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><year>2017</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>1779</fpage><lpage>1793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.29348</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28665004?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28665004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38-viruses-10-00200"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beauchemin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probing the effects of the well-mixed assumption on viral infection dynamics</article-title><source>J. Theor. Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>242</volume><fpage>464</fpage><lpage>477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtbi.2006.03.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16650441?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16650441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39-viruses-10-00200"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohani</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Modeling Infectious Diseases in Humans and Animals</source><publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ, USA</publisher-loc><year>2008</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40-viruses-10-00200"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lion</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baalen</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self-structuring in spatial evolutionary ecology</article-title><source>Ecol. Lett.</source><year>2008</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1461-0248.2007.01132.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18070102?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18070102</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41-viruses-10-00200"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lion</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moment equations in spatial evolutionary ecology</article-title><source>J. Theor. Biol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>405</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtbi.2015.10.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26555844?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26555844</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42-viruses-10-00200"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holder</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boivin</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beauchemin</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Design considerations in building in silico equivalents of common experimental influenza virus assays</article-title><source>Autoimmunity</source><year>2011</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>282</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/08916934.2011.523267</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21244331?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21244331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43-viruses-10-00200"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fackler</surname><given-names>O.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murooka</surname><given-names>T.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Imle</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mempel</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adding new dimensions: Towards an integrative understanding of HIV-1 spread</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>563</fpage><lpage>574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro3309</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25029025?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25029025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44-viruses-10-00200"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glushakova</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baibakov</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Margolis</surname><given-names>L.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmerberg</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infection of human tonsil histocultures: A model for HIV pathogenesis</article-title><source>Nat. Med.</source><year>1995</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>1320</fpage><lpage>1322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm1295-1320</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7489416?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7489416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45-viruses-10-00200"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>B.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deconstructing the third dimension: How 3D culture microenvironments alter cellular cues</article-title><source>J. Cell. Sci.</source><year>2012</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>3015</fpage><lpage>3024</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.079509</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22797912?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22797912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46-viruses-10-00200"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beltman</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maree</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Boer</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lymph node topology dictates T cell migration behavior</article-title><source>J. Exp. Med.</source><year>2007</year><volume>204</volume><fpage>771</fpage><lpage>780</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20061278</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17389236?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17389236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B47-viruses-10-00200"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jagiella</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rickert</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Theis</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasenauer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parallelization and High-Performance Computing Enables Automated Statistical Inference of Multi-scale Models</article-title><source>Cell Syst.</source><year>2017</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>194</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cels.2016.12.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28089542?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28089542</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="viruses-10-00200-f001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Schematic of the agent-based model simulating intracellular viral replication and spread by cell-free (CF) and cell-to-cell (CC) transmission among stationary cells. Cells are assumed to be hexagonally shaped and can be either uninfected (gray) or infected (red). The parameters <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm136"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm137"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> define the probability of infection by CC- and CF-transmission, respectively, dependent on the intra- and extra-cellular viral load at the corresponding grid sites; (<bold>B</bold>) Simulated time courses of intracellular viral load (black line) and produced extracellular virus (gray line) for one infected cell; (<bold>C</bold>) Realization of simulation outcomes after around three days post infection assuming simultaneous occurrence of CF- and CC-transmission (left) or only CC-transmission (right). Cells infected by CF or CC-transmission are indicated in blue and orange, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-10-00200-g001"/></fig><fig id="viruses-10-00200-f002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Sketch of a viral dynamics model in a well-mixed system as given in Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref>). In case of cell-to-cell (CC) transmission target cells (<italic>T</italic>, gray) become infected (<italic>I</italic>, red) with rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm138"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> dependent on the concentration of target and infected cells. Infection by cell-free virus occurs with rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm139"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> dependent on the viral load, <italic>V</italic>, and the target cell concentration. Viral particles are produced by infected cells with rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm140"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and cleared at rate <italic>c</italic>. For simplicity, the processes of cell death and proliferation are neglected here; (<bold>B</bold>) Simulated dynamics and model predictions for viral spread only considering CC among stationary cells starting with a single infected cell. Black dots indicate the mean and vertical lines represent <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm141"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>95</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-confidence interval for the total number of infected cells averaged over 100 individual ABM simulations sampled every 24 h. The red line indicates the best fit of the basic model as described in Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref>) with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm142"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to the data, with the red shaded area indicating the 95%-confidence interval for model predictions using the estimated standard deviation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-10-00200-g002"/></fig><fig id="viruses-10-00200-f003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Proportion of cells contributing to cell-to-cell (CC) transmission. (<bold>A</bold>) Sketch of cells contributing to focus growth for different numbers of neighbors per cell and different expansion phases assuming radial focus growth. Whereas cells in the perimeter of the focus (orange) can contribute to CC-transmission, cells completely enclosed by other infected cells (red) cannot; (<bold>B</bold>) Proportion of cells contributing to CC-transmission dependent on the focus size assuming that each cell has six neighbors (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm143"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). The theoretically-determined relationship (Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD9-viruses-10-00200">9</xref>), red dashed line) underestimates the true proportion for small focus sizes. The black line indicates the complete adjustment term as described in Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD10-viruses-10-00200">10</xref>)) with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm144"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; (<bold>C</bold>) Proportion of CC contributors with respect to focus size assuming either <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm145"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (red), 6 (green) or 8 (blue) neighbors (neigh) for each cell. Parameter <italic>z</italic> is set to 10.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-10-00200-g003"/></fig><fig id="viruses-10-00200-f004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Simulated data and corresponding model predictions describing growth of an individual focus of infected cells. (<bold>A</bold>) Individual focus growth by cell-to-cell (CC) transmission among stationary cells starting with a single infected cell. Black dots indicate the mean and 95%-confidence interval for the total number of infected cells averaged over 100 individual ABM simulations that were sampled every 24 h. Model predictions using standard mass-action kinetics (CC-model, Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref>) with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm146"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, magenta) or our adjusted model (aCC-model, Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11-viruses-10-00200">11</xref>) with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm147"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, green) to describe cell-to-cell transmission dynamics. Insertion: Profile likelihoods of the estimated cell-to-cell transmission rate, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm148"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, using either the CC- (magenta) or aCC- (green) model; (<bold>B</bold>) An additional model extension considering a time-delay for the time infected cells need to become infectious (aCC-<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm149"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, red) additionally improves model predictions; (<bold>C</bold>) Proportion of CC contributors as predicted by the aCC-model (green line), and the extended aCC-<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm150"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-model (red dashed line) in comparison to the actual proportion observed in the ABM simulations (gray lines). The corresponding parameter estimates are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="viruses-10-00200-t002">Table 2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-10-00200-g004"/></fig><fig id="viruses-10-00200-f005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Sketch of the same number of infected cells distributed on two foci that are either separate or build one merged focus. Cells contributing to cell-to-cell (CC) transmission (orange) and non-contributors (red) are indicated. Boundaries of separate foci are marked in blue; (<bold>B</bold>) Simulated data and model predictions for a scenario allowing for multiple foci growth. Black dots indicate the mean and 95%-confidence interval for the total number of infected cells averaged over 100 individual ABM simulations that were sampled every 24 h. Colored lines indicate the best fit using either the CC- (magenta) or adjusted aCC-model (green). Corresponding parameter estimates are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="viruses-10-00200-t002">Table 2</xref>; (<bold>C</bold>) Proportion of CC contributors predicted by the adjustment term (green solid line) as defined in Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD10-viruses-10-00200">10</xref>) in comparison to the proportions inferred from each individual simulation (gray lines). The dashed green line represents the corrected adjustment term multiplied with the proportion of target cells relative to the number of target cells at the beginning of the simulation, i.e., <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm151"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; (<bold>D</bold>) Approximate increase of infected cells calculated per minute in the ABM (black dots, mean and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm152"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>95</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-confidence intervals based on 100 simulations) and the ODE model (red line) as defined by Equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD12-viruses-10-00200">12</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD13-viruses-10-00200">13</xref>), respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-10-00200-g005"/></fig><fig id="viruses-10-00200-f006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Disentangling viral transmission modes: (<bold>A</bold>,<bold>B</bold>) Simulated data and best model fits for a scenario assuming simultaneous occurrence of both transmission modes given slow diffusion of cell-free virus. Black dots indicate the mean and the 95%-confidence interval of the data obtained from 100 individual simulations runs of the ABM sampled every 24 h. (<bold>A</bold>) Lines show the best fits of a model allowing for both transmission modes without (CCF-model, magenta, Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref>)) or with adjusted cell-to-cell transmission dynamics (aCCF-model, green, Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11-viruses-10-00200">11</xref>)) fitted to the number of infected cells; (<bold>B</bold>) The observed (black dots) and predicted (solid lines) proportion of cells infected by cell-free (CF) transmission dependent on the best fit shown in panel (<bold>A</bold>); (<bold>C</bold>) Simulations of a scenario only allowing for CF-transmission with slow viral diffusion (gray) and fast viral diffusion (black). Lines indicate the best fit of the standard model (Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref>) with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm153"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) to the data; (<bold>D</bold>&#x02013;<bold>F</bold>) Similar scenario as in (<bold>A</bold>) with simultaneous occurrence of both transmission modes this time assuming high viral diffusion rates (black, CC/CF trans) and additionally considering a scenario with only CF-transmission (gray, CF trans). Both scenarios are fitted simultaneously. The number of infected cells (<bold>D</bold>), as well as the dynamics of the extracellular viral load (<bold>E</bold>) are shown. (<bold>F</bold>) The observed (black) and predicted proportions of cells infected through CF-transmission in the scenario allowing for both transmission modes. Corresponding parameter estimates for each of the different models are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="viruses-10-00200-t003">Table 3</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="viruses-10-00200-g006"/></fig><table-wrap id="viruses-10-00200-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">viruses-10-00200-t001_Table 1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Overview of all different models considered that were applied to the ABM-simulated data. As&#x000a0;we always neglect cellular turnover in our simulations to focus on the effect of the spatial conditions on the transmission processes, cell death is always neglected within the model equations, meaning <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm154"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name</th><th align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Equation #</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Assumptions</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CF</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell-free (CF) transmission model</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref>)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm155"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell-to-cell (CC) transmission model</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref>)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm156"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCF</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CF and CC model</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1-viruses-10-00200">1</xref>)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aCC</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">adjusted CC model</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11-viruses-10-00200">11</xref>)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm157"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aCC-d<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm158"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">adjusted CC model with delay on infected cells</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11-viruses-10-00200">11</xref>)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm159"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm160"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> included</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aCCF</td><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CF and adjusted CC model</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11-viruses-10-00200">11</xref>)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="viruses-10-00200-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">viruses-10-00200-t002_Table 2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Estimates of the cell-to-cell (CC) transmission dynamics in the simulated data. The CC-, aCC-&#x000a0;and aCC-d<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm161"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> model (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="viruses-10-00200-t001">Table 1</xref> for equations) are fitted to the concentration of infected cells obtained for the growth of single and multiple foci. The parameter estimate of the best fit is given with the <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm162"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>95</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>-confidence interval shown in brackets. Model performance was assessed using the corrected Akaike information criterion (AICc). The difference in the corrected AIC values, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm163"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>AICc</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, is calculated relative to the <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm164"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>AICc</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of the best fitting model (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm165"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>AICc</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) for single and multiple focus growth, respectively. For the aCC-model, the neighbor distribution was defined by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm166"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The&#x000a0;parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm167"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> scales the number of infected cells within the adjustment term and defines a quantity representing irregular focus growth, with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm168"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> indicating perfect circular focus growth. For multiple foci, the&#x000a0;number of infected cells is divided by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm169"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003d5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c8;</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm170"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c8;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> defines the number of initially infected cells (see also <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-viruses-10-00200">Supplementary Material Text S1</xref>). Viral turnover rates, i.e., <italic>c</italic> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm171"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, are not taken into account when analyzing only CC-transmission dynamics.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model:</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CC</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aCC</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm172"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">aCC</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">I</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td colspan="3" align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1">
<bold>Single focus</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm173"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm174"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mi>cell</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm175"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.04</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.00</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.07</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm176"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.49</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.47</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.50</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm177"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2.04</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.82</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.34</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm178"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm179"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2.7</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.58</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.82</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm180"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.62</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.31</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.94</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>z</italic> (cells)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm181"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>13.6</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>8.82</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>17.9</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm182"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>20.2</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>12.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>28.6</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm183"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (hours)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm184"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5.71</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>3.73</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>7.89</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm185"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>AICc</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">823.1</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.2</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td colspan="3" align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1">
<bold>Multiple foci</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm186"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm187"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.166667em"/><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mi>cell</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm188"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.13</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.07</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.18</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm189"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.72</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.70</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.74</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm190"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.72</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.70</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.79</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm191"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm192"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.78</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.70</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.86</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm193"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.78</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.66</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.86</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>z</italic> (cells)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm194"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2.19</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>6.61</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm195"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2.09</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>6.31</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm196"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (hours)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm197"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.65</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="4pt"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.664</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm198"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>AICc</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.88</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.33</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="viruses-10-00200-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">viruses-10-00200-t003_Table 3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Estimated transmission rates for model predictions fitted to simulated data allowing simultaneous transmission dynamics. The transmission rates describing cell-free, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm199"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and cell-to-cell transmission, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm200"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, are denoted in <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm201"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>9</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mi>cell</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm202"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, respectively. For the simultaneous fit of both transmission modes to the number of infected cells without separate quantification of cell-free transmission (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00200-f006">Figure 6</xref>A) no reasonable values for <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm203"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> can be obtained, i.e., <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm204"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is not identifiable (ni). Confidence intervals are calculated from 2 &#x000d7; <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm205"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (CC/CF) and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm206"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (CC/CF + CF) individual fits using random starting conditions and considering all parameter combinations within a range of 3.84 of the best fit likelihood. The difference in the corrected AIC values, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm207"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>AICc</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, is calculated relative to the <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm208"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>AICc</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of the best fitting model for each scenario, i.e., <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm209"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>AICc</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenario:</th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1">Both Transmission Modes</th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1">Both Transmission Modes + Only CF</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1">(CC/CF)</th><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1">(CC/CF + CF)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model:</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCF</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aCCF</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCF</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aCCF</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm210"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.37 (0, 2.41]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.74 [2.67, 3.00]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52 [1.50, 1.54]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52 [1.50, 1.63]</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm211"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.30 [3.65, 5.20]</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.30 [3.67, 4.80]</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm212"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x00394;</mml:mo><mml:mi>AICc</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>