<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During the emerging pandemic, all patients suspected of influenza were indicated for treatment with antiviral drugs and their relatives (household contacts) were eligible for prophylactic antiviral drug use. Antiviral drugs were sufficiently available from the national stockpile that has been established since the H5N1 outbreak in 2003. In the beginning of August 2009, the Health Council of the Netherlands and the National Institute for Public Health and the Environment (RIVM) concluded, in concordance with WHO recommendations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>], that the impact of the H1N1 virus on morbidity and mortality appeared to be similar to seasonal influenza virus, based on its so far documented relatively mild course [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Treatment with antiviral drugs was now only recommended for patients at risk for severe disease and patients having a complicated course of influenza [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Prophylactic prescriptions were no longer recommended. High risk patients were defined as the same patients eligible for seasonal influenza vaccination, 
 <italic>i.e.</italic> all patients of 60 years or above and patients with certain medical conditions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. In addition to that, children under two years of age, pregnant women in their third trimester, and patients having symptoms of influenza in whom the infection occurred to be unusually severe or with complications were considered [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. In the Netherlands, oseltamivir was the drug of first choice for treatment of high risk patients suspected of influenza during the pandemic. Treatment with zanamivir was reserved for patients suspected for an infection with a resistant influenza virus. Oseltamivir was only available as a prescription drug, not over the counter, and it was in stock for approximately one third of the Dutch population (5 million doses for 16 million inhabitants).
</p>
