<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite the existence of effective measles (M) and measles-containing vaccines (MCV), resurgence of measles cases in the USA and across Europe has occurred, including individuals vaccinated with two doses of the vaccine [
 <xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In Europe, a safe and effective two-dose vaccination schedule has been made available since the 1960s. The introduction of the trivalent measles, mumps, rubella (MMR) vaccines started in the 1970s [
 <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] (in Hungary in 1991, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>), and it is still in practice, in the form of modern and safe tri- and tetravalent (measles, mumps, rubella and varicella; MMRV) vaccines. However, the risk of continued widespread circulation of measles in EU/EEA still exists, since significant immunity gaps persist, due to suboptimal historical and current vaccination coverage [
 <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Despite regional outbreaks of measles infections, in 2016, globally fewer than 1 00 000 individuals died from measles, as a result of recent improvements of national immunisation programmes. In the WHO European Region (WHO EUR), between 2009 and 2017, the estimated regional coverage was 93–95% for the first dose of measles-containing vaccines (MCV1), and increased from 73% to 90% for the second dose (MCV2) [
 <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In spite of the improving vaccine coverage tendencies, measles incidence increased again to 89.5 per 1 million population in 2018 in the EU region [
 <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. From 1 July 2018 to 30 June 2019, 30 EU/EEA Member States reported 13 102 cases of measles, also including fatalities [
 <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. According to WHO reports, the largest outbreaks occur in countries with low measles vaccination coverage. However, outbreaks occurred even in countries with high national vaccination rates [
 <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Lately, an alarming surge of measles cases was experienced in countries neighbouring Hungary. From 2017 to 2018, Ukraine had the largest increase in measles cases worldwide [
 <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In 2018, Ukraine reported &gt;54 000 measles cases; more than the entire EU. The total estimated number of measles cases for the first 5 months of 2019 was 52 034, including 17 deaths [
 <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Romania also bears a high burden of the disease; between the first outbreak (late 2016) and May 2019, Romania has reported 16 627 cases and 63 deaths. Ninety-four per cent of the reported cases were unvaccinated individuals, and 4% received only one of the two-shot vaccination series. Regarding parotitis epidemica (mumps), the last accessible ECDC surveillance report is from 2016; 28 EU/EEA countries reported 14 795 cases of mumps, of which the Czech Republic, Poland, Spain and the UK were responsible for 77% of these cases. The mumps childhood vaccination coverage in Hungary is ≥99% (MCV1 and MCV2 are equivalent to MMR1 and MMR2 in Supplementary Fig. S1. Supplementary materials are available on the Cambridge Core website), consequently, the risk of infection is predominantly by virus importation [
 <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In Hungary, the rubella vaccine was introduced in 1990 in the form of measles–rubella (MR) bivalent vaccine. A year later, in 1991, it was replaced by the MMR trivalent vaccine that is still in use today. From 1 July 2018 to 30 June 2019, EU/EEA Member States reported 483 cases of rubella. The highest number of cases was reported by Poland (372), Germany (57), Italy (24), Spain (12) and Romania (4) [
 <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. For Hungary, between 2007 and 2018, WHO reports only 10 cases [
 <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Measles, mumps and rubella statistics (cases per year) based on WHO measles and rubella ‘
 <italic>elimination country profile for Hungary</italic>’ data (i.e. the number of reported infections of the last decades) are shown in Supplementary Figure S2. WHO-UNICEF estimates of national immunisation coverage show that only four EU/EEA countries, including Hungary, Portugal, Slovakia and Sweden, reported at least 95% coverage for both doses of MCV in 2017 [
 <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Despite the estimated 99% measles vaccination coverage in Hungary [
 <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] (Supplementary Fig. S1), from February 2017 to July 2019, 70 measles cases were laboratory confirmed according to the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control (ECDC) reports. 
</p>
