<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0037">The clinical impact of major scientific advances is also amply evident in the current efforts to rapidly develop an effective vaccine against COVID-19. The advances have enabled shortening of the typical time required for developing an effective vaccine from more than a decade to anticipated less than a couple of years. This feat has been accomplished primarily because of the technological advances in molecular biology and genetics and the fact that almost all structural and functional components of SARS-CoV-2 have been delineated, even though their functions are not fully understood. The most challenging aspect of vaccine development is identification of the causal agent, which in the case of COVID-19, in contrast to AIDS, not only was identified soon after the start of the breakout but also its genome was fully sequenced within a month or two after its isolation 
 <xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. In addition, building on the knowledge gained from studies of previous outbreaks of diseases caused by coronaviruses, namely SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV, the protein constituents of SARS-CoV-2 and their modus operandi were alrerady partially understood. Moreover, technological advances have made it possible to generate RNA- and DNA-based vaccines, as was accomplished in the case of vaccine for Ebola virus disease. It is quite remarkable that the first RNA vaccine was injected to human volunteers within 3 months after sequencing of the SARS-CoV-2 genome. Given the rapid progress of scientific discoveries, it is a matter of time that an effective and safe vaccine for the prevention of COVID-19 will be developed. As is inherent to any advances, the success will be interrupted by intermittent setbacks, but the progress is inevitable. The characteristics of an ideal vaccine include ease of manufacturing in large quantity and in high purity, stable storage and transportation, convenient route of administration, absence of fortuitous adverse effects, and a low cost. Recognizing the impact of fundamental basic science discoveries on developing an effective vaccine, the US Department of Health and Human Services has launched the Operation Warp Speed, which is designed to streamline the regulatory process in vaccine development and commercialization. The bottleneck is no longer the lack of basic scientific data but rather in conducting large-scale clinical trials that are essential to demonstrate efficacy of the new vaccines. Multiple approaches to vaccine development are being pursued, which are summarized in 
 <xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> .
</p>
