<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The correct identification of viruses is critical for disease management. However, the great ability of viruses to evolve and generate molecular and biological variation is a major difficulty for virus detection and disease management. Presently, when a new virus-like disease appears, the first approach is to test for known viruses with well-established techniques (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">
  <bold>Figure 5A</bold>
 </xref>). ELISA is the most popular for routine analysis because of historical reasons, easiness to perform with little training and commercial availability of antibodies specific for the main plant viruses. However, antibody production is expensive, time-consuming, and unpredictable, and it cannot be designed to cope with viral variability. In contrast, the development of molecular techniques is fast and cheap, making them more appropriate to cope with the frequent cases of new virus emergence (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Boonham et al., 2014</xref>). PCR techniques are the most widely used because of the easy design, versatility, and low cost of primers. Real-time qPCR is becoming the molecular method of choice for routine virus analysis (especially for new viruses for which antibodies are not available or with low accumulation levels) and quantification. On-site detection techniques by LFA and isothermal amplification (RPA and LAMP) allow an almost immediate response and are rapidly developing. When these techniques fail to detect the virus causing disease, the best approach is to use HTS, which can identify all the viruses in one plant, albeit infectivity assays or field surveys are necessary to determine which of the viruses detected is likely the disease causal agent (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">
  <bold>Figure 5A</bold>
 </xref>). In some cases, such as quarantine, using HTS as first approach for virus detection can be more profitable than testing many viruses with ELISA or molecular detection techniques. However, HTS is still too expensive for most routine analyses and it is necessary to develop rapid and accurate detection techniques for each virus, being PCR the easiest to develop. The design of primers or probes for accurate detection requires to evaluate the genetic diversity of viral populations by analysis of nucleotide sequences. (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">
  <bold>Figure 5B</bold>
 </xref>).
</p>
