<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite high EIV-specific immune coverage and the use of an EI vaccine fully updated according to the last OIE recommendation on EI vaccine strain composition (i.e., EI vaccines should contain representative EIV strains of both FC1 and FC2 sub-lineages), the absence of clinical EI in France came to an end in early December 2019. Numerous EI outbreaks were reported in several European countries (Belgium, Germany, Ireland, the Netherlands, Sweden and the United Kingdom). The scale, number and duration of this epidemic had not been experienced in Europe since the late 1970s and 1980s. Sequencing results revealed that H3N8 EIV strains at the origin of the 2018–2019 French outbreaks (and EI outbreaks in other European countries, OIE ESP communication) belong to the FC1 sub-lineage, which was not isolated in France since 2009 [
 <xref rid="B13-vaccines-07-00174" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and was usually circulating in North and South Americas [
 <xref rid="B17-vaccines-07-00174" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-vaccines-07-00174" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-vaccines-07-00174" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. While several amino acids mutation were identified in the HA, results from the hemagglutination inhibition assay using mono-specific ferret sera and the associated antigenic cartography analyses indicate that FC1 EIV strains the origin of the 2018–2019 EI outbreaks were still antigenically closely related to the recommended FC1 EIV strains for inclusion in EI vaccine [
 <xref rid="B33-vaccines-07-00174" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. As a consequence, this epidemic was not considered by the OIE ESP to be linked to a mismatch with the EI vaccine strains and the EI vaccine strain recommendation remained unchanged in 2019. The introduction of more pathogenic strains could be an alternative explanation. The FC2 EIV strains isolated in Europe in recent years were of mild and decreasing pathogenicity [
 <xref rid="B34-vaccines-07-00174" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], which may provide an explanation for the absence of EI in France in recent years (results from this study indicate that EI immunity/vaccine coverage is close to the level described by Satou and Nishiura [
 <xref rid="B12-vaccines-07-00174" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]). However, a few anecdotal reports of EI induced mortality in the field in several EU countries and observation of mild but noticeable clinical signs of disease in EI vaccinated horses raise a question about the pathogenicity of the current FC1 EIV strain. At the time of this report, the current FC1 EIV strain has not been used in a controlled experimental infection, which prevents any strong assumption about its pathogenicity. Surveillance results reported in the current study highlight a larger amount of French EI outbreaks involving vaccinated horses, which is not entirely surprising when the high EI vaccine coverage measured here is taken into account. For the few cases where serum were obtained at the onset of disease, it appears that infection could be explained in half of the cases by a lower than expected SRH antibody titer at the time of contact with EIV (irrespective of the time since last immunization). With the exception of horse #6, which had an SRH antibody titer above the 154 mm
 <sup>2</sup> threshold, other vaccinated horses had average titers (between 93 and 129 mm
 <sup>2</sup>), probably high enough to significantly reduce the clinical signs of disease but insufficient to induce sterilizing immunity, which is rarely measured [
 <xref rid="B35-vaccines-07-00174" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], even in optimal study conditions.
</p>
