<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>BACKGROUND</title>
  <p>Health literacy (HL) is identified as one of the determinants, mediators or moderators of health and of utilization and outcomes of health care services. An inadequate level of HL correlates with patient disengagement, inappropriateness of care, increased health care costs, and higher mortality rates. Few previous data show that over 50% of Italians have a problematic or inadequate level of HL. As compared with the European Countries, Italy has peculiar characteristics of socio-demographic determinants of HL levels, which constitute a challenge for policy making. In so far HL has not been a strategic priority for the Italian National Health Service.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title>
  <p>The Italian National Institute of Health (Istituto Superiore di Sanità – ISS) and Ministry of Health (MoH) are promoting a national program on HL, by participating to the WHO action network on measuring population and organizational health literacy (M-POHL). Main objective of ISS and MoH engagement is the proposal of policies that could enable all citizens to share the benefits of improved HL. A national population survey, coordinated at European level and carried out by each participating country, is planned for next Autumn.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>RESULTS</title>
  <p>In 2018 a pilot survey using the HLS-EU-Q16 questionnaire was administered to 100 adults in Reggio Calabria during the Health Examination Survey of the CUORE Project. The questionnaire has now been extended to 47 specific questions about HL and 32 about lifestyles and demographic characteristics. Results will be analysed in order to define a strategy for the implementation of actions for the improvement of HL in the Italian population in the next National Prevention Plan. The national survey will be periodically scheduled and conducted to monitor results. Policies about HL will be implemented at individual, community, organization and system level. A national steering committee of experts is working for the support of all HL policy initiatives.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
  <p>As inadequate HL is a prevailing problem in Italy, the participation of Italy to M-POHL is strategic in order to set actions for HL improvement. Routinely examination and monitoring of HL levels in the future could help to define specific action plans for improvement, in order to avoid inequalities and waste in the access to health services. The comparison with existing policies in other countries participating to the M-POHL will be an important future step to develop HL policies and related activities to benefit citizens, patients and communities in general.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
