<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>BACKGROUND</title>
  <p>The widespread use of Internet and Social Media among the general population in recent years has interested a wide range of areas related to public health. The need to collect information regarding health and medical treatment on the web, such as vaccination strategies or cancer screening, has led to the circulation of fake news and many anecdotal documents on the effectiveness and safety of these and other preventive measures 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art055_ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>The recent decline observed in vaccination coverage, for instance, can be associated with the spread of erroneous information within mass and social media 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art055_ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
   </sup>. Several studies showed that parents frequently acquire information on vaccination through the web, often on non-institutional and anti-vaccination websites 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art055_ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>To date, in Italy, 54.8 million subjects are active on the web (92% market penetration index – MPI – in comparison to general population numerousness) and 35 million subjects are active on social media (59% MPI) 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art055_ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>This short report aims to evaluate the up-to-date role of Social Media in Public Health issues and the possible future opportunities to meet the communication needs of general population.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>THE EPIDEMIOLOGY OF SOCIAL MEDIA IN ITALY</title>
  <p>According to the Digital 2019 report, in Italy, the mean time spent every day on the web by general population is approximately 6 hours. Every day about 2 hours (1 hour and 51 minutes - 30% of total web usage daily time) are spent on Social Media by over 35 millions Italian 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art055_ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>The social media mainly used are: Youtube
   <sup>®</sup> (87%), Whatsapp
   <sup>®</sup> (84%), Facebook
   <sup>®</sup> (81%), Instagram
   <sup>®</sup> (55%) and Twitter
   <sup>®</sup> (31%) 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art055_ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>Specifically, Youtube
   <sup>®</sup> represents a multimedia content community where can be shared video on several topics 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art055_ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>Differently Whatsapp
   <sup>®</sup>, that was born in 2009 as a an alternative of SMS/MMS for the exchange of text/video/photo/audio messages among private citizens, has gradually evolved over the years in a “social app” with new possibility of communication: audio- or video-calls, update of personal “status” or photo, whatsapp-business (a digital tool to stay in touch with customers and increase brand loyalty) 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art055_ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>On the other hand, Facebook
   <sup>®</sup> and Instagram
   <sup>®</sup> represents actually the most important and commonly used social networking media worldwide 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art055_ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>Both social networks enable the creation of personal profiles or public pages. Public pages, otherwise than personal profiles, allow a shared usage, an unlimited number of contacts, instruments for post and private messages management, business purposes (“Facebook
   <sup>®</sup> Ads” to purchase advertising) and tools for statistical analysis of the page (“Insights”) 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art055_ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>The main difference between Facebook
   <sup>®</sup> and Instagram
   <sup>®</sup> is represented by the age classes of users. The first one has a catchment area between 25 and 80 years old subjects (more than 80% of single users; 53% over 35 years old), while Instagram
   <sup>®</sup> has an higher percentages of users under 35 years old (85%; 59% between 19 and 24 years old) 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art055_ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>Finally, Twitter
   <sup>®</sup> actually represents the most important “blog social media”, used by principal Politicians, Policy Makers, Celebrities, Authorities and Organizations all over the world.
  </p>
  <p>It represents a fundamental Institutional tool for share and spread events, messages, campaigns, fundraising or other 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art055_ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>A message or a commented news/event on Social Media (defined as “post”), to be attractive for general internet-users, should have four main characteristics: easy, attractive, social and timely.</p>
  <p>In general, a good “post” concerning health-care or public health shared on a public page of Social Media such as Twitter
   <sup>®</sup>, Facebook
   <sup>®</sup> and Instagram
   <sup>®</sup> could be viewed by millions of subjects, even if posted online by an anti-scientific organization 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art055_ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>THE IMPACT OF SOCIAL MEDIA ON PUBLIC HEALTH</title>
  <p>The impact of Social and Mass Media on Public Health is considerable. A recent manuscript, that analyzed Youtube
   <sup>®</sup> digital contents, reported a direct correlation (4 times higher) between pro-vaccine videos and the reporting of accurate information and between anti-vaccine videos and the reporting of incorrect information or omissions on HPV vaccination 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art055_ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>In Italy a research conducted on number of followers of public Facebook
   <sup>®</sup> pages of pro- and anti- vaccine organizations showed, in April 2015, a clear predominance of anti-vaccines pages (over 25,000 followers of pages of anti-vaccines health professionals or pages that stated the associations between autism and vaccination vs over 10,000 to pro-vaccines pages). After 3 years, in April 2018, trough a widespread network of health organizations (
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="vaccinarsi.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">vaccinarsi.org</ext-link> website, Iovaccino, Rete Informazioni Vaccini), over 120,000 followers of pro-vaccines pages have significantly overcomed 65,000 followers of anti-vaccines pages (Dr. Daniel Fiacchini personal data; presented at 51
   <sup>st</sup> National Congress of the Italian Society of Hygiene, Preventive Medicine and Public Health).
  </p>
  <p>In 2016, the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control (ECDC) released the technical document “Social media strategy development” that represents a guide for public health organisations to integrate social media into their overall communication activities 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art055_ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>The report underline the role of Social media for listening, informing, educating, and empowering people about health issues. During the last years Social media play a key role also in collecting surveillance data, enhancing the speed at which communication is sent and received during public health emergencies or outbreaks and facilitating desired behaviour changes 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art055_ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>The guide provides a flexibile approach due to different social media literacy and capacities within EU Member States and includes examples, drawn from European public health agencies or organizations, to illustrate practical approaches to Social Media (for instance on sharing information, retweeting public health messages, analyzing Google
   <sup>®</sup> trends ecc.). Finally, the guide reports practical advice on using the most popular social media platforms, including Twitter
   <sup>®</sup>, Facebook
   <sup>®</sup> and YouTube
   <sup>® 
    <xref rid="art055_ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>According to ECDC, Social Media are an essential tool for public health organizations, allowing to collect feedback from general population in real-time, to drive online conversations on relevant topics of interest, to have a direct contact with users and to provide a channel to rapidly respond to queries and concerns 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art055_ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>Finally, the public health professionals that approach a “social media” communicative strategy should consider that: 
   <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
     <p>the communication on Social Media is mainly visual;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>the use of impacting tile and correct key words is necessary;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>the main messages of the “post” should be included at the begniining of the text;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>main paragraphs should be separated (to better understand the steps of the logical process and metaphors and icons should be used;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>summarise the text as possible, according to the principle of “less is more” 
      <sup>
       <xref rid="art055_ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
      </sup>.
     </p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
  <p>Having recognized the importance of Social Media for public health, would be recommended the integration of a tailored and integrated social media strategy into principal health organizations.</p>
  <p>An integrated social media strategy, across all European Public Health Authorities and Organizations, could address the risk communication for communicable disease or non-communicable diseases and for other public health interventions 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art055_ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>For all these reasons, in future, Health Authorities or Organization should be present, active and interactive with users not only on the web, but also on Social Media.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
