<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>BACKGROUND</title>
  <p>Whooping cough (pertussis) represents one of the most prevalent vaccine-preventable diseases in Western countries, capable of causing disease in infants, with a high risk of severe complications, including death. To prevent the occurrence of infectious pertussis in new-borns, many European countries have introduced the acellular pertussis adult vaccine in combination with tetanus and diphtheria toxoids (Tdap) for women in the third trimester of pregnancy. Thanks to the approval of the new National Immunization Prevention Plan (PNPV) 2017-19: Italy is among those countries. The Italian health-care system is a regionally based National Health Service (NHS), therefore, regions are in charge of organizing and implementing new vaccination strategy their own. This study aims to explore how new vaccine policies have been adopted by regions, focusing on Tuscany’s experience in implementing the pertussis vaccine for expectant mothers and to identify lessons learnt that may be relevant to facilitate the implementation of future policies.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>METHODS</title>
  <p>This study had a qualitative design: we obtained information about the implementation process through interviews with relevant stakeholders involved in the planning or implementation of vaccination programme at different levels. Data generated were transcribed verbatim and analysed in four steps: familiarization, indexing/coding, charting and mapping/interpretation.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>RESULTS</title>
  <p>We noticed heterogeneous implementation’s status between Tuscan Health Care Departments. The most frequently reported barriers influencing the success of the implementation process of this prevention strategy included: lack of accountability, lack of enabling instruments, financial constraints, logistics barriers, training deficiencies, attitudes of health care workers and lack of workers specialised in communication.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
  <p>The implementation of new vaccination programs is complex and challenging. Often the importance of education and information activities targeting health professionals are underestimated and underfunded. These elements would need to be carefully considered and adequate provisions should be made to address them when designing and implementing effective vaccine interventions.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
