<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>INTRODUZIONE</title>
  <p>Online Grooming plays a relevant part in internet related child sexual abuses, being defined as a manipulative process through which an adult attempts to arrange a sexual interaction with a minor using the internet. Nowadays, children are constantly exposed to the online world, posing them at risk of dangerous interactions. Online Grooming could therefore be considered a new public health issue worthy of social preventive campaigns.</p>
  <p>The aim of this narrative review is to describe the state of online grooming preventive strategies in recent literature. Our analysis starts from an overview of online grooming phenomenon through an investigation of victim and perpetrator recurring risk factors and modus operandi, highlighting useful elements to lay foundations for future preventive strategies.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>MATERIALI E METODI</title>
  <p>A literature search was performed on PubMed, ScienceDirect, Scopus and Google Scholar in March 2019 with the following queries: 
   <list list-type="bullet">
    <list-item>
     <p>(“online grooming; OR grooming OR “sexual solicitation”) AND (prevention OR preventive strategies OR “sexual orientation”) AND (children OR child OR minor);</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>(perpetrators OR “sex offenders”) AND (“prevention” OR “preventive strategies”) AND (child OR children OR minor) AND (grooming).</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
  <p>Articles published between January 2014 and March 2019 were included, as well as respective reference lists.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>RISULTATI</title>
  <p>The analysis of the selected studies (43) provides a picture of online child sexual exploitation, identifying recurrent features of perpetrators and victims. Female sex, social/family problems, psychiatric disorder, low self-esteem, gender non-conformity and problematic internet use place teenagers at greater risk for child sexual abuse. On the other hand, being a male aged 18-25 and having been victims of particularly violent child sexual abuse have been associated with a greater risk of becoming offenders. These data could be used in order to develop suited preventive campaigns addressed both to potential victims and offenders.</p>
  <p>Several preventive strategies have so far been implemented, but they lack any kind of efficacy evaluation and miss a theory driven approach. Fragmentation of preventive initiatives among the different players involved represents a critical issue, in contrast with the need of institutional public health plans structured in primary, secondary, and tertiary levels.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>CONCLUSIONI</title>
  <p>While the attention around Online Grooming is growing, there is still the need to further sensitize the involved stakeholders. Future academic efforts should be targeted to develop evidence based preventive strategies. Institutional guidance is essential to coordinate the multidisciplinary nature of the preventive action and evaluate the outcomes.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
