<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>INTRODUZIONE</title>
  <p>The recruitment of a large sample size is often a major obstacle encountered by researchers when working on experimental studies. While fully aware of the benefit of medical research, health-care workers (HCWs) are often overwhelmed by their duties and may view the request to participate in a study as an avoidable nuisance.</p>
  <p>The aim of our study was to investigate the success of different strategies used for the recruitment of participants in a cohort study investigating the effectiveness of the 2018-2019 influenza vaccine among HCWs.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>MATERIALI E METODI</title>
  <p>The potential study participants were 4070 HCWs of a major public research and teaching hospital in the city of Milan. A total of twelve researchers were involved in the recruitment of HCWs for a cohort study investigating the effectiveness of the influenza vaccine. The population was approached using several recruitment strategies including: passive information provision within hospital wards, spread-the-word effect, active one-on-one, and active group recruitment. HCWs were also approached at differing times during the workday to understand whether timing affected recruitment success rates.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>RISULTATI</title>
  <p>A successful recruitment of 2207 HCWs (54.2%) was achieved using the various strategies outlined. Passive recruitment strategies and spread-the-word effect accounted for 19% of all successfully recruited HCWs. The remaining HCWs were recruited with the use of active strategies, namely one-on-one (51.5%) and group recruitment during CME update courses (29.5%). Timing was found to be an essential factor in the recruitment process, with HCWs responding positively to recruitment during mid-morning breaks and lunch (off-duty) as well as in group recruitment settings, in particular, CME update courses.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>CONCLUSIONI</title>
  <p>An active recruitment approach involving face-to-face communication is unsurprisingly more effective than a passive approach relying solely on the HCWs will to participate in the study and spread-the-word to colleagues. Moreover, the off-duty setting appears to be the best time for successful recruitment of HCWs.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
