<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
  <p>The anti-epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) monoclonal antibodies, as monotherapy or in combination with chemotherapy, are effective in the treatment of metastatic colorectal cancer (mCRC). Current international guidelines recommend 
   <italic>RAS</italic> (
   <italic>NRAS, KRAS</italic>) genetic testing as predictive biomarkers for response to anti-EGFR therapy. Only 
   <italic>RAS</italic> wild-type tumors should be treated with anti-EGFR agents, as tumors with 
   <italic>RAS</italic> mutations are unlikely to benefit. We aimed to review the cost-effectiveness of 
   <italic>RAS</italic> testing in mCRC patients prior to anti-EGFR therapy and to assess how well economic evaluations adhere to clinical practice guidelines.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title>
  <p>A systematic review of full economic evaluations comparing 
   <italic>RAS</italic> testing vs. no-testing was performed for articles published in English between 2000 and 2018. Study quality was assessed using the QHES scale and the BMJ checklist. Risk of bias in individual studies was evaluated with the Philips checklist for economic modelling studies.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>RESULTS</title>
  <p>Six economic evaluations (two cost-effectiveness analyses; two cost-utility analyses; two combined cost-effectiveness and cost utility analyses) were included. All studies were of good quality and adopted the perspective of the healthcare system/payer; accordingly, only direct medical costs were considered. Of particular concern were the use of not recommended genes (i.e. 
   <italic>BRAF, PTEN, ERBB2</italic>) as predictive biomarkers for response to anti-EGFR therapy, the lack of consideration of 
   <italic>NRAS</italic> mutation status and of key parameters related to genetic tests and biological agents. Two studies were funded by Roche, a leading provider of genetic tests, and the source of funding was not declared in one study. Four studies presented testing strategies with a favorable ICER under the National Institute for Clinical Excellence (£20,000-30,000/QALY) and the US ($50,000–100,000/QALY) thresholds.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
  <p>Testing mCRC patients for 
   <italic>RAS</italic> status and administering anti-EGFR therapy only to patients with 
   <italic>RAS</italic> wild-type tumors is a more cost-effective strategy than treating all patients without testing. The treatment of mCRC is becoming more personalized, which is essential to avoid inappropriate therapy and unnecessary high healthcare costs. The economic evaluations, although of good quality, do not fully adhere to international recommendations regarding the assessment of mutational status prior to therapy with biological agents. Future economic assessments should take into account 
   <italic>NRAS</italic> mutation status and other parameters that reflect the real world, such as toxicity of biological agents, genetic test sensitivity and specificity. The impact of industry sponsorship of economic evaluations on pharmacogenetic tests needs further investigation.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
