<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
  <p>Healthcare-associated infections (HAIs) affect up to 15% of all hospitalized patients, representing a global concern, whose major causes include the persistent microbial contamination of the hospital environment, and the growing antimicrobial-resistance (AMR) of HAI-associated microbes. The hospital environment represents in fact a reservoir of potential pathogens, continuously spread by healthcare personnel, visiting persons and hospitalized patients. The control of contamination has been so far addressed by the use of chemical-based sanitation procedures, which however do not prevent recontamination and can select resistant microbes. Based on the studies on the human microbiome, we characterized the microbiome of the hospital environment and hypothesized to modulate the persistent pathogenic microbiome by a competitive exclusion biological approach, inspired by the microbiome balance principles.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title>
  <p>The conventional chemical-based cleaning procedures were substituted by a probiotic-based system, and environmental contamination was examined by microbiological and molecular methods, including characterization of the resistome of the contaminating population. In parallel, the incidence of HAI onset and the associated therapy costs were evaluated.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>RESULTS</title>
  <p>The microbial-based sanitation system was shown to induce a stable and profound remodulation of the hospital microbiota, obtaining a stable control of both bioburden and AMR, associated with a significant reduction of HAIs and of associated therapy costs.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
  <p>Collected data highlight the possibility to modulate hospital microbiota and suggest that this system might be considered as one of the tools for AMR and infection prevention and control.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
