<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
  <p>It was estimated that ~570,000 women developed cervical cancer and 260,000 died in 2018. Human Papillomavirus Virus (HPV) infection is associated with the occurrence of pre-malignant and malignant cervical lesions. The high HPV-related morbidity and mortality rates have been affected by the implementation and scale-up of national vaccination programs, early diagnosis, and appropriate clinical management. However, an increased 2-year risk of recurrence (5%-10%) was shown in patients who underwent a surgical intervention. Aim of the present study was to evaluate the recurrence rate in patients immunized with HPV vaccine one month before or after a loop electrosurgical excision procedure (LEEP) for cervical intraepithelial neoplasia (CIN1-3).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>METHODS</title>
  <p>It was carried out an observational retrospective, monocentre study. 503 women with a diagnosis of cervical dysplasia and treated with a LEEP intervention between January 2012 and October 2018 were consecutively enrolled in the University Hospital of Sassari, Italy. Only 285 were considered for the current analysis owing to a follow-up of at least 24 months. HPV vaccination was offered to patients following the recommendations of the national immunization program.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>RESULTS</title>
  <p>Individuals exposed to HPV vaccine were significantly younger (median [IQR]: 41 [36-49] vs 37.5 [30-45]; p value = 0.0004). 182 (63.9%) and 103 (36.1%) women were and were not immunized, respectively. No differences were found in terms of margins of resection. Recurrence was diagnosed in 30 women (13.3%): 17 (16.5%) were vaccinated and 13 (7.1%) were not vaccinated (p value = 0.01). The majority of cervical recurrences (19/30, 63.3%) were severe (CIN2/3) lesions. Logistic regression analysis showed that HPV vaccination was the only protective covariate for recurrence occurrence (OR = 0.4; p value = 0.02).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
  <p>The administration of HPV vaccine immediately before or after LEEP significantly reduced the risk of recurrence by ~60%. Based on its observational nature, confounding factors (e.g., severity of the lesions at baseline, type of HPV vaccine, HPV genotype, etc.) could have biased the findings of the study. Experimental studies, based on randomized, and well-balanced designs, are needed and could confirm the preventative role of HPV vaccines.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
