<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
  <p>Antibiotic resistance is an international problem in Public Health. Main purpose of this study is taking over Multi-drug-resistant bacteria diffusion pattern among General Surgery patients at San Matteo Hospital.</p>
  <p>Second aim is identification of microorganism’s virulence factors and patient’s features that correlate with risk of colonization.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title>
  <p>This study includes the recruitment of 858 hospitalized patients at General Surgery Departments in two different phases (A and B). Screening for MDR provides rectal swap (at the time of patient’s admission, every 7 days and at the time of discharge) for gram negative bacteria research and nasal swap at the patient’s admission for Staphylococcus Aureus Meticillino-resistant (MRSA).</p>
  <p>During phase A of 4 months all patients over 18 years are recruited. During the phase B of 12 months, the screening is performed only for groups of patients with infection Risk Factors. Patient’s intrinsic features are analyzed using descriptive statistic methods. Parametric or not parametric tests, Chi Square or Fisher test are used to evaluate increased risk of colonization. Phylogenetic analysis for isolated strains are performed using genomic epidemiology methods. Isolated strains’ virulence and antibiotic resistance are analyzed by Kleborate software.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>RESULTS</title>
  <p>During Period A, 184 patients (38%) among 487 patients, have almost one infection risk factor. 22 swabs are positive for MDR (4,5%), which 16 nasal swabs positive for MRSA and 6 rectal positive swabs. During period B, 371 patients are recruited and positive swabs result 39 (10,5%) 24 nasal swabs for MRSA and 15 positive rectal swabs for gram negative MDR, 4 patients are positive for both swabs. Rectal swabs, during both periods, are positive for Klebsiella KPC in most cases.</p>
  <p>Patient’s BMI values and diabetes diagnosis correlate with an increased risk of colonization (p&lt;0,05). In colonized patients undergoing to ERCP procedure, we found a 5 time risk of sepsis than in not colonized ones.</p>
  <p>Microorganisms strains isolated during both periods, belong at GC258 cluster that is associated with the presence of plasmid with blacKPC gene that encodes for KPC enzyme, in ST258 or ST512. Virulence and Resistance result low, only one isolated strain is colistin resistant.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
  <p>With a targeted screening, we can improve infection control measures and health care based both on patient and epidemiological factors. ERCP procedure is an important risk factor for sepsis in MDR colonized patients and further study will be conducted in this patient setting of care.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
