<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
  <p>Kidney transplantation is the elective treatment for patients with end stage renal disease (ESRD). Despite its success in improving recipient’s health compared with dialyzed or those on waiting list, the postoperative management of these patients still represents a major challenge for Public Health. Indeed, several postoperative complications constitute leading causes for mortality, graft loss and acute rejection following a kidney transplantation. The current study aims to evaluate the association between postoperative complications and the risk of death in a population of kidney transplant patients.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title>
  <p>We used data prospectively collected from patients who underwent kidney transplantation from 2000 to 2012. All transplantation procedures were performed by the same surgical team using a standard technique. For each patient we collected the following characteristics: age, gender, cause of ESRD, neoplasia, date and cause of death and postoperative complications (i.e. cardiovascular, cerebrovascular, infectious and metabolic). The Chi-squared test was performed to compare categorical variables using SPSS software.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>RESULTS</title>
  <p>Among the 476 patients enrolled (aged 11-77 years; 63.2% men), we observed that 21.8% of kidney transplant patients died after a median follow-up of 10 years. Overall, we reported incidences of 9.7% for cardiovascular, 9.0% for metabolic, 4.4% for infectious, and 1.5% for cerebrovascular complications, respectively. Notably, the risk of death increased among patients with neoplasia (OR = 3.570; 95%CI :1.927-6.615; p &lt; 0.001) and among those with cardiovascular (OR = 3.168; 95%CI: 1.688-5.948; p &lt; 0.001) and infectious (OR = 2.842; 95%CI: 1.163-6.944; p = 0.017) postoperative complications. By contrast, other postoperative complications – specifically cerebrovascular and metabolic complications – did not increase the risk of death.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
  <p>Our results confirmed the association of cardiovascular and infectious postoperative complications with the risk of death in patients receiving kidney transplantation. Due to the increased graft survival and longer exposure to immunosuppressive therapy, neoplastic complications are emerging as the leading cause of death.</p>
  <p>In line with our findings, further research is encouraged to develop an individualized approach and screening protocols – based on patient’s characteristics – for reducing incidence of postoperative complications and improving long-term outcomes.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
