<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
  <p>Anaerobic digestion of wastewater sludges is a recognized potential viable solution to reuse their organic matter producing nutrient-rich fertilizers and biogas. Such treatment process can decompose malodorous volatile organic compounds, contribute to chemical pollution control as well as to sensibly reduce pathogenic microorganisms, contributing to the general reduction of sanitary risks. The potential pathogens reduction was investigated during the operation of a full-scale anaerobic digester daily fed with sludges from wastewater treatment plants.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title>
  <p>Experiments were conducted artificially contaminating aliquots of digestate with increasing concentrations of 
   <italic>Salmonella</italic> sp. and 
   <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>. Microbiological analyses were performed on the samples and the potential reduction of fecal bacterial indicators was investigated. Moreover, hypothesizing the synergic effect of digestate biomass in the reduction of pathogenic flora, we carried out the preliminary characterization of the microbial community during mesophilic fermentation of sewage sludge.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>RESULTS</title>
  <p>Spiked concentrations of 
   <italic>Salmonella Typhimurium</italic> and 
   <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> were extremely lowered after anaerobic digestion. The two germs survival at 37°C in aerobic conditions was up to 10 days, while the anaerobic conditions highly inhibited their persistence, reporting the bacteria die-off within 24-48 hours with slight sanitary risks. The molecular characterization of digestate identified the existing microorganisms. 
   <italic>Bacillus</italic> genus to whom non-pathogenic germs mainly belong was predominant. Besides 
   <italic>Bacillus</italic>, 
   <italic>Bacillaceae</italic> like 
   <italic>Aneuribacillus</italic>, 
   <italic>Brevibacillus</italic>, 
   <italic>Lysinbacillus</italic>, and 
   <italic>Rummelibacillus</italic> genera, holding beneficial and bioremediation properties, were found.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
  <p>The combination between anaerobic treatments, metabolites/chemicals derived from the treatment process (e.g. ammonia, and biogas), and microflora digestate by-products contributed to considerably reduce the sanitary risks of pathogenic microbial loads in 24-48 h.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
