<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
  <p>The Italian National Health System presents several critical issues such as the complex patients’ needs, the overlapping healthcare offer, the frequent recourse to hospitalization, the difficult choice between proximity or high volumes structures, the efficiency improvement and the remuneration methods 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art078_ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>The harmonization of patients’ pathways is one of the aims of the National Health Service and takes place in two different ways: overcoming the fragmentation of the care pathway, by promoting functional operative integration between health and social care providers, and the availability of solid organization and technology for managing chronic conditions, according to the “population health management approach”. In particular, the new organizational models tend to overcome the healthcare fragmentation, uniformly applying evidence-based pathways and system governance.</p>
  <p>The Liguria Region’s response to the constant increase in health needs, which depends from the demographic and epidemiological characteristics of the Ligurian population (the oldest European administrative region), and to the critical issues related to system sustainability resulted in a substantial social and health reform based on the principles of equity, effectiveness, appropriateness and efficiency of health services 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art078_ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
   </sup>. These objectives can be achieved by improving efficiency and efficiency that can only be obtained by implementing a solid governance.
  </p>
  <p>A.Li.Sa., the new Liguria Health Authority, has the mandate to improve efficiency of Local Health Agencies, as well as for other regional Authorities, through governance and healthcare. It therefore, assumes a strategic role for the management of the accredited public and private healthcare offer, centralizing on itself the moment of health needs and demand assessment, the programming function and performance monitoring 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art078_ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>A.Li.Sa., starting from the analysis of health needs and demand, guarantees an appropriate and adequate provision of the essential levels of care and the efficient use of resources, also through the development of models of taking charge of the person throughout the network of health and social- health providers. In particular, regarding the function of governing the offer, A.Li.Sa. supervises and regulates the authorization, accreditation and negotiation processes, the agreements and the contracts with the departments responsible for providing the health services.</p>
  <p>Furthermore, the reform of the Regional Social and Health System foresee among its instruments of clinical governance for the integration and standardization processes, the improvement of quality, the efficiency of activities and the appropriateness of services, the establishment of regional inter-company departments (D.I.A.R.). 6 D.I.A.R. were created: Emergency; Cardiovascular; Neuroscience; Oncohematologic; Surgery; Transfusion, Laboratories, Clinical Diagnostics and Imaging and the D.I.A.R. Paediatrics is in phase of constitution 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art078_ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>The process of strengthening horizontal structures does not end with the creation of D.I.A.R., but requires a series of interventions supporting pathology networks.</p>
  <p>Liguria is among the first regions that formed and institutionalized Breast Units, organizational centres specialized in the prevention, diagnosis and care of breast tumour with an approached based on the “disease management” aimed at improving clinical and quality of health services as recommended by the European Surgery legislation 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art078_ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
   </sup>. Specifically, Breast Units are a model of assistance where the management of the patient is entrusted to a multidisciplinary group.
  </p>
  <p>The establishment of such network has the objective of improving management, providing a centralized and homogeneous response throughout the entire region and reducing mobility to extra-regional providers. Passive mobility is a relevant criticism for the Regional Health Service and has relevant implications regarding the equity of access and financial sustainability of the regional health system due to the consequent shifting of financial resources.</p>
  <p>In this contest, the evaluation of the new model using data obtained from regional routine flows is the basis for strategic choices in healthcare.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>METHODS</title>
  <p>The analysis used administrative data, obtained from regional routine flows, such as hospital discharge records related to 2013-2018 period.</p>
  <p>The data were extracted from administrative healthcare data routinely collect data about ED accesses, hospitalizations, outpatient visits, diagnostic tests, treatments and medical fee exemptions financed by public health funding. They are transmitted by the Ligurian Local Health Agencies (LHAs) and hospitals to A.Li.Sa, where the completeness and quality of data is verified, and then sent to the national Ministry of Health. Healthcare data routinely collected by the public funded LHAs and hospitals were used to assess the impact, in terms of health demand, production and passive mobility, for the pre and post institution period of the Breast Unit. An ad hoc analysis was carried out in order to assess if the adoption of a centralized model leads to significant improvements for the regional health system.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>RESULTS</title>
  <p>We recovered data form Hospital Demission Sheet, regarding the 2014-2018 period, of all patients with a primary or secondary diagnosis for breast cancer (diagnosis codes 174*, 19881 or 2330) and who underwent to the relative specific surgery (intervention codes 852*, 8533, 8534, 8535, 8536 or 854*). Overall, 8,509 Ligurian patients underwent to 9,078 surgeries in regional or extra-regional hospitals. Patients were mostly female (9 males and 8,500 females) and had a median age of 65 (IQR: 53-75; min 16; max 99). Distribution of Ligurian patients operated in Liguria per LHA of residence and years of intervention was analyzed. The higher number of surgery for breast cancer was detected in 2016 and from the following years the number ranged between 1,435-1,484. Breast Units were constituted in 2016 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art078_ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
  <p>The number of surgery per hospital characteristics in terms of Breast Units and caseload was evaluated and a progressive centralization of cases operated in Breast Units was observed; it was particularly evident in the last years (2017 and 2018).</p>
  <p>The percentage of surgery underwent in centers with caseload equal or higher than 135 per year increased constantly from 2014 to 2018 varying from 64% in 2014 to 92% in 2018.</p>
  <p>The centralization model resulted optimal outcomes reaching the goal of 100% for San Martino hospital and LHA 2, 99% for LHA 3 and LHA 5 and 95% for LHA 1 respectively in the period 2015 versus 2018. About San Martino hospital, the proportion of interventions for malignant breast cancer performed in wards with volume more than 135 interventions per year increased from 35.8% to 98%.</p>
  <p>Analyzing the differences of percentages of new resection operations breast cancer excision within 120 days from conservative surgery for breast carcinoma between 2017 versus 2018, San Martino hospital, LHA 1, LHA 3, and LHA 5 revealed good performance (data not shown).</p>
  <p>One of the main consequence of operating in a center with a low caseload is the high probability of a secondary intervention within 120 days 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art078_ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
   </sup>, therefore we evaluated the cases of re-intervention in regional centers; in the period 2014-2015 (before the Breast Unit institution) re-intervention rates was 5.12% while in 2017-2018 was 4.97%.
  </p>
  <p>Overall passive mobility (as percentage of surgery that took place in other regions/total number of surgery) varied from 18.0% in 2014, had a peak in 2015 with 21.3% and decreased to 17.6% in 2018. LHA5 had the higher passive mobility with an overall score of 33.5% and a peak in 2015 with 43.4%.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>DISCUSSION</title>
  <p>Liguria is the region with the highest aging index in Italy and has a steadily increasing burden of chronic patients; for these characteristics, it could be considered the reference of other Italian regions 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art078_ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
   </sup>. The reform has taken into account these aspects planning strategic actions by A.Li.Sa. including a support of the network model and implementation of governance by sharing objectives, indicators and targets on a regional level. The recent reform has, therefore, addressed the coordination on a dual level: at the strategic level, through the establishment of A.Li.Sa., intermediate between the Region and the others health authorities (LHAs, hospitals etc.) 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art078_ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
   </sup>, and welfare and socio-assistance level, through the establishment of a new organizational tool, the D.I.A.R. which are based on the network, like some pre-existing organizational forms, but structured and inserted transversally with respect to the pre-existing authorities, whose maintenance was deemed necessary for respond locally to the specific needs of the population 
   <sup>
    <xref rid="art078_ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
   </sup>. D.I.A.R.s were established as an organizational tool to promote quality, appropriateness of care, homogenous and evidence-based healthcare pathways in the regional area, and clinical efficacy with consequent optimization of resources.
  </p>
  <p>Focusing on the results of the implemented model of Breast Unit, an improvement in terms of satisfaction of the healthcare need and a decrease of passive mobility for surgical treatment of breast cancer were obtained. Therefore, the Breast Unit model represents an organizational response able of overcoming the fragmentation of care in favour of a global patient management, the continuity of care pathways and the uniform application of shared evidence-based pathways that allowed containing the patient passive mobility. Indeed, Breast Units have a well-defined pathway that foresees diagnosis, reception, multidisciplinary examination, surgical procedure, rehabilitation program, medical and radio therapeutic course, examinations and exam planning, psychological support, genetic counselling and fertility preservation. Furthermore, very recently a new regional organizational and healthcare pathway (P.D.T.A) on breast cancer was approved and will lead to further improvement in patient management.</p>
  <p>In conclusion, the analysis of regional data is crucially in the supporting strategic decisions and in the assessment of new organizational model and when organisational changed are introduced there is a need of rules, tools, incentives and cultural and motivational aspects.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
