<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
  <p>Two natural compounds, 
   <italic>Allium sativum</italic> fermented extract (BGE) and cannabinol oil extract (CBD), were assessed for their activity on inhibition and removal of 
   <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> biofilm on soft contact lenses in comparison to one multi-purpose Contact Lens (CL)-care solution found in Italian market, CONTACTA
   <sup>®</sup> SOLUTION (Sanifarma Srl, Rome, Italy).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>MATERIAL ANDMETHODS</title>
  <p>
   <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> (
   <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>; ATCC 9027) and 
   <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> clinical strain isolated from ocular swab were tested. Quantification of biofilm was done using microtiter plate assay. One multipurpose CL-care solutions was examined for its ability to remove and inhibit biofilm. Also two natural extracts having antibacterial activity and are safe on eye were tested for their anti-biofilm activity. Determination of fractional inhibitory concentration index (FICI) was calculated.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>RESULTS</title>
  <p>
   <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> (
   <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>; ATCC 9027) and 
   <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> clinical strain are classified as strongly biofilm-forming. BGE at MIC concentration showed inhibition percentage higher than 55%, for both strains; CBD inhibited biofilm formation about 70%. Soft CL care solution at MIC concentration inhibited biofilm formation about 50%, for both strains tested. Effect of BGE on the eradication of microbial biofilm on contact lenses at MIC concentration is 45% eradication for 
   <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> ATCC 9027 and 36% for 
   <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> clinical strain. For CBD, we observed 24% of biofilm eradication formed by both strains. For Soft CL-care solution the eradication MIC concentration is 43% eradication for 
   <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> ATCC 9027 and 41% for 
   <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> clinical strain. It was observed that both test contact lenses solution/BGE (FICI: 0.450) and test contact lenses solution/CBD (FICI: 0.153) combinations exhibited synergistic antibiofilm activity against most of the studied bacteria.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
  <p>Our study showed that BGE and CBD have excellent effect on inhibition of biofilm formation and removal of preformed biofilm which make them promising agents that can be added to new more effective CL-care solutions.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
