<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
  <p>Since their approval in mid-2000, the combined measles-mumps-rubella-varicella (MMRV) vaccines have represented a decisive challenge for countries that recommended universal varicella vaccination in their childhood immunization schedule. However, poor evidences are currently available on the protection attributable to these vaccines administered in real-world settings. To address the gap, we estimated the vaccine effectiveness (VE) after a single dose or two doses of MMRV vaccine against varicella in children &lt; 10 years of age in Apulia region, Italy. We also estimated VE after a single dose or two doses of monovalent varicella (V) vaccine.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>METHODS</title>
  <p>We conducted a matched case-control study in Apulia region (about 397,000 children &lt; 10 years of age), where since 2009 MMRV replaced MMR and monovalent varicella vaccines in toddlers, with a second dose given at 5-6 years and a catch-up dose at 11-12 years of age. Vaccination coverage for varicella progressively increased up to 91.7% for one dose and to 85.9% for two doses of MMRV/monovalent-V vaccine in the birth cohorts 2015 and 2010, respectively.</p>
  <p>Cases of varicella were obtained from the notifiable diseases surveillance system and the hospital discharge registry. Three controls were randomly selected from the population registration system database and matched to cases on the basis of date of birth and residence. Cases and controls vaccination status was retrieved from the Apulian Immunization Information System. Odds Ratios (ORs) with 95% confidence intervals (95% CIs) were calculated by conditional logistic regression. VE was calculated as (1-OR) x100.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>RESULTS</title>
  <p>In the period 2013-2017, a total of 854 (58.1% males) varicella cases were reported among children &lt; 10 years of age (birth cohorts 2008-2016). A total of 2,562 controls were matched to cases. Excluding children who had received a second dose of MMRV or monovalent-V vaccine, VE for a single dose of MMRV was 89,4% (95% CI: 85,3-92,3%) and for two doses was 99,4% (95% CI: 98,1-99,8%). VE for a single dose of monovalent-V was 98,5% (95% CI: 88-100%); no cases had received two monovalent-V doses. Effectiveness after a single dose of any varicella containing vaccine (MMRV or monovalent-V) was 88,5% (95% CI: 84,6-91,4%) and for two doses was 99,5% (95% CI: 98,6-99,9%).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
  <p>MMRV vaccine significantly protects against varicella. Our findings are among the first ever shown on vaccine effectiveness under field conditions and strongly support the use of the combination product in the immunization schedules.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
