<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
  <p>Chronic and acute diseases disproportionately affect hard-to-reach populations, such as homelessness, migrants, or gypsies people living in regular or irregular camps. These people often face barriers in accessing health care services. Here is the description of an innovative health center (HC) developed for identifying barriers and facilitating access to healthcare services of hard-to-reach (HTR) people in Rome (Italy).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>MATERIAL AND METHODS</title>
  <p>The Community of Sant’Egidio together with the UOSD “Migrant Health Unit “of ASL Roma1, since 2016, has established a program aimed to improve health outcomes in HTR urban population</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>RESULTS</title>
  <p>During 2018 the HC reached 804 new patients: 57% were homeless, immigrants, 2% were Italian poor elderly and 41% were gypsies from Bosnia, Serbia, Montenegro, Romania and Bulgaria, living in regular or irregular camps in Rome and province.</p>
  <p>The HC is integrated in a bigger community center offering social, legal, hygiene and food assistance, this being the reason for a high number of accesses and for reduced barriers to healthcare. The program takes place two days/a week and includes an innovative figure, the “health facilitator”, from the UOSD, who is helping migrants and vulnerable people in accessing both public and charitable health services.</p>
  <p>During 2018, a total of 1,894 interventions were classified as health assistance activities. Most common health requests were generalist clinical visits (n. 989) 52%, and free of charge drug distribution (n. 673) 35,5%. The HC assisted some children and adult TB cases, supporting them for the management and the adherence to the treatment.</p>
  <p>Growth control and access to free formula milk was provided for 171 babies, mainly gypsies.</p>
  <p>Prescriptions for access to public health facilities especially for diabetic and cardiologic care (n. 86) was 4,5% of the total activities.</p>
  <p>A relevant action was performed in October-December in order to prevent influenza pandemic: in agreement with generalist associations, more than 300 HTR people resulted vaccinated in the HC.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
  <p>In conclusion the program shows as main strengths: 
   <list list-type="order">
    <list-item>
     <p>including the HC in a community center already well known in the City of Rome;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>close collaboration with the UOSD “Migrant Health Unit “of ASL Roma1, centered on the figure of “health facilitator”;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>free of charge treatment, crucial for adherence in case of chronic diseases (e.g. hypertension, diabetes, epilepsy, hypotiroidism, etc.) as well as for TB case management;</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>upporting public health services in vaccination campaigns for HTR people.</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
