<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Coronaviruses (CoVs) are single-stranded RNA viruses with large, enveloped and positive senses that can infect both animals and humans
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref>. CoVs, along with Artierivirdae and Roniviridae, belong to the Coronaviridae family in the order Nidovirales. These CoVs can infect various hosts, including avian, swine and humans. Human coronaviruses (HCoVs) represent a major group of CoVs associated with various respiratory diseases from common cold to serious pneumonia and bronchiolitis
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>2</sup>
 </xref>. Today, HCoVs are recognised as one of the fastest-evolving viruses derived from their characteristic high genomic nucleotide replacement rates and recombination
 <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref>. Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS), the first confirmed atypical pneumonia in China's Guangdong province, has spread to several countries. The most common symptoms of SARS include coughing, high fever (&gt;38 °C), chills, convulsions, headaches, dizziness and progressive radiographic changes of the chest and lymphopenia
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref>. The severity of the disease shows a death rate of about 3% to 6%, although this rate could rise up to 43% to 55% for senior citizens older than 60 years
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref>. The primary epidemic of SARS was eventually controlled, but a SARS CoV-like virus was detected in Chinese bats
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref>. Besides, a recent pandemic of middle east respiratory syndrome (MERS) caused by a novel coronavirus MERS-CoV raises fear of possible recurrence of SARS or related dangerous diseases
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref>. Since there is no vaccine and effective therapy for these viral infections, developing anti-SARS drugs against future outbreaks remains a formidable challenge.
</p>
