<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Vaccination against flaviviruses generally relies on the strategy to mount protective humoral immunity against structural proteins, in particular neutralizing antibodies (nAbs) elicited against the viral envelope (E) protein (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), though also CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells seem to contribute to the protective activity of current YFV vaccines (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Nonetheless, experimental evidence obtained with mice and nonhuman primates for YFV (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) and, more recently, in mice also for WNV (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) and ZIKV (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) clearly shows that also nonstructural (NS) proteins, in particular NS1, can evoke protective humoral and cellular immune responses. Of note, NS1 is not part of the infectious flavivirus particle and thus not a target of nAbs. Likewise, immunization with an adenovirus vector encoding the NS3 protein of YFV-17D elicited strong CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cell responses, which resulted in some degree of protection in mice against subsequent challenge (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). However, full protection was observed only when the vaccine included the structural proteins of YFV-17D as the antigen as well (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>), obviously in line with the accepted role nAbs play in YFV infection. Thus, besides humoral immune responses against the E protein, cellular immune responses against the NS proteins may to some extent also contribute to immunity against flaviviruses. However, no flavivirus vaccines that are based on any of these NS proteins as the target antigen have been developed or licensed yet for human use. Intriguingly, the genome of chimeric flavivirus vaccines (JE-CVax/Imojev or CYD-TDV/Dengvaxia) consists of sequences of antigenically distinct flaviviruses (respectively, JEV and YFV-17D or DENV and YFV-17D) and may therefore exert some dual protective activities. Here we demonstrate that vaccination of mice with a construct similar to JE-CVax/Imojev provides rapidly complete protection against a massively lethal YFV challenge, with a single dose being sufficient for full efficacy. Moreover, we show that this protection is, notwithstanding its unexpected potency, mediated not by nAbs but by multiple complementary and vigorous responses directed against the NS proteins of YFV-17D.
</p>
