<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Significant gaps remain in our understanding of the tug of war between the host and the virus and the extent to which IAV evolves in response to host defense mechanisms. This information has critical implications for the development of universal vaccination strategies. For years, the dogma had been that neutralizing anti-HA antibodies provided all the pressure necessary for the antigenic changes to occur and for the virus to escape pre-existing immunity. Monoclonal antibodies and polyclonal sera have been shown to select influenza virus mutants dissimilarly in model systems (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). While viral selection using a single monoclonal antibody may lead to HA point mutations in the antibody binding site, mutants arising under selection from polyclonal sera or combination of monoclonal antibodies exhibit increased avidity for cellular glycans and harbor mutations near the sialic acid binding site, distinct from the antibody binding sites (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Similarly, studies investigating intrahost evolution of IAVs in vaccinated and nonvaccinated hosts (dogs, horses, and humans) have been unable to demonstrate selection of viral escape variants (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). These studies suggest that immune-driven variants do not usually arise in immunocompetent individuals. This paradigm needs to be reconciled with the well-known IAV antigenic evolution observed at the population level in humans. Studies are needed to further our understanding of the mechanisms of population-based antigenic evolution and to evaluate the potential contribution from specific immune response (B cells and T cells) in driving such changes.
</p>
