<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Lastly, we estimated the number of doses needed for, and the impact of, possible future PMVCs. As the EYE strategy aims to prevent outbreaks and international spread, we focused on the 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> model which better captures urban transmission. We estimated the effective reproduction number 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>eff</italic>
 </sub> describing the transmission potential in a partially immune population across the endemic region as 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>eff</italic>
 </sub> = 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub>
 <italic>(1-vc)</italic>, where 
 <italic>vc</italic> is the 2018 vaccine-acquired population-level immunity. Based on different 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>eff</italic>
 </sub> threshold values, four vaccination strategies were simulated in which provinces were eligible for PMVCs: i) 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>eff</italic>
 </sub>≥1.25 (strategy A), ii) 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>eff</italic>
 </sub>≥1.01 (strategy B), iii) 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>eff</italic>
 </sub>≥1.00 (strategy C), and iv) 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>eff</italic>
 </sub>≥0.85 (strategy D). These strategies thus rank from a parsimonious strategy focussed on high-risk areas (strategy A) to an ambitious large-scale strategy provinces with a broader range of transmission risk (strategy D). We compared the strategies with each other under the optimistic assumptions of: i) maximized herd effects as per the use of the 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> model variant, and ii) an optimal sequence of PMVC implementation. For each strategy, the total target population was estimated. The corresponding number of vaccine doses was attributed to provinces based on a ranking of 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>eff</italic>
 </sub> values, so provinces with the highest 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>eff</italic>
 </sub> values were vaccinated first (2018) and those with the lowest 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>eff</italic>
 </sub> value were vaccinated last (2026). Vaccination campaigns were assumed to reach 90% of the population, regardless of age or previous vaccination status. For each strategy, the lifetime impact of PMVCs was estimated through comparison with a baseline scenario assuming no further reactive or preventive vaccination campaigns, but an annual 1%-increase in the coverage of routine immunization (capped at 90%) from their 2015 levels in countries where routine immunization already includes YF vaccine.
</p>
