<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>HIV patients experience more frequent ADRs to both anti-TB and other non-TB medications for other opportunistic infections, and the risk of ADRs increases with the degree of immunosuppression.
 <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>–
 <xref rid="CIT0068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref> A recent systematic review and meta-analysis reported at least one ADR in 83% of patients, which is significantly higher than a previous one that reported at least one ADR in 57% of included patients.
 <xref rid="CIT0069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref> The higher incidence was because the former study focused on high-burden HIV settings. The risk factors responsible for higher incidence of ADRs were overlapping or additive toxicity from treatment, poor general condition, low CD4 count, and body-mass index. No statistically significant association has been reported between the occurrence of ADRs and recognized risk factors. Identifying one or more offending drugs responsible for ADRs in patients receiving concomitant therapy for DR-TB and HIV is very challenging. Many of the medications used to treat coinfection have overlapping or additive ADRs, as mentioned in 
 <xref rid="T0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>. The typical strategy of stopping all medications and rechallenging them one by one is not possible in these patients, as the risk of emergence of resistance, especially for ART, is very high.
 <xref rid="CIT0071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref> It should be noted that information regarding the frequency of ADRs is relatively scarce. Most drugs have to be included in the regimens, outweighing the benefit over risk, despite awareness regarding the high probability of overlapping ADRs. If two drugs with overlapping toxicity are considered essential for therapy, intense monitoring of ADRs is to be considered, rather than disallowing a certain combination. Lzd, when used for M/XDR-TB with HIV-coinfected patients, requires intense monitoring, as there is potential for significant worsening of peripheral neuropathy associated primarily with either HIV infection or combination with stavudine (d4T) and also bone-marrow depression when coadministered with Azt. Active TB drug-safety monitoring and management should be an essential component of management of DR-TB and HIV-coinfected patients treated with anti-TB regimens containing newer or repurposed drugs.
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
</p>
