<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">An important question is if there is sufficient capacity to undertake a functional cure study based on HIV-2 in the field sites where there is a sufficient number of relevant HIV-2 cases. There are undoubtedly numerous factors to take into consideration before embarking on such highly complex clinical trials, and a number of relevant concerns need to be taken into account (summarised in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Yet, these are all manageable challenges that have been overcome in previous studies (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). For example, both the Bissau HIV cohort and the Guinea-Bissau police cohort have built a high standard trial capacity during the last decades. Moreover, a therapeutic HIV-1 vaccine trial has already been completed in the Bissau HIV cohort [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124">124</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">125</xref>]. Despite limited settings, large HIV treatment trials such as the PIONA trial have been possible through an experienced clinical trial unit that is still in place in Bissau, Guinea-Bissau [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR126">126</xref>]. This trial unit has the capacity to handle 10–20 annual project visits that such trials may entail, as well as provide complex treatments requiring long infusions. The set-up for advanced analyses of immune-mediated processes is in place, both locally and among external partners [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119">119</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127">127</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">129</xref>]. Finally, more collaborations are needed in order to fully take on the many possibilities within this emerging field of HIV-2 cure research, and the Bissau cohorts are open to any collaborative efforts in this area and possible HIV cure applications. 
</p>
