<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Varieties of computational methods for drug repositioning have been discovered and proposed over the years with the aim of improving efficiency, reducing limitations and fulfilling the duty of drug repurposing. Recently, a novel computational method which utilises machine learning-based methods, matrix decomposition-based methods and network-based methods accompanied by various algorithms for drug repositioning was developed, known as tensor decomposition [
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. This method was proposed by Wang and colleagues in 2019, and it has been outperforming several baseline algorithms such as SNScore, Network-based Random Walk with Restart on Heterogeneous network (NRWRH) and Collective Matrix Factorization (CMF) in recovering missing associations. Also, it solves the difficulty in training negative samples in deep learning methods such as the multi-layer perceptron, deep belief network and stacked auto-encoder for drug repositioning in recent years. It involves the construction and decomposition of three-dimensional tensors which entails the associations among the trios, drugs, targets and diseases (DTD) [
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Latent factors followed by topological data analysis (TDA) are then taken into account to cluster and investigate the properties of drugs, targets and diseases in their respective functional groups. This approach is able to recover not only the missing associations of drugs, target and diseases but can also predict new drug repositioning candidate and discover adverse drug effects, primarily on cancers [
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. For instance, it was found that Leflunomide (LEF), a drug for active rheumatoid arthritis, might increase the risk for pancreatic neoplasms upon investigating the latent factors and compared to KEGG NETWORK drug database followed by validation through several studies. Furthermore, when there is a small latent factors outcome, it can adhere to the fundamental assumption in drug repositioning where similar drugs and targets have similar functional effects. Repositioning can be done on drugs to diseases that come from two clusters with strong associations, instead of assuming new drug–disease associations only. To define clusters, diseases with a similar molecular mechanism tends to appear in the same cluster [
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. This effort was made by finding drugs with a similar chemical structure to the disease-associated drugs. This approach provides a vast potential and new insight to drug repositioning [
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. 
</p>
