<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The dramatic COVID-19 pandemic has surged at an increasing rate, where the characteristic transmissibility can only be defined at commencement because confirmed cases of COVID-19 may be presented with either asymptomatic or symptomatic infection, which could range from mild to severe or life-threatening pneumonia (
 <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Particularly, COVID-19 seems to be transmitted mostly during the incubation period, when most of the patients either lack the symptoms or have very mild non-specific symptoms (
 <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). The common symptoms associated with this disease are high fever, cough, difficulty in breathing, and lesions in the lungs; in the worst cases, it can cause severe pneumonia, acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), and risk for life (
 <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Individuals affected with such symptoms or who have had any International travel history or contact with a person who is ill or been quarantine should approach the government and health-care officials to monitor and check their health status for the safety of their family as well as society. The Centre for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) (
 <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), the World Health Organization (WHO) (
 <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), and the Indian Council of Medical Research (ICMR) (
 <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) has recommended a few guidelines for the collection of the specimens from the affected or suspected COVID-19 patients. It is mandatory that the affected or suspected individuals should co-operate with the state or local health-care departments for the collection, the further process like storage, and shipment of the specimens appropriately. It is highly mandatory and recommended that the specimens should be collected only in a BSL-3 laboratory for the safety of the clinicians and researchers. Based on the recommended guidelines of WHO, the sample will be isolated from two major sources, which are the lower respiratory tract and the upper respiratory tract. The specimens, such as a nasopharyngeal swab (NP) or the oropharyngeal swab (OP), will be collected from the upper respiratory tract, whereas the bronchoalveolar lavage, tracheal aspirate, or sputum will be collected from the lower respiratory tract (
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).
</p>
