<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In randomized trials, transitional case management services for incarcerated PLWH are no better than pre-release discharge planning at improving post-release linkage to care and retention [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002667.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="pmed.1002667.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="pmed.1002667.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Within an integrated prison/jail system, and when targeted to those most in need, case management may require a differentiated service delivery model that caters to PLWH at highest risk for recidivism. Differentiated service delivery is a client-centered approach that simplifies and targets key services (e.g., health insurance and treatment for addiction and psychiatric disorders) needed along the HIV continuum to reduce unnecessary burdens on the health system [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002667.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="pmed.1002667.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="pmed.1002667.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. In the absence of such services, multiple stressors and barriers to care can lead to substance use relapse, high-risk behaviors, and suboptimal healthcare engagement, such as defaulting from ART, which undermine VS [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002667.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>–
 <xref rid="pmed.1002667.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Unlike prior studies, findings here demonstrate that transitional case management is a key enabling factor that is strongly associated with RIC and VS. Despite the important role of case management to facilitate health insurance and community services to improve RIC and VS [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002667.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="pmed.1002667.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], most PLWH (54.8%) did not receive these services, and health insurance coverage remained low (56.3%) over 3 years of follow-up. This indicates an urgent need to expand the provision of case management services both during and after the transition to the community.
</p>
