<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The sociodemographic and climatic covariates were selected based on a theoretical model of disease occurrence and intensity, as described in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0202832.g003">Fig 3</xref>. Climatic factors such as precipitation, temperature, relative humidity and altitude can impact the occurrence and intensity of influenza transmission, since the virus can “live” for up to 48 hours under favorable weather conditions. Climatic factors may also influence human behavior with regard to contact rate and aggregation patterns. Poverty rate and HDI can be important global determinants of flu occurrence and intensity since they are markers of vulnerabilities that includes health, education and income components. Intercity bus, boat and airplane transportation are supposed to impact the chance of occurrence, since they facilitate the displacement of people between municipalities. Also, pendular migration can increase the occurrence of flu since it favors the disease dissemination. As influenza virus spreads through human contact, population density and bus transportation are potential factors to increase the intensity of transmission. Also, the density of physicians is supposed to impact the intensity of the disease because reflect municipalities’ development and health workforce. Following the notation in 
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0202832.e013">Eq 4</xref>, 
 <italic>M</italic> = 7 covariates (
 <bold>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </bold>
 <sup>(
  <italic>m</italic>)
 </sup>) whose effects are fixed in space-time can impact the chance of occurrence: altitude, poverty rate, HDI, pendular migration and intercity bus, boat and plane transportation. According to 
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0202832.e004">Eq 1</xref>, 
 <italic>L</italic> = 6 covariates (
 <bold>
  <italic>x</italic>
 </bold>
 <sup>(
  <italic>l</italic>)
 </sup>) are assumed to impact the intensity of the disease: altitude, poverty rate, HDI, population density, density of physicians and city bus transportation. Analogously, 
 <italic>R</italic> = 
 <italic>P</italic> = 3 climatic covariates (
 <bold>
  <italic>w</italic>
 </bold>
 <sup>(
  <italic>r</italic>)
 </sup> and 
 <bold>
  <italic>w</italic>
 </bold>
 <sup>(
  <italic>p</italic>)
 </sup>) which effects are assumed to vary in time can impact both occurrence and intensity: precipitation, temperature and relative humidity. The Pearson correlation coefficients were calculated to test for multicollinearity for both (i.e., occurrence and intensity). Next, we tested for significance of sociodemographic covariates on the occurrence and intensity of influenza excluding correlated covariates. Finally, we tested for effects of conditional climatic variables (i.e., with sociodemographic covariates from the previous step).
</p>
