<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0105">Influenza is a serious infectious disease, which is very dangerous and deadly specifically in young one, elderly, and weak immunity patients. After the invention of modernized vaccinations, the mortality rate due to flu virus has been considerably decreased, but there are chances of recurrent infestation. Vaccination, accompanying the emergence of new antiinfluenza agents, is necessary to fight against seasonal and pervasive influenza strains. Nowadays, most importance is given to the designing of inhibition agents of influenza neuraminidase, which has proved itself as an appropriate medicine for the prophylaxis and influenza infections therapy. Till now only four medicines have been accepted by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) to cure influenza ailment, of which two of these drugs have grown resistance for influenza A strains and hence are not in the application. Therefore, there are a numerous chances in this area for further development of antiviral therapy. The two recent drug mechanisms for inhibition of the influenza virus are the M2 proton channel, which involves the procedure of liberating virus particles from an infected host cell, and the neuraminidase (NA) enzyme, which works on the basis of viral recognition and entry into a host cell. Currently, neuraminidase inhibitors are the most frequently used FDA-approved treatments for the influenza virus, which is applied effectively as they have not developed any resistance yet within the virus. Oseltamivir and zanamivir are the drugs that function by affecting the activity of neuraminidase (NA) protein of the virus. The neuraminidase enzyme operates on the basis of cleaving the host cell sialic acid residues with viral hemagglutinin, in turn releasing the new viruses to carry forward and infect other healthy cells. The viral neuraminidase catalytic site is highly specific for all influenza A and B viruses. Both the drugs oseltamivir and zanamivir serve as stable transformation state counterparts of the sialosyl cation. It is a very unstable transformation state complex in the enzymatic procedure of viral sialidase. The neuraminidase inhibitor drugs 1 and 2 are similar enough in structure to the sialosyl cation transition state complex. It allows them to attach tightly to the sialic acid active site and obstruct viral budding. However, constant development of drug-resistant influenza strain enhances the need of continuous researches on innovative technologies for the production of new drugs with improved antiviral mechanism, more safety, and enhanced tolerability.</p>
