<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Knowledge of filterable albeit seemingly noncultivable agents in feces that could cause transmissible diarrhea in humans led in part to the use of electron microscopy (EM) for the detection of viruses in stool samples. Although initially and highly focused on rotavirus and enteric adenovirus, several presumed viral particles were identified in the stool of ill patients.
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>56</sup>
 </xref> In most laboratories, the coronaviruses constituted a considerable minority of such EM findings for humans. In the veterinary field, coronaviruses were found by EM in enteric specimens of many animals.
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>57</sup>
 </xref> Reports of the EM findings of coronavirus suggested that the putative pathogen(s) could be identified in outbreak settings of diarrhea.
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>55</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>58</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0065" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>65</sup>
 </xref> Studies from Argentina and Saudi Arabia respectively found the virus structure in 1.1% and 6% of samples from children with diarrhea.
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>61</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>66</sup>
 </xref> The coronavirus morphotype was also found in outbreaks among neonates during manifestations of neonatal necrotizing enterocolitis.
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>55</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0065" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>65</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0067" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>67</sup>
 </xref> Patients with HIV infection, including some with a characteristic “wasting syndrome,” were also found to have coronaviruses in stool samples.
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0068" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>68</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0071" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>71</sup>
 </xref> Corroborative evidence for some of these findings was proposed by González et al
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0072" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>72</sup>
 </xref> who found presumed viral antigen in stool specimens by enzyme immunoassays. Clarke et al,
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0073" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>73</sup>
 </xref> who were among the leaders in this field at the time, suggested that enteric excretion of such viral coronavirus‐like particles could continue for months. By 1980, a review of international proceedings on the subject had already acknowledged that coronaviruses could cause enteric disease.
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0074" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>74</sup>
 </xref> Up to 70% of presumed enteric viral particles could be coronaviruses.
 <xref rid="jmv26066-bib-0075" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>75</sup>
 </xref> Confirmatory tests were generally unavailable at the time of the above publications, although immune electron microscopy from some studies suggested an infectious link given the use of convalescent patient sera.
</p>
