<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0008">Coronaviruses are large viruses that are enveloped, non-segmented, and positive-sense single-stranded RNA viruses. Coronaviruses can be divided into four generations containing 
 <italic>alpha, beta, delta</italic>, and 
 <italic>gamma</italic>. Among these generations, 
 <italic>alpha</italic> and 
 <italic>beta</italic> are human coronaviruses (HCoVs)
 <xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>2</sup>
 </xref> In late December 2019, new cases of pneumonia caused by a new coronavirus (2019-nCoV), new human-infecting 
 <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic>,
 <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> were introduced to the world from the Wuhan city of China. The most common clinical signs and symptoms of these patients were dry coughs, fever, dyspnea, and bilateral infiltration in chest CT. All these patients were associated with Wuhan's Huanan Seafood Wholesale Market which sells fish and other live animals such as bats, poultry, snakes, etc. The causative agent, new coronavirus, was first detected through a swab sample which was drawn from the throat of these patients.
 <xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref> This new coronavirus was subsequently named Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). Soon this disease, which called coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) by World Health Organization (WHO), promptly spreads around the world,
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref> and to date over 16.5 million cases have been diagnosed with COVID-19 and this disease became a pandemic. On the late January 2020 COVID-19 Chinese outbreak, were introduced as a public health emergency of international concern.
 <xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref> So although previously coronaviruses were considered as a potential cause of the common cold now we know that they are more than just the common cold!
 <xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
