<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>IAVs have two major surface proteins, HA and NA, and one minor surface protein, the M2 ion channel. During the infection cycle, the M2 ion channel is responsible for acidification of the viral interior, facilitating virus uncoating, and unloading of viral ribonucleoproteins (RNPs) into the host cytoplasm (Pinto et al., 
 <xref rid="B193" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>). The extracellular domain of M2 protein (M2e) consists of 24 amino acids, among which 9 N-terminal amino acids are completely conserved among all IAVs (H1–H18) and minor mutations are observed in the distal portion (Deng et al., 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2015a</xref>; Tsybalova et al., 
 <xref rid="B230" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Therefore, M2e is considered as a promising target for eliciting broadly reactive antibodies. However, due to poor immunogenicity of the small M2e region, UIV approaches targeting M2e required carriers, vectors, and adjuvants to enhance immune responses (Deng et al., 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2015a</xref>; Lee et al., 
 <xref rid="B150" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). One of the most efficient approaches is to make virus-like particles (VLPs) which display M2e on their surface. It has been shown that the hepatitis B virus core (HBc) protein fused with M2e self-assembled into VLPs that resemble wild type virus particles, expressing M2e on the surface (Neirynck et al., 
 <xref rid="B177" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>). Following this work, substantial efforts were made to improve the immunogenicity and protective efficacy of M2e-HBc VLP vaccine constructs. Major strategies include the use of multiple copies of M2e by tandem repeats (Ravin et al., 
 <xref rid="B200" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Sun et al., 
 <xref rid="B221" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Tsybalova et al., 
 <xref rid="B229" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) and combination with adjuvants such as cholera toxin A1 (De Filette et al., 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>) or B subunit of 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> heat labile enterotoxin (LTB) (Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="B255" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). The M2e-HBc VLP was further harnessed with T cell immunity by combining conserved T cell epitope from NP (Gao et al., 
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). The arginine-rich domain of HBc was shown to induce Th1-biased immune response of M2e-HBc VLP by binding to RNA, leading to improved protection (Ibanez et al., 
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Besides the HBc, M2e was fused with various coat or capsid proteins derived from other viruses including Malva mosaic virus (Leclerc et al., 
 <xref rid="B143" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), tobacco mosaic virus (Petukhova et al., 
 <xref rid="B191" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), Papaya mosaic virus (Denis et al., 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>), T7 bacteriophage (Hashemi et al., 
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), and RNA phage Qβ (Bessa et al., 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Moreover, the enveloped VLPs displayed M2e in a membrane-anchored manner by combining influenza matrix protein and transmembrane (TM) domain of HA fused into M2e. The Sf9 insect cells infected with baculoviral vectors expressing influenza M1 and M2e-TM of influenza HA produced influenza VLPs displaying much higher levels of M2e than the wild type virions (Kim et al., 
 <xref rid="B124" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B126" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Other vaccine types, including DNA vaccines or recombinant protein vaccines expressing M2e with various carriers to enhance immune responses, have also been advanced (Deng et al., 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2015a</xref>).
</p>
