<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Economic and social factors hold a great potential in understanding the changing patterns of climate and associated diseases [
 <xref rid="B10-ijerph-16-02799" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B77-ijerph-16-02799" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,
 <xref rid="B128-ijerph-16-02799" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. It has been found that certain regions and communities are more vulnerable because of their inability to respond appropriately to weather events posed by climate change [
 <xref rid="B129-ijerph-16-02799" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>,
 <xref rid="B130-ijerph-16-02799" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>]. The threat of vulnerability can have two aspects: First, measures taken to abate weather and climate-associated risks through awareness programs, figuring out different diseases and biosecurity. Second, availability or access to safe and clean drinking water, hygienic food, and proper sanitation [
 <xref rid="B131-ijerph-16-02799" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>,
 <xref rid="B132-ijerph-16-02799" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>]. Uncontrolled and unplanned urbanization in India has left many regions highly vulnerable to diseases in wake of climate change. The country has seen a dramatic increase in malaria and dengue cases in the past decades. [
 <xref rid="B133-ijerph-16-02799" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>,
 <xref rid="B134-ijerph-16-02799" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>]. Likewise, communities with limited access to clean water are more vulnerable to diarrhea, as the ailment occurs more frequently in water-scarce regions [
 <xref rid="B135-ijerph-16-02799" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>]. However, an exception can also be seen in well-developed societies who have access to advanced technologies and hold alternative resources to eradicate the challenges imposed by water scarcity. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02799-f003">Figure 3</xref> illustrates the outline of social impacts of climate change on livelihood, human society and infectious diseases.
</p>
