<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="f1-viruses-03-00379" position="float">
 <label>Figure 1.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Phylodynamic techniques. (
   <bold>a</bold>) A rooted molecular 
   <bold>phylogeny</bold> represents the evolutionary relationships between individual viral sequences, as represented by circles. These phylogenies 
   <italic>may</italic> reflect transmission chains, however sampling must be sufficient for them to do so, while 
   <bold>recombination</bold> may obscure ‘true’ relationships between viral sequences. (
   <bold>b</bold>) Simple 
   <bold>molecular clock</bold> theory, predicated on the neutral theory of molecular evolution [
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48-viruses-03-00379">48</xref>] assumes that mutation occurs at a constant rate over time, thus the time that has elapsed since a pair of virus strains diverged from a common ancestor may be quantified. Methods that account for differences in the evolutionary rates of different strains, and for variation in these rates through time, have been recently developed [
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49-viruses-03-00379">49</xref>]. Here variants represented by thick lines evolve much faster than those represented by thin lines. (
   <bold>c</bold>) Using a phylogeographic approach, the location at which a sequence was sampled may be mapped onto the viral phylogeny and the likely spreading trajectory of the virus inferred. While parsimony approaches have been popular, powerful Bayesian methods that account for uncertainty of dispersal process and historical phylogeny have been developed to reconstruct viral dispersal events [
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44-viruses-03-00379">44</xref>]. Crosses on the phylogeny represent such viral dispersal events, in this example. (
   <bold>d</bold>) Coalescent theory provides the basis for many phylodynamic approaches. Here, circles on the same row represent temporally simultaneous infections. Working back from sampled infections (red circles), lineages can be traced back to the most recent common ancestor (black circle) via hypothetical, unsampled ancestors (grey circles). The time it takes for sampled lineages to coalesce is dependent on a variety of variables (
   <italic>i.e.</italic>, viral 
   <bold>effective population size</bold>, 
   <bold>population structure</bold>, selection, stochastic infection die-out and recombination). A variety of methods are available to test for selection and recombination. Figure and legend adapted with permission from Macmillan Publishers Ltd: Nature (Pybus, O.G., Rambaut, A. Evolutionary analysis of the dynamics of viral infectious disease), copyright (2009) [
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50-viruses-03-00379">50</xref>].
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="viruses-03-00379f1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
