<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0380">Fluorescence methods including FRET, fluorescence polarization or intensity endpoint measurement, and lifetime imaging of fluorescence (
 <xref rid="bb1045" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2008</xref>) including fluorescence biosensors (
 <xref rid="bb1870" ref-type="bibr">Zhang and Allen, 2007</xref>) have been reviewed elsewhere. Sulfonamido-oxine labeled peptides can be used as chromophores that bind Mg
 <sup>2 +</sup> upon phosphorylation and emit chelation-enhanced fluorescence (
 <xref rid="bb0425" ref-type="bibr">Devkota et al., 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb1115" ref-type="bibr">Luković et al., 2008</xref>). Kinase-catalyzed phosphorylation of fluorescent peptides promotes their binding to metal-coated nanoparticles, which decreases their mobility and enhances measurable fluorescence polarization (
 <xref rid="bb0990" ref-type="bibr">Lea and Simeonov, 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb1590" ref-type="bibr">Sportsman et al., 2004</xref>). TbIII complexes, in which phosphotyrosine induces fluorescence emission (
 <xref rid="bb1775" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2015a</xref>), may be used to evaluate protein tyrosine kinase activity (
 <xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">Akiba et al., 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb1635" ref-type="bibr">Sumaoka et al., 2016</xref>). Fluorescence polarization methods also can be useful for drug screening [reviewed in (
 <xref rid="bb0675" ref-type="bibr">Hall et al., 2016</xref>)]. Other alternatives are immunochemical methods that use antibodies specific to the phosphorylated amino acids, such as phosphotyrosine (
 <xref rid="bb1030" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2001</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb1850" ref-type="bibr">Youngren et al., 1997</xref>) or phosphoserine/phosphothreonine. These antibodies can be used to detect protein/peptide phosphorylation by Western blotting, ELISA, or immunoprecipitation of phosphorylated proteins for further mass spectrometry-based analysis (
 <xref rid="bb0625" ref-type="bibr">Grønborg et al., 2002</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb1875" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2002</xref>). An elegant approach that limits the false-positive hits in screening of specific kinase inhibitors is based on an 
 <italic>in situ</italic> proximity ligation assay using both an antibody against the target protein and an anti-phosphotyrosine antibody (
 <xref rid="bb1015" ref-type="bibr">Leuchowius et al., 2010</xref>). Both antibodies are coupled with oligonucleotides, which when brought together due to antibody binding, can be enzymatically ligated and replicated through rolling circle amplification to form a long linear tandem repeat of sequences detectable by a complementary fluorescent oligonucleotide.
</p>
