<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0040">In 1997, cases of human infection with a highly pathogenic avian influenza A virus (H5N1) were reported in Hong Kong 
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. Although this outbreak in humans was contained by the depopulation of all poultry in Hong Kong in December 1997, subsequent surveillance in Hong Kong on imported poultry revealed that the virus continued to circulate in the wider region. The virus spread to multiple Asian countries, and after 2005, was spread by wild bird migration to South Asia, the Middle East and Africa. Up to now the virus has caused thousands of poultry outbreaks and 860 zoonotic infections have been reported, resulting in 454 deaths (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/influenza/human_animal_interface/2018_01_25_tableH5N1.pdf?ua=1" id="interref0010" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.who.int/influenza/human_animal_interface/2018_01_25_tableH5N1.pdf?ua=1</ext-link>). Although no diagnoses of human H5N1 infection has been reported in Taiwan at the time of writing this review, this avian influenza virus is a constant threat to public health. Several imported cases of infection with another avian influenza A virus (H7N9) in humans have been reported in Taiwan since 2013 
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. Infection with the avian H7N9 virus in humans with severe respiratory complications was first reported in China in 2013 
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. According to information updated in February 2018 from the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations, 1625 human cases of H7N9 infection have been confirmed, including 621 fatalities (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/ag/againfo/programmes/en/empres/h7n9/situation_update.html)" id="intref0020" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.fao.org/ag/againfo/programmes/en/empres/h7n9/situation_update.html</ext-link>). Because the avian H7N9 virus causes severe disease in humans, the Taiwanese government has undertaken considerable efforts to prevent the virus from being imported and spread throughout the islands. Additionally, the government has established surveillance systems and early diagnostic technology to monitor the avian influenza viruses throughout Taiwan.
</p>
