<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0245">Prior studies of MERS-CoV have acknowledged that surveillance bias can complicate the inference of transmission parameters (
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">Breban et al., 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">Cauchemez et al., 2014</xref>). However, rather than accepting the possibility of surveillance bias as a limitation of our study, our analysis has explicitly incorporated its potential impact, while also considering an alternative ‘transmission bias’ scenario where observations are taken at face value. When we incorporate the possibility that less severe index cases are unobserved, the range of possible reproduction numbers in our study and previously published models (
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">Breban et al., 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">Cauchemez et al., 2014</xref>) shifts to smaller values (
 <xref rid="fig0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>). Since convergence of our model to data is high in both the ‘surveillance bias’ scenario and ‘differential transmission’ scenarios, further information is needed to tease out the extent to which observation bias operated in 2013 and beyond. For example, targeted serological studies in communities where index cases have been reported could shed light on the fraction of index cases that may be unobserved. Further, it would be helpful to know more about the MERS-CoV surveillance process in Saudi Arabia, and determine whether individual cases were detected because they self-reported to a health center or were actively discovered via contact tracing of a severe case. More information on standards of clinical practice would also be helpful, such as the probability that a patient who presents with milder symptoms to a health care facility would be diagnosed with MERS-CoV. Ancillary data from laboratories would also be helpful such as the overall number of samples that were tested for MERS-CoV and their spatio-temporal distribution.
</p>
