<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0250">A particular concern for the epidemic potential of MERS-CoV is that the virus shares features of the related coronavirus that caused outbreaks of severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) in 2003, spanning several countries and continents (
 <xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">Ksiazek et al., 2003</xref>). Both MERS-CoV and SARS viruses can invade the lower respiratory tract and cause severe pneumonia (
 <xref rid="bib0205" ref-type="bibr">de Wit et al., 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0210" ref-type="bibr">Franks et al., 2003</xref>). Both infections are considered severe, especially among older adults with underlying medical conditions (
 <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">Assiri et al., 2013b</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0215" ref-type="bibr">Donnelly et al., 2003</xref>). Our findings indicate that the transmissibility MERS-CoV in secondary cases remained well below the epidemic threshold in Saudi Arabia in 2013, ensuring that all human-to-human transmission chains go extinct (
 <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">Ferguson et al., 2004</xref>). At the time of this writing, there was not enough resolution in MERS-CoV phylogenetic data to assess whether transmission was only endemic in the animal reservoir or could persist in humans (
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">Cauchemez et al., 2014</xref>). Based on our synthesis of epidemiological data and existing models, we argue that the transmission potential of MERS-CoV is currently low based on the progression of the 2013 outbreak, and on the same order as that of other stage III viral zoonoses such as influenza A/H5N1, monkeypox or Nipah virus, although much higher than that of influenza A/H7N9 (
 <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">Blumberg and Lloyd-Smith, 2013a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">Blumberg and Lloyd-Smith, 2013b</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0220" ref-type="bibr">Chowell et al., 2013</xref>). In contrast, the reproduction number for SARS was estimated to be ∼2–3 during the pre-intervention period (
 <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">Riley et al., 2003</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr">Lipsitch et al., 2003</xref>). Although our study cannot speak to the dynamics of the recent resurgence of cases in Spring 2014, it is reassuring that disease transmission remained limited to the Arabian Peninsula throughout June 2014. Indeed, chains of transmission initiated by infected travelers returning to Europe, Africa, Asia and North America have remained extremely short (
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">Cauchemez et al., 2014</xref>).
</p>
