<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0110">Both CQ and HCQ have substantial (EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 5.47 and 0.72 μM, respectively) in vitro activity against SARS-CoV-2.
 <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>77</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>78</sup>
 </xref> A publication of a 30-patient RCT of HCQ in China reported no difference in time to viral clearance, body temperature, or radiological progression compared to conventional treatment (P&gt;.05).
 <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>79</sup>
 </xref> An article describing a 150-patient open-label RCT also reported no difference in viral clearance through 28 days between patients treated with HCQ and those treated with standard of care (P=0.34).
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>80</sup>
 </xref> No difference in mortality, ICU admission, or ventilation rates was observed with HCQ treatment in retrospective analyses of 368 US patients (P&gt;.05)
 <xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>81</sup>
 </xref> and 191 French patients (hazard ratio, 0.9, 95% confidence interval, 0.4 to 2.1)
 <xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>82</sup>
 </xref> who received HCQ or HCQ added to azithromycin or who were unexposed to HCQ. Likewise, in a 1376-patient observational study at a single hospital and a 1438-patient multicenter retrospective analysis in New York, there was no significant association between HCQ use and intubation or death (hazard ratio, 1.04, 95% confidence interval, 0.82 to 1.32)
 <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>83</sup>
 </xref> or HCQ and azithromycin use and mortality.
 <xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>84</sup>
 </xref> The first double-blind, RCT of postexposure prophylactic HCQ treatment found no apparent decrease in incidence between treatment and placebo groups (11.8% vs 14.3%; P=.35) in 821 participants at a moderate or high risk of exposure to COVID-19.
 <xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>85</sup>
 </xref> In an open-label nonrandomized trial in 36 French patients, HCQ treatment virologically cured 57% of patients (100% of patients when used in conjunction with azithromycin) within 6 days of treatment compared with 12.5% of control patients (P&lt;.001).
 <xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>86</sup>
 </xref> Although a follow-up study of azithromycin combined with HCQ in 80 additional French patients with COVID-19 confirmed considerable reductions in viral load and improved clinical outcomes,
 <xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>87</sup>
 </xref> the first study has been criticized for a lack of randomization, patients dropped from analysis, and the chosen thresholds for determining viral presence.
 <xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>88</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>89</sup>
 </xref> A statement from the International Society of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy indicated that the article did not meet their expected standards.
 <xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>90</sup>
 </xref> Interestingly, a separate team’s efforts to replicate viral clearance in a 12-patient case series using HCQ/azithromycin combination therapy found that only 20% of patients using this treatment tested negative for SARS-CoV-2 at days 5 to 6 after treatment.
 <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>91</sup>
 </xref> However, a retrospective analysis of 1061 patients (95% with mild disease) by the same group whose studies have been questioned revealed a good clinical outcome (no death, hospitalization for ≥10 days, viral shedding, or transfer to the ICU) in 91.7% of patients and mortality in 0.9%.
 <xref rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>92</sup>
 </xref> A randomized trial of 22 patients comparing CQ with LPV/RTV,
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>40</sup>
 </xref> a retrospective analysis of 48 patients receiving HCQ compared with 502 patients receiving standard therapy,
 <xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>93</sup>
 </xref> and a non–peer-reviewed preprint describing a double-blind RCT of HCQ therapy in 62 patients with mild disease also seem to indicate some benefit in time to clinical recovery or mortality from CQ or HCQ treatment.
 <xref rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>94</sup>
 </xref> Of note, one large study suggesting treatment with CQ or HCQ increases risk of in-hospital mortality was retracted when a full audit of the primary dataset could not be completed.
 <xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>95</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
