<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While the period of peak mosquito feeding on each host also corresponds to an increase in population size of each species (births/hatching of young), our data do not support the hypothesis that seasonal patterns of host use are driven by increases in host abundance alone. In white-tailed deer, the population increases by approximately two-fold during the period of birthing 
 <xref rid="pone.0017681-Saalfeld1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, yet the proportion of bloodmeals derived from deer increases by more than five-fold between May (when deer are fed upon least) and September (maximal feeding on deer). In addition, the increase in deer abundance is short-lived, as only about one to two thirds of fawns survive the first month of life, on average 
 <xref rid="pone.0017681-Saalfeld1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0017681-Linnell1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. However, deer continue to be the most important host for mosquitoes through the end of September, at which time mosquito activity abruptly declines. A slight decrease in the proportion of blood meals from deer occurs in late September (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017681-g001">Fig 1a</xref>) which may correspond to maturation and mobility of fawns, decreasing their susceptibility to attacking mosquitoes. Great blue herons and yellow-crowned night herons (both adults and recently fledged birds) continue to occupy and forage at the site after the nesting period, yet the proportion of blood meals from herons declines sharply after the nesting period. A noticeable increase in bloodmeals derived from great blue herons was observed in September, but does not correspond to any increase in heron abundance, since no nesting occurs during this period. However, post-reproductive molting by great blue herons peaks in September and October 
 <xref rid="pone.0017681-Pyle1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, and may account for the apparent increase in late-season feeding on this host by mosquitoes 
 <xref rid="pone.0017681-Blackmore1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Most telling is the increase in frog-feeding during the calling season. In frogs, increased population density associated with reproduction is not realized until months later, when aquatic tadpoles transform and become available to mosquitoes. The increased incidence of frog blood meals that we document during times of increased calling of male frogs occurs when frog abundance is generally unchanged except for the redistribution of adults during reproduction. Although the increase in abundance of each host during periods of hatching/birthing likely contributes to increased host use during the reproductive phase, our data and those of other studies 
 <xref rid="pone.0017681-Edman1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0017681-Tempelis1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref> suggest that host abundance alone cannot explain seasonal patterns of host use.
</p>
