<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Fruit bats are known to feed on a wide range of crops and they are often considered pests due to feeding in commercial orchards, although their importance in pollination is recognized [
 <xref rid="B110-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,
 <xref rid="B111-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. A study on a vineyard in India found the old world fruit bat 
 <italic>C. sphinx</italic> was responsible for &gt;90% damage to crops at the periphery of the vineyard [
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. As such, it is common practice to protect commercial crops through the use of measures such as netting or shooting; one study on a stone fruit orchard in Sydney, Australia, consisting of four hectares of nectarine trees, where shooting was known to occur in order to protect the orchard, found a total of 164 dead or injured flying foxes over 14 days at the time when the nectarine crop was ripening and being harvested [
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. NiV-Malaysia was isolated from fruit on Tioman island, and contamination of fruit by bats is thought to be a potential route for the infection of pigs during the Malaysian NiV outbreak [
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. A number of outbreaks in Bangladesh have been linked with consumption of date palm sap [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], with the sap likely being contaminated with bat urine or saliva. While the date palm sap is the only identified foodborne source of human NiV infection in Bangladesh, bats could potentially have contact with, and contaminate with saliva or urine, any unprotected fruit grown in the region. While unlikely, if these crops are exported, there could be a risk of virus introduction into the EU. Transport times can be less than 24 hours by air travel, not long enough to allow significant decay of the virus. This route is less likely for MARV as, to date, it has not been detected in the faeces or urine of either experimentally or naturally infected 
 <italic>R. aegyptiacus</italic> bats [
 <xref rid="B56-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>].
</p>
