<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Until now, although there have been few studies on the use of CDV, particularly genetic engineering CDV strains, as an oncolytic virus for canine cancer patients compared with the advanced progress of human virotherapy in clinical trials, the high similarity between human and canine cancers, including colorectal cancer, fibrosarcoma, osteosarcoma, and soft tissue sarcoma [
 <xref rid="B80-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>,
 <xref rid="B81-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,
 <xref rid="B82-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>,
 <xref rid="B83-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>,
 <xref rid="B84-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>,
 <xref rid="B85-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>,
 <xref rid="B86-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>,
 <xref rid="B87-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>] could help translate cases of successful oncolytic virotherapy from canine to humans and the reverse in a two-way street toward the development of novel antitumor drugs. Despite many similarities between CDV and MeV, including viral tropism, and vaccine-induced host immune responses, both viruses differ significantly in their potential to induce viral invasion of the CNS of hosts, as well as neuropathological lesions via nectin-4-expression-dependent infection in canine brains [
 <xref rid="B41-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. This difference highlights the fact that CDV as an oncolytic virus could exert the potential ability of neurocytoma virotherapy in canine patients. In addition, CDV infecting a much broader host range, including many carnivore species has been shown to be further opposed to MeV representing a strictly human pathogen. Thus, CDV could not only allow for the extrapolation of possible treatment schemes in veterinary medicine, but also render the canine pathogen an interesting, translational model for various human tumors. The application of oncolytic CDV for human cancers could also avoid the major issue in regard to MeV-based therapeutics: the high prevalence of anti-MeV neutralizing antibodies in the vaccine-immunized population.
</p>
