<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0050">Christian Daugthon [
 <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], former EPA scientist and pioneer on the WBE concept reported about the urgency among researchers for the need to develop Waste Based Epidemiology methods not just for COVID-19, but also for future epidemics. Basic principle is that sewage can be used as indicator of the scale of infection and it will boost worldwide attention and interest in WBE. Daughton and many others we do believe that collective efforts of the WBE community need to be granted as recognition that they deserve in addressing ongoing, urgent needs of public health. The first data detecting COVID-19 in sewage from the Netherlands [
 <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], Australia [
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] and Paris, France [
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] supports this idea of using WBE to reveal the scale of COVID-19 outbreak. Several other papers [
 <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>] reported the importance to detect viruses in untreated wastewater samples and to develop paper sensor devices to measure directly in wastewaters.. These measurements were carried out using PCR, the most widely used method for COVID-19 detection. Paper-based devices are powerful and cheap tools for the rapid diagnosis of pathogens and determination infection of transmission [
 <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. It contains different functional areas printed with a wax printer into a cheap paper material. The whole testing process using this paper-based device is very fast and sensitive, which overcomes the limitation of PCR and it was used for a variety of infections such as malaria and several pathogens [
 <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].
</p>
