<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Once the virus binds to the target cell, the S protein is cleaved by cellular proteases into the S1 and S2 subunits (priming), and also upstream of the fusion peptide (S2’ cleavage site). The serine protease TMPRSS2, which is strongly expressed in lung cells, can cleave a variety of CoV S proteins,
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref> and seems to play a key role in virus entry.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref> Camostat mesylate, a TMPRSS2 inhibitor approved for clinical use, blocks S protein processing in vitro.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0092" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>92</sup>
 </xref> Moreover, camostat mesylate and its derivative nafamostat mesylate can inhibit (in the nM to μM range) the entry of vesicular stomatitis virus pseudotypes carrying the SARS‐CoV‐2 S protein in different cell types that overexpress TMPRSS2.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0092" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>92</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0104" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>104</sup>
 </xref> This observation suggests that inhibition of S protein priming blocks ACE2‐mediated entry. However, the inhibition observed with camostat mesylate and nafamostat mesylate in VeroE6 cells infected by SARS‐CoV‐2 is lower and probably not enough for a therapeutic utilization of camostat mesylate. The picture is further complicated because other cellular proteases could be implicated in S protein processing. Indeed, cathepsin L
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0105" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>105</sup>
 </xref> and furin
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref> might be involved in S protein activation, depending on the infected cell type. Consequently, inhibitors of these different enzymes might limit virus propagation in some cell types, but their efficacy in the clinic could be limited. Perhaps, the best option is to combine furin and TMPRSS2 inhibitors to limit virus propagation.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
