<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Interestingly, several compounds identified in different screens of infected cells are implicated in endosomal acidification.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>39</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0100" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>100</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0101" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>101</sup>
 </xref> Increasing the endosomal pH might limit viral/endosomal membrane fusion, which is necessary for the release of the viral genome into the cytoplasm of the host cell. Two recent studies showed that proton pump inhibitors, such as omeprazole and vonoprazan, reduce the infection of cells by SARS‐CoV‐2.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>39</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0064" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>64</sup>
 </xref> In addition, chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine (HCQ), which have been extensively used for the treatment of malaria with known safety and efficacy, also limit acidification of endosomes, Golgi vesicles, and lysosomes.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0106" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>106</sup>
 </xref> These molecules significantly reduce SARS‐CoV and SARS‐CoV‐2 infection in vitro.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>48</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0093" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>93</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0094" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>94</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0095" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>95</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0106" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>106</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0107" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>107</sup>
 </xref> However, a recent study reported that HCQ does not have any effect on viral load levels and does not protect macaques against SARS‐CoV infection.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0108" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>108</sup>
 </xref> Moreover, chloroquine derivatives have immunosuppressive effects and inhibit the activation of innate immune receptors, such as toll‐like receptors
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0109" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>109</sup>
 </xref> and have been associated with some adverse cardiac effects. Many clinical studies are currently testing these molecules,
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0097" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>97</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0098" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>98</sup>
 </xref> and their initial results are controversial.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0110" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>110</sup>
 </xref> Randomized, double‐blind studies with a larger number of patients should bring robust conclusions. Recent in vitro studies have also suggested the therapeutic effect of the HCQ‐azithromycin combination.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0098" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>98</sup>
 </xref> Azithromycin is an antibiotic that has also antiviral activity in respiratory viral infections.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0111" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>111</sup>
 </xref> Interestingly, the MoA of azithromycin and HCQ may be related to the modulation of the endosomal and trans‐Golgi network pH.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0112" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>112</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0113" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>113</sup>
 </xref> In addition, azithromycin plays a role in regulating interleukin production that might help to control the immune response and prevent symptom worsening.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0114" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>114</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0115" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>115</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0116" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>116</sup>
 </xref> Azithromycin may also inhibit viral invasion by interfering with the CD147‐mediated recognition mechanism.
 <xref rid="rmv2143-bib-0117" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>117</sup>
 </xref> Nevertheless, both the FDA and the World Health Organization (WHO) have removed their support for the use of HCQ and chloroquine for COVID‐19, consequently the status of ongoing trials must be questioned.
</p>
