<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>WNV transmission and spread is significantly influenced by climatic conditions, e.g., shaping phenology and abundance of the vector. Temperature is one of the most important factors directly affecting the EIP in different mosquito vector species [
 <xref rid="B14-viruses-12-00448" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. High daily average temperatures (&gt; 20 °C) over several days are required to allow for WNV transmission, which is correlated to the main distribution of WNV in south-eastern Europe. This also matches the spatial pattern of WNV in Germany. The summers in 2018 and 2019 were both characterized by extraordinarily high temperatures allowing low EIP values. The area in central-eastern Germany as the main focus of WNV circulation in both years was characterized by shorter EIP compared to previous years and most other areas in Germany [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-12-00448" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Furthermore, these areas in Germany are directly neighboring countries reporting several years of WNV circulation (e.g., Czech Republic), leading to a high risk of short distance introductions e.g., by infected birds. The analysis also indicated that the areas along the Upper Rhine Valley in south-west Germany had a high suitability for WNV circulation, but no WNV activity was observed in all previous surveillance programs [
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-12-00448" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-12-00448" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-viruses-12-00448" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-viruses-12-00448" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Most likely, no WNV introduction and circulation occurred yet, which underpins the thesis of the entries over short distances. Future studies are needed to understand if the virus did not yet spread to this area or if there are other factors reducing the risk of virus circulation (e.g., distribution of suitable vector or host species). The phylogenetic analyses indicated that Germany experienced at least six distinct WNV introduction events, with Austria and Czech Republic as possible origin for the progenitors of the German WNV epizootic strain variants. The majority of these strains clustered together into a distinct subclade (EGC). 
</p>
