<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza A, belonging to the family 
 <italic>Orthomyxoviridae</italic>, causes contagious human respiratory diseases in pandemics and seasonal or zoonotic epidemics. Its genome is composed of eight negative-stranded RNA segments, each of which is encapsidated with nucleoprotein (NP) through interactions with subunits of the viral polymerase (polymerase basic protein 1 [PB1], PB2, and polymerase acidic protein [PA]) to generate viral ribonucleoproteins (vRNPs) [
 <xref rid="B1-viruses-12-00581" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-viruses-12-00581" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The viral lipid bilayer envelope bears spikes consisting of major glycoproteins, hemagglutinin (HA) and neuraminidase (NA), which determine the serologic and antigenic properties of viral strains, along with a relatively small population of matrix protein 2 (M2). Underneath the membrane, the matrix protein 1 (M1) layer selectively packages eight different vRNPs arranged in the “1 + 7” pattern [
 <xref rid="B3-viruses-12-00581" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Viral infectivity depends on the function of homotrimeric HA at the initial step of the viral life cycle, making this surface protein attractive as an antiviral target. Each HA monomer is composed of two disulfide-linked polypeptides, HA1 and HA2, produced by proteolytic cleavage of the HA0 precursor. The globular head domain of HA, accounting for most parts of HA1, recognizes α-2,3- or α-2,6-linked sialic acid receptors on host cells prior to viral internalization into the endosome [
 <xref rid="B4-viruses-12-00581" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-viruses-12-00581" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Binding of the virus to the receptor triggers endocytosis. At the acidic environment of endosomes (pH 5.0–6.0), the M2 proton channel opens to facilitate proton transport into the viral interior, causing vRNPs to dissociate from the inner M1 layer, and HA undergoes structural rearrangements, resulting in exposure of the HA2 fusion peptide from a hidden hydrophobic pocket and its subsequent insertion into the endosomal membrane [
 <xref rid="B6-viruses-12-00581" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-viruses-12-00581" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. These simultaneous events create a route for the escape of vRNPs into the cytoplasm, followed by their migration to the nucleus, mediated by nuclear localization signals (NLSs) within NP [
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-12-00581" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], where viral RNA replication and transcription occurs.
</p>
