<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">Viral fusion refers to fusion of the viral membrane and host cell membrane, resulting in the release of the viral genome into the host cell. Cleavage of the SARS-CoV-2 S1 and S2 subunits is the basis of fusion. The S protein is cleaved into two parts, the S1 subunit and S2 subunit, by host proteases, and the subunits exist in a noncovalent form until viral fusion occurs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Researchers have found that the specific furin cleavage site is located in the cleavage site of SARS-CoV-2 but not in other SARS-like CoVs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Mutation of the cleavage site in SARS-CoV-2 or SARS-like CoVs has revealed that the S protein of SARS-CoV-2 exists in an uncleaved state but that the others are mainly in a cleaved state. SARS-CoV-2 S has multiple furin cleavage sites, which increases the probability of being cleaved by furin-like proteases and thereby enhances its infectivity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. The furin-like cleavage domain is also present in highly pathogenic influenza virus and is related to its pathogenicity, as observed in the avian influenza outbreak in Hong Kong in 1997 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. In addition, host cell proteases such as TMPRSS2 are essential for S protein priming, and they have been shown to be activated in the entry of SARS-CoV and influenza A virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Another host cell protease that has been proven to cleave viral S protein is trypsin [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. In summary, the S protein of SARS-CoV-2 is similar to that of SARS-CoV, and host cell proteases are essential for promoting S protein cleavage of both SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV. The presence of a specific furin cleavage site on SARS-CoV-2 S might be one reason that SARS-CoV-2 is more contagious than SARS-CoV.
</p>
