<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza viruses fall into the Orthomyxoviridae family, which consists of six genera, 
 <italic>Influenzavirus A, Influenzavirus B, Influenzavirus C, Thogotovirus, Isavirus</italic>, and 
 <italic>Quarajavirus</italic>, classified by serological cross reactivity to the nucleoprotein and matrix proteins. Of the three types of influenza viruses, Influenza A has the most genetic variation and the broadest host range.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr8-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
 </sup> Influenza viruses are further categorized into subtypes by their hemagglutinin (HA) and neuraminidase (NA) genes: as of now, there are 18 HA and 11 NA types. Phylogenetic analyses of viral genes have indicated that these viruses have a long-established history of infections in avian hosts. The nomenclature system for AIVs was established by WHO, the World Organisation for Animal Health, and the FAO.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr9-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
 </sup> Phylogenetic analysis is performed on HA sequences that have evolved from A/goose/Guangdong/1996 H5N1 virus. Viruses are grouped into virus clades based on their phylogenetic characterization and sequence homology of the HA gene.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr9-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
 </sup> The average percentage pairwise nucleotide distances between clades is greater than 1.5% and is less than 1.5% within clades.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr9-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
 </sup> As these viruses evolve through time, new subclades emerge. Influenza A viruses contain negative-sense, single-stranded segmented genomes that encode for 10 viral proteins: HA, NA, M1, M2, NP, NS1, NEP, PB1, PB2, and PA.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr10-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
 </sup> The 10 viral proteins are encoded by 8 segmented genomic strands,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr11-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
 </sup> which are coated with NP, have a double-helical hairpin structure, and carry one polymerase heterotrimer consisting of PB1, PB2, and PA (viral ribonucleoprotein particles [vRNPs]).
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr12-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr13-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
