<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In contrast to measles and Ebola, transmitted via airborne and contact routes respectively, HIV is transmitted through contact with infected body fluids. Therefore, risk factors for HIV transmission are predominantly of a behavioral nature. While HIV is not as directly impacted by mobility as measles and Ebola, mobility and migration is often linked with behavioral mechanisms that include increased risk taking, which can impact HIV transmission [
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-12-00067" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. For example, participation in injection drug-use [
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-12-00067" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], transactional sex [
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-12-00067" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], and rape [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-12-00067" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] are more common among mobile populations, all of which are risks for HIV transmission. Furthermore, the latency period before clinical symptoms also allows a greater window of travel while infectious. Human migration from the displacement and movement of large refugee populations arising from areas of conflict, war, or economic hardship, also can increase risk of HIV transmission and acquisition [
 <xref rid="B5-viruses-12-00067" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-viruses-12-00067" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-viruses-12-00067" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-12-00067" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Globalization itself has also historically been shown to play a crucial role in the spread and rate of infectious diseases among different populations [
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-12-00067" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-12-00067" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In the United States, efforts focused on prevention of disease transmission and dissemination have produced substantial successes. Incident cases of HIV have been reduced through advancements in HIV testing technologies and implementation of evidence-based behavioral change interventions, surveillance of blood supply, condom use, needle exchange programs, and pre-exposure prophylaxis, among other preventive interventions [
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-12-00067" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Despite efforts towards control, prevention, and treatment methods for HIV through the implementation of international mechanisms and funds directed towards lower-income countries, HIV incidence continues to be unacceptably high [
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-12-00067" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].
</p>
