<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The open reading frame on the picornavirus genome encodes a very large continuous protein, which comprises more than 2,100 amino acids in all viruses. Its sequence contains all proteins and functions that are necessary for a successful infection process. The arrangement of the proteins on the precursor polypeptide is identical in all picornaviruses (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig00142" ref-type="fig">14.2</xref>). The polyprotein is subdivided into three regions and the proteins, which arise by proteolytic cleavage, are designated with capital letters according to the respective regions of the polyprotein. The amino-terminal region contains the precursor sequences of the viral capsid proteins (1A–1D); the non-structural proteins 2A–2C, which play an important role in the adaptation of the virus to the cellular metabolism, are located in the middle of the polyprotein. Moreover, enzymatically active and further non-structural proteins (3A–3D) are generated from the carboxy-terminal regions. Usually, 11 viral proteins are generated from the precursor polyprotein. In aphthoviruses, erboviruses, kobuviruses, teschoviruses and cardioviruses, a short leader protein (L protein) is found at the amino terminus, which in mengovirus comprises 67 amino acids. In FMD virus, the L protein encompasses 205 amino acids and possesses proteolytic activity. In such cases the polyprotein does not begin with the sequences of the structural proteins, but begins with the L protein. In most picornaviruses, an amino acid sequence harbouring proteolytic activity (2A protease) is located immediately downstream of the region for the structural proteins. The 2A protease develops its proteolytic activity cotranslationally. In enteroviruses and rhinoviruses the amino acid chain between the end of the capsid proteins and the beginning of the 2A protease undergoes autocatalytic cleavage. The amino-terminal region of the precursor protein is excised from the nascent, not yet completely translated carboxy-terminal moiety, generating the protomer, the precursor of structural proteins. In aphthoviruses, erboviruses and cardioviruses, the autocatalytic cleavage reaction exerted by the 2A protease occurs not upstream but immediately downstream of its own amino acid sequences, thus leading to a polypeptide product that contains both the protomer and the 2A protease. In hepatoviruses and parechoviruses, the 2A protein does not function as a protease during the early steps of the infection cycle; instead, it develops its proteolytic activity in a late phase during the formation of new capsids. In this case, the cleavage of the structural protein moiety is performed by the 3C protease at the transition site between domains 2A and 2B. The properties and functions of all proteins that arise by cleavage of the polyprotein are summarized in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab00143" ref-type="table">14.3</xref>. 
</p>
