<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0020">
 <label>Table 4</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Impacts of CCR5Δ32 on HBV infection.</p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text id="at0100">Table 4</alt-text>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th align="left">Population</th>
    <th align="left">Sample</th>
    <th align="left">Main findings</th>
    <th align="left">References</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Korean</td>
    <td align="left">349 chronic HBV-infected individuals; 243 individuals with spontaneous recover; 106 non-infected individuals</td>
    <td align="left">The CCR5Δ32 allele was not found in any studied individual</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Ahn et al. (2006)</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Information not available</td>
    <td align="left">214 chronic HBV-infected individuals; 408 non-infected individuals</td>
    <td align="left">The CCR5Δ32 heterozygous genotype was associated with chronic HBV infection; The CCR5Δ32 wild-type allele was associated with severe liver disease when analyzed in combination with other genetic variants (a/a-T/T-Wt/Wt model from VDR-Apa1/Taq1/CCR5Δ32 polymorphisms)</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib1430" ref-type="bibr">Suneetha et al. (2006)</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">American</td>
    <td align="left">190 individuals with persistent HBV infection; 336 individuals with infection recover</td>
    <td align="left">The CCR5Δ32 allele was associated with recovery from the infection</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib1480" ref-type="bibr">Thio et al. (2007)</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">American</td>
    <td align="left">181 individuals with persistent HBV infection; 316 individuals with infection recover</td>
    <td align="left">Infection recovery was associated with an epistatic interaction between the CCR5Δ32 and the 
     <italic>RANTES</italic>-403A polymorphism
    </td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib1485" ref-type="bibr">Thio et al. (2008)</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Iranian</td>
    <td align="left">57 individuals with occult HBV infection; 100 non-infected individuals</td>
    <td align="left">The CCR5Δ32 heterozygous genotype was found in 3 controls and no individuals with occult HBV infection carried the allele (small sample size study); No association between the CCR5Δ32 and occult HBV infection</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">Arababadi et al. (2010)</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Chinese</td>
    <td align="left">185 individuals who underwent liver transplantation due to HBV-related disease</td>
    <td align="left">The CCR5Δ32 allele was not found in any studied individual</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0870" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. (2011)</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Iranian</td>
    <td align="left">60 chronic HBV-infected individuals; 60 non-infected individuals</td>
    <td align="left">The CCR5Δ32 heterozygous genotype was found in 3 controls and no infected individual carried the allele (small sample size study); No association between the CCR5Δ32 and HBV infection</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0740" ref-type="bibr">Khorramdelazad et al. (2013)</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Iranian</td>
    <td align="left">357 HBV-infected individuals; 455 non-infected individuals</td>
    <td align="left">The CCR5Δ32 was associated with protection against HBV infection</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">Abdolmohammadi et al. (2016)</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Iranian</td>
    <td align="left">60 chronic HBV-infected individuals; 120 individuals with infection recover</td>
    <td align="left">The CCR5Δ32 heterozygous genotype was found in 1 individual with infection recover and no HBV-infected individual carried the allele (small sample size study); No association between the CCR5Δ32 and HBV infection</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib1250" ref-type="bibr">Safari et al. (2017)</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Chinese</td>
    <td align="left">263 HBV-infected individuals; 141 non-infected individuals</td>
    <td align="left">No association between the CCR5Δ32 and HBV infection</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib1675" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al. (2018)</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Iranian</td>
    <td align="left">100 chronic HBV-infected individuals; 40 individuals with infection recover; 100 non-infected individuals</td>
    <td align="left">No association between the CCR5Δ32 (as an individual factor) and HBV infection; The WtAGCC haplotype (from CCR5Δ32, CCR5−2459A/G, MCP-1−2518A/G, VDR-APa1A/C and VDR-Taq1T/C polymorphisms, respectively) was associated with HBV infection</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib1040" ref-type="bibr">Moudi et al. (2019)</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Brazilian</td>
    <td align="left">335 HBV mono-infected individuals; 144 HBV/HIV co-infected individuals; 300 HIV mono-infected individuals; 334 non-infected individuals</td>
    <td align="left">The CCR5Δ32 was a protective factor against HBV/HIV co-infection, but the CCR5Δ32 did not affect susceptibility or resistance to HBV mono-infection</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0430" ref-type="bibr">Ellwanger et al. (2020b)</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
