<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">DNA microarray has been used efficiently in clinical diagnostics for identifying disease-related genes with the help of its biomarkers (Loy and Bodrossy 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2006</xref>) and also for disease diagnosis. The microarray-based virus diagnosis started at the beginning of this century (Schena et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">1995</xref>). Microarrays based on oligonucleotide probes representing nucleic acid sequences conserved between members of a taxonomic group were first used for detection of the then unknown SARS coronavirus (Wang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2002</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2003</xref>) and since then has been used for detection of many viruses (Chiu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR02">2007</xref>; Chou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2006</xref>; Quan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2007</xref>; Martín et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2006</xref>, Chen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2010</xref>). The detection of multiple rhinovirus serotypes in cell culture and clinical specimen (Wang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2002</xref>), papillomavirus in cervical lesions (An et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2003</xref>), parainfluenza virus 4 in nasopharyngeal aspirates (Chiu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2006</xref>), influenza virus from nasal wash and throat swabs (Lin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2006</xref>), gammaretrovirus in prostate tumors (Urisman et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR03">2006</xref>), foot and mouth disease virus from animal tissue (Martín et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2006</xref>), coronaviruses and rhinoviruses from nasal lavage (Kistler et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2007</xref>), metapneumovirus from bronchoalveolar lavage (Chiu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR02">2007</xref>), different respiratory pathogens including influenza virus and non-influenza agents in nasal swabs and lung tissue (Quan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2007</xref>), and common food born viruses such as coxsackievirus, hepatitis A virus, norovirus, and rotavirus identified using tiling microarray (Chen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2010</xref>). Grubaugh et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2013</xref>) identified 13 of 14 flaviviruses (
 <italic>Culex</italic> flavivirus, dengue-3, and Japanese encephalitis viruses) using microarray platform.
</p>
