<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28">The 5′ UTR
 <sup>U158C</sup> was found to be associated with translation and virulence in mice [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]. Other 5′ UTR positions such as guanine at 272 (272G), uracil at 448 (448 U), and adenine/uracil at 700 (700A/U) have been found to be associated with higher prevalence in severe cases of EV-A71 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]. Li 
 <italic>et. al.</italic> had also reported on other mutations that were associated with higher prevalence in severe cases of EV-A71: VP1
 <sup>145G/Q/R</sup>, VP1
 <sup>164E</sup>, and 2A
 <sup>68K</sup> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]. Apart from the structural region of the viral genome, the non-structural region had also been found to play a role in the virulence of EV-A71. Amino acid substitutions in this region had been found to increase viral fitness (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. The 3C region has been reported to be able to interfere with the host innate defense by selectively inhibiting the synthesis of type I interferon (IFN), and in 3D polymerase, an I251T mutation resulted in decreased virulence of MP4 (a mouse adapted strain of EV-A71) and can change the temperature sensitivity of the virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>]. Arita 
 <italic>et. al.</italic> (2005) had also reported that temperature-sensitive mutants that are located in the 5′ UTR, 3D
 <sup>pol</sup>, and 3′ UTR can cause an attenuation in neurovirulence [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]. The 69th residue of 3C
 <sup>pro</sup> has also been found to influence replication and virulence of EV-A71. A 3C
 <sup>N69D</sup> mutation had shown to attenuate virulence by impacting the substrate-binding site and catalytic active site. This mutation had also diminished 3C
 <sup>pro</sup> activity and its ability to shutoff host cell metabolism, inhibition of host cellular transcription and host immune system [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>]. With being under constant selection pressure in hosts, mutations often aid viruses in surviving the different environments within a host. This is often seen in quasispecies whereby the viral population works in cooperation to adapt to adverse growth condition [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>].
</p>
