<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Understanding the mosquito species that vector ZIKV is important for estimating regional outbreak potential and for informing local mosquito control strategies, especially since 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> and 
 <italic>Culex</italic> species differ in life history traits and host-seeking behaviors that could impact control efforts. For example, oviposition traps bias towards 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> that lay in artificial containers [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006524.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] while 
 <italic>Culex</italic> typically prefer natural pools [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006524.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. For 
 <italic>Cx</italic>. 
 <italic>tarsalis</italic>, we detected an overall ZIKV infection rate of 12% (8/66) in mosquitoes tested 14 and 21 dpf. Disseminated infections in 
 <italic>Cx</italic>. 
 <italic>tarsalis</italic> were detected at &lt;5% on both 14 and 21 dpf, with high Ct values indicating low ZIKV RNA levels. We postulate that the disseminated infections detected in 
 <italic>Cx</italic>. 
 <italic>tarsalis</italic> may reflect false positives given that mosquitoes with true disseminated infections typically achieve very high viral RNA titers due to prolonged infection of multiple tissues. The absence of detectable ZIKV RNA in saliva at 14 or 21 dpf is evidence that 
 <italic>Cx</italic>. 
 <italic>tarsalis</italic> from CA is not capable of transmitting ZIKV in laboratory experiments. Furthermore, 
 <italic>Cx</italic>. 
 <italic>tarsalis</italic> feeds less often on human hosts compared to the highly anthropophilic 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006524.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0006524.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], making human-mosquito-human ZIKV transmission by 
 <italic>Cx</italic>. 
 <italic>tarsalis</italic> unlikely. We also found no evidence for ZIKV infection of 
 <italic>Cx</italic>. 
 <italic>quinquefasciatus</italic> from California, with no ZIKV RNA detected in bodies, legs/wings or saliva from nearly 80 individuals. This is the first data showing ZIKV vector competence for California mosquitoes, and it supports results from many other studies which demonstrate that 
 <italic>Cx</italic>. 
 <italic>quinquefasciatus</italic> is not a competent laboratory vector of ZIKV. By contrast, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> mosquitoes exhibited infection rates of 85–90% and transmission rates of 53–80% at 14 dpf. The transmitted dose of infectious ZIKV by Californian 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> is consistent with the range of doses observed in similar studies with Brazilian 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006524.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006524.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>].
</p>
