<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To reconstruct phylogenetic transmission networks, we first determined the deep-sequence phylogenetic relationships between all possible pairs of individuals in the sample with phyloscanner. Analysis proceeded in batches of 75 individuals, which considerably reduced the number of deep-sequence phylogenies that had to be estimated, and computational burden [
 <xref rid="B47-viruses-12-00331" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Second, from this output we identified pairs of individuals between whom phylogenetic linkage could not be excluded based on subgraph distance in deep-sequence phylogenies. Third, potentially phylogenetically linked pairs of individuals were grouped into larger phylogenetic transmission networks so that each individual was linked to at least one other individual. Fourth, each potential transmission network was separately analyzed with phyloscanner to substantiate membership of individuals in networks, and to estimate the phylogenetically likely direction of viral spread within networks. Fifth, we considered all possible transmission chains in these networks, which corresponded to all possible minimum (directed) spanning trees, similar as in [
 <xref rid="B49-viruses-12-00331" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-viruses-12-00331" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. We then identified the most likely transmission chain as the minimum spanning tree that maximized the product of phyloscanner transmission scores in the directions of the edges in the spanning tree [
 <xref rid="B47-viruses-12-00331" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Sixth, we extracted pairs of individuals with strong support for phylogenetic linkage and strong support for the direction of transmission in the phylogenetically most likely transmission chain (source–recipient pairs), using a threshold of 0.6 on the phyloscanner scores (see [
 <xref rid="B47-viruses-12-00331" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] for a justification of the threshold). The analysis protocol and phyloscanner runtime arguments were exactly as described in [
 <xref rid="B47-viruses-12-00331" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. This analysis in general cannot rule out the presence of unsampled intermediates in the phylogenetically most likely transmission chains, and among source–recipient pairs.
</p>
