<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="Tab1">
 <label>Table 5.1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Summary of medically important and most commonly occurring viral hemorrhagic fevers</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th>Viral hemorrhagic fever</th>
    <th>Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever</th>
    <th>Marburg virus disease</th>
    <th>Lassa fever</th>
    <th>Yellow fever</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td>Reported geographic distribution</td>
    <td>Most wide spread tick-borne viral infection in humans. Reported from more than 50 countries in Africa, South East Europe, Middle East and Asia. Including China, Turkey, Bulgaria, Croatia, Greece, Iran, Iraq, Saudi Arabia, Kenya, Uganda, Tanzania, Egypt, Nigeria and South Africa</td>
    <td>Angola, Democratic Republic of Congo, Kenya, Uganda, Zimbabwe</td>
    <td>Sierra Leone, Guinea, Liberia and Nigeria</td>
    <td>Endemic in more than 50 countries in tropical regions of Africa (44 countries) and South and Central America (12 countries)</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="2">Cumulative occurrence/prevalence</td>
    <td rowspan="2">Sero-prevalence of up to 20% in endemic areas in people with history of tick bites</td>
    <td rowspan="2">Only 466 cases reported from 1967 to 2014 (including cases associated with exportation of infected monkeys to Europe, Russia and USA). Outbreaks often involve single cases. Two bigger outbreaks reported in DRC and Angola in 1998–2000 and 2004–2005, respectively</td>
    <td>Up to 500,000 cases in West Africa per annum</td>
    <td rowspan="2">Up to 130,000 cases with hemorrhagic manifestation per year by estimation</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Sero-prevalence of up to 55% in certain communities in endemic areas</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="2">Mode of transmission</td>
    <td rowspan="2">Mostly through tick bites, or other contact with infected ticks, or infected tissues and blood. Nosocomial transmission has been reported, but human-to-human transmission limited</td>
    <td>Spill over from cave dwelling bats, exact mode of transmission unclear</td>
    <td rowspan="2">Human contact with infected rodent urine and fecal material. The latter may be aerosolized and transmitted 
     <italic>via</italic> this route
    </td>
    <td rowspan="2">From day feeding 
     <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitoes, particularly 
     <italic>A. aegypti</italic>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Human-to-human transmission through direct and close contact with infected persons</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td rowspan="2">Reservoir host and vector</td>
    <td>Domestic livestock and small mammals</td>
    <td rowspan="2">Believed to be cave dwelling bats such as 
     <italic>Roussettus aegyptiacus</italic>
    </td>
    <td rowspan="2">
     <italic>Mastomys natalensis</italic> (or the multimammate mouse)
    </td>
    <td rowspan="2">Maintained in sylvatic cycle in nature involving certain primates and canopy dwelling mosquitoes. May establish in urban setting involving 
     <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Ticks, particularly 
     <italic>Hyalomma</italic> ticks
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Case fatality rate</td>
    <td>Up to 30% in hospitalized cases</td>
    <td>Up to 90% in outbreaks</td>
    <td>Up to 20% in hospitalized cases, but up to 80% of people infected do not develop signs and symptoms of Lassa fever</td>
    <td>Up to 50% in hospitalized cases</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>References</td>
    <td>Uyar et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], Ergönül [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], Bente et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], Mardani and Pourkaveh [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], Elaldi and Kaya [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], Messina et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], Shayan et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], Leblebicioglu et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]
    </td>
    <td>Brauburger et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>], Olival and Hayman [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], Brainard et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], Rougeron et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]
    </td>
    <td>Richmond and Baglole [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], Ogbu et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]
    </td>
    <td>Gardner and Ryman [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], Garske et al. [
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <p>Ebola virus disease is not included in this summary, but described in detail in the text. The geographical expanse provided for each disease related to reports of naturally occurring outbreaks and does for example not include exported cases of disease</p>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
