<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">Chikungunya originated in Africa where, historically, it circulated in a sylvan cycle among forest-dwelling 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitos and nonhuman primates, with occasional human spillover. Human infection is generally symptomatic but was thought to be benign. However, during the recent pandemic, the occurrence of severe joint pain persisting for many weeks and months was recognized [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. A mutation in the viral envelope protein allowed its adaptation to and high-level replication in the cosmopolitan vector 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Subsequently, the virus emerged from Africa as a pandemic that spread across the Indian Ocean, Asia, and the Pacific starting in 2005, reaching the Americas (St. Martin in the Caribbean) in late 2013 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. The explosive (attack rate &gt;30%) 2005–2006 epidemic on Reunion Island in the Indian Ocean was met with suspension of the collection of red blood cells and plasma on the island, their importation from Metropolitan France, and the emergent introduction of pathogen reduction for platelets collected from local at-risk donors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. The virus can be transmitted by IV inoculation of monkeys [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Modeling exercises suggest a substantial risk of transmission by blood [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Donor testing in the Caribbean using nucleic acid tests during 2014–2015 identified 0.19–0.54% of tested donors to be “RNA-emic” [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. The positive units were discarded if prospectively tested or de-linked, so recipient outcomes are not available. Internationally, and during its spread in the Americas where more than 2,000,000 cases have been reported to the Pan American Health Organization from 2014 to mid-September 2017 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>], transfusion transmission has been neither recognized nor alleged. No transfusion medicine interventions are planned in the United States beyond continued surveillance. Limited local transmission in South Florida provoked a scaled response depending on the case load, monitoring in conjunction with local public health, addition of travel deferrals for potential exposures in epidemics ex-US, proactive donation quarantine in zip codes with autochthonous cases and callback to assure the donor remained well before components could be distributed for transfusion, and zip code-based staged cessation of collections for local cases beyond a predetermined threshold number [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>].
</p>
