<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An agronomical practice to limit virus dispersal consists of removing virus-infected plants from crops or weeds acting as inoculum source. This requires rapid and specific detection techniques able to analyze many samples from the field, such as ELISA and molecular hybridization, especially using tissue-prints (
 <xref rid="B207" ref-type="bibr">Rubio et al., 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B211" ref-type="bibr">Rubio et al., 2003b</xref>). Roguing is effective only if the virus incidence is low after a recent introduction or in isolated areas. Other practices consist of interrupting the virus transmission chain. Many seed-borne viruses (carried on the seed coat) can be removed with chemical disinfectants such as sodium hypochlorite, trisodium phosphate, hydrochloric acid and ozone, whereas some seed-transmitted viruses (infecting the seed embryo) can be eliminated by thermotherapy (
 <xref rid="B139" ref-type="bibr">Ling, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B187" ref-type="bibr">Paylan et al., 2014</xref>). Multiplex (RT)-PCR to detect simultaneously the seed-transmitted and seed-borne viruses for a crop can be a useful tool (
 <xref rid="B183" ref-type="bibr">Panno et al., 2012</xref>). Incidence of plant viruses mechanically transmissible by contact, like those of the genus 
 <italic>Tobamovirus</italic>, can be reduced by hygienic measures such as using disposable gloves or washing hands with disinfectant, heat sterilization of tools and debris and limiting the access to crops (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Broadbent, 1976</xref>). Most plant viruses are transmitted by arthropod vectors, mainly aphids, whiteflies, and thrips. Three strategies to prevent the spread of plant viruses by vectors have been used (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Antignus, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Fereres and Raccah, 2015</xref>): i) Reducing vector populations by pesticides; biological control with natural enemies such as arthropod predators and parasitoids (
 <xref rid="B236" ref-type="bibr">Téllez et al., 2017</xref>) or entomopathogenic fungi, nematodes, bacteria and viruses (
 <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr">Kalha et al., 2014</xref>); and biotechnology-based approaches based on protease inhibitors, neurotoxins, or RNA silencing of genes essential for insect development or metabolism (
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Fereres and Raccah, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B168" ref-type="bibr">Nandety et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B255" ref-type="bibr">Vogel et al., 2019</xref>). ii) Preventing the vector from reaching the crop with barriers (greenhouses and barrier plants), by interference of the insect vision with UV-absorbing plastics and reflective surfaces, by agronomical practices such as changing the planting or sowing dates to avoid high vector populations, or imposing a time gap between crops and/or space gap between plots to break the transmission cycle (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Antignus, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Fereres and Raccah, 2015</xref>). iii) Interfering with the transmission process by spraying mineral oils, synthetic peptides or modified proteins to outcompete virus-encoded proteins needed for virus attachment to insect receptors (
 <xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr">Lecoq and Desbiez, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Blanc et al., 2014</xref>).
</p>
