<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005">
 <label>Table 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Characteristics of included studies.</p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text id="al0010">Table 1</alt-text>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th/>
    <th>Country</th>
    <th>Design</th>
    <th>Participants</th>
    <th>Epidemic/pandemic</th>
    <th>Measures</th>
    <th>Observations</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">Chang et al. (2015)</xref>
    </td>
    <td>Taiwan</td>
    <td>Case report</td>
    <td>2 cases of transient childhood psychosis</td>
    <td>H1N1 influenza</td>
    <td>None reported</td>
    <td>Case 1, 14-year-old girl experienced eight days of schizophrenia-like symptoms following five days of antiviral therapy with oseltamivir. Patient treated with 5 mg/day aripiprazole and 20 mg/day fluoxetine.
     <break/>Case 2, recurrent influenza infections (H1N1) with co-occurring psychosis-like symptoms. Treated with 5 mg/day aripiprazole, symptoms ameliorated after four days.
     <break/>These case studies demonstrate an association between H1N1 influenza and psychosis. Four pathomechanisms proposed; maternal infection, viral-induced auto-antibody production, cytokine dysregulation, other immune-related genetic polymorphisms.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al. (2004)</xref>
    </td>
    <td>Hong Kong</td>
    <td>Case report</td>
    <td>Ten patients with SARS with psychiatric complications</td>
    <td>SARS</td>
    <td>None reported</td>
    <td>6/10 referrals = mild psychiatric problems (adjustment disorders), received telephone interviews, 4/10 = severe problems (hallucinatory/manic features), received face-to-face interviews.
     <break/>The adjustment disorder patients reported distress to be related to the specific effects of SARS. Three had distress due to total social isolation.
     <break/>Those experiencing hallucinations/mania experienced increased symptoms when steroid therapy was stepped down at the end of acute treatment (3/4), one after a high initial dose of pulsed steroid treatment
     <break/>Steroid-induced psychiatric disturbances were successfully prescribed low dose haloperidol.
     <break/>Behavioural disturbances and psychotic symptoms led to non-compliance with infection control measures.
     <break/>Clinicians (non-psych) were wary about non-essential personnel visiting bedside - challenging to get psychiatrists and psychologists face-to-face access.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">Hu et al. (2020)</xref>
    </td>
    <td>China</td>
    <td>Retrospective chart review</td>
    <td>13,783 psychiatric patients attending Xuzhou Oriental People's (psychiatric) Hospital in January 2020, 35,909 control patients</td>
    <td>COVID-19</td>
    <td>Data extracted from hospital administrative data (January 2020), clinical diagnosis based on ICD-10 criteria. Data on diagnostics results, age, gender and address also extracted. Control data were extracted from a comparable period in 2017, 2018 and 2019</td>
    <td>Among patients attending outpatients for the first time a 25% in incident cases of schizophrenia was reported. In returning outpatients, a slight decrease in incident cases of schizophrenia was reported.
     <break/>Increase in median age from 39 to 50 for those diagnosed with FEP.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">Iancu et al. (2005)</xref>
    </td>
    <td>Israel</td>
    <td>Survey</td>
    <td>30 people with schizophrenia, 30 staff members working in a psychiatric hospital</td>
    <td>SARS</td>
    <td>A questionnaire developed to assess perceptions and fears of possible contagion of inpatients and staff members. Modified Spielberger Anxiety Scale Score used to assess whether this threat had any effect on the clinical state of psychiatric inpatients</td>
    <td>83% of inpatients had heard of the SARS epidemic.
     <break/>33% of inpatients were worried about the threat compared to 50% of staff controls.
     <break/>Psychological reactions to SARS (anxious, depressed, frightened) were similar to a staff control group.
     <break/>Inpatients were significantly more likely to attribute SARS to their actions or as a message from God, than staff controls.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">Kamara et al., 2017</xref>
    </td>
    <td>Sierra Leone</td>
    <td>Cross-sectional study</td>
    <td>143 patients referred to psychiatric services</td>
    <td>Ebola</td>
    <td>Reporting the referrals to a new mental health service developed subsequent to the Ebola outbreak in Sierra Leone</td>
    <td>One hundred forty-three patients seen in the first year of a new nurse-led mental health and psychosocial support service with inpatient liaison service and an outpatient clinic, developed in response to the Ebola outbreak that forced the closure of the psychiatric hospital to prevent disease transmission.
     <break/>21% (30 patients) presented with psychosis requiring medication. During the Ebola outbreak, there were challenges getting affordable medication to those in need; as a result, “some” service users reported accessing alternative treatment such as traditional and faith healing.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al. (2018)</xref>
    </td>
    <td>South Korea</td>
    <td>Retrospective chart review</td>
    <td>40 patients admitted to the MERS inpatient unit at the National Medical Centre</td>
    <td>MERS</td>
    <td>On admission to the quarantine ward, patients were administered the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9), the Impact of Event Scale-Revised (IES-R), the Korean National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (KNHANES), and the Peritraumatic Dissociation-Posttraumatic Negative Beliefs-Posttraumatic Social Support (PTD-PTNB-PTSS) scale.</td>
    <td>Of 40 admitted patients, 30 were confirmed MERS patients, of which six died. 17/24 MERS survivors had psychiatric symptoms. 2/17 patients experienced “hallucinations” and 2 “aggressive outbursts” but were not given a psychosis diagnosis. 3/17 patients had “severe psychiatric disorder.” None of the ten patients that did not have confirmed MERS experienced psychiatric symptoms. The authors proposed that a biopsychosocial model may explain the development of psychiatric symptoms in MERS patients.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al. (2004)</xref>
    </td>
    <td>Hong Kong</td>
    <td>Retrospective chart review, matched case-control study</td>
    <td>15 patients with SARS-related psychosis, 30 nonpsychotic control patients with SARS, matched on age and sex</td>
    <td>SARS</td>
    <td>The medical records of case-patients and controls were reviewed for information on socio-demographics, past medical history, and SARS development and treatment history</td>
    <td>Of 1744 patients with SARS, 15 with psychotic disorders were identified (incidence rate of 0.9%).
     <break/>10/15 were diagnosed as a steroid-induced manic episode, 3/15 as steroid-induced psychotic disorder, 1/15 major depressive episode with psychotic features, 1/15 as psychotic disorder NOS.
     <break/>Patients with SARS related psychosis received higher total doses of steroids and had higher rates of family history of psychiatric illness.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr">Maguire et al. (2018)</xref>
     <xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>
    </td>
    <td>Australia</td>
    <td>Cross-sectional survey</td>
    <td>71 adults with schizophrenia, 238 adults without schizophrenia</td>
    <td>2009 swine influenza pandemic</td>
    <td>A new questionnaire explored: 1. Willingness to vaccinate, socially isolate, wear facial masks, hand wash; 2. Perceived effectiveness of protective measures; 3. Risk perceptions and feelings of vulnerability</td>
    <td>Compared to controls, people with schizophrenia were less willing to receive a vaccine and more concerned about adverse reactions from vaccination; they were also less willing to be isolated.
     <break/>No differences between willingness to wear a face mask or wash hands more regularly.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">Maguire et al. (2019)</xref>
     <xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>
    </td>
    <td>Australia</td>
    <td>Cross-sectional survey</td>
    <td>71 adults with schizophrenia, 238 adults without schizophrenia</td>
    <td>2009 swine influenza pandemic</td>
    <td>Mood measured with K10, an additional questionnaire asked: ‘if you caught swine flu how afraid/depressed would it make you feel?’ ‘Do you feel at risk of swine flu?’</td>
    <td>Those with schizophrenia trended towards perceiving themselves as less likely to contract swine flu than controls, no differences in other risk perception variables. Higher K10 anxiety subscale score associated with a reduced likelihood of perceived substantive risk from swine flu in the schizophrenia group. Higher levels of predicted fear associated with an increased likelihood of perceived substantive risk from swine flu.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Mak et al. (2009)</xref>
    </td>
    <td>Hong Kong</td>
    <td>Cohort study</td>
    <td>90 SARS survivors assessed 30mths after the outbreak</td>
    <td>SARS</td>
    <td>Psychiatric diagnosis as per SCID-IV</td>
    <td>4.4% of the cohort experienced post-SARS psychotic symptoms. Other diagnoses included 44.4% major depression, 47.8% PTSD, 13.3% panic disorder.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">Pang (2004)</xref>
    </td>
    <td>Hong Kong</td>
    <td>Service evaluation</td>
    <td>Psychiatric services</td>
    <td>SARS</td>
    <td>The authors do not specify how data were obtained</td>
    <td>A reduction in the use of psychiatric services following the SARS outbreak. Authors questioned mental health clinicians understanding of the signs and symptoms of SARS. Measures were put in place to prevent SARS transmission in psychiatric inpatient units. Newly admitted patients closely screened and monitored (for respiratory symptoms and temperature), leave was cancelled, mixing of patients was restricted, patients that do not comply with infection control measures (e.g., mask-wearing) were placed in compulsory quarantine.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <xref rid="bb0140" ref-type="bibr">Severance et al. (2011)</xref>
    </td>
    <td>Baltimore USA</td>
    <td>Cross-sectional survey</td>
    <td>106 adults recent-onset psychotic symptoms and 196 healthy controls</td>
    <td>Corona-viruses</td>
    <td>Coronavirus immunoglobulin G antibody levels in recent-onset psychosis compared to controls to determine the extent that coronavirus exposure may correlate with the onset of SMI</td>
    <td>Recent onset psychotic symptoms significantly associated with coronavirus exposure - in antibody levels and seroprevalence. Increased rates of immunoreactivity for certain coronavirus strains in the psychosis group. Coronavirus exposure may be a comorbid risk factor in SMI.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">Sheng et al. (2005)</xref>
    </td>
    <td>Hong Kong</td>
    <td>Cross-sectional survey</td>
    <td>103 SARS patients after discharge from hospital.</td>
    <td>SARS</td>
    <td>Frequency of neuropsychiatric symptoms (e.g. auditory hallucinations), measured using the SARS Neuropsychiatric Symptoms Checklist, completed by recovered SARS patients</td>
    <td>3.9%, 2% 3.9% recalled experiencing auditory, visual and/or persecutory ideas in the acute phase of SARS.
     <break/>SARS severity and higher doses of corticosteroids were associated with an increase in psychosis symptoms in the acute phase of the illness
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <xref rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr">Zulkifli et al. (2020)</xref>
    </td>
    <td>Malaysia</td>
    <td>Case report</td>
    <td>31-year-old male, no previous history of psychosis</td>
    <td>COVID-19</td>
    <td>None reported</td>
    <td>First presentation. Had been expressing extreme concern about novel coronavirus outbreak, was causing a public “nuisance,” brandishing a knife, talking irrelevantly, and expressing the belief that the world is going to end. The patient was a non-smoker, did not use illicit drugs or alcohol. The patient responded quickly to low dose antipsychotic medication. Returned to the premorbid state after three days in the hospital.</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn>
   <p>FEP = first-episode psychosis, MERS = Middle East Respiratory Syndrome, PTSD = Post Traumatic Stress Disorder, SARS = Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome, SCID-IV = Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV,</p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn id="tf0005">
   <label>a</label>
   <p id="np0005">Papers are from the same survey.</p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
