<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par48">It is currently not known what has triggered the surge of recent epidemics of ZIKV and the associated severe diseases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Mechanistically, aberrant suppression of the antiviral property of IFNs might facilitate infection of ZIKV as well as viral spreading in human populations. ZIKV is largely a mosquito-borne virus and can also be transmitted through sexual contact, blood transfusion, organ transplantation, and potentially via urine or saliva as well. Moreover, ZIKV may be transmitted from pregnant women to fetuses by a transplacental route [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. In consistence with such a dynamic transmission pattern, ZIKV exhibits a broad tropism and ability to persist in multiple types of tissues/organs and in body fluids, including the eyes, blood, testis and semen [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. It is also of note that immunocompromised human subjects or mice have increased susceptibility to ZIKV infection and are more vulnerable to developing severe disease than healthy individuals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Moreover, it has been well documented that nonstructural proteins of ZIKV play important roles in the life cycle of ZIKV and that several of them, including NS1, NS2B/3, NS4A, NS4B, and NS5, interact with innate immune molecules [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. We therefore hypothesize that in addition to mediating the effects of putative entry receptors on host cells being a key ZIKV infection mechanism, the ability of ZIKV to defeat the host IFN system, possibly through expressing multiple viral factors that interfere with multiple steps and nodes along the IFN signaling cascade, may also represent a key contributor to its broad cellular tropism and intracellular persistence. Hence, collaborative actions among different ZIKV nonstructural proteins need to be better understood, and further investigation of how the effect of NS4A, as identified in our current study, cooperates with other counter-IFN effects of ZIKV, such as NS1, NS2B/3, NS4A, NS4B, and NS5, is warranted.
</p>
