<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Clinical presentation of infection with any of these six viruses is often similar; undifferentiated fever, headache, nausea/vomiting, persistent myalgia/arthralgia, and rash [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Although PCR assays that can discriminate between these viruses exist, they are often not used in conjunction and are reliant on short primer sequences designed to target relatively conserved regions of the viral genomes [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. As these viruses all share a common replication strategy dependent on error-prone RNA-dependent RNA polymerases, rapid mutation necessitates the constant optimization of molecular diagnostic protocols for their accurate detection [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Further, these methodologies are limited in that they provide no information on the particular strain infecting the individual [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Recent studies have shown that polymorphisms in the viral genome can have profound effects on the pathogenicity and epidemic potential of the virus [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. In response to these shortcomings, next-generation sequencing (NGS) is increasingly being used as a tool to obtain the full genome sequence of viruses in clinical samples [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. However, the principle drawback to this methodology is the often-overwhelming amount of host material present in a clinical sample relative to the virus. In order to produce sufficient data for full viral genome assembly from these clinical samples, only a small number of samples can typically be run per lane of sequencing making this approach prohibitively expensive for many laboratories. To overcome the inherent limitations of this direct sequencing approach, a targeted enrichment approach to increase the sensitivity and efficiency of whole genome sequencing has been described for several pathogens of clinical importance [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. One limitation of this approach is the high upfront cost associated with the enrichment baits. In the current study, we present a novel computation method, BaitMaker, to design baits that target the conserved and variable regions of a viral genome. The delineation of the conserved and variable regions is made possible by employing a computationally efficient k-mer based clustering approach on the available genetic information for DENV1-4, ZIKV and CHIKV in the NCBI database. We have then applied our methodology to two large cohorts: a collection of blood samples from the 2012–2015 DENV epidemic in Sri Lanka (n = 170) and samples collected during the 2016 outbreak of ZIKV in Singapore (n = 162) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007184.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].
</p>
