<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our data suggest that NS1 binding and internalization are distinct steps in triggering endothelial hyperpermeability. Because both WT DENV NS1 and DENV NS1-N207Q are able to bind to HPMEC, but only WT DENV NS1 is internalized, we hypothesize that NS1 initially binds to heparan sulfate moieties on endothelial cells [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007938.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], independently of the N207 N-glycan. DENV NS1 may then interact with an additional binding partner(s) in a manner dependent on the N207 N-glycan, which leads to internalization, endosomal trafficking, and activation of cathepsin L and/or sialidases. Why is the N207 N-glycosylation site critical for internalization of DENV NS1? First, the N207 N-glycan may be required for engaging a specific receptor on endothelial cells, either directly through a physical interaction or indirectly through a conformational change. Based on the available crystal structure of NS1, amino acid 207 is not predicted to be surface-exposed [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007938.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. This observation favors a model where a conformational change of NS1 allows this N-glycan to be exposed and mediate an interaction required for internalization or where the N-glycan itself mediates a conformational change of NS1 that allows another domain to mediate an interaction required for internalization. Second, glycosylation patterns have been shown to be important for lateral diffusion of proteins on the plasma membrane [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007938.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007938.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Thus, an alternate possibility is that the N207 N-glycan is required for NS1 to migrate to the proper microdomain to interact with functional components on the lipid membrane required for internalization. Furthermore, NS1 is secreted from DENV-infected cells predominantly as a soluble hexameric barrel-shaped, high-density lipoprotein with a hydrophobic core containing lipid cargos such as triglycerides, cholesteryl esters, and phospholipids [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007938.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007938.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007938.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. The functional importance, if any, of these lipid cargos is yet to be determined. A third possibility for the role of the N207 N-glycan in NS1 internalization is that this sugar moiety may be important for acquisition of specific lipid cargos that play a role during NS1 binding to endothelial cells or even internalization; thus, further investigation of the lipid contents of the mutant NS1 is needed to uncover a potential role of the N207 N-glycan in lipid cargo acquisition as well as a possible role of these lipid cargos in NS1-mediated pathogenesis [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007938.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].
</p>
