<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recent research advances are beginning to shed light on the molecular mechanisms by which bats avoid pathology from these otherwise virulent pathogens (
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Brook and Dobson, 2015</xref>). Bats leverage a suite of species-specific mechanisms to limit viral load, which include host receptor sequence incompatibilities for some bat-virus combinations (
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Ng et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Takadate et al., 2020</xref>) and constitutive expression of the antiviral cytokine, IFN-α, for others (
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2016</xref>). Typically, the presence of viral RNA or DNA in the cytoplasm of mammalian cells will induce secretion of type I interferon proteins (IFN-α and IFN-β), which promote expression and translation of interferon-stimulated genes (ISGs) in neighboring cells and render them effectively antiviral (
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Stetson and Medzhitov, 2006</xref>). In some bat cells, the transcriptomic blueprints for this IFN response are expressed constitutively, even in the absence of stimulation by viral RNA or DNA (
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2016</xref>). In non-flying mammals, constitutive IFN expression would likely elicit widespread inflammation and concomitant immunopathology upon viral infection, but bats support unique adaptations to combat inflammation (
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Ahn et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Xie et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Pavlovich et al., 2018</xref>) that may have evolved to mitigate metabolic damage induced during flight (
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Kacprzyk et al., 2017</xref>). The extent to which constitutive IFN-α expression signifies constitutive antiviral defense in the form of functional IFN-α protein remains unresolved. In bat cells constitutively expressing IFN-α, some protein-stimulated, downstream ISGs appear to be also constitutively expressed, but additional ISG induction is nonetheless possible following viral challenge and stimulation of IFN-β (
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Xie et al., 2018</xref>). Despite recent advances in molecular understanding of bat viral tolerance, the consequences of this unique bat immunity on within-host virus dynamics—and its implications for understanding zoonotic emergence—have yet to be elucidated.
</p>
