<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="f1" position="float">
 <label>Figure 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>SARS-CoV-2 life cycle and potential therapeutic targets. ISGs, interferon-stimulated genes; IL6R, Interleukin 6 receptor; TLR 7,8, Toll-like receptors 7,8; TMPRSS, transmembrane protease serine 2 (
   <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-11-01224-i001.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>); mTORC1, mammalian target of rapamycin complex 1 (
   <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-11-01224-i002.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>); RLR, RIG-I-like receptors; ACE2, angiotensin converting enzyme 2 receptor (
   <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-11-01224-i003.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>); RTC, replication/transcription complex; 3CLpro, 3C-like protease; PLpro, Papain like Protease; RdRP, RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (
   <inline-graphic xlink:href="fphar-11-01224-i004.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>); Nsp, nonstructural protein. SARS-Cov-2 life cycle and pathogenesis include: the interaction between the spike protein and ACE2 receptor on host cells (1); clathrin-mediated endocytosis (2); the fusion of the virus with cell membranes facilitated by transmembrane protease serine 2 (TMPRSS) (3); autophagy and RNA release in the presence of the mammalian target of rapamycin complex 1 protein (rapamycin complex 1) (mTORC1) (4); RNA translation , polyprotein synthesis and cleavage with the help of 3C-like protease (3CLpro) and papain like protease (PLpro) (5); genomic RNA transcription catalysed by thr RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRP) in the Replication/Transcription Complex (RTC) (6); translation of viral proteins (7); assembly of viral proteins and RNA into a mature virion in the Golgi (8) ; the virion is released by exocytosis (9). Recognition of viral RNA by endosomal RIG-I-like receptors (RLRs) and Toll-like receptors (TLRs) allows the activation of type I interferon (IFNs) response, that up-regulates the expression of interferon-stimulated genes (ISGs) and activate the antiviral response. The elimination of SARS-Cov2 requires a coordinated response which should include: the cytokine release, Th1/2 immunity and synthesis of neutralizing antibodies by LB/plasma cells SARS- Cov-2 potential therapeutic targets encompass the following steps: blocking ACE2 receptors (monoclonal antibodies); TMPRSS inhibition which prevents endosomal fusion (arbidol, hidroxyclorochine); mTORC1inhibition and the controlul of autophagy and RNA transcription (remdesivir); inhibition of 2Clpro and PLpro viral proteases involved in polyprotein fragmentation (protease inhibitors namely lopinavir, darunavir, ritonavir); Nsp-12-RdRp inhibition with an essential role in the activity of the replicase RNA transcription complex (favipiravir, remdesivir); suppression of cytokine release (hydroxiclorochine, baricitinib), blocking the IL6R (tocilizumab) or Th1 response (gimsilumab); blocking the virus through the administration of neutralizing antibodies from the plasma of COVID-19 convalescents.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="fphar-11-01224-g001" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
