<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0225">Cyclosporine is a immunosuppressive agent isolated form the fungus 
 <italic>Beaueria nivea</italic>. It is widely approved for the treatment of lupus nephritis vasculitis psoriatic arthritis and as a immunosuppressant agent in organ transplantation [
 <xref rid="bb0785" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>]. Cyclosporine acts as a calcineurin inhibitor. It binds to cyclophilin receptor in the cells and forms a cyclosporine-cyclophilin complex. This complex will further block the calcium dependent interleukin (IL-2) production pathway and suppresses the gene transcription of IL-2 thereby reducing the inflammatory responses [
 <xref rid="bb0790" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>]. In the case of COVID-19, cyclosporine blocks RNA-dependent-RNA polymerase and peptidyl-prolyl isomerase activity of SARS-CoV-2 virus there by inhibiting the cyclophilin function of the virus [
 <xref rid="bb0795" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>]. To enter into the cell corona virus bids to the angiotensin converting enzyme-2 (ACE-2) at a low cytosolic Ph, cyclosporine s known to maintain the cytosolic pH at normal levels and there by aids in decreasing the viral load [
 <xref rid="bb0800" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>]. Cytokine storm in SARS-CoV-2 infection is mainly caused due to SHL and cyclosporine is the choice of drug to treat SHL as cyclosporine blocks the production of IL-2 and inhibits the proliferation and survival of T-cells [
 <xref rid="bb0805" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>]. Cyclosporine is absorbed variably with a volume of distribution 0f 4–8 L/kg. The half-life of cyclosporine is 19 h and its metabolized in intestine and liver by CYP450 enzymes [
 <xref rid="bb0790" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>]. Gingival hyperplasia, nephrotoxicity and hyperlipidaemia are the possible side effects of cyclosporine. Despite of its activity against SARS-CoV-2 virus it is not yet recommended for the treatment of COVID-19 as there is no proper pre-clinical and clinical data proving the safety and efficacy of cyclosporine in the treatment of COVID-19 available.
</p>
