<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Much more data exist for HCV infection, but DDX3’s role in its replication is less clear. Indeed, the DDX3 helicase is also an essential component in HCV replication [
 <xref rid="B63-molecules-25-01015" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. It was reported that siRNA-mediated knockdown of DDX3 causes a reduction in HCV RNA and HCV core expression levels in cells. The first data about the interaction of DDX helicase with C-terminal domain of HCV core were published in 1999 [
 <xref rid="B64-molecules-25-01015" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-molecules-25-01015" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-molecules-25-01015" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The authors hypothesized that the interaction of DDX3 with HCV genotype 1 core somehow increased HCV replication level. However, later, the statement was overcome; namely, mutations in DDX3 genotype 2a, which prevented the binding of DDX3 to the HCV core, had no effect on HCV replication, although core-derived peptides of HCV genotype 1b inhibited HCV replication [
 <xref rid="B67-molecules-25-01015" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. These contradicted results can be explained by the different type of HCV genotypes used by the authors [
 <xref rid="B68-molecules-25-01015" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Later, Oshiumi et al. explained that HCV core inactivates the IPS-1 adaptor, triggering RIG-mediated IFN-beta induction caused by DDX3 and, as a result, virus replication is propagated [
 <xref rid="B69-molecules-25-01015" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-molecules-25-01015" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. So, the authors concluded that DDX3 is a RigI adaptor protein. However, this mechanism is not quite clear, as many cell lines used in HCV research are not competent for IFNβ induction. For example, the most common cell line, Huh7.5, is characterized by inactivation of Rig-I (DDX58) [
 <xref rid="B71-molecules-25-01015" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. In addition, HCV NS3 protease triggers proteolysis of MAVS, a classical Rig-I adaptor critical for interferon induction [
 <xref rid="B72-molecules-25-01015" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. However, recently, Horner’s group described a novel TRF3-dependent but Rig-I/MAVS-independent interferon response controlled by HCV [
 <xref rid="B73-molecules-25-01015" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. So, the input of interferon signaling in the control of HCV infection and the precise role of DDX3 in its modulation still have to be investigated. 
</p>
