<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While previous studies have focused primarily on the direct impact of temperature on viral replication and competence in adult mosquitoes, there may also be indirect effects on vector competence resulting from variable aquatic temperatures during mosquito development. In general, effects of larval temperature are more apparent in 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> spp. than 
 <italic>Culex</italic> spp. Studies with Venezuelan equine encephalitis virus (VEEV), RVFV, chikungunya virus and Ross River virus (RRV) demonstrated an inverse relationship between larval rearing temperature and infectivity in 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> spp. mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="B36-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], yet no effect was measured for RVFV in 
 <italic>Cx. pipiens</italic> [
 <xref rid="B49-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>] Murray valley encephalitis virus (MVEV) in 
 <italic>Cx. annulirostris</italic> [
 <xref rid="B61-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>] or West Nile virus (WNV) in 
 <italic>Cx. tarsalis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B62-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. These relationships could be further complicated by additional environmental factors and larval density [
 <xref rid="B63-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. As temperature alters development time and mosquito size [
 <xref rid="B62-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], and size has at times been associated with altered vector competence [
 <xref rid="B69-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>] this could be one important effect of temperature on competence, yet recent studies demonstrate that larval temperature can also significantly alter stress and immune gene expression [
 <xref rid="B70-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>], including influencing important proteins in the RNA interference pathway that can directly alter susceptibility in adult mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="B71-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Additional mechanistic studies are needed to further probe how species and population-specific variability influences the impact of aquatic temperatures and other environmental factors on vector competence.
</p>
