<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the present study, we identified the host cellular protein FFAR2, a seven-transmembrane GPCR receptor, as an important cofactor for the replication of IAV, especially the H5N1 subtype, by using a genome-wide RNA interference (RNAi) screen. Knockdown of FFAR2 by using siRNA treatment can universally restrict the replication of different subtypes of IAV, and the inhibitory effect of 
 <italic>FFAR2</italic> knockout on IAV replication can be rescued by retrovirally mediated FFAR2 complementation in 
 <italic>FFAR2</italic>_KO A549 cells. We found that the effect of siRNA knockdown of FFAR2 expression on IAV replication does not involve the stimulation of the IFN pathway because the level of Mx1 protein was unchanged and ISRE reporter activity was unstimulated. Furthermore, treatment of A549 cells with 
 <italic>FFAR2</italic> siRNA or the FFAR2 agonists 4-CMTB and Cmp58 significantly inhibited both the nuclear accumulation and cytoplasm localization of vRNP complexes at early time points after IAV infection but had no effect on viral genome transcription or replication. These results demonstrate that FFAR2 is involved in an early stage of the viral replication cycle prior to the transcription and replication of the viral genome. In an effort to define the specific stage of IAV replication that involves FFAR2, we first showed that FFAR2 knockdown in A549 cells had no effect on the cell surface expression of SA receptors and that the attachment of IAV particles to the SA receptors was also not affected. However, the attached viruses on the surface of cells treated with 
 <italic>FFAR2</italic> siRNA, 4-CMTB, or Cmp58 were easily removed by washes with PBS-HCl (pH 1.3), resulting in a significant reduction in the levels of viral NP internalized in the infected cells. Of note, the treatment of A549 cells with 4-CMTB or Cmp58 inhibited the replication of H5N1 virus in A549 cells. Mechanistically, sustained stimulation with agonists could cause internalization of FFAR2, resulting in a decrease in the amount of FFAR2 on the cell surface. In this case, insufficient FFAR2 on the cell membrane would be unable to efficiently facilitate the internalization of IAV through the endocytosis pathway. By using the BiFC assay and the co-IP experiment, we demonstrate that FFAR2 interacted with viral HA and M2 among the 10 essential proteins of IAV. We speculate that the interaction between FFAR2 and HA most likely stimulates the FFAR2 signaling cascade, promoting IAV internalization after HA attachment to the SA receptors on the cell surface. Compared with HA, the amount of M2 on viral particles is small. Moreover, M2 mainly functions at the uncoating stage during IAV entry; i.e., it serves as an ion channel to acidify the interior of the virus particle, resulting in vRNP complex detachment from M1 and release into the cytoplasm. We demonstrate that FFAR2 is important in the internalization step during IAV entry. However, whether FFAR2 is also involved in the uncoating step by interacting with M2 requires further investigation. Collectively, these findings demonstrate that FFAR2 is an important cofactor for IAV entry into host cells.
</p>
