<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Specimens positive by Msn RT-PCR were selected randomly based on serotype distribution at each site to represent geographical and temporal distribution for sequencing using methods that have been published previously [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007785.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0007785.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Viral RNA was converted to complementary DNA (cDNA) using the SuperScript III First-Strand Synthesis System for RT-PCR (Invitrogen, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions, then amplified by PCR at a region covering the structural (
 <italic>capsid-pre-membrane/membrane-envelope</italic> (C-prM/M-E)) genes using the Platinum
 <sup>TM</sup> SuperFi
 <sup>TM</sup> DNA Polymerase (Invitrogen, CA, USA). The amplification primers consist of D1F751 and D1R2581 for DENV-1 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007785.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], D2F798 and D2R2516 for DENV-2 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007785.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], D3F791 and D3R2492 for DENV-3 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007785.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], and D4s1c and D4a18 for DENV-4 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007785.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], which resulted in DNA fragments of sizes 1831-bp, 1719-bp, 1702-bp, and 2550-bp for DENV-1, DENV-2, DENV-3, and DENV-4, respectively. DNA sequencing was performed on the purified PCR product by a contracted company (1st Base, Malaysia) using sequencing primers covering the structural region of dengue viruses (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0007785.s003">S1 Table</xref>). Chromatograms were edited and assembled using BioEdit 7.2.5 software. Phylogenetic trees describing genotypes within each of DENV serotypes were built using the maximum likelihood (ML) method, based on the 
 <italic>E</italic> gene of DENV, in the Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis version 7 (MEGA 7.0.20) software. The genotype classification scheme was previously described for each serotype [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007785.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007785.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0007785.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Models of nucleotide substitution that best described sequence evolution for each serotype were identified as TN93+G+I for DENV-1 and DENV-2 data sets and TN93+G for DENV-3 and DENV-4 data sets. The strength of tree topology was estimated by bootstrap analysis using 1000 replicates. Trees were unrooted.
</p>
