<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A comprehensive database was established by combining all SFTS case report, the recorded geographic distribution of 
 <italic>H. longicornis</italic>, and a set of 56 explanatory variables at the county level in the world. Briefly, the report data of SFTS patients in China was extracted from the China Information System for Diseases Control and Prevention (CISDCP). The data on the SFTS patients in South Korea and Japan were obtained from the Korea Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (KCDC) (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.go.kr/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.cdc.go.kr/</ext-link>) and the National Institute of Infectious Diseases (NIID) of Japan (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.niid.go.jp/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.niid.go.jp/</ext-link>), both supplemented by data in the published literature [
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. For each reported SFTS cases during January 2010–December 2018, the demographic information and the geographic information at the county level were obtained. The imported cases were georeferenced according to the site of acquiring infection, instead of their usual residence. A comprehensive dataset of globally reported presence of 
 <italic>H. longicornis</italic> was established that included data recording on survey sites and positive locations of 
 <italic>H. longicornis</italic> in latitude and longitude, as well as the survey dates on record (if no survey date is available, the publication date of the literature is used instead) (Supplementary Dataset S1) [
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23–26</xref>]. The 56 explanatory covariates mainly comprised data regarding eco-geography, climate, environment, mammalian richness and areas of migration and habitat of migratory birds on global range, which were chosen due to their potential effect on the suitability for SFTS transmission based upon the previous studies [
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Eco-geographical and climatic variables including global average climate data “WorldClim” during 1950–2000, elevation, population density, livestock density, land cover and mammalian richness were respectively collected and extracted at a resolution of 0.1° × 0.1° grid as well as at the administrative area level (mostly county level) for assessment and prediction of the global distribution of 
 <italic>H. longicornis</italic> [
 <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29–34</xref>]. The Global Mammal Richness Grids data set can provide information at a one-kilometer spatial resolution with grid cell values represent the number of species in a particular class, family, or threatened category issued by International Union for Conservation of Nature (IUCN) [
 <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Data on the migration and habitat of migratory birds were provided by the BirdLife International [
 <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].
</p>
