<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The ecology and distributions of fruit bats in many countries in which spillover may occur are not very well characterized, particularly quantitatively. This is the case even in Australia, although huge advances have been made there in recent years [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C47">47</xref>]. The study of zoonotic pathogens has stimulated the study of a number of species, including 
 <italic>Pteropus giganteus</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C70">70</xref>] and 
 <italic>Pteropus vampyrus</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C71">71</xref>] in India, Malaysia and Bangladesh and 
 <italic>E. helvum</italic> in Ghana [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C72">72</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C73">73</xref>]. In Australia, however, where Hendra virus spillover could come from any of four fruit bat species, the role of sympatry and cross-species virus transmission in driving spillover has not been elucidated at all [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C46">46</xref>]. A first necessary focus in many regions is the development of national schemes to locate, count and monitor bat colonies of focal bat species, to determine migratory patterns and to assess the reproductive cycle and efficiency. Quantification of social interactions between bats (e.g. mother–offspring, mating, fighting, allogrooming, etc.) would provide information on possible virus transmission routes. A second essential focus should be to understand feeding behaviour and ecology, as undertaken already in Bangladesh [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C74">74</xref>]. The use of novel high-resolution GPS data loggers allows detailed and quantitative studies of ranging behaviours of bats and their environmental determinants. Such methods would also underpin the identification of food plants and allow resource use to be quantified through faecal analyses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="RSTB20120228C75">75</xref>]. The importance of fruit bats to the structures and functions of local ecosystems is often very poorly characterized; improving our understanding of this will inform how bats influence ecosystems and how land use change might influence bat population—and consequently infection—dynamics (see below).
</p>
