<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Formerly known as T-705, this substituted pyrazinecarboxamide derivative is an inhibitor of the influenza virus polymerase. As a purine nucleoside analog, favipiravir directly inhibits the activity of the RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (
 <xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">Furuta et al., 2005</xref>) and it has broad-spectrum activity against all influenza subtypes including those resistant to neuraminidase and M2 inhibitors (
 <xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">Furuta et al., 2017</xref>). Preclinical studies demonstrated the broad antiviral spectrum of this compound against different human and avian influenza A and B viruses including avian influenza viruses H5N1 and H7N9 (
 <xref rid="ref130" ref-type="bibr">Sidwell et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref155" ref-type="bibr">Watanabe et al., 2013</xref>) where it has shown protection and reduction of virus titers in the infected mice. Furthermore, mice treated with favipiravir had a better outcome after an H7N9 infection compared to mice treated with neuraminidase inhibitors (
 <xref rid="ref155" ref-type="bibr">Watanabe et al., 2013</xref>). Combination therapy studies found that this drug works synergistically with neuraminidase inhibitors to improve lung virus titers, body weight loss, and survival in mice infected with a pandemic H1N1 influenza virus (
 <xref rid="ref141" ref-type="bibr">Tarbet et al., 2012</xref>) or with an avian influenza virus H5N1 (
 <xref rid="ref134" ref-type="bibr">Smee et al., 2010</xref>). Favipiravir is approved in Japan, but its use is restricted to patients infected with an influenza virus resistant to NAI or in the event of a pandemic (Toyama Chemical Co. Ltd). These conditions have been put in place due to concerns of teratogenicity, which have been identified in animal experiments. A couple of phase 3 clinical trials aimed to determine the efficacy and safety of favipiravir for the treatment of uncomplicated influenza infection in adults have been completed but the results have not been published yet. A new phase 2a clinical trial study to determine the pharmacokinetics of favipiravir in patients with severe influenza is reported as active but not currently recruiting with estimated study completion date of March 2019 (NCT03394209). This is a very promising broad-spectrum anti-influenza antiviral that also has a broad antiviral activity against several other RNA viruses (
 <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">Davidson, 2018</xref>). A couple of caveats may limit the use of this antiviral to compassionate use or in the case of emerging or re-emerging viruses for which a treatment is not available. Favipiravir has the potential for teratogenicity and embryotoxicity and is the reason why it has conditional approval in Japan (
 <xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">Furuta et al., 2017</xref>). A study of samples obtained for a clinical trial tested the emergence of mutations in viruses obtained from paired patients before and 1 or 2 days after the initiation of treatment showed the emergence of amino acid substitutions in the RNA polymerase subunits. Although these mutations did not significantly reduce the susceptibility to favipiravir (
 <xref rid="ref137" ref-type="bibr">Takashita et al., 2016</xref>)
 <italic>, in vitro</italic> escalation studies showed that influenza viruses can adapt to low concentration of the compound which highlights the potential for some influenza virus strains to possibly develop resistance (
 <xref rid="ref109" ref-type="bibr">Ormond et al., 2017</xref>).
</p>
