<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The outcome of SARS-CoV‑2 infections is highly variable, which may relate to several factors including (1) infectious dose, (2) general health of the infected individual and (3) appropriateness of his/her immune response. A large percentage (up to 81%) of people are unaware of being infected with SARS-CoV‑2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Analysis of 44,415 confirmed COVID-19 cases from China as of 11 February 2020 indicated that 81% had mild disease, 14% were severely ill and 5% developed critical illness, resulting in a case-fatality rate of 2.3% [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. In mildly affected individuals the infection remains largely restricted to the upper respiratory tract, while in seriously ill patients it subsequently spreads to the lower respiratory tract and, from there, possibly to other organs. The most common (flu-like) symptoms of COVID-19 are chills/pyrexia, dry cough, dyspnoea and fatigue or myalgia. Other, less common, symptoms include expectoration, nasal congestion/rhinorrhoea, sore throat, headache, conjunctivitis, abdominal pain, diarrhoea, nausea or vomiting, ageusia, anosmia, skin rash and discoloration of fingers or toes. These symptoms are usually mild and develop gradually (reviewed in [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]). More seriously affected individuals suffer from pneumonia, accompanied by progressive dyspnoea, chest pain, haemoptysis, crackles and/or respiratory insufficiency. In the most severe cases of COVID-19, the pneumonia develops into acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), which may lead directly to respiratory failure and is a major cause of COVID-19-related death. The development of ARDS is thought to largely result from the hypercytokinaemia (cytokine storm) induced by the virus and, together with secondary microbial infections (e.g. due to loss of intestinal epithelial barrier integrity), can culminate in sepsis and end-organ dysfunction [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Interestingly, manifestations of COVID-19 in children are generally less severe than in adults. The precise reason(s) for this is/are unclear. Due to the higher incidence of respiratory infections, the innate immune system of children may be ‘trained’ and therefore better capable of mounting an efficient first line of defence against the virus, preventing the induction of a cytokine storm due to vigorous replication of SARS-CoV‑2 in the lower airways. Alternatively, in children replication of SARS-CoV‑2 could be suppressed by the presence of other respiratory viruses. Also, airway epithelial cells of children may be less permissive to SARS-CoV‑2, e.g. because of lower ACE2 expression levels [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>].
</p>
