<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The latest technology of molecular tests, developed by scientists from Oxford University, is more sensitive than the previous ones and it implies the possibility of examining patients at earlier stages, reacting more quickly, and effectively preventing the spread of coronavirus. This new test for diagnosing SARS-CoV-2 provides rapid results within 30 min, whereas the fastest current methods that concentrate on viral RNA give results in 1.5 to 2 h, i.e., three times faster than the presently quickest testing methods, and which requires the application of relatively simple technical devices. Apart from those advantages, the scientists responsible for the test’s development claim that it may even help detect patients infected with coronavirus at earlier stages, in comparison with current methods, while its results can be read with the “naked eye”, which makes it more available for a wider spectrum of healthcare units and specialists. This fast-molecular test has been recently registered by the FDA and utilizes a diagnostic system, which, in recent years, proved to function perfectly in diagnosing multiple infections (including Hepatitis C Virus—HCV and influenza) [
 <xref rid="B16-diagnostics-10-00434" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. RNA detection may be performed by means of RT-qPCR or reverse transcription–loop amplification (RT–LAMP). A standard RT-qPCR test takes 90 to 120 min on average to test a set of samples, whereas LAMP may be completed in 30 min. Indirect isothermal amplification (LAMP) is a fast technology of DNA amplification, which is applied in the detection of pathogens such as viruses or bacteria. LAMP reaction usually takes place at constant temperature, and the target DNA may be amplified in 30 min. LAMP method utilizes four or six starters for binding six regions of target DNA, its specificity is exceptionally high. Because SARS-CoV-2 is a RNA-type virus with a length of some 30 kb, a single reverse transcriptase (RT) reaction and LAMP may, jointly, significantly shorten the reaction time, omitting the stage of purifying cDNA from reverse transcriptase, and thanks to this, SARS-CoV-2 may be quickly detected. It has to be noted that similarly, a one-step RT-qPCR method does not require cDNA purification (a single stage reaction). The team from Oxford University developed four sets of LAMP starters (comprising six starters in each set/kit) focused on viral RNA of SARS-CoV-2 in the regions of ORF1ab, S gene, and N gene. For the interpretation of results, a colorimetric method has been applied, which enables the reading of the results of viral RNA amplification by the naked eye, without the necessity of using expensive equipment. Moreover, the sensitivity of the method may be 80 copies of viral RNA per 1 mL in the sample and single stage process (without separate RNA extraction), which enables the amplification of RNA directly from the sample [
 <xref rid="B17-diagnostics-10-00434" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-diagnostics-10-00434" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].
</p>
