<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par35">The structure–activity correlation of some metallic antimalarial complexes was studied. A series of copper (II) complexes containing naphthoquinone ligands were synthesized, characterized, and evaluated. All complexes exhibit enhanced antimalarial activity against 3D7 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> strains. Furthermore, correlations between the antimalarial activity and the metal redox couple indicate the component of the parasitic electron transport chain as a possible target of such compounds (Gokhale et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2006</xref>). Complexes containing buparvaquone of general formula [M(II)(L1)
 <sub>2</sub>(C2H
 <sub>5</sub>OH)
 <sub>2</sub>], where M(II) = Cu, Co, Ni, Mn, and Fe and L1 = buparvaquone ({3-trans-(4-tert-butylcyclohexyl) methyl-2-hydroxy-1,4-naphthoquinone}), were studied (Gokhale et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2003</xref>). The copper complex that showed better results demonstrated a thousand-fold enhancement in the antimalarial activity of parent quinone against 3D7 strain. Furthermore, this complex was three times more active against the chloroquine-resistant 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> K1 strain when compared to the free ligand. Experiments with this strain cellular showed a 90% reduction in parasitemia at a dose of 15 mg/kg, which demonstrates the high potential of the copper complex as antimalarial agent (Gokhale et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2003</xref>). The antimalarial activity of gold(I) thiosemicarbazone complexes (
 <bold>complexes 10</bold> and 
 <bold>11</bold>, Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">8.4</xref>) and platinum (II) and palladium(II) complexes with ligands derived from pyrazole (
 <bold>complexes 12</bold>–
 <bold>15</bold>, Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">8.4</xref>) was also investigated. These complexes exhibited better efficacy in comparison to their free ligands against D10, W2, and 3D7 strains of 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> (Khanye et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2010</xref>; Quirante et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">2011</xref>). Besides the enhancement of the efficacy of organic drugs, the metal complexes correspond to new alternatives for the treatment of malaria, such as the inhibition of the parasite establishment in the vector mosquito.
</p>
