<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Molecular surveillance is neither exclusive nor new to HIV. Due to recent technological advancements in low-cost, high-throughput genome sequencing technologies, genomic data for large numbers of samples can now be generated timely and at low cost. These genomic datasets provide clues regarding pathogen evolution and spread in human and animal populations and enable healthcare professionals and scientists to forecast and prevent future outbreaks. However, due to the sensitivity and stigma associated with HIV diagnosis, there are real risks associated with genetic tracking of HIV spread in populations [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-12-01018" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-12-01018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. It is important to note that the risks associated with genetic tracking of HIV are similar to name-based reporting that is common in all US states. For example, information obtained thorough named-based reporting such as contact tracing and some of the information gained from molecular surveillance may be sensitive information, such as the grouping of individuals linked by virus transmission or that certain groups have a higher burden of HIV transmission than others. While this information is important for public health decisions on prevention efforts, this type of information can be abused in the wrong hands, especially in countries where identification of HIV infected persons or routes of infection can lead to physical, legal, or social threats. For example, an HIV-positive, undocumented person living in the US could be charged with a crime, forming the grounds for deportation, for having sex even if appropriate protections are used [
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-12-01018" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In this and similar environments, identifying the movements of infection in a population is a risk to real people. Other potentially vulnerable and marginalized populations such as men who have sex with men (MSM), sex workers, and transgender persons may fear prosecution and exposure based on mere allegations of intentional virus transmission. The potential harm can also exist on the population level. For example, a recent study suggested that transgender women in Los Angeles County were more likely to be involved in HIV transmission networks [
 <xref rid="B4-viruses-12-01018" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Although the study did not establish that transgender women were more likely to spread HIV, these associations, however wrong or misinterpreted, can elevate the stigma associated with populations that need public health services [
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-12-01018" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The reality in the US is that 35 of 50 states have laws criminalizing the potential of HIV transmission via sexual or non-sexual contacts [
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-12-01018" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-12-01018" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] even when the risk of transmission is non-existent [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-12-01018" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. These laws are not simply “on the books” but are actively used to charge and convict people. In this environment, the risk to both individuals and communities is very real and cannot be dismissed lightly [
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-12-01018" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. In addition, most patients are likely unaware that their data is being communicated to state and federal agencies and used by parties other than the clinic or laboratory providing care. While public health surveillance does not require informed consent in the same way as medical research [
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-12-01018" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-12-01018" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], this practice may be perceived as a violation of patient privacy and can increase public mistrust in the government and medical practice. It may even discourage at-risk individuals to enroll in HIV care and thus cause more harm than good. Similarly, the nature of protocols in place to safeguard patient data and confidentiality are not completely known to the public. Finally, use of genetic sequence data to describe the flow of infection in populations may need to involve more than just an informed population but rather direct involvement of community representatives in the decision-making process that we address in this paper. The imperative of public health action is to protect the public health, but the nature of infectious diseases makes the ethical calculus involved difficult. However, it is not necessarily true that doing nothing is the best option.
</p>
