<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Of the species that fulfil these population characteristics and that live in close proximity to humans, bats have been highlighted as reservoirs of many emerging zoonotic diseases, such as SARS-like coronaviruses, henipaviruses, filoviruses and lyssaviruses 
 <xref rid="pone.0030346-Calisher1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. In some cases, multiple potentially-zoonotic viruses have been identified in a single host species, such as the straw-coloured fruit bat (
 <italic>Eidolon helvum</italic>). This migratory, tree-roosting species, forms very large seasonal colonies across sub-Saharan Africa 
 <xref rid="pone.0030346-Richter1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0030346-Funmilayo1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, often near large human populations 
 <xref rid="pone.0030346-Kingdon1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0030346-DeFrees1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. The timing of 
 <italic>E. helvum</italic> birth pulses and migrations vary across its continental range 
 <xref rid="pone.0030346-Mutere1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, but little is known about the connectivity between populations. This species has been identified as a reservoir for henipaviruses and Lagos bat virus (LBV, genus 
 <italic>Lyssavirus</italic>) in continental Africa 
 <xref rid="pone.0030346-Drexler1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0030346-Hayman2" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. Other viruses detected in 
 <italic>E. helvum</italic> include a novel orbivirus 
 <xref rid="pone.0030346-Kemp1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref> and rotavirus 
 <xref rid="pone.0030346-Esona1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref> (both via viral isolation), a coronavirus 
 <xref rid="pone.0030346-Tong1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref> (via PCR), and a filovirus 
 <xref rid="pone.0030346-Hayman3" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref> (via presence of antibodies), however insufficient information is available to determine whether it is an incidental or a reservoir host for these viruses. It could be hypothesised that the large asynchronous metapopulation of 
 <italic>E. helvum</italic> ensures an ongoing supply of susceptible individuals for new infections, however mechanisms of viral transmission and maintenance at the population level are unknown.
</p>
