<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par25">The animal experiments described here were performed under protocols approved by the Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee, adhering strictly to the NIH Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals. Influenza-free and specific pathogen-free 6-month-old female ferrets (
 <italic>Mustela putorious furo</italic>) were purchased from Triple F Farms. The animal’s sera were confirmed to be negative against circulating H1N1, H3N2, and B influenza viruses before they were shipped from the company. Upon receipt, the animals were handled only by trained personnel wearing an N95 mask (that prevents the transmission of airborne pathogens), and were immediately housed individually in PlasLabs poultry incubators fitted with high-efficiency particulate air (HEPA) filters to provide them with pathogen-free air through out the experiment. Prior to the start of the experiment, the animals were allowed to acclimate for 48 h before nasal inoculation. They were also provided with access to food and water ad libitum. All infections and nasal wash samples were done on ferrets anesthetized with ketamine (25 mg/kg) and xylazine (2 mg/kg) intramuscularly. A detailed time point study was conducted in ferrets infected with 1 × 10
 <sup>6</sup> plaque-forming units diluted in a final volume of 0.5 ml of sterile PBS per animal of the A/Netherlands/602/2009 H1N1 pandemic strain through intranasal inoculation. Control animals were mock infected only with 0.5 ml of sterile PBS. Then nasal wash samples were taken from the seven uninfected and seven infected animals. To study the effect of IAV infection on the URT microbiome, samples were taken at six different time points: on day 0 (1 h post inoculation) and then on days 1, 3, 5, 7, and 14 post infection (dpi). Body weights were obtained for 14 consecutive days, and viral titers were determined by plaque assay in MDCK cells as previously described
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup> for the first 7 dpi.
</p>
