<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28">The current situation resembles the situation that happened with SARS in the 2002–2003 outbreak and the Ebola outbreak in 2014–2015 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>]. During this outbreak, special quarantine rules and protocols were set up to limit and identify the patient’s contact risk. There were no unique antiviral treatments available for SARS and Ebola at the time of outbreaks as situations were beyond control, similar to the SARS-CoV-2 outbreak. As the structure of the virus is known, so to prevent the virus entry and replication within the body of the host, various inhibitors producing hurdles at different steps are explored and tested in cell-based systems [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">108</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">109</xref>]. They involve spike (S) protein inhibitors, S cleavage inhibitors, helicase and protease inhibitors, fusion core blockers, mAbs against host cell receptor, anti-viral peptide targeting S2, RBD–ACE2 blockers, antiviral peptides, siRNAs, neutralizing antibodies, convalescent-phase plasma, repurposed drugs, among others [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">110</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">112</xref>]. During the current outbreak and pandemic situation, patients require immediate treatment. The below sections will emphasize on different potential treatment options that could be pursued for therapy despite limited knowledge of the biology of SARS-CoV-2. Food and Drug Development Agency (FDA) has started Coronavirus Treatment Acceleration Program (CTAP), and presently there are more than 570 drug development programmes in planning stages, 270 plus trials reviewed, two treatments currently authorized for emergency use however no treatment is yet approved by FDA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref>]. Of these treatments under investigation, more than 20 are based on antivirals, cell and gene therapies, 90 plus are based on immunomodulators, 30 plus on neutralizing antibodies, more than 70 include other treatments when the 30 plus are of combinations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref>]. More than 210 have reached late stages when the 60 plus are at early stages of drug trials [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref>]. The use of chloroquine/hydroxychloroquine has also been suggested [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114">114</xref>], though with some risk of harm. Besides, the evidence to support the use of lopinavir/ritonavir and remdesivir have also come up for treating COVID-19 patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115">115</xref>].
</p>
