<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para190">We analysed data for subgroup effects by virus type, intervention (different distances or face mask types), and setting (health care 
 <italic>vs</italic> non-health care). Among the studies assessing physical distancing measures to prevent viral transmission, the intervention varied (eg, direct physical contact [0 m], 1 m, or 2 m). We, therefore, analysed the effect of distance on the size of the associations by random-effects univariate meta-regressions, using restricted maximum likelihood, and we present mean effects and 95% CIs. We calculated tests for interaction using a minimum of 10 000 Monte Carlo random permutations to avoid spurious findings.
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>30</sup>
 </xref> We formally assessed the credibility of potential effect-modifiers using GRADE guidance.
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref> We did two sensitivity analyses to test the robustness of our findings. First, we used Bayesian meta-analyses to reinterpret the included studies considering priors derived from the effect point estimate and variance from a meta-analysis of ten randomised trials evaluating face mask use versus no face mask use to prevent influenza-like illness in health-care workers.
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>31</sup>
 </xref> Second, we used Bayesian meta-analyses to reinterpret the efficacy of N95 respirators versus medical masks on preventing influenza-like illness after seasonal viral (mostly influenza) infection.
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref> For these sensitivity analyses, we used hybrid Metropolis-Hastings and Gibbs sampling, a 10 000 sample burn-in, 40 000 Markov chain Monte Carlo samples, and we tested non-informative and sceptical priors (eg, four time variance)
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> to inform mean estimates of effect, 95% credibility intervals (CrIs), and posterior distributions. We used non-informative hyperpriors to estimate statistical heterogeneity. Model convergence was confirmed in all cases with good mixing in visual inspection of trace plots, autocorrelation plots, histograms, and kernel density estimates in all scenarios. Parameters were blocked, leading to acceptance of approximately 50% and efficiency greater than 1% in all cases (typically about 40%). We did analyses using Stata version 14.3.
</p>
