<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par39">The innate immune system of mosquitoes consists of two tightly interconnected responses: the cellular and humoral defense responses. These two responses act together to protect mosquitoes against a wide variety of pathogens, including bacteria, yeast and viruses. The cellular defense response includes phagocytosis, nodulation and encapsulation of pathogens by hemocytes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Humoral responses refer to the activation of downstream signaling and effector responses, leading to the synthesis and secretion of soluble effector molecules, such as antimicrobial peptides (AMPs), reactive oxygen species (ROS) and components of the phenoloxidase cascade [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Downstream signaling and humoral effector responses will be discussed later in this review. These effector molecules are secreted into the hemolymph to control infection caused by invading pathogens [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Epithelial cells in the mosquito midgut are the first line of defense against many pathogens which are acquired from blood-feeding and these cells can synthesize several AMPs and ROS. Additionally, the fat body of the mosquito is the primary site of the humoral response 
 <italic>via</italic> production and secretion of AMPs. The transcription of innate immunity genes encoding for AMPs is highly dependent on several signaling cascade pathways, including the Janus kinase-signal transducer and activator of transcription (JAK-STAT), Toll and immune deficiency (Imd) pathways [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Although activation of these pathways has been shown to limit viral replication, the most robust antiviral defense is the RNA interference (RNAi) pathway. The RNAi pathway produces small RNAs using viral double-stranded RNA as a template to ultimately target the viral RNA for degradation, thereby inhibiting viral replication [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Virus recognition is mediated by pattern recognition receptors (PRRs) that recognize virus-conserved pathogen-associated molecular patterns (PAMPs) to initiate innate immune responses.
</p>
