<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>RdRp, also termed as NSP 12, is a pivotal enzyme of RNA viruses, including coronavirus, that catalyzes the replication of RNA from an RNA template, probably with the assistance of NSP7 and NSP8 as co‐factors (Guo, Huang, Lin, &amp; Lv, 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0071" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>; Kirchdoerfer &amp; Ward, 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0095" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>; Subissi et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0162" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Venkataraman, Prasad, &amp; Selvarajan, 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0174" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). A protein complex consisting of NSP 7, NSP 8, and NSP 12 of SARS‐CoV‐2 is related to that of SARS‐CoV with a root‐mean‐square deviation value of 0.82 for 1,078 Cɑ atoms (Gao et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). RdRp protein of SARS‐CoV‐2 and SARS‐CoV share 96% amino acid sequence identity and 82% sequence identity at their genomic RNA level (Morse, Lalonde, Xu, &amp; Liu, 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0129" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). The RdRp of SARS‐CoV‐2 contains a large and deep groove as an active site for the polymerization of RNA. Residues that show variations between the SARS‐CoV‐2 and SARS‐CoV RdRps are mostly distal to this active site. This high sequence conservation and structural homogeneity of RdRp in coronaviruses suggest that nucleotide analogs developed for the SARS‐CoV RdRp are likely to be effective against the SARS‐CoV‐2 RdRp (Morse et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0129" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Previously published literature provides convincing evidence that RdRp could be a druggable target for the development of potent therapy against SARS‐CoV‐2 infection (Kandeel, Ibrahim, Fayez, &amp; Al‐Nazawi, 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0085" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>; Lung et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0115" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>), which includes nucleotide analog targeting RdRp (Deval, Jin, Chuang, &amp; Kao, 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Gordon et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>; Stephen &amp; Lin, 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0159" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Tchesnokov, Feng, Porter, &amp; Götte, 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0167" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). Remdesivir (GS‐5734), a prodrug and adenosine analog, can be incorporated into nascent viral RNA, and subsequently inhibit the RdRp (Siegel et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0155" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Furthermore, Remdesivir showed high considerable efficacy in controlling SARS‐CoV‐2 infection in a recent in vitro study (Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0179" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). β‐D‐N4‐hydroxycytidine, a ribonucleoside analog, also inhibits SARS‐CoV‐2 replication as evidenced by reducing viral genomic RNA (Sheahan et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0149" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>).
</p>
