<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0425">Three world-wide (pandemic) outbreaks of influenza virus (IV) occurred in the 20th century, in 1918, 1957, and 1968. They are now known to represent three different antigenic subtypes of influenza A virus: H1N1, H2N2, and H3N2, respectively.
 <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>71</sup>
 </xref> The 1918 “Spanish Flu” epidemic claimed an estimated 50 million lives and 20%–40% of the worldwide population became ill; approximately 675,000 Americans died during this epidemic.
 <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>72</sup>
 </xref> Since then, IV infections have caused more than 20,000 deaths yearly in each of the 20 epidemics from 1957 to 1991,
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>73</sup>
 </xref> and greater than 40,000 deaths occurred in each of the more recent epidemics, Thus, IV is a formidable pathogen.
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>74</sup>
 </xref> While influenza-related mortality can in part be attributed to direct effects on the respiratory system, many of the deaths associated with IV infection are caused by increases in susceptibility to secondary bacterial pneumonia.
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>75</sup>
 </xref> In fact, it has been suggested that the major mortality and morbidity resulting from IV infection may be caused by secondary bacterial infection that is associated with the inhibition of neutrophil function.
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>73</sup>
 </xref> The bacteria commonly causing pneumonia in the most severely ill influenza patients are 
 <italic>Streptococcus(S.) pneumoniae</italic>, 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, and 
 <italic>Haemophilus influenzae</italic>. Together, IV infection itself, and secondary bacterial pneumonia, were the most common causes of infectious death in the United States in 2002.
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>76</sup>
 </xref> Research, clinical, and epidemiological studies show that there is a positive correlation between the increase in morbidity and mortality during influenza epidemics and pandemics, and an increase in secondary 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> infection.
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>75</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>77</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>78</sup>
 </xref> It has been hypothesized that influenza infection alters neutrophil function, thereby reducing the effectiveness of phagocyte-mediated killing of bacteria. An alternative hypothesis is that the tissue damage caused by IV alters the epithelial surface of the respiratory tract, thereby exposing different surface receptors to which 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> adhere, and/or increasing the affinity of 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> for its receptors, which may result in increased growth and decreased neutrophil killing of 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> in the respiratory tract. Support for the former hypothesis comes from reports using both 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> models of influenza infection.
 <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref> Neutrophils are important in resistance to 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> infection independent of an influenza infection.
 <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>91</sup>
 </xref> Influenza A virus alters the three major properties of the neutrophil that are crucial for bacterial clearance, namely chemotactic responsiveness, phagocytosis, and intracellular killing. This alteration of neutrophil function likely increases the susceptibility of an influenza-infected patient to 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> infection because of decreased phagocytosis and killing of these bacteria by neutrophils.
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>80</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>84</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>89</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>92</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
