<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0430">In humans, IV was reported to alter cell function by interacting with G proteins.
 <xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>81</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>90</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>93</sup>
 </xref> Human neutrophils express monomeric and trimeric G proteins that have critical roles in activation and regulation of various signal pathways, leading to chemotaxis and metabolic function.
 <xref rid="bib94" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>94</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib95" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>95</sup>
 </xref> Susceptibility to 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> in mice is greatest at six days after influenza infection, consistent with the clinical findings.
 <xref rid="bib96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref> Influenza-induced tissue damage is also greatest six days after influenza infection, as is adherence of 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> to murine influenza-infected tracheas.
 <xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>100</sup>
 </xref> Influenza-induced neutrophil dysfunction is also greatest six days after influenza infection,
 <xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>101</sup>
 </xref> and murine mortality secondary to 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> infection is greatest seven days after infection. Although neutrophils accumulate in the lungs of mice infected with influenza by day six, they do not function in resistance to 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic>. Thus, it is likely that bactericidal function of lung neutrophils is suppressed, making these influenza-infected mice susceptible to 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic>. Effective neutrophil phagocytosis and killing of 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> is necessary to eliminate 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> from the lungs.
 <xref rid="bib102" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>102</sup>
 </xref> Neutrophils are affected within 30 min of 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> influenza infection,
 <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>83</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>84</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>87</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>89</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib103" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>103</sup>
 </xref> with some effects seen as rapidly as 5 min after incubation with IV. Changes in infected neutrophils include decreased protein phosphorylation, accelerated apoptosis, decreased respiratory burst activity, an altered cytoskeleton, depressed bactericidal capacity identified by release of reactive oxygen species, decreased chemotactic ability, decreased adherence, decreased release of lactoferrin into phagosomes, and inhibition of lysosome–phagosome fusion.
 <xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>81</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>82</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>84</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>87</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>89</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>92</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib103" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>103</sup>
 </xref> In addition, the effects of influenza virus infection on neutrophil function are not limited to the lungs, indicating that these effects are systemic in nature.
 <xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>89</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>90</sup>
 </xref> Influenza infection also increases susceptibility to 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> by increasing cytokine production (TNF, IFN-γ, MCP-1, IL-10, IL-6) in the lung.
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>75</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
