<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0395">In adult HCT and hematologic malignancy patients with RSV lower respiratory tract infection, use of aerosolized ribavirin was associated with decreased mortality. Oral or IV ribavirin although not statistically significant as the effect was smaller.
 <xref rid="bib_11" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib_12" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref> Of note, some data suggest pediatric HCT recipients with RSV have little morbidity and mortality even without ribavirin therapy.
 <xref rid="bib_35" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>35</sup>
 </xref> Current international guidelines recommend aerosolized or systemic (oral or IV) ribavirin with intravenous immunoglogulin (IVIG) in patients with RSV upper respiratory tract infection undergoing allogeneic HCT, allogeneic HCT recipients with risk factors for progression to lower respiratory tract infection, and allogeneic HCT patients with lower respiratory tract infection.
 <xref rid="bib_36" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>36</sup>
 </xref> Recommendations for ribavirin administration for HCT and SOT recipients, and oncology patients are outlined in 
 <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 21.1</xref> . Most data and guidance for use of ribavirin are in HCT and oncology; few studies have clearly demonstrated efficacy in SOT recipients, and most data are in lung transplant when both oral and IV ribavirin have been used,
 <xref rid="bib_37" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>37</sup>
 </xref> For HCT and oncology patients, high-risk situations include patients with lymphopenia; additional risk factors, such as smoking history and use of high-dose total body irradiation, could be used to further risk-stratify patients. In general, aerosolized ribavirin is reserved for subjects with virologically confirmed (BAL positive for RSV) lower respiratory tract infection. It is administered by small-particle aerosol from a solution containing the drug at a concentration of 20 mg/mL sterile water via aerosol for 2 to 20 hours/day, or at a concentration of 60 mg/mL water over 2 hours 3 times daily. Aerosol administration results in high levels of ribavirin in the secretions, with levels exceeding 1000 μM and little systemic absorption. The potential environmental release of ribavirin has caused concern in hospital personnel because of the potential teratogenicity of ribavirin and thus exposure is contraindicated in pregnant women because of its teratogenic potential. Administration of ribavirin via a ventilator, using a high-dose, short-duration method of drug delivery or with a vacuum-exhausted treatment hood, results in minimal or no detectable ribavirin in the rooms of treated children.
</p>
