<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <title>Abstract</title>
 <sec id="s2">
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>Parechovirus-A3 (PeV-A3) causes severe disease, including sepsis and meningoencephalitis in young infants. The first case of PeV-A3 was reported in Japan in 1999 and, although epidemics have been reported every 2 to 3 years in more than 20 countries, no major epidemic has occurred in Japan since 2014.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>This prospective study included febrile infants (&lt;4 months of age) admitted at Niigata University and its affiliated hospitals, which serve about 2.5 million people, during the period from 2014 to 2018. Neonates and infants younger than 4 months presenting with fever and suspected of having viral sepsis underwent serum and/or cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) testing by real-time PCR for parechovirus-A (PeV-A) and enteroviruses (EVs), and for herpes simplex viruses, if suspected. Bacterial infection was excluded on the basis of the results of bacterial culture of blood, urine, and/or CSF. PeV-A genotype was identified by examining the viral protein 1 (VP1) sequence, and the phylogenetic tree of the VP1 sequence was constructed.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4">
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>Of the 277 patients evaluated, 135 (49%) were positive for PeV-A (
   <italic>n =</italic> 74, 27%) or EVs (
   <italic>n =</italic> 61, 22%). Among PeV-A patients, most had PeV-A3 (
   <italic>n =</italic> 69; 93%), followed by PeV-A4 (
   <italic>n =</italic> 4; 5%). There was a PeV-A3 epidemic in 2014 (
   <italic>n =</italic> 43); however, no cases were reported in 2015. In 2016–2018, small numbers of PeV-A3 cases were reported: 10 in 2016, 7 in 2017, and 9 in 2018. In contrast, EV cases were reported throughout this period: 8 in 2014, 22 in 2015, 10 in 2016, 5 in 2017, and 16 in 2018. When data were analyzed by season, the PeV-A3 detection rate in summer (June-August) was 93% (40/43) in 2014 and 65% (17/26) during 2016–2018, indicating an increase in the number of PeV-A3 cases in seasons other than summer. Phylogenetic analysis showed that PeV-A3 strains during 2016–2018 were part of a cluster of epidemics in 2011 and differed from those in 2014.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s5">
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p>After the major PeV-A3 epidemics in 2014, we observed changes in the PeV-A3 epidemic profile, namely, a small, but constant, number of cases every year in Niigata, Japan. A future study should investigate if this trend has continued in Japan and other countries and identify the causes of this change in epidemic profile.</p>
  <p>
   <graphic xlink:href="ofidis_ofz360_f2359.jpg" position="float" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s6">
  <title>Disclosures</title>
  <p>
   <bold>All authors:</bold> No reported disclosures.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
