<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0125">Combating the current outbreak requires rigorous steps to reduce the transmission of COVID-19 infection from person to person. Special attention and efforts should be applied for protecting or reducing transmission in vulnerable populations, including infants, health care providers and the elderly. For medical personnel, health care professionals, public health individuals and researchers involved in the 2019-nCoV guidelines to follow are published [
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. The early death cases in COVID-19 outbreak occurred mainly in the elderly possibly due to a poor immune system that allows for more rapid progression of viral infection [
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The decontaminating regents should be provided by public services and facilities regularly. The physical contact with contaminated things particularly urine and facecal samples should be considered in dealing with the virus as these can potentially serve as an alternative route of transmission [
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Most of the countries around the world particularly US, China, India, UAE etc have implemented major control and prevention measures like implementing state wise or country wise lockdown and travel screenings so as to control virus spread. The epidemiological changes occurring in COVID-19 infection should be monitored carefully taking into account potential transmission routes and subclinical infections, as well as the adaptation, evolution, possible intermediate animals and reservoir and spread of virus among humans. A large number of issues still remain to be addressed. Some of which are who and how many were tested, what percentage of these came out positive, weather this rate remains constant or it varies. What proposition of people tested positive for COVID-19 but showed clinical symptoms. So far only few paediatric cases were reported, it is because real lack of susceptibility or due to inadequate testing.
</p>
