<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Interestingly, we noticed that both the contemporary isolates induced significantly higher amounts of dsRNA in the U-251 MG astrocytoma cells, while ZIKV
 <sup>BR</sup> specifically was able to replicate to significantly higher titers in these cells. Moreover, the contemporary isolates had a higher MFI of dsRNA-positive cells, with ZIKV
 <sup>BR</sup> in particular having a greater number of dsRNA foci per cell in the astrocytomas. Further quantification of positive- and negative-strand vRNA during infection revealed that the Asian lineage isolates generate more negative-strand replicative intermediate RNA than the African lineage isolate. Overall, this data supports the hypothesis that Asian lineage isolates may have a higher replicative fitness in astrocytoma cells. This is supported by the greater ratio of negative-strand replicative intermediate vRNA, and greater amounts of dsRNA foci per cell, as well as the significant increase in titer observed in ZIKV
 <sup>BR</sup> in this cell type (which correlates well with the increase in negative-strand vRNA and dsRNA foci). On the other hand, it could be argued that ZIKV
 <sup>AF</sup> may have the replicative advantage since it produces similar levels of positive-strand vRNA from fewer negative-strand intermediates; however, this does not appear to translate into higher viral infectious titers for this isolate. In addition to the higher infectious titers observed in ZIKV
 <sup>BR</sup> infection, it is also possible that, consistent with the greater amount of dsRNA-positive cells during ZIKV
 <sup>PR</sup> infection, this isolate may also mirror the increase in titer observed at later time points post-infection. However, our data suggests that ZIKV
 <sup>PR</sup> titers have plateaued by 24 h post-infection at MOI 10 in both cell types (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00728-f001">Figure 1</xref>B,C). As such, ZIKV
 <sup>BR</sup> may have an additional advantage over ZIKV
 <sup>PR</sup> in a post-replication step of the viral life cycle. In addition to the kinetic advantage ZIKV
 <sup>BR</sup> has over a single infectious cycle, this isolate also appears to have a viral replicative fitness advantage over the other ZIKV isolates at low MOI when fewer cells are infected. The similar or higher viral titers produced by ZIKV
 <sup>BR</sup> at the low MOI implies more infectious particles are released per cell during infection with this isolate. However, the higher titers of ZIKV
 <sup>BR</sup> observed in the multistep growth curve, even when the % infected cells are low, may be due to compounded differences in replication kinetics over several rounds of viral replication.
</p>
