<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Vaccines and drugs for SARS-CoV-2 are the goals of global scientific competition. DNA vaccines are leading ahead of protein vaccines. The nanoparticle vaccine composed of a stabilized form of the respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) fusion (F) protein is fused to ferritin nanoparticle (Pre-F-NP) and modified with glycans to mask poorly neutralizing epitopes, thereby eliciting a potent immune response in mice and primates.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref139">139</xref>
 </sup> Sinovac Biotech has announced a vaccine that can protect monkeys from new coronavirus infections. Moreover, Moderna and CanSino have launched small vaccine clinical trials against COVID-19. Broad-spectrum antivirals inhibit SARS-CoV-2 in human airway epithelial cells and in mice.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref140">140</xref>
 </sup> Furthermore, a systematic study of viral–host interactions identifies 332 high-confidence SARS-CoV-2 human protein–protein interactions (PPI) and 66 druggable PPIs targeted by 69 compounds.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref141">141</xref>
 </sup> The receptor-binding domain is implicated in a viral attachment inhibitor and vaccine.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref142">142</xref>
 </sup> Besides, the structure of the main protease of SARS-CoV-2 has led to the development of two lead compounds with good pharmacokinetic properties in cell assays.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref143">143</xref>
 </sup> A new α-ketoamide inhibitor reveals a pronounced lung tropism and suitability for administration by inhalation.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref144">144</xref>
 </sup> CIRSPR is an alternative strategy for viral RNA inhibition and degradation.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref145">145</xref>
 </sup> The race to find COVID-19 treatments is accelerating and may take a few months or a few years or never succeed. The development of AI-assisted plug-and-read diagnostic robots and the enforcement of social contact patterns will be critical in preventing COVID-19 epidemics before the appearance of vaccines and drugs.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref146">146</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
