<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Preclinical studies have shown that this vaccine was highly immunogenic and that induced antibodies were able to recognize and react against not only homologous genotypes but also heterologous genotypes, such as GI.3, GII.1, GII.3, and GIV.1 (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Use of this bivalent preparation adjuvanted with MPL and aluminum hydroxide in adults aged 18–83 years in two phase I studies confirmed the immunogenicity of the bivalent vaccine (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Two doses one month apart were administered. Antibodies against GI.1 and GII.4 increased rapidly, reaching a peak level at ~7 days after the first injection. First-dose seroresponse frequencies ranged from 88 to 100% for the GI.1 antigen and from 69 to 84% for the GII.4 antigen. However, the booster effect of the second dose was modest. In most subjects, a significant increase in HBGA-blocking antibody titres was evidenced, without differences according to age. The clinical efficacy of the bivalent vaccine seemed indicated by the data collected with a double-blind, placebo-controlled trial that enrolled adults aged 18–50 years. These subjects received two doses of placebo or bivalent vaccine 4 weeks apart and were challenged with a GII.4 virus not included in the consensus GII.4 sequence. Monitoring of clinical conditions after challenge revealed that signs and symptoms of NoV disease were less common and less severe in vaccine recipients than in controls, although differences did not reach statistical significance. Severe, moderate or mild vomiting and diarrhea were evidenced in vaccinees at rates of 0, 6, and 20.0%, respectively, compared to rates of 8.3% (
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.054), 18.8% (
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.068), and 37.5% (
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.074), respectively, for controls. Moreover, the modified Vesikari score for AGE severity was reduced in vaccinees from 7.3, calculated in controls, to 4.5 (
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.002). Finally, a lower number of subjects receiving the vaccine had virus shedding by day 10 after challenge than that of controls (22.4% of vaccinees vs. 36.2% of controls; 
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.179). No severe adverse event was observed (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>).
</p>
