<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="alpha-lower" id="list1-0004563220928361">
 <list-item>
  <p>Angiotensin type 1 (AT1) was originally thought to be the only receptor of angiotensin II and its actions are facilitated via this receptor.
   <sup>
    <xref rid="bibr29-0004563220928361" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
   </sup> Genetic polymorphisms are associated with hypertension and myocardial infarction. Abnormal activation of AT1 is associated with cardiovascular disease, inflammation and atherosclerosis, endothelial dysfunction, oxidative stress, insulin resistance, cancer and malignant hypertension. AT1 receptor blockers (ARB) are selective antagonists used to treat hypertension and cardiovascular disorders.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Angiotensin type 2 (AT2) has a 34% homology with AT1 but low expression in adults. Concentrations decrease soon after birth and it is found in low concentrations in the adult cardiovascular system, adrenal glands, kidney, brain, uterine myometrium and skin. Upregulation may occur in physiological stressful conditions such as vascular injury, myocardial infarction and cardiac failure.
   <sup>
    <xref rid="bibr29-0004563220928361" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
   </sup> Studies in knockout mice demonstrated the development of hypertension. Mutation of the receptor is also associated with mental retardation, and it plays a role in antidiuretic and antinatriuretic functions. As it is also found in brain tissue,
   <sup>
    <xref rid="bibr28-0004563220928361" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
   </sup> it was investigated as a possible therapeutic target for neuropathic pain. However, the treatment had poor efficacy and many side effects.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>MAS is the receptor for angiotensin (1–7) which is produced by ACE2. Activation of MAS leads to the synthesis of arachidonic acid and activation of nitric oxide (NO) synthase. High expression of MAS is found in the brain, where it is important for cardiovascular regulation. It was also found to play an important role in testicular function where immunolocalization of angiotensin (1–7), and MAS receptors showed impaired spermatogenesis in male infertility.
   <sup>
    <xref rid="bibr30-0004563220928361" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
   </sup> Knockout mice present with altered heart rate and decreased blood pressure possibly due to NO imbalance and the formation of reactive oxygen species. The protective role of MAS-angiotensin (1–7) has made it a possible drug target.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Angiotensin type 4 (AT4) receptor is beyond the scope of this review.</p>
 </list-item>
</list>
