<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The autumn/winter of 2016/2017 saw the return of H5N8 into Europe from Asia [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180257C210" ref-type="bibr">210</xref>] by a sister clade of the 2014/2015 viruses (rather than a direct continuation of the 2014/2015 lineage). The pathogenicity of the new 2016/2017 H5N8 viruses appears to be greater in ducks and has caused more deaths in wild birds [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180257C211" ref-type="bibr">211</xref>] than the previous 2014/2015 H5N8 viruses [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180257C212" ref-type="bibr">212</xref>]. Additionally, the transmission of the 2016/2017 viruses out of eastern Asia was by a more southerly route than previously observed, with detection in May 2016 around Qinghai Lake in wild birds [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180257C213" ref-type="bibr">213</xref>], near Uvs-Nuur Lake, near the Russian–Mongolian border, in June 2016 [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180257C210" ref-type="bibr">210</xref>], and finally in India, the Middle East and Europe in November 2016 [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180257C211" ref-type="bibr">211</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20180257C214" ref-type="bibr">214</xref>–
 <xref rid="RSTB20180257C218" ref-type="bibr">218</xref>] as a result of winter southward migrations. Reassortment events between the incoming HPAI H5N8 strain and other co-circulating LPAI strains occurred frequently in the 2016/2017 season, including the generation and transmission of H5N5 viruses. Multiple incursions of these HPAI H5NX strains into European countries occurred [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180257C217" ref-type="bibr">217</xref>], causing the worst epidemic so far in Germany, affecting both domestic and wild birds [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180257C214" ref-type="bibr">214</xref>]. In the following season (2017/2018), a new reassortant H5N6 derived from the 2016/2017 H5N8 viruses (i.e. different from the H5N6 that infected humans in Asia) was detected in the UK, The Netherlands and Germany in December 2017 and early 2018 [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180257C219" ref-type="bibr">219</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20180257C220" ref-type="bibr">220</xref>]. Most recently (September 2018), The Netherlands and Germany have reported their first H5N6 detection of the autumn 2018 season [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180257C221" ref-type="bibr">221</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20180257C222" ref-type="bibr">222</xref>].
</p>
