<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Where viruses reside in the time between their epidemic occurrences is often unclear. Sporadic cases of apparent infections occur repeatedly; in such cases, the virus is probably transmitted by healthy people with asymptomatic (inapparent) infections. Some viral species are able to survive in the environment for considerable time before they infect their hosts again; these include parvoviruses and rotaviruses (10.1007/978-3-642-20718-1_17 and 10.1007/978-3-642-20718-1_20), picornaviruses (10.1007/978-3-642-20718-1_14) and also poxviruses (10.1007/978-3-642-20718-1_19). Even now, poliovirus is occasionally reintroduced from countries that are not free of poliovirus infections (e.g. India and several African countries), and it proliferates in sero-negative people until a developing herd immunity or specific outbreak-control vaccinations eliminate the virus from the corresponding population. In contrast, other pathogens such as rubella virus and most paramyxoviruses (10.1007/978-3-642-20718-1_14 and 10.1007/978-3-642-20718-1_15) are instable in the environment, and do not infect animals. They are completely eliminated from the organism by the immune system during the course of infection. Only little is known concerning their whereabouts during the periods between sporadically occurring infections or epidemics. The first appearance of such a viral species must have been linked to human urbanization because such a virus would disappear from small, isolated human populations; therefore, it must be a phylogenetically relatively new virus, which could maintain its infection chains only in populations with a relatively high density. The term “emerging virus diseases” includes infectious diseases in which the viruses have been transmitted to a new host (such as SARS coronavirus; 10.1007/978-3-642-20718-1_14) or appear again as re-emerging viruses after long periods of time, as is the case for some hantaviruses (10.1007/978-3-642-20718-1_16).</p>
