<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In HIS mice, there is a disconnect between the cytokine response of the human immune system, and both the remaining mouse myeloid system and the non-hematopoietic mouse cells. While immune cells are often considered the main producers of important cytokines, other cells can also strongly impact the cytokine milieu [
 <xref rid="B88-vaccines-08-00098" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. Thus, non-hematopoietic murine endothelia and hepatocytes could contribute significantly to cytokine production, along with other murine myeloid cells that many VHFs preferentially infect. Limited cross-reactivity of human and mouse cytokines [
 <xref rid="B89-vaccines-08-00098" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>] prevents a full assessment of causes and effects in these models, as does omitting or neglecting assessment of mouse cytokines during these studies. Unobserved parallel murine cytokine messaging from endothelial or other murine cells harboring virus could occur in HIS mouse disease models [
 <xref rid="B41-vaccines-08-00098" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-vaccines-08-00098" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-vaccines-08-00098" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], but is not commonly investigated. Even less is known about the extent of human immune cell interactions with murine tissue ligands. Tissue ligands are another important factor of communication to immune cells, yet by not studying cross-reactive effects between mice and humans, the immune cells are essentially kept in undefined stimulatory milieus. Finally, VHFs also target non-immune cells during infection [
 <xref rid="B41-vaccines-08-00098" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-vaccines-08-00098" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-vaccines-08-00098" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], which further complicates studies in HIS mice due to the limited interaction of human immune cells with murine soma. In the absence of key murine immune cells, viral infection of murine cells cannot be ordinarily antagonized, which may additionally alter recapitulation of immunological events found in natural infection.
</p>
