<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0065">Viral vector vaccine works by carrying a DNA express or antigen(s) into host cells, thereby eliciting cell-mediated immunity in addition to the humoral immune responses. Viral Vectors Vaccines characterized by strong immunogenicity and safety.
 <xref rid="bib0390" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>33</sup>
 </xref> Several viral vectors are available for vaccine development including vaccinia, modified vaccinia virus Ankara (MVA), adenovirus (Ad), adeno-associated virus (AAV), retrovirus/lentivirus, alphavirus, herpes virus, Newcastle disease virus, poxvirus, and others. Viral vectors can be replicating or non-replicating viruses.
 <xref rid="bib0395" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>34</sup>
 </xref> Adenovirus and modified vaccinia virus Ankara (MVA) are the most common viral vectors used in vaccine developments as shown in 
 <xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> . There are over 50 subtypes of human Ad, with Ad serotype 5 (Ad5) is a stable, non-replicating virus that used in several vaccine development. This virus allows the insertion of large segments of foreign DNA (∼8 kb) into its genome. But, pre-existing immunity against human Ad5 is widespread, hampering its use as a vector for vaccine development.
 <xref rid="bib0400" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>35</sup>
 </xref> Chimpanzee adenovirus (ChAdOx1) represents an alternative to the human Ad vector due to its safety and lack of preexisting immunity in humans.
 <xref rid="bib0405" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>36</sup>
 </xref> Mice immunized with the Ad5 vector encoding the S protein-induced systemic neutralizing antibodies and mucosal T-cells immunity. Ad5 vectors encoding the S1 domain of the S protein displayed stronger neutralizing antibody responses than that encoding the full length, suggesting the effect of immune focusing.
 <xref rid="bib0410" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>37</sup>
 </xref> Currently, Can Sino Biological Inc. and the Beijing Institute of Biotechnology are developing Ad5- vector COVID-19 vaccine candidate in Phase 1(ChiCTR2000030906). Another adenovirus vectored vaccine developed by Chen Wei group entered in phase 1 clinical trial (NCT04313127). Johnson &amp; Johnson is developing an adenovirus vectored vaccine using AdVac®/PER.C6® vaccine platforms. Shenzhen Geno-Immune Medical Institute also developing two lentivirus vector based vaccine candidates named COVID-19/aAPC and LVSMENP- DC. Recombinant MVA, Newcastle disease virus (NDV), and poxvirus used as a viral-vector vaccine candidate due to their safety, efficacy, and decent immunogenicity.
 <xref rid="bib0415" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>38</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
