<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A recent study of the emerging tomato leaf curl New Delhi begomovirus (ToLCNDV) in Spain [
 <xref rid="B88-plants-09-00667" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>] also underlined the importance of wild 
 <italic>Solanaceae</italic> plants in research regarding virus population dynamics. It was found that ToLCNDV shows higher within-host genetic diversity and has a higher mutation rate in jimson weed compared to cultivated plants. Further, because of jimson weed extensive presence in cucurbit fields, it can serve as an inoculum source, as confirmed by the absence of signs of segregation in the ToLCNDV population, even when samples were collected from host plants belonging to different families. Another study by Ma et al. [
 <xref rid="B89-plants-09-00667" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>] took a closer look at the viral populations exchange between tomato and black nightshade. A novel virus called solanum nigrum ilarvirus 1 (SnIV 1) was capable of infecting both black nightshade and tomato, but was only prevalent in black nightshade populations. SnIV 1 was found in black nightshade regardless of whether plants grew side by side with tomato or not, suggesting that while SnIV1 is able to remain in black nightshade populations independent of the presence of tomato, infection in tomato was a consequence of the SnIV 1 transfer from black nightshade. This novel virus is phylogenetically close to other ilaviruses known to cause diseases in tomato, such as tomato necrotic spot virus (ToNSV) and tomato isolates of parietaria mottle virus (PMoV), which are responsible for outbreaks in the USA and Europe, respectively [
 <xref rid="B90-plants-09-00667" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. This suggests a scenario of occasional, possibly pollen-mediated, transfer from a black nightshade reservoir to neighboring tomato crops followed by further spread from tomato to tomato. At the same time, there seems to be an inability to persist in tomato over the long term, possibly as a consequence of limited or nil cultivation during the winter period. Further, it was found that PVY infection was prevalent in black nightshade populations only at tomato sites, which suggests a PVY spillover effect from tomato, opposite to the SnIV-1 example. In the same study, broad bean wilt virus (BBWV) was detected in black nightshade plants only, even though its ability to infect tomatoes has been previously demonstrated [
 <xref rid="B91-plants-09-00667" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>], suggesting the existence of (an) unknown ecological barrier(s) preventing BBWV1 efficient spread from black nightshade to tomato under local conditions. It is apparent that viral exchange between cultivated and wild plants is a relevant factor for the functioning of the populations of these three viruses, and that transfer can happen in both directions, from wild to cultivated and from cultivated to wild, driven by underlying biological and ecological forces that need to be better understood in the future for more effective prevention practices [
 <xref rid="B89-plants-09-00667" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>].
</p>
