<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The demographic analysis of the B
 <sub>GU-I</sub>, B
 <sub>GU-V</sub>, B
 <sub>GU-VI</sub>, B
 <sub>GU-VIII</sub>, and B
 <sub>CAM-I/GU-I</sub> clusters suggested that, even though all these clades had an initial phase of exponential growth, the dissemination of these clades declined during the 2000s. On the other hand, the B
 <sub>GU-II</sub>, B
 <sub>GU-III</sub>, B
 <sub>CAM-IV</sub> and B
 <sub>CAM-I/GU-II</sub> clades evidenced a more complex growth dynamics with phases of expansion interleaved by periods of slow growth. The B
 <sub>GU-II</sub> clade, characterized mostly by a population of young MSM, evidenced the highest mean estimated logistic growth rate (3.6 year
 <sup>-1</sup>) among the major clades circulating in Guatemala. The B
 <sub>GU-II</sub> clade growth rate was remarkably higher than those previously estimated for other country-specific B clades mainly or exclusively restricted to MSM (ranging from 0.5 to 1.6 year
 <sup>-1</sup>) [
 <xref rid="pone.0203916.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0203916.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Furthermore, the proportion of strains that corresponds to new infections within the B
 <sub>GU-II</sub> clade was higher (59.1%) compared with the rest of the B
 <sub>GU</sub> and B
 <sub>CAM</sub> clades (ranging from 6.9% of B
 <sub>GU-III</sub> to 22.1% of B
 <sub>CAM-III</sub>). As the HIV epidemic in Guatemala is concentrated in high-risk key populations, with 8.9% prevalence in MSM [
 <xref rid="pone.0203916.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], an increase in size and proportion of the B
 <sub>GU-II</sub> clade would be expected in the current Guatemalan HIV epidemic. These results, however, should be interpreted with caution because the exponential growth model, that was equally supported as the logistic one, showed a much lower mean growth rate (0.4 year
 <sup>-1</sup>) for the B
 <sub>GU-II</sub> clade. Despite the fact that other major subtype B clades in Guatemala mostly circulate among individuals infected by the same transmission route (heterosexual transmission), the mean estimated growth rate of these lineages varied considerably, ranging from 0.2 year
 <sup>-1</sup> for clade B
 <sub>GU-III</sub> to 2.1 year
 <sup>-1</sup> for clade B
 <sub>CAM-I/GU-II</sub>. This range is even higher than that estimated for country-specific B
 <sub>PANDEMIC</sub> clades circulating in the general population in different Latin American countries (0.2–0.9 year
 <sup>-1</sup>) [
 <xref rid="pone.0203916.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0203916.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0203916.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].
</p>
