<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The brief overview of risk factors that we have presented here highlights the multidimensional nature of the links between changing livestock production practices and the emergence and spread of zoonotic diseases. Given this complexity, understanding the conditions that create zoonotic risk requires a research approach that links both animal and public health sectors and natural and social sciences. Other researchers have stressed the need for integration in this area (
 <xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">Brownlie et al. 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">Dry and Leach 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr">Parkes et al. 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="r43" ref-type="bibr">Scoones 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="r55" ref-type="bibr">Wilcox and Kueffer 2008</xref>). However, few efforts have been made to translate the research agenda into novel methods and concepts that can sustain and guide empirically informed scientific work (
 <xref rid="r54" ref-type="bibr">Waltner-Toews et al. 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="r56" ref-type="bibr">Wilcox and Gubler 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="r57" ref-type="bibr">Wood et al. 2012</xref>). In contributing to these efforts, we suggest that interdisciplinary research on zoonotic risk should be able to account for the complexity of “risk environments” (
 <xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">Barnett and Blaikie 1992</xref>), rather than simple linear causal relations between risk drivers and disease emergence and/or spread. From this perspective, the key scientific challenges are 
 <italic>a</italic>) to correctly define and understand the risk environment as part of a larger system that creates risk; and 
 <italic>b</italic>) to deploy a method that combines insights along the full extent of the chain of evidence from viral genome sequencing to animal keeping and on to animal market economics and the politics of food industry regulation. To address such complex interactions and develop effective policy, we need integrated research that operates at different levels of analysis, from the study of risk environments to the development of risk scenarios and identification of policy options for risk management. These linked levels constitute a conceptual model illustrated in Figure 1.
</p>
