<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Different genetic reassorted subtypes have arose in dogs (
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). During a surveillance effort in 2012 in South Korea, a novel strain of the H3N1 subtype was isolated from canines, and whole-genome sequencing showed that it contained the HA gene segment from CIV-H3N2 and the remaining seven other gene segments from human A(H1N1)pdm09 (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Since then, at least four other reassortants involving CIV-H3N2 and A(H1N1)pdm09 have been isolated from dogs in Southern Asia, including a CIV-H3N2 harboring the M gene segment of human A(H1N1)pdm09 (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>). The emergence of these novel CIV-H3N2 reassortants likely arose through co-infection of CIV-H3N2 and A(H1N1)pdm09 virus, correlating with high co-positivity for both canine H3N2 and A(H1N1)pdm09 antibodies in the canine population (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Remarkably, multiple genomic reassortment between swine-origin subtypes of the H1N1 and endemic canine H3N2 lineages co-circulating in dogs were recently reported in pet dogs in China (
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) (
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>). Moreover, in a large-scale analysis of sequence data of IAVs from various species, the NS gene of a CIV-H3N2 subtype isolated from a Chinese dog in 2007 was found to be closely related to H5N1 avian influenza viruses, indicating that reassortment may also have occurred between canine H3N2 and avian H5N1 (
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>). Of particular concern, some CIV-H3N2 reassortants demonstrated the ability to infect and efficiently transmit to cohoused dogs in experimental settings, thus supporting potential adaptation of novel subtypes to canine populations (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>).
</p>
