<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">The influenza virus polymerase consists of three subunits, encoded by the PA, PB1, and PB2 segments, which also express several important viral proteins, such as PA-X and PB1-F2. Efficient nuclear import and assembly of the polymerase subunit RNP complex are critical steps in the viral life cycle and are closely associated with viral temperature sensitivity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. In our study, genetic analysis revealed certain unique amino acid substitutions in each group of viral strains. In the PA protein, the 2017sum strains exhibited a V668I substitution located in the PB1 interaction domain. The 2017sum viral strains differed from the 2016–2017win viral strains in regard to the K299R and K340R mutations in the PB2 protein. To further investigate the effects of these mutations on the influenza polymerase in the 2016–2017win and 2017sum virus strains, we evaluated viral replication via a TCID
 <sub>50</sub> measurement, an HA assay and the vRNA, cRNA, and mRNA levels of the NP segment in MDCK cells infected with these two viral strains at different temperatures (33, 35, 37, and 39 °C). Our data showed that replication of the 2016–2017win viruses was significantly restricted at 39 °C. A previous study demonstrated the role of the polymerase complex in determining the temperature range over which influenza viruses can replicate
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup>. Bradel Tretheway et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup> showed that the human WSN polymerase complex lost activity at 39 °C. The shutoff temperature of most temperature-sensitive viruses is 39 °C or higher. These conclusions are consistent with our results for the 2016–2017win strains. In this study, replication of the 2016–2017win strains was similar to that of temperature-sensitive viruses, exhibiting high viral replication at 33 °C and significantly low replication at 39 °C.
</p>
