<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0150">Despite 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> observations where PEDV inhibits type I and type III IFN responses (
 <xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">Deng et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0250" ref-type="bibr">Hou et al., 2019a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">Koonpaew et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0755" ref-type="bibr">Zhang and Yoo, 2016</xref>), there were increased systemic innate (IFNα and IL-22) and pro-inflammatory cytokine (TNFα, IL-6, IL-8, IL-12, and IL-17) responses in acutely infected neonatal pigs (
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">Annamalai et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">Jung et al., 2018</xref>). This coincided with increased numbers of PEDV antigen-positive cells (
 <xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0505" ref-type="bibr">Madson et al., 2016</xref>) or inflammatory cells (lymphocytes or neutrophils) in the gut-associated lymphoid tissue (GALT) (
 <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">Coussement et al., 1982</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">de Arriba et al., 2002b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">Debouck et al., 1981</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0285" ref-type="bibr">Jung and Saif, 2015</xref>), and the onset of necrosis and exfoliation of infected enterocytes (
 <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">Jung et al., 2018</xref>). Necrosis of enterocytes is in part involved in the innate or pro-inflammatory cytokine responses in infected pigs, as also observed 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> (
 <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">Koonpaew et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0460" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2017b</xref>). The increased systemic innate and pro-inflammatory cytokine responses that occur during acute PEDV infection are beneficial for differentiation of naïve T cells into cytotoxic or helper T cells, leading to removal of infected cells or production of VN antibodies, respectively (
 <xref rid="bib0615" ref-type="bibr">Siegrist, 2013</xref>). However, highly increased, prolonged pro-inflammatory cytokines that can cause decreased appetite, 
 <italic>etc</italic>. are also detrimental (
 <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">Jung et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0390" ref-type="bibr">Langhans, 2000</xref>). Increased systemic IFNα and IFNγ cytokine responses were also observed in PEDV-infected gilts at PID 13–17 and PID 6–8, respectively (
 <xref rid="bib0380" ref-type="bibr">Langel et al., 2019b</xref>).
</p>
