<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza viruses and GAS accounted for a large number of single pathogens. This is similar to the results of the previous review showing that the largest number of aetiologic agents affecting outbreaks was influenza viruses in LTCFs from 1966 to 2008 [
 <xref rid="pone.0229911.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. First, in this review, five of the six influenza virus outbreaks occurred by the influenza A virus and the other by influenza B virus. Influenza-like illness included in the studies showed a median attack rate of 24.50%, similar to that of seasonal influenza, usually 20–30% [
 <xref rid="pone.0229911.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Vaccine-related issues have been raised in influenza outbreaks that have occurred in LTCFs of highly immunized residents. This finding suggests some implications to prevent influenza outbreaks in LTCFs. Regarding vaccination coverage among staff, the study by Thomas [
 <xref rid="pone.0229911.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] found that influenza episodes were reduced if an employee was vaccinated, and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) recommend that all healthcare worker get vaccinated annually [
 <xref rid="pone.0229911.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Therefore, influenza vaccination among healthcare personnel should be considered to mitigate the risk of influenza outbreaks in LTCFs. Additionally, because vaccination does not provide complete protection, active daily surveillance for influenza-like illness is still recommended for all persons in LTCFs during influenza season [
 <xref rid="pone.0229911.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], which is evident by the outbreaks occurring in highly immunized LTCF population. Secondly, the GAS infection rate among older adults in LTCFs is from 3 to 8-fold higher than that of community-dwelling older adults, due to risk factors such as grouped living conditions, and underlying diseases [
 <xref rid="pone.0229911.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0229911.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Five of the studies on the GAS outbreaks in this review reported a median attack rate of 2.43% in LTCFs, which is within the range of 1–30% reported in the previous study [
 <xref rid="pone.0229911.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Three of them were long-lasting outbreaks with multiple clusters for more than 6 months, which suggested that an accurate identification of how pathogens spread was a fundamental step in outbreak control.
</p>
