<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During SARS-CoV-2 infection, an escalating transition from mild to severe immune activation can be observed, with a progressive rise of proinflammatory cytokines.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
 </sup> Neutrophils accumulate at the site of infection, where they wield antiviral functions but, at the same time, contribute to the propagation of the immune response. If viral clearance is inadequate, their unceasing activation sets off the progression towards a hyperinflammatory state. As a matter of fact, unfavorable outcomes in COVID-19 have been associated with an exaggerated immune response to SARS-CoV-2: a cytokine storm syndrome can develop, leading to ARDS and multi-organ failure.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, 
  <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>
 </sup> Novel pathogenic hypotheses can be formed in regard to the prevention and treatment of the immune-mediated disease caused by SARS-CoV-2 infection. Notably, the cytokines overexpressed in the most advanced stages of COVID-19 are not directly involved in virus clearance.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>
 </sup> This led to the hypothesis that targeted therapies used for the treatment of immune-mediated diseases could prove effective to treat and—possibly—prevent the main complications of COVID-19. Interleukin-6 inhibitors have been proposed and used with encouraging results.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>
 </sup> Furthermore, baricitinib, a Janus kinases (JAK) 1 and 2 inhibitor, has been conceived as another viable treatment. The role of the different JAKs in the response to viral infections is not fully understood. Even though JAK 2 inhibition could potentially reduce viral entry within the host cells, JAK 1 inhibition might lead to a further reduction in viral clearance.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, 
  <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
