<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Remdesivir is a broad-spectrum antiviral prodrug, which is a nucleotide analog and is metabolized in the cell to adenosine triphosphate analog, which inhibits the viral RNA polymerases. Remdesivir is the drug of choice against several viral families, including Ebola, SARS-CoV, and MERS-CoV. Remdesivir is being used for prophylactic and therapeutic purposes and has shown remarkable efficacy in the non-clinical model of coronaviruses [
 <xref rid="B100-ijerph-17-05904" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>,
 <xref rid="B101-ijerph-17-05904" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>]. It has also shown promising activity against SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B102-ijerph-17-05904" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>,
 <xref rid="B103-ijerph-17-05904" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. A large clinical trial of remdesivir is currently underway for patients with mild to moderate symptoms [
 <xref rid="B104-ijerph-17-05904" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. The critically ill patients treated with amicable use of remdesivir showed better efficacy, and the clinical condition of the patients was improved [
 <xref rid="B105-ijerph-17-05904" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. On 1 May 2020, the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) of the USA authorized the emergency use of remdesivir for the treatment of COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="B106-ijerph-17-05904" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]. The recent version of treatment guidelines by NHC recommends the use of lopinavir/ritonavir and IFN-α. The first version of treatment guidelines was issued on 15 January 2020, later revised five times, and the 6th edition is the most recent one that was issued on 18 February 2020. Lopinavir/ritonavir, ribavirin, and IFN-α were added in the 5th edition of treatment guidelines for combating COVID-19. Later, arbidol and chloroquine phosphate have also been added in the 6th edition, as these drugs show better clinical efficacy. Potential drugs included in the 6th edition of treatment guidelines by NHC of China, as shown in 
 <xref rid="ijerph-17-05904-t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, presented promising therapeutic effects [
 <xref rid="B107-ijerph-17-05904" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. Although the recent study was an open-label, individually randomized, controlled trial representing patients admitted in hospitals, treated with lopinavir/ritonavir (400 mg/100 mg), no clinical improvement was observed by this treatment beyond standard care [
 <xref rid="B108-ijerph-17-05904" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. On the basis of the guidelines, ritonavir is used as a booster to enhance the efficacy of lopinavir. These medications are prescribed to be taken for a short period of time (&lt;2 weeks), suggesting their acute response.
</p>
