<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Patients with vigorous immune reactions can be treated with glucocorticoids such as methylprednisolone, which is used at 1–2 mg/kg/day dose in children and 25–150 mg/day in adults. It is believed to reduce the prognosis of the disease in patients with impaired oxygen index, that is, less than 300 mm Hg, limited to 5 days [
 <xref rid="B69-ijerph-17-05904" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. For patients with premature disease stage, without hypoxia, use of corticosteroids should be avoided. However, in critical situations where mechanical ventilation is mandatory, anti-inflammatory therapy is possibly useful and can be employed [
 <xref rid="B59-ijerph-17-05904" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. A glucocorticoids-based drug dexamethasone may be employed against COVID-19. Dexamethasone is a synthetic corticosteroid approved by the FDA in 1958 as a broad-spectrum immunosuppressor, which is about 30 times as active as cortisone and possesses a longer duration of action (2–3 days). Dexamethasone may not only limit the production and damaging effect of the cytokines, but may also inhibit the protective function of T cells and reduce the ability of B cells to synthesize antibodies [
 <xref rid="B111-ijerph-17-05904" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. Dexamethasone may be a useful agent for short-term therapy in severe intubated COVID-19 patients [
 <xref rid="B112-ijerph-17-05904" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. A recent controlled open-label, randomized trial of dexamethasone in hospitalized patients, concluded that the use of dexamethasone with the aid of mechanical ventilation or oxygen alone resulted in lower mortality at the dose of 6 mg once daily for 10 days. However, dexamethasone was not effective in those patients who were not receiving respiratory support [
 <xref rid="B113-ijerph-17-05904" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. Dexamethasone is on an essential medicines list recommended by the World Health Organization and is readily accessible worldwide at a low cost. Guidelines issued by the U.K.’s chief medical officers and by the National Institutes of Health in the United States have already been updated to recommend the use of glucocorticoids such as dexamethasone in hospitalized patients with COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="B114-ijerph-17-05904" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>,
 <xref rid="B115-ijerph-17-05904" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>].
</p>
