<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The superoxide anion radical may act on organic and inorganic compounds, depending on their chemical properties, as an oxidant (E
 <sub>0</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>
 <sup>–•</sup>/H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> ꞊ +0.89 V) or a reductant (E
 <sub>0</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>/O
 <sub>2</sub>
 <sup>–•</sup>꞊ –0.16 V) (Wood 
 <xref rid="bib299" ref-type="bibr">1987</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib300" ref-type="bibr">1988</xref>). The reductive properties of the superoxide radical is produced in the area of inflammation during viral pneumonias. This may occur via reduction of ferric ions after their release from complexes with biomacromolecules. For example, iron in a molecule of ferritin is represented by Fe
 <sup>3+</sup> ions, which under the influence of the superoxide anion radical transforms into Fe
 <sup>2+</sup> and leaves the aforementioned protein (Biemond 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">1984</xref>; Bolann and Ulvik 
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">1987</xref>). In the presence of free ferric ions and partially reduced forms of oxygen, the conditions are created for a kind of 
 <italic>catalytic reactor</italic> for redox catabolic production of prooxidants, especially very toxic hydroxyl radicals (Morris, Earl and Trenam 
 <xref rid="bib185" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>). This condition of a biological system is extremely dangerous because in the presence of free ferric ions, biological fluids lose their antibacterial properties (Bullen, Ward and Rogers 
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>; Griffiths 
 <xref rid="bib93" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>; Sritharan 
 <xref rid="bib261" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). The elimination of free ferric ions from the biological media of a body is a life/death issue in case of viral pneumonias. There were earlier attempts to use available complexones (for example, deferoxamine) to bind ferric ions during viral pneumonia; contrary to the expected, not only did they show no positive effects on the pathological process, but they also led to increased mortality (Dolganova and Sharanov 
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>). The explanation of this paradox is that deferoxamine (desferal) has approximately the same affinity constant for ferric ions as siderophores of microorganisms (Hallaway 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib97" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>; Askwith, de Silva and Kaplan 
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>); for this reason, it is unable to limit the availability of Fe
 <sup>3+</sup> for pathogenic organisms (Kim, Park and Shin 
 <xref rid="bib138" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Cassat and Skaar 
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). At the same time, it seems that ferric ions chelated by deferoxamine do not completely lose their ability to redox transformation and thus support the reactions of Fenton and Osipov (Borg and Schaich 
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">1986</xref>; Klebanoff 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib142" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>; Dulchavsky 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>; Niihara 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib193" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Francisco 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).
</p>
