<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The location of the Southeast Asian country Bangladesh seems to be the fitting habitat for the survival of the primary dengue vector 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic> vector (in some cases 
 <italic>A. albopictus</italic> too) as well as its increased transmission. In Bangladesh, DENV has really posed its serious fatal effect this year, and in connection with the previous researches, the major cause of this disease has been pointed on the environmental effects (average rainfall, humidity, and temperature) as well as the improper urbanization [
 <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The gradual increase in the atmospheric temperature (thereby supporting the expansion of the habitats of the mosquito larvae and pupa) for the last couple of years, especially in the city of Dhaka, possibly led to increased frequency of dengue infection. In general, the dengue fever is pointed by the sudden onset of high fever; severe headache and pain behind the eyes; and pain in the bones, muscles, and joints. Dengue hemorrhagic fever (DHF) appears as the severe form whereby continuous bleeding and sometimes shock comes about which in turn may lead to death that is most severe and frequent among children. Bleeding usually starts after 3–5 days of dengue fever; the high fever extends for 5–6 days, which declines usually on the 3
 <sup>rd</sup> or 4
 <sup>th</sup> day before the body temperature rises again, imparting discomfort and extreme weakness. Like chikungunya, dengue fever may spread very quickly and is very likely to affect a large number of populations, resulting in extreme fatality. According to the Institute of Epidemiology, Disease Control and Research, Bangladesh, most of the people who died of dengue this year in Bangladesh suffered from the shock syndrome and were second time infected [
 <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The “Death Review Committee” of the Directorate General of Health Services (DGHS) also confirmed that most of the deaths were due to the secondary infection with a different DENV serotype [
 <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].
</p>
