<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While ASFV is known to be transmitted by ticks in the genus 
 <italic>Ornithodoros</italic>, most surveillance efforts are focused on disease detection and diagnosis in domestic and wild suids, perhaps due to the inconsistent involvement of ticks in outbreak situations. In eastern and southern African countries, ASFV circulates enzootically between ticks of the 
 <italic>O. moubata</italic> species complex and common warthogs. In contrast, transmission in West Africa, appears to occur among domestic pigs in the absence of ticks (
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>). All available experimental data to date on which vertebrate species become viremic upon infection with ASFV is restricted to animals in the family Suidae, and was reviewed by Golnar et al. Of these hosts, domestic pigs produced the highest circulating virus titers, with bush pigs and warthogs producing lesser but detectable viremias (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). 
 <italic>Ornithodoros erraticus</italic> was determined to be responsible maintaining ASFV transmission in outdoor pig production facilities on the Iberian Peninsula. This is in contrast to many other locations throughout Europe in which the distribution and role of 
 <italic>Ornithodoros</italic> ticks in the transmission of ASF is poorly known (
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>). A recombinant rtTSGP1 ELISA kit can detect antibodies to 
 <italic>O. moubata</italic> salivary gland proteins with 100% sensitivity and 99.4% specificity and directly determines the exposure history of pigs to blood feeding ticks (
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>). This and similar tests can therefore be used in addition to conventional tests for surveillance to determine potential exposure that could portend risk to ASF through ticks. While it will be important to understand the competence and distribution of potential tick vectors of ASFV in the US and areas at risk of ASFV establishment (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), efforts to monitor for an introduction event should likely focus on evidence for infection among wild and domestic suids. Once ASFV establishes itself in a new area, the role of ticks will become increasingly more important to the environmental maintenance of this virus.
</p>
