<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to showing maximal exposure of Ngazidja inhabitants to DENV and CHIKV, our study brings in the first serological evidence for RVFV circulation amongst humans on the islands of the Union of Comoros. This was demonstrated not only by high rates of IgG seropositivity to the virus but also by the detection of IgM seropositivity indicating recent or current circulation of the virus mainly through pauci- or a-symptomatic infection. Rift Valley fever is a vector borne zoonotic disease present in Africa, the Middle East, and Madagascar [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004840.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0004840.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Our data reveal higher IgG seropositivity rates in Ngazidja but higher IgM seropositivty rates in Mwali and Ndzouani. These results confirm the only suspicion going back to 2007 when an autochthonous clinical case of RVFV was detected in a child from Ngazidja admitted at Mayotte’s hospital with a 2-month history of severe encephalitis [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004840.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. They are also coherent with the demonstration of an active circulation of the virus in Comorian livestock [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004840.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0004840.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. With regard to Mayotte, an investigation carried out on 2007–2008 on dengue-like syndromes, testing negative for 
 <italic>Plasmodium</italic> spp., CHIKV, and DENV, revealed 4.5% positive cases, suggestive of recent RVFV infection, 
 <italic>i</italic>.
 <italic>e</italic>. presence of viral RNA or IgM [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004840.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. A sero-survey study (2011) conducted also on Mayotte on 1420 individuals showed an overall seroprevalence of 3.5% for RVFV antibodies in the general population aged over 5 years. Altogether these results indicate active circulation, though mostly clinically insidious, of RVFV in humans in the four islands of the Comoros archipelago.
</p>
