<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Rift Valley fever (RVF) is a major vector-borne, zoonotic, and hemorrhagic fever (
 <italic>Phlebovirus</italic>, Family 
 <italic>Bunyaviridae</italic>) that severely affects human health, animal health and livestock production mainly in Sub-Saharan Africa [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Its potential for spread and emergence in current disease-free areas (e.g. Europe, United States of America) is of growing global concern. The emergence (or re-emergence) of a disease has been defined by Woolhouse and Dye (2001) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] as an “increase [
 <italic>in its incidence</italic>] following first introduction into a new host population, or [
 <italic>an increase in its incidence</italic>] in an existing host population” following specific ecological changes, e.g. in anthropological factors, agricultural practices or climate [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Theoretically, the conditions leading to RVF emergence may result from a sudden increase in vector density, the availability of susceptible animals, and the presence of the virus. The virus could be newly introduced or already present locally; maintained in the mosquito population, or circulating at a low level in livestock or wild animal populations, although little evidence exists on the latter [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Due to little existing data on RVF, those mechanisms have not been fully quantified. Previous work on RVF emergence conducted for the Horn of Africa using ecological statistical modelling showed that above-average rainfall and vegetation density (Normalized Vegetation Difference Index, NDVI) over 3 to 4 months could lead to RVF re-emergence [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], but it did not seem to be always the case, especially in Madagascar and Southern Africa, where other factors, such as the movements of animals or the level of livestock susceptibility may also play a role [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Finally, although a range of mathematical models have been developed to study RVF, they looked mainly at RVF spread, that is once the virus is introduced [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] or they assessed the impact of vaccination strategies [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], and only few were fitted to data [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005767.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].
</p>
