<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Climate change can potentially alter the spatial range of vector-borne diseases through shifts in geographical distributions of their vectors (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Despite some positive developments, such as better access to clean drinking water, lower exposure to insect vectors, and higher-quality housing, projected changes in climate over the next decades may exacerbate infectious disease incidence even in developed regions such as North America (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Habitat changes, alterations in water storage and irrigation habits, pollution, development of insecticide and drug resistance, globalization, tourism, and travel are additional factors that may aggravate this threat (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). For instance, in Europe, short winters appear to have influenced populations of 
 <italic>Dermacentor reticulatus</italic>, the tick vector responsible for transmission of 
 <italic>Babesia canis</italic>, to expand to the East (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). In Veracruz, Mexico, a study found an association between an increase in dengue cases and increased temperature and rainfall that followed El Niño Southern Oscillation (ENSO) events (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Increased rainfall could create both microclimates, in which vectors can thrive, as well as cause high temperatures, which could allow for a rapid increase in vector densities and ultimately put humans at risk for vector-borne disease. Extreme-flooding events can cause outbursts of zoonotic diseases caused by infectious agents transmitted by rodents, as their pathogen-containing urine contaminates the water. This was the case in Nicaragua, in which a Leptospirosis epidemic followed a flooding event (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Thus, humans might face increasing exposure to zoonotic diseases as naturally occurring phenomena like ENSO and flooding events are expected to become frequent due to climate change (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). In addition, climate change can also affect the epidemiology of zoonoses indirectly. For instance, the density of vegetation in a particular area increases during heavy rainfall seasons. This vegetation indirectly supports the reproduction of rodents, which can be infected with pathogens transmissible to humans (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>).
</p>
