<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The IAV M2 and NS1 proteins are associated with autophagy signaling. The NS1 protein binds to p85β, the regulatory subunit of PI3K and activates its signaling pathway, causing the phosphorylation of Akt with subsequent phosphorylation of Beclin-1, which regulates autophagy [
 <xref rid="CIT0253">253</xref>]. M2 keeps autophagy at moderate levels by limiting the degree of lysosome fusion with autophagosomes [
 <xref rid="CIT0124">124</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0247">247</xref>]. Gannage 
 <italic>et al</italic>. showed that M2 proton channel activity is not involved in blocking autophagosome degradation. They verified this fact by using amantadine hydrochloride, an inhibitor of M2 ion channel activity, which was unable to abrogate autophagosome accumulation in IAV-infected cells. Finally, they showed that the N-terminal first 60 amino acids of M2 blocks autolysosome formation and acts independently of its proton channel function [
 <xref rid="CIT0124">124</xref>]. However, it was recently shown that the proton channel activity of M2 is involved in this blocking activity [
 <xref rid="CIT0254">254</xref>]. This discrepancy might be related to the strain of the virus used in the study, A/Hong Kong/8/68(H3N2), which was sensitive to amantadine. Fletcher at al. also confirmed that LC3 relocalization during IAV infection depends on the proton channel activity of M2. They showed non-canonical autophagy (independent of ATG genes) was dependent on WD40 CTD of ATG16L1, raising the possibility that activation of the non-canonical autophagy pathway can be triggered by the loss of cellular pH gradients. The cells lacking WD40 CTD were unable to support LC3 lipidation [
 <xref rid="CIT0255">255</xref>]. Su et al. found that M2 ubiquitination was crucial for infectious virus particle production, but not required for blocking late-stage autophagy. The levels of LC3-II at 6 hpi were threefold higher in M2-K78R mutant virus-infected cells than in WT-infected cells. Thus, a M2 ubiquitination-defective mutation (M2-K78R) induced autophagy even earlier than wild-type (WT) virus [
 <xref rid="CIT0256">256</xref>].
</p>
