<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In association with efforts to develop IAV treatment strategies, a study evaluated the role of autophagy induction using a Beclin-1 expression plasmid before and after IAV inoculation. This therapeutic approach of autophagy induction inhibited virus replication at 24 and 48 hpi, but the prophylactic approach was not successful [
 <xref rid="CIT0271">271</xref>]. Another study identified a role for K27-linked ubiquitination in tripartite motif (TRIM)23 GTPase function and its ability to activate TANK-binding kinase 1 (TBK1)-mediated autophagy, which together are key components of selective autophagy for different viruses including IAV. This could be a basis for therapeutics against diseases caused by dysregulation of autophagy such as IAV [
 <xref rid="CIT0272">272</xref>]. Scientists have recently designed a peptide called Kα2-helix, derived from the viral FLICE-like inhibitor protein (vFLIP) of Kaposi’s sarcoma-associated herpesvirus (KSHV). They detected the autophagy activity of this compound at the initial stages of IAV infection which inhibited the binding of FLIP to the E2-like enzyme Atg3 without affecting the interaction of LC3 and Atg3. Then, they fused it with a protein transduction domain [YGRKKRRQRRR] of the HIV-1 TAT protein. This construct showed significant inhibition of lethal doses of H5N1 or H1N1 virus replication and transmission by destabilizing the viral membrane. Therefore, these artificial constructs may represent promising antiviral agents to control various IAV subtypes [
 <xref rid="CIT0273">273</xref>]. Fluorescent labeling of individual viral particles has been used for decades [
 <xref rid="CIT0274">274</xref>], but was recently adapted to reveal autophagic trafficking of IAV H9N2 independent of Rab5, which could provide a better understanding of the fundamental relationship between autophagy and virus entry [
 <xref rid="CIT0275">275</xref>]. The interaction of IAV with the host autophagy pathway is illustrated in 
 <xref rid="F0004">Figure 4</xref> and a summary of autophagy and influenza virus infection is summarized in 
 <xref rid="T0004">Table 4</xref>. 
</p>
