<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The NS2 protein, is encoded by the NS2 region of the 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic> genome. The NS2 protein can be also processed into the matured proteins such as NS2A and NS2B (Chen et al., 2017[
 <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]). The NS2A is a 226 amino acid long hydrophobic protein, that is inserted in the membrane and interacts specifically with negatively charged phospholipids. This protein contains some transmembrane domains and is associated with the membrane of host endoplasmic reticulum (RE). It is involved in the evasion of the immune response since it suppresses Interferon β transcription (IFN-β), and as a result, the interferon response, which is one of the host's first lines of defense. The NS2A is required for the processing of NS1 containing specific recognition motifs targeted by specific proteases. It is also involved in the virion assembly and the synthesis of viral RNA. For example, in the case of YFV, a Lys-to-Ser mutation at position 190 in NS2A blocked the production of virus particles (Leung et al., 2008[
 <xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]). Additionally, it has been reported that in DENV there are two different sets of NS2A molecules, which could be interesting for the development of control strategies (Xie et al., 2015[
 <xref rid="R99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]). The functions of NS2A are related to the membrane structure and orientation, and mainly in both viral RNA synthesis and virion assembly (Murray et al., 2008[
 <xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]; Xie et al., 2015[
 <xref rid="R99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]). NS2B is an integral protein of 14 kDa and is composed of three domains, two transmembrane segments located at the N and C terminal regions, and a central region of 47 amino acids that acts as cofactor for the protease NS3. The complex NS2B-NS3 serves as a place for the assembly of the replication complex of the flaviviruses and modulates both the viral pathogenesis and the immune response of the host (Murray et al., 2008[
 <xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]; Chen et al., 2017[
 <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]). Although the functions of NS2A and NS2B proteins are not well understood, it is known that in DENV, apoptosis is induced by NS2B-NS3 protease precursor and NS3 protease, most likely through the caspase-8 pathway or NF-κB pathway (Uno and Ross, 2018[
 <xref rid="R88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]). 
</p>
