<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Early identification and early isolation are imperative for COVID‐19 control. COVID‐19 neonates should be placed in negative pressure rooms or in rooms in which room exhaust is filtered through high‐efficiency particulate air filters with reference to MERS management.
 <xref rid="jmv25740-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref> No visiting is allowed for neonates of COVID‐19. Treatment mainly depends on adult patients' clinical experience due to few cases in children. There is no specific drug treatment for SARS‐CoV‐2 being similar to MERS‐CoV and SARS‐CoV.
 <xref rid="jmv25740-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv25740-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>26</sup>
 </xref> Symptomatic and supportive treatment is the mainstay of therapy for patients of SARS‐CoV‐2 infection including the supply of oxygen, the maintenance of water‐electrolyte, and acid‐base balance. The supplement of water and electrolyte should be appropriate, so as to avoid aggravating the pulmonary edema and reduced oxygenation.
 <xref rid="jmv25740-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>27</sup>
 </xref> For newborns with severe acute respiratory distress syndrome, high‐dose pulmonary surfactant, inhaled nitric oxide, high‐frequency oscillatory ventilation, and extracorporeal membrane lung may be useful. In the United States, patients' conditions were improved apparently after the treatment with nucleoside analog‐remdesivir, but there was just one case, the efficacy needs further verification.
 <xref rid="jmv25740-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>28</sup>
 </xref> Interferon‐α2b nebulization were be applied in MERS‐CoV and SARS‐CoV, so it could be considered to use in SARS‐CoV‐2 infection.
 <xref rid="jmv25740-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>29</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv25740-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>30</sup>
 </xref> In addition, three potential drug combinations (sirolimus plus dactinomycin, mercaptopurine plus melatonin, and toremifene plus emodin) are candidate repurposable drugs.
 <xref rid="jmv25740-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>31</sup>
 </xref> Moreover, convalescent sera from SARS‐CoV‐2‐recovered patients may be useful for SARS‐CoV‐2 infection, because of a significant reduction in the mortality following convalescent sera from SARS‐recovered patients treatment.
 <xref rid="jmv25740-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>32</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
