<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There is increasing evidence that PD1 and programmed death ligand 1 (PDL1) interaction could be related to T-cell functionality within the CNS. PD1, an inhibitory receptor expressed by all activated T cells, regulates T-cell effector functions during various physiological responses, including acute and chronic infections. Viral-peptide-specific CD8 T cells in the brain expressed PD1 during the acute phase of mouse MuPyV infection and showed sustained expression under persistent infection whereas their splenic counterparts only exhibited transient and low expression of PD1 during the acute phase [
 <xref rid="R63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>
 <sup>▪▪</sup>]. These data suggest that PD1 may exhibit a specialized function within the CNS environment. In MyPyV model of encephalitis, PDL1 was expressed on infiltrating myeloid cells, tissue-resident microglia and astrocytes. PDL1−/− mice upon acute MyPyV infection showed increased frequency of CD103 + CD8 T cells and CD25 + FoxP3 + CD4 T cells in the brain. The association of CD103 expression on CD8 T cells and PD1 signaling has also been demonstrated in murine cytomegalovirus (MCMV) brain infection [
 <xref rid="R64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. PD-1-deficient CD8 T cells also exhibit significant decrease in CD103 expression with mixed glia 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>[
 <xref rid="R64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. These data suggest that PD1:PDL interactions may contribute to effective T-cell defense in circumstances of acute virus infection, but promote chronic activation of microglia in the postinfectious state. The functional interpretation of the expression of PD1 on CNS-infiltrating CD8 T cells regardless of acute or chronic infection or postinfection remains to be unraveled. However, one can assume that PD1 signaling in brain-residing T cells depend on dichotomous function that will 
 <italic>establish</italic> a balance between the control of viral infection and the potential immunopathology from over-reactive T cells. Of interest, PD1 levels on T cells are elevated in aged individuals [
 <xref rid="R65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], which may impact virologic control and recovery from viral encephalitis.
</p>
