<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A national noticeable infectious disease reporting system has been established to continuously report the influenza cases in China, while the system reports the flu activity one month before, putting the flu data lagged for a month. Traditional flu surveillance methods for prediction were mainly based on hospital or laboratory data (
 <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2017</xref>). The idea of applying internet search query data for the infectious diseases prediction was from 
 <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Ginsberg et al. (2009)</xref>, who presented a brand-new method providing nearly real-time surveillance of influenza-like illness and overcoming the limitations of lag-time in the traditional flu surveillance systems of the United States. Online search query data have a stronger tendency and immediacy and can maintain full synchronization with the flu epidemic. In addition, internet search query data can be measured in real time. In order to monitor the infectious diseases activity in time, numerous studies have been emerging recently based on online search query data or social media data, including Google (
 <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Seo &amp; Shin, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Pollett et al., 2017</xref>), Yahoo (
 <xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Polgreen et al., 2008</xref>), Naver (
 <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Shin et al., 2016</xref>), Daum (
 <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Woo et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Seo et al., 2014</xref>), Baidu search engine (
 <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Guo et al., 2017b</xref>), Twitter (
 <xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Wagner et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Kagashe, Yan &amp; Suheryani, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Allen et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">Yun et al., 2016</xref>) and Weibo (
 <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Fung et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2015</xref>) social media, Wikipedia (
 <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Hickmann et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">McIver &amp; Brownstein, 2014</xref>), hospital or clinicians’ database (
 <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Bouzille et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Santillana et al., 2014</xref>), and so on. As Google has been pulled out of mainland China in 2010, Google search query data and Google Flu Trends cannot be accessible in mainland China. This article will construct a forecasting model for influenza based on the ensemble data integrating traditional influenza cases data and Baidu search data, which is the most popular search engine in China.
</p>
