<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <p>We thank Anna van Weringh for reviewing the manuscript. We wish to acknowledge the contributions and support of the members of the Swiss HIV Cohort Study and the UK HIV Drug Resistance Database. Members of the Swiss HIV Cohort study and of the UK HIV Drug Resistance Database are provided as 
  <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">supplementary information</xref>. This work was supported through the PANGEA-HIV Consortium with support provided by the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation and by NIH GM110749, by the Wellcome Trust (SJL, Grant number 092807) and the Biotechnology and Biological Science Research Council (EH and MRC, Grant number BB/F017030/1). The UK HIV Drug Resistance Database is supported by the Medical Research Council (grant number G0900274) and is partly funded by the Department of Health; the views expressed in the publication are those of the authors and not necessarily those of the Department of Health. Additional support for the UK HIV RDB is provided by Boehringer Ingelheim, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Gilead, Tibotec (a division of Janssen-Cilag) and Roche. The Swiss HIV Cohort Study is supported by the Swiss National Science Foundation (SNF grant #33CS30-134277) and the SHCS Drug Resistance Database was supported by SHCS projects #470, 528, 569, 683, 752 the SHCS Research Foundation, the Swiss National Science Foundation (grant #-159868 (to HFG), the European Community’s Seventh Framework Program (grant FP7/2007–2013), under the Collaborative HIV and Anti-HIV Drug-resistance Network (CHAIN; grant 223131, to HFG), by the Yvonne-Jacob foundation, and by a further research grant of the Union Bank of Switzerland, in the name of an anonymous donor to HFG, an unrestricted research grant from Gilead, Switzerland to the SHCS research foundation, and by the University of Zurich’s Clinical research Priority Program (CRPP) “Viral infectious diseases: Zurich Primary HIV Infection Study” (to HFG). RK was supported by SNF #PZ00P3-142411. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.
 </p>
</ack>
