<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Pseudorabies virus (PRV) is the etiological agent of pseudorabies (PR) or Aujeszky’s disease that was first described in 1813 (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Lee and Wilson, 1979</xref>). Phylogenetically, this enveloped double-stranded DNA virus is an alphaherpesvirus that belongs to the genus 
 <italic>Varicellovirus</italic> within the family 
 <italic>Herpesviridae</italic> (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Mettenleiter, 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Pomeranz et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Muller et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">An et al., 2013</xref>). PRV has the ability to infect a variety of animal species (e.g., ruminants, carnivores and rodents, etc.) with often-lethal consequences, but pigs are the only natural host (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Freuling et al., 2017</xref>;
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Ai et al., 2018</xref>). Infections of pigs by PRV can cause reproductive failure of sows and high mortality of young piglets, often leading to colossal economic losses to the swine industry (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Muller et al., 2011</xref>). Currently, the disease control is carried out mainly through vaccination using attenuated gene-deletion vaccines along with differential diagnosis to differentiate vaccinated from infected animals (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Muller et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Freuling et al., 2017</xref>). Since the implementation of this strategy in 1980s, PRV has been successfully eradicated from domestic pigs of many countries, including the United States, most of Europe and New Zealand (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Pannett et al., 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">An et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Ketusing et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Freuling et al., 2017</xref>). For the Chinese swine industry, Bartha-K61 vaccine has been widely used since early 1990s (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">An et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2016</xref>); it was imported from Hungary in 1979 that contains a complete deletion of the region coding for glycoprotein E (gE) and US9 and partial deletion within the gI and US2 coding regions (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Bartha, 1961</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Yuan et al., 1983</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Lomniczi et al., 1984</xref>). Massive vaccination with the Bartha-K61 vaccine in swine farms has brought PR well under control, except sporadic cases (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Tong and Chen, 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">An et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2016</xref>).
</p>
