<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We employ phylogenetic approaches to study the evolutionary history and relationships of organisms. Heritable traits, such as genetic sequences, are represented in phylogenetic trees (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat.1006979.g001">Fig 1</xref>, top panel, center), which portray relatedness between organisms by branches and in which the length of branching lines represent evolutionary time. Phylogenetics provides an integrative perspective of the identity, classification, ecology, and evolutionary history of viral strains [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006979.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Usually, it involves mathematical models implementing mainly three kinds of methods: a) parsimony, a criterion of ‘frugality’, based on favouring the simplest explanation or fit of the data, in which the best phylogenetic tree is one that requires the fewest evolutionary changes; b) maximum likelihood (ML), based on inferring probability distributions such that the more likely a viral strain (sequence) falls within a cluster of a given tree, the more that tree is validated; and c) Bayesian inference, which relies on ML but integrates the probability of hypothesis according to previous data (prior probability) to define the best tree. All aforementioned methods are used to analyze genetic relationships among viral strains [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006979.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Bayesian approximations favoured the integration of sophisticated sampling methods such as Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) algorithms, revolutionizing phylogenetics through the incorporation of complex models of evolution and the estimation of parameters such as substitution rates, divergence times, and other population genetics patterns [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006979.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In addition, the number of infections over time, inferred from Bayesian skyline plots, allows the reconstruction of the demographic history of a pathogen during epidemics (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat.1006979.g001">Fig 1</xref>, top panel, right) [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006979.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1006979.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. These advances were significantly boosted by the increasingly abundant genomic data from next-generation sequencing techniques, which are moving from core facilities to benchtop and even to field-friendly platforms. Altogether, this workflow makes near-real-time molecular epidemiology a feasible endeavour. These approaches were used to reconstruct the emergence and spread of recent Zika virus epidemics in the Americas, identifying the timing and sources of introductions in different geographical regions [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006979.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Similarly, real-time molecular epidemiology of the recent Ebola outbreak in West Africa revealed considerable disconnection between transmission clusters and independently evolved lineages [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006979.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1006979.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Phylogenetics thus builds a clearer picture of virus outbreaks by identifying evolutionary and transmission patterns.
</p>
