<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <title>Abstract</title>
 <sec sec-type="background">
  <title>Background:</title>
  <p> Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) is one of the infectious diseases that have seriously threatened global public health since its outbreak in 2019. Due to the complicated Pathogenesis, high infectivity and high fatality rate of COVID-19, there is currently no effective treatment for such epidemic disease. Traditional Chinese medicine has a long clinical history for the prevention and treatment of this kind of acute infectious disease. Qingfei Paidu Decoction (QFPD) is widely used in treating COVID-19 in China. However, there is still a lack of comprehensive and systematic evidence on the effectiveness and safety of Qingfei Paidu Decoction.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec sec-type="methods">
  <title>Methods:</title>
  <p> We will search each database from the built-in until May 2020. The English literature mainly searches Cochrane Library, PubMed, EMBASE, and Web of Science, while the Chinese literature comes from CNKI, CBM, VIP, and Wangfang database. Simultaneously we will retrieval clinical registration tests and grey literatures. This study only screen the clinical randomized controlled trials (RCTs) about QFPD for COVID-19 to assess its efficacy and safety. The two researchers worked independently on literature selection, data extraction, and quality assessment. The dichotomous data is represented by relative risk (RR), and the continuous is expressed by mean difference (MD) or standard mean difference (SMD), eventually the data is synthesized using a fixed effect model (FEM) or a random effect model (REM) depending on whether or not heterogeneity exists. Total clinical effective rate, improvement rate of lung CT, adverse events were evaluated as the main outcomes. Effective rate of clinical symptoms, treatment time were secondary outcomes. Finally, meta-analysis was conducted by RevMan software version 5.3.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec sec-type="results">
  <title>Results:</title>
  <p> The results of our research will be published in a peer-reviewed journal.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec sec-type="conclusion">
  <title>Conclusion:</title>
  <p> This systematic review aims to provide new evidence of QFPD for COVID-19 in terms of its efficacy and safety.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>PROSPERO registration number:</title>
  <p> CRD42020200894.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
