<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0050">In parallel, a letter reported that use of methylprednisolone (1–2 mg/kg/day for 5–7 days) in 26 patients with severe COVID-19 was associated with better radiographic findings and shorter duration of supplemental oxygen therapy (
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2020</xref>). A recent preprint of a multicenter, randomized, open-label, controlled clinical trial of critically ill patients with COVID-19 demonstrated benefit of dexamethasone (orally or intravenously, 6 mg once daily for 10 days) to those who only received standard treatment. Alternatively, pregnant or breastfeeding women were randomized to receive prednisolone (orally, 40 mg) or hydrocortisone (intravenously, 80 mg twice daily). The RECOVERY trial enrolled 6425 patients in the United Kingdom’s National Health System and demonstrated a reduction in mortality by one-third in patients requiring mechanical ventilation and by one-fifth in patients who needed oxygen but no invasive ventilation. No survival benefit was observed among those who did not require supplemental oxygen at admission (
 <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Horby et al., 2020</xref>). Complete analyses of this study are pending, and peer review is ongoing. Nevertheless, given the compelling evidence of benefit, WHO and several national institutes of health are updating their guidelines to recommend that dexamethasone be administered to COVID-19-patients with hypoxemic respiratory failure (
 <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization (WHO, 2020</xref>). In a recent guideline, the Infectious Diseases Society of America (IDSA) recommended against the use of corticosteroids in COVID-19 based on data from previous coronaviruses in which no benefit was demonstrated (
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">Bhimraj et al., 2020</xref>). However, on June 25, 2020, given the findings of the RECOVERY trial, this guideline was updated to advise glucocorticoids rather than no glucocorticoids (preferably dexamethasone, alternatively methylprednisolone or prednisone) in hospitalized patients with severe COVID-19. Steroid therapy remains discouraged in patients without hypoxemia (
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">Bhimraj et al., 2020</xref>).
</p>
