<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ind Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ind Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">INDHEALTH</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Industrial Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0019-8366</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1880-8026</issn><publisher><publisher-name>National Institute of Occupational Safety and Health, Japan</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4667046</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2014-0259</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2486/indhealth.2014-0259</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Assessing real-time performances of N95 respirators for health care workersby simulated workplace protection factors</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>KIM</surname><given-names>Hyunwook</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>BAEK</surname><given-names>Jung-Eun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>SEO</surname><given-names>Hye-Kyung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>LEE</surname><given-names>Jong-Eun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>MYONG</surname><given-names>Jun-Pyo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>LEE</surname><given-names>Seung-Joo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>LEE</surname><given-names>Jin-Ho</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Preventive Medicine, College of Medicine, The
Catholic University of Korea, Republic of Korea</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Deptartment of Occupational and Environmental Hygiene,
Graduate School of Public Health, The Catholic University of Korea, Republic of
Korea</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>College of Nursing, The Catholic University of Korea,
Republic of Korea</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Deptartment of Occupational and Environmental Medicine,
College of Medicine, The Catholic University of Korea, Republic of Korea</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>3&#x02005;M Personal Safety Division, APAC Laboratory, 3&#x02005;M Korea,
Republic of Korea</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email xlink:href="hwkim@catholic.ac.kr">hwkim@catholic.ac.kr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>8</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>53</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>553</fpage><lpage>561</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9;2015 National Institute of Occupational Safety and
Health</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-nd) License. </license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>To assess performances of N95 respirators for Health Care Workers (HCWs) in a simulated
health-care setting, we measured the Simulated Workplace Protection Factors (SWPFs) in
real-time from the volunteers. A total of 49 study subjects, wearing 3&#x02005;M respirator Model
N95 1860 and 1860S, were fit tested using the OSHA Exercise Regimen. The test subjects
were asked to perform simulated scenarios, including patient assessments, suction, and
intravenous injection (IV) treatment. Two TSI PortaCount instruments continuously measured
concentrations in the respirator and the room concentration. For Quantitative Fit Testing
(QNFT), 36 out of 49 (73.5%) passed the fit factor (FF) criteria set at 100 and 13 (26.5%)
failed. The results of QNFT were found to have a low correlation with SWPF, with
R<sup>2</sup>=0.32. The geometric means (GM) and geometric standard deviations (GSD) of
SWPF were 68.8 (1.1) for those subjects who passed and 39.6 (1.3) for those who failed.
Real-time assessments of SWPF showed that lower SWPFs were; moving head up and down, and
bending at the waist. This study identifies the needs for providing different sizes of
respirators for HCWs and the importance of performing fit tests for HCWs regularly. And
particular movements were identified as attributing factors affecting more on SWPFs.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>N95 respirators</kwd><kwd>Simulated Workplace Protection Factors (SWPFs)</kwd><kwd>Real-time</kwd><kwd>Fit test</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Various types of workers comprise the health-care industry, including physicians, dentists,
and nurses as well as a broad range of other workers such as medical and nursing school
students, and volunteers who are constantly in contact with patients in settings other than
hospitals<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><sup>)</sup>. These workers could be
directly exposed to health-care-related infections as their jobs involve providing health
care and treatment to individuals with infectious diseases. Thus, the risk of infection
through contact with patients is high among workers in the health-care industry, and their
morbid risk of work-related diseases is higher than that of workers in other services<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><sup>)</sup>. Health Care Workers (HCWs) can be exposed
to infectious diseases through various modes. Among the modes of transmission is through
air-borne infection, in which infected particles larger than 5 <italic>&#x000b5;</italic>m in
diameter are projected into the air during coughing, sneezing, or conversation and
splattered to the conjunctiva, or nasal or oral mucosa of humans, thereby spreading the
infection<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><sup>)</sup>. For example, in case of
tuberculosis world-wide, 8.5 million persons were newly contracted in 2011, of whom 1.45
million died. While tuberculosis is becoming a worldwide health issue, Korea was reported to
have the highest incidence of tuberculosis and tuberculosis-related mortality rate among the
OECD member countries<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref><sup>)</sup>. For this reason,
HCW are advised to wear N95 respirators that passed the fit test or high-quality respirators
when they enter rooms where patients with suspected or confirmed respiratory organ
tuberculosis (pulmonary or laryngeal tuberculosis) are confined<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><sup>)</sup>. In addition, the Korean Ministry of Health and Welfare
established the Guideline for Nosocomial Infection Prevention Control, in which wearing of
special masks such as the N95 respirator are recommended in order to prevent infection
through inhalation of small (less than 5 <italic>&#x000b5;</italic>m) infectious particles floating
in the air current along with dusts<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><sup>)</sup>.
However, considering that reducing the inflow of pathogens to the body greatly depends on
the degree of fit of masks to the face, regardless of the quality of respirators and the
efficiency of filters, wearers are not fully protected unless the respirator appropriately
fits them<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><sup>)</sup>. In a study that evaluated the
effects of the N95 respirator and surgical masks within a simulated test space, the effects
of an inappropriately worn respirator were worse than those of a loose-fitting
respirator<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><sup>)</sup>. Furthermore, other studies
indicated that the fit factor extremely decreased, unless the N95 respirator was worn
appropriately<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p><p>Therefore, a quantitative fit test is highly important. However, environmental conditions
differ between workplaces. In addition, intrinsic respiratory rate and respiratory rate
during work could differ, making it impossible to guarantee long-term protection<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><sup>)</sup>. Fit test results only indicate the degree
of fit between the face of the wearer and the respirator under the condition at the time of
measurement and do not predict the degree of protection provided to the wearer from harmful
substances in real workplaces<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><sup>)</sup>. Thereby, NIOSH suggested that a workplace
test or a simulated workplace test should be included in the respiratory protection
program<xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p><p>When wearing a respirator in real workplaces, the amount of aerosol particles that enter
the respiratory area depends on various factors such as the concentration and size
distribution of the aerosol particles in the surrounding environment of the wearer, the
types of filters used, the amount of sweat and dusts on the face of the wearer, the movement
of the facial muscles, and the wearer&#x02019;s will to wear the respirator appropriately<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><sup>)</sup>. Therefore, it is important that
respirator fit is evaluated while workers are performing actual work activities wearing a
respirator. However, measuring respirator performance in actual workplaces is difficult<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref><sup>)</sup>. Hence, the Simulated Workplace Protection Factor (SWPF) can be
evaluated by using a laboratory-based method in combination with real workplace
environments<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p><p>Therefore, this study aimed to identify the protective effect of the N95 respirator for
HCWs in a simulated work place. In addition, several facial dimensions of test subjects were
measured so as to identify correlations with the fit factor and SWPF through the fit test,
and real-time SWPFs were measured while performing simulated tasks of nursing so as to
identify contributing activities on SWPFs.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>General Methods</title><p>A fit test using TSI PortaCount Pro+ 8038 equipment was performed while the test subjects
wore the N95 respirator. The criteria of the Occupational Safety and Health Administration
(OSHA) Protocol<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref><sup>)</sup> were used in the
Quantitative Fit Testing (QNFT). QNFT scores higher than 100 were applied as the passing
criteria. Every test subject stopped the intake of drinks or foods 30 min before the start
of the experiment and avoided smoking<xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref><sup>)</sup>. The test subjects who completed the fit test were asked to
undertake three scenarios. The real-time performances of the respirator were assessed by
measuring the ambient air-borne particle concentrations in the room and outside and inside
the respirator by using two kinds of fit test equipment. A simulated medical environment
was utilized as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_002">Fig. 2</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_002" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>View of health care setting environment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="indhealth-53-553-g002"/></fig>, and three health-care task scenarios were constructed by professional nurses and
used in the setting. SWPF was calculated by using real-time measurement data of air-borne
particle concentrations outside and inside the respirator while the subjects were
performing care for patients.</p><sec><title>1) Test subjects</title><p>For this study, test subjects were voluntarily recruited by posting advertisements or
sending advertisement through e-mail, targeting health professionals, particularly
nurses and nursing school students. In consideration of the appropriate sample size for
the respirator fit test that was calculated<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref><sup>)</sup>, 49 test subjects were evaluated.</p><p>Facial dimensions, namely face width and face length, were measured to examine if the
recruited subjects were included in the NIOSH Respirator Fit Test Panel (the NIOSH
panel). Referring to previous study results<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref><sup>)</sup>, nasal root breadth, nose width, lip length,
bitragion-subnasale arc, face length, and menton-subnasale length were also measured as
illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig. 1</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_001" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Facial dimensions measured.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="indhealth-53-553-g001"/></fig><xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><sup>)</sup>. A sliding caliper and a spreading caliper were used
as measuring tools<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><sup>)</sup>. For facial measurements, the reference points of the
measurements were determined by using the guidelines from SizeKorea<xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref><sup>)</sup>. In order to reduce errors in the measurement values,
mean values from 3 replications were calculated. In addition, only the individuals
included in the NIOSH panel were selected as test subjects.</p></sec><sec><title>2) Equipment</title><p>TSI PortaCount Pro+ 8038 and N95-Companion TSI PortaCount Plus Model 8020 equipment,
which quantitatively measure the ambient air-borne dust concentration and the fit level
of a respirator, respectively, were used. The linear correlation coefficient of the
ambient air-borne dust concentrations between the two kinds of equipment was
R<sup>2</sup>=0.9949 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_003">Fig. 3</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_003" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Relationship between the two instrument for ambient particle concentration
(p/cm<sup>3</sup>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="indhealth-53-553-g003"/></fig>). Thus two instruments were considered in good agreements to use
side-by-side.</p><p>In addition, in order not to change the condition of face seal by the weight of the
Tygon tube that was connected to TSI PortaCount Pro + 8038, which was used to measure
the dust concentration inside the respirator, the tube was supported with a necklace
attached with a binder clip<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>3) Respirator</title><p>3&#x02005;M 1860 or 1860s models of the N95 respirators, which have been used and sold in
medical work places, were used. The two models were certified by NIOSH.</p></sec><sec><title>4) SWPF</title><p>After discussion with an expert (a nursing professor), three health-care scenarios
including patient assessment, suction treatment, and IV treatment were selected among
various tasks nurses normally perform (<xref rid="tbl_001" ref-type="table">Table
1</xref><table-wrap id="tbl_001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Health care scenarios developed for the study</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenarios 1 (Assessment)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenarios 2 (Suction)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenarios 3 (IV Treatment)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 s to 1 min 48 s</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 s to 1 min 44 s</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 sec to 1 min 42 s</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1. Patient bedside diagnostics</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1. Upper airway suction</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1. Administer IV care</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000b7; Vitals : blood pressure</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000b7; Suction : by aspirator</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000b7; IV : Injection of vein</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2. Ask question</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2. Notify aspirator</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2. Notify IV care</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3. Check blood pressure</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3. Knock chest and put on gloves</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3. Clean alcohol</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4. Raise/lower stretcher as need</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4. Raise/lower stretcher as need</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4. Tie tourniquet, push IV medication</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5. Clean hands</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5. Perform aspirator</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5. Raise/lower stretcher as need</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>). To simulate real hospital bed conditions, the following were prepared in
the simulated environment: sphygmomanometer, hand sanitizer, wall aspirator, tracheotomy
tube, disposable gloves, tourniquet, 2-cc syringe, alcohol cotton balls, and dummy
(simulated patients).</p><p>SWPF was calculated by measuring the concentrations inside and outside the respirator
and using the equation (1)<xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref><sup>)</sup>.</p><p><disp-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="indhealth-53-553-e001.jpg"/></disp-formula>...(1)</p><p>SWPF = Simulated Workplace Protection Factor</p><p>CA = concentration of particles outside the respirator</p><p>CB = concentration of particles inside the respirator</p><p>Overall SWPF was calculated for each SWPF activity by using equation (2) as follows:</p><p><disp-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="indhealth-53-553-e002.jpg"/></disp-formula>...(2)</p><p>SWPF = Each SWPF calculated by the concentrations outside and inside the respirator</p><p>n = total number of SWPF activities evaluated</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The general characteristics of the subjects were subjected to a frequency analysis and
expressed as percentages. The mean and standard deviation of each facial dimension (mm) was
calculated, followed by a comparison of the mean difference between the men and women by
using the <italic>t</italic>-test. The fit factors (FF) were expressed as geometric means
(GM) and geometric standard deviations (GSD). A regression analysis between FF and SWPF was
performed. The level of significance for all the statistical values was set at &#x003b1;=0.05.
Collected data were analyzed by using the SPSS statistics 18.0 program.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Ethics</title><p>The study procedure was approved by the Catholic Medical Center Office of Human Research
Protection Program.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s5"><title>Results</title><sec><title>General characteristics of the test subjects</title><p>The test subjects were 49 individuals; 33 (67.3%) were female and 16 (32.7%) were male.
Their mean age was 23.0 &#x000b1; 3.8&#x02005;yr. The age distribution was as follows: 36 persons (75.0%)
younger than 25&#x02005;yr; 9 persons (18.4%) between 25 and 30&#x02005;yr; 3 persons (6.1%) between 30
and 35&#x02005;yr; and 1 person (2.0%) older than 35&#x02005;yr. The distribution of the subjects&#x02019;
occupations was as follows: 37 subjects (75.5%) nursing students and 12 subjects (24.5%)
nurses. The size distribution of the N95 respirator was as follows: 46 subjects (93.9%)
wore the small (S), and 3 subjects (6.1%) wore the medium (M) size respirator (<xref rid="tbl_002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref><table-wrap id="tbl_002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>General characteristics of the study subjects</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Classification</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sex</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (32.7%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (67.3%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#x02013;24</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (73.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#x02013;29</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (18.4%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30&#x02013;34</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (6.1%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;35</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.0%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Job</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nursing student</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (75.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nurse</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (24.5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">N95 Size</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medium</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (6.1%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (93.9%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>N: Number of subjects</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>).</p></sec><sec><title>Facial dimensions</title><p>The statistical data of the facial dimensions of 49 subjects are presented in <xref rid="tbl_003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref><table-wrap id="tbl_003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Summary statistics of facial dimension measurements</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="5" valign="middle" align="center" colspan="1">Item</th><th colspan="3" valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1">Male (N=16)</th><th colspan="3" valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1">Female (N=33)</th><th rowspan="5" valign="middle" align="center" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="center" colspan="1">M&#x000b1;SD</th><th colspan="2" valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1">95th percentile</th><th rowspan="3" valign="middle" align="center" colspan="1">M&#x000b1;SD</th><th colspan="2" valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1">95th percentile</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LCL</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UCL</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LCL</th><th valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UCL</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Face length</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117.2 &#x000b1; 5.0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120.0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110.8 &#x000b1; 4.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109.3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112.3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.356</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lip length</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.1 &#x000b1; 3.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.9</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.9 &#x000b1; 2.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nose width</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.4 &#x000b1; 2.0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.7 &#x000b1; 2.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.435</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nasale root breadth</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.6 &#x000b1; 3.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.6 &#x000b1; 3.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.9</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.777</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bitragion-subnasale arc</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">179.4 &#x000b1; 22.1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">167.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">191.6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176.4 &#x000b1; 19.3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">183.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.229</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bizygomatic breadth</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138.6 &#x000b1; 8.1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">143.1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">131.6 &#x000b1; 6.0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133.8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.161</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Menton-subnasale length</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.6 &#x000b1; 3.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.7 &#x000b1; 4.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.193</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>M &#x000b1; SD: Mean and standard deviation (mm). LCL: Lower control limit, UCL: Upper
control limit. *Statistically significant difference between gender by
<italic>t</italic>-test.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>. The results of the <italic>t</italic>-test to identify sex-related
differences in values indicate a statistically significant difference
(<italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.05) in lip length (<xref rid="tbl_003" ref-type="table">Table
3</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Test Panel</title><p>The study subjects were 49 individuals who were included in the NIOSH panel. Of the
subjects, 33 (67.3%) were female and 16 (32.7%) were male. Their facial lengths ranged
from 102 to 126.7&#x02005;mm, and their facial widths ranged from 120.5 to 153.3&#x02005;mm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_004">Fig. 4</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_004" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Distribution of test subjects in the NIOSH panel constructed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="indhealth-53-553-g004"/></fig>).</p></sec><sec><title>Correlation between the fit test results and SWPF</title><p>Since the results of the fit test did not follow a normal distribution, both the FF and
SWPF values were log transformed and the presented with GM (GSD). According to the results
of the fit test using the 49 test subjects who were included in the NIOSH panel, 36 test
subjects (73.5%) passed and the GM (GSD) of FF was 156.3 (1.3). However, 13 test subjects
(26.5%) failed and the GM (GSD) of FF was 37.0 (1.7) (<xref rid="tbl_004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref><table-wrap id="tbl_004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><title>Fit test result</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" align="center" valign="middle" colspan="1">Fit test</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">N (%)</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">GM (GSD)</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pass</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fail</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pass (FF&#x02265;100)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fail (FF&#x0003c;100)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (73.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (26.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156.3 (1.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.0 (1.7)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>GM: Geometric means, GSD: Geometric standard deviations</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>). The GM (GSD) of SWPF values of the test subjects who passed and those who
failed the fit test were 68.8 (1.1) and 39.6 (1.3), respectively, indicating that the
latter had generally lower values than the former (<xref rid="tbl_005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref><table-wrap id="tbl_005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><title>SWPFs by subject who passed or failed the fit test</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" align="center" valign="middle" colspan="1">SWPF</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">N (%)</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">GM (GSD)</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pass</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fail</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pass (FF&#x02265;100)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fail (FF&#x0003c;100)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (73.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (26.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.8 (1.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.6 (1.3)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>GM: Geometric means, GSD: Geometric standard deviations</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>).</p><p>The relationship between FF and SWPF was analyzed using a regression analysis. When the
fit factor was assessed regarding its effect on the SWPF, the explanatory power was 31.6%
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_005">Fig. 5</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_005" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>Relationship between the overall SWPFs and FFs for three scenarios.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="indhealth-53-553-g005"/></fig>).</p></sec><sec><title>Real-time SWPF</title><p>The mean concentrations outside and inside the N95 respirator, and the mean real-time
measurement values of SWPF for all the test subjects who either passed or failed the fit
test were calculated for each exercise and presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_006">Figs. 6</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_006" position="float"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p>Fluctuations of particle concentrations (ambient and respirator) and overall SWPFs
by exercise for three different scenarios from test subjects who passed the fit
test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="indhealth-53-553-g006"/></fig> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_007">7</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_007" position="float"><label>Fig. 7.</label><caption><p>Fluctuations of particle concentrations (ambient and respirator) and overall SWPFs
by exercise for three different scenarios from test subjects who failed the fit
test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="indhealth-53-553-g007"/></fig>. The air-borne dust concentrations outside in the simulated medical environment
ranged from 3,420 to 17,800 p/cm<sup>3</sup>. The particle concentrations inside the
respirator ranged from 11 to 3,949 p/cm<sup>3</sup>, and the real-time SWPF values ranged
from 1.4 to 364.</p><p>Among real-time SWPFs by scenario assessed, greater fluctuations were observed from the
test subjects who failed the fit test. In addition, lower SWPFs were measured while
performing the following movements; moving head up and down, and bending at the waist
(e.g. raising and/or lowering the stretcher rails). Therefore, while performing these
movements, respirator seals around the face might have been broken and thus allowed
particles leaked in the respirator, particularly from those who failed the fit test.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s6"><title>Discussion</title><p>In medical environments, HCWs may reduce their risk of infection by wearing N95 respirators
from infected patients and inhalation of contaminated substances in the air. A fit test was
performed in this study to determine the protective effect of wearing the N95 respirator
targeting HCWs, including nurses and nursing students, who are frequently exposed to health
care-related infection mediated by droplets or air-borne pathogens. A simulated medical
environment that is similar to real-world medical environments was created for the study.
Three health-care tasks, selected by a field expert, namely patient assessment (measuring
blood pressure), suction treatment, and IV treatment, were simulated and performed by the
participants. The concentrations outside and inside the mask were measured in order to
evaluate real-time SWPFs during the activities.</p><p>In the SWPF experiment, weak correlations (R<sup>2</sup>=0.316) between FF and SWPF were
found in this study. The result was similar to that of the previous studies that showed a
low correlation between two values<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref><sup>)</sup>. Another study done with the powered air
purifying respirator<xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref><sup>)</sup> found no
correlation between QNFT and WPF. But, a previous research done in a simulated environment
found that fit factor was found to be highly correlated with actual exposure measurement
values in the simulated medical workplace<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref><sup>)</sup>. Unidentified individual-specific variables were speculated to
affect correlation variations<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><sup>)</sup>. However
some exercises in this study, such as moving head up and down and bending over, were more
influential on SWPF than others. During the assessment of real-time SWPFs, these movements
were found to affect the degree of fit of the respirator. These influencing movements or
activities need to be carefully managed during patients&#x02019; care so as to minimize the breakage
of the respirator seals.</p><p>In contrast, a study on the real-time identification of the protection factor according to
OSHA Protocol 1910.134<xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref><sup>)</sup> showed that
among the SWPFs, talking or grimace was more frequent than other activities<xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref><sup>)</sup>. Hauge <italic>et al</italic>. study<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref><sup>)</sup>, however, found no specific activities (e.g., talking or movement)
to be related with the inside-respirator concentrations. Since the FF exercises used in this
study were composed of only 6 exercises, excluding grimace, we had no information on the
effects of grimace. Performing QNFT for respirator wearers is useful in terms of providing
valuable training of donning as well as selecting correct sizes. But passing QNFT does not
necessarily guarantee wearers&#x02019; protection because of lack of correlations with SWPF or WPF,
a refinement of QNFT exercises so as better predict SWPF or WPF needs to be done.</p><p>All the subjects in this study, except three (3) subjects, wore small-size N95 respirators.
This finding was similar to that of a study with subjects from the NIOSH panel 1&#x02013;7 that
showed maximum fit with the S-size respirator. Meanwhile, the subjects from test panel 8&#x02013;10
exhibited maximum fit with the M-size respirator<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
<xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><sup>)</sup>. In addition, according to the study
with the NIOSH panel, subjects with small/ medium, or large facial dimensions who wore S- or
M-size respirator, respectively, exhibited better fit<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><sup>)</sup>. According to the result of the fit test, the pass rate was 73.5% (36
persons) among the 49 test subjects. This was higher than the result of the QNFT experiment
using the same N95 respirator model, which showed a pass rate of 57.4%<xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref><sup>)</sup>. The US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC)
indicated that the QNFT fail rate of the N95 respirator was 20&#x02013;100%<xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref><sup>)</sup> and recommended the use of respirator products with an
optimal fit for each individual<xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref><sup>)</sup>. The
result indicated that respirator wearers should be provided different sizes of respirators
so as to decide a correct size for them after QNFT.</p><p>A limitation of this study is the difference in considering such influencing factors from
those in real workplaces. For example, influencing factors, including the effect of duration
of rewearing a respirator, the model or size of other respirators, and the effect of face
size or type, have different effects on fit<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref><sup>)</sup>. In addition, the ambient air particle concentrations in the
simulated room, which were generally stable throughout the experiment, may be quite
different from the real world situations where high and fluctuating concentrations can be
found.</p><p>In a series of health care simulation studies by NIOSH researchers<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref><sup>)</sup>, several
activities besides OSHA exercises were included such as, hanging an IV bag, inserting a
syringe into an IV bag, carrying weight, and walking, etc. Although it is judged that this
study did not fully consider influencing factors in real workplaces, we believe that a
further study that compensates for these activities will provide HCWs with a higher level of
protection with the use of respirators.</p><p>Despite of these shortcomings, this study evaluated the performance of the N95 respirator
through the fit test, targeting health care workers, and identified levels of protection
depending on the wearers&#x02019; activities by performing a real-time SWPF evaluation. We found
that even with a high-quality respirator, if the respirator is not worn properly or the
respirator size is not optimal, an adequate protection could not be provided to HCWs, who
have a high risk of exposure to air-borne diseases such as tuberculosis due to their job
activities and work environments.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s7"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This study aimed to determine the degree of protection that the N95 respirator provides to
HCWs by performing a real-time SWPF evaluation. Test subjects performed 3 types of scenarios
in a simulated patient treatment environment. In the SWPF evaluation depending on task, the
concentration inside the respirators of the subjects who failed the fit test exhibited a
higher fluctuation than that of the test subjects who passed the fit test. Because actions
such as raising a rail or lowering a bed, which requires moving the head down or bending at
waist, affect the fit level of the respirator, the concentration inside the respirator in
each scenario tended to have a higher variation.</p><p>During the experiment, we found that particular movements, such as bending at the waist and
moving head up and down, were identified as contributing factors affecting more on SWPFs.
Therefore, it is necessary to perform the fit test using simulated activities of the real
workplaces. Performing the fit test before distributing respirators and training the proper
use of respirators seem to be very important for HCWs. Considering the recent increase in
the incidence of air-borne diseases such as tuberculosis among HCWs, a better respiratory
protection program with regular trainings should be provided in order to protect them from
infectious diseases. This study also identified the needs for providing different sizes of
respirators for HCWs.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>This study was supported by a basic research fund from 3&#x02005;M Korea in 2014. Also a set of TSI
fit testing equipment was donated by APM Engineering. We appreciate both companies for
supporting this research.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Occupational infections of health care
personnel in Korea</article-title>. <source>Hanyang Med Rev</source><volume>31</volume>,
<fpage>200</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>. </mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">The Occupational Safety and
Health Research Institute (<year>2002</year>) A study on development health administration
manual of health care workers. The Occupational Safety and Health Research Institute,
Korea.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>How to prevent transmission of
infectious agents in healthcare settings</article-title>. <source>Hanyang Med
Rev</source><volume>31</volume>, <fpage>190</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. </mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">World Health Organization
(<year>2011</year>) Global tuberculosis control: WHO report 2011, World Health
Organization, Geneva.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">MOH (<year>2005</year>)
Prevention of nosocomial infection control guideline. Ministry of Health &#x00026; Welfare,
Korea.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name><surname>Colton</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Birkner</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brosseau</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>) Respiratory Protection: A Manual and Guideline, 2nd
Ed., American Industrial Hygiene Association, Akron.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Noti</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindsley</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Blachere</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kashon</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Thewlis</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>McMillen</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Szalajda</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Beezhold</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Detection of infectious influenza virus
in cough aerosols generated in a simulated patient examination room</article-title>.
<source>Clin Infect Dis</source><volume>54</volume>,
<fpage>1569</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22460981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Grinshpun</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Maynard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reponen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Laboratory and field evaluation of a
new personal sampling system for assessing the protection provided by the N95 filtering
facepiece respirators against particles</article-title>. <source>Ann Occup
Hyg</source><volume>49</volume>, <fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15668259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Grinshpun</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Reponen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Respiratory performance offered by N95
respirators and surgical masks: human subject evaluation with NaCl aerosol representing
bacterial and viral particle size range</article-title>. <source>Ann Occup
Hyg</source><volume>52</volume>, <fpage>177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18326870</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Oberg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Brosseau</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Surgical mask filter and fit
performance</article-title>. <source>Am J Infect Control</source><volume>36</volume>,
<fpage>276</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18455048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Workplace protection factors for
negative pressure half-mask facepiece respirators</article-title>. <source>J Int Soc
Resp Prot</source><volume>2</volume>,
<fpage>347</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Peach</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Performance measurements on a powered
air-purifying respirator made during actual field use in a silica bagging
operation</article-title>. <source>Ann Occup Hyg</source><volume>27</volume>,
<fpage>251</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6314865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Byeon</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Na</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Evaluation of workplace protection
factors for some half&#x02014;facepiece respirators in welding workplace</article-title>.
<source>J Korean Soc Occup Environ Hyg</source><volume>9</volume>,
<fpage>14</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">NIOSH (<year>1987</year>) NIOSH
Guide to Industrial Respiratory Protection, No. 87&#x02013;116, U.S Department of Health and Human
Services. National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health,
Cincinnati.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenhart</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Campell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Provost</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Letter to the editor</article-title>.
<source>Am Ind Hyg Assoc J</source><volume>44</volume>,
<fpage>B25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Coffey</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Comparison of six respirator fit-test
methods with an actual measurement of exposure in a simulated health care environment:
part I&#x02014;protocol development</article-title>. <source>Am Ind Hyg Assoc
J</source><volume>59</volume>, <fpage>852</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9866165</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Coffey</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Comparison of six respirator fit-test
methods with an actual measurement of exposure in a simulated health care environment:
part II&#x02014;method comparison testing</article-title>. <source>Am Ind Hyg Assoc
J</source><volume>59</volume>, <fpage>862</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9866166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Hauge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brosseau</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Colton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Real-time fit of a respirator during
simulated health care tasks</article-title>. <source>J Occup Environ
Hyg</source><volume>9</volume>, <fpage>563</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22924959</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Landsittel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Newcomb</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Berry Ann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Determining sample size and a passing
criterion for respirator fit-test panels</article-title>. <source>J Occup Environ
Hyg</source><volume>11</volume>, <fpage>77</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24369929</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Review on the development of
3&#x02014;dimensional face recognition and measurement for the design of
respirators</article-title>. <source>J Korean Soc Occup Environ
Hyg</source><volume>11</volume>, <fpage>92</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>101</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Development of half-masks well-fitting
for Korean faces (1)&#x02014;facial dimensions and predictors of fit for
half-mask</article-title>. <source>J Korean Soc Occup Environ
Hyg</source><volume>12</volume>, <fpage>46</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhi</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Development of half-masks well-fitting
for Korean faces (2)&#x02014;pilot study&#x02014;</article-title>. <source>J Korean Soc Occup Environ
Hyg</source><volume>14</volume>, <fpage>8</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Hack</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>McConville</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1978</year>) <article-title>Respirator protection factors: part
I&#x02014;development of an anthropometric test panel</article-title>. <source>Am Ind Hyg Assoc
J</source><volume>39</volume>, <fpage>970</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">742600</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Groce</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahlers</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Iskander</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Landsittel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Guffey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Viscusi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaffer</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Correlation between respirator fit and
respirator fit test panel cells by respirator size</article-title>. <source>J Occup
Environ Hyg</source><volume>5</volume>, <fpage>617</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18666022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradtmiller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaffer</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>New respirator fit test panels
representing the current U.S. civilian work force</article-title>. <source>J Occup
Environ Hyg</source><volume>4</volume>, <fpage>647</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17613722</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="eref">Size Korea. Size Korea of
Standardization anthropometry. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sizekorea.kr/01_sizekorea/research.asp?OlapCode=SIZU0102">http://sizekorea.kr/01_sizekorea/research.asp?OlapCode=SIZU0102</ext-link> Accessed
February 19, 2014.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="eref">OSHA Fit Testing Procedures
(Mandatory). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.osha.gov/pls/oshaweb/owadisp.show_document?p_table=STANDARDS&#x00026;p_id=9780.">https://www.osha.gov/pls/oshaweb
/owadisp.show_document?p_table=STANDARDS&#x00026;p_id=9780.</ext-link> Accessed August 4,
2014.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><institution>Inc TSI</institution> (<year>2001</year>) PortaCount Plus TM Model 8020 Operation and Service
Manual (Product Manual), TSI Inc, St. Paul.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Peach</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><name><surname>Cutright</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Iskander</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Workplace protection factor
measurements on powered air-purifying respirators at a secondary lead smelter: results
and discussion</article-title>. <source>Am Ind Hyg Assoc J</source><volume>45</volume>,
<fpage>681</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6496315</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Yau</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Charm</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Sensitivity and specificity of the
user-seal-check in determining the fit of N95 respirators</article-title>. <source>J
Hosp Infect</source><volume>77</volume>, <fpage>252</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21236516</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Centers for Disease Control
and Prevention (CDC) (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Laboratory performance evaluation
of N95 filtering facepiece respirators, 1996</article-title>. <source>MMWR Morb Mortal
Wkly Rep</source><volume>47</volume>, <fpage>1045</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9869077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Derrick</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomersall</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lui</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Predictive value of the user seal check
in determining half-face respirator fit</article-title>. <source>J Hosp
Infect</source><volume>59</volume>, <fpage>152</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15620450</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">OSHA (<year>1998</year>)
Respiratory Protection: 29 CFR 1910.134, Appendix A., US Department of Labor, Occupational
Safety and Health Administration, Washington, DC.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Coffey</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Comparison of six respirator fit-test
methods with an actual measurement of exposure in a simulated health care environment:
part III&#x02014;validation</article-title>. <source>Am Ind Hyg Assoc
J</source><volume>60</volume>, <fpage>363</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10386357</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name><surname>Coffey</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvert</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Fitting characteristics of eighteen N95
filtering-facepiece respirators</article-title>. <source>J Occup Environ
Hyg</source><volume>1</volume>, <fpage>262</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15204866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>