<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A previous description of HSV indicated that the genomic lengths of the virus types were 152 201 bp for HSV1 (strain McKrae)
 <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">40</xref> and 154 746 bp for HSV2 (strain HG52),
 <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">41</xref> and these genomes could encode at least 80 proteins, in addition to some RNA molecules. Among these proteins, approximately 20% were found to directly support viral replication,
 <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">42</xref> 12% were immunogenic surface glycoproteins,
 <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">43</xref> and more than 50% were involved in interactions with the host and indirectly supported virus survival in vivo.
 <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">44</xref> The existence of these kinds of protein in HSV, which has coevolved with humans for a long time, suggests not only that viral pathogenesis involves various interactions of viral molecules with different cells and tissues
 <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">45</xref> but also that the virus uses strategies to activate cellular transcription and evade immune monitoring to create an effective environment for viral proliferation.
 <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">46</xref> It could be proposed that immune pressure from the host has pushed HSV to fully exploit its genomic evolution by encoding a series of functional molecules and gradually creating different pathways for blocking or weakening innate and adaptive immunity during the continuous interplay between viruses and humans.
 <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">47</xref> Of note, a recently published paper indicates that the HSV1 0ΔNLS vaccine elicits antibody responses against heterogeneous viral proteins, including nonstructural proteins.
 <xref rid="rmv2054-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">48</xref> However, to some extent, the characterized pathological processes of HSV in infected individuals, including primary acute infection, immune evasion, latent infection, and reactivated infection in neurons, can be viewed as clinical phenotypes that reflect the mechanisms by which viral molecules compete with, interfere with, activate, and hijack host defense. Therefore, investigating the interplay between viral molecules and host factors could improve our systematic understanding of viral infection strategies and inspire new ideas for vaccine development.
</p>
