<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Genomic DNA was extracted from a minimum of 6 million PBMC or 200 μl of buffy coat using a QIAmp DNA blood minikit (Qiagen). HLA class I HLA-A, -B, and -C typing was performed to subtype-level (4-digit) resolution using a modified in-house sequence-based method (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>). Briefly, 1-kb fragments, including exons 2 and 3 of HLA-A, -B, and -C, were amplified using universal, locus-specific primers and the Roche Expand high-fidelity PCR system (Roche Applied Science, Laval, PQ, Canada). PCR products were cleaned up with ExoSAP-IT (Affimetrix, Cleveland, OH, USA) and sequenced on a 3730xl genetic analyzer using BigDye 3.1 chemistry (Thermo Fisher). HLA allele assignment was done using uTYPEv6 (Thermo Fisher) by comparison to the IMGT/HLA database (
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>). Using this method, a total of 92 HLA-A, 91 HLA-B, and 39 HLA-C allele pairs within the Common and Well-Documented Catalogue (
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>) present polymorphism phase ambiguities at the resolution level of the first (i.e., allele-level) or second (i.e., subtype-level) HLA fields (see Table S1 in the supplemental material). These ambiguities were resolved by assigning the most frequent allele combination according to linkage disequilibrium data obtained from our Mexican mestizo population. Ambiguous HLA pairs due to polymorphic differences outside exons 2 and 3 were managed as G groups, including A*74:01:01G (A*74:01 in the analysis, encompassing A*74:01/A*74:02), C*18:01:01G (C*18:01 in the analysis, encompassing C*18:01/C*18:02), C*17:01:01G (C*17:01 in the analysis, encompassing C*17:01/C*17:02/C*17:03), and C*04:01:01G (C*04:01 in the analysis, encompassing C*04:01/C*04:09N), among others. All HLA haplotypes were confirmed using the HLA completion web tool (available at 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://boson.research.microsoft.com/hla/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://boson.research.microsoft.com/hla/</ext-link>) (
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>). Additionally, a total of 33 HLA-A or HLA-C types that failed amplification or sequencing were imputed using the same tool. HLA haplotypes with unresolved HLA-B loci were not imputed and were considered missing data (this included 8 individuals with both HLA-B alleles and 8 with one HLA-B allele missing). Raw HLA typing data are available via direct request to the authors.
</p>
