<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Moreover, while it was accompanied by broad uncertainty, spatial vaccination scenarios indicated that vaccinating the top six populous prefectures (i.e., Tokyo, Kanagawa, Osaka, Aichi, Saitama and Chiba) could potentially be more effective than random allocation, motivating additional studies on this subject. Mechanistically, the model was accompanied by two technical issues that we aim to explicitly address in future study. First, the choice of initially infectious individuals was made by randomly generating initially infectious individuals in a specific prefecture(s) according to the size of susceptible individuals across prefectures. This simulation setting mirrors our assumption that the risk of importation in each prefecture is determined by the size of susceptible individuals. Nevertheless, to adhere to reality, imported cases would more frequently arise in urban prefectures than rural prefectures; thus, our recommendation to vaccinate urban locations might have been more conservative than the actual dynamics. Second, we assumed that the fraction susceptible was uniformly distributed across prefectures due to data limitations. Under this assumption, vaccinating urban prefectures due to selective vaccination could generate a susceptible pocket in rural prefectures, which could lead to an outbreak. Spatial heterogeneity in susceptibility could act as the key to discriminating the metapopulation model from homogeneous models, and our approach was unable to capture that aspect. It should be remembered that the susceptible pocket was observed mainly among males aged 35–49 years in Japan [
 <xref rid="pone.0205889.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0205889.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], which we intend to address in the forthcoming study with age structured model. The fraction of this “high risk” subpopulation may vary by prefecture and heterogeneous contact patterns would also differ. Again, urban prefectures, in reality, may be at greater risk than our simulations.
</p>
