<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Compared with previous HIV-1 transmission network studies, which were limited to a single HIV-1 subtype at a time, HIV-TRACE is substantially powerful in analyzing multiple HIV-1 subtypes or genotypes simultaneously [
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. A limitation of our study was that the transmission network created by HIV-TRACE cannot determine the direction and order of transmission events. Ragonnet-Cronin et al [
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] have pointed out that by using such a reconstruction method, the degree, ie, the number of links within a transmission network, may be overestimated and does not represent the true events of onward transmissions. In our study, we used 3 robust centrality indicators, including average shortest path length, closeness centrality, and radiality to investigate the position of nondisclosed MSM within a transmission network to reduce possible bias due to the size of clusters or the lack of the timing of HIV-1 infection. The results of the 3 centrality indicators were significantly different between nondisclosed MSM and MSM with whom they clustered, indicating that nondisclosed MSM may play an important role in HIV-1 transmission in Guangzhou. Our results are obviously different from those reported in the UK [
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], and they may reveal differences in sexual or transmission behavior of nondisclosed MSM in different countries or regions. However, more detailed analysis including the information of transmission directions and timing of HIV-1 infection may gain crucial insight into the behavior of this population. Ratmann et al [
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] recently specified to use viral deep-sequencing to reconstruct HIV-1 transmission networks and to determine the direction of transmission in these networks. This new technique provides us with a novel tool for further characterization of the role of nondisclosed MSM in HIV-1 transmission. In addition, we did not test the role of nondisclosed MSM in transmitting HIV-1 between MSM and heterosexual epidemics through broker analysis because there were only 16 heterosexual women in our clusters and 14 of them were in the clusters with only 2 members. A nationwide study is necessary to include a sufficient number of HIV-1 sequences and HIV-infected subjects from different regions. We want to emphasize that the inference of nondisclosed MSM is based on their linkage to MSM. Therefore, any comparison with MSM is inherently biased.
</p>
