<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec>
  <title>Simple Summary</title>
  <p>This article explains the future application of the EU regulation Animal Health Law (Reg. CE 429/2016), which will be implemented in 2021. The article describes the major changes and modifications related to notifiable diseases of sheep and goats and outlines the approach that will be taken for their surveillance and control. It explains the objective of the European Commission in applying a modern animal health system based on risk assessment, updated scientific knowledge, epidemiology, and a new culture of European diseases prevention. Five categories of diseases are recognized. Category A diseases are not usually present in the EU, which must be immediately eradicated. Category B diseases must be controlled in member states and eventually eradicated while category C diseases are present in some MS, which must be prevented from spreading to disease-free states. Category D diseases only present moderate risk but necessitate measures such as movement control to prevent their spread among MS or their entry into the EU, and category E diseases need surveillance. Lastly, differences between the previous Italian regulations and the new EU law are highlighted.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Abstract</title>
  <p>After almost 40 years, the 27 member states (MS) of the European Union (EU) will comply with the European Law 429/2016 in 2021 by completing a process of unification and harmonization of all regulations related to animal health between MS. These new provisions are based on modern scientific principles on animal health, on long-term epidemiological data, and, above all, on the most current risk assessment and analysis. The paper describes all changes and updates, which will impact the Italian current National regulation. A total of 58 animal diseases have been included in the Annex II (“Listing”) and Annex IV (“Categorization”) of the new Delegated Act (DA 2018/1629). Five diseases comprising the great viral epizooties were automatically included on the list because of their primary importance. These diseases include foot and mouth disease (FMD), African swine fever (ASF), classical swine fever (CSF), highly pathogenic avian influenza (HPAI), and African horse sickness (AHS). Another 53 diseases have been identified by the ad hoc assessment on listing and categorization of animal diseases developed by the European Food Safety Association. Seventeen communicable diseases of the Order Artiodactlya (sheep, goats, deer, etc.) have been listed including foot and mouth disease, sheep and goat pox, and pestes de petits ruminants. In addition, other endemic diseases affecting more than one species include blue tongue, tuberculosis, brucellosis, and anthrax. There are five categories (A-E) based on the degree of action to be undertaken throughout the EU for each disease. These vary from complete eradication for diseases not normally found in the EU like FMD (category A) for establishing surveillance for diseases like West Nile that present high risk but lack control tools (category E).</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
