<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The types of immune responses elicited by different seasonal influenza vaccines also impact the degree and the longevity of protection. As mentioned previously, inactivated vaccines administered intramuscularly elicit production of serum IgG antibodies but fail to induce antibody and T-cell responses in the respiratory mucosa. As such, this type of vaccine provides strain-specific protection but can leave individuals vulnerable to infection by new variant strains. Preclinical studies indicate that intranasal administration of inactivated vaccines induces robust responses in the respiratory mucosa. LAIV administered intranasally closely mimics natural infection and stimulates robust IgA and IgG antibody responses; however, this vaccine failed to provide adequate protection against influenza A(H1N1)pdm09 during the 2013–2014 and 2015–2016 seasons (
 <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Grohskopf et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). This inadequate protection prompted the Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices (ACIP) to recommend against administration of this vaccine for the 2016–2017 and 2017–2018 seasons (
 <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Grohskopf et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Later, the manufacturer determined that the reduced protection associated with the LAIV was most likely due to reduced replicative fitness of the A/California and A/Bolivia (H1N1)pdm09 LAIV strains (
 <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Ambrose et al., 2016</xref>). Currently, the quadrivalent LAIV has incorporated a new influenza A(H1N1)pdm09-like virus that provides better protection and is recommended again for use (
 <xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Grohskopf et al., 2018</xref>). While the LAIV has been demonstrated to provide robust protection in younger children, responses to LAIV vaccination in preimmune adults are likely limited due to immune-mediated restriction of LAIV replication prior to induction of effective immunity.
</p>
