<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Human cytomegalovirus (HCMV), also known as human herpesvirus 5, is a member of the 
 <italic>Betaherpesvirinae,</italic> a subfamily of the 
 <italic>Herpesviridae.</italic> Infectious HCMV particles are composed of a polymorphic lipid envelope containing viral glycoproteins, a tegument layer consisting mainly of viral phosphoproteins and an icosahedral protein capsid encasing the viral genome [
 <xref rid="B1-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The HCMV genome comprises roughly 235,000 base pairs of double-stranded DNA in a single chromosome. By harnessing cellular RNA polymerase II, the viral genome gives rise to a highly complex transcriptome encompassing both mRNAs with more than 700 translated open reading frames as well as non-coding RNAs [
 <xref rid="B3-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Upon infection of permissive cells, the HCMV genome is expressed and replicated in three sequential steps referred to as immediate-early (IE), early and late. The viral major IE gene, expressed within hours of infection, and the corresponding IE proteins will be at the center of this review. Major IE proteins inhibit intrinsic and innate host cell responses and initiate transcription from viral early genes [
 <xref rid="B10-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Early gene products regulate host cell functions to facilitate virus replication and contribute to late events including viral DNA replication and packaging. Typical early viral proteins include the DNA polymerase (pUL54), phosphotransferase (pUL97) and components of the terminase (pUL51, pUL52, pUL56, pUL77, pUL89, pUL93, pUL104), which are all targets of approved anti-HCMV drugs [
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Finally, late genes are expressed after viral DNA replication has commenced and encode mostly structural proteins of the capsid, tegument or envelope required for the assembly and egress of progeny virions [
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. HCMV replicates in a wide variety of differentiated cell types, and targets select types of poorly differentiated cells including myeloid progenitors for latent infection with limited viral gene expression [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Viral reactivation from latency is brought about by cellular differentiation and/or stimulation and contributes greatly to pathogenesis in vulnerable hosts [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].
</p>
