<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The largest outbreak of Ebola virus disease started in December 2013 in West Africa and led to &gt;28,000 confirmed cases and 11,310 deaths [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Almost all infections resulted from exposure to acutely symptomatic infected persons or recently deceased Ebola patients. Concern about possible sexual transmission of Ebola grew as the outbreak continued [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Anecdotal reports of new Ebola infections occurring among persons not in close proximity to a symptomatic or recently deceased person were followed by a report of a Liberian woman with Ebola, whose only possible source of infection was her husband, a convalescing Ebola survivor [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. The husband had a positive PCR test for Ebola RNA in his semen 199 days after symptom onset, and the homology between genetic sequences of the Ebola RNA from the man and woman suggested that the only possible source of her infection was through sexual transmission [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Ebola virus persistence in the semen of male survivors was documented in previous sporadic outbreaks [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. However, in the most recent West African outbreak, more robust systematic assessments found male survivors with Ebola virus RNA detected by PCR up to 565 days after symptom onset [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>–
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. There is little evidence supporting viral persistence in other body fluids [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Female-to-male sexual transmission of Ebola is likely inefficient, but data are limited. Although the risk of transmission from semen exposure is considered small, the sheer number of male Ebola survivors raised concern about potential flare-ups and new clusters as the West African outbreak waned [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Little is known about the public health impact of Ebola persistence among high-risk groups such as sex workers and MSM.
</p>
