<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several studies have addressed the physiological role of TMPRSS4, and three specific substrates have been identified: HA of influenza virus (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), urokinase-type plasminogen activator (PLAU) (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>), and the epithelial sodium channel (SCNN1A) (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). An increased expression of TMPRSS4 was associated with increased progression and metastatic potential of several cancers (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). TMPRSS4 transcripts have been detected in the gastrointestinal tract (esophagus, stomach, small intestine, and colon), the urogenital tract (kidney and bladder), mouse bronchiolar-alveolar epithelial cells, and human lung tissue (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Nevertheless, the 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> function of this protein is still unclear. A recent study showed that the regulation of the epithelial sodium channel is not affected by deletion of 
 <italic>Tmprss4</italic> (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). For lung tissue, TMPRSS2 expression has been described for human bronchial epithelium, AECII, and alveolar macrophages (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). We confirmed the expression of 
 <italic>Tmprss2</italic> and 
 <italic>Tmprss4</italic> in the alveolar region and the bronchial epithelial cells of murine lungs and showed that both proteases were coexpressed in granular and roughly cuboidal cells, representing AECII. In other studies, influenza A virus antigens were detected almost exclusively in AECII and, to a lesser degree, in alveolar macrophages (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). This colocalization of host proteases and virus strongly suggests that both proteases can be recruited for HA maturation.
</p>
