<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The utility of such predictive models has been proven. Long-term direct monitoring of host population density and prevalence of hantavirus infection in North American deer mice provided early warning of elevated risk for HPS in the southwestern United States (
 <xref rid="b17-ehp-118-1507" ref-type="bibr">CDC 1998</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b18-ehp-118-1507" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="b109-ehp-118-1507" ref-type="bibr">Yates et al. 2002</xref>). Models have used rainfall and temperature data to identify high-risk areas for plague and HPS in the same geographic area (
 <xref rid="b27-ehp-118-1507" ref-type="bibr">Eisen et al. 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="b28-ehp-118-1507" ref-type="bibr">Enscore et al. 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="b75-ehp-118-1507" ref-type="bibr">Parmenter et al. 1999</xref>). Remote sensors have demonstrated climate-associated changes in vegetation or other environmental parameters that foretold increased risk for Rift Valley fever (
 <xref rid="b1-ehp-118-1507" ref-type="bibr">Anyamba et al. 2001</xref>) or HPS (
 <xref rid="b34-ehp-118-1507" ref-type="bibr">Glass et al. 2002</xref>). Ecological niche modeling has been used to provide evidence for climate change-mediated range shifts for plague and tularemia and to provide predictions of continued future poleward expansion (
 <xref rid="b67-ehp-118-1507" ref-type="bibr">Nakazawa et al. 2007</xref>). Ecological niche models also used climatic data and other environmental datasets to predict the geographic distribution of the hosts and vectors for Chagas disease and the filovirus hemorrhagic fevers (
 <xref rid="b82-ehp-118-1507" ref-type="bibr">Peterson et al. 2002</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b81-ehp-118-1507" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). Another model predicted the northward spread of the Lyme disease and anaplasmosis vector 
 <italic>I. scapularis</italic> under proposed climate change scenarios (
 <xref rid="b13-ehp-118-1507" ref-type="bibr">Brownstein et al. 2005</xref>). Recent surveillance has confirmed that expansion (
 <xref rid="b72-ehp-118-1507" ref-type="bibr">Ogden et al. 2010</xref>). Continued data collection from long-term field studies combined with laboratory data providing measured physiological tolerances for specific hosts and vectors and effects of stressors on pathogen transmission can be used to develop increasingly accurate models of range expansions and effects of increased population density on heat stress and pathogen transmission.
</p>
