<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Second, theoretical studies on spatially structured populations indicate that localized transmission often favours more prudent host exploitation strategies [
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Indeed, when epidemics are spatially structured, extreme strategies of host exploitation may lead to the over-exploitation of the local host supply and therefore fail to invade. The intensity of local competition for susceptible hosts depends, however, on the precise genetic and epidemiological structure of the pathogen population [
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The effect of spatial structure on the evolution of pathogens has had some experimental support [
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] which is, however, based on experiments with obligate killing and strictly horizontally transmitting pathogens. Previous experimental work has shown that vertical transmission selects for lower virulence [
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] but the effect of spatial structure on vertically transmitted pathogens remains an open question. In the present study we explore the effect of spatial structure on the evolution of pathogens that can be transmitted both vertically and horizontally. We first develop and analyse a theoretical model to understand the evolutionary dynamics of pathogens in spatially structured epidemics (
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). This model allows infected hosts to reproduce and to transmit their pathogens vertically. We use this model to study the competition between different pathogen genotypes under various levels of mixing (see supporting information in 
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Text</xref>). Then, we confront these predictions with experiments performed with the horizontally and vertically transmitting temperate bacteriophage λ. Bacteriophage λ is an avirulent pathogen that controls its own replication by the virulence repressor 
 <italic>cI</italic> and integrates into the host genome as a prophage without killing the host cell—a process known as lysogenization. The virulence repressor 
 <italic>cI</italic> furthermore controls prophage λ reactivation and excludes superinfection by a second viral particle [
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Yet, spontaneous mutations in 
 <italic>cI</italic> can markedly increase virulence [
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. We studied competition between temperate bacteriophage λ and its virulent mutant λcI857. Mutant λ
 <italic>cI857</italic> carries an unstable virulence repressor protein (cI857) that biases the viral life cycle towards horizontal transmission: whereas λ lysogenizes about 60% of newly infected cells killing only about 40% of cell, λcI857 kills 96% of host cells upon first infection (see Fig S2B in 
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Text</xref>). In addition λcI857 shows a higher rate of prophage reactivation, sacrificing infected host cells for increased production of free viral particles (Fig S2A in 
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Text</xref>). Furthermore, λcI857 is less efficient in the exclusion of superinfection (see Fig S2B in 
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Text</xref>). Whereas the temperate λ wildtype shows an avirulent host exploitation strategy the virulent mutant λcI857 readily exploits and kills its host cell. To experimentally investigate the effect of spatial structure on the success of these opposing strategies we competed λ and λcI857 in experimental epidemics with different degrees of spatial structure (Manipulation of spatial structure is described in Material &amp; Methods and [
 <xref rid="ppat.1004810.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]).
</p>
