<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Protein stability is critical for long-term maintenance of pharmacological activity. For this reason, the susceptibility of GRFT to proteolytic digestion should be considered. GRFT was resistant to digestion by eight different proteases including pepsin, papain, leucine aminopeptidase, pronase, α-chymotrypsin, proteinase K, endoproteinase, and trypsin [
 <xref rid="B56-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. A number of different nanoparticle drug delivery systems have been tested to provide sustained and controlled delivery of GRFT, improve its solubility, protect its payloads, and enhance its mucosal permeability (
 <xref rid="marinedrugs-17-00567-t009" ref-type="table">Table 9</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B57-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. PLGA (poly lactic-co-glycolic acid) nanoparticles with a diameter of approximately 180–200 nm were successfully used in the co-delivery of GRFT and dapivirine in vitro [
 <xref rid="B60-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Both drugs showed a biphasic release with an initial burst phase followed by a sustained release phase [
 <xref rid="B60-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Grooms et al. successfully generated GRFT-modified electrospun fibers to inactivate HIV prior to cellular entry [
 <xref rid="B57-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Furthermore, Lal et al. developed a self-administered, vaginal fast-dissolving insert (FDI) produced by freeze-drying that delivered safe and effective amounts of GRFT and carrageenan (GC), a sulfated polysaccharide extracted from seaweed [
 <xref rid="B58-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Fibers comprised of methoxy polyethylene glycol-PLGA: poly n-butyl acrylate-co-acrylic acid (mPEG-PLGA: PBA-co-PAA) were able to achieve high GRFT loading. These GRFT-loaded fibers were well maintained within a simulated vaginal fluid (SVF) and showed pH-dependent release upon exposure to buffered SVF and simulated semen solutions [
 <xref rid="B59-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. 
</p>
