<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are several studies that examine N95 use as it relates to transmission of SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2. As mentioned above, Yen et al
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
 </sup> compared hospitals with and without infected healthcare workers during the SARS-CoV epidemic in Taiwan and found that 100% of hospitals with zero SARS-CoV healthcare worker infections used N95 masks in “zones of risk.”
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
 </sup> A case-matched study of healthcare workers infected with SARS-CoV compared their PPE use to healthcare workers who were not infected.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
 </sup> Nearly 100% of the participants used either a surgical mask or an N95 mask, and there was no difference in the type of mask used when comparing infected and noninfected healthcare workers.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
 </sup> A study specifically examining critical care nurses also found no differences in the rates of becoming infected when using a surgical mask compared to an N95 mask.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
 </sup> Wang et al
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
 </sup> published healthcare worker infection rates from Wuhan University from December 2019 and showed that none of the 278 staff members who wore N95 masks became infected. Doctors and nurses on surgical floors who did not interact with COVID-19 patients were considered low risk and did not wear masks, and 10 of 215 (4.6%) of these individuals ultimately became infected.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
 </sup> Currently, the CDC recommends use of an N95 mask when caring for a patient with known or suspected COVID-19 if available and recommends an N95 or higher respirator when performing or present for aerosol-generating procedures.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 </sup> In Korea, N95 masks at minimum have been recommended for all hospital interactions except disposal of medical waste.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
 </sup> In Hong Kong, they are recommended for staff working in triage, with confirmed COVID-19 cases, and when performing aerosol generating procedures.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
