<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Viruses causing respiratory tract infections have been the cause of high morbidities and mortality rates worldwide, often in a seasonal manner for decades (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). In the last 20 years, the world has experienced six major outbreaks of infectious agents (SARS-CoV: 2002-2004; H1N1 Influenza: 2009–2010; MERS-CoV: 2012–2020; Ebola virus: 2013–2016; Zika virus: 2015–2016; SARS-CoV-2: 2019-present), infection with four of which (SARS-CoV, H1N1 Influenza, MERS-CoV, SARS-CoV-2) result in respiratory tract infections. During the emergency of a viral disease, attention is initially focussed on clinical management of the primary infection, but it is imperative to consider secondary bacterial infections that develop in patients during or following initial infection. In addition, co-infections - the simultaneous infection with a second pathogen of viral or bacterial origin- can also occur and ultimately result in the same outcome: The patient suffers from complications caused by two different pathogens (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). One major complication of viral infections, especially pulmonary viruses, is colonization of the viral affected organs by bacteria which is associated with high morbidity and mortality rates (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>), following a weakened immune response and/or opportunistic and accessible routes of entry for bacterial pathogen(s) (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). While secondary bacterial infections or superinfections are largely a consequence of immune susceptibility caused by the primary viral infection, co-infections are multiple infections (viral/bacterial/yeast) that occur simultaneously. Co-infections, secondary infections or “superinfections” are common during viral pandemics. The 1918 Spanish Flu pandemic saw around 50 million deaths ascribed to bacterial co-infections and during the 2009 H1N1 Influenza pandemic up to 34% of all deaths were a result of bacterial co-infections (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). These complications are often neglected in the clinical record (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>) (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>).
</p>
