<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Repurposed broad-spectrum antiviral drugs having proven uses against other viral pathogens can be employed for SARS-CoV-2-infected patients. These possess benefits of easy accessibility and recognized pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic activities, stability, doses, and side effects (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Repurposed drugs have been studied for treating CoV infections, like lopinavir/ritonavir, and interferon-1β revealed 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> anti-MERS-CoV action. The 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> experiment carried out in the nonhuman primate model of common marmosets treated with lopinavir/ritonavir and interferon beta showed superior protective results in treated animals than in the untreated ones (
 <xref rid="B190" ref-type="bibr">190</xref>). A combination of these drugs is being evaluated to treat MERS in humans (MIRACLE trial) (
 <xref rid="B191" ref-type="bibr">191</xref>). These two protease inhibitors (lopinavir and ritonavir), in combination with ribavirin, gave encouraging clinical outcomes in SARS patients, suggesting their therapeutic values (
 <xref rid="B165" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>). However, in the current scenario, due to the lack of specific therapeutic agents against SARS-CoV-2, hospitalized patients confirmed for the disease are given supportive care, like oxygen and fluid therapy, along with antibiotic therapy for managing secondary bacterial infections (
 <xref rid="B192" ref-type="bibr">192</xref>). Patients with novel coronavirus or COVID-19 pneumonia who are mechanically ventilated often require sedatives, analgesics, and even muscle relaxation drugs to prevent ventilator-related lung injury associated with human-machine incoordination (
 <xref rid="B122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>). The result obtained from a clinical study of four patients infected with COVID-19 claimed that combination therapy using lopinavir/ritonavir, arbidol, and Shufeng Jiedu capsules (traditional Chinese medicine) was found to be effective in managing COVID-19 pneumonia (
 <xref rid="B193" ref-type="bibr">193</xref>). It is difficult to evaluate the therapeutic potential of a drug or a combination of drugs for managing a disease based on such a limited sample size. Before choosing the ideal therapeutic agent for the management of COVID-19, randomized clinical control studies should be performed with a sufficient study population.
</p>
