<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0165">To discover and design novel potent NAs against CoVs, an additional level of complexity has to be addressed relative to other RNA pathogenic viruses. NAs incorporated into coronaviral RNA have to escape the proofreading ExoN brought by the nsp14 N-terminus domain. In the absence nsp14 structural data at reasonable resolution for the drug-designer (ie., &lt;2.5 Å) (
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Ferron et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al., 2015</xref>), and in complex with relevant substrates, we show here that the related Lassa virus N protein ExoN domain for which this type of data exist (
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et al., 2013</xref>) can guide NA MoA studies. As shown in 
 <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> the replacement of a standard nucleotide by GS-441524 generate a structural distortion and a clash between its non-planar nucleobase part and the template base. To accommodate this structurally, the ribose would have to move away from its canonical position and towards the catalytic ions. Due to the small size of the catalytic cavity, this would generate in turn a displacement on the catalytic ions from the active site, as shown for a similar two-metal ion catalysis ExoN reaction where any slight modification in ion position or distortion leads to inhibition of the reaction (
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Yekwa et al., 2017</xref>). Better structurally defined nsp14:RNA complexes are needed to fully understand the structural requirements of 3′-terminal nucleotides for ExoN-mediated removal. Of note, the engineered MHV V553I RdRp mutant was found to be inextricably linked with ExoN activity, 
 <italic>i.e.</italic> the fidelity effect could only be detected in ExoN deficient virus (
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Sexton et al., 2016</xref>). Importantly, as is the case for Rbv, the ExoN of CoV may be able to recognise and excise incorporated GS 441524-MP, as shown by the increased potency against ExoN deficient viruses (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Agostini et al., 2018</xref>). However, unlike other Rbv and 5-FU, Remdesivir is active on WT, and ExoN (−) mutants show only modest 4.5 fold increase in sensitivity to Remdesivir, indicating that inhibition likely originates by a mixed effect balanced between incorporation and excision.
</p>
