<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0010">The recent emergence of the novel coronavirus severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), which caused an outbreak of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) in China, has brought about serious threats to public health worldwide. Coronaviruses belong to the Nidovirales order, which are large and positive-sense enveloped RNA viruses; divided into four genera: α, β, γ and δ. Since the start of the twenty-first century, two β-coronaviruses have caused epidemics of human fatal pneumonia. SARS-CoV-2 belongs to the genus β-coronavirus, which is comprised of crown-like, enveloped, positive-sense single-stranded RNA viruses (
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> ). In coronavirus particles, the nucleocapsid protein packages the genome RNA to form a helical nucleocapsid. Various factors are causing the situation to become more serious. First, there is a shortage of effective point-of-care testing assays for rapid, highly accurate identification of SARS-CoV-2-infected individuals. Moreover, asymptomatic and pre-asymptomatic SARS-CoV-2-infected patients are highly contagious, and there is a lack of appropriate detection assays. SARS-CoV emerged in 2002 and caused the disease SARS to spread to five continents, with a case fatality rate of 10% before it was contained in 2003 (more cases reported in 2004). In 2012, the appearance of Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) in the Arabian Peninsula caused periodic epidemics in humans with a mortality rate of 35%. SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV are zoonotic viruses, and they cross-species barriers respectively through bat/palm fruit fly [
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] and dromedary camels [
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Seven coronaviruses have been identified that cause human diseases. Four viruses—229E, OC43, NL63 and HKU1—are ubiquitous and usually cause common cold-like symptoms in individuals with immunity [
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. These zoonotic viruses are endemic in the human population, account for up to 30% of mild respiratory tract infections, and can lead to serious complications or death in young children, and in aged and immunocompromised individuals [
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].
</p>
