<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0025">In light of social media speculation about possible laboratory manipulation and deliberate and/or accidental release of SARS-CoV-2, Andersen et al. theorize about the virus’ probable origins, emphasizing that the available data argue overwhelmingly against any scientific misconduct or negligence (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Andersen et al., 2020</xref>). As has been previously described, the SARS-CoV-genome contains over 1,200 nucleotide changes as compared with RaTG13, its closest relative. Moreover, the RaTG13 S glycoprotein is 97% identical at the amino acid level to the SARS-CoV-2 S glycoprotein (
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>), and it encodes an RBD that is not optimized for hACE2 interaction (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Wan et al., 2020</xref>). Anderson cites these genetic and biological data as strong evidence against deliberate generation, and the arguments are compelling. It is noteworthy that many early COVID-19 cases had not visited the Huanan wet market, suggesting that either the index cases occurred earlier and were not identified or that these sites were not major sites of epidemic expansion. How, then, did the virus emerge? Anderson et al. cite multiple lines of strong evidence that argue, instead, in favor of various mechanisms of natural selection, either in an animal host before the virus was transmitted to humans or in humans after the zoonotic transmission event(s). These possibilities will be reviewed below. Nevertheless, speculation about accidental laboratory escape will likely persist, given the large collections of bat virome samples stored in labs in the Wuhan Institute of Virology, the facility’s proximity to the early outbreak, and the operating procedures at the facility (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Zeng et al., 2016</xref>). Transparency and open scientific investigation will be essential to resolve this issue, noting that forensic evidence of natural escape is currently lacking, and other explanations remain reasonable.
</p>
