<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0075">Virus-like particles (VLPs) are“hollow-core” virus particles formed by the viral structural component with self-assembly character into nanostructure. VLP mimic the structure of the whole virus. VLPs can elicit innate immunity response via pathogen recognition receptors. VLPs represent advanced subunit vaccine with increased immunogenicity because they contain the structural protein of the virus. VLPs have a noninfectious and non-replicative property due to lose of genomic component. VLPs help to develop safer and cheaper vaccine candidates.
 <xref rid="bib0430" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>41</sup>
 </xref> VLPs can be synthesized by encoding the viral structural proteins. In general, the VLPs-based vaccine is similar to the whole inactivated virus vaccine, but it does not require the viral inactivation step which may affect the immunogenicity of a viral protein. Because no live virus is involved in the production process, VLPs can be easily generated in a low-containment production environment.
 <xref rid="bib0430" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0435" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> So far, VLP-based vaccines produced for greater than 30 different viruses including GlaxoSmithKline's Engerix® (hepatitis B virus) and Cervarix® (human papillomavirus), and Merck and Co., Inc.’s Recombivax HB® (hepatitis B virus) and Gardasil® (human papillomavirus).
 <xref rid="bib0440" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0445" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> Currently, several VLP expression systems available like recombinant vaccinia virus, mammalian cells (293T, CHO), baculovirus and yeast expression systems. The RBD domain based VLP vaccine candidate (RBD-CuMVTT) derived from cucumber mosaic virus induced significant levels of antibodies in mice which can inhibit the binding of S protein to ACE2 receptor and effectively neutralized the SARS-CoV-2 virus in vitro.
 <xref rid="bib0450" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>45</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
