<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0145">The profile of CoVs as neurovirulent agents is not only that of rapid-acting killers, but also of slow-acting saboteurs. As previously mentioned, CoVs may remain in the CNS of experimental animals for a very long time after an acute infection, possibly inducing slowly progressing tissue damage through immunological mechanisms. The histopathologic and pathogenetic similarities between experimental CoV infections in rodents and human demyelinating diseases such as MS have already been highlighted (
 <xref rid="bb0545" ref-type="bibr">Nagashima et al., 1978a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0550" ref-type="bibr">Nagashima et al., 1978b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0340" ref-type="bibr">Jacomy et al., 2006</xref>). One of the first evidence supporting CoVs role in the pathogenesis of MS comes from the electron microscopic identification of donut-shaped CoV-like particles in the active brain lesions of a young woman deceased with MS (
 <xref rid="bb0730" ref-type="bibr">Tanaka et al., 1976</xref>). A few years later, two CoVs similar to HCoV-OC43 (named SK and SD) were isolated from autoptic cerebral samples of two MS patients (
 <xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">Burks et al., 1980</xref>). These two viruses induced encephalitis with demyelination when intracerebrally injected in non-human primates (
 <xref rid="bb0530" ref-type="bibr">Murray et al., 1992a</xref>). However, the etiological role for the SK and SD viruses in MS in these patients has not been firmly established, and the possibility that they could represent a murine contaminant has never been excluded (
 <xref rid="bb0820" ref-type="bibr">Weiss, 1983</xref>). HCoV-OC43 and HCoV-229E RNA and/or antigens have also been detected in brain samples from MS patients (
 <xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">Cristallo et al., 1997</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0535" ref-type="bibr">Murray et al., 1992b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0700" ref-type="bibr">Stewart et al., 1992</xref>). Moreover, T cells cross-reacting to myelin basic protein and human CoVs antigens were isolated from peripheral blood (
 <xref rid="bb0725" ref-type="bibr">Talbot et al., 1996</xref>), and intrathecal synthesis of antibodies to HCoV-OC43 and HCoV-229E was documented in MS patients (
 <xref rid="bb0655" ref-type="bibr">Salmi et al., 1982</xref>).
</p>
