<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To extract and quantify viscoelastic, chemical, and physical properties of viruses, the force–distance curve-based AFM (FD-based AFM) and recently multifrequency approaches are the common methods. In modern FD curve-based AFM, numerous FD curves are recorded during imaging the biological sample.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref296">296</xref>
 </sup> Based on the principle of FD-based imaging, the method to map chemical and biological properties is developed.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref297">297</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref298">298</xref>
 </sup> In this method, the tips are functionalized by specific ligands. Then, based on the adhesion and mechanical strength of bonds formed between functionalized tip and receptors of the samples, the biological properties can be explored during imaging.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref291">291</xref>
 </sup> The main challenge of FD-based AFM is the high volume and time of data acquisition.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>
 </sup> To increase the speed of imaging and reduce the amount of collected data during measurement, high-speed AFM and multifrequency methods are invented.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref299">299</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref300">300</xref>
 </sup> Several multifrequency AFM methods have been proposed, however due to their complex physical principle, theoretical development and mechanism of interpretation of data are under more investigation.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref299">299</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref301">301</xref>
 </sup> The previous studies of coronaviruses using AFM techniques
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref302">302</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref305">305</xref>
 </sup> show the significant potential of AFM to image, visualize, and explore the morphological features of the SARS-CoV virus; see 
 <xref rid="fig13" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig13" ref-type="fig">13</xref>
 </xref> as a typical AFM characterization. Generally, visualization/characterization devices are useful as they provide following information: (1) quantify the surface and subsurface properties of the affected cell by COVID-19 in real time; (2) detect multiple dynamic interactions between SARS-CoV2 virus and host cell; and (3) study the mechanism of SARS-CoV2 virus to cross the cellular membrane and deliver its genome inside the host cells and (4) its replication inside cell and characterization of the nucleic acids of SARS-CoV2 virus, to understand how it is condensed and packaged inside capsids. Recent proposed techniques to nanoscale map directional flow patterns also can be used to study the effects of different pH and ion-specific sieving properties of the host cell on the binding of S protein of SARS-CoV2 virus with receptor at the surface of the cell.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref306">306</xref>
 </sup> In fact, very recently Yang 
 <italic>et al</italic>. characterized molecular binding and inhibition interactions of SARS-CoV2 with ACE2 receptors with AFM.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref307">307</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
