<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The EVI and LST datasets were derived from satellite imagery collected by NASA's Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS) remote sensing platform (
 <xref rid="bib122" ref-type="bibr">Tatem et al., 2004</xref>). EVI is a metric designed to characterise vegetation density and vigour based on the ratio of absorbed photosynthetically active radiation to near infrared radiation (
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Huete et al., 2002</xref>). LST is a modelled product derived from emissivity as measured by the MODIS thermal sensor (
 <xref rid="bib130" ref-type="bibr">Wan and Li, 1997</xref>), which is correlated, though not synonymous with air temperature, and effective for differentiating landscapes based on a combination of thermal energy and properties of surface types. The MODIS datasets utilized in this research (EVI was derived from the MCD43B4 product and the MOD11A2 LST product was used directly) were acquired as composite datasets created using imagery collected over multiple days, a procedure that results in products with 8-day temporal resolutions. Despite compositing, the EVI and LST datasets contained gaps due to persistent cloud cover found in forested equatorial regions, and these gaps were filled using a previously described approach (
 <xref rid="bib132" ref-type="bibr">Weiss et al., 2014a</xref>). The EVI and LST datasets were then aggregated from their native 1 km × 1 km spatial resolution to a final 5 km × 5 km resolution, calculating both the mean and the range of the values of the subpixels making up each larger pixel. These spatial summaries therefore characterise both the mean temperature in each location as well as the degree of spatial heterogeneity within that pixel. This is of interest as humans and susceptible species are more likely to come into contact in transitional areas (e.g., boundary areas between areas of highly suitable susceptible species habitat and areas heavily utilised by humans). The final covariate production step consisted of summarising temporally across the 13-year data archive to produce synoptic datasets devoid of annual or seasonal anomalies (
 <xref rid="bib132" ref-type="bibr">Weiss et al., 2014a</xref>).
</p>
