<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The majority of models for dengue epidemics using meteorological factors, mosquito-vector factor, preventive and control measures, and socioeconomic factors, such as seasonal time series models, regression analyses, and generalised additive models, are based on statistical models in quantitative research[
 <xref rid="pone.0225811.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0225811.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0225811.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. However, these do not consider the interactive effects among different factors or the occurrence of special events (e.g. imported cases, extreme climate). Furthermore, most studies cover a narrow range of time, a small number of cases, and fewer meteorological factors[
 <xref rid="pone.0225811.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], leading to a poorer fit of the model. For example, the fitness of the SARIMA model constructed by Gharbietal. was 0.72[
 <xref rid="pone.0225811.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], and that of the binomial regression model constructed by Adde et al. was 0.88[
 <xref rid="pone.0225811.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Our study constructed a probitregression model, which incorporated interactive meteorological factors, the mosquito-vector factor, and the importation factor, based on dengue epidemic data from the last 9 years in Guangdong province. The model showed goodness of fit, at R
 <sup>2</sup> = 0.72, indicating that the model calibration value fits the observed value effectively. Additionally, prediction of the actual number of cases for the first 41weeks of 2017 demonstrated that our constructed model has high reliability. Moreover, our model can predict the scale of dengue cases for the following week; hence its timeliness is higher than models constructed using months as the basic unit. Based on the above results, we can use meteorological forecasts to predict future dengue fever cases. Hence, our model can serve as a good theoretical basis for the prevention and control of dengue fever. A limitation of this study is that direct data on mosquito density were not obtained; instead, calculations were based on mean temperature. Moreover, this study was based on ecological data, thus factors besides meteorological factors, such as population growth and unreasonable waste disposal methods, should also be considered in future studies.
</p>
