<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <title>Acknowledgements</title>
 <p>The VIZIONS project was supported through a Wellcome Trust research grant ref. 093724. We gratefully acknowledge the contributions made to this study by the following Vietnam institutions: the Preventive Medicine Centre Dong Thap Province; the Sub-Department of Animal Health Dong Thap Province; the Preventive Medicine Centre Dak Lak Province; the Regional Animal Health Laboratory, Buon Ma Thuot; the Sub-Department of Animal Health Dak Lak Province; Hanoi Medical University, Ha Noi; Ba Vi District Health Centre, Ha Noi; and Ba Vi District Veterinary Station, Ha Noi. We acknowledge the roles played by the entire VIZIONS consortium in obtaining these data. At the Oxford University Clinical Research Unit, Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam: Bach Tuan Kiet, Stephen Baker, Alessandra Berto, Maciej F. Boni, Juliet E. Bryant, Bui Duc Phu, James I Campbell, Juan Carrique-Mas, Dang Manh Hung, Dang Thao Huong, Dang Tram Oanh, Jeremy N. Day, Dinh Van Tan, H. Rogier van Doorn, Duong An Han, Jeremy Farrar, Hau Thi Thu Trang, Ho Dang Trung Nghia, Hoang Bao Long, Hoang Van Duong, Huynh Thi Kim Thu, Lam Chi Cuong, Le Manh Hung, Le Thanh Phuong, Le Thi Phuc, Le Thi Phuong, Le Xuan Luat, Luu Thi Thu Ha, Ly Van Chuong, Mai Thi Phuoc Loan, Behzad Nadjm, Ngo Thanh Bao, Ngo Thi Hoa, Ngo Tri Tue, Nguyen Canh Tu, Nguyen Dac Thuan, Nguyen Dong, Nguyen Khac Chuyen, Nguyen Ngoc An, Nguyen Ngoc Vinh, Nguyen Quoc Hung, Nguyen Thanh Dung, Nguyen Thanh Minh, Nguyen Thi Binh, Nguyen Thi Hong Tham, Nguyen Thi Hong Tien, Nguyen Thi Kim Chuc, Nguyen Thi Le Ngoc, Nguyen Thi Lien Ha, Nguyen Thi Nam Lien, Nguyen Thi Ngoc Diep, Nguyen Thi Nhung, Nguyen Thi Song Chau, Nguyen Thi Yen Chi, Nguyen Thieu Trinh, Nguyen Thu Van, Nguyen Van Cuong, Nguyen Van Hung, Nguyen Van Kinh, Nguyen Van Minh Hoang, Nguyen Van My, Nguyen Van Thang, Nguyen Van Thanh, Nguyen Van Vinh Chau, Nguyen Van Xang, Pham Ha My, Pham Hong Anh, Pham Thi Minh Khoa, Pham Thi Thanh Tam, Pham Van Lao, Pham Van Minh, Phan Van Be Bay, Phan Vu Tra My, Maia A Rabaa, Motiur Rahman, Corinne Thompson, Guy Thwaites, Ta Thi Dieu Ngan, Tran Do Hoang Nhu, Tran Hoang Minh Chau, Tran Khanh Toan, Tran My Phuc, Tran Thi Kim Hong, Tran Thi Ngoc Dung, Tran Thi Thanh Thanh, Tran Thi Thuy Minh, Tran Thua Nguyen, Tran Tinh Hien, Trinh Quang Tri, Vo Be Hien, Vo Nhut Tai, Vo Quoc Cuong, Voong Vinh Phat, Vu Thi Lan Huong, Vu Thi Ty Hang, Heiman Wertheim. At the Sanger Institute, Hinxton, Cambridge, UK: Matthew Cotten, Bas Oude Munnink, Paul Kellam, My Vu Tra Phan. At the University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK: Jordan Ashworth, Carlijn Bogaardt, Liam Brierley, Margo Chase-Topping, Al Ivens, Ha Minh Lam, Lu Lu, Sema Nickbakhsh, Dung Nyugen, Aine O’Toole, Andrew Rambaut, Mark Woolhouse. At Metabiota Inc., San Francisco, USA: Kimberly Dodd, Jason Euren, Ashley Lucas, Nancy Ortiz, Len Pennacchio, Edward Rubin, Karen E. Saylors, Tran Minh Hai, Nathan D. Wolfe. At the University of Oxford, UK: Peter Simmonds. At the University of Amsterdam, The Netherlands: Lia van der Hoek. We particularly note the contribution of Matthew Cotten, My Vu Tra Phan and Paul Kellam who led the metagenomic sequencing to which these data are linked.</p>
</ack>
