<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">The analysis of health data, such as viral outbreaks or presence, from a geographical perspective (e.g. geographical distribution of the outbreaks) can highlight interesting patterns that can be used to formulate hypotheses about the role of different factors in the occurrence of an infection
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>. Species distribution models (SDMs), also known as niche models, are based on correlations between environmental data and geo-referenced presence/absence data (occurrence localities) of a particular species of interest
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. These models are widely used in ecology and biogeography studies to address a broad array of questions, such as the identification of the potential distribution of an invasive species, mapping the risk of disease transmission, or anticipating the effects of climate change on the distribution of species of interest
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. Among different distribution models, the maximum entropy method (MaxEnt) developed by Philips and colleagues a decade ago
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup> is one of the most widely used. This method exclusively relies on the use of presence data of a species of interest along with a set of environmental variables to model the species´ geographical distribution. This feature is particularly interesting to model the distribution of infectious diseases, such as HEV, for which absence data are rarely available. Presence data used in MaxEnt correspond to latitude-longitude pairs where a species has been observed, and environmental variables are layers of environmental information (e.g. temperature, amount of precipitation, a landcover class, etc.) in GIS format characterizing the same geographic area like the presence data records. Specifically, MaxEnt is based on a machine-learning algorithm which predicts environmental suitability for the species of interest given the environmental information, thereby estimating “a target probability distribution by finding the probability distribution of maximum entropy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>”, thus containing a maximum of information. In other words, MaxEnt estimates what is closest to uniform distribution given a set of constraints based on current knowledge of the environmental variables at the occurrence sites
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>. Despite its popularity, the MaxEnt model does not directly estimate occurrence probability. Instead, it generates an index of relative habitat suitability. Other software, such as MaxLike, a more recent maximum-likelihood technique, has been shown to overcome the problem of directly estimating the probability of occurrence using presence-only data
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>. MaxEnt tends to under-estimate the probability of occurrence within areas of observed presences, but over-estimates it in unsampled areas beyond the spatial coverage of the data
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>. However, MaxEnt has shown to perform better than other SDMs
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup> and, unlike other software, it has been previously used in environmental virology to predict the distribution of multiple pathogens
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
