<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<notes>
 <title>Author Contributions</title>
 <p>M-F Van Bressem designed paper outlines and 
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-06-05145-f001">Figure 1</xref> and 
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-06-05145-f003">Figure 3</xref>, did the main writing and literature review; P. Duignan helped to design the ms outlines, contributed to the writing of the introduction, diagnosis, pathology and epidemiology sections, reviewed and improved earlier drafts, made many helpful suggestions, facilitated access to the 
  <italic>T. aduncus</italic> morbillivirus and helped with literature search; A. Banyard build the phylogenetic tree (
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-06-05145-f002">Figure 2</xref>), contributed to the virology section and conclusions, made useful comments and reviewed several drafts of the manuscript; F. Gulland organized the marine mammal morbillivirus workshop in Princeton, USA in August 2014, contributed to draw the paper outlines, made helpful suggestions and reviewed various drafts of the manuscript; K. Colegrove contributed to the epidemiology and pathology sections, reviewed various drafts of the manuscript and provided unpublished information; D. Fauquier and T. Goldstein contributed to the epidemiology section, reviewed several drafts of the manuscript and provided unpublished information; O. Nielsen contributed to the receptor, virology and diagnosis sections and reviewed drafts of the manuscript; S. De Guise wrote the paragraph ‘Immune function and CeMV infections’, reviewed drafts of the manuscript and provided unpublished information; J. Saliki contributed to the diagnosis and virology sections, made helpful suggestions and reviewed drafts of the manuscript; G. Di Guardo, M. Domingo, S. Mazzariol, A. Fernandez, and E. Sierra contributed to the pathology sections and to 
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-06-05145-f001">Figure 1</xref> and 
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-06-05145-f003">Figure 3</xref>, reviewed drafts of the manuscript and made useful comments; B. Stone, I. Tomo and N. Stephens contributed to the epidemiology and virology sections and to 
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-06-05145-f001">Figure 1</xref> and 
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-06-05145-f003">Figure 3</xref>, made useful comments and allowed access the Australian dolphin morbilliviruses; K. Groch contributed to the epidemiology and virology sections, greatly helped with the figures, formatting of the manuscript and literature, reviewed drafts of the manuscript and provided unpublished data; T. Raga contributed to the introduction and epidemiology section and 
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-06-05145-f001">Figure 1</xref>, made helpful suggestions and reviewed drafts of the manuscript; J. Wellehan contributed to the introduction, receptors and virology sections and conclusions, reviewed an advanced version of the manuscript and made helpful comments; T. Waltzek reviewed an advanced draft of the manuscript and made useful comments; J. Wang provided the sequences of the Australian 
  <italic>T. aduncus</italic> morbilliviruses, reviewed an advanced draft of the manuscript and made useful comments; A. Hall reviewed an advanced draft of the manuscript and made useful comments; B. Grenfell organized the marine mammal morbillivirus workshop in Princeton in August 2014, contributed to the epidemiology section and reviewed an advanced draft of the manuscript; A. Dobson made useful comments on the manuscript and reviewed an advanced draft of the manuscript; P. Jepson reviewed an earlier version of the manuscript and provided 
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-06-05145-f001">Figure 1</xref>C.; B. Jensen provided 
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-06-05145-f001">Figure 1</xref>G and made useful comments; T.K. Rowles organized the marine mammal morbillivirus workshop in Princeton in August 2014, revised drafts of the manuscript and made useful suggestions; M. Barbieri and S.E. Morris participated to the workshop, facilitated access to CeMV literature and made constructive comments; T. Kuiken provided literature.
 </p>
</notes>
