<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0049">The pace of advances in developing specific drugs to targets SARS-CoV-2 and vaccine to prevent COVID-19 is quite remarkable, facilitated largely by the existing basic science discoveries about coronaviruses, as well as technological advances in molecular biology and genetics and nucleic acid-based vaccine development. ClinicalTrials.Gov lists over 150 vaccine studies against SARS-CoV-2, which utilize a variety of platforms ranging from inactivated whole virion to specific RNA vaccines to non-specific BCG vaccine. There is, however, no concrete evidence for the success of targeted therapy or efficacy of the potential vaccines. The data on the effectiveness of existing targeted therapies, ranging from monoclonal antibodies against ACE2 to nucleotide analogues are equivocal at best. Likewise, a large number of vaccine candidates are likely to drop out from competition after the initial studies, and a considerable number are likely to fail in the phase 3 studies. Only those built upon robust basic science principles and phase 1-2 data will have the chance of succeeding in phase 3 efficacy clinical trials. It might be necessary to identify additional drug and vaccine targets and to screen chemical libraries to find suitable compounds, followed by optimization and testing in preclinical and phase 1-3 clinical trials. At the clinical level, it is important to identify and test the drugs or vaccines in the target groups, such as the elderly who face the brunt of mortality from COVID-19, and define robust clinical endpoints for efficacy of the interventions. Despite the challenges ahead, developing specific anti-SARS-CoV-2 therapies and effective vaccines against COVID-19 are global priorities and are likely essential for the successful elimination of COVID-19. The progress toward these goals is most remarkable, largely stemming from important basis science discoveries. It merits noting that typically the clinical impacts of the fundamental basic science discoveries are initially unclear. It is such discoveries, however, that are expected to pave the way for the successful eradication of COVID-19. Thus, when uncovering the secrets of nature, one should never be concerned with the immediate clinical implications. The fundamental discoveries are foundation for the successful cures of diseases.</p>
