<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="diagnostics-10-00409-f003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 3</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Protection tools against COVID-19 in the form of face masks, shields, and sanitizers. (
   <bold>a</bold>) The N95 Respirator is Food and Drug Administration (FDA)-approved and is currently the best-known form of personal protective equipment (PPE) available to healthcare professionals; (
   <bold>b</bold>) FDA-approved surgical masks are to be used by healthcare workers in the absence of N95 respirators; (
   <bold>c</bold>) The regular method for tying surgical masks compared to the newly proposed method that can secure the side openings of surgical masks; (
   <bold>d</bold>) A surgical mask design modified with filter performance rating (FPR) 9-10 air-conditioning filters; (
   <bold>e</bold>) The Stanford full-face, snorkel-inspired Pneumask. The Pneumask has deployed 2600 units all across the United States (US), with concentrations in New York, Massachusetts, and California; (
   <bold>f</bold>) The team at Duke has fully modified a powered air-purifying respirator (PAPR) design, which is attached to the surgical helmets (left) and the 3D-printed component of the PAPR (right); (
   <bold>g</bold>) The 3D printable Stopgap Mask from the Veterans Health Administration that is approved by the FDA to protect clinical personnel from COVID-19; (
   <bold>h</bold>) The 3D printable Maker Mask that can be used by non-clinical personnel when there are no FDA-approved masks available; (
   <bold>i</bold>) The Prusa Printer face shield that can be used to protect clinical personnel when no FDA-approved face shields are available; (
   <bold>j</bold>) The Georgia Tech 3D-printed rigid frame and a disposable face shield design; (
   <bold>k</bold>) The MIT origami disposable face shield. The Georgia Tech and MIT labs have collaborated to produce almost one million face shields to be used by hospitals around the US; (
   <bold>l</bold>) An illustration of the transparent acrylic barrier concept for public settings where cross-contamination is frequent. Aviointeriors has designed a possible solution for plane seats, while Safetell and Umdasch have designed and implemented their solution for retail stores; (
   <bold>m</bold>) The sanitizer station is a representation of the Umdasch Hygiene Station that could be distributed to all types of public facilities in the future as a norm.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="diagnostics-10-00409-g003" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
