<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0092">ACE2 has a critical role in cardiac and immune systems. ACE2 is related to heart function and it could be a potential cause of hypertension and diabetes mellitus development.
 <xref rid="bib0083" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>83</sup>
 </xref> Since ACE2 is a functional receptor for COVID-19, in patients with underlying cardiovascular diseases, clinical symptoms of COVID-19 are more severe and fatal than the general population because, in cardiovascular diseases, ACE2 secretion might be enhanced. Administration of renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system inhibitors, such as angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors (ACEIs) and angiotensin receptor blockers (ARBs) could enhance ACE2 level. Thiazolidinediones and Ibuprofen might also enhance the ACE2 level.
 <xref rid="bib0083" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>83</sup>
 </xref> So the potential safety of administration of these drugs in COVID-19 patients with underlying cardiovascular disease, hypertension, and diabetes mellitus is still controversial and further studies are required for making decisions.
 <xref rid="bib0084" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>84</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>85</sup>
 </xref> A recent publication declared that calcium channel blockers would be suitable alternative of these drugs in patients with cardiovascular disease who are infected with COVID-19.
 <xref rid="bib0083" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>83</sup>
 </xref> The previous meta-analysis revealed that patients with cardiovascular diseases are more likely prone to MERS-CoV infection. Also, recent studies showed that elderly group with comorbidities such as coronary heart disease, hypertension, and diabetes mellitus are more prone to COVID-19 infection
 <xref rid="bib0086" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>86</sup>
 </xref> and in these patients, COVID-19 could induce more severe systemic symptoms and more severe pneumonia and a large number of COVID-19 deaths were associated with cardiovascular diseases. COVID-19 infection could act as a precipitating factor in patients with the acute coronary syndrome (ACS), in which necrosis and myocardial ischemia have occurred. In cases with ACS, COVID-19 infection could deteriorate patients’ condition and lead to death. Coronary heart disease is related to COVID-19-induced acute cardiac events and these patients are poor prognosis after COVID-19 infection. In general, new-onset or worsening heart failure, new-onset or worsening arrhythmia, and myocardial infarction would be common features of patients with pneumonia such as COVID-19.
 <xref rid="bib0086" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>86</sup>
 </xref> So cardiovascular protection with suitable pharmacotherapy options is essential in COVID-19 patients with underlying cardiovascular diseases.
 <xref rid="bib0084" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>84</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>85</sup>
 </xref> As a hypothesis, it seems that ACEIs could precipitate COVID-19 pneumonia but ARBs, through blockade of angiotensin receptors, may have beneficial effects in these patients.
</p>
