<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0165">Representing a front-line professional component of essential health care and being the most accessible healthcare providers, pharmacists' role has been expanding along with the advancement of different configurations of pharmacy services provided to customers. The drive-through pharmacy service is one example of the numerous newly emerging community pharmacy services in Jordan. This model initiated in the nineties in the United States of America (USA) with pharmacy chains being initial adopters, though now it is a well espoused model acrossthe USA.
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>52</sup>
 </xref> In Jordan, drive-through pharmacy services have recently been introduced representing a new trend in community pharmacy services with positive customer awareness and perceptions towards the service.
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>53</sup>
 </xref> Although of course the model limits the ‘sit-down’ counseling deemed as a higher order role of pharmacists, in Jordan, this service appeared well received particularly in a certain subset of customers, but concerns regarding proper counseling represented the main disadvantage of the service.
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>43</sup>
 </xref>About 50% of the participants in this study believed that they should be allowed to sell medications for coronavirus management via the drive-through service available in some chain pharmacies in Jordan. Although benefits may be found in this approach of dispensing in the COVID-19 era, suboptimal counseling raises a concern. This discussion falls unto policymakers to make a clear announcement about whether to allow, encourage, or prohibit pharmacists from dispensing coronavirus patients' medications via the drive-through service. In public health emergencies, clinical pharmacists enact their professional expertise by analyzing the current situation rationally and working in a professionally cohesive and efficient manner to provide innovative pharmacy services around medication safety and rational use of medicines.
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>43</sup>
 </xref> We acknowledge that the scope of community pharmacy practice varies considerably across countries, hence, it is important to examine ways in which the profession can assist with the public health response to COVID-19. This can be donenot only by maintaining the continuity of healthcare services but by achieving optimal use of possible services.
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>54</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
