<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec id="sec001">
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>Dengue is a re-emerging infectious disease of humans, rapidly growing from endemic areas to dengue-free regions due to favorable conditions. In recent decades, Guangzhou has again suffered from several big outbreaks of dengue; as have its neighboring cities. This study aims to examine the impact of dengue epidemics in Guangzhou, China, and to develop a predictive model for Zhongshan based on local weather conditions and Guangzhou dengue surveillance information.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec002">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>We obtained weekly dengue case data from 1
   <sup>st</sup> January, 2005 to 31
   <sup>st</sup> December, 2014 for Guangzhou and Zhongshan city from the Chinese National Disease Surveillance Reporting System. Meteorological data was collected from the Zhongshan Weather Bureau and demographic data was collected from the Zhongshan Statistical Bureau. A negative binomial regression model with a log link function was used to analyze the relationship between weekly dengue cases in Guangzhou and Zhongshan, controlling for meteorological factors. Cross-correlation functions were applied to identify the time lags of the effect of each weather factor on weekly dengue cases. Models were validated using receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curves and k-fold cross-validation.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec003">
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>Our results showed that weekly dengue cases in Zhongshan were significantly associated with dengue cases in Guangzhou after the treatment of a 5 weeks prior moving average (Relative Risk (
   <italic>RR</italic>) = 2.016, 95% Confidence Interval (
   <italic>CI</italic>): 1.845–2.203), controlling for weather factors including minimum temperature, relative humidity, and rainfall. ROC curve analysis indicated our forecasting model performed well at different prediction thresholds, with 0.969 area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUC) for a threshold of 3 cases per week, 0.957 AUC for a threshold of 2 cases per week, and 0.938 AUC for a threshold of 1 case per week. Models established during k-fold cross-validation also had considerable AUC (average 0.938–0.967). The sensitivity and specificity obtained from k-fold cross-validation was 78.83% and 92.48% respectively, with a forecasting threshold of 3 cases per week; 91.17% and 91.39%, with a threshold of 2 cases; and 85.16% and 87.25% with a threshold of 1 case. The out-of-sample prediction for the epidemics in 2014 also showed satisfactory performance.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec004">
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p>Our study findings suggest that the occurrence of dengue outbreaks in Guangzhou could impact dengue outbreaks in Zhongshan under suitable weather conditions. Future studies should focus on developing integrated early warning systems for dengue transmission including local weather and human movement.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
