<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although large numbers of dog rabies cases were reported, the incidence of human rabies deaths remained low. The range of annual human rabies incidence (0.11 to 0.54 deaths per 100,000) was far lower than in Tanzania (4.9 deaths per 100,000) estimated using active surveillance [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005435.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], but is comparable with the situation in Bali in 2009. Between December 2008 and November 2009, the incidence of human rabies deaths was 0.51 per 100,000 persons (20/3,890,757) in Bali, Indonesia, and in the following 12 months, incidence increased to 2.13 deaths per 100,000 (83/3,890,757) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005435.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005435.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Moreover, the probability of developing hydrophobia after a dog bite decreased over time. The PEP used at that time already seemed to have high efficacy: 10–15% of unvaccinated patients bitten by rabid dogs died, whereas only 0.25–1% of patients vaccinated with the Pasteur dry toxin vaccine method died in Tokyo Prefecture [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005435.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. As shown in 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005435.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>, large numbers of PEP were administered to dog bite victims, and the number increased during the last part of the epidemic. The big differences between the number of dog-bite injuries by rabid dogs and PEP suggested that the victims of dog-bite injuries may have sought PEP immediately regardless of the status of infection of the dog. In the record of discussion at the transition of responsibility of rabies control from the Ministry of Agriculture to the Ministry of Home Affairs in 1929, it is written that human rabies was almost eliminated from Japan in 1928 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005435.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The increased PEP use in 1928 (
 <xref rid="pntd.0005435.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>) may reflect this transition of responsibility of rabies control, though a year earlier. Based on the ratio of hydrophobia cases and dog rabies cases in 1914, if PEP use had remained at initial levels, 252 humans rabies deaths would have occurred during the two epidemics in Osaka Prefecture. However, these data suggest that over 170 lives may have been saved by the increased PEP use. The time lag between the incidence of dog rabies cases and dog bite injuries might also reflect increased awareness of rabies over time, and consequently, improved reporting of dog bites. In fact, reported dog-bite injuries could include those by healthy as well as by rabid dogs.
</p>
