<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">In 2017, CHIKV autochthonous outbreaks have caused hundreds of infections in Italy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>, raising the need for a risk prediction map. We elaborated an 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic>-driven prediction of CHIKV transmission risk. Based on previously predicted probability of occurrence of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>, an European 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> vector competence data-driven map of CHIKV transmission risk was generated. Although the predicted 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> probabilities in the sampling localities were not particularly high except in Faliro region (Greece), the predicted risk of CHIKV transmission in European regions was significant: several regions share the same, and even higher risk of CHIKV transmission than in Anzio, Guardavalle, and Rome regions, where autochthonous CHIKV cases were reported in 2017
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>. Of note is that the spatial model used in this study relies on assumptions that may not fully reflect the diversity of interactions between 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> and CHIKV. First, dissemination and transmission models were informed through feeding assays using fixed virus titers in blood meals offered to mosquitoes bred under controlled conditions in the lab, in contrast with wild mosquitoes feeding from humans with varying viral loads. In particular, the contribution of varying meteorological conditions on viral pathogenicity, dissemination or transmission efficiencies cannot be explored and is likely to modulate the ability to transmit back to a human host
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>
 </sup>. Likewise, the estimated risks are based on the population-specific median viral titers recorded in lab experiments. Second, the probability for a mosquito to acquire an arbovirus requires an estimate of its prevalence in humans; in absence of such data, the computed probabilities represent higher boundaries of the risk to transmit CHIKV to the human population. The use of data from Kraemer 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup> furthermore assumes constant probability of encountering 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> throughout the year, ignoring seasonal variations in vector abundance. Third, the inverse-distance weighted spatial model would benefit from data taken at more scattered locations. However, the current experimental design, with most sampling sites being doubled within a few kilometers, allowed for robust results in a leave-one-out sensitivity analysis.
</p>
