<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Set H1N1 strains in periods 2 to 6 be designated by letters A, B, C, D, E. We need select two different strains as a pair. Since the evolution of influenza viruses is in a forward path [
 <xref rid="pone.0207777.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], the strains could evolve within one period to another period chronologically. For example, influenza strains in period 2 could only evolve directly or indirectly into strains in any period from 2 to 6, but not to period 1. Here we didn’t consider the situation that the subtype H1N1 developed into other subtypes. In this case, we built the model for the prediction of antigenic variants based on period 2 by the settings that for a pair of strains, one of the strains was from period 2 and the other strain was from any of the potential forward periods, which could represent antigenic relation of a pair of strains from period 2 and another. This situation is stated as Type II (AA, AB, AC, AD, AE). In this way, Other types of pairs of strains were presented as Type III (BB, BC, BD, BE), Type IV (CC, CD, CE), Type V (DD, DE) and Type VI (EE). We finally obtained 99, 180, 843, 369 and 74 samples from Type II to VI for the training and testing of antigenic relationship between pairs of strains. Single models were first applied to the individual types for the prediction of antigenic variants by several classifiers including logistic regression (LR), support vector machine (SVM), naïve bayes (NB), neural network (NN) and k-nearest neighbour (KNN). Due to the imbalanced distribution of antigenic similar and distinct samples, stratified sampling technique was applied to the training process to construct the validation model. We divided the samples into minor and major classes for each type and randomly selected 80% of each class for training and kept the rest for testing. It would make sure that the samples on each class were selected for training with a ratio of 0.8. This could overcome the overfitting problem that the minor class was overwhelmed by the major class with high accuracy. Three feature generation methods were applied to predict the antigenic relationship between strains for each type. The average accuracy was calculated over 10 runs by these classifiers above.
</p>
