<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Drug users and addiction have been intimately linked with HIV/AIDS since the beginning of the epidemic. Among the drug users in Manipur, ‘heroin’ which is locally better known as ‘number four’ is the most commonly (98%) used injecting drug [
 <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Ever since, the emergence of ‘heroin’ in the year 1982 from South Asia Golden Triangle, the availability in illegal drug market has sharply increased. The route of illegal drug trafficking is assumed to be via twin town Tamu (Myanmar) and Moreh (Manipur, India). Moreh (Tengnoupal district of Manipur, India) is an important town in connection with the India–Myanmar relationship. It is one of the developing places in the field of trade and commerce on the Indian border with Myanmar while the city of Tamu on the other side of the border. Due to aforementioned reasons, the contiguity to the Golden Triangle has been the most important reason for the rapid rise of IDUs [
 <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Some youth also use oral pain reliever drugs in combination with heroin as leisure-seeking drugs [
 <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Both forms of drugs can have serious negative health effects. However, use of ‘heroin’ intravenously is more deadly as it spreads the blood-borne viruses like HIV, HBV and HCV through shared injecting equipment [
 <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Young (aged 18–24 years) IDUs shared the injecting equipment more often when compared with the IDUs aged more than 35 years [
 <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The teenager and middle-aged people (mixed age group peoples) of rich families use the drug as a kind of fashion initially. Economically middle and low class originated youths follow the trend. Addicted youths afford the expenditure on drugs by stealing or extorting small to valuable goods from others or their own houses. The crimes related to drugs addiction increases day by day and therefore such crimes have become a social problem. Domestic chaos and violence to women and children were the ultimate impact of drug users [
 <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The situation has become exacerbate because of wrong belief that drug-addicted youth give up addiction when they have their own family responsibility, and therefore parent insist the addicted youth for marriage without knowing of the fact that the drug-addicted youth might have been infected with HIV or hepatitis (HBVs/HCVs). It is worth to mention that more than half of the IDUs were infected with HIV, while substantial proportion of HIV-positive people with injecting drug users were still unaware of HIV-positive status [
 <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Therefore, HIV-infected men have the risk of contracting of HIV infection to their female sexual partner [
 <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. These created a chance of transmitting virus knowingly or unknowingly to spouses and then to their children [
 <xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. It was previously reported that 95% who shared injecting equipment were engaged in unprotected sex with regular sexual partners, while 97% of IDUs who inconsistently use condom with casual partners were engaged in unprotected sex with their regular partners [
 <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Earlier, HIV/AIDS cases were confined among the IDUs. However, HIV/AIDS epidemic has now penetrated in the general population through the risk behaviours of IDUs. Meanwhile, housewives with single partners are gradually accounting for a larger proportion of infections. These monogamous women are primarily put at risk by the IDUs of their husband, from whom their infection is most probably acquired. The housewife is becoming the new face of the epidemic. However, when IDUs become aware of their HIV status, they reduce their high-risk behaviours. So, it is utmost important to heighten the HIV testing coverage scale across the entire international region.
</p>
