<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The first ProMED report relevant to the Ebola outbreak was a request for information (RFI) on an undiagnosed viral haemorrhagic disease. Hossein et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0230322.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] found that searching the keyword ‘Ebola’ in ProMED reports show awareness of spread of Ebola in early April 2014. Similar keyword searches in Google Trends revealed few initial results in March and April, 2014. Alicino et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0230322.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] compared Ebola-related relative search volumes (RSVs) by regions reported by Google Trends. The highest RSVs were from the three main affected countries. Liberia had the highest score, followed by Sierra Leone and Guinea. However, the most searches for the keyword ‘Ebola’ occurred on October 16, 2014 when President Obama issued a press release calling National Guard reserves to contain Ebola[
 <xref rid="pone.0230322.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In contrast, the first tweet from affected countries mentioning ‘Ebola’ came as early as December 26, 2013. However, the content of the tweet–“This Ebola of a virus come bad pass HIV …May God help us,” appeared ambiguous as the user typically posted about football. The next tweet containing Ebola was on March 25th, 2014 –“Guinea has banned the sale and consumption of bats to prevent the spread of the deadly Ebola virus,” showing stronger relevance to the outbreak[
 <xref rid="pone.0230322.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Different programs or algorithms have been used to extract data from online sources, ranging from text parsing and using the Twitter API to using Google Trends[
 <xref rid="pone.0230322.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0230322.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0230322.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Some studies did not specify their methods or details relating to data extraction and mining and extent of human moderation[
 <xref rid="pone.0230322.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0230322.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0230322.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. No literature to our knowledge has yet analysed the utility of symptom data from tweets for the detection of EVD[
 <xref rid="pone.0230322.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Thus, the aim of our study is to evaluate the value of symptomatic tweets for rapid infectious disease surveillance of the 2014 Ebola epidemic in West Africa, using automated monitoring.
</p>
