<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ASFV does not cause disease in humans, is highly contagious and causes high mortality in domestic and feral swine, and has a significant economic impact on the global swine industry. While the situation remains ever-changing due to continued outbreaks and spread of ASFV globally, information from peer-reviewed manuscripts, situation reports, and press releases provide some indication of the impact of ASFV emergence on animal health and economics of effected countries. 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> summarizes the ASF affected countries of Europe and Asia from 2007 to February 2020 including reported estimates of number of animals lost. ASF has especially affected China, which is the world's largest pork producer and consumer, producing about 50 percent of the world's pork supply (ChinaDaily.com.cn, 9/11/2019, “Swine fever may affect pork for several years,” global.chinadaily.com.cn). Since the first reported outbreak in China in August 2018, ASF has been detected in at least 8 other countries in Asia and has resulted in the death or culling of more than 5 million pigs, with losses accounting for more than 10 percent of the total pig population in China, Mongolia and Vietnam [(
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>); FAO situation update, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.fao.org</ext-link>; FAO press release, 09/08/2019, “One year on, close to 5 million pigs lost to Asia's swine fever outbreak”], and industry insiders predict a 30–60% loss of pig stocks due to ASF (ChinaDaily.com.cn, 9/11/2019, “Swine fever may affect pork for several years,” global.chinadaily.com.cn). This has put other countries on high alert, including Thailand which culled 200 pigs in response to mysterious pig deaths although no confirmed cases of ASF had been reported, as of September 2019 (Reuters Health News, 09/18/2019, “Thailand culls 200 pigs amid heightened fears over African swine fever,” 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.reuters.com" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.reuters.com</ext-link>). Since its identification in 1921, outbreaks of ASFV have been reported in more than 60 countries around the world, and global ASF outbreaks since late 2018 have increased 25 percent according to media reports (Global Times, 09/18/2019, “A global battle against African swine fever,” 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.globaltimes.cn" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.globaltimes.cn</ext-link>).
</p>
