<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The discrepancy between the globally fitted forward simulation and the data during the WWII era (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007305.g004">Fig 4</xref>) is intriguing. The lower amplitude seasonal pattern observed when estimated from the 1940–1946 period alone indicates that school-term forcing played less of a role during this time. This change likely reflects the city-wide evacuation. Given the age-structured nature of the exodus, it is perhaps not surprising that the well-mixed SEIR model could not predict these anomalous dynamics when (largely) trained on the other 88 years of data. Furthermore, the reliability and accuracy of demographic and incidence reporting during WWII is questionable and may have biased our inference framework locally, or even resulted in a mismatched attractor [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007305.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007305.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Given that measles cases became notifiable in 1940, initial reporting may have been less accurate [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007305.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Additionally, due to the evacuation, the Registrar General provides an explanatory statement in their September 9th, 1939 weekly report stating that “owing to the partial evacuation of populations from London …the weekly birth and death rates cannot be calculated with accuracy …the estimated populations at the middle of 1939 given in Table 1, no longer correspond even approximately with the deaths in that table”. Lastly, the inability to find London-specific vaccine data, and therefore using the population scaled country-level data, may have influenced our ability to drive the model with accurate susceptibility rates during the vaccine era. An additional complication in the vaccine data is the switch to the MMR vaccine in 1988, where a number of children were vaccinated twice [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007305.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. However, varying the vaccine efficacy from 90% to 99% from 1988 on produced very little qualitative difference, likely due to the already very low incidence by this point.
</p>
