<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0014">Co-expression of ZIKV prM and E proteins in insect 
 <xref rid="bib0039" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref> and mammalian 
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0041" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0042" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref> cell-based expression systems has been shown to result in the production of virus-like particles (VLPs). From a vaccine perspective, these VLPs are highly immunogenic, presenting repetitive epitope arrays to the immune system, and inherently safe, as they lack the infectious viral genome. We recently found that the amino-terminal 80% of the DENV E molecule (DENV-80E), of all four serotypes, expressed in the methylotrophic yeast 
 <italic>Pichia pastoris</italic> can self-assemble into 20–50 nm particles, in the absence of prM 
 <xref rid="bib0043" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0044" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0046" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. Though the reports call these particles as VLPs, they are different from the regular ‘prM + E’ VLPs referred to above in certain important respects: they lack prM by intentional design and display the envelope domain III (EDIII) more efficiently (compared to the classic VLPs). Thus, we now refer to the 
 <italic>P. pastoris</italic>-produced DENV-80E-based particles henceforth in this paper as nanoparticles (NPs), rather than as VLPs. Of note, we also observed that all four DENV-80E-based NPs were highly immunogenic, eliciting homotypic DENV-specific EDIII-focused nAbs. These studies strongly suggested that the DENV-80E NPs serve as platforms for the efficient display of EDIII. Like the DENV EDIIIs, ZIKV EDIII is also the target of potent nAbs. ZIKV EDIII-specific monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) from mice 
 <xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref> as well as humans [
 <xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] have been documented to not only neutralise ZIKV 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>, but also to confer significant protection against ZIKV challenge 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. Taken together, this prompted us to explore if the N-terminal 80% of ZIKV E protein (hereinafter referred to as ZIKV-80E), expressed using the 
 <italic>P. pastoris</italic> host, could also self-assemble into NPs, in the absence of prM. We also tested if these putative NPs would display EDIII, which is documented to contain potent ZIKV-neutralising epitopes, effectively to the immune system. Further, we investigated if the antibodies elicited by such NPs would manifest ZIKV-neutralising potency. Importantly, we wanted to investigate whether such ZIKV-80E NP-induced antibodies would enhance DENV and ZIKV infections 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. This paper describes our efforts to create such ZIKV-80E NPs and characterise them functionally in terms of their protective and pathogenic potential.
</p>
