<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The dairy farms in Israel are divided mainly into two types: cooperative farms (kibbutz) and family farms. In 2018, 58% of the milk was produced by cooperative farms, 41% was produced by family farms, and 1% by agriculture school farms. The average size of the cooperative farms in 2018 was 474 cows, with an average annual milk production of 5,826,000 kg/farm. The average size of the family farms at that year was 119 cows, and the average annual milk production was 1,361,000 kg/farm. All cows in the study were vaccinated by the veterinarians of the “Hachaklait” organization, which provides veterinary medicine services to more than 80% of the Israeli dairy cattle. We screened the “Hachaklait” vaccination database to find farms that vaccinated cattle during 2019. Overall, 116 vaccinating farms were detected, of which data were available on 82. We then excluded farms that experienced significant morbidity cause by other agents. Three farms were excluded due to the occurrence of brucellosis, one due to bovine tuberculosis, and one due to vitamin A deficiency. The study thus included 77 farms of Israeli Holstein cows held under zero grazing in free-stall sheds. Of these, 53 were family farms, 23 were herds of cooperative farms, and one was of an agriculture school farm. Of these, 73 farms were vaccinated routinely for at least five years. Routine vaccination was first performed in calves aged three months and was repeated yearly in all the cattle aged &gt;0.5 years (all the cattle in the farm were vaccinated at the same date). Another four farms were vaccinated on 2019 and 2016 but were not vaccinated during 2017 and 2018. These farms were vaccinated according to the same routine. However, in 2019 cows in lactation 1 and some of the lactation 2 cows were vaccinated for the first time with no prior vaccination at the age of three months. All 77 farms were vaccinated with the live attenuated Neethling LSD vaccine (OBP, South Africa, Lot numbers: 455,463,467) according to the manufacture instructions:</p>
