<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The 2009 influenza pandemic demonstrated how preparedness plans and efforts are key in enhancing the public health agencies and health care providers ability to respond to an emergency. Good preparedness and response plans are designed to anticipate the needs and mitigate the consequences of major public health events, including a pandemic. Influenza pandemic plans need be comprehensive, workable, updated regularly, and integrated with a multi-hazard public health emergency plan for rapid implementation. The important components include command and control; surveillance and laboratory testing; healthcare planning; infection control; clinical guidelines; vaccine procurement, distribution, and use; antiviral medication procurement, distribution, and use; community mitigation; communications, training and education; workforce support; emerging influenza strains; and public health preparedness informatics [
 <xref rid="B20-tropicalmed-04-00132" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The implementation of these planning components is considered at the local, regional and state level to help improve the response in a pandemic. The stockpiles for vaccines, personal protective equipment, supplies for diagnosis, and antiviral medications, need to be procured, maintained and packaged for distribution. Due to probable shortages of emergency responders and administrators, health care providers and laboratorians, the workforce may need to be supplemented with surge staff. Cross-training and just-in-time training alternatives can be considered for the various roles. Communication through information technology networks must be current, to enable prompt dissemination of risk assessments, guidelines, updates, and surveillance information. Information sharing between local responders and providers and local and state public health officials is imperative. Dialog can be facilitated between emergency management administration, public health agencies, and health care workers through emails, conference calls, and meetings; and for the community, through television, social media, and cell phone applications to send public service announcements and educational messages. Pandemic preparedness and response efforts need to be flexible to adjust to the waves of pandemic influenza, post-pandemic and interpandemic levels of influenza activity, and to the legal, ethical and policy issues within the jurisdictions [
 <xref rid="B28-tropicalmed-04-00132" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].
</p>
