<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0070">Chemical investigation of the culture of 
 <italic>Trichobotrys effuse</italic> DFFSCS021 that was isolated from the deep sea sediment collected from the South China Sea, resulted in the isolation of three new tetramic acid derivatives with a decalin ring, trichobotrysins A, B and D (
 <bold>46</bold>–
 <bold>48</bold>, 
 <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref> ) [
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Compounds 
 <bold>46</bold>–
 <bold>48</bold> possessed evidently anti-HSV-1 activity with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 3.08, 9.37, and 3.12 μM (acyclovir as positive control, IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 3.5 μM). This is the first time to report the anti-HSV-1 activity of this type of compounds [
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Minghe Luo et al. separated two novel hydroxamate-containing natural product cyclopeptides designated acremonpeptides A (
 <bold>49</bold>, 
 <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10)</xref> and B (
 <bold>50</bold>, 
 <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref>), along with Al(III)−acremonpeptide D (
 <bold>51</bold>, 
 <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref>) from the extract of the fungal strain 
 <italic>Acremonium persicinum</italic> SCSIO 115, which was isolated from a marine sediment sample collected in the South China Sea [
 <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. These compounds 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> exhibited moderate antiviral activities for HSV-1 with EC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 16, 8.7, and 14 μM, respectively [
 <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. A gorgonian sample collected from the South China Sea, Sanya, Hainan Province, resulted in the isolation of 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> sp. SCSIO 41501, which further led to the isolation of two new linear peptides, namely, aspergillipeptides D and E (
 <bold>52</bold>, 
 <bold>53</bold>, 
 <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref>) [
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Compounds 
 <bold>52</bold> and 
 <bold>53</bold> exhibited evidently inhibition against herpes simplex virus type 1 (HSV-1) with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 9.5 and 19.8 μM under their non-cytotoxic concentrations against a Vero cell line, respectively [
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Additionally, compound 
 <bold>53</bold> also had antiviral activity against acyclovir-resistant clinical isolates of HSV-1 [
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>].
</p>
