<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>When DCs are exposed to an intracellular pathogen, the cell secretes interleukin-12 (IL-12), which differentiates the CD4 T cell into a Th1 cell. Following this, the Th1 cell secretes interferon-gamma (IFN-γ) that causes a positive feedback loop for the DC to further produce IL-12 and produce more Th1 cells [
 <xref rid="B33-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. DCs also stimulate Th2 cells in a similar fashion but with the cytokine IL-6, which also leads to a positive feedback loop when the Th2 cell secretes IL-4 to further generate more Th2 cells [
 <xref rid="B33-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Along with Th2 cell activation, IL-6 has been shown to act in a dual role along with IL-1β and IL-23 in activating Th17 cells [
 <xref rid="B34-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. This subset is responsible for clearing pathogens as well as inducing tissue inflammation in autoimmune disease [
 <xref rid="B35-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. With such a wide range of immune responses, DCs also have a function to prevent autoimmune reactions. This is achieved by inducing the formation and differentiation of Tregs by IL-10, IL-27, and transforming growth factor-β (TGF-β). Tregs are responsible for maintaining self-tolerance and suppressing pathological immune responses by the clonal deletion of self-reactive T cells [
 <xref rid="B36-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="jcm-09-02661-f001">Figure 1</xref>). Within the MPS, Langerhans cells (LCs) are also an antigen-presenting cell that is present in the epidermis, which is distinctly important for both HIV and TB infections. However, the definition of LCs has been under controversy about whether it is a macrophage or a subset of DC [
 <xref rid="B37-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. This stems from the fact that LCs contain characteristics of both macrophages as well as DCs. The macrophage characteristics include the ability to self-renew as well as having a common macrophage precursor from the adult fetal liver [
 <xref rid="B37-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The DC characteristics include the ability to migrate into skin-draining lymph nodes as well as stimulating naïve T cells [
 <xref rid="B37-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In identifying the multitude of immune responses that are mediated by DCs, it is clearly evident that in immunocompromised states, an altered DC response will lead to significant negative downstream effects within the immune system.
</p>
