<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Here we provide a comprehensive characterization of the SFTSV L protein structure and function using a combination of cryo-EM, X-ray crystallography, SAXS and biochemical assays. The structure of SFTSV L protein in the apo conformation closely resembles the LACV L protein and influenza virus polymerase complex structures and, by analogy, allows prediction of the RNA binding sites in SFTSV L protein. Notable differences between these three viral polymerases include the length and conformation of the ribbon-like insertion, the position of the endonuclease domain relative to the polymerase core, and the conformation of the endonuclease linker region. In particular, the ribbon-like insertion has been speculated to be involved in L protein-nucleoprotein interactions, an interface that must be highly specific for each virus (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Integrating structural data from SAXS and cryo-EM experiments, reveals the likely flexibility of the endonuclease domain position relative to the polymerase core in solution. These observations are consistent with recently published analyses (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) and might explain the different positioning of the endonuclease relative to the polymerase core between LACV and SFTSV L structures. The C-terminal part of the bunyavirus L protein seems to be highly dynamic and was not well-resolved in the cryo-EM map. This has been previously observed for influenza virus PB2 (
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>) and LACV L (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Mechanisms for stabilization of this region by viral RNA or other factors have to be defined in future studies of functionally relevant stages, i.e. initiation, elongation and termination of transcription. Additionally, the expression and purification procedures as well as the biochemical assays established here will foster further structural and functional studies on bunyavirus L proteins. We demonstrated that the L protein of SFTSV binds to both 3′ and 5′ promoter RNA 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> inducing distinct conformational stages as concluded from electrophoretic mobility shift experiments. Furthermore, we show that SFTSV L likely initiates genome replication on vRNA 
 <italic>de novo</italic> without applying a prime-and-realign mechanism and that cap-dependent transcription requires an unknown switch. Altogether, the structural and functional data presented here on the L protein of SFTSV advance our understanding of this complex and multi-domain protein that is essential for viral replication. We also provide significant insights into the commonalities and differences between sNSV polymerase proteins, which will be particularly important for the development of broad-acting antivirals.
</p>
