<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>SARS-CoV-2 is an enveloped, nonsegmented single stranded, positive sense RNA virus. It has one of the largest genomes among all RNA viruses, comprising approximately 30 kilobases (kb) (NC_045512.2). SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 belong to the same 
 <italic>Coronaviridae</italic> family that also includes the highly fatal Middle East Respiratory Syndrome virus (MERS) that appeared in 2012.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>
 </sup> SARS-CoV-2 enters cells through the interaction of its surface Spike protein with the host receptor, angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>
 </sup> Subsequent proteolytic cleavage by the host serine protease TMPRSS2 or perhaps other proteases allows subsequent cell entry by endocytosis.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>
 </sup> Upon membrane fusion and endocytosis, the viral nucleocapsid with its genome payload is released into the cytoplasm of the infected cell. Following its release into the host cell, the virus usurps portions of the endoplasmic reticulum to form numerous double membrane vesicles.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>
 </sup> These vesicles are perfect sanctuaries to protect the viral genome and allow an efficient replication process to occur through a macromolecule complex called the replication–transcription complex (RTC).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>
 </sup> The viral genome is subsequently translated into viral polyproteins using the host cell protein translation machinery, which are then cleaved into structural and nonstructural viral proteins by two viral proteases, M
 <sup>pro</sup> and PL
 <sup>pro</sup>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>
 </sup> This step is followed by the assembly of viral particles (virions) in the endoplasmic reticulum/golgi compartment.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>
 </sup> The packaged virions are then transported to the cell surface, are released from the cells through exocytosis, and proceed to infect other cells.
</p>
