<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28">Until recently, there were no specific data in the literature reporting that subjects with obesity have a higher risk of developing severe forms of COVID-19, as first studies from China [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] and Italy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] did not provide data on body weight and height. However, last reports have found a strong link between obesity and admission to critical care as well as the use of invasive mechanical ventilation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. In a study from Shenzhen (China), obesity was associated with a 142% higher risk of developing severe pneumonia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. The Intensive Care National Audit &amp; Research Centre in United Kingdom observed that 72.1% of patients with confirmed COVID-19 were overweight or obese and that among patients with body mass index (BMI) &gt;30 who had undergone intensive care, 60.9% of them died [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Among 4103 patients in New York City, BMI &gt;40 kg/m2 was the second strongest independent predictor of hospitalization, after old age [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. In a retrospective single French center evaluating 124 consecutive patients, obesity (BMI &gt;30 kg/m2) and severe obesity (BMI &gt;35 kg/m2) were present in 47.6% and 28.2% of cases admitted to intensive care unit. The need for invasive mechanical ventilation was associated with a BMI ≥35 kg/m2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Several reports from around the world have previously identified obesity and severe obesity as risk factors for hospitalization and mechanical ventilation in the H1N1 influenza virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Together, these data raise the question of whether there is a mechanistic link between obesity and COVID-19 and whether obesity might independently contribute to COVID-19 risk or at least to more severe forms of the disease.
</p>
