<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12">The bacterial pellets recovered from 200 mL cultures were resuspended in 20 mL of lysis buffer [50 mM Tris HCl, pH 8.0, 300 mM NaCl, 400 mM ammonium acetate, 4 mM MgCl
 <sub>2</sub>, 10%, glycerol, 10 mM imidazole, and 0.1% (v/v) Tween 20] and sonicated on ice for 6 cycles of 20 s alternating with 5 cycles of 10 s. Cell debris was pelleted at 11,000 rpm for 30 min at 4 °C and the supernatant mixed with 800 μL of Ni-NTA resin previously equilibrated with 20 volumes of lysis buffer without ammonium acetate (BWE buffer). The lysate was incubated with the resin in batch method with gentle mixing during 1 h at 4 °C. The unbound fraction was then removed by decantation and the resin was then loaded onto a column and extensively washed with 20 × column volumes of BWE buffer and 20 × column volumes of BWE buffer containing 25 mM imidazole. The resin was further washed with increasing concentrations of imidazole (successive one-column volumes of BWE buffer containing 50, 60, 70, 80, 90, 100 and 125 mM imidazole). Finally, the His-tagged protein was eluted in 400 μL of BWE buffer containing 400 mM imidazole. The sample was dialyzed for 3 hours at 4 °C against 200 volumes of dialysis buffer [50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl, 5 mM MgCl
 <sub>2</sub>, 10%, glycerol, 1 mM DTT and 0.05% (v/v) Tween 20]. Samples obtained from different purification batches were pooled, quantified, aliquoted and stored at −80 °C until further use. Expression and purification of the recombinant ZIKV NS5RdRp-GNN (with D665N and D666N substitutions) was carried out following the same protocol. Likewise, the expression and purification of HCV NS5bΔ21 and NS5bΔ21-GNN polymerases was carried out following the same protocol described for ZIKV NS5. The protocol for the expression and purification of FMDV 3D polymerases has been described previously
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
