<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Zika virus (ZIKV) is a mosquito-borne flavivirus that is closely related to dengue (DENV) and yellow fever viruses (YFV). There are three ZIKV genotypes: one from Asia, which has caused the recent pandemic in the Americas, and two from Africa (East and West African) (
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Lanciotti et al., 2016</xref>). ZIKV infection is characterized by fever, arthralgia and conjunctivitis (
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Goeijenbier et al., 2016</xref>) and was considered an exceedingly rare human infection since only 14 cases were reported prior to 2007 (
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Faye et al., 2014</xref>). In 2007, the first ZIKV outbreak caused by an Asian lineage was reported in Micronesia, followed by epidemics in French Polynesia in 2013 and the recent pandemic (2015–2016) in the Americas (
 <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Weaver et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Aliota et al., 2017</xref>). During this period, it has been estimated that 1.5 million cases occurred in Brazil and more than 25,000 cases in Colombia (
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Focosi et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Samarasekera and Triunfol, 2016</xref>). As of January 2018, the virus was widely distributed in 50 countries in the Americas (
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">PAHO/WHO, 2018</xref>). The public health concern about Zika has been primarily driven by its maternal-fetal (
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Brasil et al., 2016a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Yockey et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Driggers et al., 2016</xref>) and sexual modes of transmission (
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Deckard et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Davidson et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Hills et al., 2016</xref>) as well as its association with congenital abnormalities, especially microcephaly, and Guillain-Barré syndrome in adults (
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Krauer et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Martines et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Miner et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Brasil et al., 2016b</xref>). These unique aspects set ZIKV apart from other flavivirus infections and have spurred efforts to understand ZIKV host-pathogen interactions.
</p>
