<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0135">According to the World Health Organization, healthy foods and hydration are vital. Individuals consuming a well-balanced diet are healthier with a strong immune system and have a reduced risk of chronic illness, infectious diseases. Vitamins and minerals are vital. Vitamin B, insoluble in water, protects from infection. Vitamin C protects from flu-like symptoms [
 <xref rid="bib0550" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. Insufficient vitamin D and vitamin E can lead to coronavirus infection [
 <xref rid="bib0555" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. Vitamin D can be found in sunlight, and vitamin E can be found in, for example, oil, seeds, and fruits. Insufficient iron and excess iron can lead to risk [
 <xref rid="bib0560" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0565" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>]. Zinc is necessary for maintaining the immune system [
 <xref rid="bib0570" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>]. Food rich in protein should be the top priority because it has immune properties (immunoglobulin production) and potential antiviral activity [
 <xref rid="bib0575" ref-type="bibr">[117]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0580" ref-type="bibr">[118]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0585" ref-type="bibr">[119]</xref>]. Therefore, in a regular meal, individuals should eat fruit, vegetables, legumes, nuts, whole grains, and foods from animal sources (
 <xref rid="fig0045" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref> ). Food from plants containing vitamin A should be consumed, and 8–10 cups of water should be drunk daily. Malnutrition is dangerous for patients with COVID-19 and thus proper nutrition should be provided [
 <xref rid="bib0590" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0595" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>]. Fruit juice, tea, and coffee can also be consumed. Too much caffeine, sweetened fruit juices, fruit juice concentrates, syrups, fizzy drinks, and still drinks must be avoided. Unsaturated fats, white meats, and fish should be consumed. Saturated fat, red meat, more than 5 g salt per day, and industry processed food should be avoided [
 <xref rid="bib0600" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. Along with diet, physical activity is another factor. Individuals should be active and perform physical exercise regularly to boost the immune system and should have proper sleep [123]. Although there is no registered medicine for COVID-19 treatment, hydroxychloroquine and remdesivir are prescribed and are partially effective [124].&lt;-- --&gt;
</p>
