<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>EBOV-specific antibody levels are known to correlate statistically with survival from EVD (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Monoclonal antibody (MAb)-based candidates, such as ZMAb (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), ZMapp (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), and MIL-77 (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), are promising treatments (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), due to successes in the treatment and reversion of advanced EVD in humans and nonhuman primates (NHPs). In addition, ZMapp appears to have a beneficial effect on survival rates in clinical trials (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). However, MAb-based products can be expensive and time-consuming to manufacture in large quantities, thus restricting their usefulness in areas with limited resources. Polyclonal antisera containing EBOV-specific human IgG produced from transchromosomic cattle have been shown to be efficacious in NHPs when given at 3 days postinfection (dpi) (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), but the cows are transgenic and may not be widely available to researchers in developing countries if they wish to produce their own antibody-based products. An alternate option is passive immunotherapy with polyclonal immunoglobulin F(ab′)
 <sub>2</sub> fragments produced from hyperimmunized horses. Advantages include high yields of antisera (120 to 250 g per horse [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]) in relatively short times, cost efficiency, low risk of contamination by adventitious agents, and standardized production procedures. F(ab′)
 <sub>2</sub> fragments are still commonly used in African, Asian, and Latin American countries to treat envenomation via animal bites and/or stings and rabies (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) and 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">Clostridium tetani</named-content> (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) infections. Additionally, we previously showed that F(ab′)
 <sub>2</sub> derived from horses hyperimmunized with a virus-like particle EBOV vaccine completely protected mice and guinea pigs 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> when treatment was initiated 24 h after challenge (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Our aim in this study was to characterize the protective efficacy of equine F(ab′)
 <sub>2</sub> in NHPs.
</p>
