<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Viral RNA extraction, RT-PCR and sequencing of complete ZIKV envelope (E) genes were performed as previously described
 <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> using two overlapping hemi-nested RT-PCRs, ZIKV (A) - round 1 and round 2 and ZIKV (B) - round 1 and round 2 with the following primers: ZIKV (A) round 1, 627 For primer 5’-
 <sup>627</sup>AATGCCCTATGCTGGATGAG
 <sup>646</sup>-3’ and 1652 Rev primer 5’-
 <sup>1652</sup>GCCAAGGTAATGGAATGTCG
 <sup>1633</sup>-3’, ZIKV (A) round 2, 723 For primer 5’-
 <sup>723</sup>AAAAAGGTGAAGCACGGAGA
 <sup>742</sup>-3’ and 1652 Rev primer, ZIKV (B) round 1, ZIKV E For primer 5’-
 <sup>1328</sup>AAGTTTGCATGCTCCAAGAAAAT
 <sup>1350</sup>-3’
 <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> and 2661 Rev primer 5’-
 <sup>2661</sup>GAGATCCCGCAGATACCATC
 <sup>2642</sup>-3’ and ZIKV (B) round 2, ZIKV E For primer and 2627 Rev primer 5’-
 <sup>2627</sup>TGACTGCTGCTGCCAATCTA
 <sup>2608</sup>-3’. Amplified DNA products from round 1 were diluted 1:100 and 5 µL added to round 2 mixes in a total of 50 µL. Alternatively, ZIKV (A) and ZIKV (B) RT-PCRs could be used as single round overlapping RT-PCRs when viral RNA levels were adequate. Amplification conditions used the following conditions: one cycle of 50
 <sup>o</sup>C for 15 min and 94
 <sup>o</sup>C for 2 min; 40 cycles of 94
 <sup>o</sup>C for 15 sec, 55
 <sup>o</sup>C for 30 sec and 68
 <sup>o</sup>C for 1 min followed by a final extension of 68
 <sup>o</sup>C for 5 min. Sequencing of the complete E gene was performed using the same amplification products and additional sequence primers: 1175 Rev primer 5’- 
 <sup>1175</sup>CCGATATTGATGCCTCATAG
 <sup>1156</sup>-3’, 1908 Rev primer 5’-
 <sup>1908</sup>GCTGCGGTACACAAGGAGTATG
 <sup>1887</sup>-3’, 2059 For primer 5’-
 <sup>2059</sup>TAACCCTGTAATCACTGAAA
 <sup>2078</sup>-3’ and 2379 Rev primer 5’-
 <sup>2379</sup>ATGAGAATTTGTGAGAACCA
 <sup>2360</sup>. Sequence positions for both the RT-PCR and sequencing primers were based on ZIKV Puerto Rico 2015, GenBank accession number KU501215.
</p>
