<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The dengue (DENV) and chikungunya (CHIKV) viruses have greatly expanded their geographic range globally in recent decades [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008320.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] and are considered emerging public health threats throughout the world, including Europe [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008320.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The global number of dengue infections in 2010 was estimated at 390 (284–528) million per year, 96 (67–136) million cases being clinically manifested [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008320.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. CHIKV has been responsible for two major epidemics in recent decades. The first spread in 2004 from Eastern Africa to the Indian Ocean and to South Asia. The second occurred in the Americas, with more than 1.2 million suspected cases reported for the 2013–2014 period [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008320.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. DENV and CHIKV are mainly transmitted between humans through the bite of 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> mosquitoes in urban settings, and are introduced in non-endemic countries by infected returning travellers [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008320.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008320.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Autochthonous transmission can then occur in areas where a competent vector is established and where climatic conditions are favourable for transmission. In the Mediterranean and central Europe, only 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> is present. Its expansion is a direct consequence of the globalization of trade [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008320.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The continued spread of this vector through trade and the constant growth in international travel will increase the risk of exotic viruses emerging in many other European areas. Italy, France, Croatia and Spain experienced several events of autochthonous DENV and CHIKV transmission between 2010 and 2018 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008320.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0008320.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Nevertheless, the number of imported cases remains well above the number of autochthonous transmission cases [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008320.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and, to date, there is no evidence-based explanation as to why autochthonous transmission occurs in some circumstances in Europe but not in others.
</p>
