<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <p>Medical writing was provided by Dr. Phillip Leventhal (Evidera).</p>
 <p>The GIHSN 2017–2018 collaborators include: Sélilah Amour (Hôpital Edouard Herriot, Lyon, France), Coulibaly Anderson N’Gattia (Institut National d’Hygiène Publique, Treichville, Ivory Coast), Victor Baselga Moreno (Foundation for the Promotion of Health and Biomedical Research, Valencia, Spain), Elsa Baumeister (National Reference Laboratory for Viral Respiratory Diseases, Buenos Aires, Argentina), Jalila Ben Khelil (Institut Pasteur de Tunis, Tunis, Tunisia), Daria Danilenko (Research Institute of Influenza of the Ministry of Healthcare, Saint Petersburg, Russian Federation), Javier Diez-Domingo (Foundation for the Promotion of Health and Biomedical Research, Valencia, Spain), Anca Cristina Drăgănescu (National Institute for Infectious Diseases “Prof. Dr. Matei Bals”, Bucharest, Romania), Gideon O. Emukule (Kenya Medical Research Institute, Nairobi, Kenya), Zhetpisbayeva Gauhar (National Influenza Center, Almaty City, Republic of Kazakhstan), M. Lourdes Guerrero (National Institutes of Health, Mexico, Mexico City, Mexico), Ainara Mira-Iglesias (FISABIO, Valencia, Spain), Lidija Kisteneva (N.F. Gamaleya NRCEM, Ministry of Health of the Russian Federation, Moscow, Russia), Parvaiz A. Koul (Sher-i-Kashmir Institute, Srinagar, India), Ainagul Kuatbaeva (National Influenza Center, Almaty City, Republic of Kazakhstan), Victor Alberto Laguna Torres (Instituto de Medicina Tropical Universidad Nacional Mayor de San Marcos, Bellavista Callao, Peru), Odile Launay (Hôpital Cochin, Paris, France), Nezha Lenzi (Hôpital Cochin, Paris, France), Shabir Madhi (University of the Witwatersrand, Johannesburg, South Africa), Zdenka Mandakova (National Institute of Public Health, Prague, Czech Republic), Snežana Medić (Institute of Public Health of Vojvodina, Novi Sad, Serbia), Mioljub Ristić (Institute of Public Health of Vojvodina, Novi Sad, Serbia), Hyder Mir (Sher-i-Kashmir Institute, Srinagar, India), Aneta Nitsch-Osuch (Medical University of Warsaw, Warsaw, Poland), Nancy Otieno (Kenya Medical Research Institute, Nairobi, Kenya), Daniela Pițigoi (National Institute for Infectious Diseases “Prof. Dr. Matei Balş”, Bucharest, Romania) Andrea Pontoriero (National Reference Laboratory for Viral Respiratory Diseases, Buenos Aires, Argentina), Estela Ramirez (Instituto de Medicina Tropical Universidad Nacional Mayor de San Marcos, Bellavista Callao, Peru), Ben Salah (Institut Pasteur de Tunis, Tunis, Tunisia), Oana Sandulescu (National Institute for Infectious Diseases “Prof. Dr. Matei Bals”, Carol Davila University of Medicine and Pharmacy, Bucharest, Romania), Natali Serafin (University of the Witwatersrand, Johannesburg, South Africa), Wei Shan (Fudan University, Shanghai, China), Anna Sominina (Research Institute of Influenza of the Ministry of Healthcare, Saint Petersburg, Russian Federation), Svetlana Trushakova (N.F.Gamaleya NRCEM, Ministry of Health of the Russian Federation, Moscow, Russia), Andrzej Zalewski (Medical University of Warsaw, Warsaw, Poland), and Tao Zhang (Fudan University, Shanghai, China).</p>
</ack>
