<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="bullet">
 <list-item>
  <p>Based on the global data available, it is very unfortunate that the spread of the virus is still ongoing and the impact of the infection is still on the rise, despite the various preventive and precautionary interventions carried out by us.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>It is mandatory that the infected or possibly infected SARS-CoV-2 patients should immediately contact the nearby health-care professional to check on their health status to safeguard both their families and their societies.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>It is necessary to follow the rules and regulations provided by the health-care professional and government officials, which include quarantine, national lockdown, and social distancing as a measure to control the spread of the infection.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>It is highly encouraged and recommended that only vigorous obedience to the guidelines amended by the government and maintaining the preventive and precautionary measures will yield the desired result of containing this viral infection.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>We should co-operate with the health-care officials if they need to test our samples by providing them with the desired specimens to confirm the presence or absence of the infection in a particular individual.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Based on the efficiency of the hydroxychloroquine and chloroquine drugs, it should be approved soon as the one-stop remedy to treat the SARS-CoV-2 infection.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>As per the government order, more state hospitals should take up the charge to carry out the clinical trials on convalescent plasma therapy as a remedial approach for this viral infection.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>The recovered patients should come forward to provide their blood samples to extract the antibody-rich plasma as a therapy to serve the severely affected COVID-19 patients.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Home quarantine should be strictly followed, as it will be easy to combat the disease more expediently.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>People who are infected or may have been infected must drink plenty of water to stay hydrated and also should be encouraged to have more nutritious food to improve their immunity and stamina to fight this infection.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Individuals should follow the guidelines of the health-care and government professionals and should reduce their intake of smoking and alcohol consumption in order to improve will improve their immunity.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>These social strategies could be a game-changer in rapidly controlling the spread of this pandemic, where a unified and strict co-operation and co-ordination from us as citizens are very important for combatting the COVID-19 disease.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>During this dreadful situation, it is highly suggested that any travel to the international sectors should be avoided, because it could increase the spread of the viral load among societies.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>It is evident that the spread of infection is mainly through human-to-human transmission; hence it is mandatory to monitor our health status regularly if we have even a mild symptom associated with this disease.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Containing the spread of SARS-CoV-2 infection will potentially reduce the stress and strain on the health-care professionals as well as on the researchers/scientist, which will enable them to concentrate more on the development of the specific vaccine for this disease.</p>
 </list-item>
</list>
