<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3065466</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21464934</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-00056</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017764</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Population Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Epidemiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Infectious Disease Epidemiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Population Dynamics</subject><subj-group><subject>Disease Dynamics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Population Modeling</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Mathematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Probability Theory</subject><subj-group><subject>Stochastic Processes</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Epidemiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Infectious Disease Epidemiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Viral Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Influenza</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Infectious Disease Modeling</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Public Health</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Can Antiviral Drugs Contain Pandemic Influenza
Transmission?</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Can Antivirals Contain Influenza
Transmission?</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>Niels G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>&#x0002a;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Dingcheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<addr-line>National Centre for Epidemiology and Population Health, The Australian
National University, Canberra, Australian Capital Territory,
Australia</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>Andrew</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Albert Einstein College of Medicine, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>Niels.Becker@anu.edu.au</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: NGB. Analyzed the data: DW. Wrote the
paper: NGB. Formulated the problems, provided the method of solution
(including the equations), supervised the direction of the analysis, and
wrote the manuscript: NGB. Wrote the computer code to solve the equations,
prepared the graphs/figures, and proposed the methodology (and its
implementation) that led to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017764-g006">Figure 6</xref>: DW. </p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>3</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e17764</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>2</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Becker, Wang.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Antiviral drugs dispensed during the 2009 influenza pandemic generally failed to
contain transmission. This poses the question of whether preparedness for a
future pandemic should include plans to use antiviral drugs to mitigate
transmission.</p><p>Simulations using a standard transmission model that allows for infected arrivals
and delayed vaccination show that attempts to contain transmission require
relatively few antiviral doses. In contrast, persistent use of antiviral drugs
when the reproduction number remains above 1 use very many doses and are
unlikely to reduce the eventual attack rate appreciably unless the stockpile is
very large. A second model, in which the community has a household structure,
shows that the effectiveness of a strategy of dispensing antiviral drugs to
infected households decreases rapidly with time delays in dispensing the
antivirals. Using characteristics of past pandemics it is estimated that at
least 80&#x00025; of primary household cases must present upon show of symptoms
to have a chance of containing transmission by dispensing antiviral drugs to
households. To determine data needs, household outbreaks were simulated with
50&#x00025; receiving antiviral drugs early and 50&#x00025; receiving antiviral
drugs late. A test to compare the size of household outbreaks indicates that at
least 100&#x02013;200 household outbreaks need to be monitored to find evidence
that antiviral drugs can mitigate transmission of the newly emerged virus.</p><p>Use of antiviral drugs in an early attempt to contain transmission should be part
of preparedness plans for a future influenza pandemic. Data on the incidence of
the first 350 cases and the eventual attack rates of the first 200 hundred
household outbreaks should be used to estimate the initial reproduction number
<italic>R</italic> and the effectiveness of antiviral drugs to mitigate
transmission. Use of antiviral drugs to mitigate general transmission should
cease if these estimates indicate that containment of transmission is
unlikely.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The threat from avian influenza H1N5 prompted many countries to establish a stockpile
of antiviral drugs, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Cheng1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Lett1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Esveld1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Harrod1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, such as oseltamivir and zananivir. The size of the
antiviral stockpile and its proposed use, therapy or prophylaxis, were keenly
debated during the preparation of pandemic management plans. The emergence of
pandemic H1N1 in 2009 prompted a variety of strategies for the use of antiviral
drugs and motivates this look at the use of antiviral drugs for prophylaxis and
implications for decisions on the size of an antiviral stockpile for a future
pandemic.</p><p>The possibility of using antiviral drugs for prophylaxis, to mitigate transmission of
pandemic influenza, arises because their use to protect against currently
circulating strains of influenza indicates a reduced chance of being infected <xref rid="pone.0017764-Hayden1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Hayden2" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Hayden3" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Moscona1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Welliver1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Also observed
are reduced levels of virus shedding <xref rid="pone.0017764-Hayden1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Hayden2" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-HaydenFGet1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Nicholson1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Treanor1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Jefferson1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Jefferson2" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, which suggests a reduction
in infectivity in the event of a breakthrough infection. Use of these observations
in modeling studies suggests that stockpiles of antiviral drugs held by some nations
are sufficiently large to defer the peak of the epidemic until a newly developed
vaccine is available to control transmission <xref rid="pone.0017764-Ferguson1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Longini1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Barnes1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-McCaw1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. These results could be expected
to apply to pandemic H1N1 since, with a reproduction number estimated to be of the
order 1.2-1.5 in some localities <xref rid="pone.0017764-Cowling1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Mercer1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, its transmissibility is relatively modest.</p><p>In practice, the antiviral drugs dispensed during the 2009 influenza pandemic
generally failed to contain transmission. This prompts us to ask why timely
administration of antiviral drugs to a sufficient number of cases, exposed
individuals and individuals at high risk of exposure did not occur. Could we have
done better? On a future occasion, should we even attempt to contain transmission
with the assistance of antiviral drugs? A consideration of these questions will
inform preparedness plans for the next pandemic.</p><p>Some argue that using antiviral drugs to mitigate transmission merely wastes doses
that are needed to treat cases experiencing severe disease. Here &#x02018;dose&#x02019;
means a course of antiviral drugs, typically lasting seven days. The fear of wastage
is fed by the fact that the protective effect of antiviral drugs acts only for the
duration of the dose (e.g. 7 days), so that individuals might need several doses
during a pandemic. On the other hand, if prophylactic use of antiviral drugs is able
to reduce the total number individuals infected then there will be fewer cases with
severe disease in need of treatment with antiviral drugs. The optimal allocation of
antiviral doses to treatment and prophylaxis depends on the size of the stockpile,
effectiveness of antiviral drugs for treatment and protection from infection, as
well as the transmission and disease progression characteristics of the new virus
strain. Many of these factors will not be known prior to the pandemic. However, it
is clearly worth asking whether a relatively modest number of antiviral doses used
for prophylaxis might be able to reduce the eventual attack rate substantially.</p><p>Here we use simple models that contain the key features needed to assess the impact
of using antiviral drugs to mitigate transmission. The aim is to clarify the
potential benefit of timely use of antivirals for prophylaxis and its limitations.
Specifically, we ask whether use of antiviral drugs should be included in an attempt
to contain an emerged pandemic, we provide guidance on the size of stockpile needed
for an attempt at containment and consider what data need to be collected at the
start of a pandemic to assess the prophylactic effectiveness of antiviral drugs
against the new virus strain.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>The basic model</title><p>To assess the potential for antiviral drugs to mitigate transmission, we begin
with the baseline model depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017764-g001">Figure 1</xref>, in which homogeneous individuals mix uniformly and
experience transitions between the <italic>Susceptible</italic>,
<italic>Infective</italic> and <italic>Removal</italic> states over time. A
removal is an individual who is immune as a consequence of vaccination or
recovery from an infection. Let <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e001.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>,
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e002.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e003.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> denote the
proportion of individuals who are susceptible, infectious and removed at time
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e004.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. The equations describing transmission and recovery
are<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e005.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float"/><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e006.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> governs the rate
of transmission and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e007.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the recovery
rate. For our purpose, we have added to the standard SIR epidemic model a rate
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e008.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> of immunisation by vaccination and a rate
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e009.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> of importing newly infected individuals from other
locations. These two rates may be time-dependent. The initial reproduction
number is the number of secondary infections generated by a typical single
primary case at the beginning when no one else has been infected. For this model
it is given by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e010.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. We do not refer
to this <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e011.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> as the <italic>basic</italic> reproduction number
because we allow for the possibility that awareness of a new pandemic strain may
have changed behaviour and individuals may have some immunity against the new
strain from previous exposure to other influenza strains.</p><fig id="pone-0017764-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017764.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Baseline transmission model.</title><p>Mass vaccination and arrival of infected individuals from other locations
has been added to the standard SIR transmission model.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.g001"/></fig><p>Our concern is with a strain of influenza that is newly emerged and so
individuals can be vaccinated only when a strain-specific vaccine has been
developed and tested. To accommodate this delay, the rate of immunising
susceptible individuals is assumed to have the form<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e012.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float"/></disp-formula>where
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e013.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the time when the new vaccine is ready to be
dispensed. A time-varying rate of importing new infectives is realistic, but
here we restrict attention to a constant importation rate
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e014.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>.</p><p>Our main focus is on using antiviral drugs for prophylaxis, to hopefully contain
or delay widespread transmission. For the moment suppose that each individual is
symptomatic and presents to the health service following onset of their
symptoms. We assume that each newly diagnosed case triggers the dispensing of
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e015.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> doses of antiviral drugs to individuals who have been
exposed to or are a potential contact of that case. It is meaningful to allow
non-integer values for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e016.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> if we interpret it
to be the average number of doses dispensed per case. In our model the effect of
dispensing <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e017.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> antiviral doses per case is to reduce the transmission
rate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e018.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e019.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, where the factor
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e020.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> decreases as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e021.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> increases and
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e022.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. Here we use the form<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e023.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float"/><label>(2)</label></disp-formula>for
a variety of values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e024.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e025.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> satisfying <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e026.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e027.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, so that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e028.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> decreases from 1
to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e029.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e030.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> increases. This
form for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e031.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> acknowledges that the first few doses dispensed are
likely to reduce transmission more effectively because they target the closest
associates of the case. The effect on the reproduction number is to reduce it
from <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e032.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e033.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, which is less
than <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e034.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> unless <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e035.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>.</p><p>To monitor the depletion of the stockpile of antiviral drugs we define
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e036.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> &#x0200a;=&#x0200a; (total number of doses in the
stockpile remaining at time <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e037.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>)/(population
size).</p><p>Then <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e038.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, the initial number of doses per individual, is the
initial size of the stockpile relative to the population size. When we dispense
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e039.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> doses for each new case we find<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e040.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float"/><label>(3)</label></disp-formula>
</p><p>A variety of values for the parameters <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e041.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>,
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e042.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e043.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>,
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e044.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e045.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e046.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> are used. In <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0017764-t001">Table 1</xref> we show baseline values for these
parameters that seem relevant in planning preparedness for pandemic influenza,
where the values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e047.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>,
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e048.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e049.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e050.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> are rates per day. Results presented here are based on
these baseline parameter values unless indicated otherwise. Initially we assume
that everyone is susceptible, i.e. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e051.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e052.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. Transmission is seeded by the importation of
infectives.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0017764-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017764.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Baseline values for model parameters.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0017764-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0017764.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x003b3;</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>R</italic>
<sub>0</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>t</italic>
<sub>v</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e053.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>a</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>b</italic>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e054.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.375</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>The recovery rate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e055.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> gives a mean
infectious period of four days, the vaccination rate
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e056.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> means that once developed the vaccine can be given to
1&#x00025; of the population per day and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e057.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> means that the
chance of transmission per close contact can be reduced by at most 50&#x00025; by
liberal use of antiviral drugs. The value <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e058.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> days assumes that
it takes five months to develop a vaccine and get it ready for distribution.</p><p>A baseline initial value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e059.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, when planning to
prepare for pandemic influenza, seems sensible on the basis of past experience.
Attack rates observed during the pandemics of 1918, 1957, 1968 and 2009 are, for
the most part, consistent with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e060.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, or less. It is,
of course, possible that a pandemic strain with a higher transmission rate might
evolve. Indeed, the basic reproduction number of the 1918 pandemic strain was
almost certainly substantially higher, but compliance with public health
measures based on social distancing during this pandemic was high because of the
recognised severity of the disease. This is evident by observing how incidence
changed as social distancing measures were introduced and removed; see Caley
<italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="pone.0017764-Caley1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. As a result, although susceptibility was uniformly
high the effective reproduction number, prior to depletion of susceptibles, was
about 1.5. A high level of compliance is also likely in the event of a future
pandemic strain with severe disease, suggesting that an initial effective
reproduction number below 1.5 is likely from social distancing measures
alone.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Distributing antiviral drugs to affected households</title><p>It is natural that individuals responsible for distributing antiviral drugs are
concerned about wastage in attempts to reduce transmission, when these drugs are
thought necessary to treat severe cases and to protect essential-service
personnel, such as health care workers and police, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Barnes1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. Faced with competing
demands it is tempting to limit community distribution of antiviral drugs to
cases with laboratory-confirmed infection and individuals with confirmed
exposure. Unfortunately, laboratory confirmation and contact tracing are time
consuming and insistence on such confirmation makes it impossible to administer
antiviral drugs quickly enough to contain transmission. A strategy of dispensing
antiviral drugs quickly and liberally to household members as soon as the first
household case presents seems to be what is needed. A focus on households helps
to clarify who is targeted for antiviral prophylaxis and the co-location of its
members makes timely dispensing to exposed individuals feasible. We therefore
look at transmission in a community of households with a focus on timeliness and
transmission characteristics that make containment of transmission feasible. For
such a community is useful to work with the reproduction number for infected
households, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Bartoszynsm1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Becker1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Ball1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, which we denote <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e061.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>.</p><p>To incorporate the effect of antiviral drugs on transmission into the calculation
of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e062.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and the mean number of eventual cases, we adopt the
effect formulation of Glass and Becker <xref rid="pone.0017764-Glass1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. They model the effect of
antiviral drugs by a change in the population dynamics of the virus population
within the host and translate this to the corresponding change in
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e063.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, the probability that a susceptible individual avoids
being infected by a single infected household member of generation
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e064.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. Infectives of one generation are the individuals
infected by the infectives of the previous generation, where household
generation 0 contains only the primary household case. For our purpose we also
include the corresponding effect on <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e065.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, the mean number
of cases a generation-<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e066.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> infective
generates outside their household. As in <xref rid="pone.0017764-Glass1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, individuals who are not
infectives of generations 0 and 1 are assumed to receive antiviral drugs before
being infected and therefore derive the full protective effect of these drugs.
Then the values of the probabilities <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e067.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> are same for
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e068.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. As in <xref rid="pone.0017764-Glass1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, we use a Reed-Frost model, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Bailey1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Becker2" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, for within-household
transmission with the modification that the probability of avoiding infection is
generation-dependent. The 2001 Australian census data was used to allocate a
distribution to household size. With these specifications we compared the value
of the reproduction number <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e069.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> for three
different settings, namely when (i) no antiviral drugs are dispensed, (ii) doses
are dispensed to household members two days after the primary case is infected,
and (iii) doses are dispensed four days after the primary case is infected.</p><p>In order to determine the largest fraction of non-compliance that still permits
transmission to be contained, we also compute the effect of antiviral drugs on
the reproduction number <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e070.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> when a fraction
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e071.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> of primary household cases fails to present early enough
for the household to receive antiviral drugs.</p><p>Finally, we determine how many household outbreaks might need to be observed to
provide evidence that the antiviral drugs are indeed effective against the newly
emerged virus strain. Here we look at establishing effectiveness via a simple
comparison of the mean outbreak size in households that receive antiviral drugs
early with the mean outbreak size in households that receive them late. This
comparison of means must accommodate heterogeneity in variances and a number of
tests permit this. We have chosen to use the Alexander-Govern test <xref rid="pone.0017764-Alexander1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, because
its computations are relatively simple, good performance has been demonstrated
<xref rid="pone.0017764-Schneider1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>
and it provides a simple and direct way to combine the comparisons for
households of different sizes.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Transmission: contained or not contained</title><p>The model given by equations (1)&#x02013;(3) was used, with a range of plausible
parameters values, to determine the eventual attack rate (percentage of the
population infected). The consistent findings are illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017764-g002">Figure 2</xref>, which shows the
eventual attack rate as given by the model with (a)
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e072.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and (b) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e073.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and other
parameters assuming the baseline values of <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0017764-t001">Table 1</xref>. The smallest value for
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e074.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is 0.75 when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e075.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and 1.125 when
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e076.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>.</p><fig id="pone-0017764-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017764.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Eventual attack rate (<italic>AR</italic>).</title><p>Percentage of the population infected, as predicted by the baseline model
with (a) <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e077.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and (b)
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e078.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, for
different <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e079.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> (stockpile
size, as a proportion of the population size) and
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e080.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> (number of
antiviral doses dispensed per case). Colours on the graphs range from
dark blue (low values) to dark red (high values).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.g002"/></fig><p>For all parameter values, increasing <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e081.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> from zero
decreases the transmission rate <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e082.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and this is
reflected in a decline in the eventual attack rate
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e083.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. For larger values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e084.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, we see an
increase in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e085.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e086.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> increases. This
arises because the value of the transmission rate
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e087.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> returns to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e088.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> as the stockpile
is depleted and epidemic transmission resumes (slightly tempered by a depletion
of susceptibles).</p><p>When <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e089.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> can be brought below 1, as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017764-g002">Figure 2(a)</xref>, there is a very steep decline in
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e090.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e091.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> increases and
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e092.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> approaches 1. Note that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e093.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> remains very low
for a substantial range of values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e094.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>. The range of
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e095.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> values for which transmission is contained depends on
the size of the stockpile. The existence of a wide range of near-optimal values
for <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e096.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and the fact that transmission is contained for any
value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e097.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> in this range provide realistic scope for practical and
effective use of antiviral drugs for prophylaxis.</p><p>In contrast, when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e098.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> cannot be brought
below 1, as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017764-g002">Figure 2(b)</xref>,
a small value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e099.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> can induce a
reduction in the attack rate. However, noting the scale on the vertical axis in
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017764-g002">Figure 2(b)</xref>, we see that
the reduction is small and very localised. It is difficult to utilise this
optimal dosage in practice because its value depends on factors that are unknown
and difficult to estimate with adequate precision.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Number of doses of antiviral drugs dispensed</title><p>The eventual number of antiviral doses dispensed per community member can be
computed numerically from equations (1)&#x02013;(3). When transmission can be
contained, it is more informative to work with a simple expression that
approximates antiviral usage, because this expression reflects directly how
various factors affect the usage.</p><p>When <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e100.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> remains below 1 there is relatively little depletion of
susceptibles, so we may write<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e101.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float"/></disp-formula>Then the fraction of
infectives is soon near its equilibrium value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e102.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and the number of
doses of antiviral drugs dispensed per community member is
approximately<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e103.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float"/><label>(4)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e104.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the time when
the vaccine is ready to be dispensed and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e105.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the additional
time required to reach a vaccination coverage that brings the effective
reproduction number below 1. By way of illustration, note that equation (4)
indicates that the required number of antiviral drug doses will be equal to
1.2&#x00025; of the population size when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e106.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and other
parameters assume their baseline value. This allows for one imported infective
per day for every million population members, for a duration of six months, and
all the transmission chains they generate. Prior to the 2009 pandemic many
nations held antiviral stockpiles with doses that numbered more than 20&#x00025;
of their population. Only a small fraction of this would be needed for sustained
containment of transmission until the vaccine controls transmission.</p><p>The 1.2&#x00025; we calculated above is based on sustained containment for six
months. When containment is not achievable we would become aware of this quite
early and would abandon the attempt of containment having spent a small fraction
of the stockpile. For example, Becker <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0017764-Becker3" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref> show that
a useful estimate of the initial reproduction number is obtained once the
cumulative incidence reaches 350&#x02013;500 cases. With
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e107.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> doses per case and a population of 1 million, we would
therefore abandon the attempt at containment having spent antiviral doses
numbering less than 0.05&#x00025; of the population size if the estimate of
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e108.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> indicates containment is infeasible.</p><p>More generally, the total number of antiviral doses used, as given by (4),
increases linearly with the rate of importations
(<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e109.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>), and the time until the vaccine is able to control
transmission (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e110.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>). Together, these terms contribute the factor
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e111.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, which is the mean number of importations of infected
cases from the start of the pandemic until the vaccine is able to reduce the
reproduction number below 1. The remaining factor in (3) is
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e112.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, the mean number of doses dispensed for each outbreak
initiated by a single infective. Its dependence on
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e113.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017764-g003">Figure 3</xref>. We see that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e114.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> declines rapidly
to a minimum as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e115.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> increases just
beyond the value required to bring <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e116.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> below 1. The
optimal <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e117.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> occurs when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e118.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is about 0.8 and
the gradual increase in <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e119.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> for larger values
of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e120.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> indicates that nothing is gained by striving to achieve
a value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e121.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> smaller than 0.8. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017764-g003">Figure 3</xref> illustrates that this conclusion is
not sensitive to our assumed value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e122.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>.</p><fig id="pone-0017764-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017764.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Doses used per imported case.</title><p>Mean number of doses used to contain each outbreak initiated by one
infected arrival, when <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e123.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> doses are
dispensed for every case.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.g003"/></fig><p>The encouraging conclusion that a relatively small stockpile of antiviral drugs
is needed for an attempt to contain the pandemic locally is not a consequence of
the specific model (1). The same conclusion is reached from branching process
models under quite general assumptions about characteristics of transmission and
disease progression.</p><p>The enormous benefit of local containment of a pandemic virus strain can be
realised only when (i) antiviral drugs are effective enough to reduce the
reproduction number from its initial value of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e124.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> to a value below
1, and (ii) timely distribution of antiviral drugs to appropriate individuals is
possible in practice. In retrospect, pandemic H1N1 influenza in 2009 seemed to
satisfy condition (i), but condition (ii) was not realised. We now consider some
possible reasons for the failure to distribute antiviral drugs effectively.</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Distributing antiviral drugs to affected households</title><p>Consider now transmission through a community of households. Suppose that every
infection that an individual generates outside their own household is of a
randomly selected community member. During the containment phase of the
pandemic, the force of infection acting on a susceptible from outside the
household is negligible relative to the force of infection exerted by an
infectious household member. Using this we can show that, in a community of
households, the number of doses of antiviral drugs dispensed per community
member is<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e125.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float"/><label>(5)</label></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e126.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the mean number
of antiviral doses dispensed to the household of a newly-infected individual who
is selected randomly from the community and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e127.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the mean number
of primary cases generated in the community by all the cases of a household
outbreak initiated by a newly-infected individual who is selected randomly from
the community. The derivation of (5) is outlined in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0017764.s001">Appendix
S1</xref>. Equation (5) is the equivalent of (4) for a community of households.
To be valid it requires, similarly to (4), that the reproduction number for
infected households (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e128.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>) is less than
1.</p><p>Equation (5) can accommodate a variety of strategies for dispensing antiviral
doses to households, including &#x0201c;every household member&#x0201d; and
&#x0201c;every household case upon onset of their symptoms&#x0201d;. From (5) we
conclude, as for (4), that an attempt to contain transmission uses relatively
few doses of antiviral drugs, be it sustained containment of transmission or an
attempt to contain transmission that is abandoned once it becomes clear that
containment is not feasible.</p><p>The key to containing transmission in a community of households lies in the
ability to bring <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e129.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> below 1. We now
take a closer look at what is required to bring <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e130.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> below 1, under the
assumption that the effectiveness of antiviral drugs for reducing susceptibility
and infectivity for the emerged virus strain is as estimated for currently
circulating influenza strains. The effect of antivirals on reducing transmission
is modeled as in Glass and Becker <xref rid="pone.0017764-Glass1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>.</p><p>To show the roles of within and between household transmission we display results
in terms of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e131.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, the mean number of individuals an infective infects
outside their household, and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e132.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, the probability
that a susceptible household partner avoids infectious contact with a household
case during the latter's infectious period. These interpretations of
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e133.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e134.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> apply for a
totally susceptible community in which antiviral drugs are not used. The curves
in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017764-g004">Figure 4</xref> display values
of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e135.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e136.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> for which
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e137.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> in three scenarios, namely (a) antivirals are dispensed
at onset of symptoms in the primary case (two days after infection), (b)
antivirals are dispensed two days after onset of symptoms in the primary
household case, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Lett1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Harrod1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref> and (c) no antiviral drugs are dispensed. For each
curve in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017764-g004">Figure 4</xref>, parameter
pairs <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e138.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> that lie below the curve satisfy
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e139.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, while <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e140.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> for parameter
coordinates above the curve. By comparing the two lowest curves we see that
dispensing drugs to all family members two days after onset of symptoms in the
primary case expands the set of parameter values for which
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e141.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> only a little. In contrast, dispensing drugs at onset of
symptoms in the primary case expands the set of parameter values for which
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e142.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> substantially. In other words, the set of scenarios for
which containment becomes feasible is much larger when antiviral drugs are
dispensed as soon as possible. When we compute values of
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e143.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> for parameter pairs <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e144.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> lying on curve (a)
but assuming that no antiviral drugs are dispensed we obtain values in the range
1.9&#x02013;2.7. This shows that antiviral drugs can bring a reproduction number
that is well above 1 down to a value of 1 if they are dispensed at onset of
symptoms in the primary case.</p><fig id="pone-0017764-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017764.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Curves for which the reproduction number for household outbreaks
(<italic>R<sub>H</sub></italic>) equals 1.</title><p>The three <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e145.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> curves
correspond to (a) antivirals are dispensed at onset of symptoms in the
primary household case, (b) antivirals are dispensed two days after
symptom onset in the primary case, and (c) no antiviral drugs are
dispensed. For each of these three intervention scenarios,
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e146.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> for every
parameter point <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e147.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> that lies
below the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e148.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> curve and
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e149.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> when
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e150.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> lies above
the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e151.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> curve.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.g004"/></fig><p>Timely dispensing of antiviral drugs is so important because, as reflected in the
model, individuals infected with influenza become infectious prior to onset of
symptoms and the bulk of their total infection potential has passed 2&#x02013;3
days after symptom onset.</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Failure to present</title><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017764-g004">Figure 4</xref> illustrates that
failure to present early can reduce the effectiveness of using antiviral drugs
to mitigate transmission. People might fail to present because their clinical
symptoms are not severe or present late due to delayed access to health
services. It seems likely that use of antiviral drugs to contain transmission of
pandemic H1N1 influenza in 2009 was not successful because the fraction of
infected individuals who failed to present, or presented late, was too high. It
is useful to have a way of determining how the fraction of primary household
cases who do not present, or present late, limits the chance of containing
transmission.</p><p>Let <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e152.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> denote the proportion of primary household cases that
fail to present early. Under the assumption that every member of a household
whose primary case presents early receives a dose of antiviral drugs and that
other households get no antiviral drugs the reproduction number for infected
households becomes <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e153.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, where
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e154.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the household reproduction number when no antiviral
drugs are dispensed and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e155.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the household
reproduction number when antiviral drugs are dispensed to all infected
households. This reproduction number is equal to 1 when<disp-formula><graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e156.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float"/><label>(6)</label></disp-formula>Therefore, even when
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e157.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, it is not possible to contain transmission if the
proportion primary household cases who fail to present early is greater than the
right hand side of (6).</p><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017764-g005">Figure 5</xref> shows the curves (6)
for the values <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e158.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e159.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> for various values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e160.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> that might be
obtained when antiviral drugs are dispensed to members of those households where
the primary case presents early. For values of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e161.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> below the curve it
is possible to contain transmission, but for values of
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e162.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> above the curve it is not. Suppose we can reduce the
reproduction number for household outbreaks to <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e163.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> when antiviral
drugs are dispensed to all infected households. Then containment of transmission
requires that less than 29&#x00025; of primary cases fail to present early when
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e164.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, and less than 12&#x00025; when
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e165.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>.</p><fig id="pone-0017764-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017764.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>How the possibility to contain transmission depends on the proportion
who fail to present early.</title><p>Transmission can be contained for values of
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e166.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> below the
curve, where <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e167.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the
proportion of primary household cases who fail to present early,
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e168.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> is the
household reproduction number when all infected households receive
antiviral drugs and the household reproduction number without antiviral
drugs is <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e169.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> for curve
(a) and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e170.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> for curve
(b).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.g005"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>Are antiviral drugs effective against the newly emerged virus strain?</title><p>The motivation to create a stockpile of antiviral drugs is based on their
demonstrated effectiveness against currently circulating influenza strains.
There is no guarantee that these drugs will be equally effective, or even
effective at all, against a newly emerged pandemic strain of influenza. Informed
decisions about the use of antiviral drugs in a pandemic require effectiveness
for reducing transmission to be established from incidence data collected early
in a pandemic. In preparation we need to know what data, and how much, are
required to establish effectiveness. Glass and Becker <xref rid="pone.0017764-Glass1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> consider this question by
estimating two specific parameters, one quantifying the effect on susceptibility
and the other the effect on infectivity. Here we look at establishing
effectiveness by comparing mean outbreak size in households that receive
antiviral drugs early and households that receive them late. We have to allow
for different household sizes. Households of size one provide no information for
our comparison and we restrict attention to households of sizes two, three and
four. The Australian census data indicate that the relative frequency of
households of size 2, 3 and 4 is about 50&#x00025;, 25&#x00025; and 25&#x00025;.
Allowing for size-biased sampling we expect to observe roughly an equal number
of outbreaks in households of size 2, 3 and 4. Accordingly, we assume that we
observe <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e171.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> outbreaks in households that receive antiviral drugs at
onset of symptoms in the primary household case in households of size 2, 3 and
4, making <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e172.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> households. In addition, we assume that we observe
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e173.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> outbreaks in households that receive antiviral drugs
late (two days after the onset of symptoms in the primary case) in households of
size 2, 3 and 4, giving observations on another <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e174.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> household
outbreaks.</p><p>An Alexander-Govern test statistic <xref rid="pone.0017764-Alexander1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref> is computed for the
comparison in households of a given size and values of these three test
statistics are then summed and the null hypothesis of no effect is rejected if
the sum exceeds the <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e175.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> percentile of the
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e176.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>distribution with three degrees of freedom.</p><p>The power curve corresponding to a given antiviral effect scenario was estimated
by simulating 500 data sets, applying the test to each data set and noting the
fraction that reject the hypothesis of equal mean outbreak sizes. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017764-g006">Figure 6</xref> shows the estimated
power curves for four antiviral effect scenarios similar to the ones considered
by Glass and Becker <xref rid="pone.0017764-Glass1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, which enables a comparison of results and
illustrates the findings. These scenarios are motivated by data on antiviral
effects for currently circulating influenza strains, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Glass1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. In the simulations we used
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e177.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> for the probability that an individual avoids being
infected by a given household infective, in the absence of antiviral drugs.</p><fig id="pone-0017764-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017764.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Power of a test to determine whether antiviral drugs are
effective.</title><p>Power of a test to compare the mean outbreak size in
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e178.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> households
who receive antiviral drugs early and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e179.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> households
who do not, for each of the household sizes 2, 3 and 4 (i.e.
observations on <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e180.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> household
outbreaks). A modified version of the Alexander-Govern test is used and
power is estimated by applying the test to each of 500 data sets for
each <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e181.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and each effect scenario. In curves (a), (b) and
(c) the simulations assume that antiviral drugs partially reduce
infectivity and their effect on susceptibility is to induce full,
partial and zero protection, respectively. Simulations for curve (d)
assume no effect on infectivity and a partial effect on
susceptibility.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.g006"/></fig><p>The antiviral effect on susceptibility is to reduce the probability of
transmission of an infection occurring during a contact by a factor
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e182.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> for a susceptible who is on antiviral drugs at the time.
The effect on infectivity depends on the time when the infective starts taking
the antiviral drug and is measured by the factor by which the area under the
infectiousness function is reduced (i.e. the potential to infect others is
reduced). Let <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e183.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> denote the factor by which the area under the
infectiousness function is reduced when the individual commences taking the drug
at onset of symptoms. The curves (a), (b) and (c) of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017764-g006">Figure 6</xref> show the power as
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e184.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> varies for the effect scenario with
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e185.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e186.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, 0.5 and 1,
respectively. Each point on the curve is obtained by simulating 500 data sets
and observing the fraction that reject the no-effect hypothesis when our
modified Alexander-Govern test is used. Curve (d) assumes the effect scenario
with <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e187.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, no effect on infectivity, and
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e188.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, partial effect on susceptibility.</p><p>When considering the results in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0017764-g006">Figure 6</xref> it is useful to keep in mind that monitoring infected
households for cases is labour-intensive. In practice, monitoring more than 300
household outbreaks during the busy early stages of a pandemic would be very
challenging. We would therefore like <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e189.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula>, the total number
of household outbreaks monitored, to be less than 300. Let us take a power of
80&#x00025; as a minimum requirement. Inspecting curves (a), (b) and (c), which
are generated by including a common effect on infectivity, illustrates that
observations on <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e190.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> household
outbreaks has a power of at least 80&#x00025; of detecting an antiviral effect if
there is also a moderate effect on susceptibility, but many more households are
needed if susceptibility is not reduced. Comparing curves (b) and (d), which are
generated by including a moderate effect on susceptibility, illustrates that a
total of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e191.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> household outbreaks are needed to detect an effect if
there is also a moderate effect on infectivity, but many more households are
needed if the effect on infectivity is weak.</p><p>The hope that a direct comparison of mean outbreak size for households would
require less data than a comparison based on specific parameters, as in <xref rid="pone.0017764-Glass1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, was not
realised. The two approaches indicate approximately the same data needs.
However, it is reassuring that a simple test based on minimal assumptions about
the nature of transmission in the community can detect an antiviral effect with
about the same amount of data.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our aim was to see whether antiviral drugs should be used to mitigate general
transmission following emergence of a future pandemic influenza strain. The main
conclusion is a strong recommendation that liberal and timely use of antiviral drugs
should be part of an attempt at local containment of transmission. The case for this
lies in the substantial benefits of successful containment and the fact that the
accumulated use of antiviral drugs over a period of successful containment is
modest, even when the immigration rate of infected arrivals is high. The recommended
plan for the attempt at containment must include abandoning prophylactic use of
antiviral drugs once there is strong empirical evidence that containment is unlikely
to succeed, because continued use of antiviral drugs to mitigate transmission when
early containment fails is likely to use a very sizable supply of antiviral drugs
with little benefit. The likelihood of successful containment should be evident by
the time 350 cases have been reported and we have data on 200 household
outbreaks.</p><p>Our basic first model acknowledges that the first few doses of antivirals dispensed
per case can be targeted more effectively than a similar number of additional doses.
That is, dispensing very many doses per cases is wasteful and likely to attract
justified criticisms and objections. A practical way to dispense doses to close
contacts only is to target household members of cases who present. Accordingly, our
second model considers transmission through a community with a household structure
and we considered delays in presentation. The conclusion that an attempt to contain
transmission uses relatively few antiviral doses continues to hold in this setting.
We also conclude that successful containment of transmission, if possible, requires
early presentation by the primary household case. We cannot wait for laboratory
confirmation of a strain-specific infection. The number of doses used by an attempt
to contain transmission is so small that one can afford, while a chance of
containing transmission remains, to be liberal in dispensing doses to household
members of any early presenter with clinical symptoms that are consistent with a
pandemic-strain infection.</p><p>Next we allowed for failure by a fraction of primary household cases to present soon
after onset of symptoms. The conclusion is that, even when antivirals are adequately
effective, containment is not possible if more than a modest fraction of primary
household cases fail to present early. In our illustration we required the
proportion of primary cases who fail to present early to be smaller than 20&#x00025;.
This 20&#x00025; includes asymptomatic cases, mildly-symptomatic cases who do not
bother to present and symptomatic cases unable to gain timely access to a health
service provider.</p><p>Finally, appropriate data must be collected at the start of the local outbreak to
estimate the initial reproduction number and to confirm that antiviral drugs do
reduce transmission of the new strain of influenza virus. It is concluded that we
can expect to detect an antiviral effect on transmission from data on
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e192.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> household outbreaks only if the antiviral drug has a
moderate effect on both susceptibility and infectivity (of the same order as for
currently circulating strains of influenza).</p><p>These conclusions are not consequences of the simplifying assumptions made in the
specific models of this paper. They rely primarily on the threshold result that
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e193.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> implies containment and this result holds under a very wide
range of community settings and disease characteristics. The likelihood of achieving
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e194.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> depends critically on the transmission characteristics of
the newly emerged disease and our ability to deliver antiviral drugs early enough to
affected households. With pandemic H1N1<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e195.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> we were close in some
locations. For example, in Western Australia, as in some other localities, most
early cases were imported infections indicating that <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e196.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> was maintained for a
substantial period, <xref rid="pone.0017764-Mercer2" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. With clear understanding and confidence that continued
liberal use of antiviral drugs is the best option at that stage it may have been
possible to sustain <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0017764.e197.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> longer.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0017764.s001"><label>Appendix S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Outline of the derivation of results for transmission in a community
of households.</bold>
</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0017764.s001.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>This work is supported by National Health and Medical Research Council grant
471436. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis,
decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0017764-Cheng1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Flu, what flu.</article-title>
<source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>746</fpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Lett1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lett</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Feds to stockpile antivirals as pandemic &#x0201c;speed
bump&#x0201d;.</article-title>
<source>Can Med Assoc J</source>
<volume>172</volume>
<fpage>1167</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15788559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Esveld1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Esveld</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Influenza as an issue on the agenda of policy makers and
government representatives. What can we do? What do we need?</article-title>
<source>Vaccine</source>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>6793</fpage>
<lpage>6795</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17167888</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Harrod1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harrod</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwyer</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Antivirals in the management of an influenza
pandemic.</article-title>
<source>Med J Aust</source>
<volume>185</volume>
<fpage>S58</fpage>
<lpage>S61</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17115954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Hayden1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayden</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Treanor</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Betts</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lobo</surname></name><name><surname>M Esinhart</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Safety and efficacy of the neuraminidase inhibitor gg167 in
experimental human influenza.</article-title>
<source>JAMA</source>
<volume>275</volume>
<fpage>295</fpage>
<lpage>299</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8544269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Hayden2"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayden</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Treanor</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritza</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lobo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Betts</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Use of the oral neuraminidase inhibitor oseltamivir in
experimental human influenza: randomized controlled trials for prevention
and treatment.</article-title>
<source>JAMA</source>
<volume>282</volume>
<fpage>1240</fpage>
<lpage>1246</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10517426</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Hayden3"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayden</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Belshe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Villanueva</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanno</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Management of influenza in households: a prospective, randomized
comparison of Oseltamivir treatment with or without postexposure
prophylaxis.</article-title>
<source>J Infect Dis</source>
<volume>189</volume>
<fpage>440</fpage>
<lpage>449</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14745701</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Moscona1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moscona</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Neuraminidase inhibitors for influenza.</article-title>
<source>N Engl J Med</source>
<volume>353</volume>
<fpage>1363</fpage>
<lpage>1373</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16192481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Welliver1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Welliver</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Monto</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Carewicz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Schatteman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Effectiveness of oseltamivir in preventing influenza in household
contacts.</article-title>
<source>JAMA</source>
<volume>285</volume>
<fpage>748</fpage>
<lpage>754</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11176912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-HaydenFGet1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayden FG et</surname><given-names>al</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Efficacy and safety of the neuraminidase inhibitor zanamivir in
the treatment of influenzavirus infections.</article-title>
<source>N Engl J Med</source>
<volume>337</volume>
<fpage>874</fpage>
<lpage>880</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9302301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Nicholson1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>FY</given-names></name><name><surname>Osterhaus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Trottier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Carewicz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Efficacy and safety of oseltamivir in treatment of acute
influenza: a randomised controlled trial.</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>
<volume>355</volume>
<fpage>1845</fpage>
<lpage>1850</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10866439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Treanor1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Treanor</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Efficacy and safety of the oral neuraminidase inhibitor
oseltamivir in treating acute influenza.</article-title>
<source>J Am Med Assoc</source>
<volume>283</volume>
<fpage>1016</fpage>
<lpage>1024</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Jefferson1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jefferson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Demicheli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivetti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietrantonj</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Antivirals for influenza in healthy adults: systematic
review.</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>
<volume>367</volume>
<fpage>303</fpage>
<lpage>313</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16443037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Jefferson2"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jefferson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Doshi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Mar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Neuraminidase inhibitors for preventing and treating influenza in
healthy adults: systematic review and meta-analysis.</article-title>
<source>BMJ</source>
<volume>339</volume>
<fpage>b5106</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19995812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Ferguson1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>DAT</given-names></name><name><surname>Cauchemez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Strategies for containing an emerging influenza pandemic in
southeast Asia.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>437</volume>
<fpage>209</fpage>
<lpage>214</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16079797</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Longini1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Longini</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nizam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ungchusak</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanshaoworakul</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Containing pandemic influenza at the source.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>309</volume>
<fpage>1083</fpage>
<lpage>1087</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16079251</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Barnes1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>The role of health care workers and antiviral drugs in the
control of pandemic influenza.</article-title>
<source>Math Biosci</source>
<volume>209</volume>
<fpage>403</fpage>
<lpage>416</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17433374</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-McCaw1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCaw</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>McVernon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Prophylaxis or treatment? Optimal use of an antiviral stockpile
during an influenza pandemic.</article-title>
<source>Math Biosci</source>
<volume>209</volume>
<fpage>336</fpage>
<lpage>360</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17416393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Cowling1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cowling</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>The effective reproduction number of pandemic influenza:
prospective estimation.</article-title>
<source>Epidemiology</source>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>842</fpage>
<lpage>846</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20805752</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Mercer1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mercer</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Effective reproduction numbers are commonly overestimated early
in a disease outbreak.</article-title>
<publisher-name>Statist Med</publisher-name>
<comment>in press</comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Caley1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Philp</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McCracken</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Quantifying social distancing arising from pandemic
influenza.</article-title>
<source>J R Soc Interface</source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>631</fpage>
<lpage>639</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17916550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Bartoszynsm1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartoszynsm</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1972</year>
<article-title>On a certain model of an epidemic.</article-title>
<source>Applications of Mathematics</source>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>139</fpage>
<lpage>151</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Becker1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>The effect of the household distribution on transmission and
control of highly infectious diseases.</article-title>
<source>Math Biosci</source>
<volume>127</volume>
<fpage>207</fpage>
<lpage>219</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7795319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Ball1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyne</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Optimal vaccination schemes for epidemics among a population of
households, with application to variola minor in Brazil.</article-title>
<source>Statist Meth Med Research</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>481</fpage>
<lpage>497</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Glass1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Estimating antiviral effectiveness against pandemic influenza
using household data.</article-title>
<source>J Roy Soc Interface</source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>695</fpage>
<lpage>703</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19064345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Bailey1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>NTJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1975</year>
<article-title>The mathematical theory of infectious diseases and its
applications.</article-title>
<publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Griffin</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Becker2"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1989</year>
<article-title>
<italic>Analysis of Infectious Disease Data.</italic>
</article-title>
<publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Chapman and Hall</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Alexander1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Govern</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>A new and simpler approximation for ANOVA under variance
heterogeneity.</article-title>
<source>J Educational Statist</source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>91</fpage>
<lpage>101</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Schneider1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Penfield</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Alexander and Govern's Approximation: Providing an
Alternative to ANOVA under Variance Heterogeneity.</article-title>
<source>J Experimental Education</source>
<volume>65</volume>
<fpage>271</fpage>
<lpage>286</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Becker3"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Clements</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Type and quantity of data needed for an early estimate of
transmissibility when an infectious disease emerges.</article-title>
<source>Euro Surveill</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>pii&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;19603</fpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0017764-Mercer2"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mercer</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Effective reproduction numbers are commonly overestimated early
in a disease outbreak.</article-title>
<publisher-name>Statist Med</publisher-name>
<comment>in press, DOI: 10.1002/sim.4174</comment>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>