<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Each year, certain European travelers return home with dengue (i.e. 1207 cases reported in 2012 reported in EU/EEA, 884 of which lived in the EU countries currently having 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> vectors (
 <xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control (ECDC), 2014</xref>) and the number increased over time (
 <xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr">Quam et al., 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0245" ref-type="bibr">Semenza et al., 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0250" ref-type="bibr">Tatem et al., 2006</xref>). If factor 2) is the main reason for preventing dengue outbreaks in Europe to date, this suggests outbreaks could occur anytime in the future when the infectious person/vector is in the suitable place at a suitable time, as was the case for chikungunya in Italy in 2007. If factor 3) is true, then the main concern for Europe is the potential introduction and establishment of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>, consistent with earlier studies (
 <xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">Liu-Helmersson et al., 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">Lambrechts et al., 2010</xref>). Madeira like Miami highlights the difference between DEP and actually having dengue epidemic transmission. This can be multifactorial. The temporal and geographic range of DEP is likely to be spatially and temporally broader than the actual areas of transmission events (over estimations). On the other hand, Nice had local dengue transmission reported as early as September 2010 (
 <xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">La Ruche et al., 2010</xref>), which may indicate that the 
 <italic>VC</italic> value was close to the threshold, and the Madeira and Japan outbreaks declined as 
 <italic>VC</italic> went below the threshold conditions (
 <xref rid="bb0210" ref-type="bibr">Quam et al., 2016</xref>). When examining the DEP for Nice, our estimate of 
 <italic>VC</italic> for 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> was very close to the threshold as expected: July and August were over while September was under the threshold during the recent decade as shown in 
 <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> (b). Therefore, we cannot ignore the dengue epidemic potential from 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> in the Southern and Mediterranean areas of Europe as agreed by other studies (
 <xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">Lambrechts et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control (ECDC), 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">Bouzid et al., 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0240" ref-type="bibr">Rogers et al., 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0290" ref-type="bibr">Whitehorn et al., 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">Benedict et al., 2007</xref>).
</p>
