<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<disp-quote content-type="editor-comment">
 <p>The work and manuscript have greatly improved, and the reviewers are satisfied with the approach of the model. However, there are some remaining issues about the way aspects of the model and the results are described that need to be addressed before acceptance, as outlined below:</p>
 <p>1) The relationship between the Zika epidemic in FSA vs. the rest of Brazil is still not very clear, although it is improved from before. For example, in the last paragraph of the Introduction it states that Zika peaked elsewhere in the country in 2016. That may be true for some locations, but data suggest otherwise for many of the most affected states. As the authors now note, Zika case surveillance changed substantially in 2016. Clearly higher case numbers are associated with this, but microcephaly numbers were much higher for many states as a result of the 2015 epidemics, so in fact many of the NE states in particular likely had much bigger epidemics in 2015, and FSA may be a very good representation of what happened in those states, not an anomaly as implied in the manuscript. The authors even found evidence of a 4-fold increase in reported FSA between 2015 and 2016. In my view, this is a very important finding and emphasizes how little we know about 2015, even in area with relatively strong surveillance.</p>
 <p>While we agree that it is not very helpful to speculate about exactly when the Zika epidemic peaked in different parts of Brazil, we think the overall message is still misleading – it currently appears to suggest that the epidemic in FSA was earlier than the rest of the country when the quality of surveillance in 2015 is probably not good enough to make such conclusions. A more appropriate message could be that detailed analysis of FSA indicated a large epidemic in 2015, which could possibly have occurred in other places although this was not picked up by the limited surveillance at that time.</p>
</disp-quote>
