<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mathematical models have been an essential tool to analyze experimental data to assess viral infection dynamics. They have allowed the quantification of viral kinetics and identification of potential antiviral therapies (reviewed in [
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]). These virus dynamics models are usually based on systems of ordinary differential equations (ODE) describing the change in concentrations of target and infected cells, as well as the viral load over time. The earliest models, including the so-called standard model of virus dynamics [
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], concentrated on cell-free transmission describing the spread of infection by a contact process between virions and target cells [
 <xref rid="B11-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Mathematically, this transmission was formulated by simple mass-action kinetics. While these models provided first estimates of viral infection kinetics and cellular turnover dynamics, they ignored the process of cell-to-cell transmission. With increasing awareness of the importance of cell-to-cell transmission for infection dynamics, revised models appeared that additionally accounted for this transmission mode by extending the standard model of virus dynamics [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. These new models considered different specific aspects of cell-associated transmission, including the possibility to transfer multiple viral strains simultaneously [
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], as well as considering a time-delay for viral production [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. However, all these models described cell-to-cell transmission by allowing target cells to get infected proportional to the concentration of infected cells and assumed that target and infected cells are well mixed. This assumption is especially violated for viral spread among stationary cells, e.g., within solid tissue environments. As the infection progresses, infected cells successively become surrounded by other infected cells, hindering cells in the center of infected foci from contributing to cell-to-cell transmission. Such foci of infected cells have been observed, for example, in HCV-infected liver tissue [
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Thus, previous models relying on the mass-action assumption overestimate the fraction of infected cells contributing to cell-to-cell transmission and lead to an inappropriate quantification of the infection dynamics. There have been several approaches to improve these quantifications for various pathogens by using probabilistic [
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and spatially explicit modeling frameworks, such as agent-based models [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-10-00200" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. However, especially the latter approach is difficult to be directly fit to experimental data. Therefore, finding an extension for the standard model of virus dynamics that appropriately accounts for cell-to-cell transmission would help to improve current analyses of viral spread.
</p>
