<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Beside viruses circulating in livestock, wildlife has the potential to be a large reservoir of unknown zoonotic viruses. Hunting, trading, preparing, and consuming so-called “bushmeat” is one of the routes by which novel viruses can be introduced into the human population (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Karesh and Noble, 2009</xref>). It may be difficult to disentangle foodborne infection from direct zoonotic exposure, but it is important to consider local practices before ruling out food as a source of human infection. A special example are the occasional introductions of Nipah viruses from bats into humans through contamination of date palm sap which is collected in open containers to which bats that harbor these viruses have access (
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">Rahman et al., 2012</xref>). Not proven but certainly interesting is the practice of drinking unprocessed camel urine which may contain MERS coronavirus, a practice that came to light during the investigations into sources of MERS coronavirus infection in humans (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Funk et al., 2016</xref>). Even if limited in scale, small foodborne infections, originating from human-wildlife interaction, constitute as many incidents potentially pushing wildlife viruses to become human-to-human transmissible (
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">Wolfe et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Islam et al., 2016</xref>). In the cases of Monkeypox and Nipah this only led to small epidemics, but when the virus is well adapted to spread from human to human this can lead to larger outbreaks, as seen during the Ebola crisis in 2015 (
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">Wolfe et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Mann et al., 2015</xref>). Continuing deforestation, increasing population and continued trade of bushmeat brings more humans in contact with wildlife and increases the risk of zoonosis (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Karesh and Noble, 2009</xref>). Urbanization and globalization of travel and trade provides ample and increasing opportunity for further spread. Therefore, even anecdotal zoonotic introductions may constitute a public health risk, and ideally should be investigated in conjunction with the animals these humans were exposed to. As the ability to spread between humans is a key property for successful further spread, enhancing the capacity to investigate clusters of disease (in humans and animals) is important (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">McCloskey et al., 2014</xref>).
</p>
