<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>IVIG is a supportive therapy prepared from pooled plasma of healthy humans. IVIG is traditionally used as replacement therapy in patients with humoral immune deficiencies [
 <xref rid="B190-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">190</xref>]. Unlike convalescent plasma, IVIG does not contain a SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibody [
 <xref rid="B191-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">191</xref>]. IVIG has various mechanisms of action including interference with B-cell antigen presentation, immune-modulation and immune substitution [
 <xref rid="B192-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">192</xref>]. During the SARS outbreak, IVIG was used as a therapy, but evidence supporting its effectiveness is inconclusive [
 <xref rid="B193-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">193</xref>]. Despite some reports on the use of IVIG in MERS infection, there is not any evidence of anti-MERS activity [
 <xref rid="B194-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">194</xref>]. As these antibodies are administered intravenously, they can cause renal failure or thrombosis in MERS patients [
 <xref rid="B195-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">195</xref>]. For COVID-19, Shi et al. reported successful treatment of a confirmed patient with advanced respiratory failure, shock and persistent diarrhea, using intensive plasma exchange (PE) and IVIG transfusion [
 <xref rid="B196-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">196</xref>]. They emphasized the importance of early initiation of PE treatment and IVIG to avoid progression to ARDS and multi-organ failure. Similarly, a multicenter retrospective cohort study of 325 critically unwell adult COVID-19 patients in China who were exposed to IVIG, demonstrated that although early administration improved their prognosis, mortality at 28-days and 60-days was not improved and total duration of disease was longer [
 <xref rid="B197-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">197</xref>]. In a retrospective study of 58 severe or critical COVID-19 patients in Wuhan treated with IVIG, administration of IVIG within 48 h of admission to ICU improved prognosis by reducing mechanical ventilation requirement and length of stay [
 <xref rid="B198-ijms-21-05559" ref-type="bibr">198</xref>]. It is important to note that all of these studies were carried out in the context of small sample size and multiple drug treatments; thus, the efficacy and the associated adverse effects of IVIG remain unclear. In order to evaluate the efficacy and safety of IVIG therapy in patients with severe or critical COVID-19, a single-center randomized, open-label, controlled study has been registered (NCT04261426). Like other proposed treatments for COVID-19, IVIG is still unlicensed and insufficient evidence exists to support its use in the management of COVID-19.
</p>
