<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>By the incorporation of reverse transcription step, real-time PCR can be combined with the conventional reverse transcription PCR (RT-PCR) to form reverse transcription quantitative real-time PCR (RT-qPCR). RT-qPCR has a number of advantages over the conventional RT-PCR technique, including reduction of contamination, possibility of quantifying the amplicons, and quick assay time since there are no post-PCR processing activities [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. As a result, RT-qPCR is widely deployed for the detection and quantification of several RNA viruses in clinical specimens, including ZIKV, Ebola virus, coronavirus, HCV, respiratory syncytial virus (RSV), dengue virus, HIV-1, and influenza A virus [
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>–
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>–
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Recently, Corman et al. [
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] developed RT-qPCR for the detection of SARS-CoV-2. The assay targeted envelope protein (E) gene and RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp) gene of SARS-CoV-2. High LoDs of 5.2 copies/reaction for E-gene and 3.8 copies/reaction for RdRp gene were demonstrated and no cross-reaction with other coronaviruses, suggesting the usefulness of the method for sensitive and specific diagnosis of COVID-19. The RT-qPCR assay (Quanty ZEBOV FAST assay) was evaluated for the detection of Ebola virus in clinical samples. CLONIT Srl (Italy) developed the assay during outbreak of Ebola in Sierra Leone, and it had overall sensitivity of 100% and specificity of 98.63%, compared to RealStar® Filovirus Screen RT-qPCR Kit 1.0 (Altona Diagnostics) [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Gueudin et al. [
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>] used RT-qPCR for diagnosis and monitoring of HIV-1 group O infection with LoD of 40 copies/ml and specificity of 100%. The method was applied for ZIKV detection in human serum and urine, and it had LoDs of 2.5 PFU/ml and 250 PFU/ml in urine and serum, respectively [
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Júnior et al. [
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>] used RT-qPCR for the detection of respiratory viruses in outpatients with acute respiratory infection. They also compared the performance of RT-qPCR with indirect immunofluorescence assay (IFA). Accordingly, RT-qPCR managed to detect viral pathogens in 88 (88/162) nasopharyngeal aspirates, but IFA detected viral pathogens in only 33 (33/162) specimens. The data indicated that the use of RT-qPCR increased the viral detection by 33.9%. Today, several real-time RT-PCR kits are available commercially. For example, real-time-qPCR test developed by Cepheid AB (Sunnyvale, CA, USA) is commercially available for the qualitative detection of Ebola virus in EDTA venous whole blood or buccal swabs. The assay targets viral nucleoprotein and glycoprotein genes of Ebola Zaire virus. The assay has a LoD of 82 RNA copies/reaction with turnaround time of 98 minutes. Simplexa™ Dengue RT-PCR assay developed by Focus Diagnostics (Cypress, CA, USA) is a commercial kit for detection and typing of dengue virus serotypes 1, 2, 3, and 4 in human serum. The assay targets four serotype specific regions, namely, dengue 1 (nonstructural (NS)5 gene ), dengue 2 (NS3 gene), dengue 3 (NS5 gene), and dengue 4 (capsid gene). The LoDs of the assay are 0.16 PFU/ml, 2.0 PFU/ml, 0.2 PFU/ml, and 0.2 PFU/ml for dengue 1, dengue 2, dengue 3, and dengue 4, respectively. Real-Star Zika Virus RT-PCR kit 1.0 is available, developed by Altona Diagnostics (Hamburg, Germany), for qualitative detection of ZIKV specific RNA in human serum or urine. The LoD of the assay is 0.61 RNA copies/
 <italic>μ</italic>l. Abbott RealTime HCV quantitative assay developed by Abbott Laboratories (Rungis, France) is commercially available for HCV RNA quantitation in human serum and plasma. The target sequence for the assay is in the highly conserved 5′untranslated region (UTR) of the HCV genome. The LoD of the assay is 12 IU/ml when testing human plasma or serum. COBAS TaqMan HIV-1 test developed by Roche Diagnostics (Branchburg, USA) is commercially available for the quantitation of HIV-1 in human plasma. The real-time RT-PCR targets two highly conserved regions of the HIV-1 genome, namely, gag and long terminal repeat (LTR). The assay has LoD of 20 HIV-1 RNA copies/ml. Recently, several developers of diagnostic tests have developed real-time RT-PCR kits for COVID-19, and they are now seeking marking and emergency use authorization (EUA) from regulatory agencies. For example, Co-Diagnostics (Salt Lake City, USA) has developed real-time RT-PCR kit (Logix Smart COVID-19 test) for qualitative detection of nucleic acid from the SARS-CoV-2 in lower respiratory samples (e.g., bronchoalveolar lavage, sputum, and tracheal aspirate) and upper respiratory specimens (e.g., oropharyngeal swabs, nasal swabs, and nasopharyngeal swabs). The kit has received EUA from United States Food and Drug Administration (US FDA) and CE-IVD marking approval. The assay targets RdRp gene of SARS-CoV-2. The LoD of the assay is 9.35 × 10
 <sup>3</sup> RNA copies/ml with thermocycler run time of 63–90 minutes, depending on PCR equipment. US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) has developed three real-time RT-PCR assays for the detection of SARS-CoV-2 genetic material in upper and lower respiratory specimens, and this panel has been granted EUA by the US FDA. CDC real-time RT-PCR panel targets 3 candidate regions of nucleocapsid (N) gene of SARS-CoV-2. The LoD of all assays are 5 RNA copies/reaction. The Agency for Science, Technology and Research (A∗STAR) and Tan Tock Seng Hospital (TTSH) (Singapore) have developed real-time RT-PCR test (Fortitude Kit 2.0) for qualitative detection of SARS-CoV-2 genetic material in oropharyngeal swabs. The kit has received Singapore Health Sciences Authority's (HAS) provisional authorization for clinical use. The US FDA has not yet approved the kit for clinical use. The assay has LoD of 1000 RNA copies/ml in in oropharyngeal swabs. The kit developers have not yet disclosed the target gene for this assay. BGI Group (Beijing, China) has developed real-time fluorescent RT-PCR kit for the qualitative detection of nucleic acid from the SARS-CoV-2 in throat (oropharyngeal) swabs, nasal swabs, nasopharyngeal swabs, and other respiratory specimens. The company has received an EUA form the China's National Medical Product Administration and the US FDA for its test kit. The assay targets open reading frame 1a and b (ORF1ab) genes of SARS-CoV-2. It has LoD of 150 copies/ml in throat samples with turnaround time of 4 hours. RADI COVID-19 Real-Time PCR kit developed by KH Medical (Korea) has CE-IVD marking and is used for qualitative detection of SARS-CoV-2 in human nasal swab or sputum sample. The assay targets two genes, namely, spike protein (S) gene and RdRP gene of SARS-CoV-2. It has LoD of 0.66 copies/
 <italic>μ</italic>l with turnaround time of 80 minutes.
</p>
