<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par64">Efficient 
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic> assembly requires an obligatory sequential cleavage at the C-prM junction by NS2B-NS3 protease at the C cytosolic side and then by cellular signalase at the ER lumen side. The coordinated processing releases the mature C protein required for encapsidation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>]. In addition to enabling the processing of C, NS3 appears to have other roles during viral assembly. As Pijlman and collaborators demonstrated, KUN WNV NS3 mutants with defects for C processing and RNA replication can be rescued in 
 <italic>trans</italic>, while mutations affecting packaging cannot be complemented with functional NS3 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>]. The authors proposed a model in which newly synthesized NS3 associates with the progeny vRNA template at the same time that it interacts with other viral (or host) proteins. This viral RNP complex is responsible for the re-localization of vRNA to the sites of encapsidation/assembly [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>]. Though proposed more than a decade ago, this hypothesis remains valid particularly in light of the new function discovered for NS2A described in the previous section. NS3 is also required for the packaging of YFV vRNA because a single mutation (Trp-349-Ala) in the helicase domain resulted in less infectious virus release without affecting the expression of viral proteins, vRNA replication and release of subviral particles lacking C protein and vRNA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>]. Interestingly, 
 <italic>trans</italic> complementation with the NS3 mutants S138A or R461Q in which the protease and the helicase are inactive, respectively, rescued virus production, suggesting that the function of NS3 during virus assembly is independent from its known enzymatic activity. Lastly, structural studies suggest that binding of NS3 to specific 5′ UTR sequences could function as a molecular signature to guide newly synthesized vRNA out of the replication complex [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>]. Nevertheless, biophysical and biochemical evidence to support this hypothesis is lacking.
</p>
