<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As biosensors provide detailed information on the binding affinity of the biomolecules to a given substrate and their associated kinetics, their use in drug discovery applications is ubiquitous. In addition, as the design of a given transducer can be tuned according to its intended application, different types of biosensors can be implemented in various levels of the drug discovery process to enhance the discovery of a potential vaccine.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref171">171</xref>
 </sup> In addition, as viruses evolve,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref172">172</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref173">173</xref>
 </sup> the need for a new drug is also inevitable, and it is in this context where sensing technologies can provide a solid backbone to bear the burden of a timely discovery of new drugs to contain an outbreak of a disease. In the drug discovery process, the research and development phase of the drug discovery process normally takes 3–5 years, preclinical studies take 1–2 years, and clinical trials take 2–3 years, followed by review and approvals which take over 6 months to 1 year.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref174">174</xref>
 </sup> Time of these stages can significantly be reduced with the use of advanced bio/chemical sensing technologies. We provide key attributes of biosensors specific to the drug discovery stages that can possibly assist in speeding up the drug discovery process:
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>Ligand fishing: Identification of potential drugs from natural resources such as the plant extracts is a critical, challenging, and time-consuming task in the process of drug discovery.
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref175">175</xref>
    </sup> For example, discovery of a bioactive constituent from traditional Indian and Chinese medicines has contributed to their well-known therapeutic effects in viral diseases, including for SARS CoV2-virus.
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref176">176</xref>−
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref178">178</xref>
    </sup> Identification of such bioactive compounds has largely been dependent on techniques such as ultrafiltration,
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref179">179</xref>
    </sup> liquid chromatography (LC),
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref180">180</xref>
    </sup> and mass spectrometry (MS),
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref181">181</xref>
    </sup> known as ligand fishing. It is in this context that all biosensors represent themselves as a useful tool for the discovery of bioactive compounds from a complex mixture of natural products while providing enhanced efficiency and reduced sample preparation time at a low cost as compared to the existing techniques such as the LS and MS. While biosensors combined with the nanomaterials have also shown high selectivity toward the targets, sensors for screening active compounds from natural products have not been reported so far. However, by combining biosensors with microfluidics, it is possible to develop such tools due to common procedures such as incubation,
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref182">182</xref>
    </sup> washing,
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref183">183</xref>
    </sup> mixing,
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref184">184</xref>
    </sup> and compartmentalization
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref185">185</xref>
    </sup> of the solution being easily achieved by microfluidics systems.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>High-throughput screening of candidate drug compounds: In contrast to the extraction of compounds from the natural products, in laboratory synthesis of chemical compounds for possible use as drugs, the ability of the compound to affect the identified target using biosensors can be tested. Here high-throughput array-based sensing technologies such as the FETs
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref186">186</xref>−
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref188">188</xref>
    </sup> surface plasmon sensors
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref189">189</xref>,
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref190">190</xref>
    </sup> have an advantage over the conventional techniques of LS and MS where effectively more than 10,000 compounds can be screened in 1 week as compared to 3–4 years of testing. In addition to compound screening, cross-reactive activity of the candidate compounds,
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref191">191</xref>
    </sup> to check their interfere with other homologous targets, could also be tested using such sensing platforms. An example of a high-throughput biosensor chip consisting 9000 electrodes is shown in 
    <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure 
     <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>
    </xref>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Affinity and kinetics: Affinity and kinetics information on a compound is vital in understanding its use as a potential drug.
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref192">192</xref>
    </sup> For instance, biosensors can closely be made to perform experiments based on the bioinformatics modeling algorithms.
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref193">193</xref>
    </sup> In preclinical trials, sensing platforms can assist in evaluating the binding affinity and kinetics of the antibodies or to assess the developed vaccine to the target protein or loci on the virus. Statistically relevant information on affinity and kinetics can also be generated in a short duration of time with use of multiplexed biosensing arrays.
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref194">194</xref>
    </sup>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Monitoring chemical parameters in the pharmaceutical production process: The production of drugs operates in a stringent safety, sterility, and precision-oriented environment. Therefore, use of biosensors in monitoring chemical parameters such as pH, temperature, and enzymatic activity in real time during the process of drug production is significant to improve the quality of the drugs.
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref195">195</xref>
    </sup> Other bio/chemical sensors which measure gases such as oxygen and concentration of byproducts in the process are also useful in the identification of physical and chemical errors in the production line of the drugs.
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref196">196</xref>
    </sup> A significant challenge and opportunity for some of the advanced biosensors is to essentially integrate themselves in the production line in the form of a sensor network. Further, with integration of machine learning programs, data from these biosensors could potentially be used to improve the delivery time of drugs in large quantities required during pandemics.
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref197">197</xref>
    </sup>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Bedside drug monitoring in hospitals: Another significant opportunity for biosensors in pandemics is in drug analysis by biomedical systems equipped along the bedside in the hospitals.
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref198">198</xref>,
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref199">199</xref>
    </sup> An appropriate quantity of drug injected in the body of the patient can significantly improve the recovery time of the patient. Most often, it is essential to monitor various parameters of the body such as the blood pressure, heart rate, temperature, oxygen concentration, and other small molecules in the blood profile.
    <sup>
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref200">200</xref>
    </sup> Establishing a real-time relationship between concentrations of aforementioned parameters is essential, and this is where biosensors, if combined with the internet of technology, can effectively be used for the measurement and analysis of drugs in real time.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
