<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F4" position="float">
 <label>FIGURE 4</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Prophylactic efficacy of AAV expressed nanobodies in a mouse challenge model of pandemic H1N1 CA/09. 
   <bold>(A)</bold> Total nanobody-Fc in serum was measured by ELISA in samples taken 39 days after IM injection of AAV vectors pre-challenge with CA/09. Comparisons are shown in brackets (
   <italic>*p</italic> &lt; 0.05). BALB/c mice were then infected intranasally with 21 MLD
   <sub>50</sub> (mouse lethal dose) of A/California/07/2009(H1N1)pdm09 42 days post-AAV IM injection. Survival 
   <bold>(B)</bold> and weight loss 
   <bold>(C)</bold> were monitored for 14 days. 
   <bold>(D)</bold> Naturally induced immune response in mice pre- and post-CA/09 challenge was assessed via Hemagglutination Inhibition (HAI) titers 39 days post-AAV administration and 3 days pre-challenge (•), and from post-challenge terminals bleeds (∘). HAI titers are expressed as the highest dilution of serum that inhibited hemagglutination completely. Points below the solid line represent no HAI activity. For panels 
   <bold>(A–D)</bold>, each point represents an individual mouse. Mean and standard error of eight recipient mice per treatment is shown in panels 
   <bold>(A)</bold> and 
   <bold>(C,D)</bold>. 
   <bold>(E)</bold> Binding and activation of mouse FcγRIV effector cells in mice given nanobody-Fc fusions delivered by AAV. Terminal mouse sera were tested for ADCC activity via activation of mFcγRIV from representative mice after IM injection of 1.0 × 10
   <sup>11</sup> vg AAV-R1a-B6-mIgG1, AAV-R1a-B6-mIgG2a, AAV-R1a-B6, and AAV-cAb1-mIgG2a. Mice were culled 14 days post-challenge for R1a-B6-mIgG1, R1a-B6-mIgG2a, and R1a-B6, and 6 days post-challenge for cAb1-mIgG2a. Activity is shown in relative luminescence units (RLU) against dilution of mouse sera containing nanobody Fc fusions expressed 
   <italic>in vivo</italic>. Each point is shown as the mean and standard error of three replicates. 
   <bold>(F)</bold> Representative histological lung sections from mice that received AAV encoding R1a-B6-mIgG1, R1a-B6-mIgG2a, R1a-B6, cAb1-mIgG2a, and PBS (untreated) post-infection with CA/09. Lungs were harvested from mice as they exited the study at the days indicated and stained with Hematoxylin and Eosin (H&amp;E). Arrows represent thickening of the alveolar walls. *Represents Mouse 3 (
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="DS1">Supplementary Figure 2</xref> and 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="DS1">Supplementary Table 2</xref>), the only mouse that survived the CA/09 challenge from the R1a-B6 group. Scale bar = 100 μm.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="fimmu-11-00627-g004" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
