<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0001">
 <label>Table 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Viral screening spectra in the three participant centres.</p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text id="alt0001">Table 1</alt-text>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th valign="top">Centre</th>
    <th valign="top">Multiplex Technique</th>
    <th valign="top">Viral screening</th>
    <th valign="top">patients</th>
    <th valign="top">Age range (years)</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top">A</td>
    <td valign="top">
     <italic>Multi Well System MWS R-GENE</italic>® 
     <italic>bioMerieux</italic>
     <xref rid="tb1fn1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>
    </td>
    <td valign="top">
     <italic>ADV, EV, RV, IVA, IVB, PIV 1-4, RSV A and B, HCoV 229E, NL63 and OC43, and HKU1, HMPV, HBoV</italic>
    </td>
    <td valign="top">
     <italic>5</italic>
    </td>
    <td valign="top">
     <italic>6-43 3 childs 2 adults</italic>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top">B</td>
    <td valign="top">
     <italic>RespiFinder</italic>® 
     <italic>SMART 22 Fast v2.0, PathoFinder</italic>
     <xref rid="tb1fn2" ref-type="table-fn">⁎⁎</xref>
    </td>
    <td valign="top">
     <italic>ADV, EV/RV, IVA, IVA(H1N1) vpdm09, IVB, PIV1-4, RSV A and B, HCoV 229E, OC43, NL63 and HKU1, HMPV, HBoV</italic>
    </td>
    <td valign="top">
     <italic>13</italic>
    </td>
    <td valign="top">
     <italic>2-29 2 childs 11 adults</italic>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="top">C</td>
    <td valign="top">
     <italic>Anyplex II RV16</italic>® 
     <italic>Seegene</italic>
     <xref rid="tb1fn3" ref-type="table-fn">⁎⁎⁎</xref>
    </td>
    <td valign="top">
     <italic>ADV, EV, RV, IVA,IVB, PIV1-4, RSV A and B, HCoV229E, OC43, NL63, HMPV, HBoV</italic>
    </td>
    <td valign="top">
     <italic>12</italic>
    </td>
    <td valign="top">
     <italic>12 adults</italic>
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn id="spara002">
   <p>ADV: Adenovirus, EV: Enterovirus, RV: Rhinovirus, IVA: Influenza virus, IVB: Influenza virus B, PIV: Parainfluenza virus, RSV: Respiratory syncytial virus, HCoV: Human Coronavirus, HMPV: Human Metapneumovirus, HBoV: Human Bocavirus</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="spara003">
   <p>The multiplex technique used by centres A and C detected rhinoviruses and enteroviruses separately although centre B's multiplex technique could not differentiate rhinoviruses from enteroviruses, which gave a combined RV/EV result.</p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn id="tb1fn1">
   <label>⁎</label>
   <p id="notep0004">
    <italic>Paba P, Farchi F, Mortati E, Ciccozzi M, Piperno M, Perno CF, et al. Screening of respiratory pathogens by Respiratory Multi Well System (MWS) r-gene assay in hospitalized patients. The new microbiologica. 2014;37:231-6.</italic>*
    <italic>Resa C, Bertrand M, Bes J, Vignoles M, Magro S, Barranger C, et al. Respiratory multi well system (mws) r-gene™: Simultaneous detection of infectious agents involved in respiratory diseases. France2010.</italic>
   </p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn id="tb1fn2">
   <label>⁎⁎</label>
   <p id="notep0005">
    <italic>Dabisch-Ruthe M, Vollmer T, Adams O, Knabbe C, Dreier J. Comparison of three multiplex PCR assays for the detection of respiratory viral infections: evaluation of xTAG respiratory virus panel fast assay, RespiFinder 19 assay and RespiFinder SMART 22 assay. BMC infectious diseases. 2012;12:163.</italic>
   </p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn id="tb1fn3">
   <label>⁎⁎⁎</label>
   <p id="notep0006">
    <italic>Kim HK, Oh SH, Yun KA, Sung H, Kim MN. Comparison of Anyplex II RV16 with the xTAG respiratory viral panel and Seeplex RV15 for detection of respiratory viruses. Journal of clinical microbiology. 2013;51:1137-41.</italic>
   </p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
