<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Vertical transmission is particularly frequent in plant viruses, as more than 25% of all known species are vertically transmitted through seeds (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Seed transmission is highly relevant for plant virus epidemiology (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Seed infection provides the virus with the means to persist for long periods of time (years) when hosts and/or vectors are not available, as many seed-transmitted viruses can survive within the seed as long as it remains viable (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). This facilitates virus emergence and reemergence in plant populations (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Seed transmission also allows for long-distance dissemination of the virus (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Indeed, evidence shows that bird dispersion and human trade of infected seeds have allowed cross-continental jumps of some plant viruses (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Finally, seed transmission represents an important source of primary inoculum for many viruses with this mode of transmission, which are disseminated afterwards via insect vectors. In this way, plant viruses initiate damaging epidemics even at very low seed transmission rates (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Although the central role of vertical transmission in plant virus epidemiology is widely acknowledged, very little is known regarding which host and virus traits interact to determine the efficiency of seed transmission (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>).
</p>
