<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Baltimore)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">MEDI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0025-7974</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1536-5964</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28072684</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">MD-D-16-04055</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000005321</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">05321</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>4500</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Research Article</subject><subject>Observational Study</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Assessment of hepatocellular carcinoma risk based on peg-interferon plus ribavirin treatment experience in this new era of highly effective oral antiviral drugs</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Seung Ho</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Young-Joo</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"><sup>&#x02217;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>Jun Young</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Jin-Woo</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Kinoshita.</surname><given-names>Akiyoshi</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Department of Internal Medicine, Inha University Hospital, Inha University School of Medicine, Incheon, South Korea.</aff><author-notes id="cor1"><corresp><label>&#x02217;</label>Correspondence: Young-Joo Jin, Department of Internal Medicine, Inha University Hospital, Inha University School of Medicine, 27 Inhang-ro, Jung-gu, Incheon 400-711, South Korea (e-mail: <email>jyj412@hanmail.net</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>96</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e5321</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>12</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2017 the Author(s). Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-Non Commercial-No Derivatives License 4.0 (CCBY-NC-ND), where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially without permission from the journal. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="medi-96-e5321.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>In this new era of highly effective oral antiviral drugs for chronic hepatitis C virus (HCV), indications for antiviral treatment may be extendable. This study undertaken to identify suitable candidates for peg-interferon plus ribavirin (PEG-IFN/RBV) treatment by evaluating hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) risk in patients with chronic HCV treated or not with PEG-IFN/RBV.</p><p>This large-scale retrospective study was conducted on 1176 patients with chronic HCV without a history of HCC (treatment group [n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;489] and no-treatment group [n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;687]). In the treatment group, patients treated with PEG-IFN/RBV were dichotomized based on the achievement of sustained virologic response (SVR) into SVR (+) and SVR (&#x02212;) groups.</p><p>Median follow-up for all study subjects was 31 months (range 6&#x02013;144 months). Three-year cumulative HCC development rates in the SVR (+) (1.1%) and SVR (&#x02212;) (8.6%) subgroups were significantly lower than in the no-treatment group (13.5%) (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01 and <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01, respectively). In all study subjects, presence of cirrhosis (hazard ratio [HR], 9.92, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01), age (HR 1.03, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01), SVR (&#x02212;) (HR 7.02, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01), and no-treatment (HR 6.76, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01) were found to be independent risk factors of HCC development. In the treatment group, age, the presence of cirrhosis, and SVR (&#x02212;) were predictors of HCC development. In the no-treatment group, age, male, and the presence of cirrhosis were independent predictors for HCC development.</p><p>HCC risk increased in patients with chronic HCV with older age, cirrhosis, SVR (&#x02212;) after PEG-IFN/RBV treatment, and no PEG-IFN/RBV treatment. Active antiviral therapy based on highly effective oral drugs needs to be considered in these patients.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords</title><kwd>age</kwd><kwd>chronic hepatitis C</kwd><kwd>hepatocellular carcinoma</kwd><kwd>liver cirrhosis</kwd><kwd>sustained virologic response</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Hepatitis C virus (HCV) has infected about 180 million population worldwide and is the major cause of liver cirrhosis (LC) and hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC).<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup> Since these diseases are associated with high mortality in the presence of chronic HCV (CHC), antiviral therapy for HCV infection could theoretically improve prognosis by preventing the development of LC or HCC. However, a substantial proportion of patients with CHC do not receive antiviral therapy.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> Moreover, previous peg-interferon plus ribavirin (PEG-IFN/RBV)-based regimens are less effective and have higher side effect rates than direct-acting antiviral (DAA) agents and are contraindicated in patients prone to severe adverse events.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup></p><p>Although previous studies have reported that the achievement of sustained virologic response (SVR) on antiviral therapy reduces the risk of HCC development, the majority were limited due to use of a conventional IFN regimen.<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup> After the introduction of the more effective PEG-IFN/RBV therapy, several studies reported that failure to achieve SVR on PEG-IFN/RBV therapy, an advanced age, and LC were associated with unfavorable long-term outcomes or HCC development.<sup>[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</sup> However, unfortunately, these studies were limited to bridging fibrosis or patients with LC<sup>[<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</sup> and did not include patients who did not receive antiviral therapy.<sup>[<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</sup></p><p>The paradigm for antiviral therapy in patients with CHC has rapidly changed from PEG-IFN-based therapy to DAA agents. After the FDA approved of DAAs in 2011, new drugs, such as sofosbuvir and daclatasvir/asunaprevir, were recently approved with much higher SVR rates and lower adverse event rates than PEG-IFN/RBV.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup> Given that SVR rate improvement may translate into improved long-term prognosis in patients with CHC, active antiviral therapy with these new drugs needs to be applied to as many patients as possible. To date, however, selection criteria for treatment with these new drugs have not been fully determined.</p><p>In the present study, therefore, we assessed the risk factors of HCC development in patients with CHC who had been treated with PEG-IFN/RBV or not, and sought to identify candidates for active anti-HCV therapy based on these risk factors in the new era of highly effective oral anti-HCV drugs.</p></sec><sec><label>2</label><title>Patients and methods</title><sec><label>2.1</label><title>Study population</title><p>A total of 2578 patients registered at our institution between January 2004 and December 2013 were initially positive for HCV antibody and had no other chronic liver disease, such as hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection, alcoholic liver disease, autoimmune hepatitis, primary biliary cirrhosis, or Wilson disease (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Anti-HCV and HCV RNA levels were positive for more than 6 months in all patients. Of these 2578 patients, those who did not undergo an examination of HCV RNA (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;445), negative for HCV RNA (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;514), follow-up &#x0003c;6 months, and those with a history of HCC or another malignancy (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;67) were excluded. Of the remaining 1292 patients, 81 treated with a conventional interferon (IFN)-based therapy and 35 with a history of a new drugs (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;35) were also excluded. Patients treated with PEG-IFN/RBV after conventional IFN-based therapy were enrolled in the study. Accordingly, 1176 patients were finally enrolled in this study, and their database records were retrospectively analyzed.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Study subjects. A total of 1176 patients were enrolled in the present study. Of these, 306 and 183 patients were allocated to SVR (+) and SVR (&#x02212;) subgroups, respectively, and 687 patients were allocated to the no-treatment group. SVR = sustained virologic response.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="medi-96-e5321-g001"/></fig><p>The 1176 study subjects were allocated to a no-treatment group (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;687) or a treatment group (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;489). Patients in the treatment group were treated with PEG-IFN (alfa-2a or alfa-2b)/RBV for 24 or 48 weeks according to HCV genotype, and allocated to 1 of 2 subgroups dependent on the achievement of SVR (the SVR (+) and SVR (&#x02212;) subgroups) after PEG-IFN/RBV treatment (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). The study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Inha University Hospital, Incheon, South Korea (approval number: INHAUH 2015-11-018).</p></sec><sec><label>2.2</label><title>Recruitment of clinical database</title><p>The following clinical data were obtained at diagnosis of CHC infection in no-treatment group and at time of antiviral therapy in treatment group; age (year), gender, body mass index (BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup>), complete blood count, serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT, IU/L) level, prothrombin time (international normalized ratio), serum albumin or bilirubin, serum alpha-fetoprotein (AFP) level, Child-Turcotte-Pugh classification, hepatitis B surface antigen or antibody, HCV RNA (IU/mL), HCV genotype, and presence of LC. LC was clinically diagnosed based on evidence of portal hypertension (encephalopathy, esophageal varices, ascites, or splenomegaly), low platelet count (&#x0003c;100,000/mm<sup>3</sup>), or liver ultrasonography (USG) findings.<sup>[<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]</sup> SVR was defined as an undetectable HCV RNA level at 24 weeks later after completing antiviral therapy.</p></sec><sec><label>2.3</label><title>Surveillance of HCC</title><p>Liver USG or computed tomography and serum AFP levels were checked every 6 months for HCC surveillance in study subjects. Follow-up started from the end of antiviral treatment in the treatment group and after diagnosis of CHC infection in the no-treatment group and continued until date of HCC diagnosis or last follow-up.</p></sec><sec><label>2.4</label><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>Patient baseline characteristics are described as medians (ranges) or frequencies. Differences between categorical or continuous variables were analyzed using the Chi-squared test, the Fisher exact test, or the Student <italic>t</italic> test. Statistical differences among 3 or more groups were analyzed by ANOVA test with Turkey multiple comparison test. Multivariate analysis was conducted using the logistic regression model to identify the independent risk factors of HCC. Odds ratios with 95% confidence intervals were calculated using the logistic regression model. Two-tailed <italic>P</italic>-values of &#x0003c;0.05 were considered statistically significant, and the statistical analysis was performed using SPSS v19.0 (SPSS Inc, Chicago, IL).</p></sec></sec><sec><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec><label>3.1</label><title>Patient baseline characteristics</title><p>A total of 1176 patients were enrolled in the study (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>); baseline characteristics are summarized in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. Median patient age was 51 years (range, 18&#x02013;95 years), and 696 (59.2%) were male. LC was present in 230 (19.6%) patients, and all were in a compensated state. Genotype 1 was the most common (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;433, 36.8%), and the majority (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;391, 90.3%) of them were genotype 1b. Median follow-up duration was 31 months (range, 6&#x02013;144 months). The SVR (+) and SVR (&#x02212;) subgroups contained 306 and 183 patients, respectively, and the no-treatment group contained 687 patients. One hundred thirty-nine (55.4%) and 141 (71.9%) of genotype 1 (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;251) and 2 (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;196) patients administered PEG-IFN/RBV achieved SVR, respectively. In the treatment group, there were 456 (93.3%) treatment na&#x000ef;ve patients. Median age was greater and the frequency of LC was higher in the no-treatment group than in the treatment group or the 2 SVR subgroups, respectively (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of the patients.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="medi-96-e5321-g002"/></table-wrap></sec><sec><label>3.2</label><title>Clinical characteristics of patients with or without HCC</title><p>Clinical characteristics of patients with or without HCC were analyzed in the treatment and no-treatment groups (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). In the treatment group, median patient age was greater (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01) and LC was more frequent (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01) in patients who developed HCC than in those who did not. Other factors, such as, gender, BMI, ALT, HCV RNA, HCV genotype, and follow-up duration, were similar in these 2 HCC subgroups (<italic>P</italic> values for all &#x0003e; 0.05) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). In the no-treatment group, median patient age was greater for those who developed HCC (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01), males (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.03), and the rate of cirrhosis (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01) were significantly higher in patients who developed HCC (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of clinical characteristics of the patients with or without HCC during follow-up.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="medi-96-e5321-g003"/></table-wrap></sec><sec><label>3.3</label><title>Cumulative HCC development in patients with CHC infection</title><p>HCC developed in 114 (9.7%) of the 1176 study subjects over a median follow-up of 31 months. The 2-, 4-, and 6-year cumulative HCC development rates of patients in the SVR (+) subgroup (0%, 0%, and 1.1%, respectively) were significantly lower than in the SVR (&#x02212;) subgroup (3.9%, 6.4%, and 9.8%) and in the no-treatment group (9.7%, 13.0%, and 17.8%) (<italic>P</italic> values for all&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>A). The 2-, 4-, and 6-year cumulative HCC development rates of study subjects with LC were significantly greater than those without LC (24.3%, 30.4%, and 38.4% vs 1.3%, 2.3%, and 3.1%, respectively, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>B).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>HCC development in all study subjects. The cumulative HCC development rate of patients who achieved SVR on PEG-IFN/RBV therapy was significantly lower than the rate of those who did not and than that of those not treated with PEG-IFN/RBV (<italic>P</italic> values for all&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01) (A). The cumulative HCC development rate of study subjects with LC was significantly greater than those without LC (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01) (B). The cumulative HCC development rate of study subjects with genotype 1 was not significantly greater than those with other genotypes (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.09) (C). HCC = hepatocellular carcinoma, LC = liver cirrhosis, PEG-IFN/RBV = peg-interferon plus ribavirin, SVR = sustained virologic response.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="medi-96-e5321-g004"/></fig><p>Data for HCV genotypes were available for 864 of the study subjects, and of these, HCC developed in 73 (8.4%) patients. The 2-, 4-, and 6-year cumulative HCC development rates of patients with genotype 1 tended to be greater than those with other genotypes (6.1%, 7.4%, and 10.4% vs 3.2%, 8.1%, and 9.6%, respectively, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.09) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>C).</p></sec><sec><label>3.4</label><title>Cumulative HCC development in patients with CHC with respect to antiviral treatment</title><p>In the treatment group, HCC developed in 20 (4.1%) patients during a median follow-up duration of 46 months. In this group, the 2-, 4-, and 6-year cumulative HCC development rates of patients with LC were significantly greater than those without LC (8.9%, 13.5%, and 19.0% vs 0.6%, 1.4%, and 2.1%, respectively, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>A), and the 2-, 4-, and 6-year cumulative HCC development rates of patients with genotype 1 were significantly greater than those with other genotypes (2.8%, 4.1%, and 6.8% vs 0.4%, 2.1%, and 2.1%, respectively, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.047) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>B).</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>HCC development in patients who received antiviral treatment. The cumulative HCC development rate of patients with LC was significantly greater than that of those without LC (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01) (A). The cumulative HCC development rate of patients with genotype 1 was significantly greater than that of those with other genotypes (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.047) (B). HCC = hepatocellular carcinoma, LC = liver cirrhosis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="medi-96-e5321-g005"/></fig><p>In the no-treatment group, HCC developed in 94 (13.7%) patients during a median follow-up duration of 21 months. In this group, the 2-, 4-, and 6-year cumulative HCC development rates were significantly greater for male than female patients (10.9%, 15.4%, and 20.0% vs 8.4%, 10.0%, and 15.0%, respectively, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.02) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>A), and the 2-, 4-, and 6-year cumulative HCC development rates of patients with LC were significantly greater than those of patients without LC (30.5%, 37.1%, and 46.1% vs 2.0%, 3.2%, and 4.1%, respectively, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>B). HCV genotype data were available for 375 patients in the no-treatment group, and HCC developed in 53 (14.1%) of these patients, and the cumulative overall HCC development rates of patients with genotype 1 or other genotypes were similar (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.59) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>C).</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>HCC development in patients who did not receive antiviral treatment. The cumulative HCC development rate of male patients was significantly greater than that of female patients (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.02) (A). The cumulative HCC development rate of patients with LC was significantly greater than that of those without LC (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01) (B). The cumulative overall HCC development rate of patients with genotype 1 or another genotype were similar (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.59) (C). HCC = hepatocellular carcinoma, LC = liver cirrhosis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="medi-96-e5321-g006"/></fig></sec><sec><label>3.5</label><title>Factors predictive of HCC development in all patients with CHC</title><p>For all study subjects, univariate analysis showed that older age (hazard ratio [HR] 1.06, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01), presence of cirrhosis (HR 14.89, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01), higher serum HCV RNA levels (HR 1.01, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.03), SVR (&#x02212;) (HR 8.52, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01), and no antiviral treatment (HR 16.19, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01) were related to HCC development (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). Multivariate analysis showed that older age (HR 1.03, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01), presence of cirrhosis (HR 9.92, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01), SVR (&#x02212;) (HR 7.02, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01), and no antiviral treatment (HR 6.76, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01) independently predicted HCC development (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Significant predictive factors of HCC development in patients with chronic HCV infection.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="medi-96-e5321-g007"/></table-wrap></sec><sec><label>3.6</label><title>Factors predictive of HCC development in patients with CHC based on antiviral treatment</title><p>Significant predictive factors of HCC development in the treatment and no-treatment groups were shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>. In the treatment group, older age (HR 1.05, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.02), presence of cirrhosis (HR 6.35, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01), and SVR (&#x02212;) (HR 10.73, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01) independently predicted HCC development (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). In the no-treatment group, older age (HR 1.03, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01), male (HR 1.68, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.02), and presence of cirrhosis (HR 11.64, <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;&#x0003c;&#x0200a;0.01) independently predicted HCC development (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Significant predictive factors of HCC development in chronically HCV-infected patients with or without antiviral treatment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="medi-96-e5321-g008"/></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>In the present study, HCC occurred in 9.7% of all 1176 study subjects over a median follow-up of 31 months. In the treatment group, the 6-year cumulative HCC development rates were 1.1% and 9.8% in the SVR (+) and SVR (&#x02212;) subgroups, respectively, and in the no-treatment group, the 6-year cumulative HCC development rate was substantially higher at 17.8%. Furthermore, among all study subjects, the risk of HCC development was significantly greater for older patients, in those with cirrhosis, in those who did not achieve SVR on PEG-IFN/RBV, and in those in the no-treatment group. Interestingly, older age, presence of cirrhosis, and failure to achieve SVR were found to independently predict HCC development even among patients in the treatment group.</p><p>In the present study, the risk of HCC development was significantly higher in the SVR (&#x02212;) than in the SVR (+) subgroup, which occurs with previous results.<sup>[<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup> This suggests that increasing SVR rates reduce HCC development risk in patients with CHC. In fact, SVR rates for genotypes 1 and 2 in the treatment group of the present study were a low as 55.4% and 71.9%, respectively. However, recently recommended first-line antiviral regimens, such as, sofosbuvir-based or daclatasvir/asunaprevir-based regimens, in the treatment-na&#x000ef;ve CHC patients have reported to have SVR rates of up to 98% to 100% in treatment-na&#x000ef;ve CHC genotype 1 patients with treatment durations as short as 12 or 24 weeks.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</sup> Moreover, in genotype 2 patients, sofosbuvir-based regimens have been reported to have high SVR rates of more than 95%.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</sup> Although long-term treatment outcomes, such as, HCC development rates have not been reported for these new drugs, it can be expected that the higher SVR rates achieved will be reflected by decrease in HCC development rates. Therefore, active antiviral therapy based on these new regimens needs to be considered to achieve high SVR rates in patients with treatment-na&#x000ef;ve CHC.</p><p>Many patients on the PEG-IFN/RBV regimen experience side effects, and as a result, about 10% to 20% and 20% to 30% of those discontinue treatment or continue at reduced dosages, respectively.<sup>[<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</sup> However, new DAA agents have fewer side effects, are better tolerated, and have higher compliance rates than the PEG-IFN/RBV regimen.<sup>[<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</sup> In a previous study, we found that 27.4% (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;181) of patients treated with PEG-IFN/RBV were nonadherent due to dose reduction and drug discontinuation in 45.3% and 54.7%, respectively.<sup>[<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</sup> In the present study, 37.4% of patients in the treatment group failed to achieve SVR, and this was found to be an independent risk factor of HCC development in patients with CHC. Although incidences of antiviral therapy discontinuation were not evaluated, the side effects of PEG-IFN/RBV are a probably an important cause of discontinuation, and thus, of treatment failure. Currently, patients with CHC who failed to achieve SVR on PEG-IFN/RBV can be retreated with new DAA agents and expected to achieve high SVR rates of 90% to 95%.<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup> Accordingly, accumulating evidence suggests the risk of HCC development in patients with CHC who failed to achieve SVR on PEG-IFN/RBV may be reduced by retreatment with new DAA agents.</p><p>Several factors are considered contraindications to the PEG-IFN/RBV regimen.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> Historically, older patients with CHC have been excluded from clinical trials using IFN-based regimens due to drug toxicities, and an advanced age has been considered as major limitation to IFN-based anti-HCV therapy for reasons of poor tolerability and response.<sup>[<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]</sup> Thus, anti-HCV therapy for older patients constitutes a major unmet need. On the other hand, new era of DAA regimen, such as, sofosbuvir- and daclatasvir/asunaprevir-based regimens, have no such contraindications, because the incidences of side effects are considerably lower.<sup>[<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]</sup> Accordingly, because an advanced age is a risk factor of HCC development in patients with CHC and new DAA agents are well tolerated, advanced age should not be contraindicate to active antiviral treatment.</p><p>In HCC, carcinogenesis is a multistep process, although the mechanism involved has yet to be elucidated. Nonetheless, LC is a well-known risk factor of HCC development regardless of underlying liver disease, and thus, cirrhotic patients are candidates for active surveillance program of HCC development.<sup>[<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]</sup> In addition, cirrhotic patients with HBV infection have been actively treated with antiviral drugs.<sup>[<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]</sup> Although the previous guideline recommended cirrhotic patients with HCV infection can be treated using PEG-IFN/RBV, it is also stated that suitable patients should have compensated liver function and acceptable hematological indices.<sup>[<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]</sup> Furthermore, PEG-IFN/RBV has been frequently related to hematologic abnormalities, such as, neutropenia, anemia, and thrombocytopenia, and as shown in our previous study, about 5% of patients experienced severe hematologic side effects.<sup>[<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]</sup></p><p>On the other hand, recently recommended DAA agents have been associated with grade 3 or 4 hematologic abnormalities in fewer than 1% of treated patients.<sup>[<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]</sup> In addition, according to current guidelines, HCV patients with decompensated cirrhosis can also be treated with new DAA agents,<sup>[<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup> and in the present study, multivariate analysis showed that LC was an independent risk factor of HCC development in patients with CHC regardless of PEG-IFN/RBV therapy. The above-mentioned evidence strongly suggests that cirrhotic patients with CHC need to be actively treated with highly active oral DAA agents to reduce the risk of HCC development. Although recent studies reported that HCC recurrence has been unexpectedly higher in patients with CHC who receiving DAAs, they were retrospective studies, and enrolled patients were not randomized.<sup>[<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</sup> Furthermore, in the other prospective study, there was no evidence of high HCC recurrence in patients with HCV after DAAs.<sup>[<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]</sup> Therefore, the results of these retrospective studies may not reduce the significance of the present study.</p><p>Several limitations of the present study require consideration. First, selection bias could not be avoided because of the retrospective design of the study. Second, histologic differences in liver tissues could have confounded our analysis of factors associated with HCC development. However, liver tissue samples could not be obtained from enrolled subjects because biopsy is not a mandatory before the initiation of anti-HCV therapy. Third, some factors potentially associated with the risk of HCV-related HCC, such as, obesity, diabetes mellitus, and insulin resistance, were not addressed in the present study. Fourth, median follow-up duration was relatively short as 31 months, and therefore, long-term follow-up data are needed. Fifth, our recommendation regarding the need for active antiviral therapy based on new DAA agents in patients with CHC with some risk factors was made based on results obtained for PEG-IFN/RBV therapy. Because of time limitations imposed by the recent introduction of the new DAA agents, the preventive effects of these drugs on HCC development in patients with CHC needs further detailed evaluation in the future.</p><p>Summarizing, the present study shows that the risk of HCC development in CHC is significantly higher for patients with an advanced age, those with cirrhosis, those who have failed to achieve SVR, and those not treated with PEG-IFN/RBV. In particular, it was found for patients with CHC treated with PEG-IFN/RBV, an older age, presence of cirrhosis, and failure to achieve SVR independently predicted HCC development, and in patients with treatment-na&#x000ef;ve CHC, an older age, a male gender, and presence of cirrhosis were found to predict HCC development. In our opinion, patients with CHC with one of these factors should be viewed as candidates for active antiviral therapy in the new era of highly effective oral antiviral drugs.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>Abbreviations: AFP = alpha-fetoprotein, ALT = alanine aminotransferase, BMI = body mass index, CHC = chronic HCV, DAA = direct-acting antiviral, HBV = hepatitis B virus, HCC = hepatocellular carcinoma, HCV = hepatitis C virus, IFN = interferon, LC = liver cirrhosis, PEG-IFN/RBV = peg-interferon plus ribavirin, SVR = sustained virologic response, USG = ultrasonography.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>SHL and Y-JJ were responsible for the concept and design of the study, the acquisition, analysis and interpretation of the data, and the drafting of the manuscript. JYS and J-WL helped with data acquisition of the manuscript.</p></fn><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p>This study was supported by an Inha University Hospital grant.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to disclose.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghany</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Strader</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Diagnosis, management, and treatment of hepatitis C: an update</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>1335</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19330875</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shepard</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Finelli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Alter</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Global epidemiology of hepatitis C virus infection</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>558</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16122679</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manns</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>McHutchison</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Peginterferon alfa-2b plus ribavirin compared with interferon alfa-2b plus ribavirin for initial treatment of chronic hepatitis C: a randomised trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>358</volume>:<fpage>958</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11583749</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fried</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiffman</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Peginterferon alfa-2a plus ribavirin for chronic hepatitis C virus infection</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>2002</year>;<volume>347</volume>:<fpage>975</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12324553</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khuroo</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Khuroo</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahab</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Meta-analysis: a randomized trial of peginterferon plus ribavirin for the initial treatment of chronic hepatitis C genotype 4</article-title>. <source>Aliment Pharmacol Ther</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>931</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15521839</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Trinh</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Higher rate of sustained virologic response in chronic hepatitis C genotype 6 treated with 48 weeks versus 24 weeks of peginterferon plus ribavirin</article-title>. <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>1131</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18477343</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Panel</surname><given-names>AIHG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Hepatitis C guidance: AASLD-IDSA recommendations for testing, managing, and treating adults infected with hepatitis C virus</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>932</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26111063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>European Association for Study of Liver</collab><article-title>EASL clinical practice guidelines: management of hepatitis C virus infection</article-title>. <source>J Hepatol</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>392</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>420</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24331294</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Korean Association for the Study of the Liver</collab><article-title>KASL clinical practice guidelines: management of hepatitis C</article-title>. <source>Clin Mol Hepatol</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>139</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27044763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Long-term effect of interferon alpha-2b plus ribavirin therapy on incidence of hepatocellular carcinoma in patients with hepatitis C virus-related cirrhosis</article-title>. <source>J Viral Hepat</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>409</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16842444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stroffolini</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Sustained virological response to interferon-alpha is associated with improved outcome in HCV-related cirrhosis: a retrospective study</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>579</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17326216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiratori</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Moriyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Interferon therapy reduces the risk for hepatocellular carcinoma: national surveillance program of cirrhotic and noncirrhotic patients with chronic hepatitis C in Japan. IHIT Study Group. Inhibition of Hepatocarcinogenesis by Interferon Therapy</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>
<year>1999</year>;<volume>131</volume>:<fpage>174</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10428733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishiguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuroki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakatani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Randomised trial of effects of interferon-alpha on incidence of hepatocellular carcinoma in chronic active hepatitis C with cirrhosis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<year>1995</year>;<volume>346</volume>:<fpage>1051</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7564784</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kasahara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Risk factors for hepatocellular carcinoma and its incidence after interferon treatment in patients with chronic hepatitis C. Osaka Liver Disease Study Group</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source>
<year>1998</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1394</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>402</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9581697</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toyoda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Risk factors of hepatocellular carcinoma development in non-cirrhotic patients with sustained virologic response for chronic hepatitis C virus infection</article-title>. <source>J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>1183</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25678094</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim do</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Lower incidence of hepatocellular carcinoma and cirrhosis in hepatitis C patients with sustained virological response by pegylated interferon and ribavirin</article-title>. <source>Dig Dis Sci</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>573</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25236421</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishigami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Masuda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Effect of peginterferon alfa-2b and ribavirin on hepatocellular carcinoma prevention in older patients with chronic hepatitis C</article-title>. <source>J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>321</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25091027</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Prospective cohort study on the outcomes of hepatitis C virus-related cirrhosis in South Korea</article-title>. <source>J Gastroenterol Hepatol</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>1281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25778783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Furusyo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kajiwara</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Efficacy of pegylated interferon alpha-2b and ribavirin treatment on the risk of hepatocellular carcinoma in patients with chronic hepatitis C: a prospective, multicenter study</article-title>. <source>J Hepatol</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>495</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>501</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23099187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandez-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Peginterferon plus ribavirin and sustained virological response in HCV-related cirrhosis: outcomes and factors predicting response</article-title>. <source>Am J Gastroenterol</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>2164</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20700116</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Moucari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueiredo-Mendes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Impact of peginterferon and ribavirin therapy on hepatocellular carcinoma: incidence and survival in hepatitis C patients with advanced fibrosis</article-title>. <source>J Hepatol</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>652</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20346533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruix</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Castells</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Surgical resection of hepatocellular carcinoma in cirrhotic patients: prognostic value of preoperative portal pressure</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source>
<year>1996</year>;<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>1018</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8831597</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Di Lelio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cestari</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lomazzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cirrhosis: diagnosis with sonographic study of the liver surface</article-title>. <source>Radiology</source>
<year>1989</year>;<volume>172</volume>:<fpage>389</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2526349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Afdhal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeuzem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Ledipasvir and sofosbuvir for untreated HCV genotype 1 infection</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>370</volume>:<fpage>1889</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24725239</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lawitz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyles</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Sofosbuvir for previously untreated chronic hepatitis C infection</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>368</volume>:<fpage>1878</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23607594</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>[26]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fried</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Side effects of therapy of hepatitis C and their management</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source>
<year>2002</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>S237</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12407599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>[27]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Fried</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Side effects of therapy for chronic hepatitis C</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source>
<year>2003</year>;<volume>124</volume>:<fpage>1711</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12761728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>[28]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manns</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pol</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>All-oral daclatasvir plus asunaprevir for hepatitis C virus genotype 1b: a multinational, phase 3, multicohort study</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>384</volume>:<fpage>1597</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>605</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25078304</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>[29]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Capraru</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuczynski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>La</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Efficacy and safety of sofosbuvir plus simeprevir in patients with advanced HCV cirrhosis</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>665a</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>[30]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonzales</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nazario</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Efficacy of Ledipasvir plus Sofosobuvir with or without ribavirin in hepatitis C genotype 1 patients who failed previous treatment with Simeprevir plus Sofosbuvir</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>775a</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>[31]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Multicenter comparison of PEG-IFN alpha2a or alpha2b plus ribavirin for treatment-naive HCV patient in Korean population</article-title>. <source>BMC Gastroenterol</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>74</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23627926</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>[32]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Katano</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Efficacy of peginterferon-alpha-2b plus ribavirin in patients aged 65 years and older with chronic hepatitis C</article-title>. <source>Liver Int</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<fpage>527</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19523048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>[33]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thabut</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Calvez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thibault</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Hepatitis C in 6,865 patients 65 yr or older: a severe and neglected curable disease?</article-title>
<source>Am J Gastroenterol</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>101</volume>:<fpage>1260</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16771947</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>[34]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saab</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rheem</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundaram</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Hepatitis C infection in the elderly</article-title>. <source>Dig Dis Sci</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>3170</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26008618</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>[35]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Modi</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nazario</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Trotter</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Safety and efficacy of simeprevir plus sofosbuvir with or without ribavirin in patients with decompensated genotype 1 hepatitis C cirrhosis</article-title>. <source>Liver Transplant</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>[36]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasser</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Delwaide</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Sofosbuvir in combination with simeprevir +/&#x02212; ribavirin in genotype 4 hepatitis C patients with advanced fibrosis or cirrhosis: real-life experience from Belgium</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>62</volume>:<fpage>746a</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>[37]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruix</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Management of hepatocellular carcinoma: an update</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>53</volume>:<fpage>1020</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21374666</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>[38]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Terrault</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bzowej</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>AASLD guidelines for treatment of chronic hepatitis B</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>63</volume>:<fpage>261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26566064</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>[39]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Buonfiglioli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Scuteri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Early occurrence and recurrence of hepatocellular carcinoma in HCV-related cirrhosis treated with direct-acting antivirals</article-title>. <source>J Hepatol</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>727</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27349488</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>[40]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Perello</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Unexpected high rate of early tumor recurrence in patients with HCV-related HCC undergoing interferon-free therapy</article-title>. <source>J Hepatol</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>719</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27084592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>[41]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>ANRS Collaborative Study Group on Hepatocellular Carcinoma (ANRS CO22 HEPATHER, CO12 CirVir and CO23 CUPILT Cohorts)</collab><article-title>Lack of evidence of an effect of direct-acting antivirals on the recurrence of hepatocellular carcinoma: data from three ANRS cohorts</article-title>. <source>J Hepatol</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>734</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27288051</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>