<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We then analyzed the sensitivity of our results to departures from the infinite sites model (Figure F in 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.115.024208/-/DC1/FileS1.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">File S1</ext-link>), from the constant population size model (Figure G in 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.115.024208/-/DC1/FileS1.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">File S1</ext-link>) and from the Wright-Fisher model (Figure H in 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.115.024208/-/DC1/FileS1.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">File S1</ext-link>). To account for repeated bottlenecks (
 <italic>e.g.</italic>, during transmission events), extinction-recolonization dynamics, and rapid adaptation, we simulated the distribution of pairwise nucleotide differences under a scenario of reconnection of isolated populations under a beta-coalescent model. Beta-coalescent models have recently been proposed to model the genealogies of many organisms with a large variance in the number of offspring per individual (
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Birkner and Blath 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib99" ref-type="bibr">Tellier and Lemaire 2014</xref>), in particular viruses (
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Neher and Hallatschek 2013</xref>). We extended the algorithm from Birkner and Blath (
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Birkner and Blath 2008</xref>) – which generates samples under a beta-coalescent at equilibrium – to include an island model of migration (each lineage migrates to another population at rate 
 <italic>M</italic>) and an isolation period. We assumed that coalescence processes follow the beta-coalescent at all times: before isolation, during isolation and after reconnection. In addition to mutation and migration rates, beta-coalescents rely on a parameter α (
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="me13">
   <mrow>
    <mn>0</mn>
    <mo>≤</mo>
    <mi>α</mi>
    <mo>≤</mo>
    <mn>2</mn>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>) that gives the probability of multiple lineages coalescing at the same time. We present the results for four different parameter values: 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="me14">
   <mrow>
    <mi>α</mi>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mn>0</mn>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> (equivalent to the classic Kingman coalescent), 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="me15">
   <mrow>
    <mi>α</mi>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mn>0.5</mn>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>, 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="me16">
   <mrow>
    <mi>α</mi>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mn>1</mn>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> [corresponding to the Bolthausen-Sznitman coalescent, used to model strong positive selection (
 <italic>e.g.</italic>, 
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Neher and Hallatschek 2013</xref>)], and 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="me17">
   <mrow>
    <mi>α</mi>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mn>1.5</mn>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>.
</p>
