<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The integration of protein functions and structures into evolutionary models has two main challenges: (1) published viral protein structural and functional information may not be available or sufficiently resolved based on current studies; and (2) The assumption of nucleotide site independence in the model cannot capture the biological reality that some sites are linked due to shared function [
 <xref rid="B113-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. Some modeling approaches with a protein structure scoring system or partitioning schemes on the protein sequence [
 <xref rid="B98-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,
 <xref rid="B110-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,
 <xref rid="B111-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>] can potentially overcome these challenges; for example, protein structure has been explored with coarse-grained models for structure prediction, prediction of protein interaction and molecular dynamics simulations of protein folding [
 <xref rid="B98-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. This provides the statistical potential like a scoring system for sequence-structure compatibility, which can be used to evaluate the probability of fixation of a given mutation and improve the precision of ancestral reconstruction [
 <xref rid="B111-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. However, few studies have incorporated protein structural information into the evolutionary analyses. Simple representations of protein functional and structural domains have been used so far. Hypothetically, novel models with a more complete representation with a full site mapping of the protein functions and structures would yield a better fit. But in a phylogenetic context, structurally informed models are still outperformed by some site-independent models in terms of fit [
 <xref rid="B111-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. Preliminary data suggest that this would become less of a concern with increased sharing of sequence data [
 <xref rid="B110-vaccines-07-00045" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]. 
</p>
