<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The current SARS‐CoV‐2 outbreak has brutally exposed the current vulnerability of society to pandemics, even those that have been long predicted and anticipated (Ge 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="emi15029-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Menachery 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="emi15029-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Most healthcare systems have not evolved for resilience in times of catastrophe, nor for effective rapid responses to pandemics. A key principle steering evolution has been value‐for‐money within a fixed budget; contingency planning within this framework (outlays for materials that may never be used) may be considered to be a nuisance that diminishes what can otherwise be done with limited funds, and so to a greater or lesser extent may be postponed. For this reason, it is crucial that budgets for contingency planning are separate from health system budgets. Equally important, it has emphasized the fact that some healthcare systems have for a long time been on the edge of the cliff, just waiting for an event to push them over. Their adaptation to changing needs has often been through a ‘sticking plaster’ response. Evolution has been 
 <italic>ad hoc</italic>, via responses to new developments and challenges, and often led to fragmentation rather than coherence. The lessons to be learned are thus not only to take scientifically‐founded pandemic predictions seriously into account in policy elaboration, but also to streamline and institute changes in healthcare systems that impose an evolutionary trajectory that increases coherence, efficiency and preparedness, and the necessary mechanisms to maintain these as new exigencies arise (e.g., see Timmis and Timmis, 
 <xref rid="emi15029-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). And, especially because this crisis has revealed enormous disparities in responsiveness, effectiveness and the quality of responses in different countries, both preparedness for pandemics and the general improvement of healthcare mandate international benchmarking for contingency planning and the evolution of healthcare systems. Comparisons/benchmarking within countries—within single systems—is no longer acceptable. Many healthcare systems need substantive improvements through strategic investments, in most cases targeted to system changes, not just extra funding of existing services. And above all, they need crisis taskforces embedded in them that can prepare for, and take charge in times of, impending catastrophes.
</p>
