<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Host preference studies involving 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> are often limited by the low sample numbers of blooded mosquitoes that are collected. This is because blooded 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> have been difficult to collect 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Ponlawat1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Muoz1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. Previous sampling methods have often used combinations of aspirators, sweep nets, human baits, sticky traps, carbon dioxide-baited traps, and gravid traps in order to increase catch counts and as mentioned, often sampled exclusively in high density areas such as tire yards and dumps 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Tempelis1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Savage1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Niebylski1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Sawabe1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Valerio1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. But trapping methods may bias results significantly 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Thiemann1" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>, and 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> is not readily attracted to traditional types of vector surveillance traps 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Ponlawat1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Farajollahi2" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. A consistent sampling tool was not available for 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> until the development of the BGS trap, which allowed us to sample populations of this species across a large geographic area over multiple years 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Unlu2" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Fonseca1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. Although we primarily utilized BGS traps for surveillance of host seeking 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>, these traps also collected blooded specimens, which were subjected to molecular testing to characterize host feeding patterns of this species. However, unlike blooded or black blooded 
 <italic>Culex</italic> mosquitoes which are easy to discern visually, blooded 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> (unless fully engorged on fresh blood) are problematic to ascertain. This is because 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> is a smaller species that imbibes smaller blood meals 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Hawley1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-EstradaFranco1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref> or on multiple hosts 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Delatte1" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Farjana1" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>, and contains a darker integument which hinders accurate detection of blood meals 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Muoz1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, particularly those in later Sella stages of development 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Ponlawat1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. For example, parity studies conducted within our sampling sites on 166 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> visually determined as unengorged, detected blood meals or eggs in over 28% of those samples (Farajollahi et al. unpublished data). Our field investigations collected over 400 blooded 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> during 2008–2011, 289 of which contained amplifiable blood for host determination analyses, with a successful amplification rate of close to 60%. In contrast, amplification rates were much higher for 
 <italic>Culex</italic> mosquitoes (80%), likely because bird blood is nucleated and amplification of target DNA is easier for identification 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003037-Kent1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. Interestingly, we collected twice as many blooded 
 <italic>Culex</italic> mosquitoes than blooded 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>, despite the demonstrable specificity of the BGS trap for the latter species. Amplification rates for 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> also varied between the seasons and counties, as several abnormal weather patterns were experienced, threatening specimen handling and maintenance of the cold chain. The summers of 2010–2011 were particularly detrimental for blooded 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> because the excessive heat (warmest and 3
 <sup>rd</sup> warmest summers on record) may have desiccated specimens much faster in the BGS traps and reduced amplifiable DNA through degradation (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://climate.rutgers.edu/stateclim_v1/data" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://climate.rutgers.edu/stateclim_v1/data</ext-link>). Nonetheless, successful blood meal results from 165 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> across a consistent spatial/temporal span provides valuable insight into the host associations of this species in the northeastern USA.
</p>
