<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Collaborations at the level of State, region, national or international level are important to ensure prompt and appropriate responses in outbreak/epidemic situations. Collective knowledge and experiences can guide the situation better and accelerate the scientific efforts to control the spread of infection or develop new therapeutics. Collaboration can be between public agencies or with private partners and in case of COVID-19, following the genome sequence released by China, global efforts were initiated to target diagnostics therapeutics control and prevention. The WHO plays an important role in coordinating efforts to control the outbreak at the global level and brings the scientific community for various countries together for undertaking critical public health research in therapeutics, diagnostics as well as innovations. Collaborations may also be needed between international partners to closely monitor the outbreak and understand the pathogen better. Preparedness is needed to have policies in place in regard to sharing the data, samples, results of studies when protecting intellectual property and ownership, as well as storage of sample for future use. At present, there is a requirement to obtain a clearance from the Health Ministry's Screening Committee (HMSC) for any research involving international collaboration and the committee looks at the sensitivity of the research and need for collaboration
 <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>. For research on outbreaks/epidemics, there should be appropriate fast-track mechanisms in place to facilitate research in international collaboration. Extensive collaborations at local, regional, national or international level involving public agencies or private entities are needed to multiply efforts to control the spread of infection and develop therapeutics to preserve lives. Ethical Considerations form an important part of the collaborative policies to allow sharing of samples/data and recognize intellectual contributions.
</p>
