<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0125">Other nonstructural proteins from coronavirus that also have the ability to prevent this virus from immune responses are nsp3 that encoded two functional proteins, macrodomains and PLpro (cleavage of nsps). Both of these proteins appear to be employed as actors in the evading of SARS-CoV from immune response-induce viruses. This possibility was supported by Fehr et al. in their in vivo study in BALB/c mice that were infected by SARS-CoV-lacking macrodomains. The findings of this study revealed that although there was an increase in expression of type I IFN, ISG15, CXCL10 and the proinflammatory cytokines IL-6 and TNF, followed by significantly higher survival, there was no lung pathology development in the mice [
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The finding is closely similar to other studies conducted in mice demonstrating a lack of deubiquitinating enzyme (DUB) activity in MERS-CoV. DUB is another role of PLpro to help coronavirus evade attack from a host’s immune response by antagonizing the IFN response. From these findings, we hypothesized that the decline in function of the two proteins may lead to the direct introduction and sticking of immune troops to continuously infected cells and prevented the replication of the virus and the life cycle [
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. In addition to using nonstructural proteins, SARS-CoV could utilize its protein accessories to avoid immune responses. For example the gene segment located on ORF3b of this virus has the ability to antagonize the INF signaling pathway and cause inhibition of the effector cell activation cascade for eradication and inhibition of viral replication [
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Equally of concern, the protein encoded in ORF6 could inhibit JAK-STAT signaling pathway by binding to karyopherin-α2, and tethers karyopherin-β1 on internal membranes to lead to blocking nuclear translocation of the transcription factor STAT1 [
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].
</p>
