<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The larval period is the only immature stage during which feeding and growth occur in the life cycle of 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic>. The chemical control measures employed preferentially focus on this stage due to three striking attributes. First, the larvae are aquatic and feed on suspended organic matter adhering to the walls or sediment at the bottom of the reservoirs. As larval eating habits are not selective, they can easily ingest chemical or biological insecticides (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Second, the larvae breathe atmospheric air through the siphon, located in the eighth abdominal segment. The moment they rise to the surface to breathe, they become more susceptible to control agents (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Third, they are restricted to the oviposition site, which restricts their ability to migrate (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). The main insecticides used act on the insects'central nervous system and belong to the groups of organochlorines, carbamates, organophosphates, and pyrethroids (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). The indiscriminate use of Dichloro-diphenyltrichlorethane (DDT) and pyrethroids induced the development of resistance, which negatively impacted the effectiveness of vector control interventions in endemic countries (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>–
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). Macoris et al. (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>) described that, after 10 years without usage of pyrethroids in São Paulo state, Brazil, 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic> showed persistent resistance. A bioassay with papers impregnated with a deltamethrin diagnostic dose (DD) was conducted yearly, from 2004 to 2015, with 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic> adults from 7 different sites, showing resistance in most cases. These results were a direct effect of pyrethroids being extensively used by São Paulo state governments between 1989 and 2000, and being the preferred insecticide for domestic use (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). This scenario is not limited only to Brazil or South America. Moyes et al. (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>) described that resistance to pyrethroids are widespread throughout the world. Temephos was the preferred larvicide used in Brazil from 2003 to 2014. As a result of continuous usage, cases of resistance were detected in most of studies in all Brazilian geographic regions as compiled by Valle et al. (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). Corte et al. (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>) conducted a study from October 2010 to August 2011 to evaluate 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic> resistance to Temephos from 7 municipalities in Sergipe state, Brazil. All mosquitoes were found to be resistant, varying between cities, even with an increased dose of Temephos. In recent years, interest has grown in the identification of plants with insecticidal properties (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). The use of plant extracts in the control of 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic> demonstrated low production cost, high biodegradability, and different active elements that delay the development of resistance in insects (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>–
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>). However, phytochemicals can also have toxic effects that vary according to the species of the plant, with the part used, age of the plant, and extraction with selected solvent (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>).
</p>
