<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Vaccines can prevent diseases beyond the specific infection they are designed to target. Infections with pathogens, in particular viruses, can predispose to the acquisition of other bacterial infections. For example, influenza virus infection, both seasonal and pandemic, is frequently complicated by bacterial pneumonia and acute otitis media (OM), and infrequently 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> pneumonia/pneumonitis. During the influenza pandemic of 1918–19, secondary bacterial bronchopneumonia with 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae, Streptococcus pyogenes</italic>, 
 <italic>H. influenzae</italic>, and 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> identified at autopsy, likely contributed to the excess mortality observed amongst healthy children and adults (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Morens and Fauci, 2007</xref>). Influenza vaccinations can be beneficial in preventing these complications and also morbidity including acute OM in children; a systematic review demonstrated influenza vaccine efficacy against OM of 51% (21–70%) (
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Manzoli et al., 2007</xref>). Further, there is evidence that inactivated influenza vaccines administered to pregnant women can reduce the hospital admission with acute respiratory illnesses in their infants up to 6 months of age (
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">Regan et al., 2016</xref>). Amongst pregnant, HIV-negative women in South Africa, infants (&lt;3 months) were protected against hospitalization with all-cause lower respiratory tract infections with a vaccine efficacy of 43% (
 <italic>p</italic> = 0.05), including primary viral and secondary bacterial causes (
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">Nunes et al., 2017</xref>). Additionally, in children pneumococcal conjugate vaccines were observed to reduce the incidence of influenza-associated hospital admissions in United States (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">Simonsen et al., 2011</xref>), Spain (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Dominguez et al., 2013</xref>), and South Africa (
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Madhi et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Abadom et al., 2016</xref>), through the prevention of secondary bacterial infections following primary influenza infection.
</p>
