<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mumps is known as an important vaccine-preventable childhood viral disease [
 <xref rid="B1-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The clinical pictures of mumps virus (MuV) infection is characterized by pain and swelling of the parotid glands, but can involve various other tissues and organs [
 <xref rid="B2-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. It can cause serious complications including encephalitis, meningitis, orchitis, myocarditis, pancreatitis, and nephritis [
 <xref rid="B2-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Although mumps is a benign disease, often with complete recovery within a few weeks after being infected, long-term outcomes, such as seizures, cranial nerve palsies, hydrocephalus, and deafness, can occur [
 <xref rid="B3-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Due to its benign clinical picture, mumps has been somewhat neglected compared with other infectious diseases (e.g., measles). However, in 2016 and 2017, the number of cases of mumps increased almost two-times compared to those reported in the previous five years in the United States (US) [
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Additionally, in recent years, several huge outbreaks of the mumps infection have been reported in developed countries [
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. How to prevent and control the epidemic of mumps has sparked a new problem of public health. Previous report showed that 70% of patients with known vaccination history had received two doses of measles, mumps, and rubella (MMR) vaccine prior to illness [
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Compared to mumps, cases of measles and rubella rarely occur in person with two doses of MMR vaccine, suggesting some factors of mumps vaccine influences its effectiveness [
 <xref rid="B3-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Therefore, understanding the characteristics of MuV epidemiology, pathogenesis, and vaccine is important to protect against the spread of MuV infection. The purpose of this study was to summarize the epidemiology, pathogenesis, and vaccine of mumps and recommendations arising from this project.
</p>
