<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0020">With the safer use of pseudoviruses in lower biosafety level facilities, it has opened up greater possibilities for antibody detection, vaccine research, and drug selection to better combat both emerging and re-emerging viruses. These viruses could be screened for the antigenicity/immunogenicity of antigen or antibody response by using neutralization tests and would be a useful tool for vaccine studies. Several studies have used pseudoviruses to detect and test neutralizing antibodies against viruses that pose a threat to the population and their response to viral infection [
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>]. The use of pseudoviruses serve as an alternative to test vaccines, thus eliminating one of the limitations once placed on vaccine development [
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>]. Furthermore, better evaluation on the efficacy of drugs and selection of new drugs has been advantageous in combatting viral infections [
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Here we established pseudovirus systems for emerging SARS-CoV/SARS-CoV-2 viruses and re-emerging avian influenza viruses including H5N2, H5N6, and H5N8 (H5Nx). We assessed the feasibility of the pseudovirus system for neutralization assay and found a broad spectrum of applications such as vaccine candidate selection and vaccine efficacy, including antigenic evolution and immunogenicity, which provide valuable information in vaccine development, especially for emerging and re-emerging viruses.
</p>
