<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0035">Monoclonal or polyclonal antibodies have been recommended as tools for preventing and treating viral infections. Considering the relatively high RBD in SARS-CoV-2, the cross-reactivity of anti-SARS-CoV antibodies with the COVID-19 S protein was evaluated. Tian et al. determined the potent binding of S protein via a SARS CoV-specific human mAb CR3022 
 <xref rid="bib0082" ref-type="bibr">[82]</xref>. Unfortunately, other SARS-CoV RBD directed mAbs (
 <italic>i.e.</italic>, 230, m396, and 80R) cannot bind to the COVID-19 RBD 
 <xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. In this respect, CR3022 may be a promising therapeutic candidate, either alone or in combination with other neutralizing mAbs, for the therapy of COVID-19 disease. In addition, tocilizumab is a monoclonal antibody for the therapy of RA exacerbation. It was designed to suppress the binding of IL-6 to its receptors, hence mitigating cytokine release syndrome. At present, it is also being trailed for the COVID-19 therapy 
 <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">[110]</xref>. Interestingly, Shi et al. reported a human neutralizing antibody targets the receptor binding site of SARS-CoV-2 
 <xref rid="bib0111" ref-type="bibr">[111]</xref>. In their work, they successfully isolated 2 specific human mAbs (named as CA1 and CB6) from a convalescent COVID-19 patient. CA1 and CB6 demonstrated potent SARS-CoV2-specifc neutralization activity 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> against SARS-CoV-2. Moreover, CB6 could suppress SARS-CoV-2 infection in rhesus monkeys at both prophylactic and treatment settings. The following structural studies unraveled that CB6 could recognize an epitope that overlaps with ACE2-binding sites in SARS-CoV-2 receptor binding domain, thus interfering with the virus/receptor interactions by both steric hindrance and direct interface-residue competition 
 <xref rid="bib0111" ref-type="bibr">[111]</xref>. Another recent study revealed the isolation and characterization of 206 RBD-specific mAbs derived from single B cells of eight SARS-CoV-2 infected individuals 
 <xref rid="bib0112" ref-type="bibr">[112]</xref>. The researchers identified antibodies with potent anti-SARS-CoV-2 neutralization capacity that correlated with their competitive capacity with ACE2 for RBD binding. Of note, crystal structure analysis of RBD-bound antibody uncovered steric hindrance that suppressed viral engagement with ACE2 and thereby blocked viral entry 
 <xref rid="bib0112" ref-type="bibr">[112]</xref>. These findings implicate that anti-RBD antibodies may be viral species-specific inhibitors.
</p>
