<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The management of severe hypoxemia in COVID-19 is drawn from the management of ARDS and also informed by experience during the 2003 SARS-CoV and 2012 Middle East respiratory syndrome–related coronavirus outbreaks. The World Health Organization has published a practice guideline on the clinical management of COVID-19 severe respiratory infection,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>
 </sup> and several other groups have also published practice recommendations for the care of patients with COVID-19–associated ARDS.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>–
  <xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>
 </sup> The treatment of patients with COVID-19–associated ARDS is made more complex due to necessary infection control interventions such as the use of isolation rooms and the need for care providers to wear appropriate personal protective equipment. Transmission of SARS-CoV-2 from patients to healthcare workers has been reported, and infection control is of primary importance to protect healthcare workers and prevent further spread of SARS-CoV-2.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
  <xref rid="R54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>
 </sup> The World Health Organization guideline recommends, in addition to routine standard precautions, that providers use droplet and contact precautions when caring for any patients with confirmed or suspected SARS-CoV-2 infection, with the addition of airborne precautions when any aerosol-generating procedure, such as intubation, bronchoscopy, suctioning, or cardiopulmonary resuscitation, is performed.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>
 </sup> Additional guidelines and frontline reports from groups in Hubei province suggest many providers are utilizing airborne precautions at all times while caring for COVID-19 patients as an additional safety measure.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
  <xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
