<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phylodynamic models describe the interaction between the epidemiological and evolutionary processes of a pathogen [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The availability of molecular data coupled with the recent development of detailed, data-driven phylodynamic models has galvanized the new field of viral predictive modeling [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. These models aim to predict the future prevalence of specific viral subtypes based on past and present molecular data. For example, one approach generates one-year ahead forecasts of clade frequency using a fitness model parameterized by the number of antigenic and genetic mutations that dictate the virus’ antigenicity and stability respectively [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Another method maps antigenic distance from hemagglutination inhibition (HI) assay data onto an HA genealogy to determine whether the changes in antigenicity among high-growth clades necessitate a vaccine composition update [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. A third model predicts which clade will be the progenitor lineage of the subsequent influenza season by estimating fitness using a growth rate measure derived from topological features of the HA genealogy [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. All three approaches have been tested on historical predictions. Łuksza’s &amp; Lässig’s model [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] predicted positive growth for 93% of clades that increased in frequency over one year. Steinbruk 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] predicted the predominant HA allele over nine influenza seasons with an accuracy of 78%. Both Łuksza’s &amp; Lässig’s [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and Neher 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] model predictions of progenitor strains to the next season’s performed similarly. Since 2015, both these models have been used to provide recommendations on vaccine composition for the upcoming influenza seasons [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].
</p>
