<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We used Cox proportional hazard models for clustered data to estimate the effect size, confidence intervals and 
 <italic>p</italic>‐values whenever between‐facility intra‐class correlations (ICCs) were greater than or equal to 0.01 [
 <xref rid="jia225610-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="jia225610-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">18</xref>]. Given the small number of facilities, with very small ICCs, robust variances gave unrealistically small 
 <italic>p</italic>‐values [
 <xref rid="jia225610-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">19</xref>]. Because there were a small number of facilities randomized, residual confounding is possible. Thus, we conducted multivariable‐adjusted analyses, where we considered known and suspected baseline determinants of retention and viral suppression, and included those with 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.20 in the models [
 <xref rid="jia225610-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">20</xref>]. Steptime was adjusted for in all analyses, to ensure that any background time trends related to quality of care or disease epidemiology did not lead to spurious differences between the two groups. Survival curves used the Breslow estimator and therefore needed to be estimated at specific covariate values in the multivariate Cox model from where the estimator was derived. The value of each covariate, including steptime, was set at the mean value of each person‐visit in the study population (Table 
 <xref rid="jia225610-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Stepwise restricted cubic splines were used to model continuous covariates, to reduces bias due to incorrect assumptions about linearity of the covariate‐outcome relationships [
 <xref rid="jia225610-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">21</xref>]. To further adjust for any bias due to time trends not addressed by the categorical steptime variable, when calendar time as a linear or non‐linear effect was significant at 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.20 in any model, it was included in the multivariate model in addition to steptime. The missing indicator method was used to handle missing covariate data [
 <xref rid="jia225610-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">22</xref>]. In sensitivity analyses for the viral suppression endpoint, Fine and Gray competing risk methods were used, treating mortality not HIV‐ or ART‐related as competing risks [
 <xref rid="jia225610-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">23</xref>]. Confidence intervals and 
 <italic>p</italic>‐values were not adjusted for multiplicity [
 <xref rid="jia225610-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">24</xref>]. Effect modification was assessed by the robust score test, accounting for within‐facility correlation of the outcomes. Analysis of effect modification was conducted among the subset of participants not missing each covariate and adjusted for the baseline covariates given in Footnote 1 of Tables 
 <xref rid="jia225610-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>,
 <xref rid="jia225610-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref>,
 <xref rid="jia225610-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3</xref>.
</p>
