<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Overall, a combination of serological IgM, rPCR testing, and virus isolation performed on 1409 patients enrolled revealed 20 that were infected by CHIKV in the survey area. Seventy percent of CHIKV-positive patients had symptoms matching the case CHIKV disease definition. This result is similar to that reported during CHIKV epidemics that occurred in Thailand [
 <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] and in the Indian Ocean [
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Overall, the clinical manifestations observed (algo-febrile eruptive illness, with vomiting and diarrhea) were similar to those described previously for acute CHIKV infection [
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Our study also revealed coinfections of CHIKV with malaria in 20% of CHIKV-confirmed cases and supporting previous observations on CHIKV-malaria coinfections reported in the Democratic Republic of the Congo and in Senegal [
 <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Except for the absence of cutaneous rash, the coinfected patients presented the same symptoms and signs described above for CHIKV-only infection. Diarrhea and vomiting were more frequently reported among confirmed malaria cases coinfected with CHIKV, but no significant difference was observed when comparing with patients infected with CHIKV only. These results (1) underscore the difficulties and challenges in clinically differentiating these conditions in areas where malaria is endemic [
 <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] and (2) reinforce malaria as an “umbrella” infection potentially masking arboviral disorders in the context of sub-Saharan Africa. Therefore, in suspected cases of malaria, CHIKV infection should be included as an alternative diagnosis, as well as other arboviral infection options. As previously described, fever and joint involvement were the most frequent manifestations, affecting most of Chikungunya patients [
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Also our study showed that 60% of infected patients presented arthralgia for which 10% experienced persistent arthralgia.
</p>
