<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Chikungunya virus isolates obtained from humans and mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] were found between October and December 2009, confirming previous studies showing that in the Kedougou area arboviruses are mostly isolated from October to December, which corresponds to the end of the rainy season [
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Chikungunya virus was mostly isolated from 
 <italic>A furcifer</italic>, which is probably the primary vector of this outbreak. In a companion study [
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], we showed that 
 <italic>A furcifer</italic> occurred in all 5 major land cover classes in the Kedougou region (forest, village, agriculture, savannah, and barren). On this behalf, there were no significant differences in the abundance of this species among these land cover classes, and the 
 <italic>A furcifer</italic> species was rarely found inside households in villages and was distinctly more abundant on the periphery than inside the villages. In addition, CHIKV was also detected at equal rates in all 5 lands cover classes. Given that, humans are rarely staying in forests during the moment when sylvatic CHIKV vectors are the more active. Because 
 <italic>A furcifer</italic> shows high biting rates in villages [
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], we suggest that humans are likely exposed to sylvatic CHIKV while outside of their homes but within their villages. Such an hypothesis is reinforced by the fact that no domestic transmission of CHIKV occurred given the absence of infection among children under 4 years, who are more likely to spend time within the household. Our results also suggest that the CHIKV epizootic began in September 2009. Hence, sylvatic circulation must precede epidemic amplification in the emergence area [
 <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The CHIKV outbreak episode that emerged in March 2010 raises a question about the transmission of the virus during the dry season in southeastern Senegal. Based in our data, the 
 <italic>Anopheles</italic> genus found infected with CHIKV could be partly involved in transmission, consistent with a previous study that demonstrated experimental CHIKV transmission by 
 <italic>Anopheles</italic> spp [
 <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].
</p>
