<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12">IAVs can be transmitted via non-mutually exclusive routes of transmission: direct contact, indirect contact, respiratory droplets, or aerosols. However, the relative contribution of each route to efficient IAV transmission remains unknown and under debate. Respiratory droplet transmission is mediated by expelled particles that have a propensity to settle quickly because of their size and is therefore reliant on close proximity between infected (donor) and susceptible (recipient) individuals, usually within 1 m of the site of expulsion
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. Aerosol transmission is mediated by expelled particles that are smaller in size than respiratory droplets and can remain suspended in the air for prolonged periods of time, allowing infection of susceptible individuals at a greater distance from the site of expulsion. A generally accepted cut-off size to discriminate between respiratory droplets and aerosols is 5 µm diameter
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>. The current paradigm adopted by the Word Health Organization (WHO) is that influenza viruses are transmitted via respiratory droplets, when aerosol-generating procedures are excluded
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, current guidelines to prevent influenza virus transmission in health care settings are only based on preventing respiratory droplet transmission (summarized in ref. 
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup>). However, the recent body of work on the detection of influenza virus genomes and infectious particles in aerosols suggests that IAVs are also transmitted by aerosols
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. This discordance between guidelines and experimental data highlights the urgent need to improve our fundamental understanding of influenza virus transmission. One current gap in this understanding is the identification of the anatomical site of the respiratory tract from which influenza virus-laden particles are generated and expelled for onwards transmission. It has been shown that preference of the virus to bind to α2,6-SA, associated with viral replication in the ciliated cells in the URT (nasal turbinates, pharynx, larynx) and part of the LRT (trachea, bronchus), is an important determinant for airborne transmissibility of IAVs
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup>. However, it still remained unknown whether the source of exhaled viruses from the donor is the epithelium of tissues in the URT, the LRT or both, and whether α2,6-SA binding preference is necessary for the virus to be exhaled from the donor or for the virus to initiate replication in the recipient.
</p>
