<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Surgical masks appear to be helpful in decreasing the transmission of influenza, SARS-CoV, and COVID-19. Two randomized controlled trials have been performed to compare surgical masks (level 3)
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
 </sup> or unspecified
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>
 </sup> to N95 masks regarding transmission of influenza to healthcare workers. The results showed no difference in the influenza infection rates between the surgical mask and N95 groups.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
  <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>
 </sup> Another study by Yen et al
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
 </sup> compared hospitals with and without SARS-CoV healthcare worker infections. These authors found that zero healthcare worker infections were more likely in hospitals where surgical masks were worn upon entering the hospital, on the wards, and in outpatient clinics.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
 </sup> This is the same plan of action currently being used in Hong Kong, Singapore, and Taiwan.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
  <xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
  <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>
 </sup> A recent study from Singapore of 41 healthcare workers in close contact (10+ min, &lt;2 m away) with a critically ill COVID-19 patient showed zero transmissions.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>
 </sup> Of these healthcare workers, 35 of 41 (85%) were using a surgical mask for respiratory protection.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>
 </sup> Thus, since surgical face masks filter particles larger than 0.1 to 5.0 μm and the droplets that carry Sars-CoV-2 are larger, it stands to reason that there should be adequate protection from transmission of COVID-19 in low risk circumstances. These findings have led many institutions to promote use of surgical face masks in lower risk patient interactions, and advocate for the futility of N95 respirator masks especially during times of scarcity. It should be noted, however, that the CDC recommends use of a surgical face mask if a respirator is not available when caring for a patient with known or suspected COVID-19.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
