<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>PyMOL was used for model building of MADAL385 fragments, their assembly into larger fragments and the full dendrimer, as well as for trajectory visualization and 3D figure generation [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007760.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Geometry optimization and point charge derivation for suitably capped fragments, namely, the pentaerythritol core, the trivalent spacer, and the peripheral N-acetylated Trp residues, were achieved by means of the PM3 hamiltonian available in the sqm program [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007760.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The standard ff14SB force field parameter set in AMBER 16 was used for both ligand and protein atoms [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007760.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1007760.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. A three-dimensional cubic grid consisting of 65x65x65 points with a spacing of 0.375 Å centered on the VP1 pore region displaying electron density for MADAL was defined for docking purposes. Electrostatic, desolvation, and affinity maps for the atom types present in MADAL385 were calculated using AutoGrid 4.2.6 and thereafter the Lamarckian genetic algorithm implemented in AutoDock4 was used to generate 100 docked conformations of a large variety of incrementally larger fragments [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007760.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Intra- and intermolecular energy evaluation of each configuration allowed the selection of the 10 best scoring solutions for each fragment. Significant clustering of solutions with the best scores was apparent for the smaller fragments and visual inspection confirmed the feasibility of the best binding poses, which were used for model building of the VP1 complex with the full dendrimer. For conformational sampling of the full dendrimer, MADAL385 was immersed in a cubic solvent box (TIP3P water molecules) extending 12 Å away from any ligand atom and neutralized by addition of 12 sodium ions to the locations with the most negative molecular electrostatic potential. The same procedure was later used for the VP1:MADAL385 complex; in this case, a weak harmonic restraint of 5 kcal mol
 <sup>-1</sup> Å
 <sup>-2</sup> on the protein Cα atoms was used throughout. Thereafter, all hydrogens and water molecules in both systems were first reoriented in the electric field of the solute and then all atoms were relaxed by performing 25 000 steps of steepest descent followed by 100 000 steps of conjugate gradient energy minimization. The resulting geometry-optimized coordinate sets were used as input for the ensuing molecular dynamics (MD) simulations at 300 K and 1 atm using the 
 <italic>pmemd</italic>.
 <italic>cuda</italic> engine, as implemented in AMBER 16 [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007760.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. The application of SHAKE to all bonds allowed an integration time step of 2 fs to be used. A cutoff distance of 9 Å was selected for the nonbonded interactions and the list of nonbonded pairs was updated every 25 steps. Periodic boundary conditions were applied and electrostatic interactions were represented using the smooth particle mesh Ewald method with a grid spacing of 1 Å [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007760.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. The coupling constants for the temperature and pressure baths were 1.0 and 0.2 ps, respectively. Water molecules and counterions were first equilibrated around the positionally restrained solute for a first run of 0.5 ns. For the remaining 150 ns of simulation the whole systems were allowed to relax and coordinates were saved every 0.1 ns for further analysis by means of the 
 <italic>cpptraj</italic> module in AMBER [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007760.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Subsequently, a simulated annealing procedure was followed to cool down snapshots taken every 5 ns from 300 to 273 K over a 1-ns period [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007760.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. The geometries of these “frozen” systems were then optimized by following an energy minimization protocol until the root-mean-square of the Cartesian elements of the gradient was less than 0.01 kcal·mol-1·Å 1. The final ensemble containing 30 energy-minimized frozen molecules, which can be expected to be closer to the global energy minimum, were taken as representative of the dendrimer and the VP1-MADAL385 complex.
</p>
