<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>By analogy to other CoVs, SARS-CoV-2 might induce a T-lymphocyte-mediated protective immune response. However, patients infected by SARS-CoV-2 that are hospitalized frequently manifest a lymphopenia, suggesting that cellular immune responses may be suppressed [
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. In this context, it becomes plausible that, after infection by SARS-CoV-2, a sort of race decides the course of the events. Either a cellular immune response rapidly clears SARS-CoV-2 – in the best-case-scenario without any (or mild) clinical signs of infection – or the virus causes a state of immunosuppression that debilitates and sometimes overwhelms the host's defense 
 <bold>(
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1A</xref>)
 </bold>. In this context, the initial dose of the viral inoculum leading to infection may have a decisive impact on all subsequent events 
 <bold>(
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1B</xref>)
 </bold>. A small burden of SARS-CoV-2 should have a higher chance to stimulate a protective immune response than a high one, although additional factors like the fitness of the individual's immune system and prior exposure to other in part cross-reactive CoVs might influence the outcome of the race between viral replication and T-lymphocyte responses as well. Hence, it is possible, but remains to be demonstrated, that SARS-CoV-2 transmission from indolent or mildly symptomatic persons to naive individuals generally occurs at a relatively low viral load (lower than if the infection stems from severely affected patients), which then might have higher probabilities to induce immunity instead of severe and sometimes lethal infection 
 <bold>(
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1C</xref>)
 </bold>. That said, current evidence suggests that the most solid predictors of disease severity after infection with SARS-COV-2 are the patient's age and the concurrence of specific co-morbidities. In contrast, there is no proof (yet) that infection by a pauci-symptomatic person would result in a milder clinical course of immunocompetent neo-infected person.
</p>
