<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Estimating the amount of a specific virus provides more precise information than just determining the presence or absence of that virus. ELISA and molecular hybridization can be used for rough quantification of viral particles or nucleic acids based on the signal intensity (
 <xref rid="B210" ref-type="bibr">Rubio et al., 2003a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B201" ref-type="bibr">Rohrman et al., 2012</xref>). Real-time qPCR is a very accurate procedure to estimate virus titer with a wide dynamic range and great sensitivity. The principle is to monitor in each cycle the increase of fluorescence. The cycle at which amplification is observed (cycle threshold, CT) is related to the inverse Log of the quantity of target being amplified (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Boonham et al., 2014</xref>). Real-time qPCR or RT-qPCR has been developed for several plant viruses (
 <xref rid="B160" ref-type="bibr">Mumford et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B193" ref-type="bibr">Picó et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B141" ref-type="bibr">López et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B138" ref-type="bibr">Ling et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr">Hongyun et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B214" ref-type="bibr">Ruiz-Ruiz et al., 2009a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Debreczeni et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Ferriol et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B225" ref-type="bibr">Sharma and Dasgupta, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B144" ref-type="bibr">MacKenzie et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">Herrera-Vásquez et al., 2015</xref>). It has been applied to evaluate some disease control methods such as i) study interactions between viruses in mixed infections (
 <xref rid="B157" ref-type="bibr">Mortimer-Jones et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Abrahamian et al., 2013</xref>), which can be used for control based on cross protection (
 <xref rid="B215" ref-type="bibr">Ruiz-Ruiz et al., 2009b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">Hanssen et al., 2010</xref>); ii) estimation of correlation between virus accumulation and transmission by insect vectors (
 <xref rid="B176" ref-type="bibr">Olmos et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B204" ref-type="bibr">Rotenberg et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">Ferriol et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Debreczeni et al., 2014</xref>), which can be used for epidemiological studies and disease control strategies based on restricting the dispersion of viruses by vectors; iii) evaluation of the resistance level to virus accumulation in plant breeding programs (
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Gil-Salas et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">Galipienso et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B232" ref-type="bibr">Soler et al., 2015</xref>); and iv) estimation of fitness in competition and evolutionary experiments (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Carrasco et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B188" ref-type="bibr">Peña et al., 2014</xref>) which can be used for evolutionary and epidemiological studies, as well as for evaluation of resistance durability. HTS can be used for a relative quantification based on the number of reads for the same sequence, but it is still too expensive for these applications.
</p>
