<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?OLF?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Formos Med Assoc</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Formos. Med. Assoc</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of the Formosan Medical Association</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0929-6646</issn><issn pub-type="epub">0929-6646</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Formosan Medical Association. Published by Elsevier Taiwan LLC.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7127252</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S0929-6646(20)30044-9</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jfma.2020.02.007</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>First case of Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) pneumonia in Taiwan</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Shao-Chung</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Yuan-Chia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Fan Chiang</surname><given-names>Yu-Long</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Chien</surname><given-names>Yu-Chan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Mingte</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Chin-Hua</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Chia-Husn</given-names></name><email>4719@mail.tygh.gov.tw</email><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">g</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref><xref rid="fn2" ref-type="fn">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>Yuan-Nian</given-names></name><email>kingjen@mail.tygh.gov.tw</email><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">h</xref><xref rid="cor2" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;&#x02217;</xref><xref rid="fn2" ref-type="fn">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Division of Pulmonary Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, Sinwu Branch, Taoyuan General Hospital, Ministry of Health and Welfare, Taoyuan, Taiwan</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Radiology, Taoyuan General Hospital, Ministry of Health and Welfare, Taoyuan, Taiwan</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Sinwu Branch, Taoyuan General Hospital, Ministry of Health and Welfare, Taoyuan, Taiwan</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Department of Orthopedic Surgery, Sinwu Branch, Taoyuan General Hospital, Ministry of Health and Welfare, Taoyuan, Taiwan</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Department of Medical Imaging, National Taiwan University Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>Department of Biomedical Engineering and Environmental Science, National Tsing Hua University, Hsinchu, Taiwan</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>g</label>Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Department of Internal Medicine, Sinwu Branch, Taoyuan General Hospital, Ministry of Health and Welfare, Taoyuan, Taiwan</aff><aff id="aff8"><label>h</label>Department of Family Medicine, Taoyuan General Hospital, Ministry of Health and Welfare, Taoyuan, Taiwan</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. <email>4719@mail.tygh.gov.tw</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2"><label>&#x02217;&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. <email>kingjen@mail.tygh.gov.tw</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p id="ntpara0010">These three authors contributed equally.</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>2</label><p id="ntpara0015">No. 1492, Zhongshan Rd., Taoyuan Dist., Taoyuan City 33004, Taiwan (R.O.C.).</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><elocation-id/><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>17</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Formosan Medical Association. Published by Elsevier Taiwan LLC.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p>An outbreak of respiratory illness proved to be infected by a 2019 novel coronavirus, officially named Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19), was notified first in Wuhan, China, and has spread rapidly in China and to other parts of the world. Herein, we reported the first confirmed case of novel coronavirus pneumonia (NCP) imported from China in Taiwan. This case report revealed a natural course of NCP with self-recovery, which may be a good example in comparison with medical treatments.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>First case</kwd><kwd>Pneumonia</kwd><kwd>Taiwan</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">On December 31, 2019, an outbreak of respiratory illness later proved to be caused by a novel coronavirus, officially named Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19), was notified first in Wuhan, a city of Hubei province, People's Republic of China (PRC). COVID-19 rapidly spreads in China and to other parts of the world. Currently more than 70,000 laboratory-confirmed cases in China have been reported, and the case count has been rising daily. Some travelers-related transmission were also identified in many countries, including Taiwan, Singapore, Vietnam, Republic of Korea, Malaysia, Thailand, Japan, Germany, France, United States (U.S.), Australia, etc. through an international conveyance, and raised a global health emergency.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> As of February 18, 2020, there were 22 confirmed cases in Taiwan. Herein we presented the first case identified in Taiwan on January 21, 2020.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Case report</title><p id="p0015">On January 20, 2020, a 55-year-old woman who worked in Wuhan, China, arrived at Taiwan Taoyuan International Airport and presented to quarantine officials immediately, with a history of sore throat, dry cough, fatigue, and low-grade subjective fever since January 11, 2020. Owing to the outbreak of COVID-19 in Wuhan city and the announcement of related symptoms, she was immediately placed in quarantine ward and underwent examination. Although the patient denied spending time at the Huanan Seafood Wholesale Market and reported no known contact with ill people during her stay in Wuhan, specimens including oropharyngeal swab and sputum were collected for severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) real-time reverse-transcriptase-polymerase-chain-reaction (rRT-PCR) in accordance with the Taiwan Centers for Disease Control (TCDC) guidance.</p><p id="p0020">Apart from a history of hypothyroidism with regular medical follow-up, she had no other underlying disease before this onset. According to the records of quarantine officials, the vital sign of the patient showed body temperature (BT) of 38.0&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and oxygen saturation (SPO2) of 88&#x02013;90% under ambient air. Before seeking medical treatment in Taiwan, she bought over-the-counter medicine to release the symptoms. After admission to our hospital, her vital signs remained stable, apart from the exertional dyspnea, intermittent dry cough and sore throat (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>
). The initial physical examination revealed a BT of 36.4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, blood pressure of 93/53&#x000a0;mm Hg, pulse of 87 bpm, respiratory rate of 20 breath/min, and SPO2 of 91% while the patient was breathing supplement oxygen by nasal cannula at 3&#x000a0;L/min. The breathing sound was normal initially. The laboratory results reflected lymphopenia (531&#x000a0;cells/ul), and elevated aspartate aminotransferase (AST, 78 U/L), alanine aminotransferase (ALT, 41 U/L), C-reactive protein (CRP, 7.8&#x000a0;mg/L), and lactate dehydrogenase (LDH, 295 U/L) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>). A rapid screening test for influenza A and B showed negative. The chest X-ray revealed bilateral perihilar infiltration and ill-defined patchy opacities. On January 21, 2020, the TCDC confirmed that the patient's oropharyngeal swab and sputum tested positive for SARS-CoV-2 by rRT-PCR assay.<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Vital sign, symptoms, and examination by the day of illness and day of hospitalization, January 11 to February 07, 2020.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Fig.&#x000a0;1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p><p id="p0025">The results of serial chest X-rays performed on illness day 10 (hospital day 1), 13, 17, and 25 coincided with the changes in SPO2 and revealed slowing remission of worsening patches infiltrating at first (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>
). These radiographic findings and a subsequent chest computed tomography (CT) indicated the tenacious COVID-19 pneumonia and sequelae (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>
). Antitussive agent, O<sub>2</sub> supplement, careful saline infusion and empiric antibiotic with ceftriaxone (2&#x000a0;gm loading and 2&#x000a0;gm everyday intravenously) were administered at first. Subsequently, antibiotics were replaced by oral amoxicillin/clavulanate 875/125&#x000a0;mg every 12&#x000a0;h on illness day 17 for another 1 week. Her urine culture showed Streptococcus gallolyticus spp pasteurianus, which was susceptible to above antibiotics. Other cultures showed non-significance.<fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Chest X-ray showed progression of prominent bilateral perihilar infiltration and ill-defined patchy opacities at bilateral lungs, which slowly resolved on the follow-up image. (a: January 20; b: Jan. 23; c: Jan. 27; d: February 04).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Fig.&#x000a0;2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Chest CT in convalescent stage showed persistent multifocal GGOs with or without superimposed reticulation and mild fibrotic change at bilateral lungs, including peripheral subpleural regions of both lower lobes. Two small irregular opacities at the RUL and RML were probably partially resolved consolidations (arrows).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Fig.&#x000a0;3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3_lrg"/></fig></p><p id="p0030">On illness day 17, her sputum turned undetectable for SARS-CoV-2 by rRT-PCR assay. The results of subsequent rRT-PCR of oropharyngeal swabs and sputum on illness day 21 and 23, respectively, were repeatedly negative. Supplemental oxygen was discontinued on illness day 27, and her SPO2 improved to 92%&#x02013;98% under ambient air. The patient's clinical condition improved, apart from intermittent exertional dyspnea. Furthermore, the final results of rRT-PCR of stool and urine tests, which were not sent for tests in the beginning, were negative on illness day 25. She was then discharged on illness day 28 (February 07, 2020).</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0035">We reported the first confirmed case of novel coronavirus pneumonia (NCP) in Taiwan. In accordance with the first report from China, the major symptoms of COVID-19 infection were mainly cough, fever and dyspnea.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Our case presented with mild fever, dyspnea and mild hypoxemia on day 10 of initial illness. At the same time, the chest X-ray showed bilateral infiltrating pneumonia, which progressed diffusely later. The progression of symptoms in this case also coincided with the first confirmed COVID-19 case in the U.S., with fever on day 5 of illness, dyspnea with mild hypoxemia and radiographical pneumonia on day 9 of illness.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> Furthermore, reports from China showed all patients had bilateral pneumonia on high resolution CT with different severity even in mild cases.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> These findings suggested that lower respiratory tract seems to be an important location for the replication of SARS-CoV-2. Our case turned afebrile since admission (illness day 10), even without antiviral treatment. Despite pneumonia on chest X-rays worsen in the following seven days, respiratory failure did not occur eventually. Even though ceftriaxone was used, the evidence of negative culture and the worsening chest X-ray findings under antibiotic treatment were not compatible with the clinical picture of bacterial pneumonia. The effective medical treatment against COVID-19 remains unknown. In spite of the first-reported case in the U.S. showing promptly-subsided fever after Remdesivir used on day 12 of illness, with well-improved clinical symptoms later, the effectiveness of Remdesivir was still questioned.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> The randomized-controlled trial of treating Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus by the combination of lopinavir/ritonavir/interferon-beta-1b is ongoing, more evidence-based data are needed.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p0040">Some laboratory abnormalities in our case, such as elevated CRP, LDH, ALT and AST, were also observed in influenza virus pandemic.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> Lymphopenia has been considered as a poor prognostic factor for severe hospitalized influenza (H1N1) pandemic 2009,<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> as well as severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS).<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> These findings may explain common biomarker presentation in viral pneumonia, including COVID-19. The quarantine period for potentially COVID-19 infected individuals was challenging by our case's laboratory results, her sputum specimens remained positive for SARS-CoV-2 on day 15 and turned negative on day 17 of illness.</p><p id="p0045">Similar to viral pneumonia due to other etiologies, ground-glass opacities (GGOs) are the main CT findings of the patients with COVID-19.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Reticular and/or interlobular septal thickening, and consolidation are common associated findings.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> Crazy-paving pattern was also detected in some cases.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> Pure consolidation without GGO is less common.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> These lesions usually involve bilateral lungs.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Peripheral distribution of disease was noted in 33% and 85% of patients, respectively.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> However, normal scan at the early stage of COVID-19 can be found in a few patients when the disease is diagnosed.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p0050">As the NCP progresses, increasing size and density of these GGOs or crazy paving pattern were reported.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> On the contrary, the GGOs will decrease in size and the consolidations, if present, will decrease in density when patients gradually recover.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> Fibrotic change may be left as a sequela after recovery as was seen in patients recovering from SARS.<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p0055">Our case demonstrated a typical NCP without progression to ARDS. The worst status of her pneumonia was on illness day 17 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>c) and then gradually resolved. Given the negative rRT-PCR of SARS-CoV-2 on illness day 21 and 23, there were persistent milder bilateral lung opacities on the chest radiograph on illness day 25 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>d) which were corresponding to bilateral ill-defined GGO patches with or without reticulation, and mild fibrotic change on CT two days later (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>). Chest CT might be a tool to assist diagnosis accompanying with symptoms and traveling history, because the chest radiograph could be normal in those patients with mild or no symptoms.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</p><p id="p0060">In summary, our case revealed a natural course of NCP with self-recovery. Rapid diagnostic assays, effective treatment and wise use of chest CT will be crucial to contain the worldwide outbreak of COVID-19 in the future.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p id="p0065">The authors have no conflicts of interest relevant to this article.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>World Health Organization</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Novel coronavirus situation report -28</chapter-title><year>2020</year><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/docs/default-source/coronaviruse/situation-reports/20200217-sitrep-22-ncov.pdf?sfvrsn=fb6d49b1_2" id="intref0010">https://www.who.int/docs/default-source/coronaviruse/situation-reports/20200217-sitrep-22-ncov.pdf?sfvrsn=fb6d49b1_2</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical features of patients infected with 2019 novel coronavirus in Wuhan, China</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>S0140&#x02013;6736</volume><issue>20</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>30183</fpage><lpage>30185</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holshue</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>DeBolt</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindquist</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lofy</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiesman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First case of 2019 novel coronavirus in the United States</article-title><source>N Englera J Med</source><year>2020</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><comment>[Epub ahead of print]</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical characteristics of 138 hospitalized patients with 2019 novel coronavirus-infected pneumonia in Wuhan, China</article-title><source>J Am Med Assoc</source><year>2020</year><fpage>E1</fpage><lpage>E9</lpage><comment>[Epub ahead of print]</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arabi</surname><given-names>Y.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alothman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balkhy</surname><given-names>H.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Dawood</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>AlJohani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al Harbi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of Middle East respiratory syndrome with a combination of lopinavir-ritonavir and interferon-beta1b (MIRACLE trial): study protocol for a randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>Trials</source><volume>19</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29382391</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheong</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heo</surname><given-names>J.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Noh</surname><given-names>J.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yong</surname><given-names>H.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical, laboratory and radiologic characteristics of 2009 pandemic influenza A/H1N1 pneumonia: primary influenza pneumonia versus concomitant/secondary bacterial pneumonia</article-title><source>Influenza Other Respir Viruses</source><volume>5</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>e535</fpage><lpage>e543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21682848</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>C.X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for nosocomial infection among hospitalised severe influenza A(H1N1) pandemic 2009 patients</article-title><source>Respir Med</source><volume>134</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29413513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedley</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chau</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>I.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thach</surname><given-names>T.Q.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The epidemiology of severe acute respiratory syndrome in the 2003 Hong Kong epidemic: an analysis of all 1755 patients</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><volume>141</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>662</fpage><lpage>673</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15520422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emerging coronavirus 2019-nCoV pneumonia</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2020</year><fpage>200274</fpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi:%2010.1148/radiol.2020200274" id="intref0015">https://doi: 10.1148/radiol.2020200274</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernheim</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CT imaging features of 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV)</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2020</year><fpage>200230</fpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi:%2010.1148/radiol.2020200230" id="intref0020">https://doi: 10.1148/radiol.2020200230</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CT Imaging of the 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) pneumonia</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2020</year><fpage>200236</fpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi:%2010.1148/radiol.2020200236" id="intref0025">https://doi: 10.1148/radiol.2020200236</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>X.Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) pneumonia</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2020</year><fpage>200257</fpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi:%2010.1148/radiol.2020200257" id="intref0030">https://doi: 10.1148/radiol.2020200257</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CT manifestations of two cases of 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) pneumonia</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2020</year><fpage>200280</fpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi:%2010.1148/radiol.2020200280" id="intref0035">https://doi: 10.1148/radiol.2020200280</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Galvin</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pulmonary sequelae in convalescent patients after severe acute respiratory syndrome: evaluation with thin-section CT</article-title><source>Radiology</source><volume>236</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>1067</fpage><lpage>1075</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16055695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Imaging changes in patients with 2019-nCov</article-title><source>Eur Radiol</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00330-020-06713-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of CT manifestations in a patient recovered from 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) pneumonia in Wuhan, China</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2020</year><fpage>200269</fpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi:%2010.1148/radiol.2020200269" id="intref0040">https://doi: 10.1148/radiol.2020200269</ext-link></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors thank the dedicated medical team, Hsiu-Hsueh Tseng, PhD and Shu-Hsing Cheng, MD for manuscript preparation, professor Yeun-Chung Chang and professor Shan-Chwen Chang for expert opinions.</p></ack></back></article>