<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>COVID-19, the disease associated with SARS-CoV-2 infection, is in some 20% of acutely affected patients associated with respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) often necessitating respirator treatment and associated with a high mortality [
 <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Epidemics in Wuhan in China and Lombardy in Italy have been devastating, and SARS-CoV-2 has developed into a pandemic necessitating urgent worldwide co-operation. Until effective treatment of COVID-19 including a useful vaccination against SARS-CoV-2 is found, it is important to seek ways of limiting or avoiding ARDS. Virus-related ARDS is initiated from a high level of angiotensin II (Ang-II) via the type 1 receptor pathway [
 <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], and Ang-II has already been demonstrated to be high in COVID-19 and linearly associated with lung injury [
 <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Inhibitors of the renin–angiotensin system (RASi), cornerstones of treatment of patients with hypertension and heart failure, have attracted attention as they may in theory influence the Ang-II level in COVID-19 and thereby the risk of ARDS [
 <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In short, Ang-II activity is influenced by the balance of Ang-converting enzyme (ACE) and ACE2 receptor activity. The activity of ACE2 normally lowers the level of Ang-II, but SARS-CoV-2 virus binds to ACE2 receptors, lower their activity and hence increase Ang-II activity [
 <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. While RASi lower Ang-II levels, and may in this respect be helpful, chronic RASi treatment may on the other hand also increase pulmonary ACE2-receptor numbers hence providing a possible higher SARS-CoV-2 viral load. As suggested from animal experiments, chronic treatment with RASi can therefore, in theory, both increase and lower the risk of ARDS in SARS-CoV-2-infected patients. Studies early listed heart disease, hypertension, and diabetes as risk factors for ARDS [
 <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], but unfortunately medication has not yet been reported on, and clinical data on the relative importance of RASi for outcome in COVID-19 are now urgently needed.
</p>
