<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Using the six 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> accessions and the two virus isolates, we conducted a time course experiment of viral infection. For each 
 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> accession, 85 plants per virus were inoculated with JPN1-TuMV and Fny-CMV each, and the other 10 were mock inoculated. Five infected plants per accession were harvested at regular intervals. Because each accession has a different developmental schedule (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>), intervals were established such that samples were collected from plant inoculation to silique ripening, and data from at least 15 time points were obtained. For each harvested plant, the amount of virus in the rosette and in 1-cm pieces of the inflorescence, which included inflorescence leaves, flowers, and siliques, if present, was quantified. These measures were used to calculate the speed of virus within-host movement. In parallel, 10 infected plants plus the mock-inoculated controls were allowed to complete their life cycle. In these plants, virus multiplication in the rosette and the inflorescence and rosette, inflorescence, and seed weights were obtained (see below). Seeds from these plants were used to estimate seed transmission rates and short-, medium-, and long-term seed survival. Note that the speed of virus within-host movement was measured through destructive sampling, whereas the other infection traits were quantified in the set of plants that completed their life cycle. Thus, for model building, the speed of virus within-host movement was considered an accession-specific trait (the averaged value derived from the destructive sampling was attributed to all plants of the same accession), whereas the other infection traits were considered plant-specific traits. Using this data set, we constructed global multivariate models that jointly considered all infection traits measured for both viruses as predictors of the efficiency of seed transmission as well as virus-specific models where infection traits were considered for each virus separately (see “Statistical analysis,” below). In this way, we could differentiate infection traits broadly associated with seed transmission from virus-specific determinants of this process.
</p>
