<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig1">
 <label>Figure 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>SPR-Based Analysis of Human Plasma from EBOV-Infected Survivors and following ChAd3-MVA Vaccination to EBOV-GP Purified Protein</p>
  <p>(A) Serial dilutions of plasma samples collected from EBOV survivors (#28, black; #43, blue; #79, red; and #92, purple) or humans vaccinated with ChAd3-MVA vaccine (#58, pink triangle and #64, green triangle) or control (#36, empty circle) were analyzed for total binding to purified mature GP from EBOV/Makona strain by SPR. Total antibody binding is represented in SPR resonance units.</p>
  <p>(B) Total GP-binding antibody (Max RU) of human plasma against EBOV/Makona GP correlated with the homologous virus neutralization titers (PsVN; 
   <italic>r= 0.911,</italic> p &lt; 0.0008). Pearson correlations are reported for the calculation of correlations between total anti-GP antibody binding and PsVN titers.
  </p>
  <p>(C) Polyclonal antibody affinity to EBOV GP following ChAd3-MVA vaccination or EBOV infection in survivors. Binding affinity of serially diluted post-vaccination and post-infection plasma to EBOV/Makona-GP. Antibody off-rate constants that describe the fraction of antibody-antigen complexes decaying per second were determined directly from the plasma sample interaction with EBOV/Makona-GP using SPR in the dissociation phase as described in 
   <xref rid="sec5" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>.
  </p>
  <p>(D) Correlation between anti-GP-binding antibody affinity as measured by antibody dissociation rates (off-rates) and homologous virus neutralization titers (PsVNA80; 
   <italic>r= -0.539,</italic> p = 0.2698). The color scheme in (B)–(D) is the same as that in (A).
  </p>
  <p>(E) Antibody isotype of GP-binding antibodies following EBOV infection or ChAd3-MVA vaccination. The isotype composition of plasma antibodies bound to GP of EBOV/Makona isolate as measured in SPR. The resonance units for each anti-GP antibody isotype was divided by the total resonance units for all antibody isotypes combined to calculate the percentage of each antibody isotype for individual plasma.</p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="gr1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
