<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">Immaturity of the newborn immune system might contribute to the increased susceptibility to pathogens and to lower vaccine response when compared to adults. Due to this immaturity, routine childhood vaccination often requires multiple immunization to elicit full immunity. An earlier study with an Ad35 vector-based TB vaccine candidate in young infants (4–6 months of age) indeed demonstrated a lower cellular immune response rate and magnitude when compared to adults
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, potency of novel childhood vaccine candidates should preferentially be tested in neonatal nonclinical models prior to proceeding to clinical testing. However, it should be kept in mind that the ontogeny of the immune system differs between humans and different animal species. Animals with relatively short gestation periods (e.g. mice, rats) have relatively immature immune systems at birth with ongoing immune system development after birth compared to humans
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>. Even in the very immature immune system in mice of 4–5 days of age, Ad26.RSV.preF induced robust and durable immune responses. These responses were both qualitatively and quantitatively similar to those in animals immunized at 3–4 weeks of age when the immune system is considered to be matured
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup> and in adult mice. This suggests that responses to Ad26.RSV.preF are not severely affected by immaturity of the immune system, and that this vector might also be immunogenic in young infants. Recently, the potency of various RSV vaccine candidates was studied in larger infant animal models, for which the immune system ontogeny might better parallel the human situation. However, these studies do not describe a direct comparison of the vaccine potency or Th1/Th2 bias of the response between infants and adults of the same species. ΔF/TriAdj, a truncated adjuvanted fusion protein, was shown to be immunogenic in lambs, both in the presence and absence of maternal anti-RSV antibodies
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup>. Efficacy of adjuvanted bovine RSV F-based vaccine candidates has been demonstrated in calves in a species homologous bovine RSV infection model
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>. Interestingly, human RSV F, N and M2-1 antigens expressed by a chimpanzee Adenoviral vector were immunogenic and protected calves against challenge with the heterologous bovine RSV
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
