<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The outbreak of Zika infection in Brazil has exposed the high risk this arbovirus imposes during pregnancy to the fetus. Brazil experienced an approximately 20-fold increase in the total number of congenital microcephaly cases from 2014 to 2015, following the confirmation of autochthonous Zika virus transmission [
 <xref rid="pone.0201452.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In December 2015, the Brazilian Ministry of Health enhanced congenital microcephaly surveillance by implementing a more sensitive case definition, and added Zika to the list of “TORCHS” pathogens (Toxoplasmosis, Rubella, Cytomegalovirus, Herpes simplex virus, Syphilis) that are screened [
 <xref rid="pone.0201452.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0201452.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In February 2016, WHO declared the link between Zika virus and microcephaly to be a Public Health Emergency of International concern. Subsequently, several cases of microcephaly associated with mothers infected with Zika during pregnancy were reported in different Federal Units of Brazil, most of them in the Northeast region [
 <xref rid="pone.0201452.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Several studies have shown that the arbovirus can be transmitted vertically during pregnancy and cause congenital problems of the fetus. A recent case-control study performed in Recife, Pernambuco State, revealed that babies with microcephaly were 55 times more likely to have been infected with Zika virus during pregnancy than non-infected [
 <xref rid="pone.0201452.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The virus has been detected in the placenta, amniotic fluid and neural tissues of newborns with microcephaly [
 <xref rid="pone.0201452.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0201452.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In addition to microcephaly, other birth defects have been reported such as intracranial calcifications and abnormalities of the corpus callosum and the cerebellum, mainly when the exposure to the virus occurs during the first trimester of pregnancy [
 <xref rid="pone.0201452.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].
</p>
