<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Similar to neutrophils, monocytes are susceptible to IAV infection [
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>–
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>] irrespective of the subset [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], and infection rates may vary with the IAV subtype with the highest infectivity for H5N1 and H7N9 than pH1N1 [
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. Virus-infected monocytes secrete inflammatory cytokines and chemokines [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>) in a virus dose-dependent manner [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Infected monocytes produce large amounts of IFNs [
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>] well known for their anti-influenza activity in addition to serving as a source for an array of cytokines and chemokines; for example, U937 promonocytic cells produce IL-1
 <italic>β</italic>, IL-8, IL-18, CCL3 [
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>], and IFN-
 <italic>α</italic>/
 <italic>β</italic> [
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Importantly, the microenvironment of infected lungs drives monocyte differentiation into macrophages and DCs (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>) which play a pivotal role in phagocytosis of virus-infected cells thereby priming the adaptive immune system. During airway inflammation, migration and differentiation of blood monocytes contribute to the pool of pulmonary macrophages [
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The absence of CD14 on monocytes/macrophages alters the immunopathogenesis during complex disease-disease interactions that occur when IAV infects hosts with underlying allergic states [
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>] suggesting that the function of each subset is regulated by the inflammatory milieu during influenza. The role of monocyte-derived macrophages in protection from IAV infection is described elsewhere [
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>].
</p>
