<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For each homestead, which is comprised of a small cluster of traditional homes constructed of mud waddle and thatch roofing (mode: 5 huts, range 2–6 huts per homestead; median numbers of huts included per elevation were similar), 2 Tomahawk and 2 Sherman traps were set inside of each hut, 8 Tomahawk and 8 Sherman traps were set in the family compound outside of the huts, and 64 traps comprised of 32 Tomahawk and 32 Sherman traps were set in the peridomestic setting extending 40 m away from the huts. One Tomahawk and one Sherman trap was placed per trap station and trap stations were set 10 m apart radiating from the homestead in the 4 cardinal and 4 inter-cardinal directions (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035598-g002">figure 2</xref>). Traps were baited with a mixture of 1/3 corn, 1/3 ground nuts, and 1/3 dried fish. For each trap session, trapping was conducted for two consecutive nights with rodents retrieved each morning and traps reset at dusk. We acknowledge that our sampling is biased towards nocturnally active small mammals and abundances of diurnal rodents, such as 
 <italic>Arvicanthis niloticus</italic> may be underrepresented. Upon capture, small mammals were anesthetized using an inhalation anesthetic (halothane). Sedated animals were measured, weighed, identified to genus or species and combed for fleas. For host species that could not be identified to species because of a lack of morphological differences that were detectable in the field, individuals were identified to genus (e.g., 
 <italic>Crocidura spp.</italic>, 
 <italic>Mastomys spp.</italic> and 
 <italic>Praomys spp.</italic>). Collected fleas were preserved in 70% ethanol for later identified to species following published taxonomic keys 
 <xref rid="pone.0035598-Haselbarth1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0035598-Hopkins1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0035598-Smit1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0035598-Hopkins2" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. All animal procedures described in the study were approved by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention Division of Vector Borne Diseases Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (protocol 09-023).
</p>
