<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The DNA of 30 cats (15 from the Valdivia area, 15 from Chiloe Island) was extracted from 0.3 m
 <italic>l</italic> peripheral whole blood samples as described by [
 <xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The eukaryotic 18S RNA Pre-Developed TaqMan Assay Reagents (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, U.S.A.) were used as internal reference for cat genomic DNA amplification, to ensure the quality of each sample for PCR amplification and that negative results corresponded to true negative samples rather than to a problem with DNA loading, sample degradation or PCR inhibition. Real-time PCR (qPCR) targeting 
 <italic>Ehrlichia/Anaplasma</italic> spp., piroplasmids, 
 <italic>Rickettsia</italic> spp. and 
 <italic>Bartonella</italic> spp. was performed as previously described [
 <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The thermal cycling profile was 50°C 2 min and 95°C 10 min followed by 40 cycles at 95°C 15 sec and 60°C 1 min, using a QuantStudioTM 12K Flex Real-Time PCR System (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, U.S.A.). Sterile water was used as a negative PCR control and positive controls were obtained from commercial slides coated with cells infected with the pathogens (MegaScreen
 <sup>®</sup> 118 FLUOEHRLICHIA c., MegaScreen
 <sup>®</sup> FLUOBABESIA canis, MegaScreen
 <sup>®</sup> FLUORICKETTSIA 119 ri., MegaScreen
 <sup>®</sup> BARTONELLA h. (Megacor, Hörbranz, Vorarlberg, Austria). Target genes amplified for each pathogen, primers used and sequencing of each positive qPCR product was conducted as previously described [
 <xref rid="r53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] (
 <xref rid="tbl_001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Positive samples were sequenced with the BigDye Terminator Cycle Sequencing Ready Reaction Kit (AB, Life Technologies). The sequences obtained were compared with sequences from the GenBank database (www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/BLAST). Ultrapure water was employed as negative control in each PCR run and sequenced positive cat samples were used as positive controls.
</p>
