<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0085">The proportion of case fatalities among HCP during the SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV epidemics was 12% (12 of 98) and 7% (9 of 128), respectively.
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>32</sup>
 </xref> In the United States, from February 12, to April 9, 2020, of the 315,531 COVID-19 cases reported to the CDC, 9282 (3%) were identified as occurring in HCP. Most HCP with COVID-19 (6760; 90%) were not hospitalized. Severe outcomes, including 27 deaths, occurred across all age groups, although death frequently occurred in HCP aged 65 years or older. These preliminary findings have highlighted that, regardless of whether HCP acquire the infection at work or in the community, it is necessary to protect the health and safety of this essential national workforce (
 <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> ). If HCP have been exposed to a patient with COVID-19 or a patient suspected to have COVID-19, the recommended data collection forms available should be used to assess the healthcare worker's risk of exposure and, any breaches in infection prevention and control policies. The World Health Organization emphasizes the importance of direct face-to-face communication with HCP in a blame free environment. A daily self-check method should be established for all HCP. The CDC self-checker is an example of such a survey that can be used by the staff (available at: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/331496/WHO-2019-nCov-HCW_risk_assessment-2020.2-eng.pdf" id="intref0025" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/331496/WHO-2019-nCov-HCW_risk_assessment-2020.2-eng.pdf</ext-link>; 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/guidance-risk-assesment-hcp.html" id="intref0030" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/hcp/guidance-risk-assesment-hcp.html</ext-link>; and 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/technical-guidance/health-workers" id="intref0035" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/technical-guidance/health-workers</ext-link>). Generally, 5 strategies represented by a hierarchical model are included to protect personnel from exposure to occupational hazards: 
 <italic>1)</italic> elimination, 
 <italic>2)</italic> substitution, 
 <italic>3)</italic> engineering controls (ie, ventilation, pressure differential of rooms, ultraviolet [UV] germicidal irradiation [UVGI]), 
 <italic>4)</italic> administrative controls (ie, staggering work schedules of staff to limit exposure and crowding of offices, facilitating working from home when feasible), and 
 <italic>5)</italic> PPE. Elimination offers the best protection, and the use of PPE offers the least protection. These strategies can be implemented concurrently and/or sequentially.
</p>
