<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Lastly, host adaptive mutations may affect the regulation of transcription and genome replication in specific hosts. Several models have been proposed over the years for the mechanism that regulates the switch from viral mRNA transcription to cRNA transcription and subsequent vRNA replication. A detailed analysis of viral transcription and replication indicates that initial transcripts produced from infecting IAV virions can be detected rapidly following infection. Viral mRNA can be detected almost immediately following infection while cRNA can be detected within four hours and further genome replication to produce both vRNA and cRNA can continue thereafter [
 <xref rid="B80-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Some studies suggest that the non-structural nuclear export protein (NEP/NS2) or small viral RNAs play a role in regulating the switch from viral transcription to genome replication by directly interacting with the vRdRp [
 <xref rid="B81-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,
 <xref rid="B82-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. However, it was also found that in vitro, the presence of high concentrations of additional copies of the vRdRp was able to trigger the switch from mRNA transcription to replication [
 <xref rid="B83-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. This is somewhat in agreement with this recent structural data which suggest that the dimerization of two vRdRps is required for the initiation of vRNA synthesis from a cRNA template and that this dimerization interface involves the C-terminal domain of PA and N-terminal domain of PB2 [
 <xref rid="B6-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The residues in PA that are involved in this dimerization are 352–356 and a number of host-adaptive mutations have been observed in this area including 336M, 349G, and 356R [
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. The host adaptive mutation, K356R, is one of the residues identified to be involved in dimerization. This mutation, which was characterized in an avian H9N2 virus, increases vRdRp activity, viral replication in cell culture, and pathogenicity in a mouse model. How this mutation may contribute to dimerization of the vRdRp remains to be seen [
 <xref rid="B70-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. It is possible that the dimerization of the polymerase could be regulated in a species-specific manner and be related to host-adaptation [
 <xref rid="B84-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Future studies will be necessary to test the effect of these and other previously identified mutations on dimerization and the switch from viral mRNA transcription to viral genome replication. 
</p>
