<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Human iSLK.219 cells (Dox-inducible SLK carrying rKSHV.219), derived from SLK cells (although a recent study reported SLK is not of endothelial origin, but is a contaminant from a known renal carcinoma cell line [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008156.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]), are latently infected with a recombinant rKSHV.219 virus and contain a doxycycline (Dox)-inducible RTA, constructed and named by Dr. Don Ganem’s lab [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008156.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The rKSHV.219 virus expresses both the red fluorescent protein (RFP) under the control of KSHV lytic PAN promoter and the green fluorescent protein (GFP) under the control of the elongation factor 1 promoter (EF-1α) [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008156.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. The iSLK.219 cells can be reactivated and then to release infectious virion progeny under the condition of Dox (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) in combination with sodium butyrate (NaB) (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) as described previously [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008156.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. HEK293T (Human embryonic kidney 293T) cells were purchased from American Type Culture Collection (ATCC) and cultured as recommended by the manufacturer. Body cavity-based lymphoma cells (BCBL-1, KSHV
 <sup>+</sup>/EBV
 <sup>neg</sup>) cells were kindly provided by Dr. Dean Kedes (University of Virginia) and maintained in RPMI 1640 medium with supplements (10% fetal bovine serum, 10 mM HEPES, 100 U/mL penicillin, 100 μg/mL streptomycin, 2 mM L-glutamine, 0.05 mM β-mercaptoethanol, and 0.02% sodium bicarbonate). The lytic replication in BCBL-1 was induced by 20 ng/mL 12-O-tetradecanoyl-phorbol-13-acetate (PMA/TPA) (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) as described previously [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008156.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The antagonists and agonists of histamine receptors were all purchased from Sigma-Aldrich. SB203580, Ly294002 and A6730 were obtained from Selleck Chemicals (Houston, TX, USA).
</p>
