<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Garissa County</italic>: The Garissa study site (0° 27’ 25” S, 39° 39’ 30” E, 151 m elevation), has an annual mean temperature and rainfall of 28.8°C and 576 mm respectively, with high inter-annual inter-variability in rainfall. The vegetation in the area is mainly Acacia-Commiphora deciduous bush land and thicket (Savannah, Shrub land, open to very open shrubs) and on the coastal end lies the Boni Forest with indigenous open canopy forest that forms part of the Northern Zanzibar-Inhamdare Coastal Forest Mosaic. The site includes sandstones, dark clays and red sand soils. The site covers areas of Garissa, Ijara, and Lamu located between Tana River County and the boundary to Somalia (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0007979.g001">Fig 1</xref>). It has a population of 623,060 with most inhabitants from the Somali ethnic group. We sampled from Ijara, Fafi, Lamu East, and Lamu West sub-counties all in Garissa county. The main economic livelihood for the people living in Garissa is keeping nomadic livestock. About 90% of the population is directly dependent on livestock for daily nourishment and as a source of income. In Garissa, large livestock herds have to be moved during the dry season in search of pasture and water to the Tana River delta or into the Boni forest, which leads them through human settlements, wildlife and/or villages, different ecological zones (agro-pastoral, bushed low-lying grassland and dry humid ecological zones) and brings them in contact with wildlife (warthogs, gerenuk, waterbuck and buffalo) and different vector communities (
 <italic>Aedes</italic> and 
 <italic>Culex</italic> mosquitoes). It is classified as a RVF high risk zone [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007979.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007979.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] and is a major hotspot area in Kenya affected by the last outbreaks of RVF in 1997/98 and 2006/07 with over 300 cases reported [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007979.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007979.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].
</p>
