<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0115">After entry of virus in to the cell, IL-6 is produced by activated leukocytes and acts on a large number of cells and tissues. Levels of tumor necrosis factor α (TNF-α), IL-1β, IL-8, IL-12, monocyte chemoattractant protein 1 (MCP1), macrophage inflammatory protein 1A (MIP1A)and interferon-gamma inducible protein (IP10) are also increased in SARS CoV-2 infected patients as shown in 
 <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> [
 <xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The incidence of ARDS, shock, secondary infection, acute kidney injury and heart was significantly higher in patients with intensive care unit (ICU) than in non-ICU patients. The main proportion of IL-6 above normal was significantly higher than that in the patients. Infection with MERS coronavirus can induce increased concentration of pro-inflammatory cytokines (tumor 616 necrosis factor α, IL15, and IL17, and interferon-γ,). The severe COVID-19 cases may benefit from IL-6 pathway inhibition given the associated Cytokine Release Syndrome (CRS) and sHLH (Secondary hemophagocytic lymphohistiocytosis) like serum cytokine elevations, which may be a target of the treatment of COVID-19 infected patients [
 <xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Excessive tissue damage is occurred owing to the excessive release of cytokines. In some cases, a reaction takes place which is labeled as ‘cytokine storm’. This is given in 
 <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> with its possible treatments [
 <xref rid="bb0180" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. It is able to promote the differentiation of B lymphocytes, promotes the growth of some categories of cells, and inhibits the growth of others [
 <xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].CD4
 <sup>+</sup>T/CD8
 <sup>+</sup>T counts continued to decline until death. Wan et al. found that CD4
 <sup>+</sup>T and CD8
 <sup>+</sup>T were lower in severe patients, which suggested that lymphocytes were more inhibited in severe patients. Lymphocytopenia may be related to a cytokine storm caused by viral invasion. In mild patient, reduction rate of CD4
 <sup>+</sup>T, CD8
 <sup>+</sup>T, B cell is less as compared to severe patients [
 <xref rid="bb0185" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].
</p>
