<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">Virus prediction from the signal intensity data has been the subject of intense study. Unlike gene expression microarrays, diagnostic microarrays have no up or down-regulated gene. In diagnostic microarray, a signal cannot be low, high, or unchanged; it has to be defined in binary numbers—present or absent, on or off. A signal is defined as present if it is above a predefined cutoff. This cutoff signal has arrived differently as the microarray technology for diagnosis developed. In the first broad-spectrum microarray chip, the control hybridization was carried out with the RNA from uninfected cell culture. In this particular chip, each spot was spiked with a known probe in a fixed ratio to normalize the expression of all the probes. The complementary sequence of the spike probe was labeled with Cy3 dye. Two color hybridization experiments were done for both infected and uninfected cell culture. The Cy5 signal for each probe was normalized against Cy3 signal. Cy5 labeled-infected and uninfected signal for each probe were calculated; from these values, a value of 1500 was arbitrarily defined as cutoff value, and the prediction was based on aggregate hybridization (Wang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2003</xref>). In diagnostic arrays, it is not always possible to have controls for identifying cutoff value like Wang et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2003</xref>) where they used mock-infected cell culture as control. To overcome this control problem, random probes which have no sequence similarity with NR database have been introduced (Gardner et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2010</xref>). If control samples are available, they are used for calculating the cutoff value; otherwise signal intensity of random probes is used for calculating cutoff value. The cutoff value is kept at median + 2 SD of the random probe signal intensity, 95–99% percentile of random signal intensity (Gardner et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2010</xref>). The virus identification from the signal intensity data makes use of different approaches. The simplest approach for predicting presence of virus in the sample is based on averaging signal intensity of all the probes of a virus or virus genus/family: if it is above a cutoff value, virus is predicted to be present; the other approach is based on the number/percentage of probes giving positive signal above a preset threshold (Sharma et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2012</xref>; Yadav et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2015</xref>). The first broad-spectrum virus-detecting microarray chip, ViroChip, made prediction based on the aggregate hybridization pattern (Wang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">2003</xref>). Chou et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2006</xref>) adopted similar criteria but with some modifications. Their method makes use of both signal intensity and a number of probes for making prediction. First, sum of all the signal intensity of a probe set is calculated, and then this is divided by the maximum intensity obtained for any group in the probe set. Based on the percentage, prediction is made. For the GreenChip (Palacios et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2007</xref>), virus prediction was done by a specially developed software called Green-LAMP. This software subtracts background values from the probe intensities, calculate Z-score from log intensities by dividing with standard deviation and compute tail probabilities (p-value) assuming log normality. Presence of a positive or negative signal is computed from a fixed P-value threshold, 0.1 for arrays with matched controls and 0.023 otherwise. The background levels are derived from matched control samples or from random 60-mer control probes if matched control samples are not present. The following assumptions were made for making predictions: (1) spot intensities are normally distributed, (2) spots represent independent observations, and (3) there are relatively few (&lt;100) positive probes for any given virus. DetectiV (Watson et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2007</xref>) tool was developed for handling array data by selecting groups of probes comprising a species, genus, or family and computing a one-sample t-test with null hypothesis that log intensity ratio for each group is zero. PhyloDetect (Rehrauer et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">2008</xref>), another tool for making virus prediction, converts the probe intensities to binary indicators (e.g., by thresholding against the median + 2 SD of the background intensities). In Pan-Microbial Detection Array (MDA) (Gardner et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2010</xref>), the threshold for positive signal was kept at 99th percentile of negative controls which were randomly generated probes. Prediction for presence or absence of a pathogen was based upon two conditional probabilities: the probability of observing a signal in the presence of a specific microbial target in sample and the probability of observing signal in the absence of microbial target in the sample. Liu et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2006</xref>) compared five different methods of virus prediction and concluded that hypergeometric distribution and log transform ranking method give good prediction, but other methods like the number of probes with a threshold or ratio method also give suitable prediction.
</p>
