<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ebolavirus transmission to wildlife via fruit contamination by infected bat saliva or faeces has been a prevailing hypothesis [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. But frugivory could also be associated with Ebolavirus transmission through a variety of mechanisms. Fruiting phenology, often corresponding to dry seasons when other food resources may be scarce, could increase interspecific contact and probability of transmission. In addition to support for seasonal shifts from wet to dry conditions as triggers of Ebolavirus spillover [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], Ebola outbreaks in apes are known to have occurred in dry seasons, during which fruit consumption made lead to direct or indirect contact between primates and bats [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Recent analyses of viral sequences suggest that primates are more likely to be reservoirs of the Tai Forest and Bundibugyo Ebolaviruses than bats [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. This, combined with recent observations of gorilla foraging (successive temporal foraging on fruiting trees) suggests that Ebolavirus transmission is linked to seasonally dynamic behaviours in primates that centre on resource availability [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Reliance on seasonally available resources may also affect the timing of pregnancy in primates [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], which may have implications for susceptibility. Finally, over 70% of animals harvested for bushmeat in the moist forests of West and Central Africa were frugivorous to some degree, suggesting that bushmeat of frugivorous mammals is more likely to present a transmission pathway of Ebolavirus to humans [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>].
</p>
