<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since Manipur has the highest HIV prevalence rate in the country, any study with respect to HIV/AIDS in this region need to encourage not only to solve the health issues, but also the development issue of the country as whole. The prime cause of the HIV pandemic in this international border area is the uses of ‘heroin’ which are smuggled from the ‘South Asia Golden Triangle’. This study indicates that drug abuse, social stigma, geographical location and resource limitation and socio-political problem of the region have contributed strongly on spreading and failure of preventive program of HIV/AIDS. The HIV pandemic in this border region is much more complex than any other region of the country due to the emergence of recombinant HIV forms and DR HIV-1. Intravenous drug use and complex patterns of cross-border movement have combined to produce serious problems of HIV/AIDS pandemic. Improved knowledge about the causes, challenges and current scenario of HIV/AIDS should lead to improvement in the investigation and treatment of patients. However, in-depth studies such as the role of the emerging genetic variant in response to antiretroviral treatment, effect of co-infections with different viruses, etc., need to be inspired in all international borders to limit the expansion of more complex form of virus. It has also become evident that the importance to heighten the HIV testing coverage scale across the entire international region to reduce the risky behaviour of IDUs. The collaborative approaches to HIV prevention across all international borders as whole are anticipated in future. These will not only improve HIV prevention in international border region but also help to increase and diversify cross-border collaboration in HIV prevention and public health. These will certainly help to thrust for positive changes in governmental policies related to drug use and HIV prevention. Nevertheless, the information generated from this study will provide vital information for the policy makers, medical practitioners and researchers in adopting new strategies in restraining the transmission across the border area. The understanding developed from this study on the profile of the HIV-1 variants, DR, co-infections and main mode of transmission in a ‘geographic recombination hotspots’ may help to fight back the deadly AIDS pandemic.</p>
