<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Epidemiological models such as disease transmission models or game theoretical models can be used to address how disease dynamics unfold over time and influence risk perception and behavior in a single population
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>. Previous disease transmission models have addressed the issue of how HAART optimism may occur and how it may influence disease dynamics and/or behavior. For example, Ramadanovic 
 <italic>et al.</italic> focus on changing risk behaviors in the context of preventive HIV treatment
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>. The authors create a deterministic compartmental model that treats HIV risk behavior and infection as linked processes wherein the individual increases risk behavior as a precursor to contracting HIV. Ramadanovic 
 <italic>et al.</italic> demonstrate that HIV incidence and prevalence only decline above threshold levels of HAART coverage, indicating a strong connection that is dependent on risk behavior parameter values. Results showed that expanding HAART coverage combined with interventions aimed to reduce risky behaviors would amplify the preventative impact and possibly eliminate the HIV epidemic. A model of HIV and vaccination by Smith? 
 <italic>et al.</italic>, defines a fitness ratio as the average number of secondary HIV infections caused by an infected vaccinated individual, divided by the basic reproduction number
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>. By holding risk behavior constant, they were able to determine thresholds at which HIV prevalence would increase instead of decrease due to the vaccine, in the case that disease modifying vaccines provide only a low degree of protection against infection and/or generate high fitness ratios. Their findings report that the success of a vaccination campaign hinges upon the fitness ratio, the proportion of the population that were vaccinated, and the degree of change of risk behavior in unvaccinated infected individuals
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>.
</p>
