<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We have proposed that KD pathogens may be a species of normal flora of the host (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). The disturbance of microbiota of the host, i.e., dysbiosis, has been reported in a variety of diseases, including obesity, autism spectrum disorders, allergic diseases, cancers, and autoimmune diseases such as inflammatory bowel disease, JIA and KD (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>–
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). It has been known that microbiota differ across ethnic groups along with different cultural environments such as diets, antibiotic use, and possibly genetic factors (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>–
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Kinumaki et al. reported that 
 <italic>Streptococcus</italic> spp. in intestinal microbiota markedly increased during the acute phase of KD, and suggested that KD-related streptococci may be involved in the pathogenesis of KD (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Recently, Esposito et al. reviewed the possible role of the microbiota-host partnership on etiology and pathogenesis of KD (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Because normal flora spread via colonization in individuals in populations, a new disease that is associated with normal flora may take a long period of time during which to spread, and would show different incidences across populations at given times as shown in KD epidemiology in Asian countries. Since pathogens exist in healthy human reservoirs as normal flora, the diseases may occur mainly in immunologically or genetically susceptible groups such as young children group that have developing immune system and microbiota (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Also, the epidemiology in these diseases can change over time along with an increasing number of people who obtain pathogens as normal flora in the populations, since normal flora that have adapted to the host may be less virulent compared to initial external pathogens. For example, scarlet fever caused by Group A beta-hemolytic streptococcus (GAS) was a severe disease in the past, with two notorious complications: acute rheumatic fever (ARF) and APSGN. Now, scarlet fever, ARF and APSGN have become rare diseases with a milder clinical phenotype in the developed countries (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). However, pharyngitis caused by GAS without complications is not uncommon, and a relatively high proportion of GAS carriers among healthy children have been reported in the developed countries (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). In addition, GAS strains have been susceptible to penicillin throughout the antibiotic era, with few genetic variations (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Given that the evolutional purpose of external pathogens may be to become a species of normal flora in the host, these findings suggest that GAS strains may be changing to be part of normal flora in humans, though ARF still occurs in small populations (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). Thus, it is natural that initially severe diseases take on milder phenotypes over time, as shown in scarlet fever, pandemic influenza, and AIDS (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). It was also reported that recently diagnosed KD patients showed a less severe clinical phenotype, manifesting a higher incidence of incomplete KD and a lower incidence of CALs and less activated laboratory values such as C-reactive protein and albumin compared to patients who developed the disease in earlier periods (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>).
</p>
