<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We constructed a modified model for smallpox transmission. Population residual immunity and contact mixing are based on assumptions used in our previous study [
 <xref rid="pone.0217704.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Using ordinary differential equations as described in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217704.s001">S1 File</xref>, the population moves through the disease compartmental epidemiological states of being susceptible, exposed, infected and recovered (SEIR) from smallpox. Once infected, people move into the next state following disease duration rates. Euler’s approximation was used to estimate age-specific force of infection, assuming contact would be similar to observed patterns in the UK [
 <xref rid="pone.0217704.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0217704.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Different infectivity levels were based on the reproduction number for hemorrhagic, flat, ordinary and modified smallpox as previously described [
 <xref rid="pone.0217704.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The force of infection was multiplied by a parameter (α1, α2, α3, α4) to account for different population susceptibility levels. Model parameters and their estimation are described in our previous study [
 <xref rid="pone.0217704.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The model runs for 300 days. The model assumptions are shown in 
 <xref rid="pone.0217704.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. To test the preparedness of the health system we assumed the base case response would be case isolation and treatment, contact tracing and ring vaccination. As the study was examining health system factors, ring vaccination was kept constant in the model at 90% with assumed adequate vaccine supply and trained vaccinators, and 95–98% vaccine efficacy for uninfected people and 50–53% for latent infected [
 <xref rid="pone.0217704.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0217704.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0217704.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] as described in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217704.s001">S1 File</xref>.
</p>
