<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0095">There seems to be an inverse relationship in the overall number of COVID-19 cases and malaria cases [
 <xref rid="bib110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib114" ref-type="bibr">[114]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib115" ref-type="bibr">[115]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib116" ref-type="bibr">[116]</xref>]. For instance, three of the African countries most affected by COVID-19 on 4 June 2020 are South Africa (37 525 cases and 792 deaths), Algeria (9733 cases and 673 deaths) and Egypt (28 615 cases and 1088 deaths), which belong to the countries less affected by malaria [
 <xref rid="bib117" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]. The use of antimalarial drugs to treat uncomplicated malaria in Africa could be another hypothesis explaining the relatively low number of confirmed cases in Africa [
 <xref rid="bib118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. Since 2002, the WHO has recommended the use of artemisinin-based combination therapy (ACT) in the treatment of uncomplicated falciparum malaria (artemether-lumefantrine, artesunate-amodiaquine, dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine or artesunate-mefloquine) (
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). In 2018, these ACTs were widely used (
 <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). These ACTs, evaluated at plasma concentrations expected after oral uptake at the recommended doses used in uncomplicated malaria treatment, showed an 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> inhibition of SARS-CoV-2 replication that ranged from 30% to 70% [
 <xref rid="bib119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. The combination mefloquine-artesunate was found to be the most effective 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> against SARS-CoV-2. A patient treated with ACT for uncomplicated malaria could be protected from SARS-CoV-2 during treatment. Another study reported that some artemisinin derivatives used alone (dihydroartemisinin and artesunate) showed 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> activity with median effective concentration (EC
 <sub>50</sub>) around 10 μM [
 <xref rid="bib120" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>]. Moreover, amodiaquine, a quinoleine antimalarial and one of the partners of artemisinin derivative, was found to be active 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> at a micromolar concentration against SARS-CoV-1 (2.5 μM) [
 <xref rid="bib121" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>]. Another ACT partner, mefloquine, exerts 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> cytopathic effects on Vero cells infected by SARS-CoV-2 at 10 μM [
 <xref rid="bib122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. A molecular docking study showed that pyronaridine, another ACT partner (artesunate-pyronaridine), can interact with the non-structural protein 5 (Nsp5), which is an essential protein for the transcription and replication of SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="bib123" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>]. Pyronaridine showed effective antiviral activity with EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 0.72 μM and pyronaridine is 165 times more concentrated in lungs than in plasma (Pradines B, unpublished data). The use of antimalarial drugs and the dynamics of COVID-19 should now be compared on a country-by-country basis to confirm the potential effects of antimalarial drugs on COVID-19 transmission. It could be necessary now to evaluate clinically the efficacy of ACT to treat COVID-19, and more particularly that of mefloquine-artesunate, and the potential prevention of ACT against SARS-CoV-2 during malaria season, which currently begins in some African countries, taking into account the antimalarial drug, its dose, the number of treated patients, the number of cases of COVID-19 and deaths.
</p>
