<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0120">In order to effectively address the opioid epidemic, several important actions are urgently needed:
 <list list-type="simple" id="olist0010">
  <list-item id="o0010">
   <label>1.</label>
   <p id="p0125">Increasing access to MOUD (buprenorphine, methadone, and extended-release naltrexone) is urgently needed to treat persons with OUD, which means that federal and local government agencies should provide funding to access these medications through Medicaid or local state government , similar to how the CARE Act provided funding for ART for PLWH.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0015">
   <label>2.</label>
   <p id="p0130">Expanding training and education of all health care professionals from students through practicing providers in all disciplines (physicians of all disciplines, nurses, physician assistants, dentist, pharmacists, midwives) regarding how to screen, diagnose, and treat OUD and other SUDs is needed.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0020">
   <label>3.</label>
   <p id="p0135">Removal of federal and local barriers to accessing treatment of OUD, including removal of the DATA 2000 X-waiver mandatory training to provide buprenorphine and removal of limitations of numbers of persons with OUD who can be treated by a provider, are needed to combat the opioid epidemic.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0025">
   <label>4.</label>
   <p id="p0140">Removal of prior authorizations that are burdensome to doctors and also impede the ability to provide in-the-moment appropriate life-saving medication treatment of OUD when a patient requests it is needed.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0030">
   <label>5.</label>
   <p id="p0145">Successful directed stigma reduction regarding persons living with OUDs and substance use in general is required to combat the opioid epidemic, and this involves all persons, including providers, administrators, the community, the media, and patients.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0035">
   <label>6.</label>
   <p id="p0150">Accessible widespread harm reduction services are needed to combat the dueling opioid and HIV epidemics, especially in light of the polysubstance epidemics that include an increase in methamphetamine use, that does not have effective medications to treat it. Thus, services must expand to provide clean syringes, fentanyl testing, and naloxone distribution. Further, federal dollars should be released to states to fund provision of the syringes, fentanyl test strips, and naloxone, along with the staff to provide them.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
