<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>RT-LAMP offers improved sensitivity and specificity in screening SARS-CoV, HCoV-NL63, and MERS-CoV compared to conventional real-time RT-PCR [
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>–
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Recently, Yu et al. used a commercial LAMP kit to amplify fragmented ORF
 <italic>1ab</italic> genes of 2019-nCoV (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3(b)</xref> and (c)) [
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. They optimized the LAMP system through incubation at 65°C for different periods using a 2019-nCoV-positive RNA sample as the template. Results require a 15 min reaction time at 65°C, and detection sensitivity is comparable to that of the TaqMan-based qPCR approach (10 copies). RT-LAMP employs two additional protocols for 2019-nCoV RNA detection. Park et al. performed RT-LAMP at 65°C for 40 min to identify the nsp3, S, and N genes of 2019-nCoV using colorimetric detection [
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. The sensitivity of this RT-LAMP assay was 100 copies of 2019-nCoV RNA. The other RT-LAMP protocol was conducted at 63°C for 30 min to detect the ORF
 <italic>1ab</italic>, E, and N genes simultaneously [
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The results confirmed the specific nature of ORF
 <italic>1ab</italic> and the high sensitivity of the N gene. Based on an analysis of 208 clinical specimens, the sensitivity of this RT-LAMP was similar to conventional RT-PCR, and the specificity was 99%. Interestingly, EI-Tholoth et al. designed a two-stage isothermal amplification procedure by combining RPA (37°C) with LAMP (63°C) to detect synthesized DNA fragments of 2019-nCoV [
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. The test was performed in closed tubes within 1 h using either fluorescence or colorimetric detection. This method has a sensitivity of 100 times better than conventional LAMP and RT-PCR, suggesting a rapid, sensitive, point-of-care test for use at home.
</p>
