<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There is no clear evidence that genetic liability to schizophrenia increases the likelihood of influenza infection or predisposes to a disrupted immune response to influenza, or that influenza genetic risk loci are implicated in schizophrenia. In terms of genetic risk for influenza infection, while significant genetic effects accounting for the antibody level in influenza A and B (
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>) have been reported with 
 <italic>h</italic>
 <sup>2</sup> (heritability) range of 0.20–0.27 and 
 <italic>c</italic>
 <sup>2</sup> (shared environnment) = 0.19 for influenza A and B (
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>), results for discrete serostatus (seropositive/seronegative) were significant for influenza B only. However, another GWAS of IgG response to viruses identified HLA class II residues as causal variants and found an overlap between variants affecting the humoral response to influenza A and variants linked to influenza-related autoimmune disorders including narcolepsy (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>). Neither of these studies nor any others to date have directly addressed the issue of overlap between genetic risk for schizophrenia and specific risk for influenza infection, although this has been explored for other pathogens (
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>–
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>). A UK population-based cohort study of 7,921 mothers found no association between schizophrenia polygenic risk score (PRS) and perinatal infection (using a single “any infection” category) (
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>). Similarly, a case-control study by Benros et al. explored an association between schizophrenia PRS and a history of hospital contacts for viral infections, including influenza infection: PRS for schizophrenia did not account for the association between hospitalisation for infection and subsequent schizophrenia risk, indicating that schizophrenia risk does not increase proneness to such severe infections (
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>).
</p>
