<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite the widespread availability of ART, there is still a considerable burden of HIV-related morbidity and mortality. In South Africa, HIV accounted for almost two-thirds of medical admissions at one hospital in 2012 and 2013,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
 </sup> with no improvement in the number of deaths due to AIDS nationally from 2013 to 2017,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
 </sup> and in West Africa, AIDS-defining conditions remained the primary cause of hospitalisation among HIV-infected adults years after the scale-up of ART services.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
 </sup> High morbidity and mortality is specifically associated with late presentation for HIV care, as indicated by low baseline CD4 counts or advanced clinical stage.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
  <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
  <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
  <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
 </sup> These poor outcomes potentially undermine the population-level impact of the ART programme, as ART coverage in individuals is known to impact HIV transmission, incidence and community viral load.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
  <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
 </sup> Interventions to improve ART initiation, specifically among clients at risk of presenting late for HIV care, are therefore essential to improve both individual- and programme-level outcomes. This study used operational programme data to describe ART initiation and outcome trends over time, with a focus on clients presenting late for care, so as to identify programmatic gaps that can guide interventions to reduce HIV-associated morbidity and mortality. Two districts were investigated as examples of the urban and rural HIV epidemics in South Africa, namely, Johannesburg and Mopani districts. Specifically, this study aims to use routine TIER.Net data from adult clients in an urban and rural district of South Africa to (1) describe ART programme growth and baseline CD4 count over time, (2) analyse 5-year mortality in the context of baseline CD4 count and (3) describe the population initiating ART at low CD4 counts (&lt; 200 cells/mm
 <sup>3</sup>) in 2017 in order to identify priority groups at high risk of mortality for intervention.
</p>
