<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="Stable8" position="anchor">
 <label>Supplementary Table 8.</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Current studies investigating COVID-19/ other coronavirus strains and Tacrolimus.</title>
 </caption>
 <table frame="border" rules="all">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study Ref</th>
    <th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Title</th>
    <th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Authors</th>
    <th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country of study</th>
    <th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Year</th>
    <th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Summary of results</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[
     <xref rid="refS81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Replication of human coronaviruses SARS-CoV, HCoV-NL63 and HCoV-229E is inhibited by the drug FK506</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carbajo-Lozoya 
     <italic>et al</italic>.
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany/Switzerland</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2012</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coronaviruses represent the group of RNA viruses with the largest RNA genome to date therefore the development of resistant mutants to targeted drugs remains a concern.
     <break/>Viral replication represents potential antiviral targets.
     <break/>Study performed genome-wide SARS-CoV yeast-two-hybrid interaction screen with human cDNA libraries identifying FK506-binding proteins as interaction partners of SARS-CoV non-structural protein 1 (Nsp1).
     <break/>FK506-binding proteins bind the immunosuppressive drug FK506 (tacrolimus).
     <break/>Since Nsp1 interacts with FK506-binding proteins, investigated whether FK506 inhibits replication of human coronaviruses.
     <break/>VeroFM cells infected with SARS-CoV and other human coronaviruses and treated with FK506.
     <break/>Study found that FK506 inhibits the replication of SARS-CoV, HCoV-NL63 and HCoV-229E at non-toxic, low-micromolar concentrations with reduction in viral titers to undetectable levels.
     <break/>All human coronaviruses sensitive to FK506 indicating the involvement of FK506-binding proteins in viral replication.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[
     <xref rid="refS82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MERS CoV infection in two renal transplant recipients: Case report</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Al Ghamdi et al</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saudi Arabia</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pneumonia caused by MERS-CoV associated with severe morbidity and mortality in immunocompromised patients.
     <break/>Data on clinical picture in solid organ transplant recipients and effect of anti-rejection immunosuppressive regimens unclear.
     <break/>30-year old patient with renal transplant on immunosuppressive regimen of tacrolimus.
     <break/>Tested positive for MERS CoV through nasopharyngeal swab.
     <break/>Received antibacterial therapy and mycophenolate mofetil dose reduced and underwent full recovery.
     <break/>Difficult to pinpoint why made full recovery compared to other case study (not on tacrolimus) who died.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[
     <xref rid="refS83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human coronavirus NL63 replication is cyclophilin
     <break/>A-dependent and inhibited by non-immunosuppressive
     <break/>cyclosporine A-derivatives
     <break/>including Alisporivir
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carbajo-Lozoya 
     <italic>et al</italic>
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous study shown that FK506 inhibit coronavirus replication.
     <break/>This study further shows that novel non-immunosuppressive derivatives of CsA and FK506 strongly inhibit the growth of human coronavirus HCoV-NL63 at low-micromolar, non-cytotoxic concentrations in cell culture.
     <break/>HCoV-NL63 and HCoV-HKU1 discovered in 2004 and 2005 causing more severe lower respiratory tract
     <break/>infections in younger children.
     <break/>PPIase-independent activities of CsA and FK506 exerted by gain-of-function, result from binary complexes formed by binding of the drugs to FKBPs. Based on inhibition of the protein phosphatase activity of calcineurin, these complexes block the cellular calcineurin/NFAT pathway
     <break/>thereby interfering with T-cell activation and IL-2 production.
     <break/>FK506 analogues (altered by side chain modification)
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
