<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The other important factor to manage is the reduction of the frequency of administration, to make the prophylaxis useful in resource-poor settings. mAbs used in therapy are generally IgGs (immunoglobulin Gs), which have plasma half-lives of 20 to 25 days in humans [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007860.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007860.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Such antibodies can be used to provide several months of protection, as in the case of the once-per-season anti-RSV antibody MEDI8897 (nirsevimab) discussed earlier or the anti–calcitonin gene-related peptide (anti-CGRP) fremanezumab, recently approved for prevention of migraines with a dose of 675 mg every 3 months. An alternative to simply increasing the dose would be increasing the half-life of the circulating mAb. Several strategies have been proposed here [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007860.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]: Mutations can be made in the IgG Fc (fragment crystallizable) region, which interacts with the receptors responsible for the uptake of antibodies. Such mutations, as for MEDI8897, can significantly extend an mAb’s plasma half-life. Mutations derived from the neonatal Fc receptor (FcRn) increase the strength of the interaction between the Fc region and the Fc receptors under the acidic pH conditions in lysosomes, and as a result, the receptor–Fc complex is recycled back to the cell surface, escaping degradation [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007860.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007860.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. This approach was followed for bevacizumab and cetuximab, by mutating Met
 <sub>428</sub> to Leu and Asn
 <sub>434</sub> to Ser. Discussion about even longer periods of protection has been stimulated by recent results from virally mediated expression of antibodies targeting HIV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007860.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. These technologies hold out the promise of sustained serum titers of antibodies for more than a year from a single injection, although the technological development is more complicated than for the direct injection of antibodies.
</p>
