<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">ZIKV is a blood-borne pathogen that is known to be transmitted by infected mosquitoes. Although mosquitoes transmit ZIKV to and acquire it from humans primarily through blood feeding, our experiments mimicking natural settings demonstrate that mosquitoes may acquire ZIKV from human urinal discharge and sewage during breeding. Our conclusions are supported by several lines of laboratory evidence. First, ZIKV may survive for up to 8 h in harsh environments, such as urinal discharge and sewage. Second, both lab-adapted and field mosquitoes were infected during hatching by ZIKV in the urinal and sewage environments at concentrations as low as 1–2 pfu/ml. Third, the adult mosquitoes that hatched from ZIKV urine/sewage were capable of transmitting ZIKV to mice and eliciting viremia. In favor of our laboratory findings, recent clinical studies have shown the presence of 10–20 infectious ZIKV particles per ml of ZIKV patient urine
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. In particular, cesspits are still commonly used in areas with recent ZIKV epidemics, including Brazil and the Pacific islands
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>. Poor public sanitary infrastructure may have created a physical environment for urinal ZIKV to be acquired by mosquitoes. Nonetheless, these experimental studies attempting to mimic natural settings cannot fully represent the natural scenarios in the field. The potential limitations in experimental design, such as the number of urine and sewage samples, the experimental parameter settings (temperature, incubation time, etc.), and usage of animal models (mosquito species/strains, mouse models, etc.), suggest that the laboratory conditions may not comprehensively represent realistic conditions. Epidemiological studies will be needed to prove human viruria-mediated ZIKV infection in mosquitoes.
</p>
