<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Modeling</italic> R
 <italic>
  <sub>0</sub>
 </italic>
 <sub>.</sub> The 
 <italic>I. scapularis</italic> model is a deterministic model consisting of 12 ordinary differential equations as described by 
 <xref rid="r95" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al. (2013)</xref>, based on the mechanistic simulation model described by 
 <xref rid="r63" ref-type="bibr">Ogden et al. (2005)</xref>. This model captures the effects of temperature on host-seeking activity and the rates of development from one life stage to the next (effects common to, but variable among, all arthropod vectors), parameterized from field and laboratory studies on 
 <italic>I. scapularis</italic>. Mortality rates of nonfeeding 
 <italic>I. scapularis</italic> in Canada and the northeastern United States are similar in summer and winter, presumably due to the insulating effects of the litter layer in woodland habitats (
 <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">Brunner et al. 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">Lindsay et al. 1995</xref>). Our analyses operated on the hypothesis that the effects of ambient temperature on 
 <italic>I. scapularis</italic> population survival are indirect via effects on temperature-dependent rates of development of ticks from one life stage to the next. The lower the temperature, the longer is the tick life cycle and, due to constant daily per capita mortality, the fewer larval ticks survive to become mated adult female ticks. At a threshold temperature, mortality outstrips reproduction and the tick populations die out (or fail to become established)—that is, at this temperature, threshold 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> falls below unity (
 <xref rid="r63" ref-type="bibr">Ogden et al. 2005</xref>). At the latitudes under study here, effects of climate change on 
 <italic>I. scapularis</italic> are expected to be the effect of climate warming on shortening the life cycle, resulting in increasing 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> (
 <xref rid="r68" ref-type="bibr">Ogden et al. 2006b</xref>). Quadratic effects of temperature on arthropod vector life history traits are common (
 <xref rid="r50" ref-type="bibr">Mordecai et al. 2013</xref>), and quadratic effects of temperature on tick activity are included in the model. High temperatures may impact tick survival, causing a northward contraction of the southern range of 
 <italic>I. scapularis</italic>, resulting in a northward shift, rather than overall expansion, of the geographic range of climatic suitability for 
 <italic>I. scapularis</italic> (
 <xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">Brownstein et al. 2005</xref>). Here we confined our study to Canada and the main regions of Lyme disease risk in the United States north of 40°N (
 <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">Diuk-Wasser et al. 2012</xref>). Impacts of rainfall on off-host tick survival and on host-seeking activity are considered accounted for in the model in assuming 
 <italic>a</italic>) tick populations only become established in woodlands where the microclimate is suitable for tick survival, and 
 <italic>b</italic>) most temperate woodlands types occur where rainfall is sufficient for 
 <italic>I. scapularis</italic> survival, which is supported by studies in Canada (
 <xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr">Lindsay et al. 1995</xref>). Future projections for increased precipitation across much of Canada with climate warming are already being seen to occur (
 <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">Environment Canada 2013</xref>), so rainfall changes are not expected to limit the northward spread of 
 <italic>I. scapularis</italic>. For the present study, we modified the simulation model of 
 <xref rid="r63" ref-type="bibr">Ogden et al. (2005)</xref> in order to calculate 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> by the next generation operator as described by 
 <xref rid="r95" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al. (2013)</xref>. Apart from the temperature values used to calculate tick development and host-finding rates, the values for host numbers (20 deer and 200 rodents) and all other parameter values were those used as starting values by 
 <xref rid="r95" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al. (2013)</xref>. 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> was estimated using mean monthly temperature data for each year and location as described in the following sections. Variations in host abundance affect the final size of the tick population but not the temperature threshold (
 <xref rid="r63" ref-type="bibr">Ogden et al. 2005</xref>). The temperature threshold would be affected by variations in the mortality rates of ticks in the environment, and slight variations in this have been observed in the field (
 <xref rid="r61" ref-type="bibr">Ogden et al. 2006a</xref>). For the sensitivity analysis of 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> to variations in model parameter values, see Supplemental Material, “Model sensitivity analysis,” pp. 7–11, Table S2 and Figures S5 and S6.
</p>
