<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Vertical transmission of CHIKV was observed in humans [
 <xref rid="pone.0207554.ref146" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0207554.ref149" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0207554.ref244" ref-type="bibr">244</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0207554.ref288" ref-type="bibr">288</xref>]. The impact of intra-uterine CHIKV infection on the fetus and neonates is not clearly understood with conflicting results from several studies. One study looked at dizygous twins born to a mother infected during pregnancy and reported one healthy neonate, while the other twin was severely ill due to congenitally acquired chikungunya [
 <xref rid="pone.0207554.ref267" ref-type="bibr">267</xref>]. Another study examining outcomes of CHIKV infection to the fetus during each trimester of pregnancy until post-partum reported vertical transmission in all three trimesters, with more serious outcomes to neonates when mothers were viremic at delivery [
 <xref rid="pone.0207554.ref289" ref-type="bibr">289</xref>]. It is important to keep in mind that vertical transmission of chikungunya in an asymptomatic infected mother or neonate can also trigger a cluster of cases among pregnant women or new mothers and neonates in maternity units. A single case of microcephaly in a neonate born to a mother with gestational chikungunya infection has been described [
 <xref rid="pone.0207554.ref290" ref-type="bibr">290</xref>]. Microcephaly is believed to be an outcome associated with ZIKV infections [
 <xref rid="pone.0207554.ref291" ref-type="bibr">291</xref>]. We acknowledge that this could be a coincidental finding, but CHIKV associated microcephaly certainly warrants future research given that CHIKV and ZIKV co-circulate in many regions. There has been no research on sexual transmission of CHIKV, despite evidence for this with ZIKV. Interestingly, viable CHIKV has been isolated from an individual’s semen and urine sample up to 30 days post-infection [
 <xref rid="pone.0207554.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>] and one study provided experimental evidence for the presence of infectious CHIKV in human saliva [
 <xref rid="pone.0207554.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], so the possibility of sexual transmission of CHIKV in humans needs to be clearly elucidated.
</p>
