<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In a study comparing patients with COVID-19 pneumonia, non–COVID-19 pneumonia and healthy controls, Varchetta and colleagues [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008820.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] reported increased CD57+FcεRIγ- adaptive NK cells and CD16
 <sup>+</sup> NK cells and decreased CD56
 <sup>bright</sup> NK cells. While they did not observe any differences in NKG2A/C expression, there was reduced expression of Siglec-7, NKG2D, DNAM-1, and NKp30 in COVID-19 patients [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008820.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Interestingly, NK cells from these patients exerted more antibody dependent cell mediated cytotoxicity (ADCC) than healthy controls [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008820.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. This study though limited by a small sample size, provides promising data that there is a potential development of memory-like or trained NK cells, as evidenced by the elevated FcεRIγ
 <sup>-</sup> NK cells and improved ADCC response in COVID-19 patients. Similarly, Maucourant and colleagues [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008820.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] reported strong NK cell activation with expansion of adaptive NKG2C
 <sup>+</sup> NK cell in the blood of COVID-19 patients. However, the high expression of NKG2C, perforin, and ksp (killer specific secretory protein)-37 correlated with disease severity. Perforin expression of CD56
 <sup>bright</sup> NK cells positively correlated with IL-6, Sequential Organ Failure Assessment (SOFA) scores and neutrophil count and inversely correlated with partial pressure of oxygen (PaO2) and fraction of inspired oxygen (FiO2) in COVID-19 patients [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008820.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], indicating hyperinflammed state of NK cells in severe COVID-19. Granzyme A–expressing NK cells were negatively correlated with serum IL-6 levels in COVID-19 patients, and the impaired cytotoxic potential was restored when treated with tocilizumab [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008820.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. These studies further emphasize the need for more rigorous studies with larger sample sizes to understand NK cells, which could prove useful in the current race against the COVID-19 pandemic since the virus mediated immune dysfunction appears to extend to NK cells [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008820.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. More significantly, the role of NK cell at primary sites of infection, lungs, and other tissue would be more crucial to understand pathogenesis of this disease, since most studies in COVID-19 patients have been focused on immune cell subsets in the periphery.
</p>
