<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>When placed into the context of the viral life cycle it is interesting to consider the various interactions of flavivirus capsid proteins. Antivirals such as ST-148 have been investigated for having a stabilizing effect, preventing uncoating and genome release of DENV upon viral entry [
 <xref rid="B69-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Of course, the canonical function of capsid is to package the viral genome so that it may be successfully transmitted to another host cell. This has been the focus of vaccine development, in the production of assembly or packaging defective viruses. Before capsid can form the nucleocapsid, it is stored on lipid droplets via interactions with host proteins MBOAT2, AUP1 and others [
 <xref rid="B14-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. In order for capsid dimers to make it to and from the lipid droplets, interactions with vesicular trafficking proteins is necessary (YKT6, USE1, etc.) [
 <xref rid="B61-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Once enough protein has been translated and viral genomes replicated capsid is shuttled back to the ER for nucleocapsid assembly, again utilizing host vesicular transport machinery. This would appear to be the end of the capsid protein’s role in the flavivirus life cycle, however, it is now clear that there are a number of other roles and interactions that capsid proteins have that aid in the pathogenesis of these viruses, as highlighted in 
 <xref rid="pathogens-09-00042-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. For example, capsid’s ability to enter the host nucleolus resulting in ribosomal stress and Tp53-mediated apoptosis induction in neural progenitors is a concern for development of microcephaly in fetuses growing within infected mothers [
 <xref rid="B20-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-pathogens-09-00042" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>].
</p>
