<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While daylight’s effect on indoor viruses and SARS-CoV-2 is still unexplored, spectrally tuned electric lighting is already implemented as engineering controls for disinfection indoors. UV light in the region of shorter wavelengths (254-nm UV C [UVC]) is particularly germicidal, and fixtures tuned to this part of the light spectrum are effectively employed in clinical settings to inactivate infectious aerosols and can reduce the ability of some viruses to survive (
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>). It is important to note that most UVC light is eliminated in the atmosphere, while much of the UVA and UVB spectrum is eliminated through building glass layers. Airborne viruses that contain single-stranded RNA (ssRNA) are reduced by 90% with a low dose of UV light, and the UV dose requirement increases for ssRNA viruses found on surfaces (
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>). A previous study demonstrated that 10 min of UVC light inactivated 99.999% of CoVs tested, SARS-CoV, and MERS-CoV (
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>). However, UV germicidal irradiation (UVGI) has potential safety concerns if the room occupants are exposed to high-energy light. For this reason, UVGI is safely installed in mechanical ventilation paths or in upper-room applications to indirectly treat air through convective air movement (
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>). More recently, far-UVC light in the 207- to 222-nm range has been demonstrated to effectively inactivate airborne aerosolized viruses. While preliminary findings from 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> rodent models and 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> three-dimensional (3-D) human skin models appear favorable to not cause damage to human skin and eyes (
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>), further research must be conducted to verify the margin of safety before implementation. If implemented safely, UVC and UVGI light offers a range of potential disinfectant strategies for buildings and is a common strategy for deep clean practices in health care settings. Implementing targeted UVC and UVGI treatment may be prudent in other space types where individuals that tested positive for COVID-19 were known occupants, but routine treatment may have unintended consequences and should be implemented with appropriate precaution.
</p>
