<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0090">Another desired criterion is that it is safe, that is, non-toxic. In this sense, we already have data on its safety at the doses it is intended to be used because chloroquine and/or hydroxychloroquine are used at high doses in the acute attack of malaria, Q fever and Whipple's disease
 <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0210" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> and, specifically on COVID-19 patients, the 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> studies conducted so far have reported no serious adverse reactions.
 <xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> In this sense, previously published studies confirm that the cardiac complications reported in case of hydroxychloroquine overdose, a risk that we can face with short regimens at high doses, could be actively prevented if its administration is avoided in patients with contraindications, intermittent electrocardiogram monitoring is used during treatment, a maintenance dose lower than that of induction is applied to prevent its accumulation, and the dose is adjusted in those patients who may require it, as specified in the drug's SmPC of the Spanish Agency of Medicines.
 <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> The evidence for the concomitant use of azithromycin and chloroquine is more limited. Although in a 2011 article evaluating the safety and tolerability of both drugs in combination, only minor adverse events such as the presence of nausea associated with azithromycin were reported,
 <xref rid="bib0215" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref> a recent study of 84 patients with COVID-19 treated with hydroxychloroquine and azithromycin demonstrates QTc interval prolongation, from 435 ± 24 ms to 463 ± 32 ms. In 11% of patients, the maximum QTc value exceeded 500 ms, with this being an important and recognized risk factor for the development of potentially fatal malignant arrhythmias.
 <xref rid="bib0220" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref> Furthermore, QTc prolongation was independent of baseline values, underscoring the importance of continuous or frequent monitoring in these patients
 <xref rid="bib0220" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref> and consolidates the resounding demand for caution in the use of the combination of these drugs, as already supported by some authorities.
 <xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref> In any case, a multinational study on the safety profile of hydroxychloroquine alone and in combination with azithromycin is currently underway in more than 130,000 patients with COVID-19 pneumonia (ClinicalTrials.gov identifier: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04321278" id="intr0010" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04321278</ext-link>).
 <xref rid="bib0230" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
