<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Remdesivir (GS-5734) is a nucleoside analogue prodrug that inhibits viral RNA polymerases, and was developed by Gilead Science in response to the Ebola outbreak in 2017.
 <xref rid="b42-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>–
 <xref rid="b44-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> It is considered to be one of the most promising broad-spectrum antivirals for treating COVID-19. 
 <italic>In vitro</italic> antiviral activities of remdesivir have been demonstrated in SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV, and SARS-CoV-2.
 <xref rid="b45-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="b46-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> In early April, a preliminary report describing the clinical outcomes of a cohort of 53 hospitalised COVID-19 patients who received remdesivir, 68% of patients showed improvement of their oxygen-support status, but 60% of patients reported adverse events during follow-up.
 <xref rid="b42-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> Subsequently, a double-blinded randomised controlled trial in 237 adult patients with severe COVID-19 showed that remdesivir was not associated with statistically significant clinical benefits whilst adverse events were reported in 66% of patients.
 <xref rid="b47-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> Separately, the results of an interim analysis of the Adaptive COVID-19 Treatment Trial involving 1063 patients are more encouraging, as it indicated that patients who received redmesivir had a 31% faster time to recovery than those who received placebo (median time to recovery was 11 
 <italic>versus</italic> 15 days).
 <xref rid="b48-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">48</xref> More recently, a phase 3 SIMPLE clinical trial demonstrated that patients receiving a 5-day and 10-day treatment course of remdesivir achieved similar improvements in clinical status.
 <xref rid="b49-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> Common adverse events reported in the preliminary studies included elevated hepatic enzymes, diarrhoea, constipation, hypoalbuminaemia, rash, renal impairment, anaemia, thrombocytopenia, and hypotension.
 <xref rid="b42-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="b47-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> Potential drug–drug interactions with other medications metabolised through the cytochrome P450 system were also reported. The safety profile of this drug needs to be further evaluated. Randomised controlled trials on remdesivir are still ongoing, and two studies are in phase III of clinical trials to evaluate the safety and efficacy of remdesivir.
 <xref rid="b50-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>–
 <xref rid="b53-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>
</p>
