<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">A conventional PCR was performed for the detection of the DENV genome, and the positive samples were confirmed by real-time PCR. In both cases, mD1 (F-5’-TCA ATA TGC TGA AAC GCG AGA GAA ACC G-3′) and D2 (F-5′-TTG CAC CAA CAG TCA ATG TCT TCA GG TTC-3′) primers were used for a region of the gene that encodes for the C-prM protein, which has been previously reported [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. The amplification in the conventional PCR was performed with the Maxima® Hot Start Green PCR Master Mix (2X) enzyme (Thermo Scientific®), using 10 μmol of each primer and 2 μl of the cDNA from each sample. The amplification conditions included denaturation for 5 min at 95 °C, followed by 35 cycles at 95 °C for 30 s, 55 °C for 45 s, and 72 °C for 33 s, with a final extension at 72 °C for 10 min. To perform conventional PCR we used ProFlex 3 × 32-well PCR System (Thermo Fisher Scientific ®). The products were visualized on 1.5% agarose gel using SYBR® Safe (Thermo Scientific®) in a MiniBIS® (DNR Bio-Imaging Systems) gel photo documentation system. The expected size of the PCR products was 511 base pairs (bp). For the amplification in the real-time PCR, the Maxima® SYBR® Green/ROX qPCR Master Mix (2X) Kit (Thermo Scientific®) was used with the following thermal profile protocol: a first step of 50 °C for 2 min, a DNA polymerase activation step at 95 °C for 10 min, 35 cycles at 95 °C for 15 s for denaturation, 50 °C for 15 s for the alignment of the primers, and an extension at 72 °C for 30 s, measuring the fluorescence immediately after finishing the extension step. A melting curve (T
 <sub>m</sub>, melting temperature) was run after the final extension to confirm the specificity of the specific products. The melting curve included a step at 78.5 °C for 10 s and a ramp of 75 to 90 °C at a rate of 0.5 °C/s, with constant fluorescence measurements. To perform the real-time PCR we used the QuantStudio 3 Real-Time PCR System (Thermo Fisher Scientific ®) and the cut-off Ct value was ≤36, based in previous results of several groups, including ours, where both culture cells and serum specimens can be considered as positives when the value Ct was &gt; 36 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. As positive control for all four serotypes of DENV we used supernatants of culture cells infected with reference strain of each virus obtained from the National Institute for Biological Standards and Control (DENV-1 West Pac 74, DENV-2 S16803, DENV-3 CH53489 and DENV-4 TVP360) and as negative control we used RNAse-free water.
</p>
