<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">Mosquito is also capable of transmitting parasitic diseases such as malaria and filariasis. Malaria is the most serious and fatal parasitic disease worldwide with more than 214 million annual clinical cases and half a million deaths, 90% of which live in Africa. These numbers are expected to expand in response to global warming. The situation is additionally complicated due to the growing resistance against anti-plasmodium drugs and by mosquitoes against insecticides (Gunda et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2017</xref>; Ssempiira et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR178">2018</xref>). Historically, malaria invaded Europe on many occasions. Old reports from ancient Roma reported the presence of Malaria in Italy thousands of years ago (Micallef 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120">2016</xref>; Sallares 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR167">2002</xref>). Newer reports from the year 1265 reported the presence of malaria in Croatia; seventeenth century documented the re-introduction of malaria to Europe through Spain. However, in the twentieth century, WHO launched a global malaria eradication program which resulted in the eradication of malaria from 79 countries worldwide (mainly in Eurasia, Australia, northern America, and northern Africa with the exception of Turkey and countries of middle Asia including Azerbaijan, Georgia, Kyrgyzstan and Tajikistan) (Askling et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2012</xref>; Caminade et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2014</xref>). The eradication of malaria from Europe was officially declared in 1975 and was achieved via the drainage of wetland and stagnant water, chemical treatment of patients, biological control of the mosquito larvae using the fish 
 <italic>Gambusia holbrooki</italic>, improvement of water system and sewage infrastructure (Talapko et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR181">2019</xref>). However, recently, between 2009 and 2012, several cases were diagnosed in Greece (Danis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2011</xref>). Later on, malaria was re-introduced in Croatia, Italy, Malta, Bulgaria, France, Germany and Spain (Krüger et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">2001</xref>; Medialdea-Carrera et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">2018</xref>; Monge-Maillo and López-Vélez 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">2012</xref>). In Greece, in 2011, 
 <italic>Plasmodium vivax</italic> could be isolated from the blood of 40 patients from different regions of the country. The patients were infected locally as they have no travelling history to the outside (Ivanescu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">2016</xref>). In the same year, in Romania, malaria was also diagnosed but fortunately, the disease was imported with travellers from Italy (Neghina et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132">2011</xref>; Nicolescu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134">2016</xref>). However, and although most countries in Europe are malaria-free since decades, the 
 <italic>Anopheles</italic> vector continued to live and exist there. The persistence of the vector represents a great threat for the re-emerge of the diseases any time, and it is expected to re-emerge in the rest of Europe and USA as the climatic changes favour the re-emergence of the disease (Askling et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2012</xref>). These speculations are supported by computer modelling programs which predict the re-emergence of malaria in Europe and USA in the near future (Kuhn et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">2003</xref>). On the other hand, in the already endemic countries such as Iran and Zimbabwe, the prevalence of malaria increased in the last few years as reported (Babaie et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2018</xref>; Gunda et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2017</xref>).
</p>
