<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>cDNAs of full-length human codon-optimized murine 
 <italic>Anp32A</italic> and 
 <italic>Anp32B</italic> isoforms were generated by gene synthesis (GeneArt, Thermo Fisher) using GenBank sequences 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_033802.2" assigning-authority="ncbi:protein" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NP_033802.2</ext-link> (mouse 
 <italic>Anp32A</italic>) and 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/NP_570959.1" assigning-authority="ncbi:protein" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NP_570959.1</ext-link> (mouse 
 <italic>Anp32B</italic>) and cloned into pCAGGS expression plasmids that included a C-terminal GSG linker followed by a FLAG tag and 2 stop codons. Human pCAGGS 
 <italic>ANP32A</italic> and 
 <italic>ANP32B</italic>, chicken 
 <italic>Anp32A</italic>, pig 
 <italic>Anp32A</italic>, and duck 
 <italic>Anp32A</italic> expression plasmids have been previously described (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). The chimeric mouse construct and human ANP32A point mutants were cloned by overlapping PCR, using primers CCAACCTGAATGCCTACCGCGAGAAC and GTTCTCGCGGTAGGCATTCAGGTTGG (huANP32A-D130A), and GGTCACTTCGCAGTTAAACAAATCCAG, GTTTAACTGCGAAGTGACCAACAGAAGC, GCCCTCCACGTCGCTGTCAGGGGCCTC, and GACAGCGACGTGGAGGGCTACGTGGAG (mouse Anp32A/Anp32B domain swap). Mouse ANP32A mutant A130D was generated by overlapping PCR using primers GGTAACCAACCTTAATGATTACCGGGAGAACGTC and GACGTTCTCCCGGTAATCATTAAGGTTGGTTACC. pCAGGS expression plasmids encoding each polymerase component and NP for H3N2 Victoria, H5N1 (PB2-627K) 50-92, pH1N1 England 195, and IBV Florida 06 have been described (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>) pPolI reporter plasmids containing firefly luciferase or blue fluorescent protein flanked by IAV- or IBV-specific promoters have been previously described (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). All plasmid constructs were verified by Sanger sequencing and analyzed manually in Geneious v6.
</p>
