<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>CHIKV infected cells are killed by the induction of cytolytic mechanisms along with the several antiviral factors by the immune cells, mainly CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells (
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>). Naïve CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells induce a development environment upon activation leading to effector and memory T-cell proliferation and differentiation (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). Once activated, effector CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells exhibit functions, such as cytotoxicity and cytokine production, against the virus, resulting in its elimination (
 <xref rid="B101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>). Furthermore, it is known that CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T lymphocytes mediate cytolytic activity against target cells in two major pathways either by the release of cytolytic granules through exocytosis or granule independent pathway, in which they bind to the death receptors of the target cells (
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>). Studies have reported that the peripheral blood of acute and chronic CHIKD patients had no differences in the percentage of CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells in relation to healthy individuals. Analysis of early activation marker CD69 for CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells revealed increased CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cell activation in both acute and chronic diseases (
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>). The study further observed that CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T lymphocytes in patients with acute CHIKD have increased secretion of CD107A along with granzyme and perforin expression in comparison to the control group, suggesting that CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells may have a role in mediating cytolytic killing of CHIKV infected cells during the acute phase of CHIKD (
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>). Interestingly, the CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells failed to present any such increase in the expression of granzyme and perforins in patients with chronic disease in comparison to healthy controls (
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>). Such observations point to the possibility that these mechanisms slow down or even shut off, owing to the process of T-cell exhaustion during the later stages of the disease.
</p>
