<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Work in molecular virology has revealed why virus replication tends to be so specific for particular host species (
 <bold>
  <xref ref-type="boxed-text" rid="pbio.3000217.box001">Box 1</xref>
 </bold>). Viruses replicate themselves inside the cells of their hosts, and to do so, they must correctly execute tens to hundreds of protein–protein interactions. For instance, HIV is thought to interact with as many as 400 proteins in human T cells [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Animal viruses will replicate in human cells when they can interact with all of the useful host proteins that they need and simultaneously avoid interaction with all of the immunity proteins that will destroy them. Viruses might not interact correctly with host proteins in a new species (binding to useful proteins, avoiding immunity proteins) because of differences in the primary sequences of these proteins in the new species. Even small primary sequence differences between orthologs of a host protein can change the virus interaction surface, either directly or by changing the structure or pattern of post-translational modification, such as the addition of glycans. While an animal virus could be selected for perfecting interactions with human proteins (enhancing interaction with useful host proteins and avoiding interaction with antiviral proteins), the conditions for human adaptation will not exist until after viral replication in a human has commenced. Instead, only “alive-on-arrival” animal viruses, meaning those already able to launch replication cycles upon encountering a human, will have any opportunity to further optimize themselves for the human host. (Alive-on-arrival viruses have also been referred to as “off the shelf” [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].) Stated another way, zoonosis requires that human-compatible viral variants pre-exist in the animal reservoir, arising before these viruses have ever even experienced the selective constraints of the human body. For the vast majority of animal viruses in nature, there are just too many protein–protein interactions to master by chance in a random encounter with humans.
</p>
