<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>BCG was first used as an immunotherapy for the treatment of bladder cancer around 40 years ago.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>
 </sup> BCG being a liquid drug can be deposited directly into the bladder through a catheter. Immunotherapy is used to induce the immune system for attacking cancer cells. Several immune molecules and cell types were indetified involved
 <sup>
  <xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>–
  <xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>
 </sup> in the action of BCG. It is apparent that the effects of BCG on the immune system are complex, multifactorial, and likely to evolve. The data suggest that the anticancer effects of BCG are due to the direct action on tumor cells by BCG and the host’s immune response.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>
 </sup> The activation of the immune system led to recognition and subsequent destruction of tumor cells through nonspecific and specific cell-mediated mechanisms.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>
 </sup>The concept of trained immunity was first proposed by Netea et al.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>
 </sup> and is defined as an improved nonspecific response by the innate immune cells to secondary infection caused by different or same microorganisms.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>
 </sup> In adult humans, BCG vaccine induces trained phenotype in monocytes, leading to an increase in their capacity to secrete proinflammatory cytokines, which provide nonspecific protection against 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> and 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
  <xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
  <xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>
 </sup> BCG vaccination also induces the adaptive immune response, which leads to activation of both CD4+ and CD8 + T cells
 <sup>
  <xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>
 </sup> and increased production of interferon-gamma (IFN-γ), which increases the anti-mycobacterial activity of macrophages.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>
 </sup> Further, cytokines help in B cell activation and successive antigen-specific antibody production by plasma cells. After vaccination, a pool of mycobacteria-specific CD8 + T cells multiplies, and remains in the peripheral blood for around 10 weeks. Beyond providing protection against TB, BCG vaccine also has some other clinical applications, particularly in immunotherapy, such as treatment of autoimmune diseases like type-1 diabetes and various cancers including melanoma.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
