<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">Lassa fever infects humans of all age groups and sexes. The disease is associated with a broad spectrum of clinical manifestations. The incubation period ranges from 7 to 21 days (McCormick et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">1987</xref>). The clinical presentation is usually mild or asymptomatic in about 80% of infections (Richmond and Baglole 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">2003</xref>). The onset of the symptomatic disease is usually gradual, starting as a flu-like illness characterized by mild fever, weakness and general malaise. This may be accompanied by a headache, sore throat, muscle pain, chest pain, nausea, vomiting, diarrhoea, cough and abdominal pain (Bausch et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2001</xref>). In mild cases, the fever subsides, and the patient usually recovers. Other cases progress towards a more severe illness. Symptoms include haemorrhage, respiratory distress, facial oedema and fluid in the pulmonary cavity. Shock, seizures, tremor, disorientation and coma have also been reported during this stage of the disease, indicating a poor prognosis for the disease outcome (Mertens et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">1973</xref>). Approximately 15–20% of hospitalized Lassa fever patients die from the illness, generally within 2 weeks after the onset of symptoms due to multi-organ complication and failure involving the liver, spleen or kidneys. Pregnant women are more likely to have severe illness due to infection with LASV than women who are not pregnant, with maternal case fatality rates as high as 80% and nearly 100% mortality in foetuses. Infection in infants can result in “swollen baby syndrome” with oedema, abdominal distension, bleeding and often death (McCormick et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">1987</xref>). Neurological problems, including hearing loss and encephalopathy, have been shown to occur in patients who survive the disease (Mateer et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2018</xref>).
</p>
