<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the absence of a better understanding of sexual transmission of EVD, mathematical modeling currently remains the only tool to explore its potential impact on the epidemic trajectory. There are several extensions to this work that future models should consider including in order to make accurate predictions. These include: transmission by other bodily fluids (e.g., vaginal secretions [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]), asymptomatic infection [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], considering spatial aspects of both social and sexual transmission [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], and heterogeneity in sexual behavior [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Sexual behaviors, for instance, are often specific to a given culture, and may change drastically in response to such a devastating epidemic that can destroy entire communities and create stigma, disrupting existing social and sexual contact networks [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]; the lack of these details particularly in developing countries presents a challenge for parameterizing a more complex model. We assumed the duration of convalescence to be exponentially distributed. Eggo 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] fitted a series of unimodal distributions to the data on Ebola virus RNA detection in semen recently reported by Deen 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] and found that the convalescence period could be best described by a gamma distribution. Furthermore, Deen 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] found that the cycle-threshold values decreased over time, indicating that the Ebola virus load in semen and the viral infectivity might also decrease during the convalescence period. It is also critical to measure the length of time viral particles persisting in the seminal fluid remain infectious. Molecular techniques to detect intermediate (replicative) positive-sense RNA stages of the virus, infection of human cell lines in tissue culture, or tests in animal models are some typical methods. Retrospective studies using phylodynamics could also prove helpful for estimating this type of parameter [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Uncertainty in the data is not limited to sexual transmission; we fitted our model to weekly incidence of confirmed and probable cases in Sierra Leone, but did not take into account potential underreporting as others have done recently [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. In addition, the incidence data to which we fit our model will, for the most part, be driven by direct transmission of the virus and thus, to better parameterize and estimate the risk of sexual transmission, we would need data with greater resolution (e.g. knowledge of which cases were caused by sexual transmission events). Another caveat is that EVD is known to exhibit superspreading characteristics [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], and superspreading events could lead to explosive regrowth of the epidemic after the occurrence of a new case through sexual transmission [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. And finally, like other negative-sense single-stranded RNA ((-)ssRNA) viruses [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], the species currently circulating in West Africa has been estimated to have high substitution rates [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0004676.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. This rapid evolution detected throughout the current outbreak zone suggests that within- or between-host adaptation of the virus leading to pro-longed persistence in the seminal fluids is possible. However, without significant attenuation of EVD’s high mortality and morbidity virulence, evolution of sexual transmission becoming the primary route of spread is highly unlikely, as the subsequent infections that arise from a sexual transmission event will be caused primarily through transmission during the acute non-sexual transmission phase of the infection.
</p>
