<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>However, our study has some limitations. First, we compared the timings when a particular virus was positively identified and the incidence of HSP. The results were confirmed using statistical methods by experts specializing in preventive medicine and statistics. But it was not possible to confirm whether the virus caused HSP. It is known that IgA-containing immune complexes triggered by infectious diseases are deposited on organs such as skin, kidneys, and gastrointestinal tract and can cause HSP, and we can only assume that the viruses suspected of causing HSP have similar mechanisms.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
  <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
  <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]
 </sup> However, studies on whether only specific viruses or bacteria cause HSP should be continued. Second, there is a limitation in the extent of virus detection. While the data included HSP outbreaks for all patients &lt;18 years of age in South Korea, virus detection tests were given to only patients with severe respiratory symptoms. Therefore, the patients who were not tested but have symptoms were not included in the study. Also, if the causative virus itself is not as severe as rhinovirus, its detection rate would have been much lower than actual incidence. On the contrary, if there was, for example, an influenza virus epidemic which caused severe symptoms, and relatively more tests were conducted, its actual detection rate would have been higher than that of other viruses. Finally, there is a limitation in the HIRA data. The possibility of duplicate diagnoses could not be totally excluded, even though only the initial diagnosis was included by examining the cases by the unique number given to each individual. Also, for the same reason, patients who visited clinics for recurrence and not for a simple follow-up, would not be identified. Because the patients evaluated were based on the HIRA data, information regarding their clinical aspects was not included in this study. It is necessary to investigate whether the clinical features differ based on the infectious agent causing HSP, and information about the prognosis should also be evaluated. In addition, the diagnosis of HSP was based on the final diagnosis only, not grounded on all patients or chart review, so there may be some errors in the total number of patients. Nevertheless, our study will be the first to investigate an association between the occurrence of HSP and outbreaks of different viruses using the National health data.
</p>
