<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0055">The key determinant of SARS coronavirus host specificity is the Spike glycoprotein, an envelope-anchored trimeric protein responsible for binding human ACE2 as the principle receptor for virus docking and entry. SARS-CoV S glycoprotein also binds C-type lectins like DC-Sign and/or L-Sign as a coreceptor, an interaction which is blocked by mannose binding lectin [
 <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0250" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Importantly, SARS-CoV docking and entry is also highly dependent upon transmembrane protease/serine subfamily member 2 (TMPRSS2) S and ACE2 cleavage, especially in airway and alveolar sites, and cathepsin L cleavage and subsequent S2 fusion activation [
 <xref rid="bib0255" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0260" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0265" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Several studies in the past two years have worked to clarify the plasticity of this protein, with particular emphasis on the RBD. The Spike glycoprotein underwent rapid evolution during the human epidemic [
 <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], was the most significantly variable protein across civet and human isolates [
 <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and shows evidence of positive selection during both interspecies and intraspecies transmission events [
 <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0270" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. The SARS Spike can recognize and use bat, civet, mouse, and raccoon dog ACE2 receptor molecules for docking and entry, indicating that SARS trafficked along receptor ortholog networks to move between species [
 <xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0275" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0280" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. As several alphacoronaviridae also use APN from different species, these data suggest a common theme in coronavirus host range switching: recognizing receptor orthologs from different species [
 <xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Additionally, the role of different ortholog proteases for facilitating coronavirus S glycoprotein cleavage and entry processes remains undefined, and could significantly contribute to the efficiency of virus cross-species transmission processes.
</p>
