<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Additional measures to reduce virus propagation can be adopted at three different levels: (1) by redesigning the future infrastructure of shared spaces such as offices, toilet rooms, buses, and trains; (2) by emphasizing further compliance from people with the aforementioned measures; and (3) by deploying measures that will inactivate viruses that are emitted in indoor environments and become airborne or that are deposited on surfaces. Level (1) requires long-term planning and might be an excellent option for future pandemics, but it does not address the acute needs of the current SARS-CoV-2 situation. Level (2) depends strongly on political and social considerations that may vary across countries and, therefore, does not provide a complete solution on the global scale. We focus here on level (3) measures such as washing and wiping surfaces, spraying disinfectants, or illumination with UV-C (200–280 nm wavelength) light sources. The efficiency of each depends on how much they fulfill the following requirements:
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>
    <underline>Fast implementation</underline>. The financial burden of sustaining the level of social distancing required to prevent exponential growth of the pandemic is immense. Particularly after the first wave, the possibility of recurring waves of infection and potential changes in virus pathogenicity triggered by mutations is of major concern. Timeliness is paramount to address these concerns.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>
    <underline>Scalability</underline>. The implementation of new measures involves massive economical, geographical, and social scales, affecting billions of workers in possibly hundreds of millions of shared workspaces and, therefore, requires similarly high numbers of physical units to be handled and produced at unprecedented rates.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>
    <underline>Affordability</underline>. The investment needed to act on a sufficient fraction of workspaces worldwide may quickly reach multibillion dollar figures, a demand that many countries are not prepared to spend, unless these measures can be made sufficiently inexpensive.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
