<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">Mesenchymal stromal cells (MSCs) are characterized with their immunomodulatory and anti-inflammatory properties [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. Because of these characteristics, they have been used for the treatment of various inflammatory and autoimmune disorders including diabetes, graft-versus-host disease (GvHD), and multiple sclerosis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. It is proven that MSCs and MSC extracellular vesicle (EV) infusion have beneficial effects in the treatment of virus-induced pneumonia by reducing the lung inflammation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. EVs are stable, could distribute to the lungs, and have the same immunomodulatory and anti-inflammatory properties of parental MSCs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. MSCs decreased inflammatory cytokines and chemokines in animal model of avian influenza. They could also prevent immune cell infiltration into the lungs and improved alveolar injury [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. Recently, there are studies evaluating allogenic MSCs and MSC-derived exosomes as potential therapeutic tools for reducing inflammation and improving COVID-19-related ARDS [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. It is indicated that adoptive transfer of allogenic umbilical cord mesenchymal stem cells (UC-MSCs) could inhibit inflammation and attenuate symptoms in patients with advanced COVID-19. Four days after cell therapy, patients are disconnected from the ventilator. UC-MSC therapy also elevated T cell numbers and boosted the immune system [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. Administration of ACE negative MSCs to seven COVID-19 patients improved clinical symptoms with no side effects just 2 days after injection. The number of inflammatory cytokine secreting cells reduced significantly. Regulatory DC subpopulation (CD14+CD11c+CD11b
 <sup>mid</sup>) elevated. The levels of IL-10 anti-inflammatory cytokine increased while TNF-α decreased [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. Infusion of MSCs also induced lung tissue regeneration by modulating inflammatory microenvironment in COVID-19 patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. There are several ongoing clinical trials using different sources of MSCs for the treatment of COVID-19 (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Taken together, MSC therapy could inhibit excessive immune system reaction, modulate inflammatory milieu, and prevent virus-mediated cytokine storm [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. It seems that MSC therapy could be a novel therapeutic approach for the treatment of COVID-19 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>].
</p>
