<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A growing body of work suggests that plant viruses manipulate vector behavior in order to enhance their own transmission (Mauck et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>, Groen et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>, Carr et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>), and that beyond plant viruses, manipulation of vector host choice by pathogens (Gandon 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>) can have dramatic consequences for epidemiology. Several NPT viruses induce biochemical changes in their host plants that affect the host‐locating behavior of aphids, as well as the insects’ feeding behavior and growth after they alight on infected plants (Mauck et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>, Groen et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>, Carr et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). In this paper, we will refer to such virus‐induced effects on plant–vector relations as virally modified plant phenotypes (VMPPs; Box 1). Some important examples of VMPPs come from studies of cucumber mosaic virus (CMV). It was found that CMV‐infected squash plants (
 <italic>Cucurbita pepo</italic>) emit a blend of volatile organic compounds that attracts aphids (Mauck et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>, Pickett et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>), i.e., a VMPP conditioning 
 <italic>plant attractiveness</italic> (Box 1). However, the plants contain increased levels of distasteful metabolites, which deter aphids from prolonged feeding following exploratory probes in which virus particles may have been acquired (Mauck et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>), i.e., virus‐induced decrease in 
 <italic>plant acceptability</italic> (Box 1). Similar results were obtained for cucumber, 
 <italic>Cucumis sativus</italic> (Carmo‐Sousa et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>), and it was found that CMV‐infected 
 <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> plants were also distasteful to aphids (Westwood et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). A hypothesis has emerged that this particular combination of VMPPs, which we term “attract and deter” (Table 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>), is a form of viral manipulation by which NPT viruses increase the likelihood of their transmission to new hosts (Mauck et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>, Groen et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>, Carr et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). However, it is not clear if “attract and deter” viral manipulation would lead to more severe epidemics, because, for instance, increases in virus acquisition do not always lead to higher incidence of virus‐infected plants (Sisterson 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>).
</p>
