<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Aedes malayensis</italic> (Colless 1962) is a relatively understudied species with a wide distribution in Southeast Asia [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Its presence has been recorded in Taiwan, Vietnam, Cambodia, Peninsular Malaysia, the Andaman and Nicobar Islands of India and across several regions in Thailand [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. In our study, differences in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>malayensis</italic> prevalence between sampling sites may reflect variable microhabitat characteristics [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Sites with a majority of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>malayensis</italic> were mainly young secondary forests, whereas sites devoid of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>malayensis</italic> were a mixture of primary and secondary forests. 
 <italic>Aedes malayensis</italic> vector competence has not been fully characterized for DENV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] and is undocumented for CHIKV. A previous study showed the susceptibility of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>malayensis</italic> to all 4 DENV serotypes after oral infection [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] but did not determine the presence of virus in the saliva. Our data clearly established the high susceptibility of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>malayensis</italic> and validated its transmission capacity for both DENV-2 and CHIKV. Detection of virus in field-caught vectors is important evidence of potential vector capacity in natural settings. We did not detect DENV or CHIKV in our field-caught 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>malayensis</italic>. However, virus detection in field-caught vectors is challenging. For instance, a previous study failed to detect DENV in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> from the Cape Verde Island where the four DENV serotypes are endemic [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Importantly, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>malayensis</italic> have been shown to bite humans [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>] even though they oviposit outside of domiciles [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Altogether, these results establish for the first time the vector competence of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>malayensis</italic> for sympatric DENV-2 and CHIKV and warrants additional study to determine its role as a vector in Southeast Asia. There are a number of other 
 <italic>Stegomyia</italic> species in Southeast Asia that may be capable of transmitting DENV and CHIKV and should be investigated as well [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Such peridomestic vectors have been involved in transmitting epidemics of dengue and chikungunya [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>].
</p>
