<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Singapore represents a particular case in Southeast Asia and may illustrate the long-term frailties of the current vector control approach. We should learn from this example to support the continued monitoring of the efficacy of vector management. One of the richest countries (GDP per capita) in the world [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>], Singapore is primarily comprised of high-rise buildings [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>] equipped with architectural features that reduce potential larval habitats. This city-state can afford a permanent evidence-based integrated vector control programme widely regarded as a worldwide success [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. The 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> house index has been maintained at 1–2% for the past 45 years [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], which is well below the 4% threshold defined as an epidemic alert [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. Yet, the low dengue and chikungunya incidence could not be sustained for more than 30 years [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Here, we propose that the presence of highly competent vectors in city parks and forested areas may be contributing to transmission and maintenance of the viruses. Maintenance of low infection rates in few areas is enough to ensure the persistence of arboviruses in large cities and to initiate an outbreak when conditions are favorable [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. The presence of non-human primates, such as macaques in Singapore, coupled with competent zoonotic vectors may also provide alternative reservoirs as refugia for arboviruses [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. Risk of infection in parks is increased by the low herd immunity of the Singaporean population [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], the potential presence of asymptomatically infected people or those prior to clinical disease onset who are infectious to mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>], and wearing clothes that expose skin to mosquito biting. Furthermore, the high selection pressure [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>] on arbovirus transmission due to the overall low domestic vector population may select for more transmissible virus strains. Although further studies, including fine-scale tracking of patients and molecular epidemiology, are required to confirm localization of the foci of infection, our results strongly support the inclusion of peridomestic areas in the scope of vector control and surveillance programmes.
</p>
