<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0013">We analyzed the data using the so-called renewal process model. With 
 <italic>c</italic>
 <sub>t</sub> being the number of new cases of illness onset in week 
 <italic>t</italic>. The model intended to capture the renewal of cases according to the equation:
 <disp-formula id="eqn0001">
  <label>(1)</label>
  <math id="M1" altimg="si1.gif" overflow="scroll">
   <mrow>
    <msub>
     <mi>c</mi>
     <mi>t</mi>
    </msub>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <msub>
     <mi>R</mi>
     <mi>t</mi>
    </msub>
    <munderover>
     <mo>∑</mo>
     <mrow>
      <mi>τ</mi>
      <mo>=</mo>
      <mn>1</mn>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mi>t</mi>
      <mo>−</mo>
      <mn>1</mn>
     </mrow>
    </munderover>
    <mrow>
     <msub>
      <mi>c</mi>
      <mrow>
       <mi>t</mi>
       <mo>−</mo>
       <mi>τ</mi>
      </mrow>
     </msub>
     <msub>
      <mi>f</mi>
      <mi>τ</mi>
     </msub>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula>where 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>t</sub> is the effective reproduction number, i.e., the average number of secondary cases per single primary case in week 
 <italic>t</italic>, and 
 <italic>f</italic>
 <sub>τ</sub> is the probability mass function (pmf) of the serial interval of length 
 <italic>τ</italic>, defined as the time from illness onset in a primary case to illness onset in the secondary case produced by the primary case. The serial interval 
 <italic>f</italic>
 <sub>τ</sub> is modeled as a mixture distribution, 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="M2" altimg="si2.gif" overflow="scroll">
   <mrow>
    <msub>
     <mi>f</mi>
     <mi>τ</mi>
    </msub>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mrow>
     <mo>(</mo>
     <mn>1</mn>
     <mo>−</mo>
     <mi>p</mi>
     <mo>)</mo>
    </mrow>
    <mspace width="0.16em"/>
    <msub>
     <mi>g</mi>
     <mi>τ</mi>
    </msub>
    <mo>+</mo>
    <mi>p</mi>
    <mspace width="0.16em"/>
    <msub>
     <mi>h</mi>
     <mi>τ</mi>
    </msub>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>, where 
 <italic>p</italic> is the proportional weight of sexual transmission among the total secondary transmission events and 
 <italic>g</italic>
 <sub>τ</sub> is the pmf of the serial interval through a non-sexual route which is assumed to follow a gamma distribution (see below for discretization). 
 <italic>h</italic>
 <sub>τ</sub> is the pmf of the serial interval through sexual contact. The distribution 
 <italic>g</italic>
 <sub>τ</sub> was calculated as 
 <italic>g</italic>
 <sub>τ</sub> = 
 <italic>G</italic>(7
 <italic>τ</italic>)˗
 <italic>G</italic>(7(
 <italic>τ</italic>˗1)) for week τ &gt; 0, where 
 <italic>G</italic>(
 <italic>s</italic>) is the cumulative distribution function of the serial interval of direct contact during acute phase, following the gamma distribution, of length 
 <italic>s</italic> with mean (±standard deviation) estimated at 19.0 (±11.0) days in Guinea, 13.1 (±6.6) days in Liberia and 11.6 (±5.6) days in Sierra Leone, respectively, as estimated from the line list (
 <xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">WHO Ebola Response Team, 2014</xref>).
</p>
