<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The leaves were harvested 4-day-after infiltration for protein detection and quickly frozen into liquid nitrogen and stored in −80℃ until further analysis. Hand-held ultraviolet lamp at 365 nm was used for visual detection of GFP in the plant (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A, B</xref>). To obtain the expression levels of rHA, sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) and western blot were carried out. For total protein extraction, agroinfiltrated leaves of 50 mg (fresh weight) were ground to the fine powder in liquid nitrogen and then mixed with 150–200 µL Laemmli loading buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl [pH 6.8], 2% sodium dodecyl sulfate, 5% beta-mercaptoethanol, 10% glycerol, 0.2 mg/mL bromophenol blue, 1× protease inhibitor cocktail [GenDEPOT, Katy, TX, USA]) followed by 10-minute incubation in boiling water and centrifuged for 10 minutes. Alternatively, 200–300 µL of extraction buffer (50 mM Tris pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl, 2 mM ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid, 0.1% Triton X-100, 1× protease inhibitor cocktail [GenDEPOT]) was added to 100 mg and centrifuged at 13,000 rpm at 4℃ for 30 minutes. The supernatant was transferred to a new tube and protein concentration was determined by the Bradford assay. Total protein of 20 µg was resolved in the 10% Tris-glycine SDS-PAGE gel. The gel was then either stained with Coomassie brilliant blue G-250 or electrotransferred to polyvinylidene difluoride membrane (Merck, Darmstadt, Germany) using FLASBlot transfer buffer (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://advansta.com" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://advansta.com</ext-link>). The membrane was probed with a rabbit polyclonal influenza A H3N2-HA antibody (PA5-34930, Thermo Fisher, Waltham, MA, USA) in a dilution factor of 1:3,000 followed by the secondary antibody-alkaline phosphatase goat anti-rabbit IgG (AP-100-1, Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, CA, USA) in a dilution of 1:4,000 in phosphate buffered saline. Protein in the membrane was detected by using the ECL detection reagent. For the yield quantification, 100 ng and 125 ng commercially available H3N2-HA (recombinant partial length, Ab124562, Abcam, Cambridge, MA, USA) were used as a positive control. The plant made rHA yield was calculated by analyzing the protein band intensity in the membrane using the Image J software (National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA) and compared with that of commercially available recombinant.
</p>
