<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Myocardial injury can occur due to nonischemic myocardial process or myocardial ischemia. As a nonischemic myocardial factor, myocarditis and stress cardiomyopathy may make a significant contribution in acute myocardial injury of COVID-19 patients. In SARS, Oudit et al. demonstrated that SARS-CoV viral ribonucleic acid (RNA), macrophage infiltration, and myocardial damage were detected simultaneously in 35% of autopsied human heart samples from SARS patients [
 <xref rid="B53-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. They confirmed their findings by inducing pulmonary infection with human SARS-CoV in mice, which led to ACE2-dependent myocardial infection in the heart. Likewise, an acute myocarditis in MERS has also been proved by cardiac magnetic resonance image [
 <xref rid="B54-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. In line with these findings, a small study including 41 patients with COVID-19 suggested that patients who were clinically severe or critical had an increase of troponin I levels as well as low density of epicardial adipose tissue detected by CT, indicating cardiac inflammation [
 <xref rid="B55-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. An early report from China demonstrated that the late increase of hs-cTnI in nonsurvivors (day 16 after disease onset) showed a similar trend to inflammatory markers, including D-dimer, ferritin, IL-6, and lactate dehydrogenase. This kinetics may reflect cytokine storms and systemic inflammatory response syndrome, which provide a possible mechanism for acute myocardial injury due to myocarditis or stress-cardiomyopathy [
 <xref rid="B44-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. A recent case report by Tavassi et al. suggested that the heart can be directly involved in the viral infection by SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B57-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Endocardial biopsy from a COVID-19 patient with acute myocardial injury demonstrated low-grade myocardial inflammation and viral particles in interstitial cytopathic macrophages and their surroundings, but not in cardiomyocytes. In addition, another report by Meyer et al. described a typical case of takotsubo myocardiopathy in COVID-19 patient with acute myocardial injury [
 <xref rid="B58-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Altogether, these findings suggest that an acute myocardial injury in SARS-CoV-2 infection may occur as the disease severity advance by cytokine storms and systemic inflammation or viral infection to the myocardium. Several COVID-19 cases were reported to have cardiac symptoms at admission and diagnosed as fulminant myocarditis [
 <xref rid="B59-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. However, based on current available, but limited, data, the incidence of isolated fulminant myocarditis appears to be low.
</p>
