<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Lessons from the previous influenza epidemics suggest that viral infections can trigger acute coronary syndromes [
 <xref rid="B61-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. In a limited study of 75 patients hospitalized with SARS, acute myocardial infarction was the cause of death in two of five fatal cases [
 <xref rid="B26-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Although reports of type 1 myocardial infarction in the setting of COVID-19 are yet to be published, the profound inflammatory response and hemodynamic changes associated with such severe disease may confer an increased risk for atherosclerotic plaque rupture in susceptible patients [
 <xref rid="B7-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Moreover, the imbalance of oxygen supply and demand in the heart (type 2 myocardial infarction) may also play a partial role in the myocardial ischemia of COVID-19 patients. Several studies indicated that acute myocardial injury was observed in patients who required oxygen supports, including invasive ventilation and/or ECMO [
 <xref rid="B7-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Those patients may have hypoxemia or hypotension along with intense systemic inflammation, which may cause an oxygen supply and demand imbalance in the heart [
 <xref rid="B20-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>], especially when underlying CAD exists. Two recent clinical studies clarified the characteristics of patients having acute myocardial injury. In one cohort of 187 patients from China, 52 patients (28%) experienced troponin T elevation, which was related to the presence of underlying CAD (32.7% vs. 3.0%, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), cardiomyopathy (15.4% vs. 0%, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), and CV risk factors. Likewise, another cohort study including 416 Chinese patients suggested that chest pain at admission (13.4% vs. 0.9%, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), CAD (29.3% vs. 6.0%, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), and chronic heart failure (14.6% vs. 1.5%, 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001) were more common in patients with myocardial injury than those without myocardial injury. Although there are few pieces of evidence to establish a direct association between myocardial injury and CV comorbidities, it is rational to presume that patients with CAD or heart failure are susceptible to cardiac injury, and once such patients are infected with severe pneumonia, myocardial ischemia or cardiac dysfunction are more likely to occur, ultimately leading to a sudden deterioration. Microvascular thrombosis in small coronary vessels due to disseminated intravascular coagulation is another potential but unproven mechanism that may contribute to myocardial injury [
 <xref rid="B63-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Another important mechanism is that troponin levels can also be exacerbated in patients with renal insufficiency due to delayed excretion, which is common in patients with advanced disease.
</p>
