<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0030">ZIKV is a member of the 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic> family, which comprises other major global pathogens such as dengue virus, West Nile virus and yellow fever virus. Flavivirus encapsulate a positive-sense RNA genome that encodes a polyprotein that is co- and post-translationally cleaved into three structural (C, prM and E) and seven nonstructural (NS1, NS2A/2B, NS3, NS4A/4B and NS5) proteins [
 <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Nonstructural protein 1 (NS1) is a highly conserved glycoprotein among flaviviruses, which shows a molecular weight of 46−55 kDa depending on its glycosylation status. NS1 exists in multiple oligomeric forms: it is present in infected cells as a dimer and it is secreted as a hexameric soluble lipoparticle [
 <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>]. Intracellular NS1 has been associated with early steps of viral replication, whereas secreted NS1 has been involved with immune evasion [
 <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0115" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>]. The extracellular NS1 hexamer is highly immunogenic during flavivirus infection: high levels of this protein circulate in the bloodstream of infected patients during the acute phase up to the ninth day after the onset of the symptoms, and anti-NS1 IgM or IgG antibodies can be detected within 4–7 or 8 days after the initial exposure, respectively [
 <xref rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>]. These properties turn NS1 glycoprotein into a good diagnostic marker, allowing flavivirus early detection in infected patients [
 <xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].
</p>
