<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0040">Obtaining a functional ZIKV hexameric NS1 protein for diagnosis is not trivial. Post-translational modifications play a critical role in preserving biological functions of proteins. In the case of NS1, the hydrophilic monomer that is released from the viral polyprotein to the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) lumen contains 12 cysteines that form 6 discrete disulfide bonds, which contribute to its stabilization and correct folding [
 <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In line with this, mutagenesis reports have shown that the last 3 cysteines are crucial for NS1 maturation, oligomerization and secretion [
 <xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Following cleavage in the ER, the NS1 monomer is glycosylated by the addition of high-mannose carbohydrate moieties [
 <xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Next, it rapidly forms dimeric species, leading to the acquisition of a partially hydrophobic nature and thus associating with the ER membrane [
 <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. NS1 traffics from the ER through the Golgi, where dimeric subunits associate to form soluble hexamers and exposed carbohydrates are trimmed and processed to more complex sugars [
 <xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Considering that bacterial expression systems produce recombinant proteins that are usually not soluble and lose their structural and immunological features of the native viral protein, recombinant protein production by mammalian cells is preferred since it allows proper protein folding, post-translational modifications and protein assembly [
 <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. With this strategy in mind ―and considering that recombinant expression studies have reported that NS1 multimeric species form spontaneously in the absence of other viral proteins― [
 <xref rid="bib0195" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], the aim of this study consisted of establishing a stable and optimized recombinant ZIKV NS1 (rZNS1) expression system from HEK293 cells in order to purify high yields of the hexameric protein, which could potentially be used in the development of diagnostic tests to detect ZIKV infection. Stable rZNS1-hexa-histidine (His)-expressing HEK293 cells were generated through transduction with a lentiviral vector. Enrichment of positive rZNS1-His-expressing cells was carried out by limiting dilution cloning, obtaining 1E4-C9 clone, which presented the highest intracellular and secreted rZNS1-His protein levels. Optimization of rZNS1-His protein secretion in 1E4-C9 HEK293 cells was achieved with 50 nM rapamycin treatment followed by serum-free media incubation for 9 days, obtaining a 29-fold protein production increase. Purified rZNS1-His hexamer was recognized by anti-NS1 antibodies in ZIKV patient's serum and showed the ability to induce a humoral response in immunized mice. The obtained recombinant protein may be of significant value for the development of improved diagnostic methods for the detection of ZIKV in infected patients during the acute phase.
</p>
