<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Equity Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Equity Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal for Equity in Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1475-9276</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7226711</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1190</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12939-020-01190-8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Letter to the Editor</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>&#x0201c;Pairing assistance&#x0201d;: the effective way to solve the breakdown of health services system caused by COVID-19 pandemic</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Tianxiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Ying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1447-3349</contrib-id><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>Lei</given-names></name><address><email>leihuapir@gmail.com</email><email>leihuapir@outlook.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.12981.33</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2360 039X</institution-id><institution>School of Government, </institution><institution>Sun Yat-sen University, </institution></institution-wrap>Guangzhou, Guangdong China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.12981.33</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2360 039X</institution-id><institution>Department of Public Administration, </institution><institution>Nanfang College of Sun Yat-sen University, </institution></institution-wrap>Guangzhou, Guangdong China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><elocation-id>68</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">The most terrifying thing about pandemic could be the large number of patients running against the health service system, which causes a serious shortage of health resources, especially medical personnel. Plotting mortality and diagnosis rates against medical staff resources in 16 cities in Hubei Province, where the epidemic was initially concerned and the most severe, shows a significant negative correlation, indicating the critical role of medical staff resources in controlling epidemics. Nevertheless, it is difficult to ensure that there exist enough medical personnel in cities severely hit by the outbreak. China provides solutions by adopting nationwide &#x0201c;pairing assistance&#x0201d; measures with at least one province assisting one city to alleviate pressure in the most severe area. By plotting the number of patients receiving treatment against day, it is clear that implementing &#x0201c;pairing assistance&#x0201d; is a turning point in China&#x02019;s fight against epidemics.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Pairing assistance</kwd><kwd>Health resources</kwd><kwd>Health service system</kwd><kwd>Medical personnel</kwd><kwd>COVID-19 pandemic</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par2">An epidemic of Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), which was first identified in Wuhan City, Hubei Province, China in late December 2019, has spread throughout the world rapidly. The coronavirus crisis in China has abated after 2 months of hard work, while the rest of the world has sunk into an increasingly complex quagmire. Scholars own China&#x02019;s success in controlling COVID-19 to aggressive control measures, such as shutting down industrial and commercial restrictions, monitoring infected person and preventing cross-infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. However, the terrifying thing about a pandemic is that the influx of patients overloads the health services system, which leads to a serious shortage of health resources, especially for medical personnel.</p><p id="Par3">By plotting mortality (by Mar 31, 2020) and diagnosis rates (the number of confirmed cases per 1000 population by Mar 31, 2020) against medical personnel resources (the number of medical personnel per 1000 population before the COVID-19 pandemic) in 16 cities in Hubei Province where the virus epicenter in China, we find a significant negative correlation shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, suggesting the crucial role of medical personnel resources in controlling the pandemic.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Mortality and diagnosis rates against medical personnel resources</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12939_2020_1190_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par4">Thus, the medical personnel resources are so important that we should spare no effort to ensure adequate numbers of medical personnel. However, it is difficult for cities severely hit by the outbreak. China offers a solution by taking the nationwide &#x0201c;pairing assistance&#x0201d; measure, mobilizing 29 provinces to alleviate pressure on cities in Hubei province. For example, Wuhan, the provincial capital and the city hardest hit by the disease, had already received 32,572 medical personnel nationwide by Feb 20, 2020. Meanwhile, the other 16 cities with fewer technologies, personnel, and equipment than Wuhan were each partnered with at least one province that has sufficient capacity to assist them (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Pairing assistance with 29 provinces mobilized to support cities in Hubei province</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12939_2020_1190_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par5">The massive mobilization of medical staff, which aims to assist 16 cities besides Wuhan, was started on Feb 11, 2020, while the &#x0201c;pairing assistance&#x0201d; medical personnel got to work in pairing cities from Feb 13, 2020 (the 22nd day after the lockdown of Wuhan). Plotting the number of patients still undergoing treatment against the day clearly showed that the 22nd day after the lockdown of Wuhan was the turning point in fighting the epidemic (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) although the total number of confirmed cases was still increasing rapidly at that time, illustrating the evident effect of &#x0201c;pairing assistance&#x0201d; on increasing the cure rate and relieving the pressure on health services system. It is worth noting that Shennongjia Forestry District has a high level of medical personnel resources (2.999 medical personnel per thousand population) and the smallest number of patients (only 11 confirmed cases), so it shows a different curve pattern.
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>The change of the number of patients still undergoing treatment</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12939_2020_1190_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par6">In the context of globalization, what we can learn from China&#x02019;s &#x0201c;pairing assistance&#x0201d; is that the COVID-19 pandemic is not just the business of a single province or a single country. Every sector, every individual and every country must be involved in the fight and support each other. Areas with less severe outbreaks should provide medical resources within their capabilities to the areas with the most severe pandemics. Only by taking the &#x0201c;pairing assistance&#x0201d; measures can we defeat COVID-19, because no one can be immune from the worldwide pandemic.</p></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>Not applicable.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>TC and LH conceived of the study, collected statistical data, conducted analyses, and prepared the manuscript draft; YW collected statistical data and commented on manuscript drafts. All authors contributed to manuscript revision, read and approved the submitted version.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>There was no funding for the research reported in the present article.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The datasets are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par7">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par8">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par9">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kupferschmidt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Can China&#x02019;s COVID-19 strategy work elsewhere?</article-title><source>Science.</source><year>2020</year><volume>367</volume><fpage>1061</fpage><lpage>1062</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.367.6482.1061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32139521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>S-Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characteristics of and public health responses to the coronavirus disease 2019 outbreak in China</article-title><source>JCM.</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>575</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm9020575</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spector-Bagdady</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hospitals should act now to notify patients about research use of their data and biospecimens</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>306</fpage><lpage>308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-020-0795-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32161402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>EJY</given-names></name></person-group><source>The China Experience &#x02013; Understanding the Evolution of the COVID-19 Crisis (Updated on 6 April, 2020)</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kraemer MUG, Yang C-H, Gutierrez B, Wu C-H, Klein B, Pigott DM, et al. The effect of human mobility and control measures on the COVID-19 epidemic in China. Science. 2020. 10.1126/science.abb4218.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>