<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ADE is a kinetic force of infection but by itself is not a direct cause of pathology. Recent work in several laboratories has uncovered a pathogen that mediates DVPS with enhanced infections that occur with actively or passively acquired dengue antibodies. It was long known that fatal DENV infections of mice could be prevented by anti-NS1 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>
 </sup>. NS1 is produced during all four DENV infections as well as those of other pathogenic flaviviruses 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>
 </sup>. Instead of remaining cell-bound, dengue NS1 is released as a hexamer circulating in great quantities in acute-phase blood 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>
 </sup>. A perceptive study, published in 2006, suggested that the high levels of circulating NS1 documented in patients with severe dengue might activate complement to mediate vascular permeability 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>
 </sup>. Dengue NS1 has been shown to activate complement by the alternative pathway, target liver cells promoting intracellular DENV infection, complex with thrombin in acute-phase blood of severe dengue, activate platelets 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> via Toll-like-receptor 4 (TLR4), and produce thrombocytopenia in TLR4 knockout and normal mice 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>– 
  <xref rid="ref-93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>
 </sup>. In 2015, an analogy between the cellular biology of bacterial lipopolysaccharides (LPSs) and that of DENV NS1 was discovered 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>
 </sup>. Each interacts with TLR4 on the surface of monocytes, macrophages, and endothelial cells, inducing the release of a range of cytokines and chemokines. Some of these same cytokines and chemokines have been found in the blood of patients accompanying DVPS. 
 <italic>In vitro</italic>, NS1 disrupted endothelial cell monolayer integrity. The authors concluded that DVPS was a viral protein toxicosis. NS1-mediated cytokine release could be inhibited by the TLR4 antagonist LPS– 
 <italic>Rhodobacter sphaeroides</italic>, suggesting an avenue for therapeutic intervention.
</p>
