<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par31">Previous researches have reported on the molecular genetic evolution of LNV isolated in China and Australia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. However, the data used for analysis were only limited to the local LNV isolates [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. China in Asia and Australia in the South Pacific are located in the northern and southern hemispheres, respectively. The natural environment in the two regions were significant different from each other. These observations raise several questions. What is the genetic relationship between the LNVs isolated from different regions? What are the characteristics of the molecular evolution of the entire LNV population? Where is the origin of LNVs? Recent revolutionary developments in virology bioinformatics provide unprecedented opportunities for analyzing the viral genetic data (nucleotide or amino acid) to model the evolutionary relationships between virus samples and help to explain epidemiological patterns and uncover processes of transmission [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Examples of such analyses include the estimation of origin and divergence time of 
 <italic>Japanese encephalitis virus</italic> (JEV) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>],identification of phylogenetic relationships among viral lineages in 
 <italic>Zika virus</italic> (ZIKV) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], inference of phylogeographic history and migration patterns of recent epidemics of 
 <italic>Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus</italic> (MERS-CoV) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] and 
 <italic>Ebola virus</italic> (EBOV) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Therefore, in the present study a comprehensive phylogeographic study of all the LNVs isolated worldwide were conducted to explore the molecular genetic evolution and migration patterns of LNVs isolated from different vectors since 1990 in China and Australia.
</p>
