<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our model has several limitations but also some strengths compared with past work. We captured spatial heterogeneity in the disease using a statistical rather than a mechanistic approach. Our model does not explicitly represent the spatial distribution of vectors nor disease reservoirs unlike Shearer et al’s model [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008304.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. However, the set of spatial predictors we used has been demonstrated to have good predictive power for both presence and seasonality of YF [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008304.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Moreover, the environmental covariate we used as spatial predictor for case reports are frequently used to predict the spatial distribution of vectors or reservoirs [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008304.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008304.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. To our knowledge, our model is the only one calibrated against serological data that captures the whole spectrum of disease severity. Other YF burden estimates stem from models calibrated on reported cases [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008304.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008304.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], that may lead to underestimation due to under-reporting and misdiagnosis. For instance, the Global Burden of Disease estimates for 2016 around 5,000 YF-deaths in Africa, which is near to the lower bound of our 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> model estimates. Lastly, the development of the 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> variant of our model constitutes a novel approach to account for herd effects in the impact of YF vaccination. Our results highlight that heterogeneity in transmission intensity imply different vaccination threshold to be reached in order to prevent YF outbreaks. This can be used to locally adapt the empirical threshold of 80% vaccination coverage that is often considered sufficient for YF outbreak prevention [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008304.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].
</p>
