<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To analyze the determinants of NHIF enrollment among HIV positive pregnant women, we began by using cross-tabulation to describe the average distribution of the demographic and behavioral characteristics of HIV positive pregnant women by their NHIF status, in both the EMR and institutional delivery sample (
 <xref rid="ijerph-17-02892-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Next, we undertook a bivariate logistic regression analysis [
 <xref rid="B61-ijerph-17-02892" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>] to explore how each individual demographic, clinical and behavioral characteristic is associated with NHIF membership, the nature and strength of the association, and if it predicts enrollment in the NHIF (
 <xref rid="ijerph-17-02892-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). In the bivariate logistic regression, the dependent variable is NHIF enrollment (Yes/No) and the predictor is a demographic, clinical or behavioral variable. Beyond the bivariate analysis, we were interested in establishing which of the demographic, clinical and behavioral characteristics, considered together, have the greatest influence on NHIF enrollment. We thus used multivariate logistic regression [
 <xref rid="B62-ijerph-17-02892" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-ijerph-17-02892" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] to model how the different variables determine health insurance enrollment (
 <xref rid="ijerph-17-02892-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). We implemented the multivariate regression models by using substantive theory to select the variables included in the model [
 <xref rid="B64-ijerph-17-02892" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. After model specification, we performed two goodness-of-fit (gof) tests using the ‘estat gof’ command in Stata. The first iteration was an ‘estat gof’ command with no options that performs a Pearson gof test, and the second iteration was ‘estat gof’ with the group option (we specified 10 groups) that performs a Hosmer-Lemeshow goodness-of-fit test [
 <xref rid="B65-ijerph-17-02892" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-ijerph-17-02892" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The chi-square statistic from these models were 0.83 and 0.38, respectively. As such, we cannot reject our model. We also used a correlation matrix to check for collinearity [
 <xref rid="B67-ijerph-17-02892" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. The discussion of the results is based on the results from the multivariate regression model. All the analysis was done in Stata 16.
</p>
