<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Viral attachment to the cell requires many sequential interactions with various receptors. DC-SIGN and glycosaminoglycans (GAGs) are known as the first line of attachment receptors. The second line of higher affinity receptors may then be recruited to permit DENV entry because of the diverse tissue tropism of the virus [
 <xref rid="B94-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. DENV uses two pathways to enter DCs, whereby infection can enter immature DCs through DC-SIGN, or through Fc gamma receptors (FcɣRs) in mature DCs. DCs expressed FcɣRs as the second line of a higher affinity receptor in host cells, and activation of FcɣRs in hematopoietic cells serves to remove antibody-opsonized antigens—including DENV—from the body circulation system. However, cross-reactive or sub-neutralizing levels of antibodies grant an alternative entry pathway of DENV, where DENV enters monocytes, macrophages, and dendritic cells through the activating FcɣRs [
 <xref rid="B95-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. DENV can enter cells via cellular attachment molecules’ TIM and TAM receptors [
 <xref rid="B76-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>], as both are able to recognize the apoptotic marker phosphatidylserine (PtdSer) and are responsible for the engulfment and removal of apoptotic cells. Since DENV is a virus that exposes PtdSer in its membrane, it naturally enters the cell as a PtdSer through direct binding of the TIM receptor or indirectly via the TAM receptor. Moreover, apoptotic marker PtdSer binds with TIM and TAM by the help of the growth arrest-specific 6 (Gas6) binder molecule (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="microorganisms-07-00296-f003">Figure 3</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B96-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>,
 <xref rid="B97-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. Cell surface chaperones, heat shock protein (HSP-90, HSP-70), and GRP-78 are known as a receptor complex, which allows DENV entry into human cells from hepatic, neural, and monocytic cells [
 <xref rid="B75-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>,
 <xref rid="B98-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. The interaction between apolipoprotein A-I and the scavenger receptor class B type I (SCARB1), also known as SR-BI, promotes DENV infections, necessitating further research in order to elucidate the functional importance of lipoproteins in dengue pathogenesis [
 <xref rid="B87-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>].
</p>
