<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">Respiratory syncytial virus (RSV), parainfluenza virus (PIV), and human metapneumovirus 
 <bold>(</bold>HMPV) are enveloped, nonsegmented, negative-sense, single-stranded RNA viruses belonging to the 
 <italic>Paramyxoviridae</italic> family
 <italic>.</italic> These viruses are a significant cause of morbidity and mortality globally, especially among children in developing countries [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. RSV is the most important pathogenic infection of childhood worldwide, causing a variety of manifestations from mild upper respiratory tract illnesses or otitis media to severe and potentially life-threatening lower respiratory tract illnesses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Four PIV types (PIV1–4) have been identified [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. PIV1 and PIV2 are best known as the cause of croup whereas PIV3 is a common cause of bronchiolitis and pneumonia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. PIV4 infection has low prevalence [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. HMPV was first discovered in patients with acute respiratory illness (ARI) in 2001 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Since then, HMPV has been associated with ARI in children as well as elderly and immunocompromised adults [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. RSV, PIV, and HMPV are also important causes of nosocomial infection, which might be life-threatening in certain individuals, such as transplant or immunocompromised patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Until now, no effective vaccine for RSV has been available. The RSV-specific monoclonal antibody palivizumab has been advocated for use as prophylaxis in high-risk patients against RSV infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. However, there is no available vaccine or specific antiviral treatment for PIV and HMPV infection. Consequently, it is imperative to conduct further research, especially in low- and middle-income countries, to understand the epidemiological features of these pathogens in different areas and populations.
</p>
