<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0025">The age of exploration led by Europeans starting in the 15th century inevitably spread many infectious diseases globally. Without previous exposure, as many as 90% of the indigenous people inhabiting North and South America perished due to smallpox, measles, and bubonic plague among other infectious diseases brought by Europeans. Upon arrival at new continents, colonists encountered many indigenous medicinal plants, which they then introduced back to Europe and other parts of the old world through trade. For instance, the miraculous antimalarial property of Cinchona tree bark was rediscovered by Spanish settlers in Peru in the mid-17th century. In the following years, Cinchona tree bark quickly became a highly prized medicine and was traded globally. Driven by curiosity and the need to deter species adulteration in medicinal plant trade, the field of plant systematics flourished. This culminated in the publication of 
 <italic>Species Plantarum</italic> by Carl Linnaeus in 1753, which established the foundation of plant taxonomy as we know it today. In addition, the growing interest in medicinal botany prompted the origins of botanical gardens in several European countries, so that plants brought back by colonists from all over the world could be cultivated and studied. Long-distance maritime voyages also caused health problems, such as scurvy, a common disease among sailors in the British Navy in the 18th century, manifested by deteriorating connective tissue. To find a cure for scurvy, James Lind, a naval physician, ran the first reported, controlled clinical trial in the history of medicine on the ship HMS 
 <italic>Salisbury</italic> in 1747, and found citrus fruit to be an effective cure for scurvy. The rapid advances in medicinal botany and medical sciences for diseases during this period in turn protected the health of colonists when they continued to explore distant territories, contributing to the establishment of many colonial empires by the 19th century.
</p>
