<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While previous studies established a link between empirical differences in EIP duration and epidemiological fitness of arbovirus strains [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], the effect of EIP on transmission has typically been extrapolated using a single value of EIP for the entire mosquito population. Our study went one step further by considering EIP as a quantitative trait following a population distribution [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Our results support the conclusion that the classic approach of measuring EIP as a ‘threshold’ time point at which the first mosquitoes become infectious is likely misleading for a mosquito population (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1007187.s007">S1 File</xref>). We used the cumulative proportion of infectious mosquitoes over time to infer the population distribution of lag time values (our proxy for EIP). Our results confirm that the distribution of lag time values cannot be described with a fixed threshold model because it derives from the sigmoid shape of a logistic function [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Furthermore, the inferred distribution of individual EIP values had a different shape between DENV isolates, adding another layer of complexity for comparing the epidemiological and evolutionary potential of different strains. Thus, our results lead to the conclusion that EIP is a quantitative trait that cannot be encapsulated in a single value for a given set of conditions. Although our general recommendation for future modeling studies is to use a full 3-parameter model whenever possible, EIP
 <sub>50</sub> can be considered as the most relevant single parameter because 
 <italic>M</italic> (half of the maximum proportion of infected mosquitoes with a systemic infection) was the most influential in our model.
</p>
