<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is well established that the duration of DENV EIP can be influenced by environmental factors such as temperature [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Recently, Ye and colleagues used a breeding design to demonstrate that the duration of DENV EIP is also influenced by mosquito genes [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Genetic variation is a prerequisite for the evolution of a trait, but it is unlikely that natural selection would act on mosquito populations to drive evolution of DENV EIP. This is because DENV infection in natural 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> populations is rare [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] and does not significantly affect mosquito lifespan [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Conversely, variation in EIP duration among DENV strains could fuel the evolution of a shorter EIP. Under field conditions, a significant proportion of adult mosquitoes are expected to die before they are capable of transmitting virus. A shorter EIP would confer virus variants a significant evolutionary advantage by increasing their probability of transmission. However, DENV transmission rarely occurs before at least 7 days of EIP in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Unlike other arboviruses with an EIP that can be as short as 2–3 days [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], the longer duration of DENV EIP is presumably evolutionarily constrained. Results from the present study indicate that evolution of a shorter DENV EIP is not restricted by a lack of standing genetic variation for this trait among virus strains.
</p>
