<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We used the kinetics of systemic mosquito infection as a proxy for EIP dynamics due to the logistical and ethical constraints of experimentally measuring mosquito-to-human DENV transmission. We assumed that the virus presence in mosquito head tissues indicated the potential for onward transmission based on evidence that DENV is detected a few days earlier in head tissues than in salivary glands [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], and lack of evidence for a salivary gland escape barrier in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. However, it is possible that our measurements of EIP duration based on the lag time of systemic infection are underestimates. The probability of detecting DENV in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> saliva is positively correlated with the infectious titer of disseminated virus [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Therefore, we cannot exclude that some mosquitoes had virus titers in their head tissues that were high enough to be detected, but too low to result in virus release in saliva. The extent of underestimation is unknown but should not change the interpretation of differences between strains under the assumption that this underestimation is proportionate. Another limitation of our study is that we used a very narrow range of infectious doses to orally challenge the mosquitoes. Infectious dose is one of the most powerful determinants of DENV infection probability and EIP duration in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007187.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. It is therefore possible that the parameter estimates of mosquito infection kinetics would have been different if we had used a larger range of infectious doses. Finally, we used a minimal number of cell culture passages to produce the viral stocks, which may have promoted adaptation to mosquito cells. However, we know of no evidence that adaptation to mosquito cell culture would translate into differences in viral dissemination 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>.
</p>
