<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par74">Chemical warfare agents (CWAs) and toxic industrial chemicals (TICs) can pose problems during military conflicts and terrorism since most CWA and TIC exposures are difficult to manage as these agents have a rapid onset of action and can kill, injure or incapacitate human beings within no time. The mostly unprepared individuals get affected almost immediately; the first responders can get accidentally exposed, and the population in the vicinity can get affected rapidly. The specific mode of toxicity of these agents is varied; they are often mediated either directly or indirectly with increased oxidative stress in biological systems. Consequently, a plethora of antioxidants have been explored as potential medical countermeasures for CWA/TIC exposures. In DRDO, studies have been performed with a diverse array of CWAs, model organisms, exposure systems, target organs and antioxidants, looking at an almost equally assorted set of endpoints. Endeavours at treating CWAs/TICs with antioxidants have often met with mixed results, though exploration of antioxidants as medical countermeasures for CWA/TIC management has shown some potential. A plethora of herbal drugs have been utilized for their protective efficacy against chemical warfare agents, including extremely toxic sulphur mustard (SM). Ethanolic extract of 
 <italic>Hippophae rhamnoides</italic> leaf (HL-EOH), water and ethanolic extract of 
 <italic>H. rhamnoides</italic> fruit (HF-W and HF-EOH) and 
 <italic>H. rhamnoides</italic> flavone from fruit (HR-flavone) were evaluated against percutaneously administered sulphur mustard (Vijayaraghavan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2006</xref>). The 
 <italic>H. rhamnoides</italic> extracts (1 g/kg; 3 doses; po) significantly protected SM-induced lethality. Following percutaneous administration of sulphur mustard, reduced glutathione and oxidized glutathione levels decreased, and malondialdehyde was elevated. Oral administration of HL-EOH and HR-flavone significantly protected against loss of body weight. Following oral administration of ethanolic leaf extract and HR-flavone, recovery GSH, GSSG and MDA levels were recorded. The authors concluded that percutaneous administration of sulphur mustard induces oxidative stress, and ethanolic extract of leaf of 
 <italic>H. rhamnoides</italic> and 
 <italic>H. rhamnoides</italic> flavone from fruit can significantly protect against sulphur mustard-induced toxicity.
</p>
