<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An alternative approach to targeting IE mRNA and hence IE gene silencing, is to utilize gene-targeting ribozymes, which are catalytically active RNA molecules that specifically cleave target mRNA sequences. M1GS ribozyme technology has been used to target both IE1 and IE2 by utilizing the shared mRNA region of these genes [
 <xref rid="B303-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">303</xref>,
 <xref rid="B304-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">304</xref>,
 <xref rid="B305-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">305</xref>,
 <xref rid="B306-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">306</xref>]. Target IE1/2 mRNA sequences have been selected by determining accessibility for M1GS binding via dimethyl sulfate mapping [
 <xref rid="B303-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">303</xref>,
 <xref rid="B304-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">304</xref>,
 <xref rid="B305-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">305</xref>,
 <xref rid="B306-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">306</xref>]. M1GS is partially derived from the M1 RNA catalytic subunit of the 
 <italic>E.coli</italic> RNase P ribozyme, which mediates tRNA maturation [
 <xref rid="B307-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">307</xref>,
 <xref rid="B308-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">308</xref>]. M1 RNA can be converted into an M1SG sequence-specific ribozyme by covalently linking it to an external guide sequence (EGS) that contains nucleotides complementary to the target mRNA sequence [
 <xref rid="B307-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">307</xref>,
 <xref rid="B308-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">308</xref>]. The tertiary structure generated upon hybridization between the mRNA substrate and the EGS is required for recognition and cleavage by the ribozyme active site [
 <xref rid="B307-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">307</xref>,
 <xref rid="B308-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">308</xref>]. The initial IE1/2-targeted study used a wild-type M1 sequence and IE1/2 exon 3 as the cleavage site. This IE1/2-targeted ribozyme reduced IE1/2 gene expression by 75–80% and inhibited HCMV replication 150-fold in cell culture [
 <xref rid="B303-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">303</xref>]. A protein engineering and selection strategy has subsequently been employed to identify various highly active M1SG variants containing mutations in M1 that enhance substrate binding and cleavage rates [
 <xref rid="B304-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">304</xref>,
 <xref rid="B305-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">305</xref>,
 <xref rid="B306-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">306</xref>,
 <xref rid="B309-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">309</xref>]. The most potent variant reported to-date, F-R228-IE, reduced IE1/2 expression by 98%–99% and inhibited HCMV replication 50,000-fold in cell culture [
 <xref rid="B306-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">306</xref>]. F-R228-IE uses nucleotide position 43 downstream from the IE1/2 initiation codon as the designated cleavage site and contains three M1 RNA point mutations (G59A, C123U, C326U). However, the mechanism by which these mutations enhance cleavage is currently unknown [
 <xref rid="B306-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">306</xref>]. Whilst M1SG technology has potential for HCMV therapeutic applications, to the best of our knowledge it has not yet been clinically tested.
</p>
