<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0070">Over time, there was a change from addiction to prescription opioids to a new heroin epidemic across the country, which was predominantly found to involve the rapidly available and less expensive black tar heroin coming from Mexico,
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>28</sup>
 </xref> which in turn led to another spike in overdose deaths and associated with more HCV and HIV outbreaks nationally. It is important to remember that the early HIV epidemic was associated with white heroin from Asia, which had low supply levels in the United States back then and was predominantly affecting urban African Americans.
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>28</sup>
 </xref> Very little public outcry was heard and, in response, there was a war on drugs that led to the country’s mass incarceration of predominantly PWUD, who were predominantly young African American men. In comparison, the current opioid epidemic is affecting urban and rural communities among mainly young white men and women. Later, the opioid epidemic worsened again with the availability of the less expensive illicitly manufactured fentanyl, and this epidemic has been plaguing the country in isolation as well as now more routinely associated with an increasing stimulant epidemic involving widespread use of methamphetamine, which is causing even more overdose deaths and more infectious disease outbreaks without any evidence of abating.
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>29</sup>
 </xref> The reason the United States did not have a rapidly expanding opioid epidemic in the 1970s and 1980s was predominantly that there was a lack of widespread opioid supply, but, with the rapidly expanding prescription opioid epidemic, the supply increased dramatically in the late 1990s, leading to rapid opioid addiction by persons affected by OUD that was easily fulfilled by the less expensive and easily available black tar heroin that was supplied through Mexico and now the illicitly manufactured fentanyl.
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>28</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>30</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
