<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 6.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>METTL3 interacts with EV71 polymerase 3D. (
   <bold>A</bold>) Coomassie blue staining. pFlag-METTL3 was transfected into RD cells followed by EV71 infection. Cell lysates were subjected to IP with an anti-Flag antibody and then to Coomassie blue staining. (
   <bold>B</bold> and 
   <bold>C</bold>) Western blotting. HEK293T cells were transfected with pMETTL3 and pFlag-3D. Co-IP was performed with anti-Flag or IgG (B) or anti-METTL3 or IgG (C) antibodies. The immunoblots were probed with the anti-Flag or anti-METTL3 antibodies. (
   <bold>D</bold>) Confocal microscopy images of Vero cells transfected by Vector or 3D. Costaining was performed using an anti-METTL3 antibody (green) and anti-Flag antibody (red), together with Hoechst to stain the nucleus (blue). (
   <bold>E</bold>) Relative fluorescence intensity of METTL3 in the cytoplasm versus the nucleus was quantified using ImageJ and graphed in box-and-whisker plots, representing the minimum, first quartile, median, third quartile, and maximum. Unpaired Student's 
   <italic>t</italic>-test was performed (
   <italic>n</italic> ≥ 10). **
   <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.01. (
   <bold>F</bold>) Western blotting. HEK293T cells were transfected with 1 μg of pFlag-3D and pMETTL3 (0, 0.5, 0.75, 1, 2 and 4 μg, respectively) in 30-mm dishes. The expression of METTL3 and 3D was detected by western blotting. Relative intensity of 3D versus GAPDH was quantified using ImageJ program. The data are shown as the means ± SD (
   <italic>n</italic> = 3). (
   <bold>G</bold>–
   <bold>I</bold>) Western blotting. HEK293T cells were transfected with pMETTL3, pMETTL14, pHA-WTAP, and pFlag-3D. Co-IP was performed with anti-Flag or IgG (G), or anti-HA or IgG (H), or anti-METTL14 or IgG (I) antibodies. The immunoblots were probed with indicated antibodies.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="gky1007fig6" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
