<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Among all means of transport, herein we emphasize the role of road transportation in the spatial diffusion of the 2009 influenza A (H1N1) virus in mainland China. It has been reported recently that both aviation and road travel have a significant association with the epidemic arrival day in each prefecture-level city during the whole viral diffusion period, but the role of rail travel was only significant after August 1st 2009 [
 <xref rid="B41-ijerph-16-01223" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Although air travel is a significant factor in the global spread of the influenza virus, short-range daily travel on the ground is more important at the regional scale [
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-16-01223" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], which our results support. To the best of our knowledge, most Chinese people do not travel by air very often (at least in 2009, except for businessmen). Airplanes bring virus carriers to areas that are far from each other and disease-free before landing, which may lead to a spatially random dispersal of viral pathogens. In daily commuting, an infectious individual is likely to infect anyone with whom he/she is in contact, with the probability of infection associated with spatial distance and time length of contact, which may result in a spatially structured viral population [
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-16-01223" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In our spatial regression analyses, the spatial dependence coefficient 
 <italic>ρ</italic> of three epidemiological features are all significant and positive, which means that the epidemic in a city was positively correlated with those in neighboring cities and indicates that road travel would be more important than air travel for the spatial transmission of the 2009 influenza A (H1N1) virus in China. Unlike some countries in Europe and America which experienced two infection peaks of influenza during 2009, China had only one autumn-winter wave in 2009, which could be attributed to the strict prevention and control strategies conducted by China at the early stage of the pandemic [
 <xref rid="B34-ijerph-16-01223" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. For example, fever screenings performed in airports and railway stations could be expected to detect most symptomatic passengers with a fever, but the expected efficiency of fever screenings in long-distance highway passenger stations should be much lower because a bus is allowed to pick up passengers along the way and they need not gather in a specifically designated station before boarding and because a considerable number of highway passengers would choose private vehicles. Therefore, it is much more difficult to restrict the diffusion of influenza virus by road travel. In this respect, the role of highway passenger transport in dispersing viruses spatially is more important than air and railway modes.
</p>
