<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>WC5′s discovery together with its novel mechanism of action provided proof-of-principle that IE2 is a valid target for drug discovery and encouraged a screening campaign to identify new compounds targeting IE2 [
 <xref rid="B364-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">364</xref>,
 <xref rid="B380-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">380</xref>]. A screen has been performed employing essentially the same cell-based assay used to determine WC5′s mechanism of action as an inhibitor of IE2-mediated transactivation of early gene expression [
 <xref rid="B374-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">374</xref>]. Assay optimization identified conditions using the stable cell-line that expresses EGFP under the control of the IE2-dependent UL54 early promoter as suitable for screening purposes [
 <xref rid="B364-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">364</xref>]. A 2320 bioactive compound library including all FDA-approved drugs was screened and six hit compounds have so far been selected for further study [
 <xref rid="B364-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">364</xref>,
 <xref rid="B381-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">381</xref>,
 <xref rid="B382-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">382</xref>]. These hit compounds are deguelin (DGN), nitazoxanide (NTZ), thioguanosine (TGN), alexidine dihydrochloride (AXN), manidipine dihydrochloride (MND) and berberine (BBR). All hits inhibited HCMV replication with EC
 <sub>50</sub> values in the low micromolar range and lacked significant toxicity. This antiviral activity was observed for laboratory, clinical and drug-resistant HCMV isolates. Further, MND was shown to be inactive against a selection of other DNA and RNA viruses and is thus likely to be a specific anti-HCMV compound [
 <xref rid="B381-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">381</xref>]. The antiviral mechanism of these compounds was confirmed to be inhibition of IE2-mediated viral early gene transactivation and, like with WC5, a minimal 150-bp segment of the UL54 promoter is sufficient for inhibitory activity. However, the precise mechanism of action has not been elucidated, although prior knowledge of these bioactive compounds has led to the proposal that they are likely to interfere with pathways in HCMV-infected cells that are required for the switch from the IE to early phase of viral replication [
 <xref rid="B364-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">364</xref>]. Despite the lack of a precise mechanism of action, repurposing of bioactive compounds for anti-HCMV activities may allow compound development to be fast-tracked, especially in the case of MND, as it is already an FDA-approved drug used in the treatment of hypertension [
 <xref rid="B381-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">381</xref>].
</p>
