<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para240">This study was designed as an exploratory trial with defined group sizes of 25 participants per dose group, and was not statistically powered to measure any specific outcome. The safety analysis population included all participants who received at least one study treatment and for whom post-dose safety data were available, and were analysed as to the treatment they received. The per-protocol analysis population was used for the clinical study report's primary analysis and included participants who received all vaccine doses, had no major protocol deviations, and had primary endpoint data available. Because ten (13%) participants were excluded from the per-protocol analysis, the more inclusive modified intention-to-treat (ITT) analysis of immunogenicity, comprised all participants who received at least one dose of GLS-5300, is presented to support the main analysis. Participants in this population were grouped according to their original treatment assignment. S1-ELISA, full-length S-ELISA, and EMC-2012 Vero neutralisation assay results are reported as geometric mean endpoint titres with 95% CIs for each dose-group at each timepoint. The Kruskal-Wallis test was used to compare values by dose at each timepoint. Fisher's exact test was used to compare S1 ELISA response rates by group. Two-sided t tests were used to compare mean IFN-γ-ELISPOT values between groups. Intracellular cytokine staining data are reported as the mean frequency with 95% CI of MERS coronavirus S-peptide-stimulated cytokine responses in CD4+ and CD8+ T cells. Statistical significance was defined as a two-sided p-value of less than 0·05 and were nominal as we did not adjust for multiple comparisons. Differences between acute and convalescent samples from natural MERS coronavirus infections and week 14 GLS-5300 samples were assessed by one-way ANOVA with Tukey's multiple comparison. We used GraphPad Prism statistical software (v.7) for analyses. This study is registered on 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov" id="interrefs40" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> (number 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT02670187" id="interrefs50" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT02670187</ext-link>).
</p>
