<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><front><journal-meta><?QA-only?><journal-title-group><journal-title>Infection Prevention in Practice</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2590-0889</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2590-0889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of The Healthcare Infection Society.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7148660</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2590-0889(20)30005-6</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.infpip.2020.100041</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100041</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Preventing respiratory syncytial virus infections in hospitalized children and adults: should we do better?</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Frange</surname><given-names>Pierre</given-names></name><email>pierre.frange@aphp.fr</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Toubiana</surname><given-names>Julie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Parize</surname><given-names>Perrine</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Moulin</surname><given-names>Florence</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Scemla</surname><given-names>Anne</given-names></name><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">g</xref><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">h</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Leruez-Ville</surname><given-names>Marianne</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff9" ref-type="aff">i</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Laboratoire de Microbiologie Clinique, Assistance Publique &#x02013; H&#x000f4;pitaux de Paris (AP-HP), H&#x000f4;pital Necker &#x02013; Enfants Malades, Paris, France</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Institut Imagine, Universit&#x000e9; de Paris, EHU 7327, Paris, France</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Universit&#x000e9; de Paris, Service de P&#x000e9;diatrie G&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;rale et Maladies Infectieuses, AP-HP, H&#x000f4;pital Necker &#x02013; Enfants Malades, Paris, France</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>CNR de la Coqueluche et Autres Bordetelloses, Unit&#x000e9; &#x000ab; Biodiversit&#x000e9; et &#x000e9;pid&#x000e9;miologie des Bact&#x000e9;ries Pathog&#x000e8;nes &#x000bb;, Institut Pasteur, Paris, France</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Universit&#x000e9; Paris Descartes, Centre d&#x02019;Infectiologie Necker-Pasteur, IHU Imagine, AP-HP, H&#x000f4;pital Necker &#x02013; Enfants Malades, Paris, France</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>Service de R&#x000e9;animation et Surveillance Continue M&#x000e9;dico-chirurgicale P&#x000e9;diatrique, AP-HP, H&#x000f4;pital Necker Enfants-Malades, Paris, France</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>g</label>Service de N&#x000e9;phrologie &#x02013; Transplantation, AP-HP, H&#x000f4;pital Necker-Enfants Malades, Paris, France</aff><aff id="aff8"><label>h</label>RTRS Centaure, Labex Transplantex, Universit&#x000e9; de Paris, Paris, France</aff><aff id="aff9"><label>i</label>CNR Cytomegalovirus, Laboratoire Associ&#x000e9;, 149 Rue de S&#x000e8;vres, 75015, Paris, France</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. Pierre Frange, Laboratoire de Microbiologie clinique, H&#x000f4;pital Necker &#x02013; Enfants Maladies, 149 Rue de S&#x000e8;vres, 75015, Paris, France. Tel.: +33 1.44.49.49.61; Fax: +33 1.44.49.49.60. <email>pierre.frange@aphp.fr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>100041</fpage><lpage>100041</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><title>Summary</title><sec><title>Objective</title><p>To compare the burden of nosocomial and community-acquired respiratory syncytial virus (RSV)-associated acute lower respiratory tract infections (ALRIs) in adult and pediatric patients concomitantly admitted to a French tertiary hospital, and to evaluate the effectiveness of existing infection control measures.</p></sec><sec><title>Patients and methods</title><p>We prospectively included all adult and pediatric patients admitted to Necker hospital (Paris) between October 2018 and February 2019 with a diagnosis of RSV-associated ALRI. We compared characteristics of ALRIs between patients with community-acquired versus nosocomial infections and, in each group, between children and adults.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Community-acquired and nosocomial RSV-associated ALRIs were diagnosed in 229 and 11 inpatients, respectively. The burden of community-acquired infections was higher in children than in adults: 2.1% versus 0.2% of the total number of pediatric and adult inpatients, respectively (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001); 4.2% versus 0.2% of the total number of hospitalization days in pediatric and adult units, respectively (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001). Compared to inpatients with community-acquired ALRIs, those with nosocomial infections were more frequently adults (45.5% versus 2.6%, p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0005) and subjects with at least one chronic complex condition (100.0% versus 41.0%, p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001). The total number of hospitalization days due to nosocomial ALRIs was higher in adults than in children (0.32% versus 0.11%, p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Nosocomial RSV-associated ALRIs rarely occurred, suggesting a good effectiveness of our infection control strategy. However, the burden of nosocomial infection was higher in adults than in children, suggesting that education and training of healthcare personnel, patients and visitors about the risk of nosocomial RSV infections should be reinforced in adult wards.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Respiratory syncytial virus</kwd><kwd>Prevention</kwd><kwd>Palivizumab</kwd><kwd>Nosocomial</kwd><kwd>Children</kwd><kwd>Adults</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) is associated with 19&#x02013;81% of viral acute respiratory infections causing hospitalization in infants and children [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. RSV also has a burden on healthcare services and winter mortality in older adults [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>]. Published data on the epidemiology of nosocomial RSV infections are still limited. In infants, a severe course of nosocomial disease has been described, especially in subjects with comorbidities [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], even more severe than community-acquired RSV infections [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In adults, RSV acquisition seems to be frequently nosocomial or healthcare-related, with a higher mortality than with influenza virus infection [<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. However, to the best of our knowledge, no previous study compared the burden of community-acquired versus nosocomial RSV-associated acute lower respiratory tract infections (ALRIs) in both adult and pediatric patients concomitantly admitted at the same hospital.</p><p id="p0015">Necker hospital (Paris) is a French 600 bed tertiary hospital, where large cohorts of adult and pediatric patients with chronic complex conditions (CCC) are regularly followed. A bundle of measures has been implemented to prevent nosocomial RSV-associated ALRIs, including implementation of droplet and contact precautions for symptomatic patients, annual education and training of all healthcare personnel, providing instructional materials for patients and visitors on recommended hand hygiene, respiratory hygiene/cough practices and limitation of pediatric visitors during seasonal outbreaks of viral ALRIs. Infants predisposed to developing severe RSV disease receive passive antiviral immunization with palivizumab in accordance to French guidelines [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Finally, our hospital has recently been partly rebuilt and includes now a high rate of single-patient rooms (91%), which may help to prevent healthcare-associated infections.</p><p id="p0020">This study aims to compare the burden of nosocomial and community-acquired RSV-associated ALRIs in both adult and pediatric inpatients and to evaluate the effectiveness of our infection control measures.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Patients and methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>Ethics</title><p id="p0025">Participants provided informed consent for the anonymous use of their clinical and biological data for biomedical research (for paediatric patients, informed consent was provided by parents/guardians). This study was reviewed and approved by the Necker Hospital Institutional Review Board (registration number in the registry of the Assistance Publique &#x02013; H&#x000f4;pitaux de Paris: 20190729122906).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>Patients and definitions</title><p id="p0030">We performed a prospective observational study in adult and pediatric patients admitted to Necker hospital between October 1, 2018 and February 28, 2019, with a minimum hospital stay of 2 days and a diagnosis of RSV-associated ALRI. RSV-infected patients were identified from the data provided by the virology laboratory. RSV-associated ALRI was defined as diagnosis of pneumonia, bronchiolitis, bronchitis or bronchial hyper-reactivity with concomitant detection of RSV in upper respiratory (nose/throat swabs) or lower respiratory (bronchial aspirate or bronchoalveolar lavage fluid) samples using PCR (RSV/hMPV r-gene&#x000ae;-Argene&#x000ae;, bioM&#x000e9;rieux, Marcy l&#x02019;Etoile, France). Patients with isolated upper respiratory tract infection and those without respiratory symptoms were excluded from this analysis, even if RSV was detected from their clinical samples.</p><p id="p0035">Because the RSV incubation period may range from 2 to 8 days [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], the origin of ALRIs was designated as &#x0201c;possibly nosocomial&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;definitely nosocomial&#x0201d; when the patient had been hospitalized continuously 2&#x02013;7 days and &#x02265; 8 days before the onset of respiratory symptoms, respectively. ALRIs were considered community-acquired in patients whose symptoms occurred before hospitalization or &#x0003c; 2 days after hospital admission.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>Clinical and microbiological data</title><p id="p0040">The clinical data collected included age, gender, term of birth (for infants), underlying complex chronic conditions (CCC; as previously defined [<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]), laboratory-confirmed bacterial and viral co-/supra-infections, level of care required (admission to the intensive care unit [ICU], ventilation requirement, prescription of antibiotics), length of hospital stay (in the case of nosocomial infection, the length of hospital stay after the onset of symptoms was recorded) and death.</p><p id="p0045">The number of hospital admissions and total hospitalization days of patients with ALRIs were compared to those of all patients admitted to our hospital during the study period, in order to estimate the burden of RSV infection.</p><p id="p0050">Finally, we evaluated the proportion of RSV-infected subjects who adequately received palivizumab-based prophylaxis before the onset of their ALRIs according to the 1999 marketing authorization of palivizumab by the European Medicines Agency (EMA) [<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], the 2007 guidelines of the French Health Authority (HAS), [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] and the 2014 guidance for palivizumab use of the American Academy of Pediatrics (AAP) [<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0055">Categorical variables appear with their frequency distribution. Non-normally distributed continuous variables are expressed as the median and interquartile range. Chi-squared tests or Fisher's exact tests were used to compare discrete variables, and the Wilcoxon rank test was used to compare continuous variables between patients with community-acquired versus nosocomial ALRIs. P&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3.1"><title>Community-acquired RSV-associated ALRIs requiring hospitalization: characteristics and burden</title><p id="p0060">Between October 2018 and February 2019, 229 patients admitted to our hospital were diagnosed with community-acquired RSV-associated ALRIs. Their characteristics are summarized in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>
. The majority were less than 6 months old (60.3%) and, among them, few were born preterm (18.8%). At least one CCC was present in 40.1% of subjects, most frequently a respiratory CCC. Viral and bacterial co-/supra-infections were documented in 17.5% and 5.7% of cases, respectively, but around one in two patients received antibiotics. The proportion of patients requiring ICU admission was high (40.1%) but only 3 patients (1.3%) died. All of them were children with severe cardiovascular&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;respiratory CCC and died from acute respiratory distress syndrome.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Comparison of characteristics and follow-up of patients admitted at Necker Hospital (Paris, France) between October 2018 and February 2019 and presenting with community-acquired versus nosocomial RSV-associated ALRI</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Table&#x000a0;1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th align="char">Total (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;240)</th><th align="char">Patients with community acquired RSV-associated ALRI (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;229)</th><th align="char">Patients with nosocomial RSV-associated ALRI (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;11)</th><th><italic>p</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Male sex (n, %)</td><td>113 (47.1)</td><td>107 (46.7)</td><td>6 (54.5)</td><td align="char">0.61</td></tr><tr><td><bold>Age (n, %)</bold></td><td/><td/><td/><td align="char">0.0005</td></tr><tr><td>0&#x02013;5 months</td><td>141 (58.8)</td><td>138 (60.3)</td><td>3 (27.3)</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>including children born between 32 and 36 WOG</italic></td><td><italic>23</italic></td><td><italic>23</italic></td><td><italic>0</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td align="char"><italic>including children born &#x0003c;</italic>&#x000a0;<italic>32 WOG</italic></td><td><italic>3</italic></td><td><italic>3</italic></td><td><italic>0</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td>6&#x02013;11 months</td><td>28 (11.7)</td><td>27 (11.8)</td><td>1 (9.1)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>12&#x02013;23 months</td><td>23 (9.6)</td><td>23 (10.0)</td><td>0 (0.0)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>2&#x02013;17 years</td><td>37 (15.4)</td><td>35 (15.3)</td><td>2 (18.2)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>18&#x02013;59 years</td><td>4 (1.7)</td><td>4 (1.7)</td><td>0 (0.0)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02265; 60 years</td><td>7 (2.9)</td><td>2 (0.9)</td><td>5 (45.5)</td><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><bold>Underlying medical conditions (n, %)</bold></td></tr><tr><td>At least one CCC</td><td>105 (43.8)</td><td>94 (41.0)</td><td>11 (100.0)</td><td align="char">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Neuromuscular CCC</italic></td><td><italic>15 (6.3)</italic></td><td><italic>13 (5.7)</italic></td><td><italic>2 (18.2)</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Cardiovascular CCC</italic></td><td><italic>24 (10.0)</italic></td><td><italic>21 (9.2)</italic></td><td><italic>3 (27.3)</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Respiratory CCC</italic></td><td><italic>52 (21.7)</italic></td><td><italic>48 (21.0)</italic></td><td><italic>4 (36.4)</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Renal CCC</italic></td><td><italic>11 (4.6)</italic></td><td><italic>7 (3.1)</italic></td><td><italic>4 (36.4)</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Gastrointestinal CCC</italic></td><td><italic>7 (2.9)</italic></td><td><italic>6 (2.6)</italic></td><td><italic>1 (9.1)</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Hematological CCC and/or immune deficiency</italic></td><td><italic>24 (10.0)</italic></td><td><italic>18 (7.9)</italic></td><td><italic>6 (54.5)</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Metabolic CCC</italic></td><td><italic>2 (0.8)</italic></td><td><italic>2 (0.9)</italic></td><td><italic>0 (0.0)</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>Other congenital or genetic defect</italic></td><td><italic>22 (9.2)</italic></td><td><italic>21 (9.2)</italic></td><td><italic>1 (9.1)</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><bold>Antiviral prophylaxis (n, %)</bold></td></tr><tr><td>palivizumab</td><td>6 (2.5)</td><td>6 (2.6)</td><td>0 (0.0)</td><td align="char">1.0</td></tr><tr><td>i.v. or s.c. polyvalent immunoglobulin</td><td>3 (1.3)</td><td>3 (1.3)</td><td>0 (0.0)</td><td align="char">1.0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><bold>Viral co-/super-infection (n, %)</bold></td></tr><tr><td>At least one virus</td><td>42 (17.5)</td><td>40 (17.5)</td><td>2 (18.2)</td><td align="char">1.0</td></tr><tr><td><italic>influenza virus</italic></td><td><italic>4</italic></td><td><italic>3</italic></td><td><italic>1</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>parainfluenza virus</italic></td><td><italic>3</italic></td><td><italic>3</italic></td><td><italic>0</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>rhinovirus</italic></td><td><italic>24</italic></td><td><italic>23</italic></td><td><italic>1</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>adenovirus</italic></td><td><italic>4</italic></td><td><italic>4</italic></td><td><italic>0</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>human metapneumovirus</italic></td><td><italic>1</italic></td><td><italic>1</italic></td><td><italic>0</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>coronavirus</italic></td><td><italic>11</italic></td><td><italic>10</italic></td><td><italic>1</italic></td><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><bold>Bacterial lower respiratory tract co-/super-infection</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Microbiologically proven infection</td><td>14 (5.8)</td><td>13 (5.7)</td><td>1 (9.1)</td><td align="char">0.49</td></tr><tr><td>Suspected infection</td><td>67 (27.9)</td><td>64 (27.9)</td><td>3 (27.3)</td><td align="char">1.0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><bold>Clinical follow-up</bold></td></tr><tr><td>LOS (days) (median, IQR)</td><td>7 [5&#x02013;10]</td><td>7 [5&#x02013;9]</td><td>17 [11&#x02013;26]<xref rid="tbl1fna" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td><td align="char">&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td>ICU admission (n, %)</td><td>97 (40.4)</td><td>94 (41.0)</td><td>3 (27.3)</td><td align="char">0.53</td></tr><tr><td>Oxygen requirement (n, %)</td><td>189 (78.8)</td><td>182 (79.5)</td><td>7 (63.6)</td><td align="char">0.25</td></tr><tr><td>Mechanical ventilation requirement (n, %)</td><td>9 (3.8)</td><td>8 (3.5)</td><td>1 (9.1)</td><td align="char">0.35</td></tr><tr><td>Non-invasive ventilation and/or high-flow nasal oxygen requirement (n, %)</td><td>73 (30.4)</td><td>72 (31.4)</td><td>1 (9.1)</td><td align="char">0.18</td></tr><tr><td>Antibiotic treatment (n, %)</td><td>142 (59.2)</td><td>137 (59.8)</td><td>5 (45.5)</td><td align="char">0.36</td></tr><tr><td>Death (n, %)</td><td>3 (1.3)</td><td>3 (1.3)</td><td>0 (0.0)</td><td align="char">1.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>RSV&#x000a0;= respiratory syncytial virus; ALRI&#x000a0;= acute lower respiratory tract infection; WOG&#x000a0;= weeks of gestation; CCC&#x000a0;= chronic complex conditions; i.v.&#x000a0;= intraveinous; s.c.&#x000a0;= subcutaneous; LOS&#x000a0;= length of stay; ICU&#x000a0;= intensive care unit.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl1fna"><label>a</label><p id="ntpara0010">For healthcare-associated infections, the length of stay after the diagnosis of RSV ALRI was described.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0065">When compared to all other patients admitted to our hospital during the same period of time, patients with community-acquired RSV infections accounted for 1.6% of inpatients and 3.1% of the total number of hospitalization days. The burden of community-acquired RSV infections was disproportionately higher in pediatric than in adult patients: 2.1% versus 0.2% of the total number of pediatric and adult inpatients, respectively (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001); 4.2% versus 0.2% of the total number of hospitalization days in pediatric and adult units, respectively (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001).</p><p id="p0070">Among children with community-acquired RSV infections, palivizumab &#x02013;based prophylaxis was given to 6/18 (33.3%), 6/6 (100%) and 4/4 (100%) of those for whom antiviral prophylaxis was recommended by the 1999 EMA, the 2007 French and the 2014 American guidelines, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title>Nosocomial RSV-associated ALRIs: characteristics and burden</title><p id="p0075">Eleven patients were diagnosed with a possibly (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6) or definitely (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5) nosocomial RSV-associated ALRI (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>). Almost half of them (45.1%) were 60 years old or older. All subjects with nosocomial RSV infection had at least one CCC but none of them died from RSV.</p><p id="p0080">Compared to inpatients with community-acquired RSV-associated ALRIs, those with nosocomial infections were more frequently adults (p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0005) and subjects with at least one CCC (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001). The rates of viral and bacterial co-/supra-infections, oxygen/ventilation requirement, ICU admissions, antibiotic treatments and deaths did not differ between inpatients diagnosed with community-acquired versus nosocomial infections. However, the length of stay was statistically longer in the latter than in the former (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001).</p><p id="p0085">When compared to all patients admitted to our hospital during the same period of time and free from community-acquired RSV-associated ALRIs, patients with nosocomial RSV ALRIs accounted for 0.08% of all inpatients and 0.17% of the total number of hospitalization days. The proportion of inpatients with nosocomial infections did not differ between children and adults (0.06% versus 0.15%, p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.14). However, the total number of hospitalization days due to nosocomial RSV-infected patients was higher in adults than in children (0.32% versus 0.11%, p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001).</p><p id="p0090">No children with nosocomial RSVreceived palivizumab &#x02013;based prophylaxis prior to the onset of their infection. Retrospectively, such prophylaxis was not recommended for any of&#x000a0;these children by the EMA, the French or the American guidelines.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0095">To the best of our knowledge, we report one of the first studies evaluating the efficacy of the same bundle of infection control measures to prevent RSV ALRIs in both adult and pediatric patients admitted to the same tertiary hospital.</p><p id="p0100">Some results regarding community-acquired RSV infections requiring hospitalization are in line with previous reports: most of the subjects hospitalized with RSV were aged &#x02264;&#x000a0;12 months, and especially &#x02264;&#x000a0;6 months [<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>]. The median length of hospital stay was in the range of that reported in previous pediatric studies (between 2 and 11 days). However, the prevalence of admission to ICU and the mortality rate were higher than previously described in high-income countries (41.0% versus 2&#x02013;12%, and 1.3% versus &#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.5%, respectively) [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. This could be explained by the high prevalence of CCC in the population of children followed in our tertiary hospital, and, consequently, in those admitted for community-acquired RSV infections. This proportion was higher than in previous studies, where typically &#x0003e;&#x000a0;70% of children hospitalized with RSV-related ALRI/bronchiolitis had no underlying medical conditions [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>,<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>]. Thus, the epidemiological characteristics of patients admitted at our hospital with community-acquired RSV infections cannot be extrapolated to other French pediatric centers.</p><p id="p0105">In our study, the burden of RSV among community-acquired ALRIs requiring hospitalization was strongly lower in adults compared to infants and children, despite the high prevalence of CCC (especially immunodeficiency) among adults followed in our center (data not shown). Our findings suggest that, although RSV has the potential to cause severe community-acquired ALRIs in high-risk adults (such as immunocompromised patients) [<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], RSV infections seem to rarely require hospitalization in this population.</p><p id="p0110">Few of our patients (2.6%) admitted with community-acquired infections received palivizumab-based antiviral prophylaxis prior to the onset of the infection. However, the retrospective evaluation of the medical files of all RSV-infected inpatients revealed that no other patient required palivizumab according to the 2007 French and the 2014 American guidelines [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Our results suggest that guidelines of antiviral prophylaxis are appropriately applied in our center but that most of the patients admitted for RSV infections (and most of those admitted to pediatric ICU), did not fall into the recognized indications for RSV prophylaxis, as recently reported by Ghazaly et&#x000a0;al. [<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. In light with the ongoing research into the development of new and more cost-effective strategies against RSV infections than palivizumab (including long acting monoclonal antibodies and vaccines), further larger studies defining the characteristics of patients hospitalized with severe RSV infections, may help to rethink the guidelines of RSV prophylactic strategies.</p><p id="p0115">RSV is known to be a major nosocomial hazard on paediatric wards, especially in cases of age less than 5 months, prematurity and chronic lung disease of prematurity [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Previous studies described rates of nosocomial RSV infections between 0.4 and 9.6% [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>], with poorer clinical outcomes than community-acquired RSV infections [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Contrasting with these results, we observed in our pediatric wards a low rate of nosocomial RSV-related ALRIs (0.06% of inpatients) and no death related to nosocomial RSV infection. This low rate of nosocomial infections could be related to our multifaceted infection control strategy including a high proportion of single-patient rooms (for both infected and uninfected patients), staff training repeated before each season of viral epidemics, screening of symptomatic patients, isolation/cohorting, hand washing, gloves and masks, gowns (for staff attending infants with respiratory symptoms) and restriction of visitors.</p><p id="p0120">Interestingly, our study suggests that the efficacy of this infection control strategy may be less effective in adult than in pediatric wards. Indeed, nosocomial infections were proportionately more frequently diagnosed in adults than community-acquired ALRIs (p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001) and the total number of hospitalization days due to nosocomial RSV infection was higher in adults than in children (0.32% versus 0.11%, p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001). Similarly, Kestler M et&#x000a0;al. recently described that RSV acquisition was frequently nosocomial or healthcare-related in adults during flu season [<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Although we did not observe the high RSV-related mortality described in adults by Kestler (14.7%), we described longer length of hospital stay in case of nosocomial versus community-acquired infections in adults. Our results suggest that, despite a low rate of nosocomial infections observed in adults (0.15% of inpatients), our multifaceted infection control strategy may be reinforced in adults wards in order to obtain similar results seen in pediatric units. Because of the low number of nosocomial infections during the 2018/2019 RSV epidemic, it could be interesting to repeat this study during several successive seasonal epidemics in order to evaluate the effectiveness of our bundle of measures in a larger population.</p><p id="p0125">This study has five main limitations. First, RSV-related ALRIs were defined from the data provided by the virology laboratory. Because RSV may not have been screened in a significant proportion of patients with ALRI, this study may underestimate the real burden of RSV infection in our center. This underestimation may be more pronounced in patients with mild symptoms (especially those with isolated upper respiratory tract infection), where RSV may have been less frequently screened than in case of severe infection. However this potential limitation does not hamper evaluation of the efficacy of our infection control strategy, which mainly aims to prevent severe infections. Second, although the ALRIs were primarily attributed to RSV by clinicians in all patients described in this study, we cannot exclude that viral and bacterial co-infections may have influenced their clinical outcome. This confounding factor cannot be excluded in our non interventional study because all other respiratory pathogens may not have been screened for. In order to evaluate the impact of this potential bias, further prospective studies are needed with systematic screening of all potential viral and bacterial co-infections. Third, this observational study does not allow the effectiveness of individual components of our multi-component control measures to be assessed. Similar observation was done by French CE <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> in the recent review of published and unpublished literature about the effectiveness of control measures to prevent nosocomial RSV transmission events [<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. However, because similar preventive strategies were applied in all units of our center, this limitation does not hamper the comparison of their efficacy on pediatric versus adult wards. Further studies are needed in order to evaluate to what extent the compliance with each measure of our infection control bundle differs between adult and paediatric populations. Because nosocomial infections may be transmitted by healthcare personnel, visitors and patients, it would be interesting to differentiate the compliance to measures targeting each of these populations in such further studies. Fourth, as previously discussed, the high prevalence of CCC among patients followed in our tertiary hospital hampers extrapolation of our results to other French hospitals. The higher prevalence of CCC among patients with nosocomial versus community-acquired RSV infections (100.0% versus 41.0%) may at least partly explain the longer length of stay in the former than in the latter. Fifth, we used a very large definition of a nosocomial case, by pooling &#x0201c;possibly&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;definitely&#x0201d; nosocomial infections. In previous studies investigating the risk of RSV transmission to patients and providing a clear definition of a nosocomial case, various cut-off were used to define it (mostly 5 days or more after hospital admission) [<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Here, we chose a wider definition of a nosocomial case (i.e. infection occurring in a patient hospitalized continuously &#x02265;&#x000a0;2 days before the onset of respiratory symptoms), because (i) the RSV incubation period may be as short as 2 days [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], and (ii) we did not want to minimize the real burden of RSV nosocomial ALRIs. Interestingly, although we used such a wide cut-off, the burden was not high in our center. This limitation does not hamper comparison of the burden of nosocomial infections between pediatric and adult wards at our center.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="p0130">In summary, the burden of community-acquired infections requiring hospitalization is disproportionately higher in infants/children than in adults admitted to our center. Nosocomial RSV-associated ALRIs rarely occurred, suggesting good efficacy of our multi-component preventive strategy. However, the burden of nosocomial infection was higher in adults than in children, suggesting that education and training of healthcare workers, patients and visitors about the risk of nosocomial respiratory viral disease should be reinforced on adult wards. The fact than &#x0003e; 97% of patients hospitalized with community-acquired or nosocomial RSV-associated ALRI were not considered at &#x0201c;high-risk&#x0201d; (i.e. requiring immunoprophylaxis with palivizumab) according to the French and American guidelines, highlights the urgent need to develop new and more&#x000a0;cost-effective antiviral preventive strategies, in order&#x000a0;to&#x000a0;decrease the burden of RSV infections requiring hospitalizations.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bont</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Checchia</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fauroux</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueras-Aloy</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manzoni</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paes</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defining the epidemiology and burden of severe respiratory syncytial virus infection among infants and children in western countries</article-title><source>Infect Dis Ther</source><volume>5</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40121-016-0123-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27480325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McClure</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kieke</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundaram</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meece</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sifakis</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal incidence of medically attended respiratory syncytial virus infection in a community cohort of adults &#x02265;50 years old</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>9</volume><year>2014</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e102586</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0102586</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Widmer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Talbot</surname><given-names>H.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Respiratory syncytial virus- and human metapneumovirus-associated emergency department and hospital burden in adults</article-title><source>Influenza Other&#x000a0;Respir Viruses</source><volume>8</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/irv.12234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24512531</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daily Kirley</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Emerson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aragon</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>E.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating influenza disease burden from&#x000a0;population-based surveillance data in the United States</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>10</volume><year>2015</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0118369</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0118369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorburn</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pre-existing disease is associated with a significantly higher risk of death in severe respiratory syncytial virus infection</article-title><source>Arch Dis Child</source><volume>94</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/adc.2008.139188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18653625</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khurana</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelhart</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Exner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schildgen</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nosocomial infection: a risk factor for a complicated course in children with respiratory syncytial virus infection- results from a prospective multicenter German surveillance study</article-title><source>Int J Hyg Environ Health</source><volume>211</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17869579</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kestler</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mateos</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adrados</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouza</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Respiratory syncytial virus burden among adults during flu season: an underestimated pathology</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Hosp Infect</source><volume>100</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>463</fpage><lpage>468</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2018.03.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29614245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Autorit&#x000e9; de Sant&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>Haute</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Palivizumab. Avis de la Commission de la Transparence</chapter-title><year>2007</year><comment>accessed</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.has-sante.fr/upload/docs/evamed/CT-15884_SYNAGIS_QD_INS_Avis2_CT15884.pdf" id="intref0010">https://www.has-sante.fr/upload/docs/evamed/CT-15884_SYNAGIS_QD_INS_Avis2_CT15884.pdf</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>C.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Respiratory syncytial virus and parainfluenza virus</article-title><source>N&#x000a0;Engl J Med</source><volume>344</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>1917</fpage><lpage>1928</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11419430</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feudtner</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hays</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Geyer</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neff</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koepsell</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deaths attributed to pediatric complex chronic conditions: national trends and implications for supportive care services</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><volume>107</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>E99</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11389297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>European Medicines Agency</collab></person-group><chapter-title>European public assessment report (EPAR) for Synagis</chapter-title><year>2009</year><comment>accessed</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/medicines/human/EPAR/synagis" id="intref0015">https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/medicines/human/EPAR/synagis</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>American Academy of Pediatrics Committee on Infectious Diseases</collab><collab>American Academy of Pediatrics Bronchiolitis Guidelines Committee</collab></person-group><article-title>Updated guidance for palivizumab prophylaxis among infants and young children at increased risk of hospitalization for respiratory syncytial virus infection</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><volume>134</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>e620</fpage><lpage>e638</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2014-1666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25070304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vicente</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montes</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cilla</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Yarza</surname><given-names>E.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Trallero</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hospitalization for respiratory syncytial virus in the paediatric population in Spain</article-title><source>Epidemiol Infect</source><volume>131</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>867</fpage><lpage>872</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14596527</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fjaerli</surname><given-names>H.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farstad</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bratlid</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hospitalisations for respiratory syncytial virus bronchiolitis in Akershus, Norway, 1993-2000: a population-based retrospective study</article-title><source>BMC Pediatr</source><volume>4</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>25</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15606912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herv&#x000e1;s</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reina</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ya&#x000f1;ez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>del Valle</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Figuerola</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herv&#x000e1;s</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of hospitalization for acute bronchiolitis in children: differences between RSV and non-RSV bronchiolitis</article-title><source>Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis</source><volume>31</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>1975</fpage><lpage>1981</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10096-011-1529-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22240853</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>C.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumkin</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Staat</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Respiratory syncytial virus-associated hospitalizations among children less than 24 months of age</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><volume>132</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>e341</fpage><lpage>e348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2013-0303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23878043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhore</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soriano-Fallas</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trost</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chason</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramilo</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors in children hospitalized with RSV bronchiolitis versus non-RSV bronchiolitis</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><volume>126</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>e1453</fpage><lpage>e1460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1542/peds.2010-0507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21098154</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Resch</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gusenleitner</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandl</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of respiratory syncytial virus infection in Southern Austria</article-title><source>Pediatr Infect Dis J</source><volume>19</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>587</fpage><lpage>588</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deshpande</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Northern</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The clinical and health economic burden of respiratory syncytial virus disease among children under 2 years of age in a defined geographical area</article-title><source>Arch Dis Child</source><volume>88</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>1065</fpage><lpage>1069</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14670770</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grimaldi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornet</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Milou</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouyon</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[Prospective regional study of an epidemic of respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) bronchiolitis]</article-title><source>Arch Pediatr</source><volume>9</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>572</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12108310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratard</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Respiratory syncytial virus-associated hospitalizations in Louisiana</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;La State Med Soc</source><volume>164</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23362592</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>C.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwane</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumkin</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Staat</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The burden of respiratory syncytial virus infection in young children</article-title><source>N&#x000a0;Engl J Med</source><volume>360</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>588</fpage><lpage>598</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa0804877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19196675</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Resch</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gusenleitner</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of respiratory syncytial virus infection: a prospective study in hospitalized infants younger than 2 years</article-title><source>Infection</source><volume>30</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12236559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyce</surname><given-names>T.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mellen</surname><given-names>B.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchel</surname><given-names>E.F.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>P.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rates of hospitalization for respiratory syncytial virus infection among children in medicaid</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Pediatr</source><volume>137</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>865</fpage><lpage>870</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11113845</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>N.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Binnicker</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chirila</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brumble</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandrekar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morbidity and mortality among patients with respiratory syncytial virus infection: a 2-year retrospective review</article-title><source>Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis</source><volume>85</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2016.02.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27179369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghazaly</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characteristics of children admitted to intensive care with acute bronchiolitis</article-title><source>Eur J Pediatr</source><volume>177</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>913</fpage><lpage>920</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00431-018-3138-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29654399</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahm</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frederiksen</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibsen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iyore</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of respiratory syncytial virus infection requiring hospitalization in East Denmark</article-title><source>Pediatr Infect Dis J</source><volume>17</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>996</fpage><lpage>1000</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9849981</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Obwegeser</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aberle</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Langgartner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Popow-Kraupp</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nosocomial transmission of respiratory syncytial virus in neonatal intensive care and intermediate care units: a prospective epidemiologic study</article-title><source>Pediatr Infect Dis J</source><volume>29</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>670</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/INF.0b013e3181d76d61</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20305582</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdeve</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cakir</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akduman</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zenciroglu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akcakus</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Outcome of the Respiratory Syncytial Virus related acute lower&#x000a0;respiratory tract infection among hospitalized newborns: a&#x000a0;prospective multicenter study</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Matern Fetal Neonatal Med</source><volume>29</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>2186</fpage><lpage>2193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/14767058.2015.1079614</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26365531</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>French</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coope</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajanaidu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paranthaman</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pebody</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk of nosocomial respiratory syncytial virus infection and effectiveness of control measures to prevent transmission events: a systematic review</article-title><source>Influenza Other Respir Viruses</source><volume>10</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/irv.12379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26901358</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1"><title>Declaration of interest</title><p id="p0140">P.F. has received research grants (to his institution) from the French National Agency for AIDS Research (ANRS) and honoraria and travel grants from ViiV Healthcare, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Janssen Cilag, Gilead Sciences, Pfizer, Medtronic and MSD France for participation in advisory boards, educational programs and conferences, outside the submitted work. M.L.-V. has received nonfinancial and other support from BioM&#x000e9;rieux and nonfinancial support from Abbott and Ferring SAS, outside the submitted work. All other authors report no potential conflicts.</p></sec><sec id="appsec2"><title>Funding source</title><p id="p0145">This study was carried out as part of our routine work.</p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank all patients (and the parents/guardians of pediatric patients) who agreed to participate; the members of the Infection Control Unit (I. Le Guinche, P. Husson, S. Gotty, R. Beauvais, A. M&#x000e9;tois) and the doctors, midwives, and personnel in the units of our center for their sustained efforts to prevent and monitor healthcare-associated infections.</p></ack></back></article>