<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Estrogen reduces platelet aggregation, the opposite effect of testosterone (
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>,
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>). Notelovitz et al. (
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>) studied the short-term effects of estrogens on the coagulation-fibrinolysis process in surgically treated women, and the results did not show abnormal or thrombogenic changes in coagulation parameters. 
 <italic>In vitro</italic>, 17β-estradiol is able to inhibit platelet aggregation by promoting Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> extrusion or reuptake activity, and its action is dependent on the increase of NO synthesis (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>). Platelet reactivity plays a pivotal role in thrombus formation, and 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> data suggest that although women have a higher magnitude of platelet reactivity, their response to aspirin is similar or even larger compared to that of men (
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>). Experimental data show that a chronic high physiologic level of estrogen equivalent to that observed in pregnant mice had a significant inhibitory effect on platelet aggregation (
 <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>). Estrogen mediates beneficial effects on the cerebral microcirculation and moderated cerebral thrombotic mechanisms by enhancing the plasma levels of NO (
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>). Moreover, estrogens exert positive effects on the pulmonary vasculature by increasing prostacyclin release and NO production by eNOS (
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>). Cowman et al. (
 <xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>) evidenced a connection between age and decreases in platelet tracks, platelet translocation, and unstable platelet interactions. The altered platelet function associated with aging was more profound in females compared with that of males and could be a result of a reduction in estrogen levels in women.
</p>
