<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack id="JVEv5-ack-0001">
 <title id="JVEv5-title-0012">Acknowledgements</title>
 <sec id="JVEv5-sec-0010">
  <title id="JVEv5-title-0013"/>
  <sec id="JVEv5-sec-0011">
   <title id="JVEv5-title-0014">Conflict of interest</title>
   <p id="JVEv5-para-0076">SP: an unrestricted education grant from Gilead Sciences and further receives funding from Gilead, MSD, ViiV Healthcare and Jansen.</p>
   <p id="JVEv5-para-0077">CB: grants from Gilead Sciences, MSD, ViiV Healthcare and Janssen.</p>
   <p id="JVEv5-para-0078">MvdV: participated in ad boards with fees paid to his institution for: Abbvie, Gilead, J&amp;J, MSD, ViiV; received independent research grants from: Abbvie, Gilead, MSD, J&amp;J.</p>
   <p id="JVEv5-para-0079">MES: PI in a Gilead Sciences-sponsored investigator-initiated trial (received no PI fees).</p>
   <p id="JVEv5-para-0080">OS: Speakers fees: MSD, Gilead Sciences.</p>
   <p id="JVEv5-para-0081">VS: Gilead, Abbvie.</p>
   <p id="JVEv5-para-0082">TM: received funding for clinical trials performed by: Abbvie, BMS, Genfit, Gilead and Merck.</p>
   <p id="JVEv5-para-0083">AG: no conflict of interest.</p>
   <p id="JVEv5-para-0084">CM: no conflict of interest.</p>
   <p id="JVEv5-para-0085">SDB: received grants from ARHEL and MSD; served on advisory boards for Abbvie, BMS, Gilead and MSD; lecture fees from Abbvie, BMS and Gilead, outside the submitted work.</p>
   <p id="JVEv5-para-0086">MN: grant support from Gilead Sciences, MSD and Abbvie.</p>
   <p id="JVEv5-para-0087">JF: grant funding from Abbvie, Abbott, Gilead, Janssen and Merck, and scientific consulting from Abbvie, Contravir, Gilead and Merck.</p>
   <p id="JVEv5-para-0088">MH: funding from Gilead Sciences, Abbvie and GSK for investigator-initiated research.</p>
   <p id="JVEv5-para-0089">JW: no conflict of interest.</p>
   <p id="JVEv5-para-9003">The IVHEM meeting, organised by Virology Education, received financial support from Gilead.</p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</ack>
