<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Like other African countries, Gabonese resources for public health and health monitoring are unequally allocated; 60% are spent at a central level. Public health services and clinical practitioners need more resources to be able to actively educate the public about the risks of repeated contacts with wildlife or other sources potentially harmful for health.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0048">48</xref> However, Gabon could be considered as a good model to investigate the emergence or re-emergence of zoonotic EID. On one hand, Gabonese forests are a hot spot for biodiversity (wild animals and unknown pathogens) and on the other hand there is a relatively small population (1.5 million of habitants), which is often in contact with surrounding wildlife. Also, the CIRMF, a research center advantageously located, offers high quality researchers and facilities that study pathogens and wildlife ecology. Altogether the combination of these factors should help to better understand the mechanisms of contact and transmission of new pathogens from wildlife to human, the emergence of zoonotic EID and the breaking of species barriers by the pathogens. Indeed the emergence of infectious diseases in wildlife is a continuous and ongoing process. The factors that give rise to zoonotic EID, such as ecosystem perturbations and modifications, climate changes, migrations of reservoirs species, pathogens or vectors, and intrinsic changes of pathogens may be of natural origin or due to human influences.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0017">17</xref> To understand the underlying mechanisms that govern relationships between reservoir species, ecological factors and environmental perturbations with the emergence, transmission and dissemination of viral diseases in tropical forests, the CIRMF wishes to set up permanent surveillance of the health of the population by the establishment of (1) a network reference laboratories (WHO based reference laboratories including CIRMF, Pasteur Institute Network and other National laboratories or universities based) and (2) a Health Ecology Observatory (that is,. The CIRMF's Scientific Station in la Lopé National Park). Such measures will compile data from the public health system with the monitoring of the emergence of new pathogens. The collected information would favor better outbreak risk appraisal in the Gabonese human population as well as for the entire Congo basin region.
</p>
