<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0070">Despite this, NAs remain a good option for the treatment of CoV infections based on the high level of structural conservation of the viral RdRps, particularly regarding nucleotide binding sites. Additionally, NAs display a relatively high barrier to resistance relative to other antivirals, as escape mutations likely come at a high cost to viral replication. In support of this, the broad-spectrum AMP analogue Remdesivir (GS-5734) which is currently used for the treatment of several diverse viral infections has shown promising results, inhibiting viral replication of both SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV in various 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> systems, including primary human airway epithelial cultures, and reducing disease severity in a mouse model (
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Sheahan et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Agostini et al., 2018</xref>). Recently, Remdesivir was shown to inhibit SARS-CoV-2 viral replication in cell culture, supporting the potential of this NA produg to be used for the broad-spectrum treatment of CoV infections (
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2020</xref>). Importantly, passaging of the model β-CoV murine hepatitis virus (MHV) in the presence of the parent nucleoside GS-441524 yielded two resistance mutations in the viral RdRp (F476L and V553L), which were also shown to confer resistance in SARS-CoV (F480L and V557L in SARS-CoV) (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Agostini et al., 2018</xref>). However, resistance came at a cost to viral replication 
 <italic>in vitro,</italic> and furthermore attenuated SARS-CoV 
 <italic>in vivo.</italic> As is the case for Rbv-TP, the ExoN of CoV may be able to excise incorporated GS 441524-MP, as shown by the increased potency against ExoN deficient viruses (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Agostini et al., 2018</xref>). This raises interesting questions as to the balance between incorporation of NA-TPs by the RdRp and removal by the ExoN of the NA-MPs, whereby the NA-TPs must be incorporated by the polymerase faster than the excision rate of the ExoN.
</p>
