<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In Japan, NVI outbreak events with confirmed virus detection are notified via the prefectural institutes of public health to the National Institute of Infectious Diseases as part of the National Epidemiological Surveillance of Infectious Diseases (NESID; 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nih.go.jp/niid/ja/iasr-noro.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.nih.go.jp/niid/ja/iasr-noro.html</ext-link>) requirements [
 <xref rid="pone.0173996.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The present study used the time series of the notified outbreak events (i.e., the count data of outbreak events) from September 2000 to August 2016 across Japan. When an outbreak is notified via the prefectural institute of public health, the notification document includes whether the outbreak was foodborne or mainly caused by human-to-human transmission. The notification system trusts prefectural institutes to judge whether the outbreak involves human-to-human transmission or is foodborne based on the epidemiological investigations, and if the cause remains unclear even after an epidemiological investigation, the outbreak events are reported as cause “unknown”. In many instances, foodborne outbreaks (attributed to “environmental” exposure) are notified to this surveillance due to the need to virologically verify that a foodborne outbreak was caused by noroviruses, because Food Hygiene Law enforces the suspension of business at any restaurant or other eating facilities with norovirus outbreaks. Because the type of virus responsible for the outbreak is typed using the detected virus, the notification data also contains genogroup and genotype information. Also, because the notification relies on virological confirmation, the absolute number of outbreak events will be under stated, but here we assume that the proportion of observed foodborne outbreaks among all notified outbreaks reflects the unbiased proportion. Potential ascertainment biases are examined in sensitivity analysis.
</p>
