<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13">Arenaviruses (Lassa virus—Old World/Junin, Machupo virus—New World) can also cause viral hemorrhagic fevers and are therefore on the list of potential biological threat agents (NATO AMed P-6 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>]; Argentine—Bolivian hemorrhagic fevers). Handling of Lassa virus (LassaV) requires BSL-4 containment. Annual case numbers of Lassa fever (LassaF) are estimated to be between 100.000 and 300.000 in West Africa, but the true public health burden of LassaF is unknown, as are exact case numbers on New World arenavirus infections [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR147">147</xref>]. Transmitted by aerosolized rodent droppings, arenavirus infections start with a generalized flu-like illness and then cause a range of conditions from aseptic meningitis/encephalitis with choroid plexus infiltration (Lymphocytic Choriomeningitis Virus; LCMV) to potentially fatal hemorrhagic fevers (Lassa, Junin, Guanarito, Machupo, Sabia, and Whitewater Arroyo Virus), with case fatality rates over 30%. Recently a person-to-person transmission of Lassavirus in Germany [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR148">148</xref>] and an outbreak in Nigeria raised public health concerns. Arenaviruses are enveloped viruses incorporating ribosomes (‘arena’ in Latin for sand; ‘sand’-like appearance of ribosomes in electron microscopy of virus particles, hence arenavirus), with a Group IV genome of two ambisense ss-RNA segments. They use the ubiquitously expressed alpha-dystroglycan as their cellular receptor, and their main cellular targets are antigen-presenting cells. 
 <italic>Anti-arenavirus drugs</italic>. Ribavirin is used under compassionate use protocols for the treatment of LassaF [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">112</xref>], while recently favipiravir was evaluated and found to enhance survival in cynomolgus (crab-eating) macaques [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125">125</xref>]. A further interesting compound is LHF 535, an entry inhibitor targeting arenaviral GP2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>].
</p>
