<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The quantity of sprays, spatter, or aerosol generated by ultrasonics, the distance travelled by the aerosolized particles and their composition have been studied using air samplers,
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>58</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>59</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>60</sup>
 </xref> bacterial growth medium placed at strategic locations,
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>58</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>59</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>60</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>61</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>62</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0063" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>63</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0064" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>64</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0065" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>65</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>66</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0067" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>67</sup>
 </xref> filter paper strips (with and without dye) on the patient and operator,
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0068" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>68</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0069" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>69</sup>
 </xref> and heme‐detectors.
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0070" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>70</sup>
 </xref> Sprays are generated during all types of procedures using ultrasonic instruments, whether it be supragingival scaling, subgingival scaling of periodontally diseased teeth or endodontic instrumentation. The amount of spatter and aerosol generated by sonic, ultrasonic or piezoelectric devices and distance travelled by airborne particles from these devices is similar or comparable.
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>58</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0064" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>64</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0071" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>71</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0072" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>72</sup>
 </xref> These sprays expose the inhabitants of the operatory to 1.86 × 10
 <sup>5</sup> particles per cubic meter of space, and the contaminants settle to a great extent on the dominant arm of the operator, and eyewear and chest of the patient and to a lesser extent on the non‐dominant arm and chest of the operator and assistant.
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>66</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0068" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>68</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0069" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>69</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0073" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>73</sup>
 </xref> They can also be detected as far away as 2 to 11 m from the treatment site.
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>59</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>66</sup>
 </xref> However, in the absence of a coolant, the aerosol is limited to an 18 inch radius.
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0072" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>72</sup>
 </xref> The levels of aerosolized particles return to pre‐operative levels within 30 minutes
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0068" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>68</sup>
 </xref> to 2 hours.
 <xref rid="jper10596-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>60</sup>
 </xref> In summary, there is unequivocal evidence that some of the spray from all types of ultrasonic devices is converted to aerosol, and while the spatter settles on the person of the operator, assistant and patient, the aerosolized particles can travel much larger distances and settle up to 2 hours after creation.
</p>
