<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<boxed-text position="float" content-type="Box" id="fea-0001" orientation="portrait">
 <label>Box 1</label>
 <caption>
  <title>WHO National and Global Sexually Transmitted Infection Surveillance Priorities for Action 
   <xref rid="jia225361-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">7</xref>
  </title>
 </caption>
 <sec id="jia225361-sec-0007">
  <title>Priority actions for countries</title>
  <p>
   <list list-type="bullet" id="jia225361-list-0002">
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Strengthen and integrate sexually transmitted infection surveillance into the national health information system</bold> as a part of health system strengthening, using standardized indicators and methodologies 
      <italic>as guided by WHO; ensure that data collection methods yield high‐quality information, meet ethical standards, and do not pose risks for communities or the health care workers involved</italic>. 
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Increase the “granularity” of data</bold> including through: enhanced sexually transmitted infection‐related disaggregated data collection based on different stratifiers that include age, sex, population and location
      <italic>; involve affected communities and specific populations to achieve high‐quality data and analysis</italic>. 
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Identify specific populations</bold> who are most at risk for sexually transmitted infections and places where most of the transmission is occurring; 
      <italic>establish mechanisms to promote the participation of affected communities;</italic> conduct routine case reporting and periodic prevalence assessments of core sexually transmitted infections to assess the magnitude of the sexually transmitted infection problem in target populations, including by disaggregating the data
      <italic>; describe the sexually transmitted infection epidemics and measure the impact in terms of sequelae and cost</italic>. 
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Include data on the risk factors and determinants of sexually transmitted infections</bold> in order to understand and address these determinants. 
      <italic>Include a focus on pre‐exposure prophylaxis as appropriate. Use both standard and innovative participatory survey methodologies to develop accurate estimates of key population sizes and detailed understandings of subnational epidemics; integrate biological surveillance with other programmes, such as a behavioural surveillance survey in the HIV files – include contact tracing and treatment of partners</italic>. 
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Strengthen national laboratory capacity</bold> through quality assurance and the introduction of point‐of‐care diagnostics to ensure routine monitoring of sexually transmitted infections and antimicrobial resistance to 
      <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic>. 
     </p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="jia225361-sec-0008">
  <title>Priority actions for WHO</title>
  <p>
   <list list-type="bullet" id="jia225361-list-0003">
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Provide global leadership and assistance to countries</bold> in strengthening sexually transmitted infection surveillance and in using standard methodologies for such surveillance and estimation of the burden and impact; support the development of strategic information systems and sexually transmitted infection epidemics and response mapping, including the analysis of disaggregated data for monitoring inequities; support countries in strengthening case reporting, prevalence assessment, aetiologic assessment and antimicrobial resistance monitoring; strengthen global systems for collecting and sharing national surveillance data on sexually transmitted infections, including disaggregated data and analysis for monitoring equity. 
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Provide guidance on the collection and analysis of disaggregated data</bold> based on different stratifiers and the involvement of affected communities and specific populations, including key populations for HIV, in efforts to obtain high‐quality data and achieve high‐quality analysis; use internationally endorsed methods for estimating the sizes of key populations for HIV and on setting programme targets for services for key populations for HIV. 
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item>
     <p>
      <bold>Ensure linkages</bold> of some components of sexually transmitted infection surveillance to existing mechanisms including HIV and antimicrobial resistance surveillance.
     </p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
 </sec>
</boxed-text>
