<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The evolutionary rate of all ZIKV genomes (8.61 × 10
 <sup>−4</sup> substitutions/site per year) is similar to the rate only in Asian lineage (1.05 × 10
 <sup>−3</sup> substitutions/site per year), which is consistent with other study,
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]
 </sup> and the rate is comparable to that of other Flaviviruses.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
  <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]
 </sup> Based on the result of polygenetic analysis, ZIKV isolates imported into China are assigned into two clusters, that agrees well with previous study.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]
 </sup> However, there are three sequences (KU7744693, MF593625, and KY328290) that do not appear to belong to the two clusters. KU7744693 is isolated from the first imported case in China from Venezuela.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]
 </sup> It was imported into Jiangxi, that is a likely reason why it does not cluster with other strains in Venezuela-origin cluster which were all imported into Guangdong. MF593625 is a strain imported from Guatemala and it shares a common ancestor with strains in Guatemala. It is remarkable to note that that strain KY328290 was originally imported into Yunnan, China from Bangladesh in 2014.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]
 </sup> It is undetected until retesting the ice-stored serum samples retrospectively in 2016 and reported as the first recorded ZIKV imported case in China. KY328290 share a common ancestor with the ZIKV strain in Thailand in September 2010. Although the case is imported from Bangladesh, no ZIKV strain in Bangladesh was included in the NCBI database. It was confirmed as an Asian-lineage transition-state intermediate between low-prevalence and explosive pandemic strains. This strain indicates that China may have imported ZIKV long before 2016, so, the risk of autochthonous transmission of ZIKV in China has increased.
</p>
