<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We used complete LASV sequences from 
 <italic>Mastomys</italic> spp. trapped in Guinea (
 <italic>n</italic> = 5), Mali (
 <italic>n</italic> = 4), Nigeria (
 <italic>n</italic> = 2), and Sierra Leone (
 <italic>n</italic> = 10) [
 <xref rid="B3-biology-09-00026" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-biology-09-00026" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-biology-09-00026" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-biology-09-00026" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-biology-09-00026" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Since these full genomes are few in number, we supplemented them with partial sequences from other 
 <italic>Mastomys</italic> trapped in Guinea and Nigeria. In Guinea, we sequenced the GP 1kb portion to complement NP sequences published in Lecompte et al. [
 <xref rid="B12-biology-09-00026" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] and Fichet-Calvet et al. [
 <xref rid="B11-biology-09-00026" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. A fragment of 950 nucleotides was amplified using a RT-PCR protocol with the following primers: LVS 36-fwd (ACCGGGGATCCTAGGCATTT) and OWS 1000-rev (AGCATGTCACAGAAYTCYTCATCATG) for the strains from Faranah and Denguedou. In Nigeria, we sequenced the NP to complement LASV GP sequences published in Olayemi et al. [
 <xref rid="B14-biology-09-00026" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] from 
 <italic>Mastomys natalensis</italic> that were sampled during 2011–2012. We designed primers to amplify the NP at the same position of those published in Bowen et al. [
 <xref rid="B4-biology-09-00026" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. A fragment of 800 nucleotides was amplified using a RT-PCR protocol (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-biology-09-00026">supplementary information</xref>) with the following primers: LVSnig 1669-fwd (TATATTGAGTCCTCCTGACACAG) and LVSnig 2511-rev (TGTTGGAGACCATCAAGGTT) (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-biology-09-00026">Table S1</xref>). Furthermore, to expand the timeframe of our collection in Ekpoma, we added LASV GP 1kb and partial NP sequences from 13 
 <italic>M. natalensis</italic> trapped during 2014–2016. All PCR fragments were sequenced on both strands. The sequences were assembled and aligned using the Mac Vector software (Mac Vector 16.0.8, Inc, Apex North Carolina 27502, USA). In total, we generated 46 partial GP sequences of LASV from 
 <italic>M. natalensis</italic> in Faranah and in Denguedou; 13 partial NP from 
 <italic>M. natalensis</italic> in Ekpoma collected in 2011–2012; and GP 1kb plus partial NP from 13 
 <italic>M. natalensis</italic> also trapped in Ekpoma during 2014–2016 (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-biology-09-00026">Table S2</xref>). Sequences were submitted to GenBank under accession numbers MN123651-MN123709 and MT001745-MT001770. The sequences from 
 <italic>Mastomys</italic> used in our study are listed in 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-biology-09-00026">Table S2</xref>.
</p>
