<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par25">We acknowledge the limitations of our study design. Our results might only represent the population of pigs from which the cohort was selected. However, the pig farm selected for this study represented a common commercial wean-to-finish farm in the USA and the epidemiological findings of this study are similar to prior studies in the USA
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>, Europe
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>
 </sup>, and field reports by veterinarians in the USA. Since there was limited information from the farrow-to-wean herd prior to the start of the study, we cannot rule out that VG2 or VG3 originated from the farrow-to-wean ﻿herd﻿. Overall, we found VG1 IAVs at the arrival of pigs and proved that pigs at weaning can be the source of IAVs to wean-to-finish farms. Additionally, our random sample selection and large sample size minimized the random error and allowed us to make conclusions at the population level. Moreover, the detection of IAV by RRT-PCR might not represent true infections, as it cannot differentiate the stage of IAV infection or whether replicating virus was present, which needs to be taken into consideration for all data interpretation. Additionally, it is possible that the estimated genetic diversity of IAVs during this study is biased because we only selected a set of positive samples and for certain weeks the proportion of samples sequenced might appear low. However, we sequenced 25% of all positive samples and performed the genome amplification directly from nasal swabs, which avoided genotype selection during virus isolation. The number of samples tested and sequenced in this study is probably the largest in any cohort study done to date in pigs. Finally, prospective cohort studies in pigs could also serve as an excellent animal model to study IAV transmission and evolution in humans, or to test the efficacy of health interventions given the physiological and immunological similarities between humans and pigs
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>, the homology between human and swine IAV subtypes, and the similarity on IAV transmission routes among humans and pigs
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
