<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>When a disease management strategy is primarily reactive to the detection of infected individuals, monitoring effort plays an important role in reducing the severity of epidemic impact on host populations [
 <xref rid="pone.0232705.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. However, while monitoring radio-collared sentinels is a commonly recommended component of epidemic mitigation, little research has been done on optimal monitoring strategies. Our model showed that more monitoring effort, both in terms of increasing the number of sentinels monitored and monitoring frequency, always led to earlier epidemic detection and fewer infected foxes on the day of detection. However, realistic budget constraints require that choices be made about how many foxes are monitored and at what frequency, with increases in one generally leaving fewer resources available for the other. Our findings corroborate conclusions from nonspatial models of disease spread in island foxes that reducing the time between sentinel mortality and implementation of epidemic management actions is more effective than increasing the number of sentinels in a population [
 <xref rid="pone.0232705.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. These results are driven by the fact that early in the course of an epidemic the rate at which susceptible foxes become infected is increasing more rapidly than the rate at which infected animals are dying, with the number of new infections per day peaking between the median detection date of the first and fifth sentinel mortality [
 <xref rid="pone.0232705.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0232705.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The cost of delays in epidemic detection or management response time will be greatest for pathogens capable of rapid initial spread. For example, differences in the number of infected animals at the time of the first vs. fifth sentinel mortality were greater for CDV than for rabies, and greater for epidemics beginning in regions of high fox density than those beginning in regions of low fox density (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0232705.g003">Fig 3</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0232705.s002">S2 Table</xref>).
</p>
