<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21">Our findings herein summarily show that the marmoset model faithfully recapitulates key characteristics of CZS in humans that are not observed in other rodent nor NHP models. Notably, ZIKV-infected rhesus macaques exhibited no fetal CNS abnormalities with maternal infection
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. Pigtail macaques exhibited neural injury with severe hypoplasia and asymmetry within the occipital-parietal lobes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup>, but did not manifest the diffuse effects on neuroprogenitor cells observed in both the marmoset and human cases. In contrast, neuronal disorganization in ZIKV-infected pregnant marmosets was observed during early gestation at the posterior and crown in what will later comprise the occipital–parietal lobes (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). We speculate that the capacity for the marmoset to better recapitulate human infection is related to ongoing placental development and trophoblast renewal, whereby the virus is permissive to replication in both placental trophoblasts
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup> and placental macrophages (Hofbauer cells)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup> without evidence of inflammation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup>. As is likely the case in humans, the placenta may be viewed as an effective “shuttle” to the fetus, functioning first as a reservoir and later as a source of fetal infection of susceptible cell types and tissues, including neuroprogenitor cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup>. Nevertheless, in fetuses from both dam 1 and dam 2, the virus appears to have caused injury to the neocortex documented by histopathological examination and neuronal disorganization in the absence of localized inflammation, as also seen in mouse models
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup> and human cases
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
