<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32">Besides the serious agriculture losses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], the effectiveness of LPMs needs further evaluation. One field study demonstrated that during the closure, H7N9 viral RNA detection and isolation rates in retail markets decreased by 79 and 92%, respectively. However, viable H7N9 virus could be cultured from wastewater samples collected up to 2 days after the market closure began [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Overall, LPMs reopen and temporary interventions cannot completely halt A (H7N9) virus persistence and dissemination. In order to balance the interests of agriculture economics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] and public health, government encourages residence purchase chilled chicken instead of live poultry. Chilled chickens are slaughtered and packaged chicken stored at between 0 °C and 4 °C after going through a chilling process and has a shelf-life of 5–7 days, which can highly reduce the risk of virus transmission from live poultry to human [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Since the outbreaks of H7N9, many cities that reported the cases have launched a pilot program (named “Centralized Slaughtering, Cold Chain Delivery, Chilled Poultry Supply”) in designated areas, such as 2013 in Shanghai, 2014 in Guangzhou and Shenzhen [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Furthermore, the long-lasting circulation of the H7N9 virus in market poultry has often preceded the emergence of H7N9 outbreaks [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Based on the above considerations, on 1st June 2016, Shenzhen was the first city in China implemented the LPMs all closure in the whole city and sold chilled poultry instead of live poultry in urban and suburb areas. This policy of live poultry ban in the whole city can prevent any type of avian influenza not only H7N9. It is an optimal measure with long-term effectiveness to block the avian infected virus transmit to human, our results proved that as well.
</p>
