<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our model projections provide 
 <italic>qualitative</italic> insight into why ART clusters may affect the impact of ART on HIV incidence. Our goal was not, however, to make precise, quantitative statements about the expected effects of ART clustering for specific populations or geographical regions. Accordingly, our analysis has several important limitations. Firstly, empirical investigations of ART homophily (the value of 
 <italic>m</italic>) are required to obtain a quantitative understanding of the effect of ART homophily on the effectiveness of ART. Such data are not currently available, so we let our model span the entire range of possible parameters. Questions about the ART status of one’s sexual partners should thus be included in studies of sexual behaviours conducted among ART patients, as is already the case in the MaxART study, an ongoing implementation study of early access to ART for all PLWH in Swaziland [
 <xref rid="pone.0163159.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Secondly, our model only considered situations in which there was no risk compensation among ART patients. Future investigations of ART homophily should incorporate interactions between risk compensation and the emergence of ART clusters. Thirdly, we only considered ART-related sexual mixing patterns. But partner choices could be more complex in the context of combination prevention, in which ART is scaled-up alongside other HIV prevention interventions such as medical male circumcision. Fourthly, our model did not include the acute phase of HIV infection, during which PLWH have an elevated viral load and are highly infectious [
 <xref rid="pone.0163159.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0163159.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Incorporating an acute phase with increased infectiousness and (near) zero coverage of ART during this phase would change the model’s estimate for the impact of ART on HIV incidence. However, given that ART coverage and ART clustering are likely extremely low among people in the acute phase of HIV infection in both the base scenario and comparison scenario, adding this phase to the model would not affect the 
 <italic>relative</italic> impact of ART on HIV incidence. We also only considered populations in which all individuals have the same number of sexual partners, even though heterogeneity in sexual activity and other forms of sexual network structure influence the impact of ART on HIV incidence [
 <xref rid="pone.0163159.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. It is less clear, however, if these network attributes also affect the relative effect of ART clusters on the HIV prevention benefits of ART. Moreover, assortative mixing, by sexual activity level, age, or other demographic or behavioural attributes, may lead indirectly to apparent serosorting. While our model assumes homogeneous sexual activity, it does allows for an arbitrary degree of serosorting among HIV-positive individuals, without making specific assumptions about the underlying dynamics that led to serosorting. Therefore, our model is not necessarily at odds with a more complicated model in which heterogeneity in sexual activity and some degree of assortative mixing by sexual activity level leads to serosorting. Finally, we focused on exploring the instantaneous change in the effectiveness of ART in reducing HIV incidence following the emergence of ART homophily. In doing so, we did not fully characterise the dynamics of the HIV transmission system we analysed, nor did we investigate its equilibrium properties. Future research on the impact of ART homophily should thus use more refined modelling strategies including network models or compartmental models, which permit addressing these questions.
</p>
