<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par88">The availability of the sequences of IAV strains in the public databases, when they are not suggested in the literature, were checked online using Google, GenBank and GISAID search engines, or search offline in the genomeset.dat and influenza_na.dat files that were retrieved from NCBI Influenza Virus Resource [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. The sequences of the viruses, if available, were collected from GenBank [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>] or GISAID [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. When the genome of a particular virus were incomplete, the HA and/or NA of the virus were/was BLASTed against GenBank database of all influenza viruses and the top virus hit whose complete genome was available was used to extrapolate the incomplete genome (Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM11" ref-type="media">11</xref>: Table S7). Considering the closeness between their collection year and name, the genomes of A/Turkey/15/2006(H5N1) and A/chicken/Shandong/L1/2007(H9N2) were used to represent the genomes of A/Turkey/13/2006(H5N1) and A/chicken/Shandong/lx1023/2007(H9N2), respectively, which were not available during this study. Furthermore, we extrapolated partial IAV sequences by using the closest complete IAV sequence identified by BLAST (Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM12" ref-type="media">12</xref>: Table S8). Following the collection of IAV genomes and their extrapolation, the 12 IAV proteins were obtained by identifying their coding sequence regions using Influenza Virus Sequence Annotation Tool available at the NCBI Influenza Virus Resource [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>] and then translating them into proteins according to standard genetic code. Some proteins, mainly for recombinant and/or mutant viruses, were generated from existing proteins according to the list of amino acid differences at various sites reported in the literature. Note that some IAVs were represented by different versions of genomes or sets of proteins, but the reassortant or mutant viruses were mainly reconstructed from one of the versions. The metadata for IAV nucleotide sequences used in this study, reconstructed recombinant and/or mutant IAVs generated from those sequences, and the acknowledgement of the source of the GISAID sequences are provided in Table S4-S6 (Additional files 
 <xref rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="MOESM9" ref-type="media">9</xref> and 
 <xref rid="MOESM10" ref-type="media">10</xref>), respectively. They were also made available in DR-NTU (Data) under the title “Virulence Information for Influenza Virus Infections (VI2VI) in Mice” [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>], and further update will be available in the link: 10.21979/N9/ILQBAB.
</p>
