<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The most effective mode of prevention is to avoid contact with infected subjects. In the hospital setting, careful adherence to infection control practices is important for the protection of high-risk patients from RSV infection. Careful hand washing may reduce transmission in family and day-care settings. Pharmacologic intervention is indicated to prevent hospitalization for the highest risk infants, however. Passive RSV immunoprophylaxis with antibodies has proven a costly but relatively effective intervention. Parenteral infusion of RSV-neutralizing antibodies into experimental animals was shown early on to confer substantial resistance in the respiratory tract to a subsequent RSV virus challenge [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR154">154</xref>]. Significant reductions in RSV-associated hospitalizations and disease severity in high-risk human infants were first accomplished with prophylactic administration of human immunoglobulin with high RSV-neutralizing activity given by the intravenous route (RSV-IVIG; FDA licensed in 1996) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR155">155</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR156">156</xref>]. Monthly intravenous infusions during the RSV season reduced the frequency of pediatric hospitalization and duration of stay by approximately 55 % and decreased the number of days spent in intensive care by 97 %. The use of RSV-IVIG was superseded by the use of a monoclonal antibody (MAb) that was developed subsequently that could be given by intramuscular route, and production of the former has been discontinued. Several MAbs were developed for immunoprophylaxis against RSV. The most successful of these was based on murine MAb 1129 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR157">157</xref>], which is specific to the F protein and efficiently neutralizes viruses of both RSV subgroups A and B. This MAb was humanized by recombinant methods by transferring its variable regions onto a human IgG1 backbone, resulting in a recombinant antibody now named palivizumab [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR158">158</xref>]. This MAb is 50–100-fold more effective for in vitro neutralization on a per weight basis than was RSV-IVIG, and thus the total amount of immunoglobulin administered could be reduced to an amount that could be given IM. Palivizumab (trade name Synagis) was licensed in 1998 for RSV prophylaxis of high-risk infants, following studies demonstrating its safety and efficacy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR159">159</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR162">162</xref>]. Palivizumab is administered monthly through the RSV season and has been widely used in high-risk patients with prematurity, chronic lung disease, and hemodynamically significant heart disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR163">163</xref>]. More potent derivatives of this recombinant antibody have now been developed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR164">164</xref>]; however, the lead candidate from these affinity maturation efforts exhibited increased side effects in a large efficacy study.
</p>
