<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0035">An incubation period of 4–5 days usually precedes symptoms of SARS-CoV-2 infection. The peak of viral load is reached after another 5–6 days (
 <xref rid="bib112" ref-type="bibr">Tay et al., 2020</xref>). In the case of an efficient immune response rapid inactivation of SARS-CoV-2, clearance of infected cells, and the induction of an adequate immune response halt lung vascular damage and adverse disease progression (
 <xref rid="bib112" ref-type="bibr">Tay et al., 2020</xref>). Conversely, infection of airway epithelial cells by SARS-CoVs may induce pronounced pyroptosis, a type of cell death associated with a strong inflammatory response (
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Cookson and Brennan, 2001</xref>). This has been demonstrated to be triggered in human alveolar epithelial cells (
 <xref rid="bib131" ref-type="bibr">Yue et al., 2018</xref>) and macrophages by the SARS-CoV 3a protein (
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2019</xref>) and likely also happens in SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="bib112" ref-type="bibr">Tay et al., 2020</xref>). Pyroptosis may result in substantial vascular leakage and release of cytokines and chemokines, attracting monocytes and T cells to the site of injury or inflammation. Direct viral damage can thus be intensified by high levels of proteases and oxidative stress, an integral factor in COVID-19 progression (
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Delgado-Roche and Mesta, 2020</xref>), caused by the host defense. SARS-CoV-2 infection is characterized by an inappropriate cytokine host response: a relatively low induction of type I and III interferons blunt the anti-viral host defense and is paralleled by a high induction of chemokines and interleukin (IL)-6 (
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Blanco-Melo et al., 2020</xref>), similar to what has been reported for SARS-CoV infection. Damage to the airways and the resulting inflammatory host response may in turn contribute to the development of symptoms resembling acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS). Characteristic diffuse alveolar damage, pulmonary edema, and occasional hyaline membranes impair pulmonary gas exchange and may cause hypoxemia (reduced arterial oxygen pressure) and breathing difficulties. Direct respiratory failure or systemic cytokine-storm-mediated sepsis (including, for example, death from circulatory failure) may ensue, both conditions representing common causes of COVID-19-related death (
 <xref rid="bib90" ref-type="bibr">Ruan et al., 2020</xref>).
</p>
