<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Inorganic materials have been used in vaccine formulations for a long time. Back in 1926, an aluminum compound (alum) was discovered to be able to precipitate the toxoid to enhance the immunogenicity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref106">106</xref>
 </sup> Alum is still the most widely used adjuvant today. In spite of over 80 years of development, the underlying mechanisms for alum as an adjuvant are still controversial.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref107">107</xref>
 </sup> Popular explanations include the “depot theory” for extended antigen release
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref106">106</xref>
 </sup> and enhanced uptake by APCs through antigen absorption on alum.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref108">108</xref>
 </sup> Various immunity signaling and activation pathways have also been identified to contribute to the function of the adjuvants.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref109">109</xref>
 </sup> Recently, Moyer 
 <italic>et al</italic>. utilized the interaction between alum and phosphoserine (pSer) to engineer a short peptide-immunogen conjugate to significantly prolong the immunogen release from pSer-immunogen:alum complexes.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref73">73</xref>
 </sup> The complexes could form NPs for efficient trafficking to LNs and initiated antigen processing and presentation by APCs.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref73">73</xref>
 </sup> Site-specific pSer modification on the base of the HIV trimer could enable the immunogen (HIV trimer) to be displayed with a specific orientation, which could prevent the induction of undesired NAbs.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref73">73</xref>
 </sup> Apart from alum, other inorganic materials have been proposed that may stimulate vaccine-specific immune responses, such as silica crystal
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref110">110</xref>
 </sup> and calcium phosphate.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref109">109</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
