<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to the traditional use as immunostimulatory adjuvants, a wide range of biocompatible inorganic particles have also been developed as vaccine formulations,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref111">111</xref>
 </sup> including quantum dots (QDs),
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref80">80</xref>
 </sup> gold nanoparticles (Au NPs),
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref77">77</xref>
 </sup> carbon nanotubes (CNTs),
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref82">82</xref>
 </sup> and Si NPs.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref79">79</xref>
 </sup> The physical properties of formulations, such as surface charge, hydrophobicity, and aspect ratios, are closely associated with the efficacy of vaccines.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref112">112</xref>
 </sup> Inorganic materials have a high degree of tunability to allow them to fulfill the requirements of vaccine formulations. Easy preparation and good storage stability are additional advantages of inorganic particles.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref113">113</xref>
 </sup> For example, Au NPs have been chemically functionalized to investigate the relationship between surface hydrophobicity and the associated immune activity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref74">74</xref>
 </sup> It is also expected that other functional groups may bring a pathway-dependent immune activation that is specifically desirable for antiviral defense. Xu 
 <italic>et al</italic>. described surface-engineered Au nanorods (NRs) for plasmid DNA vaccine delivery.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref75">75</xref>
 </sup> With certain surface modifications and aspect ratios, cellular toxicity of Au NRs can be lowered, internalization can be enhanced, and intrinsic adjuvant features can be utilized.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref76">76</xref>
 </sup>
 <italic>In vivo</italic> vaccination with HIV-1 envelope glycoprotein (Env) plasmids demonstrated enhanced cellular and humoral immunity.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref75">75</xref>
 </sup> Zhou 
 <italic>et al</italic>. synthesized a series of Au NPs (15 to 80 nm) for co-delivery of antigens (OVA peptides) and adjuvants (CpG) by surface conjugation.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref77">77</xref>
 </sup> Particles of 60 and 80 nm outperformed other sizes (15, 30, and 40 nm) in activating DCs; this was most likely due to a higher payload of antigens. Notably, they promoted DC homing to the LNs and induced potent cellular immune response.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref77">77</xref>
 </sup> High tunability is also achievable in other organic particles, such as adjuvant-based mesoporous Si NPs,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref78">78</xref>
 </sup> mesoporous Si NP-based antigen/adjuvant co-delivery systems,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref79">79</xref>
 </sup> antigen density tunable QDs,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref80">80</xref>
 </sup> size-controlled antiviral QDs,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref81">81</xref>
 </sup> and surface oxidized antigen/adjuvant-based multiwall CNTs.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref82">82</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
