<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It has been reported that oxidation products derived from omega-3 and omega-6 polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs) have various functions such as causing and resolving inflammation and are involved in signal transduction as lipid mediators.
 <sup>(
  <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
  <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>)
 </sup> Morita 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <sup>(
  <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>)
 </sup> reported that the omega-3 PUFA-derived lipid mediator protectin D1 (PD1) attenuates influenza virus replication. They performed a screen of PUFA-derived lipid metabolites in human lung epithelial (A549) cells infected with influenza A virus (PR8 virus) by using bioactive lipid libraries containing prostaglandins, resolvins, protectins, and other PUFA-derived metabolites.
 <sup>(
  <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>)
 </sup> They evaluated the antiviral effect by influenza virus nucleoprotein mRNA expression at 8 h after infection and found that 12-HETE, 15-HETE, 17-hydroxy-4
 <italic>Z</italic>,7
 <italic>Z</italic>,10
 <italic>Z</italic>,13
 <italic>Z</italic>,15
 <italic>E</italic>,19
 <italic>Z</italic>-docosahexaenoic acid, or PD1 treatment of PR8-virus-infected A549 cells inhibited nucleoprotein mRNA expression.
 <sup>(
  <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>)
 </sup> Results of their report indicate that there are several PUFA-derived metabolites, which have anti-influenza activity, produced by lipid-metabolizing enzymes such as lipoxygenase. We demonstrated the antiviral activity of 5-HpETE in the present study (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>A); however, the mechanism remains unclear. 5-HpETE is further metabolized to leukotrienes by leukotriene-converting enzymes and leukotrienes exert physiological functions in the pathophysiology of asthma and inflammation.
 <sup>(
  <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>)
 </sup> Additionally, there is another 5-LOX associated arachidonate-derived metabolite: lipoxin A4.
 <sup>(
  <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>)
 </sup> It is possible that daidzein-induced enzymatic activation of 5-LOX produced 5-LOX-associated PUFA-derived metabolites other than 5-HpETE and that these metabolites exert antiviral activity. Further studies are needed to determine whether 5-HpETE or another 5-LOX-associated PUFA-derived metabolite exerts antiviral functions and how these lipid metabolites suppress viral replication.
</p>
