<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0025">Chinese patented medicine is widely used in all stages of COVID-19 because of its convenience and good taste. At present, the COVID-19 diagnosis and treatment plan (trial version 7) includes Chinese medicine. During the medical observation period, the clinical manifestation is fatigue. In case of gastrointestinal discomfort, Huoxiang Zhengqi (capsule, pill, water, or oral liquid) is recommended as the Chinese patented medicine with the most effectiveness. In cases of fatigue with fever, a combination of Jinhua Qinggan granules, Lianhua Qingwen capsules (granules), and Shufeng Jiedu capsules (granules) are recommended as the Chinese patented medicines with the most effectiveness. In the clinical treatment period, Qingfei Paidu decoction is used for the treatment of mild, regular, and severe patients. In addition, the corresponding prescriptions are recommended for different syndromes of mild, regular, severe, and critical patients; for severe and critical patients, Xiyanping injection, Xuebijing injection, Reduning injection, Tanreqing injection, and Xingnaojing injection are recommended (
 <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2020</xref>). The possible mechanism of Huoxiang Zhengqi in the prevention and treatment of COVID-19 has been discussed. Huoxiang Zhengqi can increase the level of anti-inflammatory cytokine IL-10, regulate the inflammation-related NF-κB pathway, suppress excessive inflammatory response, and resist a variety of viruses. There is in vitro experimental evidence that Huoxiang Zhengqi has a significant inhibitory effect on COVID-19 pathogens (
 <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">Huo et al., 2020</xref>). TCM injection is widely used in the treatment of COVID-19 (Wang, 2019). There are still some risks of the use of TCM injections. Attention should be paid to its safety, especially standardization, combination, adverse reactions, and use in special populations (
 <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Lin and Zhang, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">Xiang et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0089" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2020</xref>).
</p>
