<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="order">
 <list-item>
  <p>It is known that, being located in tropical-subtropical region, Taiwan often experiences summer influenza epidemics. This is confirmed by our modeling, with a wave of some influenza strain almost every year during June-August, or around weeks 24–36 of each year, for example, AH3 in 2008, and A(H1N1)pdm09 in 2009 and again in 2010 (
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0154695.g002">Fig 2</xref>).
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>A(H1N1)pdm09 virus circulated in six separate waves in Taiwan between summer of 2009 and spring of 2014 (
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0154695.g002">Fig 2</xref>), although some of these waves were co-circulating with other strains. For example, the summer wave of 2010 (weeks 22–39) co-circulated first with B and later with AH3 (
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0154695.g004">Fig 4a</xref>), while the two waves in 2013–2014 co-circulated with two respective waves of H3N2 (
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0154695.g004">Fig 4b</xref>).
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>A(H1N1)pdm09 first appeared in Taiwan in two pairs of swiftly succeeding waves in less than two years, first in summer and autumn/winter of 2009, then again in summer and autumn/winter of 2010 (
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0154695.g001">Fig 1a</xref>). It then occurred only sparingly for more than one year until another two waves, respectively at the beginning of 2013 and 2014, or the latter half of influenza seasons in Taiwan (Figs 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0154695.g001">1b</xref> and 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0154695.g002">2</xref>). The pattern is similar to what occurred in the aftermath of 1918–1919 pandemic [
   <xref rid="pone.0154695.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Moreover, since 2009 a wave of A(H1N1)pmd09 occurred every fall/winter influenza season during our study period except 2011–2012 season, when influenza B circulated. We note that, although it did not return in the 2014–2015 influenza season, AH1N1 circulated again in Taiwan in the 2015–2016 season [
   <xref rid="pone.0154695.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>At most of the times during the time period under investigation, one of the three strains always tend to be the dominant circulating strain, even when co-circulation with some other strains occurred (
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0154695.g004">Fig 4</xref>). One exception is the first half of 2013 (
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0154695.g004">Fig 4b</xref>), where one would be difficult to conclude which, among A(H1N1)pdm09 and H3N2, is the dominant strain in that particular time period. Moreover, we are able to fit a wave of infections for 
   <italic>both</italic> of these two strains during some parts of that half year (see 
   <xref rid="pone.0154695.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0154695.g001">Fig 1(a) and 1(b)</xref>). Although we note that a much larger study period than our data allows would likely offer more insights.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>It has been proposed that, due to school/business closure due to traditional lunar New Year holidays in Taiwan that falls typically between week 4 to week 8 of each year, more frequent contacts in the households among family members who spent more time at home during the holidays tends to result in increased transmission [
   <xref rid="pone.0154695.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. It is interesting to note that during 2008–2014, at least one wave of cases was detected in the first two months of every year, including two circulating waves of B and A(H1N1)pdm09 in 2014 (
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0154695.g002">Fig 2</xref>).
  </p>
 </list-item>
</list>
