<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Thirdly, persistent arthralgia and joint swelling are common long-term manifestations of CHIKF. Unlike other mosquito-borne viruses such as dengue, Zika, and even yellow fever, CHIKV typically causes symptomatic infection, and consequently outbreaks are accompanied by high attack rates. Chronic joint pain, along with asthenia and mood changes, is a common cause of quality-of-life impairment. Ninety-four percent of symptomatic travelers infected in La Reunion complained of joint or bone pain 6 months after the epidemic peak; this pain was continuous in 41% of the cases. The effect of chronic symptoms on the quality of life was defined as totally disabling or important in almost half of the patients, whereas only 16% reported a normal mood [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006919.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. A study conducted in La Reunion on 147 individuals over the age of 16 found that 84 confirmed cases (57%) self-reported rheumatic symptoms; of these, 63% reported permanent pain, whereas 37% had recurrent symptoms. An age of over 45 years (odds ratio [OR] 3.9), severe initial joint pain (OR 4.8), and the presence of underlying osteoarthritic comorbidity (OR 2.9) were independent predictors of nonrecovery [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006919.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. An assessment of 173 individuals with CHIKF conducted in Mauritius found that 79% reported persisting musculoskeletal symptoms 27.5 months after infection, associated with older age, female gender, and a baseline symmetrical distribution of arthralgia [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006919.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. A study conducted on Italian patients found that over 66% of those with CHIKF developed long-lasting rheumatic disorders, leading to functional impairment affecting daily living activities up to one year after infection [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006919.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Therefore, the long-term impact of CHIKF is far from negligible in terms of suffering, need for care, impairment of work ability, psychological problems, diminished quality of life, and associated economic costs.
</p>
