<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The dynamics of dengue transmission depends on the interactions among hosts, viruses, vectors and environmental factors. Given the restricted range of mosquito flying distance [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005095.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005095.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], population movement may play a critical role for dengue transmission. At broad spatial scales (e.g., national, international), human movements may make dengue virus being introduced and reintroduced into a region with lower herd immunity [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005095.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Travel acquired cases were repeatedly imported to Europe from Africa, Southeast Asia and the Americas [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005095.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0005095.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Local dengue transmission has occurred in Europe for the first time in many decades, with indigenous cases reported in France and Croatia in 2010 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005095.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005095.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In addition to sporadic cases, dengue outbreak also occurred in Europe. For example, an outbreak with more than 2,000 cases happened in Madeira, Portugal in 2012, which was most probable origin of Venezuela [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005095.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Aware of the importance of air travel in dengue transmission, researchers developed simple models to estimate the importing risk of dengue or even the possible origin of importation in Europe [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005095.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005095.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In Asia, because of the reintroductions of dengue viruses from Southern Vietnam where dengue is endemic, Northern Vietnam had dengue epidemics occurred frequently [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005095.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. At finer spatial scales (regional, intra-urban, neighborhood), population movements associated with work and recreation are important for dengue transmission [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005095.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], and house-to-house human movements may shape spatial patterns of dengue incidence, causing significant heterogeneity in dengue incidence [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005095.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].
</p>
