<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Adaptive immunity is composed of humoral (B cell)- and cellular (T cell)-based immune responses. The humoral immune response plays a key role in the pathogenesis of WNV. Antibody and B cells are essential in the defense against WNV infection in that mice deficient in B cells and antibody (μMT mice) developed increased serum and CNS viral burdens and were vulnerable to lethal infection [
 <xref rid="B99-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. Prophylactic and therapeutic transfer of human IgG or mouse serum delayed or protected WT, μMT and RAG1 (T and B cell-deficient) mice from WNV infection. Antibody by itself did not eliminate viral reservoirs in host tissues, suggesting an intact cellular immune response may be required for viral clearance [
 <xref rid="B100-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. Furthermore, sIgM
 <sup>−/−</sup> mice, which are deficient in the production of secreted IgM but capable of expressing surface IgM and secreting other antibody isotypes, are vulnerable to lethal WNV infection [
 <xref rid="B101-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>]. These results demonstrated that the early anti-WNV IgM in the course of WNV infection limits viremia and dissemination into the CNS. The innate immune responses are required to activate B cell response and antibody production. A study showed that mice deficient in MyD88, the essential adaptor for the signaling of the majority of TLRs except TLR3, significantly diminished B cell response by impairing B cell activation, development, and generation of long-lived plasma cells and memory B cells. In contrast, TLR3 deficiency had more effects on the maintenance of germinal centers and the development of long-lived plasma cells, whereas, differentiation of memory B cells was unaffected [
 <xref rid="B102-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. Signaling through type I IFN-α/β receptor has also been shown to be required for B cell activation in the draining lymph nodes, but not the spleen [
 <xref rid="B103-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. In line with this, mice deficient in interferon-induced transmembrane protein, Ifitm3, infected with WNV showed decreases in the total number of B cells, CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells, and antigen-specific CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells and increases in viral burden in the peripheral organs and CNS tissues [
 <xref rid="B104-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. However, mice deficient in interferon regulatory factor 5 (
 <italic>Irf5
  <sup>−/−</sup>
 </italic>) infected with WNV exhibited small differences in the type I IFN response also resulted in reduced IgM and IgG secretion that was associated with fewer antigen-specific memory B cells and long-lived plasma cells, which may relate to the reduced proinflammatory cytokine production in these mice [
 <xref rid="B105-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Furthermore, B cell and humoral responses to WNV infection have been suggested to be regulated by many factors related to DCs, the complement system, CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells and other immune factors [
 <xref rid="B91-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>,
 <xref rid="B106-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>,
 <xref rid="B107-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>,
 <xref rid="B108-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>,
 <xref rid="B109-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>,
 <xref rid="B110-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>].
</p>
