<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0002">Before SARS-CoV-2, the use of convalescent plasma has been investigated, with reported positive outcomes, in outbreaks of other viral infections, including the 1918 Spanish H1N1 influenza A pandemic and, more recently, the 2003 Avian H5N1 influenza A epidemic, the 2003 SARS-CoV-1 epidemic, the 2009-2010 H1N1 influenza pandemic, the 2012 Middle East Respiratory Syndrome (MERS)-CoV epidemic, and the 2014 Ebola epidemic 
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Pertaining to the respiratory CoV infections, a number of studies have been conducted during the past decade to evaluate the clinical effectiveness of convalescent plasma. A systematic review and exploratory meta-analysis performed in 2015 identified 32 studies of SARS coronavirus infection and severe influenza. These studies involved 699 treated patients and 568 untreated controls 
 <xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. In the pooled analysis of the data, the review revealed the evidence for a consistent reduction in mortality in the group treated with plasma therapy compared with that receiving placebo or no therapy (odds ratio, 0.25; 95% CI:0.14–0.45 with a low degree of heterogeneity: 
 <italic>I</italic>
 <sup>2</sup> = 0%) 
 <xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Only few reports have been published so far on the use of convalescent plasma in COVID-19 patients. Shen and colleagues reported a case series of 5 critically ill patients, all receiving convalescent plasma containing SARS-CoV-2 antibodies (titer &gt; 1:1000) and a neutralization titer greater than 40, administered between day 10 and 22 of admission 
 <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Following transfusion, 4 out of 5 patients experienced increases in viral antibody titers, decreases in SARS-CoV-2 viral loads, and normalization of temperature and resolution of acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) 
 <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Duan and colleagues presented a series of 10 severely ill COVID-19 patients, all receiving a 200 mL transfusion of convalescent plasma with high titers of neutralizing antibody (&gt;1:640) at a median of 16.5 days 
 <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. The primary endpoint was safety, which was demonstrated as all patients tolerated plasma transfusion without severe adverse events. The secondary endpoints included improvement of clinical symptoms and of laboratory values from day 3 post-infusion. They reported increase neutralizing antibody titer, oxygen saturation and lymphocyte count and decrease in C-reactive protein, SARS-CoV-2 viral load and lung lesions on radiological examination 
 <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. Zhang and colleagues described retrospectively 4 critically ill patients who were transfused with 200-2400 mL of convalescent plasma ranging from day 11 to day 18 of admission 
 <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. All the patients (including a pregnant woman) recovered from the SARS-CoV-2 infection. Finally, Zeng and colleagues tested the role of convalescent plasma in 6 critically end-stage COVID-19 patients 
 <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Although the blood component, which was transfused at a median of 21.5 days after first detection of viral shedding, led to the discontinuation of the SARS-CoV-2 shedding by 3 days after infusion, it was not able to improve the survival in these patients with advanced disease (5/6 and 14/15 deaths in the convalescent plasma group and control group, respectively). Based on the results of this trial, the authors concluded the convalescent plasma should be used in an early phase of the disease to obtain the best effect 
 <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>.
</p>
