<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0003">Following these first reports on the successful use of convalescent plasma in COVID-19 patients in China and considering the efficacy of this treatment in previous severe viral epidemics and the absence of standardized treatments, the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approved the use of convalescent plasma to treat critically ill patients on 26 march 2020 and this action has fueled the planning of several trials. A research performed on May 4, 2020 on clinicaltrials.gov (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://https://clinicaltrials.gov" id="interref0001" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link>) with the terms “convalescent plasma and COVID-19” showed 38 active ongoing trials on the use of convalescent plasma in COVID-19 patients, heterogeneous in term of study design and outcomes’ criteria: 14 of them are randomized versus other approaches (2 studies versus placebo, 5 studies versus standard fresh frozen plasma and 7 versus various pharmacologic agents including hydroxychloroquine and antiviral drugs). Also our group, in collaboration with University of Pavia, has given a contribute to this research. Indeed, considering the dramatic situation and the high lethality rate of COVID-19 in Italy, we have planned an interventional single-arm trial (NCT04321421) to produce hyperimmune plasma for treating critical patients with COVID-19. The results of these numerous trials are greatly awaited as they will permit to respond to the many still unanswered issues regarding convalescent plasma, including donors’ selection (i.e., age, gender, diagnosis of SARS-Cov-2 infection and of recovery, anti-SARS-CoV-2 antibody titer required for plasma donation), plasma collection and biologic qualification (number, volume and frequency of donations, infectious disease markers and pathogen inactivation) and treatment and disease characteristics (i.e., dose and timing of convalescent plasma infused and stage of the disease at which to start convalescent plasma treatment).
</p>
