<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0010">Coronavirus is one of the major pathogens which targets primarily the human respiratory system. Earlier coronaviral outbreaks (CoVs) include Middle East respiratory syndrome (MERS)-CoV and severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS)-CoV which have significantly caused great threat to human beings. In December 2019, a number of patients were admitted to hospitals with an initial diagnosis of pneumonia. These patients were found to have epidemiological links with wet animal and seafood wholesale market in Wuhan, Hubei Province, China [
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Early studies predicted the onset of a possible coronavirus outbreak. The WHO on 11th February 2020 estimated the reproduction number for COVID-19 significantly largely ranging between 2.24 to 3.58 [
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In December 2019 the first cases for COVID-19 infections were reported [
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. From 18th December, 2029 to 29th December 2019, 5 patients having acute respiratory distress syndrome were hospitalized among which one patient died [
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Upto 2 January 2020, 41 patients were identified to possess laboratory confirmed COVID-19 infection. Almost half of these patients had underlying diseases particularly cardiovascular diseases, hypertension and diabetes [
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. It was believed that these patients were infected in hospital possibly due to nosocomial infection. Thus it was concluded COVID-19 is not a super-hot spreading virus (spread to many others from one patient) but it most likely spread as many patients get infected by unknown mechanisms at different locations in the hospital. Furthermore only those patients were tested that were clinically sick and probably there were several more patients who were infected. As of January 22, 2020 a total of 571 COVID-19 infection cases were reported in 25 provinces of China [
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Upto 22 January 2020 China National Health Commission reported the details of first 17 deaths. On 25th January 2020 a total of 1975 COVID-19 infection cases were confirmed along with 56 deaths in mainland China [
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Another report of 24th January 2020, estimated 5502 COVID-19 infections in China [
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The first COVID-19 infection case was reported on 10th January 2020 which was led by identification, description, clinical diagnosis and management of the case. It included initial mild symptoms of the patient which leaded to pneumonia on 9th day of illness [
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Moreover on 30 January 2020 first case of COVID-19 human-to-human transmission was reported in US (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/media/releases/2020/p0130" id="intref0010" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.cdc.gov/media/releases/2020/p0130</ext-link>). Until 5th April 2020, total number of COVID-19 infected cases in USA mounted to 311,635 surpassing the infected cases of Italy (124,632) and China (81,669). Out of these 288,356 cases are active and 8454 are death cases while as rest i.e. 14825 cases have recovered (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/" id="intref0015" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/</ext-link>). A study published in Nature reported that Chinese health authorities concluded that 31,161 people had contracted the infection in China as of 7 February 2019, and that more than 630 people had died of the infection (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.natur.com/articles/d41586-020-00154" id="intref0020" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.natur.com/articles/d41586-020-00154</ext-link>). On 5th April 2020, total number of infected cases in Italy has reached to 124,632 out of which 20,996 have recovered and 88,274 cases are active. Out of these 15,362 are death cases (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/" id="intref0025" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/</ext-link>). Currently total number of corona virus cases in India reported so far 3374. So far there are 77 COVID-19 deaths cases reported in India. At the time of preparation of this manuscript i.e. 5th April 2020 the WHO has reported 1056159 COVID-19 confirmed cases throughout the world including 57,206 confirmed death cases. So far COVID-19 has spread to 208 countries around the globe (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019" id="intref0030" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019</ext-link>). The number of confirmed COVID-19 cases per million people around the globe as on 4th April, 2020 is represented in 
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> .
</p>
