<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A fundamental challenge in the use of genetic clustering to identify potential outbreaks is that these methods usually require the specification of one or more clustering criteria (
 <xref rid="veaa011-B30" ref-type="bibr">Poon 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="veaa011-B13" ref-type="bibr">Hassan 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2017
 </xref>). Many HIV-1 studies that employ pairwise clustering use similar genetic distance thresholds, where a genetic distance is a measure that adjusts for the possibility of multiple substitutions at the same nucleotide. For instance, a recent review (
 <xref rid="veaa011-B13" ref-type="bibr">Hassan 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2017
 </xref>) of 105 articles defining HIV-1 clusters found that 1.5 per cent was the most commonly used threshold among 52 studies that employed a genetic distance. In contrast, the United States Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (US-CDC) currently recommends a stricter pairwise distance threshold of 0.5 per cent (National Center for HIV/AIDS, Viral Hepatitis, STD, and TB Prevention 2018) for the purpose of identifying clusters with the most recent and rapid growth. In some cases the selected threshold is informed by the expected divergence between HIV-1 sequences sampled longitudinally from the same patient (
 <xref rid="veaa011-B31" ref-type="bibr">Poon 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2015
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="veaa011-B44" ref-type="bibr">Wertheim 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2017
 </xref>)—however, this empirical distribution can vary substantially among subjects (
 <xref rid="veaa011-B35" ref-type="bibr">Ratmann 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2016
 </xref>) and may be influenced by the extent of clinical follow-up. In other cases, the threshold is based on the expected number of substitutions between two epidemiologically unrelated individuals in the same sample space (∼5% for the USA; 
 <xref rid="veaa011-B2" ref-type="bibr">Aldous 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2012
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="veaa011-B27" ref-type="bibr">Oster 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2018
 </xref>), which makes the optimal threshold sensitive to regional variation in HIV prevalence and population density. On the other hand, population studies in Botswana (
 <xref rid="veaa011-B24" ref-type="bibr">Novitsky 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2014
 </xref>), South Africa (
 <xref rid="veaa011-B8" ref-type="bibr">De Oliveira 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2017
 </xref>), and South America (
 <xref rid="veaa011-B17" ref-type="bibr">Junqueira 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2016
 </xref>) have used substantially higher distance thresholds (10%, 4.5%, and 4.5%, respectively) that imply the optimal thresholds may vary substantially among settings and HIV-1 subtypes (
 <xref rid="veaa011-B14" ref-type="bibr">Hemelaar 2013</xref>). Furthermore, simulation-based studies (
 <xref rid="veaa011-B24" ref-type="bibr">Novitsky 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2014
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="veaa011-B30" ref-type="bibr">Poon 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="veaa011-B7" ref-type="bibr">Dasgupta 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2019
 </xref>) have demonstrated that clustering is highly sensitive to the sampled proportion of the infected population. Given the known differences in the empirical distributions of HIV-1 genetic distances among populations, as well as the significant global disparities in prevalence and access to testing and treatment, it is urgently necessary to establish an objective, quantitative framework for optimizing a clustering method to the target population.
</p>
