<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Immunosuppression and other physiological changes during pregnancy cause high susceptibility to respiratory pathogens and severe pneumonia in pregnant women (
 <xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">Jamieson 
  <italic>et al</italic>., 2006
 </xref>) which may require hospitalization in intensive care units and ventilatory support (
 <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">Goodnight &amp; Soper, 2005</xref>). Hormone levels and immune competence show considerable variation throughout pregnancy. Early pregnancy seems to be more risk-prone due to adaptive changes in response to fetal antigens, but conditions typically stabilize with gradual adjustment of the mother's immune and endocrine systems, with highest stability in the late stages of pregnancy. Early pregnancy is a crucial period of fetal organ development, and the immune system is particularly sensitive at this stage, which likely affects the course of infections (
 <xref rid="r44" ref-type="bibr">Wong 
  <italic>et al</italic>., 2004
 </xref>). Experience with previous respiratory virus epidemics may offer some insights regarding COVID-19 susceptibility and complication rates during pregnancy. Swine-origin influenza A (H1N1) virus is an influenza virus type A, which also causes respiratory disease that can develop into an acute respiratory syndrome. During the H1N1 epidemic in 2009, pregnant women were found to be at higher risk of complications as they were four times more likely to be hospitalized than the rest of the population (
 <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">Jamieson 
  <italic>et al</italic> ., 2009
 </xref>). Regarding other coronaviruses, the SARS epidemic in 2002/2003 produced 8,442 cases and 916 deaths, and studies have shown that clinical outcomes during this epidemic were worse in pregnant women than in non-pregnant women. In addition, increasing rates of premature births and abortions have been associated with SARS-CoV infections (
 <xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">Schwartz and Graham, 2020</xref>). Approximately 50% of pregnant women suffering from SARS required intensive care, and approximately 33% needed mechanical ventilation. The death rate of pregnant women suffering from SARS reached 25% (
 <xref rid="r44" ref-type="bibr">Wong 
  <italic>et al</italic> ., 2004
 </xref>). From the MERS epidemic which produced 2,500 confirmed cases and caused 858 deaths, we can affirm that MERS progresses much more quickly to respiratory failure and results in higher mortality rates than SARS. However, there was no evidence of vertical transmission of MERS or SARS. Based on this evidence, there is no doubt that SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV infections, as even the H1N1, are associated with higher rates of complications in pregnant women (
 <xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr">Schwartz and Graham, 2020</xref>).
</p>
