<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One-year retention in care in this cohort (73% in females and 77% in males) was lower than in the Asia-Pacific region in 2016 (86%) [
 <xref rid="pone.0218781.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Poorer pre-ART retention in this study correlated with being older, never having ART prior to entry to the clinic, and anemia. Male sex and lower education were identified as factors influencing pre-ART loss in Mozambique [
 <xref rid="pone.0218781.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>], whereas in this study the effect of sex and education diminished after adjusting for clinical variables. A study of HIV-infected key populations in four cities in Indonesia found being diagnosed at a facility that provided both testing and treatment services increased treatment initiation [
 <xref rid="pone.0218781.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In this study, lower patient retention after receiving ART was associated with living outside the city and lower education. Analysis of Indonesian MSM and transgender subsample from an Asia Pacific AIDS Positive Network (APN+) study showed an improved retention in care among patients who started ART, had medical insurance, and used the Internet to find HIV-related information [
 <xref rid="pone.0218781.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Other studies have associated lower treatment retention with lack of monthly income [
 <xref rid="pone.0218781.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>], lower education [
 <xref rid="pone.0218781.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0218781.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], and higher CD4 cell count [
 <xref rid="pone.0218781.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0218781.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]–characteristics that were more common in females than males in this study. Being older and having a higher education were correlated with ART initiation, while unemployed patients less likely to initiate ART. ART initiation was also associated with having a lower CD4 and ongoing treatment for TB. Similar to a study in Rwanda, ART initiation among patients with better clinical presentation seemed to be delayed [
 <xref rid="pone.0218781.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>].
</p>
