<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>IAV ion channel M2 protein has an important role in viral assembly and morphogenesis and it is a proven target for anti-influenza drugs [
 <xref rid="B218-viruses-11-00190" ref-type="bibr">218</xref>]. Viruses lacking the cytoplasmic tail domain of M2 have been used as LAIV for different IAVs, such as PR8 H1N1 [
 <xref rid="B219-viruses-11-00190" ref-type="bibr">219</xref>], HPAI H5N1 [
 <xref rid="B220-viruses-11-00190" ref-type="bibr">220</xref>], or pH1N1 [
 <xref rid="B221-viruses-11-00190" ref-type="bibr">221</xref>]. All of the LAIVs provided effective protection in mice against challenge with homologous viral strains. Next, Sarawar et al. developed a second-generation M2-knockout (M2SR) PR8, in which M2 expression was abrogated by deleting the M2 transmembrane domain plus inserting two stop codons downstream of the M1 ORF [
 <xref rid="B214-viruses-11-00190" ref-type="bibr">214</xref>]. The resulting M2SR virus encoded the M2 ectodomain, but it lacked the coding capacity for the M2 transmembrane domain and cytoplasmic tail (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00190-f009">Figure 9</xref>F). M2SR virus amplification relied on the use of MDCK cells that stably expressed the M2 protein, since M2SR replication was restricted in parental MDCK. However, the virus conserved the ability to elicit systemic and mucosal immune responses that protected mice against homosubtypic (sterilizing) and heterosubtypic (non-sterilizing) challenges [
 <xref rid="B214-viruses-11-00190" ref-type="bibr">214</xref>]. More recently, a similar strategy (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00190-f009">Figure 9</xref>F) was used to generate a PR8 M2SR containing the HA and NA from a HPAI A/Vietnam/1203/2004 (M2SR H5N1) or a pH1N1 (M2SR H1N1) [
 <xref rid="B213-viruses-11-00190" ref-type="bibr">213</xref>]. The LAIV potential of these viruses was evaluated in both mice and ferrets. In mice, M2SR H5N1 provided sterilizing immunity and both M2SR H5N1 and M2SR H1N1 conferred complete protection with 100% survival after lethal challenge with WT H5N1. Likewise, ferrets that were vaccinated with either M2SR H5N1 or M2SR H1N1 in a prime-boost regime were protected against lethal challenge with WT H5N1. In both animal models, only the M2SR H5N1 provided protection by inducing neutralizing antibodies against H5N1. In contrast, M2SR H1N1 conferred heterologous protection, which might rely on cross-reactive HA2 stalk region and/or NA antibodies. In summary, the authors have shown that the M2SR platform could be used to provide effective homo- and hetero-subtypic protection against IAV in both mice and ferrets [
 <xref rid="B213-viruses-11-00190" ref-type="bibr">213</xref>]. Notably, all of these sciIAVs showed a great potential as LAIVs since mice or ferrets (in the case of M2SR H5N1 and M2SR H1N1) were effectively protected against WT homologous challenges. Currently, a phase I clinical trial is evaluating the safety and immunogenicity of a monovalent M2SR-based LAIV based on 5 gene segments from influenza PR8 and the HA and NA glycoproteins from an A/Brisbane/10/2007-like virus (
 <uri>ClinicalTrials.gov</uri> Identifier: NCT03553940).
</p>
