<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pntd.0007965.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0007965.g002</object-id>
 <label>Fig 2</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Evaluation of Ebola sGP Detection Kit LOD with supernatant from cell culture and infected monkey plasma.</title>
  <p>(A) Supernatant of Vero cells containing ZEBOV viral particles at 3 x 10
   <sup>6</sup> FFU/ml was diluted as indicated in human plasma or blood and subjected to RT-qPCR and Ebola sGP Detection Kit. Results are test line delta OD of single measurement or mean of genome copies/ml from RT-qPCR duplicates performed on dilutions made in plasma. Sample positively detected by sGP Detection Kit are in bold characters. (B) Monkey infected intravenously with 10
   <sup>2</sup> FFU of EBOV Gabon 2002 was bled at day 7 post-infection. The plasma containing 2.15 x 10
   <sup>10</sup> genome copies/ml was subsequently diluted in human plasma or blood. Genome copies and sGP Detection Kit test were then performed. Results are test line delta OD (positive Ebola sGP Detection Kit tests are in bold characters) and mean of genome copies/ml from RT-qPCR duplicates performed on dilutions made in plasma. (C) Delta OD and related Log 2 genome copies/ml of samples tested in Fig 2A and 2B diluted human plasma (black) or in human blood (white) were plotted, adjusted R
   <sup>2</sup> values calculated with positive values, are 0.95 and 0.925 for monkey plasma and cell supernatant respectively. Linear regression analysis showed no effect of human matrices on Delta OD measurement (Student p values of 0.797 and 0.37 for monkey plasma and cell supernatant respectively). Culture supernatant diluted in human blood and plasma are shown as white circle and black square respectively. Infected monkey plasma diluted in human blood and plasma are shown as white and black triangle respectively.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pntd.0007965.g002" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
