<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Especially in pregnant ruminants (sheep, goats and cattle), the virus causes high abortion rates up to 100% in sheep and displays a similar mortality in infected newborn lambs. Generally increasing age reduces susceptibility, but adult animals can also be affected and suffer from weakness, anorexia, diarrhea, bloody nasal discharge and jaundice [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008143.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Apart from abortions, no clinical symptoms can be observed in camels; however, (hyper) acute clinical courses are described in an outbreak in Northern Mauritania [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008143.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Human infection mainly results from direct contact or inhalation during the handling of infected animals and tissues. Most infections display non-specific flu-like symptoms [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008143.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Severe cases are associated mostly with ocular complications (e.g. retinitis, reduced vision) and in 1–2% of the cases with jaundice and hemorrhagic manifestations. The course is normally preceded by a febrile phase of 3 to 4 days including temporal recovery or long-lasting fever up to 10 days [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008143.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Severe complications can be also associated with encephalitis [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008143.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0008143.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] Up to now no approved antiviral therapeutics nor approved vaccine for Rift Valley fever is available [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008143.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Known antivirals like Ribavirin or Favipiravir showed only limited efficacy in animal models [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008143.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Additional small molecules are currently still under development [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008143.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Most recently, rabbit and human derived monoclonal antibodies against glycoprotein Gn were shown to be protective in mice against Rift Valley fever infections [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008143.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008143.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Gn is a type I transmembrane protein which forms together with glycoprotein Gc non-covalently linked heterodimers on the lipid bilayer envelope of the virion and allows virus attachment, uptake into cells and Gc mediated cell fusion. The Gn protein consists of an N-terminal ectodomain and a C-terminal transmembrane domain followed by a cytoplasmic tail. The ectodomain is main target for neutralizing antibodies and composed of three domains including an N-terminal helical domain, followed by a β-ribbon and a small globular domain [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008143.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].
</p>
