<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Here, we present the results obtained from a small number of samples selected on the basis of their HI titers. The ELISA IgG signal that was obtained against the HA protein agrees with those obtained with HI and SRH assays, for which we observed a better correlation (HI–SRH) (R
 <sup>2</sup> = 0.70) to HI–MN and MN–SRH with R
 <sup>2</sup> values of 0.55 and 0.3, respectively. Despite the low number of samples that were analyzed in the present work, these results seem to confirm previous studies that have supported strong agreement between the HI and SRH assays [
 <xref rid="B46-vaccines-08-00043" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-vaccines-08-00043" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] in respect to the higher correlation found by Wang et al. [
 <xref rid="B48-vaccines-08-00043" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] between the SRH and MN. The MN assay generally suffers from high interlaboratory variability due to the lack of common protocols (long vs short/CPE vs. ELISA-based) and discrepancies in endpoint determination. On the other hand, although ELISAs are not officially acknowledged by EMA and other regulatory authorities, they usually provide unbiased and precise results. The responses that were obtained in the two age groups support the statement that the described ELISA-based assay is able to distinguish between immunological responses against head and stalk epitopes in adults and children in a very selective manner. Moreover, inside each group (adults and children), the assay is able to reveal subtle differences in HA-specific responses. Upon comparing the results obtained in children and in adults, it appears that the immunological memory could play an important role in antibody responses after vaccination [
 <xref rid="B49-vaccines-08-00043" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Indeed, in children, in whom we observed no or very low stalk signals, most of the response after vaccination was directed against the globular head domain. This particular ‘conserved’ trend that was observed in pediatric samples can be attributed to the low age of children (3–9 years) and the possibility for at least some of them of being completely naïve for A/H1N1/California/7/2009 influenza strain at the time of blood draw. The high anti-head antibody signal that was observed after vaccination in children, in contrast to the low anti-stalk signal, can be explained by different reasons: 1) the head domain of the HA is the most immunogenic part of the HA protein, in contrast to the stalk, which appears to be less immunogenic; 2) antibodies against the stalk domain are generally difficult to be elicited by classical inactivated split and subunit influenza vaccines [
 <xref rid="B50-vaccines-08-00043" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]; and 3) the influenza specific B- (and T-) cells repertoires in young children contain a greater frequency of naïve cells. However, adults have pre-existing populations of influenza-specific memory cells that can target conserved epitopes [
 <xref rid="B51-vaccines-08-00043" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. This last point seems to validate our results from adult subjects, where we observed a boost in both head and stalk responses after vaccination and a more heterogeneous scenario in comparison to children. In one adult subject, we detected a particularly high anti-stalk response after vaccination and a very low anti-head response, despite a very high HI titer accompanied by increased SRH and NA responses. The unpredictability and complexity of immune responses against influenza vaccination are illustrated by the fact that this subject did not show an increase in the neutralizing antibody response. This peculiar observation can be explained by the interference of a large number of antibodies directed against conserved epitopes of the influenza virus, thus causing the steric hindrance of the hemagglutination activity. This was confirmed by the high SRH titer and the very low MN titer after vaccination, and it supports the superiority of the SRH assay over the HI and MN assays to detect a broader range of functional antibodies. This characteristic may not only reflect the specific nature of the SRH assay, which detects all antibodies directed against various epitopes of HA and NA, it may also reflect the fact that internal influenza virus proteins may be involved in the complement fixation reaction. The small increase in the MN titer, along with the low head response detected with the ELISA, seems to confirm this theory. This particular case supports the strategy that has been adopted in the last few years by some regulatory agencies, such as EMA [
 <xref rid="B45-vaccines-08-00043" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-vaccines-08-00043" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], to take into account a combination of different immune responses that are measured by multiple assays for the evaluation of the effectiveness of influenza vaccines. In the present study, we also included the measurement of the NA antibodies in order to broaden the view of the antibody-mediated immune response in both age groups. However, it is important to point out that current licensed influenza vaccines are made with a well standardized amount of HA antigens but not of NA antigens. The understanding of the NA response could become extremely important for the study of the immune response after LAIV administration or natural infection.
</p>
