<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Pneumonia is the most serious inflammatory disease of the respiratory tract and also the most common infectious disease. The classification of pneumonia into Hospital-Acquired Pneumonia (HAP), Community-Acquired Pneumonia (CAP) and Ventilated-Acquired Pneumonia (VAP) indicates the source of disease by a wide variety of microorganisms including bacteria, viruses and fungi. Respiratory tract infections and in particular pneumonia represent the most common cause of sepsis [
 <xref rid="B5-viruses-11-00420" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Long-time associated with bacterial infection, sepsis definition became more in focus as a multifaceted host response to an infecting pathogen, which leads to organ failure [
 <xref rid="B6-viruses-11-00420" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, Influenza Virus (IV) as a pneumotropic virus can lead to lung failure and systemic host reaction with subsequent multiple organ failure. IV circulates worldwide and causes highly contagious respiratory diseases characterized by mild to severe symptoms. The seasonal IV-associated bronchopneumonia is one of these infectious diseases with the highest population-based mortality rates [
 <xref rid="B7-viruses-11-00420" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Besides virulence factors, the sudden increase of pathogenicity is the most striking problem of influenza accompanied by bacterial co-infection. In a single-centre study conducted at the Jena University Hospital during the winter season 2017/2018, we detected 1197 influenza-virus-positive samples and 89 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>-positive respiratory specimens. However, the diagnosis of a co-infection was significantly lower with 17 samples. Interestingly, the mortality rate increased dramatically from single infection (approximately 20%) to co-infection (approximately 80%). Even larger studies indicating similarly dates and also the Spanish flu of 1918 showed that co-infection results in high mortality rates [
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-11-00420" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. While the pathogen–host interaction-induced severe dysregulations of the immune response is under investigation in many studies, the regulatory effects between the different pathogens and the subsequent impact on the host are barely understood. In a multifactorial process, a wide range of pathogen factors and pathogen-regulated signalling events are involved in co-pathogenesis. This process is associated with elevated host-response, changed repair-processes, and modifications in the cellular immune response [
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-11-00420" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. It is shown that primary IV-infection inhibits the apoptosis mechanism and the following infection with 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> inhibits IV-induced apoptosis by procaspase-8 activation [
 <xref rid="B10-viruses-11-00420" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Various models are available for studying the mechanisms of the viral–bacterial interference. However, the use of murine models is adversely regarded because of obvious discrepancies between men and mice despite the attempts of humanized murine models to fill the gaps. New methods enable investigations with cost-saving and efficient cell culture models as an excellent supplement to animal experiments. Organ-on-a-chip technology allows species-specific investigations for different cell types and also immune cells. Using this method, viral-bacterial interference can be investigated in a human-specific manner.
</p>
