<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In Senegal, CHIKV was first isolated in 1962 from bats [
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], and CHIKV outbreaks and sporadic cases were subsequently reported in 1966, 1982, 1996, 1997, and 2004–2006 [
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). In addition, CHIKV has been repeatedly isolated from wild caught 
 <italic>Aedes furcifer</italic>, 
 <italic>Aedes luteocephalus</italic>, and 
 <italic>Aedes taylori</italic> in a sylvatic focus near Kedougou in southeastern Senegal [
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18–20</xref>] as part of an entomological surveillance programme that began in 1972 [
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Various vertebrates, including monkeys, bats, gophers, and galagos, have been proven for implication as hosts of CHIKV by serological evidence or viral isolation [
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Amplifications of CHIKV in the Kedougou area have occurred at approximately 5-year intervals, which is hypothesized to be the time necessary for the turnover of susceptible vertebrate hosts [
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Despite active circulation of CHIKV in the sylvatic cycle in Senegal, limited information is available on its transmission on human and wildlife populations. To address this question, we conducted passive surveillance for CHIKV infection among patients attending 5 health clinics with febrile illness, together with active surveillance of students recruited from 4 schools in Kedougou. In a parallel effort, we also investigated monkey serosampling in the region and surveyed mosquitoes in the area for CHIKV. In this study, we report the investigation of the CHIKV zoonotic amplification that occurred among monkeys, mosquitoes, and humans in the Kedougou region by 2009–2010.
</p>
