<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Nested PCR was used to recover proviral sequences for Sanger sequencing as follows: First Round 5 µl Kapa Hotstart Hifi polymerase (Kapa Biosystems, USA), 2 µl H
 <sub>2</sub>O, 1 µl of both the forward and reverse primer (
 <xref rid="vez058-T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) and 2 µl of DNA. Second Round—10 µl Kapa Hotstart Hifi polymerase (Kapa biosystems, USA), 6 µl H
 <sub>2</sub>O, 1 µl of both the forward and reverse primer (
 <xref rid="vez058-T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) and 2 µl of R1 PCR product. Cycling conditions were followed according to manufacturer’s specifications and an annealing temperature of 60°C. Reactions were run on a C1000 Touch Thermal Cycler (Bio-Rad, USA). Full genomes were amplified in two ∼6.3 kb fragments with ∼1 kb overlapping regions. PCR products were resolved on a 0.7 per cent agarose gel using electrophoresis for 30 min at 110 V. Bands of the correct size were excised from the gel and purified using a MEGAquick-spin™ Total Fragment DNA Purification Kit (iNtRON Biotechnology, Korea). Purified DNA was then cloned using pJET 1.2 blunt vector using the CloneJET PCR Cloning Kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA) and XL1-Blue 
 <italic>E</italic>
 <italic>scheri</italic>
 <italic>chia</italic> 
 <italic>coli</italic> competent cells (Agilent technologies, USA). Plasmids were isolated using DNA-spin Plasmid Purification Kit (iNtRON Biotechnology, Korea) and subsequently Sanger sequenced using primer walking at Quintarabio in San Francisco, CA. Genetic sequences were verified and assembled using Geneious 7.0.6 (Biomatters Ltd., New Zealand). Datasets of full genomes, 
 <italic>pol</italic> and 
 <italic>env</italic> (which both include 
 <italic>pol</italic> and 
 <italic>env</italic> regions from the full genome isolates) were compiled together with those downloaded from the public database GenBank. Nucleotide and amino acid datasets for both genes were used for downstream analyses. 
</p>
