<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The viral membrane of IAV is characterized by the two key proteins on the surface of the virus, hemagglutinin (HA) and neuraminidase (NA), both of which are important for IAV infection and could potentially be affected by binding of CATH-B1 to the viral surface. HA functions as a receptor binding and fusion protein, while the NA protein is involed in release of (nascent) virus particles from decoy receptors or the cell surface (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Gamblin and Skehel, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Dou et al., 2018</xref>). Recently, it has been reported that NA activity of IAV is influenced by virus-receptor binding (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Guo et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Du et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Lai et al., 2019</xref>). NA activity is altered based on enhanced or a reduced HA-receptor binding property. Our results suggest that CATH-B1 did not affect NA activity but rather inhibited virus-receptor binding activity, in agreement with CATH-B1 only affecting virus infection when present during virus inoculation. Presumably the inhibiting effect on virus-receptor interaction is related to CATH-B1 induced aggregation of virus. Whether this phenomenom results from a direct interaction of CATH-B1 with HA remains to be established, and other or additional antiviral mechanisms, such as the interaction of CATH-B1 with the viral membrane should be explored further. This antiviral mechanism of CATH-B1 appears to differ from that of LL-37. LL-37 bound to virus but did not inhibit HA-receptor binding and failed to inhibit virus binding to and uptake into cells (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Tripathi et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Tripathi et al., 2015</xref>). Moreoever, the inhibitory activity of LL-37 depends on the IAV strain used which is consistent with our observation that LL-37 showed much more antiviral activity against H3N1 than against H1N1 and H5N1. Of note, CATH-B1 showed broad antiviral activity against IAVs carrying different HA proteins.
</p>
