<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>FIG 3 </label>
 <caption>
  <p>Interferon-independent LE/L cholesterol accumulation impairs early IAV infection. (A) A549-WT cells transfected with GFP, AnxA6-GFP, or AnxA6-GFP together with YFP-NPC1 were infected with IAV (PR8M; MOI of 5, 4 h). Cells were stained with anti-NP antibodies, and nuclei were labeled with DAPI. Bar, 20 µm. Numbers of transfected cells with NP-positive nuclei were determined from 150 transfected cells per condition from at least three independent experiments. Data are expressed as mean percentages ± SEM. **, 
   <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.01; ***, 
   <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.001; ns, not significant (one-way ANOVA with Tukey’s multiple-comparison test). (B) A431-WT and A431-AnxA6 cells were transfected with GFP or YFP-NPC1 as indicated and were infected with IAV (PR8M; MOI of 20, 4 h). Numbers of transfected cells with NP-positive nuclei were determined from 150 transfected cells per condition from three independent experiments. Data are expressed as mean percentages ± SEM. ****, 
   <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.0001 (two-way ANOVA with Tukey’s multiple-comparison test). (C) A431-WT cells expressing GFP or YFP-NPC1 were stimulated with IFN-β (10 ng/ml, 16 h) as indicated and then infected with IAV (MOI of 20, 4 h). Numbers of cells with NP-positive nuclei were determined from 150 transfected cells per condition from at least three independent experiments, and the mean percentages ± SEM of NP-positive nuclei were quantitated. *, 
   <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.05 (unpaired Student’s 
   <italic>t</italic> test). (D) A549-WT and A549-IFITM3KO cells were exposed to U18666A (U18) (2 µg/ml, 16 h) and were infected with IAV (PR8M; MOI of 2, 4 h), stained for NP, and analyzed by FACS (10.000 cells per sample). Data are expressed as the mean percentages ± SEM of NP-positive nuclei from three independent experiments. ****, 
   <italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.0001 (two-way ANOVA with Tukey’s multiple-comparison test).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="mbo0041839900003" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
