<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0245">With the increasing number of infected individuals and lack of effective antiviral therapies, the need for SARS-CoV-2 vaccine development has been an international priority. The current vaccine developments include RNA vaccines, DNA vaccines, recombinant protein vaccines, viral vector-based vaccines, live attenuated vaccines, and inactivated vaccines [
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. An mRNA-based vaccine co-developed by Moderna and the Vaccine Research Center at the National Institutes of Health has begun dosing patients with mRNA-1273 in their Phase III study, COVE (Coronavirus Efficacy) [
 <xref rid="bib0715" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>]. The results from their Phase I study showed that mRNA-1273 was safe and well-tolerated. It elicited Th1-biased CD4 T cell responses, produced neutralizing antibody titers in 100 % of evaluated participants at the 100 μg dose [
 <xref rid="bib0505" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>]. Another mRNA based vaccine, co-developed by Pfizer and BioNTech, has advanced the candidate BNT162b2 into Phase II/III study [
 <xref rid="bib0805" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>]. Phase I/II results showed that BNT162b2 was safe and well-tolerated and stimulated the production of neutralizing antibodies and elicited CD4
 <sup>+</sup> and CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cell responses against the RBD [
 <xref rid="bib0800" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>]. While both aforementioned mRNA vaccines encode for the SARS-CoV-2 S proteins, other viral recombinant proteins are being investigated [
 <xref rid="bib0630" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. One group has employed immune-informatics to identify and characterize SARS-CoV-2 S protein-based epitopes 
 <italic>in silico</italic> for vaccine development [
 <xref rid="bib0595" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. Li et al. used a myriad of online tools to analyze the structure of SARS-CoV-2 S protein to predict and identify highly antigenic B-cell and T-cell epitopes [
 <xref rid="bib1095" ref-type="bibr">219</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib1005" ref-type="bibr">201</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0115" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0315" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0285" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. The peptide epitopes were further characterized for allergenicity, physiochemical features, toxicity, and stability [
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0980" ref-type="bibr">196</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0925" ref-type="bibr">185</xref>]. The immuno-informatic approach has identified four peptide epitopes (VRQIAPGQTGKIAD, VLGQSKRVDFCGKG, GLTGTGVLTESNKK, and KIADYNYKLPDDFT). Unlike mRNA vaccines, peptide-based vaccines require careful design to identify epitopes that are capable to induce a strong immune response against the desired pathogen and the strategies reported by Li and colleagues can be used for other targets of interest.
</p>
