<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The increasing threat of vector-borne diseases emphasizes the importance of vector surveillance systems and diagnostic tests for early detection of pathogens.
 <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref> Early identification of the virus causing equine encephalitis will improve the effectiveness of many disease control measures. As previously mentioned, clinical diagnosis of equine encephalitic viruses is often unreliable due to overlap in the clinical signs seen; therefore, laboratory testing is usually necessary to confirm the etiology of the disease. The OIE (World Organisation for Animal Health) Manual of Diagnostic Tests and Vaccines for Terrestrial Animals describes internationally agreed diagnostic tests for each of the virus species presented in this review with the exception of BoDV-1. The preferred diagnostic test varies for the different viruses and the purpose for which it is being performed, which can include confirmation of a clinical case, surveillance, demonstrating freedom from infection of an individual animal or population and monitoring the response to vaccination. Virus isolation can be time-consuming and for many of the viruses described requires high levels of laboratory containment, but the OIE recommends it as a definitive diagnostic of VEE virus. Polymerase chain reaction (PCR)-based techniques are widely used for virus detection as they offer the advantages of being specific and rapid to perform. However, for some viruses, particularly the flaviviruses, the transient nature of viremia means that RT-PCR tests frequently return false-negative results. Therefore, serological confirmation is necessary. Enzyme-linked immune-sorbent assays (ELISA) are increasingly popular as a relatively inexpensive and rapid diagnostic test. However, cross-reactivity between closely related co-circulating viruses complicates serological testing, particularly for flaviviruses.
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Therefore, confirmatory testing using a virus-neutralizing test such as the plaque-reduction neutralization test is often required. Disease surveillance often includes random testing of animals in order to observe whether a pathogen is present within a population,
 <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref> which also requires cost-effective and accurate assays to be developed.
</p>
