<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0120">The RNA was extracted from supernatants of each sample. Viral RNAs were extracted using the Trizol Total RNA extraction kit (Invitrogen™, Carlsbad, USA) according to the manufacturer's instructions. The RNA was reverse transcribed into cDNA which in turn was the template for the following real-time quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR). Quantitative amplification and melting curve analysis were carried out by real-time qPCR (C1000 Touch Thermal Cycler, Bio-Rad, USA). Two FIPV-specific primers were used for the quantification of its nucleic acid. The primers for FIPV-PCR that targeted the 3′-untranslated region (3′-UTR) of ORF7ab were used for the amplification (
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Herrewegh et al., 1995</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Manasateinkij et al., 2009</xref>). The sequences of primers specific to the FCoV viral genome were: 5′-GGCAACCCGATGTTTAAAACTGG-3’ (upstream; nucleotides 1 to 23) and 5′-CACTAGATCCAGACGTTAGCTC-3’ (downstream; nucleotides 211 to 192). The reaction mixture for qPCR was prepared using SsoFast EvaGreen Supermix (2x) (Bio-Rad, Hercules, USA) and the cycling conditions were set according to the manufacturer's protocol. The qPCR amplification for each sample was carried out in duplicate. The standard curve was generated by ten-fold serial dilution (10
 <sup>−2</sup> to 10
 <sup>−7</sup>) of plasmid containing the FIP 3′-UTR sequence. The linear part of the amplification curves was plotted against the log values of the starting concentrations, which yielded r
 <sup>2</sup> ≥ 0.99. The Cq values were then automatically generated using the software CFX Maestro™ (Bio-Rad, Hercules, USA). The absolute quantities of viral copy numbers were calculated for each treatment and control. The antiviral activities of the selected candidate compounds were presented as percent viral reduction by each compound compared to the control, and validated by three independent experiments.
</p>
