<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0155">We estimated three parameters (daily rate of zoonotic infection, 
 <italic>α</italic>; the human-human transmission rate, 
 <italic>β</italic>; and the relative transmissibility of hospitalized cases, 
 <italic>l</italic>) by fitting our transmission model predictions of 
 <italic>C</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub>(
 <italic>t</italic>), 
 <italic>C</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>s</italic>
 </sub>(
 <italic>t</italic>) and 
 <italic>C</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>IH</italic>
 </sub>(
 <italic>t</italic>) to the total observed numbers of index, secondary and hospital-based secondary cases at the end of our study period. We minimized the “sum of square errors” between the corresponding model outputs and observed case counts for each of the three transmission settings (reservoir, community, hospital). We used a delayed rejection adaptive Metropolis-Hastings (DRAM) algorithm in a Markov-Chain Monte-Carlo (MCMC) framework which has been previously described in ref. (
 <xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">Haario et al., 2006</xref>) (Matlab package available from: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://helios.fmi.fi/~lainema/mcmc/" id="intr0005" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://helios.fmi.fi/∼lainema/mcmc/</ext-link>). We assumed uniform prior distributions for 
 <italic>α</italic>, 
 <italic>β</italic> and 
 <italic>l</italic> with broad ranges (
 <xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). We allowed the algorithm to run for 10,000 iterations with an initial burn-in of 5000 iterations to allow runs to reach a stationary regime. The Geweke diagnostic method was employed to assess convergence of chains (
 <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">Geweke, 1992</xref>), with values close to 1 deemed satisfactory. Posterior distributions for each parameter were obtained from the underlying joint posterior distribution of resulting Markov chains. Since our study period starts with a large hospital outbreak, the outbreak simulation was initialized with one initial spillover case (i.e., 
 <italic>I</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub>(0) = 1) and also included a low number of exposed secondary cases (i.e. 
 <italic>E</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>s</italic>
 </sub>(0) = 5). Parameter estimates were not sensitive to these initial conditions.
</p>
