<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ART for HIV appears to benefit coinfected M/XDR-TB patients, and various studies have shown favorable outcomes.
 <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>–
 <xref rid="CIT0090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref> Treatment outcomes have been reported from different regions worldwide, with marked interregional variation. A systematic review and meta-analysis revealed a pooled treatment-success rate of 56.9% (95% CI 46.2%–67.6%): 49.9% (95% CI 38.5%–61.2%) among adults and 83.4% (95% CI 74.7%–92%) among children.
 <xref rid="CIT0089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref> That rate is almost similar to that reported among MDR-TB patients in general, regardless of HIV status. Mortality was 38% in adults (95% CI 28%–48.1%), and 11.4% (95% CI 5.8%–17.1%) in children.
 <xref rid="CIT0089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref> Mortality was higher for XDR-TB (82%) than MDR-TB (67%) with HIV coinfection. Another study from sub-Saharan African countries reported pooled cure and mortality rates of 34.9% and 18.1%, respectively.
 <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> MDR-TB and HIV–coinfected patients had more unfavorable outcomes than HIV-negative MDR-TB patients (RR 0.87, 95% CI 0.97–0.96). However, the pooled cure rate from the European region is even lower (16%).
 <xref rid="CIT0090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref> Factors responsible for the variable results are difference in populations affected, sample size, extent of disease burden, and quality of treatment services offered. Shorter regimens might show promising results, particularly in MDR-TB patients with HIV coinfection, but current evidence is sparse in programmatic settings.
 <xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref> A study from Africa reported a high level of success among HIV-positive patients with shorter regimens.
 <xref rid="CIT0091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref> Resistance to FQs, whether at baseline or acquired, was responsible for unfavorable outcomes. An important concern remains: whether an MDR-TB regimen will work in all settings, particularly outside trial conditions. Further research is required to assess its efficacy. The factors responsible for unfavorable outcomes were atypical clinical manifestations of TB and lack of rapid and sensitive genotypic tests, leading to delayed management and poor adherence to treatment. Adequate adherence to treatment remains challenging, because of the long and difficult treatment associated with M/XDR-TB and HIV coinfection; additional comorbid illnesses, such as diabetes mellitus, anemia, renal or hepatic failure, and other opportunistic infections; a higher pill burden resulting from the coadministration of anti-TB and ART drugs; and the potential for overlapping adverse events and drug–drug interactions. Other factors showing poor outcomes were advanced age, profound immunosuppression (CD4 count &lt;100 cells/cm
 <sup>3</sup>), unemployment, male sex, smoking, pregnancy, drug abuse, coinfection with hepatitis B or C, and a higher degree of drug resistance, including to second-line drugs.
 <xref rid="CIT0092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0093" ref-type="bibr">93</xref> High-burden countries do not have adequate infrastructure to detect or manage an outbreak. Outbreaks should be prevented to reduce the impact on mortality.
</p>
