<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To enhance 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> sustained-release characteristics, bioavailability and stability of anthocyanins, the nanocomplexes with chitosan hydrochloride (CHC), carboxymethyl chitosan (CMC) and β-Lactoglobulin (β-Lg) were provided. The results showed that nanocomplexes encapsulation significantly improved the stability and bioavailability of anthocyanins in simulated GIT (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Ge et al., 2019</xref>). In another study, to improve the physicochemical stability of anthocyanins, nanoemulsion and nanoliposome were prepared. According to the results, nanoemulsion and nanoliposome enhance the anthocyanin stability and biological activity (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Stephen Inbaraj, 2019</xref>). In this line, self-assembled nanoparticles were prepared by chitosan (CH) and chondroitin sulfate (CS) biopolymers to enhance the biological activity of black rice anthocyanin. The thermogravimetric analysis also proposed that the anthocyanin/CH/CS nanoparticles displayed high thermal stability. Significant increases in apoptosis by 12.1% and 35.1% were reported with 0.05 mg/ml anthocyanin and anthocyanin/CH/CS nanoparticles in the HCT-116 cell line, specifying that the nanoparticle system caused to considerable increase in apoptosis (
 <xref rid="B137" ref-type="bibr">Liang et al., 2019</xref>). In another study anthocyanins-loaded CHC/CMC nanocomplexes exhibited excellent stability against different temperature, different concentration of ascorbic acid, varying pH or white fluorescent light (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Ge et al., 2018</xref>). Another investigation evaluated the bioavailability of anthocyanins-loaded nanoparticles to overcome their poor bioavailability. Based on results, pH-sensitive polymer along with the hydrophilic polymer exhibited suitable delivery system for anthocyanins. The anthocyanins delayed release profile, found in all formulations, can improve their poor bioavailability (
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">Dupeyrón et al., 2017</xref>). Polymer-based nanoparticles are of other approaches to enhance the bioavailability of unstable hydrophilic drugs like anthocyanins. This approach is due to the improved bioavailability and high stability. Encapsulating anthocyanins in poly lactic-co-glycolic acid (PLGA)-polyethylene glycol (PEG) nanoparticles did not ruin its natural properties and showed more potent neuroprotective properties (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Amin et al., 2017</xref>). Altogether, the results suggest a practical approach to enhance the efficiency of anthocyanins in the form of nano-drug delivery systems.
</p>
