<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To date, more than 30 coronaviruses have been identified to infect various species including humans, pigs, casts, dogs, horses, poultry, camels, and other wild animals [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Wild animals, such as bats and rodents, are the natural reservoirs of coronaviruses, and they transmit them to the intermediate hosts of camelids, civets, dromedary camels, pangolins, or domestic animals. They sometimes are eventually transmitted to the human population, resulting in severe epidemics in humans, such as SARS and MERS [
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Recently, a pneumonia outbreak by SARS-CoV-2 was thought to have originated in bats [
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. This novel emerging coronavirus can efficiently replicate in ferrets and cats, but it replicates poorly in dogs, pigs, chickens, and ducks [
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Together, these data show that some coronaviruses are critical zoonotic viruses that can cause public health problems for humans, and they also notoriously affect the agricultural industry. Based on the genotypic and serological characterization of coronaviruses, they are divided into four main genera: (a) Alphacoronaviruses, which mainly include human CoV-229E, human CoV-NL63, porcine epidemic diarrhea virus (PEDV), and transmissible gastroenteritis virus (TGEV); (b) Betacoronaviruses, which mainly include severe acute respiratory symptoms coronavirus (SARS-CoV), Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV), severe acute respiratory symptoms coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), mouse hepatitis virus (MHV), and bovine CoV (BCoV); (c) Gammacoronaviruses are related to avian diseases, including infectious bronchitis virus (IBV) and turkey blue comb virus (TBV); (d) Deltacoronaviruses. Generally, Alpha and Betacoronaviruses invade mammalian hosts, whereas Gammacoronaviruses infect avian hosts. The Deltacoronavirus genus is a novel group of coronaviruses identified from pigs, one of which, porcine Deltacoronavirus (PDCoV), emerged in the USA, Korea, and China, resulting in huge economic losses in the pig industry [
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-12-01039" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].
</p>
