<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To achieve these results, we first developed a novel, within-host, theoretical model elucidating the effects of unique bat immunity, then undertook bifurcation analysis of the model’s equilibrium properties under immune absent, induced, and constitutive assumptions. We considered a cell line to be constitutively immune if possessing any number of antiviral cells at disease-free equilibrium but allowed the extent of constitutive immunity to vary across the parameter range for 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="inf65">
   <mi>ε</mi>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>, the constitutive rate of antiviral acquisition. In deriving the equation for 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="inf66">
   <mi>ε</mi>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>, the basic reproduction number, which defines threshold conditions for virus invasion of a tissue (
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="inf67">
   <mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0">
    <mrow>
     <msub>
      <mi>R</mi>
      <mrow>
       <mn>0</mn>
      </mrow>
     </msub>
     <mo>&gt;</mo>
     <mn>1</mn>
    </mrow>
   </mstyle>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>), we demonstrated how the invasion threshold is elevated at high values of constitutive antiviral acquisition, 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="inf68">
   <mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0">
    <mrow>
     <mi>ε</mi>
    </mrow>
   </mstyle>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>. Constitutive immune processes can thus prohibit pathogen invasion, while induced responses, by definition, can only control infections 
 <italic>post-hoc</italic>. Once thresholds for pathogen invasion have been met, assumptions of constitutive immunity will limit the cellular mortality (virulence) incurred at high transmission rates. Regardless of mechanism (induced or constitutive), interferon-stimulated antiviral cells appear to play a key role in maintaining longer term or persistent infections by safeguarding susceptible cells from rapid infection and concomitant cell death.
</p>
