<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Chikungunya epidemics have been mainly distributed in tropical and subtropical regions of Africa, Asia, and the Americas [
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Chikungunya spread in Tanzania, East Africa from 1952 to 1953 [
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] and in various other African and Asian regions between 1960 and 1982; a large-scale outbreak occurred in the Democratic Republic of the Congo [
 <xref rid="B8-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] in 1999–2000. Since 2004, it has been spread continually in Sri Lanka, the Maldives, Thailand, Malaysia, Singapore, India, Saudi Arabia, New Guinea, and islands in the Indian Ocean including Madagascar, the Seychelles, Comoros, Mayotte, and Réunion [
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. A severe outbreak occurred in the Gabonese Republic in 2007. In the same year, Italy was the first European country to which the disease spread; 205 confirmed cases were reported [
 <xref rid="B10-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. An outbreak occurred in Singapore in 2008. In October 2013, Micronesia became the first West Pacific island to have locally infected cases. In December of the same year, an outbreak took place in the Caribbean, marking the first locally infected cases in the Americas [
 <xref rid="B11-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In 2014, an outbreak started in the Pacific islands, including the Marshall Islands and Cook Islands. Chikungunya has spread to more than 60 countries in Asia, Africa, Europe, and the Americas [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. According to public data on the online platform of the Pan American Health Organization [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], 693,489 suspected cases of chikungunya were reported in the Americas in 2015, of which 37,480 were confirmed cases; the number of confirmed cases increased to 152,769 the following year. Chikungunya spread to Argentina for the first time in March 2016. In 2017, the number of confirmed cases in the Americas totaled 123,087, 98% of which occurred in Brazil; this indicated a high risk of chikungunya spread in the Americas. Since the March 2019 outbreak, Ethiopia has reported 20,000 cumulative confirmed cases. Infection occurs through bites by vector mosquitoes, mainly 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B15-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Individuals are infected by bites from mosquitoes carrying the chikungunya virus.
</p>
