<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par37">Pro-inflammatory cells, cytokines and chemokines amplify the vicious cycle of vessel coagulation and thrombosis, by acting to simultaneously activate the coagulation system and dampen anticoagulant mechanisms
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR154">154</xref>
 </sup>. Infiltrating, activated neutrophils (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>) produce large amounts of histotoxic mediators, including reactive oxygen species
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref>
 </sup>, as well as NETs, which have been found in arterial microthrombi in the post-mortem lung specimens from four deceased patients with COVID-19 (ref.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR155">155</xref>
 </sup>). The expression of tissue factor (TF) by activated monocytes stimulates the coagulation cascade and the subsequent generation of thrombin; these processes are ineffectually counterbalanced by tissue factor pathway inhibitor (TFPI), which is present in plasma and platelets, and produced mainly by endothelial cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR154">154</xref>
 </sup>. Concurrently, endothelial cell-associated anticoagulant pathways, in particular the protein C system, are impaired by pro-inflammatory cytokines
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR154">154</xref>
 </sup>. In response to activation by IL-1β and TNF, endothelial cells promote coagulation by expressing P-selectin, von Willebrand factor and fibrinogen, leading to massive platelet binding
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref>
 </sup> (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>). This process is further supported by the release of trophic cytokines by endothelial cells, which augment platelet production
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref>
 </sup>. The recruited platelets release VEGF, which amplifies the expression of TF by endothelial cells, further stimulating the coagulation cascade
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref>
 </sup>. Together, these events contribute to the increase in fibrin generation, inducing the deposition of blood clots in the microvasculature
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR154">154</xref>
 </sup> (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).
</p>
