<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Proteases have a crucial role in many signaling pathways and represent promising drug targets fora wide range of diseases, including viral diseases. A few protease blockers are currently under Phase 1, Phase 2, or Phase 3 clinical trials as potential drugs for treating COVID‐19 (Tables 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>). ASC09/Ritonavir, Lopinavir/Ritonavir, ASC09F + Oseltamivir, and Ritonavir + Oseltamivir are some protease inhibitor drug candidates that inhibit 3CLpro and prevent subsequent progression of replication (Table 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>). For example, monotherapy or combination of Lopinavir and Ritonavir has been studied against MERS‐CoV both in vitro and in an animal model and found to be effective (Chan et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; de Wilde et al., 2014). Studies showed that the combination of Lopinavir and Ritonavir with Ribavirin and Interferon alfa (IFN‐α) resulted in the survival of MERS‐patients through viral clearance (Kim, Won, Kee, Jung, &amp; Jang, 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0093" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). Some investigators are operating randomized, open‐label trials to evaluate and compare the efficacy and safety of Lopinavir and Ritonavir for COVID‐19 patients (Table 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-tbl-0003" ref-type="table">3</xref>). A recent case report claimed that a 54‐year‐old patient administered with lopinavir/ritonavir showed a significant reduction of viral loads with no or little coronavirus titers (Lim et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0111" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). A recent clinical trial (ChiCTR2000029308), however, showed that lopinavir–ritonavir treatment caused no benefit to hospitalized patients with severe COVID‐19 compared to standard care (Cao et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Treatment with lopinavir–ritonavir was not associated with time to clinical improvement, mortality at 28 days, detectable viral RNA, and gastrointestinal adverse events compared with the standard‐care group (Cao et al., 
 <xref rid="ddr21709-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). These contradictory yet promising findings highlight the importance of conducting clinical trials before using a drug as a therapeutic candidate.
</p>
