<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0030">Sections were dewaxed in Roticlear® (Roth C. GmbH &amp; Co. KG) and subsequently rehydrated in isopropanol and 96% ethanol (Roth C. GmbH &amp; Co. KG). Endogenous peroxidase activity was blocked by incubation of sections in 85% ethanol with 0.5% H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub> (VWRTM International GmbH) for 30 min at room temperature and antigen retrieval was performed by incubation in citrate buffer (2.1 g citric acid monohydrate in 1 l distilled water, adjusted with NaOH to pH = 6.0) for 20 min in a microwave (800 W). In a preliminary experiment two of the eight antibodies (1.10f3 and 1.2g5) were additionally tested without pretreatment and with enzymatic digestion by Proteinase K antigen retrieval solution (Merck KGaA) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. All sections were transferred to Shandon Coverplates™ (Thermo Electron GmbH) and nonspecific binding was blocked by inactivated 20% goat serum diluted in phosphate buffered saline (PBS) including 1% bovine serum albumin (BSA; PBS/BSA) for 30 min. Afterwards sections were incubated with the primary antibody (1.2g5, 1.6c7, 1.10f3, 1.6f9, 4.6e10, 7.7g6, 3.5g6, and 1.8e5) in their respective dilution (
 <xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) for 90 min at room temperature and the secondary biotinylated antibody diluted in PBS (1:200) was added. Incubation for 60 min at room temperature was followed by treatment with the avidin-biotin-peroxidase complex (Vectastain ABC Kit Standard, VectorLaboratories) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. Visualization of the reaction was achieved by addition of chromogen 3,3-diaminobenzidine tetrahydrochloride (DAB, 0.05%, Sigma Aldrich Chemie GmbH) and 0.03% H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>. Sections were finally slightly counterstained with Mayer’s hematoxylin (Roth C. GmbH &amp; Co KG). For positive control and elucidation of virus distribution, additional sections were stained with two different commercially available, previously published monoclonal mouse and polyclonal rabbit anti-MERS-CoV nucleocapsid antibodies (Sino Biological Inc.; 
 <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">Haagmans et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">Haverkamp et al., 2018</xref>), respectively. For negative controls, the primary antibody was replaced by ascites fluid from Balb/c mice (1:1,000) and normal rabbit serum (1:3,000), respectively. Moreover, all antibodies were applied to tissue of a non-infected alpaca (section 
 <xref rid="sec0020" ref-type="sec">2.2</xref>).
</p>
