<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0030">Social distancing and other public health interventions to combat the spread of COVID-19 may have immediate and longer-term effects on people with, or who are at risk of, psychosis. Statutory (health and social care) and non-government services that support and treat people with psychosis need guidance on how COVID-19 may impact on their services and the people that use them, and how they may respond accordingly. The World Health Organization (
 <xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">Tricco et al., 2017</xref>) advocates that rapid reviews are essential in providing informative summaries of these issues in such circumstances. We, therefore, aimed to undertake a rapid review of research on the impact of epidemics and pandemics on people with psychosis and the mental health services they use. Our review aimed to address the following questions related to living in a community exposed to an epidemic or pandemic:
 <list list-type="simple" id="l0005">
  <list-item id="li0005">
   <label>1.</label>
   <p id="p0035">Is there a change in the incident cases of psychosis/being identified as ultra-high-risk (
    <xref rid="bb0190" ref-type="bibr">Yung et al., 2004</xref>) of psychosis?
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="li0010">
   <label>2.</label>
   <p id="p0040">Are changes reported in the form and content of psychotic symptoms (i.e., do people incorporate beliefs about the virus into their symptoms)?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="li0015">
   <label>3.</label>
   <p id="p0045">Is there a change in demand for inpatient and community-based crisis services by people with psychosis?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="li0020">
   <label>4.</label>
   <p id="p0050">Is there a deterioration in the physical health of people with psychosis?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="li0025">
   <label>5.</label>
   <p id="p0055">Does the number of people with psychosis suiciding or attempting suicide change?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="li0030">
   <label>6.</label>
   <p id="p0060">Is there an increase in the number of people with psychosis who experience social issues such as homelessness, unemployment, domestic violence, and loneliness?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="li0035">
   <label>7.</label>
   <p id="p0065">How do people with psychosis experience the preventative measures put in place in pandemics (e.g. social distancing, increased handwashing)?</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
