<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During the study period, polymerase chain reaction (PCR) tests were performed at 4 different laboratory facilities: the joint Dakar Pasteur Institute and “Laboratoire du Projet des Fièvres Hémorragiques de Guinée” laboratory in Donka National Hospital; the European West African Mobile Laboratory (EUWAM-Lab) and the laboratory of “Institut National de Santé Publique (INSP)”, all located in Conakry, the capital city. The laboratory facility deployed by the Pasteur Institute (Lyon, France) within the ETU of Macenta analyzed samples from this area during the outbreak. The laboratory facilities from Macenta and EUWAM-Lab stopped activities soon after the epidemic ended, and the activities of the laboratory at Donka hospital were interrupted due to renovation of Donka Hospital. All samples have been processed at the INSP since September 2016. Each laboratory used their specific PCR methods, and, depending on availability of assays and laboratories where tests were performed, the following quantitative reverse-transcription PCR (qRT-PCR) assays were used: RealStar Filovirus Screen RT-PCR Kit 1.0 (Altona Diagnostics GmbH, Hamburg, Germany), 2 published in-house techniques targeting the viral nucleoprotein (NP) [
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], and 1 unpublished assay. For this latter assay, primers and probes described by Huang et al [
 <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] were adapted as follows: NP2F_ZR (forward primer) 5’-AGTACATGCAGAGCAAGGACTGATACA-3’, NP2R_ZR (reverse primer) 5’-GTTCGCATCAAACGGAAAATCAC-3’, and sNP2_ZR (probe) 5’-FAM-ATCCAACAGCTTGGCAATCAGTAGGACA-BHQ1-3’. For the qRT-PCR assays, RNA was extracted from 100 μL semen, urine, saliva, cervicovaginal fluid, and fecal samples with the QIAamp Viral RNA Mini Kit (QIAGEN, Hilden, Germany). To circumvent PCR inhibition due to seminal compounds, crude semen and seminal fluid were extracted separately when possible, and both extracts were tested undiluted and at 1:10 dilution. The qRT-PCR results are expressed as cycle threshold (Ct) values, with a Ct cutoff for positivity of &lt;41. All other samples were also tested undiluted and at 1:10 dilution to reduce impact of PCR inhibitors.
</p>
