<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The following reasons might contribute to the inconclusive results of Chinese herbs. Firstly, all the included trials were of poor methodology quality, which were in accordance with previous studies 
 <xref rid="pone.0028093-Tang2" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0028093-Liu5" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>. Only six RCTs stated randomization procedure, however, most of them provided insufficient information to judge whether randomization was conducted properly. For the rest fourteen trials, they just mentioned that ‘the patients were randomized into two groups’ with no further information. Allocation concealment was only mentioned in one RCT. Therefore, we could not exclude the possibility that some of these claimed RCTs are not real RCTs. This possibility came to forefront in the trial of Han 2011 and Li 2010 
 <xref rid="pone.0028093-Han1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0028093-Li2" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>; these trials only has one author, which is impossible for a RCT to be done properly in terms of randomization procedure and the allocation concealment. In addition, no trials claimed double-blind. We understood that it was difficult to perform double-blinding because of certain features associated with Chinese herbs, for example, aroma and appearance, but blinding to the outcome assessors and data analyzer could be feasible. Unfortunately, none of the RCTs mentioned blinding to the outcome assessors or data analyzer. All the trials did not report pre-sample size estimation except one 
 <xref rid="pone.0028093-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, and for majority trials, the sample size was small. Therefore we are not sure if they could provide enough power to detect the difference between groups. It is well known that methodologically poorly designed trials show larger differences between experimental and control groups than those conducted rigorously 
 <xref rid="pone.0028093-Kjaergard1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0028093-Moher1" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref> and as such the small improvements in outcomes should be regarded with caution.
</p>
