<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par40">In contrast, the influence of variations in viral genes to IAV virulence have been investigated in a number of ways. These included the generation of mouse-adapted IAVs through serial lung-to-lung passaging and recombinant IAVs harboring specific mutations using plasmid-based reverse genetic techniques combined with mutagenesis approaches. The application of these techniques has provided various insights about viral mutations involved in IAV virulence. For example, the increased virulence of IAV during its adaptation in mice has been associated with mutations in the region 190-helix, 220-loop and 130-loop, which surround the receptor-binding site in the HA protein (reviewed in [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]). Mutations in PB2 have also been considered to play a significant role in the increased IAV virulence in mice, which include mutations E627K and D701N that are considered as general markers for IAV virulence in mice [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Interestingly, a single mutation N66S in the accessory protein PB1-F2 could also contribute to increased virulence [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Mutations in multiple sites of a specific viral protein and mutations in multiple genes have also been shown to have a synergistic effect on IAV virulence in mice. For example, synergistic effect of dual mutations S224P and N383D in PA led to increased polymerase activity and has been considered as a hallmark for natural adaptation of H1N1 and H5N1 viruses to mammals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Another example is the synergistic action of two mutations D222G and K163E in HA and one mutation F35 L in PA of pandemic 2009 influenza H1N1 virus that causes lethality in the infected mice [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Furthermore, virulence may not only be encoded at protein level, but also at nucleotide and post-translational level. In a very recent study, synonymous codons were interestingly able to give rise different virulence levels [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. On the other hand, the HA N-linked glycosylation is known to affect viral virulence by impacting the host immune response (reviewed in [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]).
</p>
