<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As used in traditional and complementary medicine, the Lamiaceae family are used with outstanding antiviral activity (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Cohen et al., 1964</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Dimitrova et al., 1993</xref>), but there is still a lack of information regarding the antiviral effects of many plants of the Lamiaceae family (
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">Jassim and Naji, 2003</xref>). The Lamiaceae family, like sage, basil, and thyme, has long been assessed as a rich source of unique and diverse anthocyanins. Several anthocyanin structures were isolated, consisting of cyanidin and peonidin-based pigments, such as cyanidin 3,5-diglucoside, cyanidin 3-glucoside, cyanidin based, 
 <italic>p</italic>-coumaryl and malonyl acids, peonidin 3,5-diglucoside, peonidin 3-(
 <italic>p</italic>-coumarylglucoside)-5-glucoside and peonidin (aglycon) (
 <xref rid="B184" ref-type="bibr">Phippen and Simon, 1998</xref>). In their research study, Nolkemper et al. studied the activity of six species of the Lamiaceae family, including thyme (
 <italic>Thymus vulgaris</italic>), rosemary (
 <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis)</italic>, prunella (
 <italic>Prunella vulgaris)</italic>, peppermint (
 <italic>Mentha x piperita)</italic>, lemon balm (
 <italic>Melissa officinalis)</italic>, and sage (
 <italic>Salvia officinalis)</italic> against HSV. The inhibitory activities of phenolic compounds against HSV type 1 (HSV-1), type 2 (HSV-2), and HSV-1 acyclovir-resistant strain (ACV
 <sup>res</sup>) were assayed 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>, which indicated a high antiviral effect against three strains of HSV time-dependently. According to the results, the extracts had efficacy in anti-HSV before adsorption stage and, in contrast, had no efficacy in the replication stage (
 <xref rid="B173" ref-type="bibr">Nolkemper et al., 2006</xref>). Therefore, the results offer a chance to use the Lamiaceae family for therapeutic application against viral diseases like HSV.
</p>
