<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30">Although similar phylodynamic techniques as described above for other viral species were used to infer the spatial origins of CRF02_AG, the timing of the origin of this viral clade was inferred using both coalescent analysis of molecular sequence data and prevalence information [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>]. Coalescent models allow for estimation of the effective population size (
 <italic>Ne</italic>), of fundamental importance to infectious disease epidemiology, as it describes the level of genetic diversity within a population over the course of its evolutionary history. During the exponential growth period of an epidemic, the change in 
 <italic>Ne</italic> has been shown to linearly correlate with prevalence of infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>] and can, therefore, be used to estimate the latter, as mentioned above, but also, when combined, Faria et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>] were able to show that fitting of 
 <italic>Ne</italic> and prior prevalence data can narrow the uncertainty of the temporal origin estimates by over 29% as compared to coalescent estimates alone. Furthermore, surveillance data was recently used during simultaneous phylodynamic coalescent estimation to identify factors associated with 
 <italic>Ne</italic> dynamics throughout the entire evolutionary history of the Cameroonian sequences [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>], revealing that changes in 
 <italic>Ne</italic> were more reflective of incidence dynamics rather than prevalence, consistent with previous mathematical modeling [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>]. Although associations between 
 <italic>Ne</italic> and potentially related factors are frequently assessed, statistical analysis of these has until recently been primarily limited to 
 <italic>post hoc</italic> examination (e.g., [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>]), which ignores uncertainty in demographic reconstruction, as discussed above. Simultaneous implementation of evolutionary reconstruction and estimation of the relationship of covariate data with 
 <italic>Ne</italic> will be available in the newest version of BEAST v1 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>]. Although this tool has obvious implications for global assessment of factors contributing to the growth and dynamics of an epidemic, similar applications of this method to other data sets has suggested that reduced molecular data relative to covariate data may result in an impact of inclusion of the data on 
 <italic>Ne</italic> estimates. This finding posits a potential concern for convenience sequence sampling, as factors that are not responsible but are represented by large amounts of data may influence 
 <italic>Ne</italic> estimates, resulting in unreliable population dynamic inferences. As mentioned above, care is needed to ensure sufficient sampling and an appropriate sampling strategy for reliable reconstruction of the evolutionary and epidemiological history of the infectious organism of interest.
</p>
