<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The HA protein is the most important antigen in IAVs and plays a critical role in receptor binding and membrane fusion during virus entry, being an attractive target for developing vaccines and anti-IAV drugs [
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-11-00665" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-viruses-11-00665" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Based on sequence comparisons and structural characteristics, the HA subtypes are further divided into five clades that fall into two groups. Group 1 consists of subtypes H1, H2, H5, H6, H8, H9, H11, H12, H13, H16, H17, and H18, and Group 2 is composed of subtypes H3, H4, H14, H7, H15, and H10 [
 <xref rid="B11-viruses-11-00665" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The genetic similarity of HA amino acid sequences between the subtypes within each group is about 60–74%, while the similarity between different groups is only 40–44% [
 <xref rid="B10-viruses-11-00665" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Seasonal influenza vaccines are prepared in advance according to the recommendations issued by WHO, containing two IAV strains (H1N1 and H3N2) and one (trivalent influenza vaccine) or two (quadrivalent influenza vaccine) influenza B virus (IBV) strains. These vaccines usually become less effective when the vaccine virus strains do not match the circulating strain(s), particularly in the context of an influenza pandemic [
 <xref rid="B12-viruses-11-00665" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Several compounds have been shown to block virus infection as HA inhibitors, most of which, however, showed subtype-specificity. Inhibitors for Group 1 HAs include CL-61917, CL-385319, and CL-62554 [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00665" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], Stachyflin [
 <xref rid="B14-viruses-11-00665" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], BMY-27709 [
 <xref rid="B15-viruses-11-00665" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-11-00665" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], LY-180299 [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-11-00665" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], RO5464466 and RO5487624 [
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-11-00665" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], MBX2546 [
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-11-00665" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], and FA-583 and FA-617 [
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-11-00665" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], while TBHQ [
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-11-00665" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-11-00665" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], and S19 and C22 [
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-11-00665" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] are currently known inhibitors targeting group 2 HAs. Arbidol has been shown to have inhibitory effects against HAs of both group 1 and group 2. However, Arbidol is likely not an IAV-specific antiviral, since it is effective against a number of enveloped and non-enveloped viruses [
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-11-00665" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].
</p>
