<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Total RNA was extracted from the midguts of non-blood-fed and 24-hours post-blood-fed TADV-A, TADV-B, TADV-C or WT adult females using the Ambion mirVana mRNA Isolation Kit (ThermoFisher Scientific #AM1560). Following extraction, the RNA was treated with Ambion Turbo DNase (ThermoFisher Scientific #AM2238). The RNA quality was assessed using an RNA 6000 Pico Kit for Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies #5067–1513) and a NanoDrop 1000 UV-vis spectrophotometer (NanoDrop Technologies/Thermo Scientific, Wilmington, DE). mRNA was isolated using an NEBNext Poly(A) mRNA Magnetic Isolation Module (NEB #E7490), and libraries were constructed using an NEBNext Ultra II RNA Library Prep Kit for Illumina (NEB #E7770). The libraries were quantified using a Qubit dsDNA HS Kit (ThermoFisher Scientific #Q32854) and a High Sensitivity DNA Kit for Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies #5067–4626) and sequenced on an Illumina HiSeq2500 in single-read mode with a read length of 50 nt and sequencing depth of 30 million reads per library following the manufacturer's instructions. Reads were mapped to the 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> genome (AaegL5.0) supplemented with the 1C19 cDNA sequence using STAR aligner [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008103.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>], and the expression levels were determined with featureCounts [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008103.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1008103.s008">S4 Table</xref>). Correlation coefficients of the transcripts-per-million (TPM) values between WT and transgenic animals were calculated in R[
 <xref rid="ppat.1008103.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] and plotted with ggplot2 (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1008103.s001">S1 Fig</xref>). Differential expression analysis between transgenic and WT sample pairs of the same feeding status (NBF or PBM) for each line using DESeq2 [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008103.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] identified no significantly changed genes (padj &lt; 0.05) for all six comparisons (data not shown). To increase the sensitivity of the assay, two factor analysis using both NBF and PBM samples per line with design = ~ feeding + genotype was also performed and identified a number of differentially expressed genes for each line (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1008103.s009">S5 Table</xref>). However, expression of only nine genes was consistently altered in all three lines (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1008103.s010">S6 Table</xref>), suggesting that expression of the 1C19 scFv transgene had minimal impact on overall expression patterns of endogenous genes. All sequencing data can be accessed at NCBI SRA (study accession ID PRJNA524725).
</p>
