<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par9">Biological sex affects innate and adaptive immune responses to self and foreign antigens, resulting in sex differences in autoimmunity as well as in responses to infections and vaccines
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>. Immune cell subsets have sex-specific patterns of gene expression, with most differentially expressed genes found on autosomes, demonstrating sex-specific regulation of shared genetic material
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. The sex chromosomes also directly contribute. Males are at higher risk of diseases caused by deleterious X-linked alleles. Incomplete inactivation of immunoregulatory genes on the X chromosome can also occur in females, which results in a gene dosage imbalance between sexes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>. Incomplete X chromosome inactivation has been implicated in female-biased autoimmune diseases
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup> and in vaccine efficacy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. The Y chromosome has immunoregulatory function, broadly impacting immune transcriptional profiles linked to autoimmune disease
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup> and impacting outcomes of influenza virus and coxsackie virus infection in animals
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. Sex-specific features of epigenomic organization also dictate differential availability of transcriptional targets
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>. Superimposed on these genomic elements is the direct effect of sex steroid exposure. Oestrogens
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>
 </sup>, progesterone
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup> and testosterone
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>
 </sup> have direct effects on immune cell function that are driven by the signalling of these hormones through their respective cellular receptors. The variation in sex steroid concentrations that occurs over the life course contributes to differences in immune profiles and disease susceptibility patterns at different ages
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup>. Consistent with this variation, both sex and age contribute to unique transcriptional signatures of immune cells both at the baseline and after exposure to immunostimulants
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>. The summative effect is a sex-specific transcriptional regulatory network of genetic variants, epigenetic modifications, transcription factors and sex steroids that leads to a functional difference in the immune response
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>
 </sup>. Figure 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> highlights intersections between SARS-CoV-2 infection and sources of sex bias in pathophysiology that warrant further investigation.
</p>
