<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For the most commonly fed upon hosts, we collected data on various aspects of reproductive biology, including nesting phenology, birth dates, and male vocalizations for mate attraction. White-tailed deer (
 <italic>Odocoileus virginianus</italic>) fawning dates were obtained from herds on managed lands within 65 km of the mosquito collection site (2002–2003, 2005–2008). Alabama Division of Wildlife and Freshwater Fisheries personnel collected female deer using firearms and determined age (days) of fetuses, used to estimate date of parturition 
 <xref rid="pone.0017681-Hamilton1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. Cumulative births (number of available fawns) per semimonthly period were used in the analysis. The timing of great blue heron (
 <italic>Ardea herodias</italic>) nesting was determined by semiweekly observations of a heron rookery within the study site (2008–2009). Adult, juvenile and nestling herons observed in the rookery were counted at each visit until the rookery was abandoned each year (late June). Counts were then used to calculate the number of individuals occupying the rookery per semimonthly period. Nesting data for yellow-crowned night-heron, (
 <italic>Nyctanassa violacea</italic>), were obtained from the Cornell Lab of Ornithology, North American Nest-Record Card Program. The predicted number of chicks per nest per semimonthly period was calculated from historic nesting records from six southeastern states (Florida (northern counties only), Georgia, Louisiana, South Carolina, Tennessee and Texas) from 1976 to 1995. No records from Alabama were available. The presence of calling male frogs (males attracting mates) was determined from monthly visits (February – October) to five ponds within the study site in 2008 
 <xref rid="pone.0017681-USGeological1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. Detection/non-detection data were then used to model monthly detection probabilities using general linear mixed models 
 <xref rid="pone.0017681-Cunningham1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref> with a binomial distribution and a logit-link. Models were built using a stepwise procedure in which non-significant predictor variables (p &gt; 0.05) were sequentially removed 
 <xref rid="pone.0017681-Miller1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. Candidate variables included linear and squared terms for the month in which the observation was made. Modeling was performed using R 
 <xref rid="pone.0017681-R1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. Resulting monthly detection probabilities were used to categorize each frog species as either early breeder or late breeder. Mean detectability was then calculated for each breeding cohort. Frog species that were not detected in mosquito blood meals and which showed no significant changes in detectability across months were not used in the analysis. Months with fewer than five frog-derived blood meals (September and October) were not used in the analysis.
</p>
