<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The first conditional mutants of a non-defective avian sarcoma virus that are temperature-sensitive for their ability to transform cells in culture were isolated by Kumao Toyoshima. These mutants carried multiple mutations in replicative and oncogenic functions [
 <xref rid="B41-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Steven Martin then isolated a temperature-sensitive mutant that affected only oncogenic activity, delivering genetic evidence for a specific viral oncogene, later termed 
 <italic>src</italic> [
 <xref rid="B43-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. The existence of this oncogene could also be deduced from biochemical data. During the replication of cloned non-defective avian sarcoma viruses, derivative viruses are generated that are no longer oncogenic but reproduce and are fully infectious [
 <xref rid="B44-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. At high-virus dilution, they can be separated from the parental sarcoma virus and grown independently in the cell culture. They are transformation-defective. The size of their genome is smaller than that of the parental sarcoma virus. They have lost the specific viral gene encoding oncogenic activity [
 <xref rid="B45-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Temperature-sensitive mutants affecting oncogenicity map to the genome section that is deleted in the transformation-defective viruses [
 <xref rid="B46-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Oncogenic and transformation-defective avian sarcoma viruses are isogenic pairs, except for the deletion of the 
 <italic>src</italic> gene in the non-transforming derivative [
 <xref rid="B44-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Such isogenic pairs provide the opportunity to generate a specific probe for 
 <italic>src</italic> using subtractive hybridization with DNA transcripts of transforming and transformation-defective genomes. This 
 <italic>src</italic> probe showed that homologous sequences were present in the genome of normal avian as well as mammalian cells [
 <xref rid="B47-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Other retroviral oncogenes were also identified as cellular genes [
 <xref rid="B48-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. The cellular origin of oncogenes was a revolutionary discovery with far-reaching consequences. It showed that the genomes of normal cells encompass genes with oncogenic potential. In the ensuing years, the functional characteristics of these genes illuminated mechanisms of cellular signaling and regulation. This became the core of a genetic interpretation of human cancer [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-viruses-11-00080" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>].
</p>
