<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">In ZIKV infection, individuals should have adequate water intake, ample rest and treat pain and fever with liquid solutions. If the symptoms aggravate, they should look for counselling and therapeutic consideration (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). There are no specific medications or vaccine available to treat or prevent ZIKV infections until now; only medications for symptomatic relief can be considered such as paracetamol to relieve pain and fever associated with this infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) should be avoided and individuals should seek medical advice before taking additional medication if they are already taking medicines for another medical condition [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. Homeopathy is a worthy treatment option in ZIKV infection as it proved to be effective in Japanese encephalitis virus which is included in the same genus like Zika virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Treatment with belladonna efficaciously reduced the severity of Japanese encephalitis virus infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. 
 <italic>Atropa belladonna</italic> plant belongs to family Solanaceae [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. It has been effective in numerous medical conditions having great commercial significance as a major source of alkaloids, mainly scopolamine and hyoscyamine that are pharmaceutical bioactive compounds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. Belladonna is native to North Africa, Western Asia and Europe. In 
 <italic>Atropa belladonna</italic> majority of alkaloidal contents are present in ripe fruit and green leaves. It has been used from ancient times in order to treat various human ailments including menstrual disorders, headache, peptic ulcer, inflammation and histaminic reaction [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. Ultra-diluted belladonna concentrations like 1:10 or 1:100 are used in homeopathy and they are recommended for management of all the infectious diseases and illnesses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>].
</p>
