<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Viruses have been exploited as gene delivery vectors for many years owing to their highly evolved mechanisms for efficient delivery of genetic material to host cells (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Recombinant Adeno-Associated virus (rAAV) vectors have been modified to improve safety and are suitable vectors for clinical gene therapy (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). The ability of rAAV vectors to provide long term stable transgene expression in different animal cells, their low immunogenicity, and overall versatility, make them the vector of choice for 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> gene therapy (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>–
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). AAV-mediated delivery of broadly neutralizing human monoclonal antibodies against the HA stem has already been shown as a viable approach to protect from influenza (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). The intramuscular injection of AAV8 expressing the cross-subtype neutralizing human mAb F10 could protect young, old, and immunocompromised mice from influenza challenge through sustained expression in the systemic circulation for at least 11 months at levels between 150 and 200 μg/mL (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Similar studies have investigated the AAV-mediated delivery of another broadly neutralizing human mAb, FI6, which was shown to protect mice and ferrets from lethal influenza challenge. In this study FI6 was delivered intranasally which may be beneficial as this is the natural site of influenza infection (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Despite these findings, significant challenges remain for the successful development of vectored immunoprophylaxis for influenza. Although AAV is an excellent vector for gene therapy, it is still hampered by limitations to the size and complexity of antibody transgenes that it can express (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). This is a challenge for antibody gene therapy given that mAbs are large complex glycoproteins comprising four separate chains. As such, smaller, simpler binding molecules expressed from a single open reading frame would be a significant advantage (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>).
</p>
