<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0130">HIV, HBV and HCV are three blood-borne viruses that cause emerging infectious diseases in humans worldwide (
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Leoni et al., 2018</xref>). According to the WHO, viral hepatitis caused 1.34 million deaths in 2015, a number that is comparable to the number of annual deaths caused by tuberculosis and that is even higher than those attributed to HIV. A global hepatitis report concluded that mortality from HIV, tuberculosis, and malaria is now declining, while mortality from viral hepatitis has been increasing over time (
 <xref rid="bib107" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization, 2017</xref>). In the last report, the WHO estimated that in 2015, 257 million people, that is, 3.5% of the population, were living with chronic HBV infection. Individuals in the African and Western Pacific regions accounted for 68% of those infected. These individuals are at risk of developing severe complications, including cirrhosis and hepatocellular carcinoma. In 2015, hepatitis B resulted in 887,000 deaths, mostly due to complications. Among the 36.7 million persons living with HIV in 2015, an estimated 2.7 million had chronic HBV infection, and 2.3 million had been infected with HCV. Liver diseases constitute the major cause of morbidity and mortality among those living with HIV and coinfected with viral hepatitis. People with these conditions should be prioritized for diagnosis and provided appropriate and effective treatment for both HIV and hepatitis. Currently, HIV and HBV preventive strategies and treatment options are characterized by lifelong and chronic treatment, while for HCV, short-term and curative treatment is available. In contrast to HCV, for which a definitive cure has been developed because it does not persist in cells, the elimination of HBV and HIV infections worldwide is primarily hindered by their persistence in the host organism (
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Leoni et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
