<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0135">Several nucleos(t)ide-based therapies are currently approved for the treatment of chronic HBV infection (
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2018</xref>). Approved nucleos(t)ide inhibitors of HBV polymerase include lamivudine, adefovir, telbivudine, entecavir and tenofovir. Two of them, lamivudine and tenofovir, exhibit multi-target activity and are also approved as inhibitors of HIV replication (
 <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> ). This targeted HBV polymerase is functionally and structurally related to HIV reverse transcriptase, and in the case of both viruses, inhibitors act as chain terminators because they belong to the family of competitive substrate analogue inhibitors (
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Menéndez-Arias et al., 2014</xref>). According to the mechanism of action, the nucleos(t)ide analogue is converted into its active triphosphate form by cellular kinases. Then, the activated nucleos(t)ide inhibitor competes with natural nucleotide substrates for incorporation into the elongating viral DNA chain. The lack of a 3′-OH group in the incorporated nucleos(t)ide analogue prevents the formation of the 5′ to 3′ phosphodiester linkage essential for continued DNA chain elongation, and therefore, the viral DNA growth is terminated. Lamivudine (2′,3′-dideoxy-3′-thia-β-L-cytidine, 3TC) is an analogue of L-cytidine in which a sulphur atom replaces the 3′ carbon of the pentose ring. Tenofovir is an acyclic analogue of adenosine 5′-monophosphate and is marketed in the form of two prodrugs: tenofovir disoproxil (TDF, Viread) and tenofovir alafenamide (TAF, Vemlidy). The roles of the two prodrugs in the treatment and prophylaxis of HIV and HBV infections were comprehensively compared by De Clercq (
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">De Clercq, 2018</xref>). The tendency to substitute tenofovir disoproxil with tenofovir alafenamide in both anti-HIV and anti-HBV treatment has been reported, although both drugs pose little or no risk of virus drug resistance.
</p>
