<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Overall, the level of broadly reactive antibodies in infected or vaccinated individuals is low due to immunodominance of variable epitopes in the HA‐head region (Ellebedy 
 <italic>et al</italic>, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). However, substantial antigenic changes of the HA‐head region, for example as consequence of antigenic shift, can lead to the expansion of HA‐stalk antibodies, in which the stalk‐specific recall response outcompetes the 
 <italic>de novo</italic> response against the shifted head (Li 
 <italic>et al</italic>, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). Immunization strategies employing chimeric HA (cHA) or headless HA thus make use of this phenomenon (Steel 
 <italic>et al</italic>, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0076" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Hai 
 <italic>et al</italic>, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Li 
 <italic>et al</italic>, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Impagliazzo 
 <italic>et al</italic>, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Yassine 
 <italic>et al</italic>, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0093" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). However, since the production of these antigens either includes vaccine bulk production in eggs or requires technically challenging protein purification processes as well as adjuvants, alternative vaccine platforms offer an attractive development perspective (Ramezanpour 
 <italic>et al</italic>, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0070" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Grimm &amp; Buning, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Vaccinia‐ or adenovirus‐based vectors currently represent the most widely used platforms in clinical vaccine trials (Ramezanpour 
 <italic>et al</italic>, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0070" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). However, adeno‐associated virus (AAV) vectors might be particularly suited as influenza vaccine carrier, since AAV is naturally replication‐incompetent and apathogenic in humans, which was a prerequisite for licensure as the first gene therapy vector for use in humans (Grimm &amp; Buning, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). The “gutless” AAV vectors can be produced readily in cell culture according to good manufacturing practice criteria, avoiding some of the aforementioned limitations regarding vaccine production (Tripp &amp; Tompkins, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0079" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Also, AAV vectors are re‐administrable into the respiratory tract in the context of pre‐existing immunity without need to change the vector capsid (Limberis &amp; Wilson, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>). Intriguingly, AAV vectors have been used for passive immunization of mice and ferrets via expression of broadly reactive HA‐stalk antibodies in the respiratory tract (Balazs 
 <italic>et al</italic>, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Limberis 
 <italic>et al</italic>, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">2013a</xref>,
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">b</xref>; Adam 
 <italic>et al</italic>, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Laursen 
 <italic>et al</italic>, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). Furthermore, active vaccination with AAV vectors expressing internal (nucleoprotein (NP), matrix protein 1) and surface (HA) influenza virus antigens protected mice from challenge infection (Xin 
 <italic>et al</italic>, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0092" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>; Lin 
 <italic>et al</italic>, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Sipo 
 <italic>et al</italic>, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0074" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). In the absence of neutralizing antibodies against heterologous HA, the protection against a non‐matched influenza virus observed in that study was attributed to the presence of cross‐reactive T cells. However, the quality and influence on protection of non‐neutralizing antibodies were neither evaluated nor compared to an inactivated vaccine (Sipo 
 <italic>et al</italic>, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0074" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). Furthermore, immunization with AAV‐vectored cHA or headless HA antigens has not been tested, and there are no data as to the transferability of active AAV vector vaccination to the ferret model, thought to most accurately represent human influenza disease (Enkirch &amp; von Messling, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). A detailed knowledge of the effects of the AAV vector on the immune response is needed to advance the AAV vector vaccine approach toward clinical development (de Vries &amp; Rimmelzwaan, 
 <xref rid="emmm201910938-bib-0082" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>).
</p>
