<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A potential factor affecting the prevalence of viruses, regarding the risk of zoonotic transmission, is seasonal pulsing, or oscillations of prevalence, with peaks in prevalence at specific times of the year. Periods of higher risk are relevant to EU incursion as they will affect factors such as the probability of EU tourists contacting an infected bat and thus impact on routes such as human travel to and from NiV and MARV areas. Indeed, seasonal pulses of MARV circulation in juvenile 
 <italic>R. aegyptiacus</italic> bats coincide with periods of increased risk of human infection [
 <xref rid="B74-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. The influx of susceptible young is a crucial driver of infection dynamics and bat reproduction and survival are thought to be major drivers of bat disease dynamics [
 <xref rid="B97-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. Many bat species exhibit highly synchronised parturition which can dramatically alter population contact rates and susceptibilities. Sex differences in behaviour and distribution of bats during times of the year when the potential for disease transmission is greatest may also have important implications for disease dynamics [
 <xref rid="B97-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,
 <xref rid="B98-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. The role of bat torpor in infection dynamics is largely unstudied [
 <xref rid="B97-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. Torpor typically reduces pathogen replication rates and hence lengthens the incubation periods. A study found a clear indication for torpor being a key factor in allowing perpetuation of rabies virus through the hibernation period, through prolonged incubation period and reduced mortality [
 <xref rid="B99-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. This enabled the virus to persist in the population until susceptible individuals from the annual birth pulse could become infected and continue the cycle. Migration and coloniality may also be important drivers of disease dynamics [
 <xref rid="B97-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>], altered migration behaviour may result in declining immunity within specific colonies which could lead to more explosive HeV epidemics [
 <xref rid="B100-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>].
</p>
