<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>SARS‐CoV‐2 has strong transmission ability, and it has been occurred human‐to‐human transmission. The basic reproductive number (R
 <sub>0</sub>) of SARS‐CoV‐2 was estimated ~2.2 based on early patients and a subsequent study based on 75 815 individuals (from 31 December 2019 to 28 January 2020) estimated that R
 <sub>0</sub> was 2.68.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref> Recent study from the Los Alamos National Laboratory has collected extensive individual case reports and designed mathematical modelling, which calculated the median R
 <sub>0</sub> value as 5.7 (95% CI 3.8‐8.9).
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref> Therefore, the R
 <sub>0</sub> of SARS‐CoV‐2 is rising with the increased number of confirmed cases and so far it has exceeded the R
 <sub>0</sub> of MERS (R
 <sub>0</sub> = 0.6) and SARS (R
 <sub>0</sub> = 1).
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref> Scientists have predicted the trend of COVID‐19 development by studying its epidemic dynamics. It was indicated that Wuhan epidemic would peak around April 2020 and local epidemic across cities in mainland China would lag by 1‐2 weeks in a study.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref> In another study, researchers estimated the epidemic peak would be on 17 February 2020 in China and an obvious rise could occur from 25 to 29 February 2020 overseas.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref> Asymptomatic cases with COVID‐19 accounted for ~1% of the total number of patients and the viral load of asymptomatic patients was similar to that of symptomatic patients, which indicated that asymptomatic patients also had the potential to transmit virus.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref> SARS‐CoV‐2 is mainly transmitted by droplets, which invade the human body through contaminating the human conjunctival epithelium such as nose and eyes and cause infection.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref> In addition to droplet transmission, faecal‐oral spread is also a potential mode of transmission.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref> Although no studies have found COVID‐19 in newborns, specific antibodies have been detected in some newborns,
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>17</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref> which indicated the possibility of transmission from the mother to her baby. Due to the particularity of droplet transmission, close contact activities, such as family clustering, usually increase the possibility of infection.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref> To block the viral transmission by isolation, wearing masks and other ways of reducing close contact are recommended.
</p>
