<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Many factors contribute to enhance of the transmission intensity of dengue. For example, increasing population, international tourism, global trading, and uncontrolled urbanization are considered important factors that could explain the rapid global spatial spread of dengue [
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-17-01392" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-17-01392" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Additionally, regional expansion of the disease could be attributed to lack of public health infrastructure and inadequate knowledge about dengue fever [
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-17-01392" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-17-01392" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In the context of these socioeconomic factors, the interactions between three spheres, namely human, mosquito, and virus factors in a given country, need to be associated with suitable weather and climate conditions before dengue fever can be established [
 <xref rid="B8-ijerph-17-01392" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-17-01392" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. However, climate conditions do not directly influence the incidence of dengue. Instead, the larval development time, larval and adult survival, and duration of the gonotrophic cycle of the major dengue vector, 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>, are directly affected by climactic factors such as ambient temperatures, rainfall, and relative humidity [
 <xref rid="B10-ijerph-17-01392" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-ijerph-17-01392" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Many previous studies have indicated that meteorological parameters play an important role in increasing the risk of dengue transmission, depending on local ecology [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-17-01392" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-17-01392" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-17-01392" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-ijerph-17-01392" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-17-01392" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. As there is no effective vaccine against dengue fever, dengue vector control remains the key measure for the prevention of 
 <italic>Ae.-aegypti</italic>-transmitted diseases. Currently, the World Health Organization (WHO) recommends vector surveillance as a routine practice for predicting dengue outbreaks and evaluating disease control in dengue-endemic countries [
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-17-01392" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Using different statistical approaches such as regression coefficients, odd ratios, and rate ratios, many previous studies have provided evidence for positive correlations between vector indices (e.g., Breteau (BI), container (CI), and house indices (HI)) and human dengue cases [
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-17-01392" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-ijerph-17-01392" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-ijerph-17-01392" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. However, some studies have concluded that there is no significant correlation between vector indices and dengue [
 <xref rid="B21-ijerph-17-01392" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-ijerph-17-01392" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-ijerph-17-01392" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].
</p>
