<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While AI is a part of computer-aided drug design (CADD), this computational approach has been applied for drug discovery and repositioning for decades. The prime machine learning (ML) theories, such as the logistic regression (LR), naive Bayesian classifier (NB), k-nearest neighbors (KNN) algorithm, multiple linear regression (MLR), Gaussian process [
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and many more have relied on AI integration for the purposeful interpretation of drug repositioning opportunities [
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Today, the ML theory, accompanied by the advancement of AI, have moved forward to deep learning (DL) methods which promote stronger data processing accompanied by reliable results in the shortest possible time and with high cost-efficiency. For instance, with the use of the deep neural network (DNN), Ma and colleagues have successfully overcome a few limitations. As such, the difficulty in training and screening a large number of compounds accompanied by the improvement in the prediction accuracy of the quantitative structure-activity relationship (QSAR) method is essential for predicting on- and off-target activities in drug discoveries [
 <xref rid="B36-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. With that being said, drug–target interaction (DTI) identification is a critical aspect to look at in drug repositioning. The DTI in drug repositioning lies within the traditional ligand and structure-based methods which utilise the QSAR to predict biological activities of target molecules with the assumption of structurally similar molecules that give almost similar biological activities and authentic molecular docking imitations [
 <xref rid="B33-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. However, the limitations in these traditional computational methods draw attention to the DL methods. For instance, a DL based algorithm framework namely, the DeepDTIs, has successfully predicted new DTIs between approved drugs and targets accurately without the need to separate the targets into different classes. The DeepDTIs has also been proven to outperform the other ML methods such as the random forest [
 <xref rid="B37-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] and support vector machine (SVM). This approach provides a vast potential to be further used for new drug targets prediction based on existing targets, or new target interaction with existing drugs [
 <xref rid="B38-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].
</p>
