<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We revealed that DENV-induced phospholipidome reconfiguration is partially mediated by lowering 
 <italic>AGPAT1</italic> expression. Indeed, 
 <italic>AGPAT1</italic> was downregulated upon infection and its depletion partially recapitulated DENV-induced aminoPL reconfiguration both 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. That we only partially recapitulated the DENV-induced phospholipidome reconfiguration suggests that other enzymes, such as those directly producing and those hydrolyzing aminophospholipids [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008199.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], play a role. AGPAT enzymes can influence PL composition at several levels. By catalyzing the second acylation that produces PA (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat.1008199.g002">Fig 2A</xref>), AGPAT enzymes are responsible for a rate-limiting step in PL biogenesis [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008199.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. However, we did not observe PA reduction upon AGPAT1 depletion and instead reported an alteration of aminoPLs. This pattern was previously observed in hAGPAT-depleted human cells [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008199.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] and was attributed to compensation by other AGPAT isoforms. Lack of AGPAT1 may unbalance substrate competition with other isoforms with different lysoPA and acyl affinity [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008199.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Consequently, this can influence PA structure and subsequent PL composition. In addition, certain AGPAT isoforms can transfer acyls to lysoPL, thus, participating in PL remodeling independently of 
 <italic>de novo</italic> synthesis [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008199.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. In mosquito cells, AGPAT2 depletion also altered PL profile. However, 
 <italic>AGPAT2</italic> expression is not reduced by DENV infection and its depletion does not impact virus multiplication. The correlation between expression of 
 <italic>AGPAT</italic> isoforms and their impacts on infection indicates a fine regulation of metabolism by DENV, and identifies a new mechanism by which the virus hijacks the host phospholipidome.
</p>
