<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Gene Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Gene Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Gene Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2452-0144</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier Inc.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7452913</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2452-0144(20)30274-0</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.genrep.2020.100860</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100860</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>In silico</italic> structure modelling of SARS-CoV-2 Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 and repurposing of FDA approved antiviral drugs as dual inhibitors</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name><surname>Gurung</surname><given-names>Arun Bahadur</given-names></name><email>arunbgurung@gmail.com</email></contrib><aff id="af0005">Department of Basic Sciences and Social Sciences, North-Eastern Hill University, Shillong 793022, Meghalaya, India</aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>21</volume><fpage>100860</fpage><lpage>100860</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>14</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Elsevier Inc.</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="ab0005"><p>The high mortality rate from the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) infections in humans and the lack of effective therapeutic regime for its treatment necessitates the identification of new antivirals. SARS-CoV-2 relies on non-structural proteins such as Nsp13 helicase and nsp14 which are the key components of the replication-transcription complex (RTC) to complete its infectious life cycle. Therefore, targeting these essential viral proteins with small molecules will most likely to halt the disease pathogenesis. The lack of experimental structures of these proteins deters the process of structure-based identification of their specific inhibitors. In the present study, the <italic>in silico</italic> models of SARS-CoV-2 nsp13 helicase and nsp14 protein were elucidated using a comparative homology modelling approach. These <italic>in silico</italic> model structures were validated using various parameters such as Ramachandran plot, Verify 3D score, ERRAT score, knowledge-based energy and Z-score. The <italic>in silico</italic> models were further used for virtual screening of the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approved antiviral drugs. Simeprevir (SMV), Paritaprevir (PTV) and Grazoprevir (GZR) were the common leads identified which show higher binding affinity to both nsp13 helicase and nsp14 as compared to the control inhibitors and therefore, they might be potential dual-target inhibitors. The leads also establish a network of hydrogen bonds and hydrophobic interactions with the key residues lining the active site pockets. The present findings suggest that these FDA approved antiviral drugs can be subjected to repurposing against SARS-CoV-2 infection after verifying the <italic>in silico</italic> results through <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> studies.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="ab0010"><title>Graphical abstract</title><p><fig id="f0025" position="anchor"><alt-text id="al0105">Unlabelled Image</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="ga1_lrg"/></fig></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="ab0015"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="l0005"><list-item id="li0005"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0005">
<italic>In silico</italic> model structures of nsp13 helicase and nsp14 were elucidated.</p></list-item><list-item id="li0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0010">Structure-based virtual screening was performed using FDA approved antiviral drugs.</p></list-item><list-item id="li0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0015">SMV, PTV and GZR are the leads common for both Nsp13 helicase and nsp14.</p></list-item><list-item id="li0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0020">Needs further experimental studies for repurposing these drugs against SARS-CoV-2.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><kwd-group id="ks0005"><title>Abbreviations</title><kwd>3CL<sup>pro</sup>, 3C-like proteinase</kwd><kwd>COVID-19, coronavirus disease 2019</kwd><kwd>DOPE, discrete optimized protein energy</kwd><kwd>FDA, Food and Drug Administration</kwd><kwd>GpppA, Guanosine-P3-adenosine-5&#x02032;,5&#x02032;-triphosphate</kwd><kwd>GRAVY, grand average of hydropathicity</kwd><kwd>GZR, Grazoprevir</kwd><kwd>MERS-CoV, Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus</kwd><kwd>N7-MTase, S-adenosyl methionine (SAM)-dependent (guanine-N7) methyltransferase</kwd><kwd>Nsps, non-structural proteins</kwd><kwd>PDB, protein data bank</kwd><kwd>PL<sup>pro</sup>, papain-like proteinase</kwd><kwd>PTV, Paritaprevir</kwd><kwd>RdRp, RNA-dependent RNA polymerase</kwd><kwd>RMSD, root mean square deviation</kwd><kwd>RTC, replication-transcription complex</kwd><kwd>SAH, S-adenosyl homocysteine</kwd><kwd>SARS-CoV, severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus</kwd><kwd>SARS-CoV-2, severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2</kwd><kwd>SAVES, Structure Analysis and Verification Server</kwd><kwd>SF, Sinefungin</kwd><kwd>SMV, Simeprevir</kwd><kwd>TMHs, transmembrane helices</kwd><kwd>ZBD, zinc binding domain</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group id="ks0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>Nsp13 helicase</kwd><kwd>Nsp14</kwd><kwd>FDA approved antiviral drugs</kwd><kwd>Molecular docking</kwd><kwd>Homology modelling</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0025">The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) has posed a serious health emergency worldwide. There has been a total of 5,701,337 confirmed cases and 357,688 deaths due to COVID-19 till May 29th 2020 (WHO Situation report-130). Bats are considered to be the natural reservoirs of SARS-CoV-2 with pangolin as the intermediary host (<xref rid="bb0210" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2020</xref>). SARS-CoV-2 infections in humans were first reported in late December 2019 from Wuhan, China where the clinical symptoms showed resemblance to viral pneumonia (<xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2020</xref>). Coronaviruses have a history of causing severe epidemics such as the infections caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) during 2002&#x02013;2003 in Guangdong province of China with a mortality rate of 11% (<xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">Chan-Yeung and Xu, 2003</xref>) and the disease caused by the Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) in 2012 which emerged in Saudi Arabia with a fatality rate of 34% (<xref rid="bb0185" ref-type="bibr">Singhal, 2020</xref>). It has been around two decades since when the coronavirus has caused severe epidemics yet there is currently no clinical treatment available for coronavirus infections in humans to date (<xref rid="bb0220" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2020b</xref>).</p><p id="p0030">SARS coronavirus is an enveloped, positive-stranded RNA virus with the largest known RNA genome size of approximately 29.7&#x000a0;kb (<xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr">Marra et al., 2003</xref>). There are many aspects of SARS-CoV gene expression which is still yet to be understood at the transcription and translational levels (<xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">Adedeji et al., 2012a</xref>). Upon entry into the host cell, the virus initiates the synthesis of two large replicative polyproteins- pp1a and the pp1ab from the ORF1a and ORF1b respectively (<xref rid="bb0180" ref-type="bibr">Prentice et al., 2004</xref>). Subsequently, the virus-encoded papain-like proteinase (PL<sup>pro</sup>) and 3C-like proteinase (3CL<sup>pro</sup>) processes these polyproteins (<xref rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr">Thiel et al., 2003</xref>). The cleavage activity of these proteases leads to the release of 16 non-structural proteins (Nsps) which include Nsp12 (RNA-dependent RNA polymerase), Nsp13 (NTPase/helicase) and nps14 (<xref rid="bb0180" ref-type="bibr">Prentice et al., 2004</xref>). These proteins are the key components of replication-transcription complexes (RTC) indispensable for the life cycle of SARS-CoV (<xref rid="bb0205" ref-type="bibr">Van Hemert et al., 2008</xref>). The structural information about SARS-CoV-2 nsp13 helicase enzyme and nsp14 are poorly understood as the structure of both the proteins have not been elucidated till date and much of the information about them are derived from their corresponding structures from SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV. SARS-CoV Nsp13 helicase enzyme plays a key role in catalysing the unwinding of double-stranded oligonucleotides into single strands using energy derived from hydrolysis of NTPs (<xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr">Jia et al., 2019</xref>). Based on conserved motifs and the ability to unwind both RNA and DNA duplexes in the 5&#x02032; to 3&#x02032; direction, SARS-Nsp13 belongs to superfamily 1 (SF1) (<xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">Fairman-Williams et al., 2010</xref>). All natural nucleotides and deoxynucleotides can be targeted as substrates by the cognate NTPase activity of the helicase enzyme (<xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">Ivanov et al., 2004</xref>; <xref rid="bb0195" ref-type="bibr">Tanner et al., 2003</xref>). The sequence conservation and essentiality of the Nsp13 helicase enzyme across all coronaviruses have provided an opportunity to target this enzyme for the development of anti-viral drugs (<xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">Adedeji et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">Jang et al., 2008</xref>). Both MERS- and SARS-CoV Nsp13 has a triangular pyramid architecture and is composed of five domains. While the two domains including the N-terminal Zinc binding domain (ZBD) and the stalk domain are pointed towards the apex of the pyramid, the remaining three domains comprising of two &#x02018;RecA-like&#x02019; domains known as 1A and 2A and the 1B domain constitutes the triangular base of the pyramid (<xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr">Jia et al., 2019</xref>). The NTPase activity of the enzyme resides in a cleft located at the base between 1A and 2A domains and consists of six important residues such as Lys288, Ser289, Asp374, Glu375, Gln404 and Arg567 (<xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr">Jia et al., 2019</xref>). Four basic amino acid residues such as Arg337, Arg339, Lys345 and Lys347 positioned at the entrance of nucleic acid binding channel are critical for the unwinding activity of the helicase enzyme (<xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr">Jia et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p id="p0035">The other target protein chosen in the present study is the Nsp14 protein which is important for viral replication and transcription and is highly conserved within the Coronaviridae family (<xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">Becares et al., 2016</xref>). SARS-CoV Nsp14 is a bimodular protein with the proofreading 3&#x02032; to 5&#x02032; exonuclease activity in the exon domain (residues 1&#x02013;287) located at the N-terminal region and residues 288&#x02013;527 constitute the S-adenosyl methionine (SAM)-dependent (guanine-N7) methyltransferase (N7-MTase) domain located at the C-terminal region (<xref rid="bb0140" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al., 2015</xref>). While the exon domain confers replication fidelity of RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp) by excising mismatched nucleotides during RNA biosynthesis process (<xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">Denison et al., 2011</xref>), the N7-MTase domain helps in assembly of 5&#x02032; viral mRNA cap structure by addition of a methyl group to the cap guanosine at the N7 position which is essential for the stability of mRNAs, translation process and evading host defence (<xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">Becares et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">Decroly et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr">Marcotrigiano et al., 1997</xref>). The N7-MTase domain contains binding pockets for the substrates-S-adenosyl homocysteine (SAH) and Guanosine-P3-adenosine-5&#x02032;,5&#x02032;-triphosphate (GpppA) wherein residues Trp292, Asp331, Gly333, Pro335, Lys336, Asp352 and Val389 are important for SAH binding and GpppA binding pocket consists of residues-Asn306, Arg310, Trp385, Asn386, Phe401, Leu419, Tyr420, Asn422, Lys423, Phe426, Thr428, Phe506 (<xref rid="bb0140" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al., 2015</xref>). Since Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 are important target proteins playing a key role in the transcription and replication processes. The structures of the proteins are not available in the protein data bank. In the present study, comparative homology modelling was used to decipher the structures of the target proteins and these <italic>in silico</italic> models were further used for virtual screening of FDA approved drugs and few potential inhibitors were identified which can inhibit the activity of Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 and these molecules could be applied as dual-target inhibitors.</p></sec><sec id="s0010"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s0015"><label>2.1</label><title>Retrieval of protein sequences</title><p id="p0040">The SARS-CoV-2 replicase polyprotein 1ab (pp1ab) amino acid sequence was retrieved from UniProt Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.uniprot.org/" id="ir0005">https://www.uniprot.org/</ext-link>) using the accession ID: P0DTD1 where the residues 5325&#x02013;5925 corresponds to Nsp13 helicase and residues 5926&#x02013;6452 belongs to the Nsp14. The amino acid sequences of both Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 were saved in FASTA format for further <italic>in silico</italic> studies.</p></sec><sec id="s0020"><label>2.2</label><title>Sequence homology with <italic>Homo sapiens</italic></title><p id="p0045">The sequences of the target proteins were analysed for homology against the human proteome using standard protein basic local alignment search tool (BLASTp) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi" id="ir0010">https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi</ext-link>). The BLAST parameters include- maximum target sequences of 100, word size of 6, expect (E) threshold value of 10 and BLOSUM62 as a substitution scoring matrix. The database was set as &#x0201c;non-redundant protein sequence (nr)&#x0201d; and the organism as &#x0201c;<italic>Homo sapiens</italic>&#x0201d; with taxid: 9606.</p></sec><sec id="s0025"><label>2.3</label><title>Prediction of secondary structure elements</title><p id="p0050">Garnier-Osguthorpe-Robson (GOR) IV secondary structure prediction method was used to determine the secondary structure elements of Nsp13 and Nsp14 using their respective amino acid sequences. The prediction of protein secondary structure elements by GOR IV is based on information theory and Bayesian statistics (<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">Garnier et al., 1978</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0030"><label>2.4</label><title>Prediction of transmembrane helices</title><p id="p0055">The transmembrane helices in the target proteins were predicted using TMHMM server version 2.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TMHMM/" id="ir0015">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TMHMM/</ext-link>) which uses a hidden Markov model algorithm to predict the topology of a protein (<xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">Krogh et al., 2001</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0035"><label>2.5</label><title>Determination of physicochemical properties of Nsp13 helicase enzyme</title><p id="p0060">The physicochemical properties of the proteins such as molecular weight, theoretical isoelectric point (pI), extinction coefficient, estimate half-life, instability index, aliphatic index, grand average of hydropathicity (GRAVY) were calculated using ExPASy ProtParam tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://web.expasy.org/protparam/" id="ir0020">https://web.expasy.org/protparam/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s0040"><label>2.6</label><title><italic>In silico</italic> homology modelling</title><p id="p0065">Due to the absence of the three-dimensional structure of SARS-CoV-2 helicase and Nsp14 in protein data bank (PDB), their structure models were deciphered using a comparative homology modelling approach. Suitable template structures were identified by performing protein BLAST using the SARS-CoV-2 as query protein against PDB database. The template showing &#x02265;95% of similarity to the query protein with 100% query coverage was selected for homology modelling studies. The structure of the template was extracted from protein data bank. The <italic>in silico</italic> model structures of Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 were generated using MODELLER 9.22 program (<xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">Eswar et al., 2006</xref>). The MODELLER program uses an automated approach for comparative modelling of protein structures by the satisfaction of spatial restraints (<xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">Eswar et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">Fiser and &#x00160;ali, 2003</xref>). A total of five <italic>in silico</italic> models for each target was build and the structures were saved in PDB format. The conformations of loop regions in model structures were predicted using an <italic>ab initio</italic> method implemented in MODELLER program. The predicted structures were ranked according to MOLPDF value, DOPE score and GA341 score. The best structure was selected having both the lowest MOLPDF and DOPE scores and GA341 score close to 1. The structure was optimized further by energy minimization <italic>in vacuo</italic> with GROMOS96 43 B1 parameters using Swiss-PdbViewer version 4.1.0 (<xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">Guex and Peitsch, 1997</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0045"><label>2.7</label><title>Model validations</title><p id="p0070">The quality of the model structures was evaluated by comparing Ramachandran plot (checks the stereochemical quality of a protein structure), ERRAT score (evaluates the statistics of non-bonded interactions between different atom types), Verify 3D score (analyses the compatibility of an atomic 3D model with its own amino acid sequence) and ProSA knowledge-based energy plot (the plot evaluates model quality by plotting energies as a function of amino acid sequence position) and <italic>Z</italic>-score (indicates the overall model quality) with their respective template structures. The first three parameters were calculated using Structure Analysis and Verification Server (SAVES) version 5.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://servicesn.mbi.ucla.edu/SAVES/" id="ir0025">https://servicesn.mbi.ucla.edu/SAVES/</ext-link>) and the two last parameters were determined using Protein Structure Analysis (ProSA)-web server (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://prosa.services.came.sbg.ac.at/prosa.php" id="ir0030">https://prosa.services.came.sbg.ac.at/prosa.php</ext-link>) by submitting the model and template structures in PDB format.</p></sec><sec id="s0050"><label>2.8</label><title>Structure superimposition and structure-based sequence alignment</title><p id="p0075">The root mean square deviation between the model structure and template structure and the structure-based sequence alignment were performed by superposing the two structures using the comparative module of UCSF Chimera version 1.14 (<xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">Pettersen et al., 2004</xref>). The alignment algorithm used in the study is Needleman-Wunsch with BLOSUM-62 as the scoring matrix.</p></sec><sec id="s0055"><label>2.9</label><title>Retrieval of FDA approved antiviral drugs</title><p id="p0080">The three-dimensional structures of 54 FDA approved antiviral drugs (<xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">De Clercq and Li, 2016</xref>) (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
) and the control inhibitors-SSYA 10-001, SSYA 10-002, Myricetin, Scutellarein and Sinefungin were downloaded from Pubchem database (<xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2016</xref>) in SDF format. The drugs lacking the 3D structure were converted into the 3D structure using OpenBabel version 2.4.1 (<xref rid="bb0170" ref-type="bibr">O'Boyle et al., 2011</xref>) and optimized using MMFF94 force field (<xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">Halgren, 1996</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of 54 FDA approved antiviral drugs selected for molecular docking studies.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0025">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Drugs</th><th>Abbreviation</th><th>PubChem ID</th><th>Inhibitors class</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Idoxuridine</td><td>IDU</td><td>5905</td><td rowspan="3">5-Substituted 2&#x02032;-deoxyuridine analogues</td></tr><tr><td>Trifluridine</td><td>TFT</td><td>6256</td></tr><tr><td>Brivudine</td><td>BVDU</td><td>446727</td></tr><tr><td>Vidarabine</td><td>VDR</td><td>21704</td><td rowspan="3">Nucleoside analogues</td></tr><tr><td>Entecavir</td><td>ETV</td><td>135398508</td></tr><tr><td>Telbivudine</td><td>LdT</td><td>159269</td></tr><tr><td>Foscarnet</td><td>PFA</td><td>3415</td><td>Pyrophosphate analogues</td></tr><tr><td>Zidovudine</td><td>AZT</td><td>35370</td><td rowspan="7">Nucleoside reverse transcriptase (RT) inhibitors (NRTIs)</td></tr><tr><td>Didanosine</td><td>ddI</td><td>135398739</td></tr><tr><td>Zalcitabine</td><td>ddC</td><td>24066</td></tr><tr><td>Stavudine</td><td>d4T</td><td>18283</td></tr><tr><td>Lamivudine</td><td>3TC</td><td>60825</td></tr><tr><td>Abacavir</td><td>ABC</td><td>441300</td></tr><tr><td>Emtricitabine</td><td>(&#x02212;)FTC</td><td>60877</td></tr><tr><td>Nevirapine</td><td>NVP</td><td>4463</td><td rowspan="5">Nonnucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NNRTIs)</td></tr><tr><td>Delavirdine</td><td>DLV</td><td>5625</td></tr><tr><td>Efavirenz</td><td>EFV</td><td>64139</td></tr><tr><td>Etravirine</td><td>ETR</td><td>193962</td></tr><tr><td>Rilpivirine</td><td>RPV</td><td>6451164</td></tr><tr><td>Saquinavir</td><td>SQV</td><td>441243</td><td rowspan="15">Protease inhibitors</td></tr><tr><td>Ritonavir</td><td>RTV</td><td>392622</td></tr><tr><td>Indinavir</td><td>IDV</td><td>5362440</td></tr><tr><td>Nelfinavir</td><td>NFV</td><td>64143</td></tr><tr><td>Amprenavir</td><td>APV</td><td>65016</td></tr><tr><td>Atazanavir</td><td>ATV</td><td>148192</td></tr><tr><td>Fosamprenavir</td><td>FPV</td><td>131536</td></tr><tr><td>Tipranavir</td><td>TPV</td><td>54682461</td></tr><tr><td>Darunavir</td><td>DRV</td><td>213039</td></tr><tr><td>Telaprevir</td><td>TVR</td><td>3010818</td></tr><tr><td>Boceprevir</td><td>BOC</td><td>10324367</td></tr><tr><td>Simeprevir</td><td>SMV</td><td>24873435</td></tr><tr><td>Asunaprevir</td><td>ASV</td><td>16076883</td></tr><tr><td>Paritaprevir</td><td>PTV</td><td>45110509</td></tr><tr><td>Grazoprevir</td><td>GZR</td><td>44603531</td></tr><tr><td>Raltegravir</td><td>RAL</td><td>54671008</td><td rowspan="3">Integrase inhibitors</td></tr><tr><td>Elvitegravir</td><td>EVG</td><td>5277135</td></tr><tr><td>Dolutegravir</td><td>DTG</td><td>54726191</td></tr><tr><td>Docosanol</td><td>C22</td><td>12620</td><td rowspan="2">Entry inhibitors</td></tr><tr><td>Maraviroc</td><td>MVC</td><td>3002977</td></tr><tr><td>Acyclovir</td><td>ACV</td><td>135398513</td><td rowspan="6">Acyclic guanosine analogues</td></tr><tr><td>Ganciclovir</td><td>GCV</td><td>135398740</td></tr><tr><td>Famciclovir</td><td>FCV</td><td>3324</td></tr><tr><td>Valacyclovir</td><td>VACV</td><td>135398742</td></tr><tr><td>Penciclovir</td><td>PCV</td><td>135398748</td></tr><tr><td>Valganciclovir</td><td>VGCV</td><td>135413535</td></tr><tr><td>Cidofovir</td><td>CDV</td><td>60613</td><td>Acyclic nucleoside phosphonate analogues</td></tr><tr><td>Amantadine</td><td>AMT</td><td>2130</td><td rowspan="8">Influenza virus inhibitors</td></tr><tr><td>Ribavirin</td><td>RBV</td><td>37542</td></tr><tr><td>Rimantadine</td><td>RIM</td><td>5071</td></tr><tr><td>Zanamivir</td><td>ZAN</td><td>60855</td></tr><tr><td>Oseltamivir</td><td>OTV</td><td>65028</td></tr><tr><td>Laninamivir octanoate</td><td>LO</td><td>9847629</td></tr><tr><td>Peramivir</td><td>PRV</td><td>154234</td></tr><tr><td>Favipiravir</td><td>FPV</td><td>492405</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0060"><label>2.10</label><title>Preparation of protein and compounds</title><p id="p0085">The compounds were prepared for docking by addition of Gasteiger charges, hydrogen atoms and assignment of torsions. The proteins were prepared for docking by addition of polar hydrogen atoms and Kollman charges. Both the proteins and ligand files were saved as PDBQT files.</p></sec><sec id="s0065"><label>2.11</label><title>Protein-ligand interaction studies</title><p id="p0090">Each drug molecule along with the control inhibitors was docked into the active site pocket of Nsp13 helicase enzyme and Nsp14 protein using AutoDock 4.2 (<xref rid="bb0165" ref-type="bibr">Morris et al., 2009</xref>). A grid box with xyz coordinates of 411.902, 36.890 and 63.540, number of grid points of 70&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;70&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;70 and grid point spacing of 0.375&#x000a0;&#x000c5; was used for Nsp13 helicase enzyme whereas in case of Nsp14 the grid box was centred at x: &#x02212;8.5767 y: &#x02212;44.469, z: &#x02212;5.2724 with number of grid points of 70&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;70&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;70 and grid point spacing of 0.375&#x000a0;&#x000c5;. The molecular docking was carried out using Lamarckian genetic algorithm (LGA) with the parameters specified as follows- a) An initial population size of 150 individuals, maximum number of 2,500,000 energy evaluations, the maximum number of 27,000 generations, the gene mutation rate of 0.02 and cross over rate of 0.8 with number of 50 GA runs. The conformations were clustered based on root mean square deviation (RMSD) cut off value of 2.0. The most favourable binding conformation was selected based on the lowest binding energy and lowest inhibition constant values. The nature of molecular interactions between the ligand and the enzyme was studied using LigPlot+ version 1.4.5 program (<xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">Laskowski and Swindells, 2011</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0070"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="s0075"><label>3.1</label><title>Sequence homology of the target proteins against the human proteome</title><p id="p0095">The sequences of SARS-CoV-2 Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 protein were evaluated for homology against human proteome. No significant-high similar hit was obtained for Nsp13 helicase and the nearest homologous protein was found to be Zinc Finger GRF-Type Containing 1 (ZGRF1) isoform X10 which shows low identity (22.41%) in the DNA2 superfamily domain and low query coverage (34%) with the query protein (Suppl. Fig. 1A). The blast results of Nsp14 did not show any significant hits (Suppl. Fig. 1B). Thus, both Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 protein can be targeted with small-molecule inhibitors which are highly likely to show minimum cross-reactivity with the human proteins.</p></sec><sec id="s0080"><label>3.2</label><title>Secondary structure analysis</title><p id="p0100">Secondary structure analysis for Nsp13 helicase enzymes shows that 17.64%, 26.29% and 56.07% of residues are present in alpha helix, extended strand and random coil respectively (Suppl. Table 1). In the case of Nsp14 protein, 13.85%, 29.79% and 56.36% of residues are present in alpha helix, extended strand and random coil respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s0085"><label>3.3</label><title>TMHMM prediction</title><p id="p0105">The number of predicted transmembrane helices (TMHs) in Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 was found to be none and the expected number of amino acids in TMHs were found to be 0.0107 and 0.79382 for Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 respectively (Suppl. Fig. 2A&#x02013;B, Suppl. Table 2). The expected number of amino acids in TMHs in the first 60 amino acids were 0.00055 and 0.00095 for Nsp13 helicase and nsp14 respectively. The total probability that the N-terminus is on the cytoplasmic side of the membrane was found to be 0.00101 and 0.00313 for Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 respectively. The topology of both the proteins was predicted to be outside which indicates that there are no transmembrane helices in both the target proteins.</p></sec><sec id="s0090"><label>3.4</label><title>Physiochemical characteristics</title><p id="p0110">The physicochemical properties of Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 proteins are enumerated in <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
. The molecular weight for Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 was calculated to be 66.85&#x000a0;kDa and 59.82&#x000a0;kDa respectively. Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 have a theoretical isoelectric point (pI) of 8.66 and 7.80 respectively which indicates that the surface of both the proteins is positively charged (basic). The number of negatively charged residues (Asp and Glu) in Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 was found to be 52 and 50 respectively whereas the number of positively charged residues (Arg and Lys) present in Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 were 64 and 52 respectively. The extinction coefficient values of Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 were found to be 68,785&#x000a0;M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 93,625&#x000a0;M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> respectively measured in water at 280&#x000a0;nm and with the assumption that all pairs of Cys residues form cysteines. The estimated half-life of both the proteins was predicted to be 4.4&#x000a0;h in mammalian reticulocytes <italic>in vitro</italic>, &#x0003e;20&#x000a0;h in yeast <italic>in vivo</italic> and &#x0003e;10&#x000a0;h in <italic>Escherichia coli in vivo</italic>. Both Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 protein were found to be stable with an instability index of 33.31 and 28.85 respectively. An aliphatic index of 84.49 and 78.96 was found for Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 respectively. The aliphatic index of a protein gives an idea about the relative volume occupied by amino acids having aliphatic side chain structures such as Ala, Val, Leu and Ile (<xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">Ikai, 1980</xref>). The grand average of hydropathicity (GRAVY) which is the ratio between the summation of hydropathy values of each amino acid residues and the length of the sequence (<xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Kyte and Doolittle, 1982</xref>). The GRAVY values for Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 were calculated to be &#x02212;0.096 and &#x02212;0.134 respectively which means the target proteins are relatively hydrophilic.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0010"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Physico-chemical properties of SARS-CoV-2 Nsp13 helicase and SARS-CoV-2 Nsp14 protein.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0030">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Physico-chemical properties</th><th>SARS-CoV-2 Nsp13 helicase</th><th>SARS-CoV-2 Nsp14</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>No. of amino acids</td><td>601</td><td>527</td></tr><tr><td>Molecular weight (kDa)</td><td>66.85</td><td>59.82</td></tr><tr><td>Theoretical pI</td><td>8.66</td><td>7.80</td></tr><tr><td>Total number of negatively charged residues (Glu&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;Asp)</td><td>52</td><td>50</td></tr><tr><td>Total number of positively charged residues (Lys&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;Arg)</td><td>64</td><td>52</td></tr><tr><td>Extinction coefficient assuming all pairs of Cys residues form cystines (M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td>68,785</td><td>93,625</td></tr><tr><td>Extinction coefficient assuming all pairs of Cys residues are reduced (M<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>&#x000a0;cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td>67,160</td><td>92,250</td></tr><tr><td>Estimated half-life</td><td>4.4&#x000a0;h (mammalian reticulocytes, <italic>in vitro</italic>)<break/>&#x0003e;20&#x000a0;h (yeast, <italic>in vivo</italic>)<break/>&#x0003e;10&#x000a0;h (<italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, in vivo)</td><td>4.4&#x000a0;h (mammalian reticulocytes, <italic>in vitro</italic>)<break/>&#x0003e;20&#x000a0;h (yeast, <italic>in vivo</italic>)<break/>&#x0003e;10&#x000a0;h (Escherichia coli, in vivo)</td></tr><tr><td>Instability index</td><td>33.31 (stable)</td><td>28.85 (unstable)</td></tr><tr><td>Aliphatic index</td><td>84.49</td><td>78.96</td></tr><tr><td>Grand average of hydropathicity (GRAVY)</td><td>&#x02212;0.096</td><td>&#x02212;0.134</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0095"><label>3.5</label><title>Structure modelling of nsp13 helicase enzyme and nsp14</title><p id="p0115">The experimental structure of SARS-CoV-2 Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 have not been reported to date which are the major deterrents in the structure-based discovery of inhibitors. In the present study, three dimensional <italic>in silico</italic> model of the target proteins were deciphered using a comparative homology modelling approach. This approach uses the search for the most similar structure to the query sequence. Based on the BLASTp results against PDB database, the most suitable template for <italic>in silico</italic> modelling was found to be the X-ray crystal structure of Nsp13 helicase protein from SARS-CoV which shows percent identity of 98.50%, query coverage of 100% and E-value of 0.0 (Suppl. Fig. 3A). Out of five <italic>in silico</italic> models, Model 5 was chosen to be the best structure for further studies since it has the lowest MOLPDF value (4498.63232), low discrete optimized protein energy (DOPE) score (&#x02212;63,878.37500) and GA341 score of 1 (<xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>
). A GA341 score of 1 indicates that the model has a correctly folded structure similar to native conformation of the protein. A reliable model usually has the lowest MOLPDF score, lowest DOPE score and GA341 score close to 1. Similarly, the <italic>in silico</italic> model for Nsp14 protein was constructed using homology modelling approach and the most suitable template identified was the X-ray crystal structure of the SARS coronavirus Nsp14 with a resolution of 3.33&#x000a0;&#x000c5;. The template structure has a total score of 1071, query coverage of 100%, E-value of 0.0 and identity of 95.07% with the query sequence (Suppl. Fig. 3B). Out of five <italic>in silico</italic> models, model 1 was chosen to be the best structure which exhibits the lowest MOLPDF value (3168.02441), lowest DOPE score (&#x02212;57,913.47656) and GA341 score of 1 (<xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0015"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The top 5 models of SARS-CoV-2 Nsp13 helicase and SARS-CoV-2 Nsp14 generated by MODELLER 9.22 program.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0035">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Model</th><th colspan="3">SARS-CoV-2 Nsp13 helicase<hr/></th><th colspan="3">SARS-CoV-2 Nsp14<hr/></th></tr><tr><th>MOL PDF</th><th>DOPE score</th><th>GA341 score</th><th>MOL PDF</th><th>DOPE score</th><th>GA341 score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td align="char">4671.77832</td><td align="char">&#x02212;63,483.94922</td><td align="char">1.00000</td><td align="char">3168.02441</td><td align="char">&#x02212;57,913.47656</td><td align="char">1.00000</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td align="char">4705.85107</td><td align="char">&#x02212;63,925.37109</td><td align="char">1.00000</td><td align="char">3218.28516</td><td align="char">&#x02212;57,498.24609</td><td align="char">1.00000</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td align="char">4710.93066</td><td align="char">&#x02212;63,588.42578</td><td align="char">1.00000</td><td align="char">3394.02734</td><td align="char">&#x02212;57,235.86719</td><td align="char">1.00000</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td align="char">4666.35889</td><td align="char">&#x02212;63,838.10156</td><td align="char">1.00000</td><td align="char">3232.29370</td><td align="char">&#x02212;57,363.0000</td><td align="char">1.00000</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td align="char">4498.63232</td><td align="char">&#x02212;63,878.37500</td><td align="char">1.00000</td><td align="char">3340.44995</td><td align="char">&#x02212;57,343.57813</td><td align="char">1.00000</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0100"><label>3.6</label><title>Model evaluations</title><p id="p0120">The <italic>in silico</italic> model structures was optimized using GROMOS96 43 B1 force field and the energy of the final Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 model structure was found to be &#x02212;23,828.428&#x000a0;kJ/mol and &#x02212;19,511.188&#x000a0;kJ/mol respectively. The structures of the models were validated using different parameters such as Ramachandran plot, ERRAT values, Verify_3D scores, knowledge-based energy and <italic>Z</italic>-scores with their respective target proteins. The Ramachandran plot which evaluates the stereochemistry of the protein by analysing the distribution of backbone dihedral angles (phi and psi) of each amino acid residues (<xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">Gurung and Bhattacharjee, 2017</xref>) shows that the total number of residues in most favoured regions for Nsp13 helicase and its template was 450 (83.8%) and 398 (75.0%) respectively and the corresponding number of residues in disallowed regions were 6 (1.1%) and 7 (1.3%) respectively (Suppl. Fig. 4A&#x02013;B, Suppl. Table 3). In case of Nsp14 and its template, the total number of residues in most favoured regions were 422 (90%) and 421 (92.5%) respectively and no residues were found in disallowed regions (Suppl. Fig. 4C&#x02013;D, Suppl. Table 4). The ERRAT (overall quality factor) values which give statistics of non-bonded interactions between different atom types were found to be 68.2968 and 69.3333 for Nsp13 helicase and its template respectively (Suppl. Fig. 5A&#x02013;B). In the case of Nsp14 and its template, the ERRAT scores were found to be 63.1068 and 64.3021 respectively (Suppl. Fig. 5C&#x02013;D). The Verify_3D scores which determine the compatibility of 3D structure with its amino acid sequence were 89.52% and 81.49% of the residues with averaged 3D-1D score&#x000a0;&#x02265;&#x000a0;0 for Nsp13 helicase and its template respectively (Suppl. Fig. 6A&#x02013;B) whereas Nsp14 and its template have Verify_3D scores of 88.24% and 77.24% respectively (Suppl. Fig. 6C&#x02013;D). The conformational knowledge-based energy was found to be negative for Nsp13 helicase and template structure across the sequence length except for a small region near the C terminal region where slightly higher energy for the template was observed as compared to the model structure (Suppl. Fig. 7A&#x02013;B). Similarly, the knowledge-based energy for Nsp14 and template structure was found to be negative throughout the sequence except for a slightly higher energy peak at the N terminal and near the C-terminal region of the template structure (Suppl. Fig. 7C&#x02013;D). The <italic>Z</italic>-score measures the deviation of the total energy of the protein structure concerning an energy distribution of their random conformation and is an indicator of the overall quality of a model structure (<xref rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr">Llorca et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bb0190" ref-type="bibr">Sippl, 1993</xref>). The Z-score values for Nsp13 helicase and its template were calculated to be &#x02212;8.78 and &#x02212;8.33 respectively (Suppl. Fig. 8A&#x02013;B) and in case of Nsp14 and its template, the Z-score values were&#x000a0;&#x02212;&#x000a0;8.85 and &#x02212;8.82 respectively which are within the optimum range of native proteins (Suppl. Fig. 8C&#x02013;D).</p></sec><sec id="s0105"><label>3.7</label><title>Structure superposition</title><p id="p0125">The <italic>in silico</italic> model of SARS-CoV-2 Nsp13 helicase obtained in this study has a three-dimensional structure similar to that of MERS- and SARS-CoV with a typical triangular pyramidal geometry with five domains-ZBD, stalk, 1B, 1A and 2A domain (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
A). The structural superposition between Nsp13 helicase and template yields an RMSD value of 0.259&#x000a0;&#x000c5; and structure-based sequence percent identity of 99.83 between 594 pruned atom pairs with alignment showing (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>B&#x02013;C). The <italic>in silico</italic> model structure of SARS-CoV-2 Nsp14 with the two domains-ExoN and N7-MTase domain along with the ligand-binding pocket is shown in <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>A. An RMSD value of 0.380&#x000a0;&#x000c5; and structure-based sequence percent identity of 94.94 between 513 pruned atom pairs was obtained when Nsp14 is superimposed on the template structure (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>B&#x02013;C). The low RMSD values of the model structures indicate that they are very similar to the template proteins.<fig id="f0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>(A) <italic>In silico</italic> model structure of SARS-CoV-2 Nsp13 helicase enzyme showing five domains in ribbons - ZBD: 1&#x02013;99 residues (turquoise), Stalk: 100&#x02013;149 residues (yellow), 1B: 150&#x02013;260 residues (orchid), 1A: 261&#x02013;441 residues (light green) and 2A: 442&#x02013;596 residues (light blue). The NTPase active site (grey spheres) is composed of six residues-Lys288, Ser289, Asp374, Glu375, Gln404 and Arg567. (B) Superposition of the silico model structure of SARS-CoV-2 Nsp13 helicase enzyme (cyan) with the template (tan) (C) pairwise sequence alignment between SARS-CoV-2 Nsp13 and the template protein with identical residues represented by white characters inside the red box. The secondary elements such as &#x003b1;-helices and 3<sub>10</sub>-helices (&#x003b7;) are rendered as coils whereas &#x003b2;-strands, strict &#x003b2;-turns and strict &#x003b1;-turns are represented by arrows, TT letters and TTT letters respectively. (For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of this article.)</p></caption><alt-text id="al0005">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig><fig id="f0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>(A) <italic>In silico</italic> model structure of SARS-CoV-2 Nsp14 showing two domains in ribbons &#x02013; ExoN domain: 1&#x02013;287 residues (plum) and N7-MTase domain: 288&#x02013;527 residues (sky blue). The ligand-binding pocket consists of SAH binding site (gold spheres) which encompasses residues-Trp292, Asp331, Gly333, Pro335, Lys336, Asp352 and Val389 and GpppA binding site (spring green spheres) contain residues such as Asn306, Arg310, Trp385, Asn386, Phe401, Leu419, Tyr420, Asn422, Lys423, Phe426, Thr428 and Phe506. (B) Superposition of the silico model structure of SARS-CoV-2 Nsp14 (cyan) with the template (tan) (C) pairwise sequence alignment between SARS-CoV-2 Nsp14 and the template protein with identical residues represented by white characters inside the red box. The secondary elements such as &#x003b1;-helices and 3<sub>10</sub>-helices (&#x003b7;) are rendered as coils whereas &#x003b2;-strands, strict &#x003b2;-turns and strict &#x003b1;-turns are represented by arrows, TT letters and TTT letters respectively. (For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of this article.)</p></caption><alt-text id="al0010">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0110"><label>3.8</label><title>Molecular docking analysis</title><p id="p0130">A set of 54 FDA approved antiviral drugs were used for virtual screening in the present study (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Four standard inhibitors of Nsp13 helicase enzyme was also docked with the target enzyme to benchmark the binding energy scores of other compounds. The NTPase binding pocket of Nsp13 helicase was used for docking the antiviral drugs. The standard inhibitors-SSYA10-001, SSYA10-002, Myricetin and Scutellarin scored binding energies of &#x02212;7.44&#x000a0;kcal/mol, &#x02212;8.16&#x000a0;kcal/mol, &#x02212;6.91&#x000a0;kcal/mol and &#x02212;7.05&#x000a0;kcal/mol respectively and their corresponding inhibition constants values were found to be 3.50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M, 1.05&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M, 8.56&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M and 6.84&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M (<xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>
). SSYA10-001, SSYA10-002, Myricetin and Scutellarin are potent inhibitors with previously reported to inhibit SARS-CoV Nsp13 helicase activity with half maximal inhibitory concentration (IC<sub>50</sub>) values of 6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M, 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M, 2.71&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M and 0.86&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M respectively (<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">Adedeji et al., 2012b</xref>; <xref rid="bb0225" ref-type="bibr">Yu et al., 2012</xref>). Three lead molecules-Simeprevir (SMV), Paritaprevir (PTV) and Grazoprevir (GZR) for SARS-CoV-2 Nsp13 helicase enzyme were identified by screening of FDA approved antiviral drugs. The binding modes of the lead molecules and control inhibitors within the active site pocket of Nsp13 helicase enzyme are represented in <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>
. SMV was found to be the best-docked molecule with a binding energy of &#x02212;10.42&#x000a0;kcal/mol and inhibition constant of 23.0&#x000a0;nM. The SMV-helicase enzyme complex was stabilized by five hydrogen bonds with residues-Ser310, Arg443, Asp534, Gly538 and Arg567 and hydrophobic interactions with Arg178, Pro284, Gly285, Thr286, Lys288, Ser289, Ala312, Ala313, Ala316, Glu375, Met378, Gln404, Ser535, Gln537 and Ser539 (Suppl. Fig. 9A). PTV is the second-best lead molecule which binds with Nsp13 helicase with a binding energy of &#x02212;9.70&#x000a0;kcal/mol and exhibited inhibition constant of 78.25&#x000a0;nM. The molecular interaction between PTV and the target enzyme include two hydrogen bonds with Thr286, Gly287 and Ser289 and hydrophobic interactions with Gly285, Lys288, His290, Ala312, Ala313, Ala316, Leu317, Lys320, Asp374, Arg442, Gln537, Gly538, Ser539 and Glu540 (Suppl. Fig. 9B). The third best lead molecule for Nsp13 helicase enzyme was identified to be GZR which interacts with the target with a binding energy of &#x02212;9.15&#x000a0;kcal/mol and exhibits inhibition constant value of 172.33&#x000a0;nM. GZR is bound within the enzyme pocket using five hydrogen bonds with Thr286, Lys288, Gln404, Gly538 and Glu540 and the complex is further stabilized by hydrophobic interactions contributed by residues such as Pro284, Gly285, Gly287, Ser289, His290, Ala313, Ala316, Asp374, Arg443, Arg442, Gln537, Ser539 and Arg567 (Suppl. Fig. 9C). The binding mode of the most potent inhibitor, Scutellarin reveals eight hydrogen bonds with residues-Gly285, Lys288, Gln404, Gln537, Arg553 and Arg567 and seven residues- Pro284, Thr286, Ser289, Ala316, Arg442, Gly538 and Glu540 contributes towards hydrophobic interactions (Suppl. Fig. 9D).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0020"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Molecular docking results of top 3 lead molecules of SARS-CoV-2 Nsp13 helicase along with the control inhibitors.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0040">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Molecule</th><th rowspan="2">Structure</th><th colspan="2">SARS-CoV-2 Nsp13 helicase<hr/></th></tr><tr><th>Binding energy (kcal/mol)</th><th>Inhibition constant (Ki)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Simeprevir (SMV)</td><td><inline-graphic xlink:href="t1_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="al0045">Image 1</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="char">&#x02212;10.42</td><td>23.00&#x000a0;nM</td></tr><tr><td>Paritaprevir (PTV)</td><td><inline-graphic xlink:href="t2_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="al0050">Image 2</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="char">&#x02212;9.70</td><td>78.25&#x000a0;nM</td></tr><tr><td>Grazoprevir (GZR)</td><td><inline-graphic xlink:href="t3_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="al0055">Image 3</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="char">&#x02212;9.23</td><td>172.33&#x000a0;nM</td></tr><tr><td>SSYA10-001</td><td><inline-graphic xlink:href="t4_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="al0060">Image 4</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="char">&#x02212;7.44</td><td>3.50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td></tr><tr><td>SSYA10-002</td><td><inline-graphic xlink:href="t5_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="al0065">Image 5</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="char">&#x02212;8.16</td><td>1.05&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td></tr><tr><td>Myricetin</td><td><inline-graphic xlink:href="t6_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="al0070">Image 6</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="char">&#x02212;6.91</td><td>8.56&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td></tr><tr><td>Scutellarin</td><td><inline-graphic xlink:href="t7_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="al0075">Image 7</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="char">&#x02212;7.05</td><td>6.84&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="f0015"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>(A) Surface representation of SARS-CoV-2 Nsp13 helicase enzyme highlighting the five domains-ZBD (turquoise), stalk (yellow), 1B (orchid), 1A (light green) and 2A (light blue) along with the ligand-binding pocket (black encircled region). The binding conformation and molecular interaction between SARS-CoV-2 Nsp13 helicase enzyme and (B) Simeprevir (SMV) (C) Paritaprevir (PTV) (D) Grazoprevir (GZR) (E) Scutellarin (control inhibitor). The coloured spheres are labelled with the residue name and residue number where different colours represent the residue type such as red indicating acidic residues (Asp and Glu), green indicating hydrophobic residues (Ala, Val, Ile, Leu, Tyr, Phe, Trp, Met, Cys and Pro), purple indicating basic residues (Lys and Arg), blue indicating polar residues (Ser, Thr, Gln, Asn and His), light grey indicating others (Gly and water) and darker grey indicating metal atoms. The molecular interactions between ligand atoms and protein residues are represented as a solid pink line indicating H-bonds to the protein backbone, dotted pink indicating H-bonds to protein side chains, green indicating pi-pi stacking interactions and orange indicating pi-cation interactions. The grey spheres are the ligand atoms that are exposed to solvent. The binding pocket is displayed with a curve line around the ligand, coloured with the colour of the nearest protein residue. The opening of the pocket is shown by a gap in the curve line. (For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of this article.)</p></caption><alt-text id="al0015">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3_lrg"/></fig></p><p id="p0135">Similarly, 54 approved drugs along with the control inhibitor were docked within the N7-MTase domain ligand binding sites of Nsp14 protein and the docking results of the top 3 leads and control are summarized in <xref rid="t0025" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>
. The top-ranked lead compounds identified through virtual screening of FDA approved drugs were PTV, SMV and GZR which binds to the target protein with binding energy of &#x02212;13.29&#x000a0;kcal/mol, &#x02212;13.26&#x000a0;kcal/mol and &#x02212;12.16&#x000a0;kcal/mol. The inhibition constants of PTV, SMV and GZR were 181.23 pM, 190.01 pM and 1.22&#x000a0;nM respectively. The binding conformations of the lead molecules along with the control inhibitor within the active site pocket of Nsp14 protein are illustrated through <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>
. The complex between PTV and Nsp14 is stabilized by three hydrogen bonds with residues Arg289 and His427 and hydrophobic interactions <italic>via</italic> residues- Tyr260, Val287, Gly333, Pro335, Asp352, Ala353, Leu366, Phe367, Tyr368, Asn386, Cys387, Asn388, Val389, Phe401, Tyr420, Phe426, Thr428, Pro429 and Phe506 (Suppl. Fig. 10A). SMV interacts with its target protein through only hydrophobic interactions with residues Arg289, Val290, Trp292, Ile305, Asn306, Cys309, Arg310, Gln313, Gly333, Pro335, Asp352, Ala353, Gln354, Trp385, Asn386, Cys387, Asn388, Tyr420, Asn422, Phe426, His427, Thr428 and Phe506 (Suppl. Fig. 10B). The third lead compound-GZR establishes one hydrogen bond with Asn388 and the interaction with the protein is further stabilized through hydrophobic interactions with residues- Arg289, Val290, Trp292, Arg310, Ile332, Gly333, Lys336, Asp352, Ala353, Gln354, Leu366, Tyr368, Asn386, Cys387, Ile338, Phe401, Tyr420, Phe426, His427 and Thr428 (Suppl. Fig. 10C). The control, Sinefungin (SF) binds to Nsp14 protein with a binding energy of &#x02212;6.73&#x000a0;kcal/mol and exhibits inhibition constant of 11.72&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M. The molecular binding is mediated through six hydrogen bonds with residues- Asp352, Ala353, Asn388, and His427 and hydrophobic interactions with residues-Val290, Asn386, Tyr420, Phe426, Thr428, Pro429 and Phe506 (Suppl. Fig. 10D). It is to be noted that SF has been previously reported to inhibit SARS-CoV N7-MTase activity with an IC<sub>50</sub> value of 500&#x000a0;nM (<xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">Aouadi et al., 2017</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0025"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Molecular docking results of top 3 lead molecules of SARS-CoV-2 Nsp14 along with the control inhibitor.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0080">Table 5</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Molecule</th><th rowspan="2">Structure</th><th colspan="2">SARS-CoV-2 Nsp14<hr/></th></tr><tr><th>Binding energy (kcal/mol)</th><th>Inhibition constant (Ki)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Paritaprevir (PTV)</td><td><inline-graphic xlink:href="t8_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="al0085">Image 8</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="char">&#x02212;13.29</td><td>181.23 pM</td></tr><tr><td>Simeprevir (SMV)</td><td><inline-graphic xlink:href="t9_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="al0090">Image 9</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="char">&#x02212;13.26</td><td>190.01 pM</td></tr><tr><td>Grazoprevir (GZR)</td><td><inline-graphic xlink:href="t10_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="al0095">Image 10</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="char">&#x02212;12.16</td><td>1.22&#x000a0;nM</td></tr><tr><td>Sinefungin (SF)</td><td><inline-graphic xlink:href="t11_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="al0100">Image 11</alt-text></inline-graphic></td><td align="char">&#x02212;6.73</td><td>11.72&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="f0020"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>(A) Surface representation of SARS-CoV-2 Nsp14 highlighting the two domains-ExoN domain (plum) and N7-MTase domain (sky blue) along with the ligand-binding pocket- SAH binding site (gold) and GpppA binding site (spring green). The binding conformation and molecular interaction between SARS-CoV-2 Nsp14 and (B) Paritaprevir (PTV) (C) Simeprevir (SMV) (D) Grazoprevir (GZR) (E) Sinefungin (control inhibitor). The residues are represented as coloured spheres labelled with the residue name and residue number. The coloured spheres are labelled with the residue name and residue number where different colours represent the residue type such as red indicating acidic residues (Asp and Glu), green indicating hydrophobic residues (Ala, Val, Ile, Leu, Tyr, Phe, Trp, Met, Cys and Pro), purple indicating basic residues (Lys and Arg), blue indicating polar residues (Ser, Thr, Gln, Asn and His), light grey indicating others (Gly and water) and darker grey indicating metal atoms. The molecular interactions between ligand atoms and protein residues are represented as a solid pink line indicating H-bonds to the protein backbone, dotted pink indicating H-bonds to protein side chains, green indicating pi-pi stacking interactions and orange indicating pi-cation interactions. The grey spheres are the ligand atoms that are exposed to solvent. The binding pocket is displayed with a curve line around the ligand, coloured with the colour of the nearest protein residue. The opening of the pocket is shown by a gap in the curve line. (For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of this article.)</p></caption><alt-text id="al0020">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4_lrg"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="s0115"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0140">Nsp13 helicase enzyme and Nsp14 protein are among the 16 non-structural proteins formed from the processing of viral replicative polyproteins-pp1a and pp1ab. These two proteins are the key components of the viral replication and transcription complexes which are essential for the life cycle of SARS-coronavirus. Both the proteins are highly conserved within the <italic>coronaviridae</italic> family members. While Nsp13 helicase utilizes the energy derived from NTP hydrolysis to unwind duplex oligonucleotides into single strands, Nsp14 exhibits dual functions such as proofreading 3&#x02032; to 5&#x02032; exonuclease activity conferred by the ExoN domain and methylation of guanosine cap by the N7-MTase domain. Because of the indispensability of both the proteins to complete the life cycle of the coronavirus, they are promising drug targets. Due to the paucity of the three-dimensional experimental structures of both the proteins, the structure-based drug discovery of specific inhibitors of SARS-CoV-2 Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 is a challenge. However, in the absence of experimental structures of the target proteins, a bioinformatics approach driven structural elucidation is another promising alternative. <xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2020a</xref>, <xref rid="bb0220" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2020b</xref> used <italic>in silico</italic> model of Nsp13 helicase protein and proposed few potential inhibitors such as antibacterial drugs- lymecycline, cefsulodine and rolitetracycline, anti-fungal drug itraconazole, anti-human immunodeficiency virus-1 (HIV-1) drug saquinavir, anti-coagulant drug dabigatran, diuretic drug canrenoic acid and few flavonoids and xanthones (<xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2020a</xref>). <xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">Mirza and Froeyen (2020)</xref> screened chemical compounds from ZINC database using <italic>in silico</italic> model of Nsp13 helicase and identified few potential inhibitors such as cmp1, cmp3a, cmp11 and cmp15 which scored the AutoDock Vina binding energy between &#x02212;10.2 to &#x02212;10.9&#x000a0;kcal/mol (<xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">Mirza and Froeyen, 2020</xref>). In the present study, SARS-CoV-2 Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 protein sequences were checked for homology against human proteome. Nsp14 did not show any significant hit whereas the nearest homolog of Nsp13 was found to be Zinc Finger GRF-Type Containing 1 (ZGRF1) isoform X10 showed both less identity and low query coverage in the DNA2 superfamily domain. However, the binding pocket of Nsp13 does not include the DNA2 superfamily domain and therefore, the antiviral drugs are highly likely to exhibit less binding affinity to the human homolog thereby causing minimal adverse reactions. Both the structures of Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 <italic>in silico</italic> models were generated using the homologous structures from SARS-CoV. The <italic>in silico</italic> models were validated using different parameters and both the models were found to be reliable and robust for further studies. Subsequently, these structures were utilized to probe the binding of FDA approved drugs to identify their respective potential inhibitors. Virtual screening of FDA approved drugs screening is the most promising strategy available as these drugs have already been tested in clinical trials and have proven antiviral activity which reduces both the time and costs incurred in the discovery of novel drugs. The NTPase domain of Nsp13 helicase and N7-MTase domain of Nsp14 were targeted by FDA approved drugs in the present study. NTPase domain consists of residues which are vital for the NTP hydrolysis activity essential for the unwinding of a duplex nucleic acid molecule and N7-MTase domain has a pocket consisting of binding of substrate SAH. A set of 54 approved drugs were screened for their Out of 54 approved drugs, three lead molecules were identified for each target proteins. These lead molecules are accepted drugs which are potent inhibitors of hepatitis C virus (HCV) NS3/4A protease (<xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">De Clercq and Li, 2016</xref>). Interestingly, the top 3 hits- Simeprevir (SMV), Paritaprevir (PTV) and Grazoprevir (GZR) were also the top leads identified for Nsp14 protein and therefore, these molecules can be used as dual inhibitors. It is a novel finding and provides an opportunity to design dual inhibitors for both the target proteins sharing similar functions and further can disrupt the RTC machinery thereby impeding the infectious cycle of the coronavirus. The present study would pave the way for the discovery of dual-target inhibitors and help understand how a single molecule could be designed to block the pathogenic cycle of the deadly virus. This approach is more advantageous over the conventional one target-one drug approach given the fact that the actions and interactions of many proteins drive the pathogenesis of the disease and blocking one target might be less effective. Previously, <xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al. (2015)</xref> attempted to design selective dual inhibitor of both Papain-like Protease (PL<sup>pro</sup>) enzymes of MERS-CoV and SARS-CoV and demonstrated that 8-(Trifluoromethyl)-9H-purin-6-amine acts as an allosteric inhibitor against SARS-CoV (IC<sub>50</sub> 11&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M) and a competitive inhibitor against MERS-CoV (IC<sub>50</sub> 6.0&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M). <xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al. (2020)</xref> discovered calpain II and XII inhibitors as potent SARS-CoV-2 antivirals and concluded that design of dual inhibitors against the viral Main protease (M<sup>pro</sup>) and the host calpains/cathepsins might be attainable given that both of which are essential for viral replication. The studies further highlighted an additional benefit of dual inhibitors in providing a high genetic barrier to drug resistance. It would be interesting to study the dynamics of the proteins complexed with the inhibitors which will provide further mechanistic insights into the modes of inhibition though time-dependent conformational changes in the structures of the protein and the stability of the inhibitors within the active site pocket of the proteins. Various <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> biological assays are further needed to validate the findings of the present study.</p></sec><sec id="s0120"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0145">The <italic>in silico</italic> models of Nsp13 helicase and Nsp14 protein were deciphered using comparative homology approach and were further used for structure-based identification of inhibitors from a set of FDA approved antiviral drugs. Three potential inhibitors- Simeprevir (SMV), Paritaprevir (PTV) and Grazoprevir (GZR) were identified which show dual inhibition potential against NTPase function of Nsp13 helicase enzyme and N7-MTase activity of Nsp14 protein.</p></sec><sec id="s0125"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="p0150">
<bold>Arun Bahadur Gurung:</bold> Conceptualization, Methodology, Software, Data curation, Writing - original draft, Visualization, Investigation, Writing - review &#x00026; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0155">The author declares that there are no conflicts of interest in this work.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bi0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bb0005"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adedeji</surname><given-names>A.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchand</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>te Velthuis</surname><given-names>A.J.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Snijder</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eoff</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarafianos</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of nucleic acid unwinding by SARS-CoV helicase</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>7</volume><year>2012</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0010"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adedeji</surname><given-names>A.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calcaterra</surname><given-names>N.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>DeDiego</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Enjuanes</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarafianos</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus replication inhibitor that interferes with the nucleic acid unwinding of the viral helicase</article-title><source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source><volume>56</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>4718</fpage><lpage>4728</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22733076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0015"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adedeji</surname><given-names>A.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kassim</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frieman</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarafianos</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of SSYA10-001 as a replication inhibitor of severe acute respiratory syndrome, mouse hepatitis, and Middle East respiratory syndrome coronaviruses</article-title><source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source><volume>58</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>4894</fpage><lpage>4898</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24841268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0020"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aouadi</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eydoux</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coutard</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Debart</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasseur</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Contreras</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morice</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qu&#x000e9;rat</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>M.-L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toward the identification of viral cap-methyltransferase inhibitors by fluorescence screening assay</article-title><source>Antivir. Res.</source><volume>144</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>330</fpage><lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28676301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0025"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becares</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascual-Iglesias</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nogales</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sola</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Enjuanes</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zu&#x000f1;iga</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutagenesis of coronavirus nsp14 reveals its potential role in modulation of the innate immune response</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><volume>90</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>5399</fpage><lpage>5414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27009949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0030"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan-Yeung</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>R.-H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SARS: epidemiology</article-title><source>Respirology</source><volume>8</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>S9</fpage><lpage>S14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15018127</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0035"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Clercq</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Approved antiviral drugs over the past 50 years</article-title><source>Clin. Microbiol. Rev.</source><volume>29</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>695</fpage><lpage>747</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27281742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0040"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Decroly</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferron</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lescar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Canard</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conventional and unconventional mechanisms for capping viral mRNA</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source><volume>10</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>65</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0045"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denison</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Donaldson</surname><given-names>E.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckerle</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baric</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coronaviruses: an RNA proofreading machine regulates replication fidelity and diversity</article-title><source>RNA Biol.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>270</fpage><lpage>279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21593585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0050"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eswar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marti-Renom</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Madhusudhan</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eramian</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>M.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieper</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sali</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Comparative protein structure modeling using Modeller</chapter-title><source>Curr. Protoc. Bioinforma. Chapter 5, Unit-5.6</source><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/0471250953.bi0506s15</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0055"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fairman-Williams</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guenther</surname><given-names>U.-P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jankowsky</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SF1 and SF2 helicases: family matters</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol.</source><volume>20</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20456941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0060"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fiser</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x00160;ali</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Modeller: generation and refinement of homology-based protein structure models</chapter-title><source>Methods in Enzymology</source><year>2003</year><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>491</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0065"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garnier</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Osguthorpe</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the accuracy and implications of simple methods for predicting the secondary structure of globular proteins</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><volume>120</volume><year>1978</year><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">642007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0070"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guex</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peitsch</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SWISS-MODEL and the Swiss-Pdb Viewer: an environment for comparative protein modeling</article-title><source>Electrophoresis</source><volume>18</volume><year>1997</year><fpage>2714</fpage><lpage>2723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9504803</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0075"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gurung</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharjee</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure based virtual screening identifies Pranlukast as a potential inhibitor against Plasmodium falciparum Adenosine Deaminase enzyme</article-title><source>Gene Rep.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.genrep.2016.12.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0080"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halgren</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Merck molecular force field. I. Basis, form, scope, parameterization, and performance of MMFF94</article-title><source>J. Comput. Chem.</source><volume>17</volume><year>1996</year><fpage>490</fpage><lpage>519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1096-987X(199604)17:5/6&#x0003c;490::AID-JCC1&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-P</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0085"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical features of patients infected with 2019 novel coronavirus in Wuhan, China</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>395</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31986264</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0090"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikai</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thermostability and aliphatic index of globular proteins</article-title><source>J. Biochem.</source><volume>88</volume><year>1980</year><fpage>1895</fpage><lpage>1898</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7462208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0095"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiel</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobbe</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Meer</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Snijder</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziebuhr</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple enzymatic activities associated with severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus helicase</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><volume>78</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>5619</fpage><lpage>5632</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15140959</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0100"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>N.-R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>W.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>Y.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D.-E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of inhibitory RNA aptamers against severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) coronavirus NTPase/Helicase</article-title><source>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</source><volume>366</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>738</fpage><lpage>744</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18082623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0105"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ming</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Delicate structural coordination of the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus Nsp13 upon ATP hydrolysis</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>47</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>6538</fpage><lpage>6550</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31131400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0110"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiessen</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolton</surname><given-names>E.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gindulyte</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoemaker</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PubChem substance and compound databases</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0115"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krogh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Von Heijne</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnhammer</surname><given-names>E.L.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predicting transmembrane protein topology with a hidden Markov model: application to complete genomes</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><volume>305</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>567</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11152613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0120"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kyte</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doolittle</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple method for displaying the hydropathic character of a protein</article-title><source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><volume>157</volume><year>1982</year><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7108955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0125"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laskowski</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Swindells</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LigPlot+: multiple ligand-protein interaction diagrams for drug discovery</article-title><source>J. Chem. Inf. Model.</source><volume>51</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>2778</fpage><lpage>2786</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ci200227u</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21919503</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0130"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santarsiero</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatuz</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Szypulinski</surname><given-names>M.Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ojeda</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibitor recognition specificity of MERS-CoV papain-like protease may differ from that of SARS-CoV</article-title><source>ACS Chem. Biol.</source><volume>10</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>1456</fpage><lpage>1465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25746232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0135"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Llorca</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Betti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valencia</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquez</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valpuesta</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The three-dimensional structure of an eukaryotic glutamine synthetase: functional implications of its oligomeric structure</article-title><source>J. Struct. Biol.</source><volume>156</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>469</fpage><lpage>479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsb.2006.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16884924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0140"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural basis and functional analysis of the SARS coronavirus nsp14-nsp10 complex</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source><volume>112</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>9436</fpage><lpage>9441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26159422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0145"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurst</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Szeto</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarbet</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marty</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Boceprevir, GC-376, and calpain inhibitors II, XII inhibit SARS-CoV-2 viral replication by targeting the viral main protease</article-title><source>Cell Res.</source><volume>30</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>678</fpage><lpage>692</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41422-020-0356-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32541865</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0150"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marcotrigiano</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gingras</surname><given-names>A.-C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonenberg</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burley</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cocrystal structure of the messenger RNA 5&#x02032; cap-binding protein (eIF4E) bound to 7-methyl-GDP</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>89</volume><year>1997</year><fpage>951</fpage><lpage>961</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9200613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0155"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marra</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>S.J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Astell</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks-Wilson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Butterfield</surname><given-names>Y.S.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khattra</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asano</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genome sequence of the SARS-associated coronavirus</article-title><source>Science (80-.)</source><volume>300</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>1399</fpage><lpage>1404</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0160"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0160"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mirza</surname><given-names>M.U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Froeyen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural elucidation of SARS-CoV-2 vital proteins: computational methods reveal potential drug candidates against main protease, Nsp12 polymerase and Nsp13 helicase</article-title><source>J. Pharm. Anal.</source><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>320</fpage><lpage>328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpha.2020.04.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32346490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0165"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huey</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindstrom</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanner</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Belew</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodsell</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AutoDock4 and AutoDockTools4: automated docking with selective receptor flexibility</article-title><source>J. Comput. Chem.</source><volume>30</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>2785</fpage><lpage>2791</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.21256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19399780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0170"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0170"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Boyle</surname><given-names>N.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Banck</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morley</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandermeersch</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutchison</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Open babel: an open chemical toolbox</article-title><source>J. Cheminform.</source><volume>3</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>33</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1758-2946-3-33</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21982300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0175"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0175"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pettersen</surname><given-names>E.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goddard</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Couch</surname><given-names>G.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenblatt</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrin</surname><given-names>T.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>UCSF Chimera&#x02014;a visualization system for exploratory research and analysis</article-title><source>J. Comput. Chem.</source><volume>25</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>1605</fpage><lpage>1612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.20084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15264254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0180"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0180"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prentice</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>McAuliffe</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Subbarao</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Denison</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus replicase proteins</article-title><source>J. Virol.</source><volume>78</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>9977</fpage><lpage>9986</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15331731</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0185"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0185"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singhal</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review of coronavirus disease-2019 (COVID-19)</article-title><source>Indian J. Pediatr.</source><volume>87</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12098-020-03263-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32166607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0190"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0190"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sippl</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recognition of errors in three-dimensional structures of proteins</article-title><source>Proteins</source><volume>17</volume><year>1993</year><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/prot.340170404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8108378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0195"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0195"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanner</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watt</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>Y.-B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peiris</surname><given-names>J.S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poon</surname><given-names>L.L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kung</surname><given-names>H.-F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.-D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) coronavirus NTPase/helicase belongs to a distinct class of 5&#x02032; to 3&#x02032; viral helicases</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><volume>278</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>39578</fpage><lpage>39582</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.C300328200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12917423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0200"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0200"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thiel</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Putics</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hertzig</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schelle</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei&#x000df;brich</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Snijder</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabenau</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doerr</surname><given-names>H.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms and enzymes involved in SARS coronavirus genome expression</article-title><source>J. Gen. Virol.</source><volume>84</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>2305</fpage><lpage>2315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12917450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0205"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0205"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Hemert</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Worm</surname><given-names>S.H.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knoops</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mommaas</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorbalenya</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Snijder</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SARS-coronavirus replication/transcription complexes are membrane-protected and need a host factor for activity in vitro</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2008</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0210"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0210"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review of the 2019 Novel Coronavirus (COVID-19) based on current evidence</article-title><source>Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents</source><volume>105948</volume><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0215"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0215"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of therapeutic targets for SARS-CoV-2 and discovery of potential drugs by computational methods</article-title><source>Acta Pharm. Sin. B</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apsb.2020.02.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0220"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0220"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>H.-C.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shannar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hudlikar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An update on current therapeutic drugs treating COVID-19</article-title><source>Curr. Pharmacol. Rep.</source><volume>1</volume><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0225"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0225"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>Y.-W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jee</surname><given-names>J.-G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keum</surname><given-names>Y.-S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>Y.-J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of myricetin and scutellarein as novel chemical inhibitors of the SARS coronavirus helicase, nsP13</article-title><source>Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett.</source><volume>22</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>4049</fpage><lpage>4054</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22578462</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="s0130" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0165">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ec0005"><caption><p>Supplementary material</p></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.docx"><alt-text>Image 12</alt-text></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec><ack id="ac0005"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The author sincerely acknowledges the Department of Basic Sciences and Social Sciences, <funding-source id="gts0005"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100007781</institution-id><institution>NEHU</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> for the research support.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="s0135" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="p0170">Supplementary data to this article can be found online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.genrep.2020.100860" id="ir0035">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.genrep.2020.100860</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>