<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The entry of viruses into cells is often mediated by specific physical interactions between virus surface proteins and host-encoded cell surface receptors. In the case of the New World arenaviruses, the surface glycoprotein, GP, contacts TfR1 to trigger cellular entry 
 <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Radoshitzky1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. These viruses infect various rodent species found in the Americas, and each virus has evolved compatibility with the particular TfR1 ortholog encoded by its host species (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001571-g001">Figure 1A</xref>) 
 <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Radoshitzky2" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Flanagan1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Several of these viruses, including Junin virus, Machupo virus, and Guanarito virus, have acquired the ability to bind human TfR1 and are currently emerging into human populations through zoonotic transmission 
 <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Choe1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Charrel1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. These viruses cause hemorrhagic fevers in humans with case fatality rates of 15–30%, but fortunately, they do not yet spread from human to human efficiently enough to cause large epidemics. Another rodent virus that uses TfR1 for cellular entry is the retrovirus mouse mammary tumor virus (MMTV). The MMTV surface glycoprotein, Env, contacts TfR1 to trigger cellular entry 
 <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Ross1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. MMTV infects 
 <italic>Muridae</italic> rodents specifically of the genus 
 <italic>Mus</italic>, including 
 <italic>Mus musculus</italic>, the house mouse (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001571-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). In contrast to the arenaviruses, MMTV is not known to infect other rodent species or humans. Incompatibility with human TfR1 appears to be the major cellular barrier to zoonosis because MMTV replicates robustly in human cells when receptor-mediated entry is bypassed by transfection of the viral genome directly into cells 
 <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Bhadra1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. Finally, in carnivores, parvoviruses also bind TfR1 for cellular entry 
 <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Parker1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Canine parvovirus serves as one of the most important models for disease emergence in the wild, as this virus first came into existence in the 1970s when a virus was passed to dogs from another carnivore species 
 <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Allison1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. This event centered around viral evolution for compatibility with the dog TfR1 ortholog 
 <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Parrish1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.1001571-Stucker1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. Thus, in all three of the virus families that use TfR1, existing evidence suggests that the ability to enter cells through the TfR1 ortholog of a particular species is a necessary criterion for infection in the wild, and that viral adaptation is often required to utilize the TfR1 of new species.
</p>
