<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par40">The whole of M2 is highly conserved, but its extracellular part is of the greatest interest as a potential antigen. We analyzed 27,253 human, 15,367 avian and 5379 swine individual sequences of influenza A virus M gene (obtained from the Influenza Research Database (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://fludb.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">fludb.org</ext-link>)) and generated a phylogenetic tree using MAFFT [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. The tree was visualized using the Interactive Tree Of Life (iTOL) server [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]. As shown on Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a, the M2e sequences of influenza A viruses have evolutionary diverged into several lineages mainly related to host species. The generated phylogenetic tree basically repeats the published analysis of Furuse et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], but in contrast to this study published before the 2009 pandemic, our analysis included a large number of sequences of H1N1pdm09 virus M gene, which is known to originate from the Eurasian avian-like swine H1N1 lineage [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">109</xref>]. We selected six different lineages of M2e protein based on their phylogenetic relatedness and obtained consensus sequences for each lineage using UGENE Multiple Alignment software (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). As mentioned above, the first nine amino acids have the lowest variability for each analyzed group. The remaining residues have different percentage mutations for each origin; however, the residues Arg12, Trp15, Cys17, Cys19, Ser22 and Asp24 have the lowest frequency of mutations, which may reflect their functional significance. The only exception is the residue at 19th position in the swine influenza viruses that fall into lineage 2, in which Tyr dominated in this position (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). The slight difference between the consensus sequences is also significant for the choice of the appropriate sequence for a universal vaccine. For example, immunization of pigs with human M2e using different carriers did not protect the animals from the lethal swine subtype of influenza A virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. It has also been shown that monoclonal antibody 8C6, which protects mice against lethal challenge virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>], is able to recognize the consensus part of human M2e “EVETPIRN” sequence (а.a. 6–13), but not the consensus fragment of avian M2e “EVETPTRN” (a.a. 6–13). Thus, it is possible that an amino acid substitution at the 11th position in avian M2e may allow avian influenza A virus to escape the immune response in humans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]. Based on our analysis of all available M2e sequences, in order to develop a M2e-based universal influenza vaccine we propose using four different consensus M2e protein sequences that will cover most human, avian and swine influenza A viruses (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c). In contrast to previously published studies, we suggest using two different M2e sequences for human influenza viruses due to the significant variations between the human viruses isolated before the 2009 pandemic and the H1N1pdm09 viruses. 
</p>
