<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Prior to loading equi-volume samples on a 20% polyacrylamide, 8 M urea, TBE (89 mM Tris-Borate, 2 mM EDTA) denaturing gel, the quenched samples were combined with dye (formamide, 0.01% xylene cyanol, 0.01% bromophenol blue) and 1 µL of 5 µM D10 (5′-AGTTGTTGAT-3′) trap, followed by incubation at 95 °C for 5 min. The trap was used to bind to RNA template to reduce gel smearing [
 <xref rid="B30-viruses-11-00365" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Oligos were separated via electrophoresis at a maximum of 1900 V and 75 W for 3–6 h. Phosphorimaging (FLA 9500 imager, GE, Marlborough, MA, USA) was used to visualize the bands, and bands were quantified using ImageQuant software (GE). Plots of percent incorporation versus time were fit to a single exponential equation using Prism (Graphpad Software, San Diego, CA, USA) to compare relative incorporation. While single-turnover conditions were used, non-physiologically relevant rates were obtained, as incorporation occurred during a steady-state time scale. This has been a common issue in the field when measuring ZIKV RdRP incorporation [
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-11-00365" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-11-00365" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-11-00365" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] due to measuring incorporation into a double-stranded template instead of physiologically preferred de novo RNA replication (an issue seen in HCV incorporation assays [
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-11-00365" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]), and perhaps the presence of purification tags [
 <xref rid="B33-viruses-11-00365" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. However, since here we were interested in comparing relative incorporation efficiency rather than obtaining rate constants, we and others [
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-11-00365" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-11-00365" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] have found this experimental set-up ideal and better suited to scaling up the number of analogues to be assessed.
</p>
