<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Face masks combined with other preventative measures, such as social distancing and regular hand washing, can play a crucial role in reducing the spread of COVID-19.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
  <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
 </sup> Wearing a face mask in public may impede the spread of infectious diseases, including COVID-19, by preventing the inhalation, as well as, the exhalation and dissemination of infectious droplets.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
 </sup> While it is established that COVID-19 is carried by airborne droplets, mostly from coughing and sneezing, there is some dispute as to the distance that these airborne droplets can travel. Researchers at Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) in Cambridge, Massachusetts, recently experimented with laboratory conditions, which showed that coughs could project liquid up to 6 meters away. At the same time, sneezes, which involve higher velocities, can allow fluids to travel up to 8 meters.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
  <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
 </sup> However, the current advised social distance is 2 meters. There have been early reports that COVID-19 is spreading rapidly between people, while most scientists agree that the virus is transmitted. Droplets, either directly or indirectly, on objects are of concern, and there is preliminary evidence that airborne transmission may indeed be occurring.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
 </sup> Some experts suggest that the virus can be spread by either talking or breathing and can linger in the air and on surfaces hours after being expelled.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>
 </sup> Also, wearing face masks in public can prevent asymptomatic and presymptomatic persons from unknowingly transmitting the virus.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
 </sup> As tests are only being conducted on people who present with symptoms or persons who are high risk, the number of COVID-19 cases do not include asymptomatic carriers, which could be spreading the virus unknowingly. Asymptomatic and presymptomatic infected persons are less likely to practice social isolation. There are substantial considerations that using facemasks provides an extra layer of protection.
</p>
