<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are potential challenges to the implementation of widespread face masks in the general population. Unless this order is mandatory, persons would have a choice whether to adhere to this recommendation. Sim et al. stated that individuals are more likely to wear facemasks due to the perceived susceptibility and perceived severity of the disease.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>
 </sup> Taylor et al. found that younger people are less willing to comply with wearing face masks than older persons, and that married people are more willing to wear face masks than persons who were never married.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
 </sup> Several studies indicated that women were more likely to wear facemasks than men. At the same time, some cultures and ethnic groups, such as Asians, are more likely to wear facemasks than others.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
 </sup> While face masks would play a critical role in reducing the spread of COVID-19, unless a mandatory order is in place, compliance would be a key influence on the overall outcome. Discordant and ineffective data have also been published and lead confusion to health-care administrators. Bae et al. studied the effectiveness of surgical and cotton masks in 4 patients.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
 </sup> This article is flawed and has been retracted, but has generated false reports.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
 </sup> The authors did not fully recognize the concept of limit of detection (LOD) of the in-house reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction used in the study (2.63 log copies/mL), failing to express the values below LOD as “&lt;LOD (value).” Numerous comments were added to the original publication in 
 <italic>Annals of Internal Medicine</italic>. Inexplicably, the researchers who published in this journal discovered a 36-fold reduction to be “ineffective.” We and others disagree, and the editors decided for a retraction of the article.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
