<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Viruses are defined as obligate intracellular parasites that infect cells susceptible and permissive to their life cycle [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Viruses have an amazing architectural arrangement with a protein capsid that protects the nucleic acid and forms from repetitive building units to give a mainly spherical arrangement of structures [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Viral diseases continue to appear and pose a major public health concern, according to the WHO. Many epidemics have been reported over the past 20 years, including severe acute respiratory coronavirus syndrome (SARS-CoV) from 2002 to 2003 and influenza A subtype H1N1 from 2010. Most recently, Saudi Arabia was initially infected by Middle East coronavirus respiratory syndrome (MERS-CoV), a member virus of the same family [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The latest coronavirus strain, severe acute respiratory coronavirus syndrome-2 (SAR-COV-2), is very infectious and highly contagious and spread across the globe very fast. WHO proclaimed the epidemic as an international disaster for the public safety of importance since it has expanded to over 18 nations. Four nations confirmed a human-to-human infection, at the meeting of 30 January 2020 under the International Health Regulations (IHR), 2005. The WHO announced this epidemic on 30 January 2020; a further milestone was established when the first case of the disease was recorded in the USA and not imported from China. This review highlights the prevention measures, available clinical therapies and the potential of vaccine development against SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Antivirals, antimalarials and immunomodulators that have shown to be active against SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV will be reviewed. Other potential therapies that have been suggested or proposed and are in the Research and Development process will also be discussed.
</p>
