<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The implication of HS binding in dissemination and neurotropism has been investigated for several viruses and remains controversial. Studies on aphtoviruses [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007190.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], flaviviruses [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007190.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], togaviruses [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007190.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], alphaviruses [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007190.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] and even enteroviruses such as coxsackievirus B3 [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007190.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] suggest that binding to HS may lower viremia due to virus trapping in tissues expressing high HS levels, while it may improve neurotropism and ability to cross the blood-brain barrier [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007190.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Of note, two recent papers reported that infection by EV71 with VP1 E145Q substitution was associated with an attenuated phenotype in mice and cynomolgus monkeys and that this attenuation was linked to the ability of VP1 145Q to bind HS [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007190.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007190.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The authors conclude that HS binding and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> virulence are negatively correlated due to trapping and abortive infection of HS-dependent viruses in tissues expressing high levels of HS but low levels of SCARB2. In the clinical case investigated here, the HS binding variant was the only variant sequenced from the blood of the patient suggesting that HS binding did not prevent viremia and dissemination but rather promoted it. Several hypotheses could explain these different observations: first, mice and monkeys may not faithfully reproduce EV71 infection in human as suggested by studies showing that isolates with VP1 145G/Q are frequently associated with severe neurological disease in humans [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007190.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1007190.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]; second, the inoculation site may modulate the infection outcome. Huang and colleagues [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007190.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] showed that broad mutant spectra with divergent mutations are observed at the initial infection sites (the respiratory and digestive systems) and that a selection bottleneck occurs afterwards with subsequent enrichment of advantageous mutations in the viral population. Intraperitoneal or intravenous injections may thus prevent the natural evolution of the viral population observed after fecal-oral or respiratory transmission; third, the binding affinity for HS may differ according to the number and/or location of positive charges on the viral capsid, and different mutations (VP1 E145Q versus VP1 L97R) may result in different binding intensities and different trapping strengths; finally, the host immunity certainly plays a key role. In the clinical case presented here, the patient underwent immunosuppressive therapy with rituximab, an anti-CD20 antibody that depletes the peripheral B‐cell pool. Seroneutralisation experiments performed with the patients’ serum at a time when the VP1 97R mutation was already present in the plasma failed to highlight the presence of an antibody-mediated selective immune pressure against HS-dependent and HS-independent variants [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007190.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. This absence of neutralizing antibodies was correlated with a negative complement fixation assay confirming a poor antibody response against enterovirus linked to the immunosuppressed state of the patient. Fujii et al showed that viruses with VP1 145E are more resistant to neutralizing antibodies than viruses with VP1 145G [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007190.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The absence of immune pressure may thus be a prerequisite for the emergence of HS-dependent variants 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>, since critical residues, such as VP1 98 and 145, seem to play an important role both in immune escape [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007190.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007190.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] and HS binding [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007190.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007190.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007190.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007190.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. The emergence of HS-dependent mutants and their dissemination could thus be favored in the presence of a poor antibody response. Additional clinical investigations are needed to further assess the implication of HS binding in dissemination and disease severity in humans.
</p>
