<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Official notification of Zika infections in Brazil started on the 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="inf91">
   <msup>
    <mn>1</mn>
    <mrow>
     <mi>s</mi>
     <mo>⁢</mo>
     <mi>t</mi>
    </mrow>
   </msup>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> of January 2016, although cases were reported in many other regions in Brazil during 2015. It is therefore plausible that the observation rate changed upon official guidelines and that the capacity to accurately diagnose and report Zika infections could have been lower in 2015 compared subsequent years. To explore this, we reran our fitting approach allowing for a possible change in the observation rate for 2016 and onwards (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3s2">Figure 3—figure supplement 2</xref>) and found a similar observation rate for 2015 (0.0039 versus 0.0034) as well as a similar attack rate between the two model variants. However, the estimated observation rate for 2016 and beyond was 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="inf92">
   <mrow>
    <mi/>
    <mo>≈</mo>
    <mn>4</mn>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> times larger than for 2015, implying a positive change due to changes in the surveillance system. Nevertheless, only about 13–14 out of 1000 Zika cases were reported after the 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="inf93">
   <msup>
    <mn>1</mn>
    <mrow>
     <mi>s</mi>
     <mo>⁢</mo>
     <mi>t</mi>
    </mrow>
   </msup>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> of January 2016. It is hard to discern where the positive changes took place, but we suggest the revised diagnosis guidelines may have increased the proportion correctly diagnosed while the proportion of symptomatic individuals visiting medical facilities did not change. It is also tempting to speculate that the 2015/2016 imbalance in reporting may have been a general phenomenon across Brazil. As described elsewhere, it is thus possible that FSA is a good example of states and urban centres that may have witnessed larger epidemics than reported in 2015 (
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">de Oliveira et al., 2017</xref>). This, together with our conclusion that low MC risk with very high attack rates makes ZIKV a public health concern, could explain why most MC reports at the level of the country were in 2015 (
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">de Oliveira et al., 2017</xref>), although for many regions the total reported number of ZIKV cases may have been surprisingly small that year.
</p>
