<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par25">The current Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) has become a great threat to public health and has attracted the attention of the majority of scientists and researchers to develop a specific drug or vaccine to outweigh the threat to this pandemic. It was initially originated in Wuhan, Hubei Province of China, in December 2019, as pneumonia-like symptoms [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] and spread rapidly to other parts of the world, affecting 10,922,324 individuals, causing more than 523,011 fatalities in over 210 countries by July 4, 2020 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. It was discovered to cause by a novel coronavirus having more than 79% sequence homology with the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) and 96% genome similarity with bat coronavirus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], named as severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) by the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Owing to the alarming level of its severity and rapid spread to many countries in a short period, the World health organization (WHO) has declared this epidemic as pandemic on March 12, 2020 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. COVID-19 pandemic is a pandemic of respiratory illness characterized by flu-like symptoms, sometimes associated with immune dysfunction and acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), which might lead to death [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. It is the third time in the twenty-first century, after severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) in 2002 and 2003 and Middle East respiratory syndrome (MERS) in 2012 when a highly pathogenic coronavirus of zoonotic origin has affected humans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. To date, this has affected the lives of many people worldwide and put pressure on the health system and the global economy. SARS-CoV-2 has a high potential to cause infection with a higher transmission rate in comparison to SARS-CoV or MERS-CoV, making it difficult to control and thereby increasing its pandemic potential.
</p>
