<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Emulsions could improve antibiotic efficacy against pathogens without necessarily exerting an antibiotic action, but rather by supporting drug delivery and accumulation. For instance, dipalmitoyl phosphatidyl choline (DPPC) liposomes loaded with the anti-tubercular drugs isioniazid, ethambutol and rifampicin in a ratio of 1:1 (the drug-by-weight ratio was 1:3:2) prolonged the release and alveolar deposition of the antibiotics in mice. Importantly, no hemolytic activity was reported in the human blood samples exposed to the liposomes. Moreover, the mixture remained stable and active after a month-long storage at 4 °C, permitting its use in clinical settings [
 <xref rid="B49-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. In this line, ciprofloxacin-loaded polyethylene glycol (PEG)ylated phosphatidylcholine (PC)-rich nanovesicles (phosphatiosomes) coated with soyaethyl morphonium ethosulfate (SME), facilitated the antibiotic release and accumulation of ciprofloxacin in the lungs of a rat model of MRSA lung infection, thus resulting in lower lung bacterial counts compared to the animals that were treated with free ciprofloxacin [
 <xref rid="B50-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. In another recent study, a new nano-emulsion (comprised of oils, surfactants and co-surfactants that increased the solubilization of the broad-spectrum antifungal factor sulconazole (SCZ) was synthesized and when tested in SD male rats, showing a higher skin penetration capacity and stronger inhibitory activity against 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> and 
 <italic>Trichophyton rubrum</italic> compared to the commercial miconazole cream [
 <xref rid="B51-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Likewise, such approaches have been tested for the ocular delivery of anti-microbials as well. A nano-emulsion made from Tween-80, Soluphor
 <sup>®</sup> P, ethyl-olate and deionized water was used as a vehicle for the ocular delivery of the antibiotic moxifloxacin, in the irritated eyes of Albino rats. Although the nano-emulsion did not affect the anti-microbial activity of moxifloxacin, it did prolong the contact time and release of the antibiotic in the eye, accelerating the recovery process [
 <xref rid="B52-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. In the same manner, nanoparticles carrying ofloxacin (with PEGylated lipids and chitosan) enhanced the drug-mucoadhesion strength that could be linked to better therapeutic outcomes [
 <xref rid="B53-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. 
 <xref rid="pharmaceutics-12-00688-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> summarizes the anti-microbial effects of surfactants against common pathogens: 
</p>
