<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 5.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Structure of SFTSV CBD and m
   <sup>7</sup>GTP binding. (
   <bold>A</bold>) The figure shows SFTSV CBD crystal structure in complex with an m
   <sup>7</sup>GTP. SFTSV CBD is presented as a ribbon diagram with the side chains of the two aromatic residues (F1703, Y1719) involved in stacking interaction with the m
   <sup>7</sup>GTP ligand shown as sticks. m
   <sup>7</sup>GTP is presented as lines and the surrounding electron density (2|Fo|-|Fc| omit map at 2.0σ) as gray mesh. (
   <bold>B</bold>) In a close-up of the m
   <sup>7</sup>GTP binding site, the protein is shown as ribbon diagram and side chains involved in m
   <sup>7</sup>GTP binding as well as the carbonyl oxygen of residue D1771 are presented as sticks. The m
   <sup>7</sup>GTP is shown as lines. The residues I1774, I1738, N1745, are involved in stabilizing the binding site cavity, D1771 (carbonyl oxygen), Q1707 and L1772 directly interact with m
   <sup>7</sup>GTP. A detailed list of interactions between the CBD and the m
   <sup>7</sup>GTP ligand is given in 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S4</xref> and a ligand plot in 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figure S13A</xref>. (
   <bold>C</bold>) Thermal stability of SFTSV CBD and influenza A virus PB2 CBD was tested in the presence and absence of different concentrations (2.5, 5.0, 7.5 and 10 mM) of m
   <sup>7</sup>GTP, m
   <sup>7</sup>GpppG, GTP and ATP. The melting temperatures (
   <italic>T</italic>
   <sub>m</sub>) are presented as mean and standard deviations of three independent measurements (
   <italic>n</italic> = 3). (
   <bold>D</bold>) The affinity of SFTSV CBD for m
   <sup>7</sup>GTP and GTP was measured by isothermal titration calorimetry at 25°C. A representative titration curve is shown. Titrations were done three times with 150 μM SFTSV CBD in the cell and 5.0–6.5 mM m
   <sup>7</sup>GTP or GTP in the syringe. The upper panel shows the raw data, the lower panel the integrated data fitted to a single-site binding model with the stoichiometry fixed to 1. The dissociation constant 
   <italic>K</italic>
   <sub>D</sub> is given as a mean and standard deviation of three independent measurements for m
   <sup>7</sup>GTP.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="gkaa253fig5" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
