<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>293T cells and DF-1 cells were transfected with pCAGGS plasmids encoding the wild-type or mutant PB2, PB1, PA or NP genes of EG/2013 and G1/1997 and a human or chicken polymerase-I driven plasmid encoding a full-length NA vRNA or cRNA template to reconstitute the NA RNP. At 24 h post-transfection, viral RNAs were extracted from the cells with an RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen) and treated with RNase-free DNase Set (Qiagen) to eliminate any residual transfected plasmid DNA. cDNAs derived from NA vRNA, cRNA and mRNA were reverse transcribed with the tagged primers listed in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1007919.s007">S1 Table</xref> and the hot-start modification of the SuperScript III first-strand synthesis system (Invitrogen) using saturated trehalose [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007919.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The same tags, as described elsewhere [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007919.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], were used and the primers were designed to target both EG/2013 and G1/1997 NA. Quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR) was performed using the PowerUp SYBR Green Master Mix (ThermoFisher) with the strand-specific primers listed in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1007919.s007">S1 Table</xref>. The qPCR cycle conditions were 50째C for 2 min and 95째C for 2 min, followed by 40 cycles of 95째C for 15 sec and 60째C for 1 min. Serial 10-fold dilutions (10
 <sup>9</sup>, 10
 <sup>8</sup>, 10
 <sup>7</sup>, 10
 <sup>6</sup>, 10
 <sup>5</sup>, 10
 <sup>4</sup>, 10
 <sup>3</sup> and 10
 <sup>2</sup> copies) of 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> transcribed viral RNA standards were used to generate a standard curve. The specificity of strand-specific qRT-PCR was tested using an NA gene that was amplified by PCR using a human polymerase-I driven plasmid encoding a full-length EG/2013 NA vRNA template. The primers, listed in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1007919.s008">S2 Table</xref>, were designed to include T7 promoter sequences to produce template vRNA, cRNA and mRNA. PCR products were purified by a PCR Purification Kit (Qiagen). Template vRNA, cRNA and mRNA were transcribed 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> using the RiboMax Large-Scale RNA Production System-T7 (Promega). Reverse transcription was performed with 10
 <sup>9</sup> copies of each template RNA (vRNA, cNRA and mRNA) using the tagged primers described above. The cDNA products were quantified by qPCR reactions using the strand-specific primer sets described above.
</p>
