<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Due to intensive agriculture, pesticide, and insecticide use and urbanization, the mammal biodiversity in Belgium is in almost all habitats changed. Although 21 rodent and 6 insectivore species are endemic in Belgium (Wilson and Reeder, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B168">2005</xref>), trapping data – as obtained in the forenamed 1999–2008 study of the Belgian Ministry of Defense – reveals that only five rodent (
 <italic>Microtus arvalis</italic>, 
 <italic>M. glareolus</italic>, 
 <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic>, 
 <italic>Apodemus flavicollis</italic>, 
 <italic>Rattus norvegicus</italic>) and two insectivore species (
 <italic>Sorex araneus</italic>, 
 <italic>Crocidura leucodon</italic>) are readily captured in live traps. In the study Ugglan Special No2 traps (Grahnab, Gnosjö, Sweden) that are suitable for trapping the vast majority of 
 <italic>Apodemus</italic>, 
 <italic>Myodes</italic>, 
 <italic>Microtus</italic>, 
 <italic>Sorex</italic>, and 
 <italic>Crocidura</italic> species were used. 
 <italic>Talpa europaea</italic> is also common but requires a specific trapping strategy due to its subterranean life. In Belgium, 
 <italic>M. arvalis</italic> is the carrier for Tula virus (TULV; Heyman et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">2002a</xref>), 
 <italic>M. glareolus</italic> carries PUUV, and 
 <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic> is a spill-over host for PUUV (Heyman et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">2009b</xref>), 
 <italic>A. flavicollis</italic> carries Dobrava virus (DOBV) but this virus is so far not found in Belgium, 
 <italic>R. norvegicus</italic> carries Seoul virus (SEOV) which is readily present in Belgian rural brown rats (Heyman et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">2009a</xref>) but to this point no human cases have been detected. The remaining 22 species are rare (Pucek, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B127">1989</xref>). It is generally regarded that high biodiversity has a diluting effect for pathogen transfer to a single host (Mills, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B113">2006</xref>; Peixoto and Abramson, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B122">2006</xref>; Keesing et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">2010</xref>), deteriorating landscape and subsequent decrease of biodiversity could thus favor hantavirus infections. The disturbance of trophic interactions is considerable for virtually all species (Olsson et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B117">2010</xref>).
</p>
