<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The roles that each subset of T cells play in the joint swelling during CHIKV infection is illustrated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. Despite their participation in CHIKV immunopathology, they have the potential to be included as mediators of effective anti-CHIKV vaccine strategies. Although researchers have been investigating experimental vaccines against CHIKV, most of these still rely on antibodies to neutralize the viruses (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>–
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). Furthermore, some of the CHIKV vaccines have been demonstrated to protect against other alphaviruses, such as RRV (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) and O'nyong'nyong virus (ONNV) (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). In the RRV challenge study, the lowest effective dose (0.1 μg virus) that conferred complete protection (denoted as the absence of viremia) did not increase the antibody response against CHIKV. Full protection only happens when the authors increased the dosage to 10 μg (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). This observation suggests that T cells may be instrumental in conferring protection at the lower doses. However, vaccination with recombinant baculovirus expressing CHIKV envelope proteins caused aged mice (&gt;18 months old) to become more susceptible to CHIKV infection (
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>), which was partly explained by the lower antibody titers in the aged mice. Although antigenic variations among CHIKV isolates are not prevalent currently, subtle changes in the CHIKV proteome was demonstrated to affect the neutralizing effect of pre-existing anti-CHIKV antibodies (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>). Thus, any mutation that results in reproductive-competent virus and yet abolishes antibody binding to CHIKV epitopes may result in future pandemic outbreaks.
</p>
