<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the absence of approved antiviral agents and vaccines, the most effective strategies are based on the disruption of the transmission cycle of the virus (human-to-human) via droplets or close contact. To achieve this, the most critical step would involve maintaining strict hand hygiene and adherence to basic cough etiquettes, across all strata from children to the elderly. A study reported the employment of prevention and control strategies at three levels: case-related population, general population, and national level [
 <xref rid="B132-pathogens-09-00519" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>]. Additionally, the National Health Commission of China issued protocols for the mitigation of COVID-19 in order to contain the further spread of the virus by a “big isolation and big disinfection” policy during the Chinese spring festival [
 <xref rid="B133-pathogens-09-00519" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>]. A national-level mitigation strategy has also been adopted for the elderly population and in rural areas [
 <xref rid="B134-pathogens-09-00519" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>,
 <xref rid="B135-pathogens-09-00519" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>]. Awareness regarding the connotations of hand hygiene amongst the general public, instead of stressing the usage of masks, is the need of the hour in view of the multiple modes of transmission. The use of sanitizers or soaps is one of the essential components of the prevention and control of COVID-19. Sanitizers containing 60–70% ethanol or 70% isopropanol are effective against SARS-CoV-2. Similarly, household detergents or soaps are also useful in sanitization. While sanitizers are sufficient for relatively clean hands, soiled hands need to be washed using soap and water for 20 s. Additionally, the WHO issued guidelines on the use of face masks during homecare visits and in the community, along with health care settings in the context of COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="B136-pathogens-09-00519" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>]. Moreover, the use of particulate respirators, such as certified N95 or FFP2, is recommended for health care workers who perform aerosol-generating procedures.
</p>
