<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">An emerging respiratory disease COVID-19 started to circulate among human in December 2019. Since its first outbreak in China from an unknown origin, it quickly became a global pandemic. As of May 26, 2020, there are 343,562 deaths among 5,406,282 confirmed cases in 215 countries (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019</ext-link>). The etiological pathogen of COVID-19 is a new coronavirus, the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), also called novel coronavirus (nCoV-2019). As the name indicates, SARS-CoV-2 is similar to SARS-CoV, the virus that causes severe acute respiratory symptoms in human and killed 774 people among 8098 infected worldwide in 2003.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>
 </sup> SARS-CoV-2 shares ~82% of sequence identity with SARS-CoV and to a less extent with Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) (~50%).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>
 </sup> SARS-CoV-2 is an enveloped, positive-sense, single-stranded RNA virus that belongs to the β-lineage of the coronavirus.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup> The β-lineage also contains two other important human pathogens, the SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV. The mortality rate of COVID-19 is around 6.35% as of May 26, 2020, which is lower than that of SARS (~10%) and MERS (~34%).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>
 </sup> However, current data indicate that COVID-19 is more contagious and has a larger R0 value than SARS and MERS
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup>, resulting in higher overall death tolls than SARS and MERS. The SARS-CoV-2 virus is currently spreading at an alarming speed in Europe and the United States.
</p>
