<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>By using metatranscriptomics, we confirm E11 as the genotype causing the nosocomial outbreaks and the three fatal cases sampled in this study. The retrospective surveillance in Guangdong also identifies E11 infections are associated with a wide range of symptoms including ARI, AFP, and HFMD cases. Previous surveillance data from the USA indicates that E11 infection causes fatal infections in 4.6 per cent of the cases, which is higher than infections with most of the other enterovirus genotypes (
 <xref rid="veaa029-B17" ref-type="bibr">Khetsuriani et al. 2006</xref>). The most serious, potentially fatal clinical presentation caused by E11 is neonatal systemic illness, presenting like a hepatitis-hemorrhage syndrome (
 <xref rid="veaa029-B26" ref-type="bibr">Nagington 1982</xref>; Khetsuriani et al. 2006). In this study, we found that pneumonia or acute respiratory diseases were observed in fatal cases at the onset of illness. In addition to the viral reads, RNA metatranscriptomics provided rRNA and mRNA profiles (
 <xref rid="veaa029-B3" ref-type="bibr">Bashiardes, Zilberman-Schapira, and Elinav 2016</xref>). 
 <italic>Micrococcus luteus</italic> was the commonly detected and dominant bacteria in oropharyngeal, anal, and blood samples from all three fatal cases (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="veaa029-F1">Fig. 1B–D</xref>). Similar with the dynamic of E11, the increasing level of 
 <italic>M. luteus</italic> transcriptomes is also observed accompany with the illness progression of Case 5 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="veaa029-F1">Fig. 1D</xref>, left panel). 
 <italic>Micrococcus luteus</italic> is a constituent of the normal human bacterial flora that inhabit or contaminate the skin, mucosa, and the oropharynx, but has been reported as opportunistic pathogen for immunocompromised patients, associated with bacteremia (
 <xref rid="veaa029-B27" ref-type="bibr">Peces et al. 1997</xref>), pneumonia (
 <xref rid="veaa029-B8" ref-type="bibr">Dürst et al. 1991</xref>), septic arthritis (
 <xref rid="veaa029-B1" ref-type="bibr">Albertson 1978</xref>), endocarditis, and meningitis (
 <xref rid="veaa029-B10" ref-type="bibr">Fosse et al. 1985</xref>). The co-occurrence of 
 <italic>M. luteus</italic> and E11 virus is associated with these severe cases is worth further investigation.
</p>
