<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our model provides fine-scale, high coverage surveillance of ILI in the United States, allowing for a better understanding of influenza spatio-temporal patterns. Through an examination of significant group effects, we observed that South Atlantic states may experience longer and more acute seasons than other parts of the U.S during both seasonal and pandemic influenza scenarios and across ILI surveillance for children and adults. Our results also suggest that county-level spatial dependence and state effects explain a substantial part of the variation in epidemic intensity, while county-level spatial dependence and season effects best capture variation in epidemic duration. The explanatory power of county spatial dependence for surveillance models in both measures adds evidence to the importance of local mobility in the spatial spread and distribution of influenza disease burden [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006020.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006020.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Moreover, we posit that state groupings explained variation in epidemic intensity because state-level policy recommendations and laws drive the probability for influenza infection and seeking of insured healthcare. For instance, influenza vaccination guidelines and access to free vaccinations are driven by local policy recommendations, and insurance policies are tied to state-level rules and regulations. Additional evidence for this hypothesis comes from our 2009 pandemic model where state effects also played a large role in explaining the variance in the data. On the other hand, variation in epidemic duration was better captured by season-level effects, and fixed effects that varied more between seasons than within them (e.g., influenza A/H3 and B circulation) were significant, similar to other studies [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006020.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. We hypothesize that the duration of heightened ILI activity is more closely tied to population-level susceptibility and the identities of the predominantly circulating strains —factors that are likely to vary more across seasons than across space.
</p>
