<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">Although people have been hunting wild species for food for millennia, there has been a marked increase in the harvest of wild species over the last several decades (Milner-Gulland and Bennett 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2003</xref>; Ziegler 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">2010</xref>). For example, the development of industrial logging in Republic of Congo has led to a 69 % increase in the population of logging towns and a 64 % increase in bushmeat supply (Poulsen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2009</xref>). The emergence of market-based economies and the commercialization of wild-harvest animals in urban centers have further increased demand. The scale of the trade in wild-harvest meat has also changed considerably due to advances in hunting practices, population growth, and increasing accessibility to remote areas (Nyaki et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2014</xref>). The trade of wild-harvested meat for food can now be viewed as a continuum ranging from subsistence-based rural consumption to commercial hunting for the international trade in wild animal meat and products (e.g., exotic food and traditional medicine), with this leading to dramatic price point differences (Brashares et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2011</xref>; Chaber et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2010</xref>). For example, bushmeat traders have reported pricing per kg of wild meat in Paris markets at up to double the price of domestic meat for sale in French supermarkets (Chaber et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2010</xref>). Similarly, in New York, USA, smoked duiker (an antelope) from Ghana can be readily attained, although at up to 25 times the cost of the same species sold near its source (Brashares et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2011</xref>). Such “urban” demand, which also occurs locally, places a premium on wild species and often permits local hunters to earn incomes comparable to or higher than local wages for other occupations, sustaining commercial hunting on a large scale (Schulte-Herbrüggen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">2013</xref>). Market factors thus provide a significant additional incentive for wild harvest beyond the protein needs of an individual hunter or family.
</p>
