<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>DENV ADE has been observed in animal models. Second heterotypic DENV2 infections produced enhanced viremia but not vascular permeability in rhesus monkeys 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>
 </sup>. Efforts to reliably achieve vascular permeability disease during second heterotypic DENV infections in animals, including mice, have not been successful 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>
 </sup>. When DENV antibodies were passively transferred to rhesus monkeys prior to infection with DENV2, enhanced viremias were observed but without vascular permeability. Administration of monoclonal or polyclonal dengue antibodies to mice has regularly resulted in enhanced DENV infections accompanied by vascular permeability and other features of DVPS 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>
 </sup>. Also, it has been possible to produce vascular permeability in DENV-infected infant mice born to dengue-immune mothers 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>
 </sup>. But other hypotheses of severe dengue pathogenesis that attribute disease (1) to a weakened ability of secondary T cells to contain DENV infection because of the original antigenic sin phenomenon, (2) to the hyper-production of endothelium-damaging secondary infection T-cell cytokines and chemokines, (3) to the DENV non-structural protein 1 (NS1) heterophile antibodies raised during first DENV infections that damage platelets, endothelial cells, or blood clotting proteins during second infections, or (4) to the ability of dengue IgG immune complexes to stimulate mast cells to release vasoactive amines fail to satisfy the requirements of Occam’s razor 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>– 
  <xref rid="ref-86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>
 </sup>. None of these hypotheses explains the phenomenon of infant DVPS where B- and T-cell responses are primary and anti-DENV or anti-NS1 IgG antibody concentrations at the onset of illness are absent or very low.
</p>
