<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The influenza PB1 component contains the RdRp catalytic site and is the core of the viral polymerase complex (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00560-f002">Figure 2</xref>A). Similarly to others viral RdRp, the structure of IAV PB1 has the characteristic right hand fold, containing fingers, palm, and thumb domains that include the classic pre-A (or F) and A-E polymerase motifs (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00560-f002">Figure 2</xref>A), although IAV RdRp is bigger than other viral polymerases (compare 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00560-f002">Figure 2</xref>A for IAV RdRp and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00560-f002">Figure 2</xref>D for poliovirus polymerase) [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B78-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,
 <xref rid="B83-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>,
 <xref rid="B85-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. These conserved polymerase regions have been mapped in the central region of PB1 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00560-f003">Figure 3</xref>A). However, IAV PB1 needs the cap-binding action of PB2 and the endonuclease activity of PA to carry out viral mRNA synthesis [
 <xref rid="B87-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>], making the whole transcriptase complex significantly larger than the core RdRp that is often contained within a single protein in other RNA viruses. IAV PB1 possess N- and C-terminal domains that interact with PA and PB2, respectively, to stabilize this complex (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00560-f003">Figure 3</xref>A). Moreover, PB1 contains a NLS (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-10-00560-f003">Figure 3</xref>A), although it has also been observed that PB1 depends on an interaction with IAV PA for its nuclear import [
 <xref rid="B90-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. Importantly, because the unique characteristics of the viral RdRp and the crucial role of PB1 for RNA synthesis, IAV PB1 is a promising target for the generation and identification of novel antivirals to treat influenza infections [
 <xref rid="B62-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B91-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>].
</p>
