<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Foot-and-mouth disease (FMD) is one of the world’s most important infectious diseases of livestock.
 <xref rid="b1-ijn-9-5603" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Currently available FMD vaccines are mainly based on inactivated viral antigens formulated with various proprietary adjuvants.
 <xref rid="b2-ijn-9-5603" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Despite tremendous progress in FMD vaccine production in recent years, the use of conventional and chemically inactivated FMD virus (FMDV) vaccines is associated with a number of concerns and deficiencies:
 <xref rid="b3-ijn-9-5603" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>–
 <xref rid="b5-ijn-9-5603" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> (1) large doses are required and induce only a short duration of immunity and a limited spectrum of antiviral immune responses; (2) unless highly purified, the vaccines do not allow differentiation between infected and vaccinated animals; (3) animals vaccinated with the current vaccines are generally protected against disease and induce serum immunoglobulin (Ig)G antibodies but have low stimulation of secretory IgA (sIgA) at respiratory mucosal sites and show sporadic CD8
 <sup>+</sup> cytotoxic T lymphocytes; and (4) the current vaccines requires 7–14 days to induce protection.
 <xref rid="b6-ijn-9-5603" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> The time for protection to develop leaves an immunity gap, a window of susceptibility prior to induction of the adaptive immune response in which vaccinated animals are still susceptible to disease; (5) protection is short-lived, often requiring frequent revaccination, and manipulation of large amounts of virulent virus could result in viral dissemination; (6) vaccination does not prevent colonization of the upper respiratory tract and development of the carrier state.
 <xref rid="b7-ijn-9-5603" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="b8-ijn-9-5603" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> To address these issues and to induce an earlier onset of protection and longer duration of immunity, different vaccine administration routes, vaccine delivery systems, and alternative approaches to conventional vaccines are urgently needed.
</p>
