<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>At present, cases of COVID-19 continue to occur around the world, so the rate of asymptomatic infections cannot be accurately determined. Identification and isolation of asymptomatic patients is essential to control virus outbreaks. Various studies have shown that asymptomatic persons with SARS-CoV-2 infection are generally not discovered until after their families, relatives, friends or close contacts have symptoms that are diagnosed [
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26–28</xref>]. Therefore, in order to not miss any infected patients, it is best to perform screening for all close contacts of patients with confirmed or suspected infections [
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The main tests used to diagnosis COVID-19 are the SARS-CoV-2 nucleic acid test (NAT) of nasopharyngeal swab samples, the SARS-CoV-2 specific serological test and chest computed tomography (CT) scanning. NAT by reverse transcription-PCR (RT-PCR) is well established as the gold standard for the diagnosis of COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], but still the test is associated with false negatives due to problems with sample collection and the operating procedures [
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Therefore, for cases that are highly suspicious of COVID-19 but test negatively by NAT, diagnosis via screening with a SARS-CoV-2 specific serological test and chest CT scan may be of great value [
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In one study of 285 COVID-19 patients with acute antibody responses to SARS-CoV-2, in 19 days after the onset of symptoms, 100% of the patients were positive for antiviral IgG. Importantly, the seroconversion of IgG and IgM occurs simultaneously or sequentially, and the titers of IgG and IgM were found to be stable within 6 days after seroconversion [
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. However, if the NAT result is negative and the SARS-CoV-2 specific serological test is positive, the diagnosis still cannot be directly confirmed. It is necessary to continue to observe and conduct multiple NAT tests until either the NAT result is positive or the SARS-CoV-2 specific serological test is determined to be a false positive. A study conducted in the USA used 1020 serum specimens that were previously tested for HSV serology by western blotting in 2018 and 2019 (prior to SARS-CoV-2 circulation) and detected one false positive using the Abbott SARS-CoV-2 IgG test [
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. In addition, many studies on SARS-CoV-2 specific serological tests have shown that it is difficult to achieve 100% sensitivity and specificity [
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Thus, for now, the diagnosis of COVID-19 remains a challenge globally. No test method is completely mature and reliable, but the combination of multiple testing methods can improve the effectiveness of screening [
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] and avoid missed diagnoses and misdiagnoses as much as possible [
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].
</p>
