<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite the large burden of LTBI and risk of progression to active TB, pregnant women have been systematically excluded from the &gt;12 Phase III and postmarketing clinical studies of TB preventive therapy [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002882.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="pmed.1002882.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Data from nonpregnant individuals and small observational studies have informed the guidance for isoniazid preventive therapy (IPT) in pregnancy [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002882.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="pmed.1002882.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. The first randomized placebo-controlled trial to assess safety and optimal timing of IPT in HIV-infected pregnant women in high-TB-burden settings (IMPAACT P1078) was recently completed (
 <bold>
  <xref rid="pmed.1002882.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
 </bold>) [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002882.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The relative risks and benefits of immediate antepartum versus deferred postpartum IPT initiation was assessed and included careful monthly monitoring of maternal, fetal, pregnancy, and infant outcomes. No differences in maternal safety outcomes, maternal–infant TB, or infant safety outcomes were found between arms, but an increase in composite adverse pregnancy outcomes was observed in the immediate IPT arm. Shorter-course, efficacious TB preventive therapy regimens have been studied in nonpregnant adults [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002882.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="pmed.1002882.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. With greater advocacy and effort on behalf of groups focused on high-quality data for pregnant women, postmarketing trials assessing shorter LTBI regimens are also now underway or in development for pregnant women (
 <bold>
  <xref rid="pmed.1002882.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
 </bold>). These include IMPAACT P2001 (PK and safety of 3 months of weekly isoniazid and rifapentine [3HP]) and IMPAACT Concept 5021 (safety, tolerability, optimal timing, and PK of 3HP versus 1 month of daily isoniazid and rifapentine [1HP]).
</p>
