<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The strategy we describe here provides an efficient “cargo” gene that can be coupled with a gene-drive system to reduce or eliminate the risk of DENV transmission by mosquitoes. In fact, previous efforts have demonstrated effective Cas9-mediated homing-based gene drives in malaria vectors [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008103.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1008103.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>], and even 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008103.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Additionally, since homing-based drive systems quickly convert heterozygotes to homozygotes [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008103.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], linking the anti-DENV 1C19 scFv antibody described here to such a drive system could, in theory, rapidly convert wild mosquito populations into transgenic homozygotes that would be completely resistant to DENV transmission. Of paramount importance to the viability of such an approach is the evolutionary stability of the refractory transgene, specifically in terms of the likelihood of viral-resistant evolution. Indeed, several studies have shown that, in some contexts, DENV can rapidly evolve resistance in response to neutralizing antibodies [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008103.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008103.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>], and this may be especially likely in the TADV-A heterozygotes described in this study. However, this potentially can be managed through the selection of antibodies with mechanisms/epitopes that minimize the chance of evolved resistance and the use of a combination of distinct anti-DENV antibodies (many of which have been described, e.g.,[
 <xref rid="ppat.1008103.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008103.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1008103.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]), as well as a combination of antibody and non-antibody based DENV refractoriness transgenes (e.g., [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008103.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008103.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]; [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008103.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]; [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008103.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>])). The deployment of such a pan-serotype-targeting strategy could serve as an effective component of a comprehensive program to reduce the incidence and impact of DENV.
</p>
