<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par83">By providing a space only accessible to women and non-gender conforming people, Metzineres creates an environment for healing, training and recovery that addresses the challenges its participants face holistically. Through the physical space in El Raval and connections with other local social movements, networks and organisations, the organisation aims to meet basic needs, give social health care and provide a range of services and activities for healing, bonding, experience and wisdom sharing, self-defence, solidarity and mutual support. Focus group participants expressed the benefits of having access to a safe space, without any requirement to participate in any specific activity:
 <disp-quote>
  <p id="Par84">I come here every day, inject my dope safely, clean my clothes, sleep for a few hours knowing that nothing bad is going to happen, have something to eat, see a female doctor and participate in a workshop where I can make my own shampoo. And if I don’t want to do any of these, I can be just having a coffee with my friends [amigas], being some of them staff members.</p>
  <p id="Par85">It is the only place that I am allow to stay with my dog, he is my partner, I don’t want to leave him outside. It’s funny, they allow dogs but not men.</p>
 </disp-quote> Recognition of and solidarity with the common challenges and experiences of women who use drugs is a crucial part of the mission of Metzineres, shared by the women who attend the centre. In February 2019, Metzineres organised a meeting in Barcelona with the Eurasian Harm Reduction Association and the Association for Women’s Rights in Development and also invited other groups such as the International Network of Women who Use Drugs, the Women and Harm Reduction International Network and the European Network of People who Use Drugs. The meeting shared experiences and best practices and resulted in the Barcelona Declaration, recognising the gendered aspects of drug policy, and the disproportionate harms woman have to suffer as a consequence of structural inequalities. One focus group participant shared her experience of engaging in this forum:
 <disp-quote>
  <p id="Par86">It was amazing meeting women from around the world that have similar lives and problems than us. We could do more things together. It is hard to know that they cannot have access to methadone, as we do. Now we have the responsibility to fight not just for us but for our friends’ rights also.</p>
 </disp-quote>
</p>
