<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0115">Recombination processes involving S gene particularly, have been reported for SARS- and SARS-like CoV but also for HCoV-OC43. In the case of sister species HCoV-NL63 and HCoV-229E, recombination breakpoints are located near 3′- and 5′-end of the gene [
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,65]. S is a trimeric protein, which is cleaved into two subunits, the globular N-terminal S1 and the C-terminal S2 [
 <xref rid="bib0330" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Our analysis revealed that similarly to other genomic regions, the S1 subunit hosts many low-frequency SNVs, characterized by higher density compared to the rest of the S gene sequence (
 <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>-E). The S2 subunit is highly conserved [
 <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and contains two fusion peptides (FP, IFP) [
 <xref rid="bib0330" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. In S gene, the same rearrangement event has taken place in two samples analyzed in this study, located in nt24,000, which corresponds to the ∼200 nt linking region between FP and IFP (aa 812-813). This observation highlights a potential recombination hot-spot. Examining closely the secondary structure of the RNA genome around the breakpoints, we suggest a model where the palindromes 5′-UGGUUUU-3′ and 5′-AAAACCAA-3′, have served as donor-acceptor sequences during the recombination event, since they are both exposed in the single-stranded internal loops formed in a highly structured RNA pseudoknot (
 <xref rid="fig0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>-C). The RB domain of the S protein has been tested as a potential immunogen as it contains neutralization epitopes which appear to have a role in the induction of neutralizing antibodies [
 <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. It should be mentioned though that the S protein of SARS-CoV is the most divergent in all strains infecting humans [
 <xref rid="bib0335" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], as in both C and N-terminal domains variations arise rapidly, allowing immunological escape [
 <xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Our findings support that apart from these variations, the N-terminal region also hosts a recombination hot-spot, which together with the rest of the observed rearrangements, indicates the genomic instability of SARS-CoV-2 over poly-A and poly-U regions.
</p>
