<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our study aimed at identifying pathogens associated to febrile illnesses in Madagascar. To our knowledge, few studies on etiologies of fever have targeted outpatients’ febrile diseases etiologies widely in a country[
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], as most focused on severe illnesses and/or children[
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Due to non-specificity of some infections and the varieties of pathogens that may circulate concomitantly in tropical countries like Madagascar, laboratory confirmation is needed to estimate the prevalence of each of the pathogens associated to febrile illnesses in the community. We detected at least one pathogen in almost half of the febrile outpatients attending our 21 sentinel sites throughout the country. In this study, ILI was the leading cause of consultation, which is in line with our laboratory results as respiratory viruses were the predominant pathogens detected. Due to financial constraints, we only tested four of these viruses that were found as the most prevalent in previous studies[
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Thus, our detection rate (20.2%) may represent an underestimate in light that other common respiratory viruses such as parainfluenza viruses, human metapneumovirus and coronaviruses might have been detected. This result is consistent with other studies[
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] where proportions of respiratory viruses detected in nasopharyngeal swabs varied between 11% and 20% and where acute respiratory infections were the major cause of healthcare seeking behavior. In our study, two thirds of patients were under 15 years of age thus explaining the high prevalence of acute respiratory infections[
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Malaria was the second etiology detected followed by viral infection detected in the blood. One patient tested positive for HIV and had a clinical presentation of low grade fever, asthenia, mild cough, lymphadenopathy and leucorrhea. This patient previously tested positive for HIV but had been lost to follow-up on treatment. This situation highlights the need to strengthen screening, care, treatment and follow-up of HIV infections in Madagascar, despite the low prevalence of the infection in the country compared to neighboring African countries[
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. We found a prevalence of active Tuberculosis (TB) infection of 0.6% which is higher that estimated prevalence of tuberculosis in Madagascar (237 per 100 000 populations per year in 2016)[
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. This could emphasize the underestimation of TB diagnosis in health care centers. In addition, TB in children is often missed due to non-specific symptoms and difficulties in diagnosis, thus our results might also underestimate the number of TB cases since we were only able to test patients with productive cough and able to produce sputum. We used predominantly molecular assays to detect pathogens in specimens, allowing high sensitivity of detection although carriage may not necessarily be related to the clinical event[
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. A comparison group of healthy individuals would have allowed us to describe the background level of carriage in the asymptomatic population and estimate the probability that a detected pathogen is truly responsible of the illness. To detect potential multiple infections, we performed the same analyses on all patients regardless of their clinical status. We are aware that this approach cannot be used in an operational manner, but some infrequent pathogens would have been missed if tests had been guided by clinical characteristics. Thus, it allows us to obtain a deeper profile of febrile-associated pathogens. But more importantly, our study allowed us to detect one case of infection with 
 <italic>Leptospira spp</italic>. To our knowledge, this is the first leptospirosis laboratory-confirmed case detected in Madagascar, in Maroantsetra, a city located in a per humid area of the eastern coast. To date, all studies regarding leptospirosis in Madagascar are related to its reservoir or based on serological surveys[
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Only three cases of human leptospirosis infection have already been described since 1955 and only one case of molecular confirmation has been described in La Réunion in a patient with an history of travel to Madagascar[
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. As described in previous leptospirosis case reports, this patient presented a suspicion of cholecystitis[
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Interestingly, no bacterial zoonoses diseases like Q fever or rickettsiosis described in other studies to be largely incriminated in fever cases[
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] were detected, nor arboviral infections. None of the 13.9% of Dengue-like Syndromes were confirmed with dengue virus or other common arboviruses tested, although investigation by IgM ELISA may detect cases that have passed the viremic phase otherwise missed by molecular tests. This emphasizes the low Positive Predictive Value of the DLS case definition when arboviruses (including dengue and chikungunya viruses) prevalence is low and probably its overall limited specificity. HBV was detected in the blood of six patients (0.9%) of which three were children below 5 years. Madagascar has a high-intermediate level of endemicity for HBV infection[
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. National immunization program introduced HBV vaccine in 2002 as part of the pentavalent vaccine after the age of six weeks. These results emphasize not only the need to improve vaccination coverage and prevention of mother to child transmission but also the necessity of scheduling a vaccine dose at birth to avoid perinatal infections. One case of infection with RVFV was detected in a child with initial mumps clinical diagnosis. Several RVFV epidemics occurred in Madagascar in past years[
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006642.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] but as far as we know, no human case was identified during inter-epidemic periods. Our recent data on malnutrition in children less than 5 years are in line with the Millennium Development Goals (MDG) survey 2012–2013, highlighting the need to continue and expand interventions in Madagascar to tackle these conditions.
</p>
