<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">Anonymized call detail records (CDRs) were collected over a two month period in 2011 by one of the mobile phone operators in Singapore with a significant market share (a statistical analysis is reported in Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S9</xref> in the supplementary materials.). The data includes more than 2 billion records in total and includes the approximate time and location of events (including phone calls and text messages). Locations are collected at the cell tower level with further noise applied for privacy reasons. We use this data to assign two “favorite” locations to each user: (i) home and (ii) work. In Singapore, according to a study by the Land Transport Authority, about 80% of all trips go to either a work or a home location
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup>. This implies that the infection with the dengue virus in Singapore very likely happens either at home or at work, thus we focus on commuting between these two locations when modeling human mobility in this paper. To estimate home and work locations, we perform a spatial clustering of the CDRs, creating overlapping clusters of events which are spatially close to each other (a threshold of 500 m was used so as to account for the potential uncertainty regarding which one of nearby antennas a phone connects to). To be able to distinguish between home and work locations, we performed this clustering procedure separately for records generated between 8 pm and 6am on weekdays and during weekend (for home locations) and records generated between 10 am and 4 pm on weekdays (for work locations). After this procedure, we selected the largest clusters for both cases and filtered the list of users who had at least 10 events in both clusters. Following this procedure, there are 2,307,230 users to whom we can assign a home and a work location. We then assign users’ home and work locations into a 
 <inline-formula id="IEq39">
  <alternatives>
   <tex-math id="M77">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$320\,m\times 320\,m$$\end{document}</tex-math>
   <math id="M78">
    <mn>320</mn>
    <mspace width=".25em"/>
    <mi>m</mi>
    <mo>×</mo>
    <mn>320</mn>
    <mspace width=".25em"/>
    <mi>m</mi>
   </math>
   <inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_53127_Article_IEq39.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </alternatives>
 </inline-formula> grid overlay 
 <italic>G</italic> which we use as the basis of the epidemic simulation. We display the distribution of these home and work locations in Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>, while we show the nonempty grid cells in Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S12</xref> in the Supplementary Material.
</p>
