<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Contingency planning involves 
 <italic>inter alia</italic> the acquisition and maintenance of resources, such as beds, ICU capacity, stocks of ventilators, protective clothing, and so forth, in the case of pandemics (e.g., Kain and Fowler, 
 <xref rid="emi15029-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>), that are 
 <italic>by definition</italic> surplus to day‐to‐day requirements, and that will only be used if and when the catastrophe occurs. It also includes the development of generic platforms for rapid responses; in the case of pandemics, the development and testing of diagnostics, vaccine candidates, and effective treatments (see also below). This entails a significant recurring budgetary commitment. Political and economic viewpoints that such costs are not cost‐effective are fundamentally flawed because they generally only take into account the immediate cost elements, not the potential overall cost of the crisis and all its knock‐on effects. These are being brutally revealed by the unfolding SARS‐CoV‐2 outbreak which, at this still early stage, is involving governmental support of national economies amounting collectively to trillions of dollars. And this is only the tip of the economic iceberg. Bankruptcies, loss of employment, recession, loss of tax revenues, large scale deterioration of existing medical conditions in populations, potentially wide‐scale deterioration of mental health, and so forth, and the economic costs of these, also need to be taken into account when reflecting on the cost of the contingency planning insurance policy. As an illustration of knock‐on effects, global economic estimates of the benefits of vaccination have also shown that they extend well beyond those estimated from prevention of the specific disease in vaccinated individuals (Bloom, 
 <xref rid="emi15029-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). It is also worth comparing crisis preparedness costs with military expenditures. The latter are indeed budgetary commitments for preparedness for another type of crisis, namely a military conflict (excepting countries that use their military for internal affairs). And, as is the case in epi/pandemic preparedness, a considerable fraction of military resources is dedicated to surveillance operations. While accepting that military expenditures are also justified in terms of deterrence of hostile actions, and a multitude of non‐combat roles armed forces may undertake, it is not self‐evident that future military conflicts may result in losses of life and economic damage as high as the current COVID‐19 pandemic. In any case, in terms of protecting citizens, it should be abundantly clear that effective contingency preparedness for pandemics, and other crises,
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="emi15029-note-0003">3</xref> should be equated with military preparedness, and budgeted accordingly.
 <list list-type="bullet" id="emi15029-list-0010">
  <list-item id="emi15029-li-0012">
   <p>
    <italic>The principle of citizen protection demands that governments budget for adequate crisis preparedness in the same way that they budget for military preparedness. It is simply one of several essential ‘insurance premiums’ to which the state must commit</italic>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
