<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although only discovered recently, the impact of PA-X on IAV-induced host shutoff is much greater than that of NS1. Studies in our lab using recombinant H1N1pdm09 viruses expressing active or inactive NS1 (on the basis of mutations in the conserved CPSF30 binding residues) or PA-X clearly indicate that PA-X is the major driving force in general host shutoff [
 <xref rid="B102-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. While the frameshift motif leading to PA-X expression is highly conserved amongst different strains of IAVs, the shutoff activity of PA-X is variable. Some studies, including ours, suggest that PA-X from human-adapted IAVs is less active than that of PA-X from avian-adapted IAVs. In agreement with this, H1N1pdm09 viruses expressed a PA-X protein with high shutoff activity likely due to their avian-origin PA gene [
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B101-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>,
 <xref rid="B103-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>,
 <xref rid="B104-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. The difference in shutoff activity between avian and human PA-X proteins is possibly due to mutations within the N-terminal domain that is shared with PA [
 <xref rid="B103-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>,
 <xref rid="B105-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Recent transcriptomic analysis indicates that a virus expressing shutoff active NS1 with reduced PA-X expression most efficiently suppresses antiviral and innate immune responses in human cells. Interestingly, it appears that the mRNA from the NS gene segment can also become a target of PA-X mediated degradation in infected cells [
 <xref rid="B102-viruses-12-00365" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. These studies suggests that IAV needs to finely tune the activities of these two shutoff proteins in order to circumvent host responses for optimum viral replication and transmission.
</p>
