<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This session opened with a keynote lecture from 
 <bold>Ed Gane</bold> (New Zealand Liver Transplant Unit, Auckland Hospital, New Zealand) entitled “Eradication of chronic hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection—translating clinical virology into practice.” Global elimination of HBV has become a reality due to the availability of a safe, effective and inexpensive vaccine but 300 million adults currently live with chronic HBV infection. Although nucleoside polymerase inhibitors can maintain viral suppression and reduce complications, life-long therapy is associated with high cost, risk of breakthrough and potential toxicity. Other steps of the HBV lifecycle can be targeted by small molecules including inhibitors of entry, capsid and virion assembly/release. Capsid assembly modulators (i) prevent encapsidation of pregenomic RNA (pgRNA) and block HBV replication; and (ii) inhibit de-novo formation of covalently closed circular DNA (cccDNA) by interfering with disassembly of the capsid. These inhibitors have recently been demonstrated to be synergistic with nucleos(t)ide analogues (NUCs) in reducing HBV DNA, pgRNA and HBsAg. Translation inhibitors such as small interfering RNAs and antisense oligonucleotides can silence multiple HBV transcripts, potentially blocking the production of the core, polymerase, surface, X-protein. The first clinical studies show potent suppression of HBsAg with only three doses. Chronic HBV infection is characterised by high viral load and antigen burden and inadequate host immune responses. Innovative approaches to restore innate and adaptive immune responses against HBV are currently in clinical development and include therapeutic vaccines, RIG-I agonists, and TLR-7 and TLR-8 agonists. Pilot studies with checkpoint inhibitors, which reverse T cell exhaustion, have also produced promising results. It is likely that HBV Cure will require combinations of novel immunomodulatory, antiviral and cccDNA silencing strategies. Efficacy, safety, route of administration and cost will ultimately determine the impact of these new regimens on the burden of HBV.
</p>
