<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The next step of the internalization is the release of the viral genome (RNA segments) into the cellular cytoplasm; this phase depends on the activity of Na
 <sup>+</sup>/K
 <sup>+</sup>-ATPase located in the endosomal membrane, which functions as a proton pump. Na
 <sup>+</sup>/K
 <sup>+</sup>-ATPase is responsible for the acidification of the internal environment of endosomes/lysosomes (to pH 5.0) (Cain, Sipe and Murphy 
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>). The acidification of the internal endosomal medium, i.e. the accumulation of protons (Н
 <sup>+</sup>) inside the endosomes, helps the tetramers of the M2 protein of the viral envelop to realize its potential as a protonophore (Sugrue and Hay 
 <xref rid="bib266" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>; Pinto, Holsinger and Lamb 
 <xref rid="bib214" ref-type="bibr">1992</xref>; Manzoor, Igarashi and Takada 
 <xref rid="bib167" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). When hydrogen ions enter a viral particle, it mediates conformational changes and decomposition of the structural components of the viral envelope, which finally leads to an increase in the lability of its genome (Shibata 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib241" ref-type="bibr">1983</xref>; Yoshimura and Ohnishi 
 <xref rid="bib309" ref-type="bibr">1984</xref>). However, the fusion of the viral envelope membrane and the endosomal membrane, which releases the RNA genome of the virus into the cellular cytoplasm, is possible only with the participation of the viral HA after the previous proteolytic processing with serine (secretory trypsin-like) proteases (Klink 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib143" ref-type="bibr">1975</xref>; Lazarowitz and Choppin 
 <xref rid="bib150" ref-type="bibr">1975</xref>; Tashiro 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib271" ref-type="bibr">1987</xref>; Steinhauer 
 <xref rid="bib264" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Kido 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib135" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>).
</p>
