<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0080">The risk of skin diseases is increasing after flooding and skin infections are considerable in these situations. These diseases are categorized as inflammatory skin diseases, traumatic skin diseases, wound infections and other miscellaneous skin diseases (
 <xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0205" ref-type="bibr">Tempark et al., 2013</xref>). Skin injuries are frequently occurred after natural disasters and may be resulted from glass/metal pieces under water or falling debris of buildings or trees. Wound contamination can occur through contact with contaminated water, soil, metal, wood and other debris. The destruction of infrastructures and unavailable clean water for washing the wounds, limited facilities to medical treatments and poor hygiene may lead to sever infection even with initial minor trauma. The most dangerous outcome of wound contamination with soil is tetanus and gas gangrene which are caused with (
 <italic>Clostridium tetani</italic>) and (
 <italic>Clostridium perfringens</italic>) respectively (
 <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Ivers and Ryan, 2006</xref>). Other frequent bacteria which are responsible for skin and soft-tissue infections are 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus, Streptococcus pyogenes, Aeromonas Spp., Vibrio spp., Shewanella spp., Leclerciaadecarboxylata, Chromobacterium violaceum</italic> and 
 <italic>Burkholderia</italic> (
 <xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">Paterson et al., 2018</xref>). However, bacteria are the most cause of skin infections post flooding but infections with fungal pathogens or poly microbial infections may occur (
 <xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">Paterson et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0205" ref-type="bibr">Tempark et al., 2013</xref>). Anaerobic infection, mucormycosis and melioidosis and cases of disseminated 
 <italic>Scedosporium apiospermum</italic> and 
 <italic>Mycobaceterium chelonae</italic> resulted from inoculation of soil pathogens can be considered a threat for wounds (
 <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Ivers and Ryan, 2006</xref>).
</p>
