<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13">Epidemiological studies suggest OUD can increase AIDS progression (Donahoe and Vlahov 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118">1998</xref>; Dronda et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120">2004</xref>; Meijerink et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR332">2014</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR333">2015</xref>). In the pre-cART era, opiate abuse was found to exacerbate HIV encephalitis (HIVE) (Bell et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">1998</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2002</xref>). In Indonesian injection heroin abusers who lacked access to cART, CD4 counts (a measure of HIV progression) were reduced compared to PWH not using heroin (Meijerink et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR332">2014</xref>). However, with the introduction of cART, the clinical picture has significantly changed with a 50% decline in the rate of death from AIDS, reduced incidence of opportunistic infections and HIVE, and a 40–50% decrease in the incidence of HIV-associated dementia (HAD), the most severe form of HIV-associated neurocognitive disorders (HAND) (Maschke et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR313">2000</xref>; McArthur et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR321">2010</xref>; Saylor et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR454">2016</xref>). Nevertheless, chronic opiate exposure (which almost always is confounded by the use of other illicit and legal drugs) in PWH can worsen neuroHIV (Anthony et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2005</xref>; Bell et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2006</xref>; Anthony et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2008</xref>) and cognitive impairment (Rodriguez Salgado et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR432">2006</xref>; Martin-Thormeyer and Paul 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR311">2009</xref>; Byrd et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2011</xref>; Smith et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR474">2014</xref>; Martin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR309">2018</xref>; Rubin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR440">2018</xref>) despite cART, even though some studies fail to show that opioids worsen neuroHIV (Royal et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR439">1991</xref>; Applebaum et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2010</xref>) or HAND (Martin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR310">2019</xref>). Opiate exposure in cART-treated PWH worsens CD4 counts and viral loads (Ryan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR444">2004</xref>), neuropathology (including increased tauopathy; Smith et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR474">2014</xref>), CNS inflammation (Anthony et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2005</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2008</xref>; Smith et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR474">2014</xref>), and neurocognition (Applebaum et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2009</xref>; Byrd et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2011</xref>; Meyer et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR336">2013</xref>) including deficits in memory and working memory (Byrd et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2011</xref>). Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> gives an overview on reported interactive effects of HIV and opioids in some of the clinical and preclinical CNS studies referenced in this review.
</p>
