<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Based on this there is considerable evidence [
 <xref rid="B105-vaccines-07-00203" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>,
 <xref rid="B106-vaccines-07-00203" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>,
 <xref rid="B137-vaccines-07-00203" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>], although mixed [
 <xref rid="B127-vaccines-07-00203" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>,
 <xref rid="B132-vaccines-07-00203" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>] which suggests that eliciting a carefully targeted CD8 response, possibly one with MHCI interactions involving long TCR engagement that elicit polyfunctional responses and/or against epitopes conserved across serotypes without variants [
 <xref rid="B106-vaccines-07-00203" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>,
 <xref rid="B127-vaccines-07-00203" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>,
 <xref rid="B137-vaccines-07-00203" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>] could achieve this goal (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="vaccines-07-00203-f003">Figure 3</xref>). Key benefits of this approach include the avoidance of antibody responses which may enhance infection or have autoreactivity to host. It also avoids the use of a tetravalent approach which increases the chances of raising unequal immune responses against each serotype due to differences in replication of each virus within a tetravalent vaccine. Although including CD4 epitopes such as ones raising neutralising antibodies against E would be protective, you need to be able to maintain high titers to prevent disease enhancement. Additionally, by using CD8 epitopes conserved across serotypes you ensure all genetic lineages are covered, avoiding the replacement of circulating lineages with more virulent lineages. Whilst avoiding CD4 epitopes also avoids ADE-mediated lineage replacement. Such an example candidate shows how a greater understanding of dengue correlates of protection could help to achieve the ideal cross-serotype prophylactic dengue vaccine and we hope that this review encourages further thoughts on the development of new and distinct dengue interventions.
</p>
