<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0160">The preclinical and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> potential of M2 Ser31Asn-inhibiting adamantane derivatives are now beginning to be elucidated. For example, Compounds 
 <bold>5</bold>, 
 <bold>8</bold>, 
 <bold>10</bold>, and 
 <bold>16</bold> have been reported to inhibited virus strains with resistance to the licensed neuramindase inhibitor oseltamivir (
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Hu et al., 2017a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib144" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2018</xref>). In oseltamivir-sensitive viruses, 
 <bold>5</bold> and 
 <bold>16</bold> also synergized with oseltamivir, raising the possibility of combination therapies where lower doses of drugs can be used to minimize the risk of toxicities without sacrificing antiviral efficacy (
 <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">Ma et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib144" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2018</xref>). Compound 
 <bold>16</bold> also exhibited favorable 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> pharmacokinetic properties such as half-life of at least 145 min in mouse and human liver microsome stability assays. It also exhibited good cellular permeability in Caco-2 cells (~28 × 10
 <sup>−6</sup> cm/s) and did not inhibit a panel of five CYP enzymes. (
 <xref rid="bib144" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2018</xref>). Additional M2 Ser31Asn adamantane-derived inhibitors have shown similar supportive preclinical results, indicating that these properties are fairly common for this chemical class (
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Hu et al., 2018</xref>). Furthermore, injection of mice with the dual-inhibitor compound 
 <bold>9</bold> at up to 100 mg/kg/day resulted in no changes in body weight. Importantly, at up to 100 mg/kg/day, compound 
 <bold>9</bold> also rescued mice from lethal infection of viruses containing either WT M2 or M2 Val27Ala, thereby demonstrating 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> efficacy (
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Hu et al., 2017a</xref>). While initial results are encouraging, 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> results for most adamantane derivatives remain limited and await further study.
</p>
