<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In most cases, epithelial cells are damaged during the primary viral infection, impeding mucociliary clearance that leads to an accumulation of mucus (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">Perry et al., 2005</xref>). Bacteria are able to diffuse into the mucus but thickened dense mucus impedes penetration of host immune cells. Secondary bacterial infections are also facilitated by the immune response of the host to a viral attack. One of the more important factors seems to be the immunosuppression of the host innate immune response initiated by the viral infection which facilitates opportunistic bacteria, like 
 <italic>Streptococcus</italic> to infect the host (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2011</xref>). Cells of a host suffering from a viral infection are more susceptible to bacterial attachment and colonization (
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Pittet et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">Nyangacha et al., 2017</xref>). Many viruses, including influenza virus, rhinovirus, and respiratory syncytial virus (RSV), have detrimental effects on the mucosal layer facilitating bacterial adherence of, e.g., 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic>, 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>, and 
 <italic>H. influenzae</italic>, as well as biofilm formation on the linings of the lungs (
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Morris, 2007</xref>). For some pulmonary viruses such as influenza, Toll-like receptor (TLR) pathways are altered, possibly from sustained de-sensitization, which results in an increase of attachment of bacteria to epithelial cells (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Kurt-Jones et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Haynes et al., 2001</xref>). TLR and RIG-I-like receptor activation results in the production of Type I Interferon, changing the inflammatory response to TLR ligands, e.g., bacterial lipopolysaccharide (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Doughty et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">Nansen and Thomsen, 2001</xref>). Polymicrobial, viral–bacterial co-infections can develop as a result of an altered immune response combined with accessible routes of entry for the bacterial pathogen(s).
</p>
