<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Second, when looking at journal publications, we noted that very similar patterns occurred for citations and publications. This result emphasizes that fewer publications, and hence fewer citations, translate into fewer papers in Q1 journals (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">4</xref>). Also, we observed the same patterns as Fire and Guestrin [
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], with most of the papers being published in Q1 journals and the minority published in Q2–Q4 journals. This trend started to change when zooming in and analyzing publications in top-10–ranked journals (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">5</xref>). While we can see some correlation to outbreaks in Ebola, swine flu, and SARS, it is harder to interpret the curve of HIV because there were no focused epidemics in the past 20 years but a global burden, and we did not observe similar patterns in publications and citations. Observing the JScore (Journal Trends section) results (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">6</xref>), most diseases showed a steady increase, but 2 diseases behaved rather anomalously. MERS had a decline since 2013, which is reasonable to expect after the initial outbreak, but we did not see the same trend in the other diseases and there is a general trend of increasing average SJR [
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The second anomaly is that SARS had an increase in JScore alongside a decrease in citations and publication numbers. Inspecting the data, we discovered that in 2017 there were 3 published papers in 
 <italic>Lancet Infectious Diseases</italic> and in 2015 2 papers in 
 <italic>Journal of Experimental Medicine</italic> about SARS, and both journals have a very high SJR. These publications increased the JScore drastically. This anomaly is a result of outliers in the data that biased the results. We can observe in Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">4</xref> that in the past decade the number of SARS papers published in ranked journals decreased drastically. It dropped low enough that 2 outliers created a bias on the JScore. Generally, the less data we have, the greater chance for outliers to cause bias in the data.
</p>
