<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The incubation period lasts about 10–14 days, then the fever appears up to over 40 °C accompanied with cough, coryza, and conjunctivitis. Pathognomonic for this pathology are Koplik spots, which occur the day before the onset of the rash and persist for 2 or 3 days. Koplik spots appear as bluish-white lesions, slightly raised by 2–3 mm, on a reddened base and are identifiable on the oral mucosa at the level of the first molar but may also occur at the level of the soft palate and vaginal mucosa [
 <xref rid="B30-microorganisms-08-00276" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-microorganisms-08-00276" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The early pre-rash symptoms are similar to those of other common respiratory illnesses. Gradually, the picture intensifies in 24–48 h, after which, in some cases, skin manifestations can also affect the palms. The rash lasts 3–7 days, in some cases followed by a fine scaling. An exaggerated desquamation is commonly observed in malnourished children [
 <xref rid="B32-microorganisms-08-00276" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-microorganisms-08-00276" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-microorganisms-08-00276" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Initially, the areas involved are those of the face, with a subsequent distribution in 2–3 days of the caudal skull (erythematous macules of 3–8 mm subsequently confluent); instead, a cough can persist for up to 10 days. Accompanying these signs are other symptoms, such as photophobia from iridocyclitis, pharyngodynia, headache, abdominal pain, and mild generalized lymphadenopathy. Based on the signs described above, a clinical diagnosis can be made: The combination of generalized maculopapular rash, fever (≥38 °C), and either cough, coryza, or conjunctivitis has a high sensitivity (75–90%) but a low positive predictive value when the incidence of measles is low, hence the need for serological confirmation [
 <xref rid="B35-microorganisms-08-00276" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Transaminases elevation is a common finding, with two thirds of measles patients experiencing it [
 <xref rid="B36-microorganisms-08-00276" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. In the past, measles-associated hepatitis was thought to be related to the severity of the infection, but this has not been confirmed. Measles hepatitis is more common in children than in adults, the damage is generally hepatocellular rather than cholestatic, and is caused by a direct viral action [
 <xref rid="B37-microorganisms-08-00276" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-microorganisms-08-00276" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].
</p>
