<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Epidemiological investigations have played major roles in mitigating COVID-19. In the context of an emerging virus, epidemiologists gather data regarding new cases, including their timing, location, origin, and outcome. The data are based on diagnosed cases that present symptoms, as well as on laboratory-confirmed cases of infection, which could also be asymptomatic. Potential animal reservoirs and sources of environmental contamination are also being evaluated. The collected data are incorporated into models that illustrate modes of transmission, such as droplet infection, and predict the infection spread. Populations at high risk for infection and severe outcome, such as the elderly or individuals with chronic disease, can also be identified via epidemiologic investigation. Among other parameters, the prediction of disease spread is based on the basic reproductive number (
 <italic>R0</italic>) representing the average number of people who will become infected directly by a single infected individual. One of the goals of epidemic containment is to restrain the transmission of the virus and reduce 
 <italic>R0</italic>, which is modulated by the time interval of viral shedding, viral infectiousness, and the interface that mediates transmission between infected and susceptible individuals. Understanding how a virus spreads in a population, together with knowledge on the virus stability in the environment (e.g. aerosol, water, or different surfaces), helps develop guidelines for prevention and containment. Sequence analysis of viral genomes may also help tracking virus dissemination within a population. Epidemiology also allows determination of case fatality rate (CFR), although it is very difficult to determine this value during an ongoing outbreak, in particular when the number of asymptomatic infections is high. Finally, research has shown that people become infectious before any symptoms of illness appear, during the pre-symptomatic incubation period, while others do not develop a disease and remain asymptomatic. Asymptomatic individuals may be those in whom the virus replication is low and therefore their ability to spread the virus is limited. However, because disease symptoms are affected by the immune response, lack of symptoms may reflect a well-balanced immune response and does not necessarily correlate with high or low viral loads. Either way, it is interesting to examine the relationship between the severity of the disease and the response of the innate, humoral and cellular immune systems over time. Knowing the proportion of asymptomatic infections and whether asymptomatic individuals are contagious and can spread the virus are top public health objectives which may help define ways to avoid infections, such as wearing masks and social distancing.
</p>
