<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat.1007462.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007462.g001</object-id>
 <label>Fig 1</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Diverse array of research projects related to understanding the effect of CoRSV on coffee.</title>
  <p>(A) Whether enjoyed alone or in the company of others, coffee is an integral component of daily life in all countries around the world. Only one small-scale study has been done to determine the effect of CoRSV on coffee quality [
   <xref rid="ppat.1007462.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. (B) The effect of CoRSV on the yield of coffee plants has not been examined. (C) No formal investigations have been made to determine how CoRSV influences the development of coffee cherries. (D) Only one study has investigated the population structure of CoRSV [
   <xref rid="ppat.1007462.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
   <xref rid="ppat.1007462.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. It remains to be determined if phylogenetic trees derived from different CoRSV genes or from viral RNA isolated from plants or mites are congruent. Furthermore, evidence for recombination or reassortment of CoRSV genomes has not been investigated in detail. (E) The reservoir of CoRSV in wild species, particularly in the Cerrado of Brazil, has not been investigated. It is unknown if the population structure of CoRSV in the wild is similar to that in coffee plants. (F) The molecular basis for temperature dependent susceptibility to systemic infections has not been determined [
   <xref rid="ppat.1007462.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. (G) The cell biology of CoRSV beyond generation of protein interaction and localization maps is poorly characterized, particularly with respect to identification of host factors required for replication and cell-to-cell movement, viroplasm formation, and nucleocytoplasmic trafficking of CoRSV nucleocapsids and proteins [
   <xref rid="ppat.1007462.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. CoRSV, coffee ringspot virus; NPC, nuclear pore complex; VP, viroplasm; XPO1, Exportin 1.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1007462.g001" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
