<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Here, the antiviral activities of LiCl and DG, which are both HAAs, were studied against PDCoV. LiCl can inhibit the replication of a variety of viruses, including Herpesvirus type 1 (HSV-1) [
 <xref rid="B24-pathogens-08-00144" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], transmissible gastroenteritis virus (TGEV) [
 <xref rid="B25-pathogens-08-00144" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome virus (PRRSV) [
 <xref rid="B26-pathogens-08-00144" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], pseudorabies virus (PRV) [
 <xref rid="B27-pathogens-08-00144" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], and porcine epidemic diarrhea virus (PEDV) [
 <xref rid="B28-pathogens-08-00144" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. LiCl can also regulate apoptosis and promote resumption of the synthesis of host proteins in infected cells [
 <xref rid="B25-pathogens-08-00144" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-pathogens-08-00144" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Recent studies showed that LiCl could effectively inhibit the entry and replication of PEDV in Vero cells in a dose-dependent manner [
 <xref rid="B28-pathogens-08-00144" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. In addition, LiCl can inhibit early and late apoptosis induced by PEDV. PDCoV and PEDV belong to the family Coronaviridae and have similar genomic structure. However, antiviral drugs against PDCoV have not been researched. Therefore, we explored whether LiCl could inhibit infection by PDCoV. The licorice extract isolated from the rhizome of 
 <italic>Glycyrrhiza uralensis</italic> has a strong antiviral activity [
 <xref rid="B29-pathogens-08-00144" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. In recent years, licorice extracts have been shown to have antiviral effects on many viruses including human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) [
 <xref rid="B30-pathogens-08-00144" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], hepatitis B virus (HBV) [
 <xref rid="B31-pathogens-08-00144" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], hepatitis A virus (HAV) [
 <xref rid="B32-pathogens-08-00144" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="B33-pathogens-08-00144" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], infectious bronchitis virus (IBV) [
 <xref rid="B34-pathogens-08-00144" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], PRRSV [
 <xref rid="B29-pathogens-08-00144" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], and PRV [
 <xref rid="B27-pathogens-08-00144" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. According to previous studies, DG pre-treatement inhibited PRV infection in a dose-dependent manner and reduced apoptosis [
 <xref rid="B27-pathogens-08-00144" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Glycyrrhizin and DG have antiviral effect against SARS-CoV and IBV. Additionally, the water solubility of DG is better than that of glycyrrhizin, so we chose to verify the effect of DG on PDCoV. 
</p>
