<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Herd (population) immunity requires high levels of vaccine uptake, to limit the number of unvaccinated people and the opportunity for pathogen transmission between them. The proportion of a given population required to induce herd immunity through vaccination is lower for the bacterial infections and conjugate polysaccharide vaccines, as their basic reproductive number (R
 <sub>0</sub>) is lower than viral infections like measles, varicella or polio (
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Measles virus can cause devastating disease ranging from acute presentations with pneumonia or encephalitis, to immune amnesia and long-term complications such as subacute sclerosing panencephalitis (
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">Mina et al., 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Moss, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">Petrova et al., 2019</xref>). The live-attenuated measles vaccine is highly efficacious and the first dose is recommended at 9–12 months of age. To protect those who cannot receive live vaccines (younger infants, pregnant women, the immunosuppressed) from acquiring measles in the community, at least 93–95% of the population is required to be vaccinated with two doses in order to interrupt measles virus transmission. In many countries in Europe and in the United States, this level of vaccination uptake is falling (
 <xref rid="B121" ref-type="bibr">Wise, 2018</xref>), due to a combination of reduced accessibility to health services and vaccine misinformation. As a result, some countries, including the United Kingdom and United States, where elimination of measles had been declared have had a resurgence of disease (
 <xref rid="B122" ref-type="bibr">Wise, 2019</xref>). For high-risk individuals who are unable to be vaccinated, herd immunity represents a life-saving protection strategy against many infections. An alternative strategy, cocooning, has been employed with limited success for pertussis and influenza (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Grizas et al., 2012</xref>), where their close/household contacts are vaccinated to prevent transmission.
</p>
