<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Avian influenza viruses (AIVs) are of great significance to public health due to their potential to cause influenza epidemics and pandemics. Influenza is caused by negative sense single-stranded RNA viruses which belong to the 
 <italic>Orthomyxoviridae</italic> family [
 <xref rid="B1-vetsci-07-00073" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. 
 <italic>Orthomyxoviridae</italic> includes seven genera, of which only influenza A, B, C and D cause influenza in vertebrates, whereas the influenza A virus genus is mostly known to infect wild and domestic birds [
 <xref rid="B2-vetsci-07-00073" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. High pathogenicity avian influenza (HPAI) H5N1 is a continuous major pathogen causing high mortality in a variety of avian species and is capable of causing sporadic human infections and mortality [
 <xref rid="B3-vetsci-07-00073" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. HPAI H5 viruses continue to be a devastating threat to the poultry industry and an incipient threat to humans with a low level of infection. Since 1997, the HPAI H5 virus has continued to spread and evolve. Since 2004, the HPAI H5 virus has spread to many countries worldwide and has been responsible for the destruction of many millions of birds. Wild birds are often blamed for the dispersal of AIVs including HPAI H5 viruses, but definitive proof is often lacking. To date, all human influenza pandemics are associated with H1, H2 and H3 subtypes, but H5, H6, H7, H9 and H10 can also cross the species barrier and infect mammalian species including humans by either antigenic drift or viral strain re-assortment with a human strain as the antigenic shift [
 <xref rid="B4-vetsci-07-00073" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-vetsci-07-00073" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The outbreak of HPAI has occurred in over 60 countries [
 <xref rid="B6-vetsci-07-00073" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], though it was first identified in China in 1996, and the influenza A/Goose/Guangdong/1/96 (H5N1) isolate is regarded as the ancestor of the present zoonotic H5N1 virus evolution of H5N1 AIVs across Asia [
 <xref rid="B7-vetsci-07-00073" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].
</p>
