<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There were 15 parameters, 
 <italic>β</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>mp</italic>
 </sub>, 
 <italic>β</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>pm</italic>
 </sub>, 
 <italic>ω</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>p</italic>
 </sub>, 
 <italic>ω</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>m</italic>
 </sub>, 
 <italic>q</italic>, 
 <italic>γ</italic>, 
 <italic>γ</italic>’, 
 <italic>a</italic>, 
 <italic>c</italic>, 
 <italic>n</italic>, 
 <italic>b</italic>, 
 <italic>τ</italic>, 
 <italic>T</italic>, 
 <italic>j</italic> and 
 <italic>x</italic>, in the models (
 <xref rid="pntd.0007659.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Symptoms of infection usually begin 4–8 days after the mosquito bite [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007659.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Here we simulated 6 days of the incubation period in our model, thus 
 <italic>ω</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>p</italic>
 </sub> = 0.1667. After entering the mosquito in the blood meal, the virus will require an additional 8–12 days incubation before it can then be transmitted to another human [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007659.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Here we simulated 10 days in our model, thus 
 <italic>ω</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>m</italic>
 </sub> = 0.1000. The ratio of symptomatic compared to asymptomatic infection is 2.2:1 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007659.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], thus 
 <italic>q</italic> = 0.6875. The infectious period is ranging from 3 days to 14 days [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007659.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007659.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Here we simulated 7 days in our model, thus 
 <italic>γ</italic> = 
 <italic>γ</italic>’ = 0.1429. 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> appears to be an efficient vertical transmitter of DENV-1 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007659.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Vertical infection rates (the percentage of offspring vertically infected) of individual positive families are ranging from 1.4% to 17.4% [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007659.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Here we simulated 10.0% in our model, thus 
 <italic>n</italic> = 0.1000. The mosquito remains infected for the remainder of its life, which might be from 4 days to 50 days [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007659.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Since the outbreak occurred in August, we simulated 14 days in our model, thus 
 <italic>b</italic> = 0.0714. Since we simulated the transmission in August when the density of the vector was at the peak, which means that the vector has a balance population and the birth rate is equal to the death rate, thus 
 <italic>a</italic> = 
 <italic>b</italic> = 0.0714. However, the vector population decreased after August and the two parameters were adjusted by the seasonality equation accordingly.
</p>
