<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the continental United States, 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> is found throughout the southern states, and recent enhanced surveys of 
 <italic>Stegomyia</italic> mosquitoes have documented the presence of this species in 26 states [
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-12-00453" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Despite this wide distribution of the primary vector and the Asian tiger mosquito (
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>), a secondary vector for these viruses in many locations, the only regions experiencing autochthonous transmission of DENV, CHIKV, and ZIKV by mosquito exposure, are South Florida and South Texas [
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-12-00453" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-viruses-12-00453" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. While the Mexico cities along the U.S.—Mexico border have experienced consistent epidemics of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>-driven viruses, markedly fewer human cases have occurred in the communities of the Lower Rio Grande Valley (LRGV) on the Texas side of the border. For example, the state of Tamaulipas, Mexico, recorded an estimated 11,760 probable cases of DENV and 2677 cases of Dengue Hemorrhagic Fever between 2009 and 2019 [
 <xref rid="B11-viruses-12-00453" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In contrast, in the LRGV, local mosquito-borne DENV epidemics occurred only in 2005 and 2013 [
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-12-00453" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], and the outbreaks were associated with relatively small numbers of human cases. For example, in 2005 the LRGV documented three symptomatic cases and six asymptomatic cases of DEN with no travel history [
 <xref rid="B12-viruses-12-00453" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], compared to 7062 reported DEN cases in Tamaulipas the same year [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-12-00453" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In contrast, these viruses are recorded with only isolated cases of local transmission in South Texas, including a single CHIKV case in Brownsville, TX in 2015 (Texas Department of State Health Services, 2016) and 11 cases of locally acquired ZIKV in the LRGV between 2016–2017 [
 <xref rid="B14-viruses-12-00453" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].
</p>
