<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Arboviruses such as SINV, WNV, and JEV use apoptosis as a virulence factor to promote their pathogenesis [
 <xref rid="CIT0178">178</xref>–
 <xref rid="CIT0180">180</xref>]. Each of these viruses has its own-specific targets and biochemical-induced mechanisms during virus-induced programmed cell death. Observations suggest that apoptosis induced by SINV plays an important role in virus pathogenesis and mortality [
 <xref rid="CIT0178">178</xref>]. After the entry of SINV into host cells, dsRNA intermediates are formed, then dsRNA-dependent protein kinase (PKR) recognizes these particles [
 <xref rid="CIT0181">181</xref>–
 <xref rid="CIT0183">183</xref>]. PKR blocks cellular translation through eIF2α phosphorylation, which inhibits MCL-1 biosynthesis, an anti-apoptotic Bcl2 family protein [
 <xref rid="CIT0184">184</xref>]. PKR also controls c-Jun N-terminal kinases (JNK) through IRS1 phosphorylation and then activates 14–3-3 proteins (
 <xref rid="F0002">Figure 2</xref>). Thus, 14–3-3 proteins affect the accessibility of Bad to kinases and serves to localize kinases to their substrates, causing the release of Bad and disruption of the complex between anti-apoptotic Bcl2 family proteins, Bcl-xl and Bak. Both Bad and Bik can displace Bak from MCL-1, which results in Bak oligomerization and cytochrome C release, and subsequent induction of apoptosis in MOSEC tumor cells, derived from the ovarian epithelium, and Pan02, derived from a pancreatic adenocarcinoma [
 <xref rid="CIT0185">185</xref>]. CHIKV triggers the apoptosis pathway to evade the immune system and facilitate its dissemination by infecting neighboring cells [
 <xref rid="CIT0186">186</xref>]. CHIKV infection triggers both apoptosis and autophagy. However, based on kinetic studies, it was found that CHIKV-induced autophagy delays caspase-dependent apoptotic cell death by inducing the IRE1α-XBP-1 pathway in conjunction with ROS-mediated mTOR inhibition [
 <xref rid="CIT0168">168</xref>].
</p>
