<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Until recently, the role of apoptosis in determining the outcome of arbovirus infection in mosquitoes was not clear; however, to find a correlation between apoptosis and arbovirus infection, it is reasonable to also study this pathway in the invertebrate mosquito vector. A study for the first time tested the roles of apoptosis and caspases directly in determining mosquito vector competence for arboviruses infection using the SINV model. Silencing of the 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic> anti-apoptotic gene iap1 (Aeiap1) in adult female 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic> mosquitoes caused apoptosis in midgut epithelium, and enhanced mosquito mortality and susceptibility to SINV infection. However, silencing of initiator caspase gene, Aedronc, protected mosquitoes against mortality and reduced SINV midgut infection [
 <xref rid="CIT0224">224</xref>]. Arboviruses have evolved mechanisms to avoid apoptosis in mosquito vectors. Mosquitoes were infected with SINV that expressed a proapoptotic gene, Reaper. The Reaper-expressing virus showed replication defects in mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="CIT0225">225</xref>]. 
 <italic>A. albopictus</italic> also is a vector of various arboviruses. Aadnr1, a novel gene related to innate immunity and apoptosis in 
 <italic>A. albopictus</italic>, an ortholog of dnr1 in Drosophila, was studied in C6/36 mosquito cells. Aadnr1 encodes a protein that contains an N-terminal FERM domain and a C-terminal RING domain which are involved in signal transduction pathways and ubiquitination, respectively. The transcriptional level of Aadnr1 and subsequently apoptosis were reduced after SINV infection [
 <xref rid="CIT0062">62</xref>]. An effector caspase, AaCASPS7, in 
 <italic>A. albopictus</italic> also induced caspase-dependent apoptosis in C6/36 cells [
 <xref rid="CIT0226">226</xref>], which could indicate an apoptotic caspase in arbovirus infection. Thus, apoptosis could be considered one of the defense pathways in mosquitoes against arbovirus infections, and is probably a factor to determine vector competence [
 <xref rid="CIT0227">227</xref>]. A study by Troupin et al. showed that mosquito ubiquitin Ub3881 in an Aag2 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic> cell line plays roles in apoptosis of the mosquito cells during DENV infection. Ub3881 overexpression targeted DENV envelope protein and reduced virion production. The loss of Ub3881 function reduced the level of apoptosis during DENV infection [
 <xref rid="CIT0228">228</xref>]. This suggests it would be worthwhile to test Ub3881 peptides as inhibitors of DENV infection in mosquitoes.
</p>
