<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite an efficient vaccine, YFV still remains an important public health concern in Africa and South America. YFV is maintained in sylvatic cycles between non-human primates and arboreal mosquitoes, and human outbreaks occur when the virus is introduced into an urban cycle mediated by 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007783.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Although there is no evidence of a sylvatic cycle of YFV in the Asia-Pacific region, the risk of spillover transmission exists. The lack of YFV outbreaks in the Asia-Pacific region to date could be due to cross-protective immunity conferred by other widespread flaviviruses such as DENV and Japanese encephalitis virus, but it could also reflect relatively fewer opportunities for YFV introduction until now. Rampant globalization now puts the Asia-Pacific region at an unprecedented risk of YFV introduction [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007783.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0007783.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Billions of immunologically naïve people, together with competent 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> populations [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007783.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007783.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], create a dangerous set of conditions that are theoretically favorable to a massive YFV epidemic. On the other hand, a scenario whereby YFV would establish a novel sylvatic cycle [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007783.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] seems unlikely in Singapore given the small size of resident non-human primate populations. Clearly, places with high densities of the domestic vector 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> are most at risk of spillover transmission, but we emphasize that in the absence of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic>, ancillary vectors should not be overlooked. Competent mosquito species such as 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>malayensis</italic> could facilitate introduction of YFV into the Asia-Pacific region. In Singapore, strict and sustained vector control measures have achieved low densities of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007783.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] but this has failed to prevent arbovirus outbreaks in the last two decades [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007783.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Following a previous study on the ability of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>malayensis</italic> from Singapore to transmit DENV and CHIKV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007783.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], we reiterate the need to account for peridomestic species in the management of mosquito vector populations.
</p>
