<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Red knots that developed clinical disease had higher levels of viral shedding from the pharynx than knots that remained sub-clinically infected. This has also been described in other experimentally infected waterbirds 
 <xref rid="pone.0027814-Keawcharoen1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Clinically affected red knots developed severe neurological disease, associated with viral replication in neurons and other cells of the central nervous system, demonstrating neurotropism of HPAIV H5N1 in this species. Neurological disease has been described in wild birds following natural and experimental infection with HPAIV H5N1, in association with viral replication in brain neurons 
 <xref rid="pone.0027814-Kalthoff1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0027814-Keawcharoen1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0027814-Brojer1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0027814-Teifke1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. Importantly, affected knots suddenly developed clinical disease at 5 to 11 dpi, and did not show visible changes in behavior on the preceding days. It is unlikely that even minor clinical signs in these knots would have been missed during the daily behavioral observations of 15 min duration, because of their high level of activity and the nature of their behavior (e.g., sand probing). Likewise, most other species of experimentally infected birds that developed clinical disease upon infection with HPAIV H5N1 showed debilitating signs of disease at 4 to 8 dpi, without visible signs during the preceding days 
 <xref rid="pone.0027814-Kalthoff1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0027814-Keawcharoen1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Shedding of HPAIV H5N1 by experimentally infected knots lasted from 1 to 5 dpi and peaked at 1 to 3 dpi. This is comparable to other species of experimentally infected birds, which typically shed virus up to 4 or 5 dpi with a peak at 1 to 2 dpi 
 <xref rid="pone.0027814-Kalthoff1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0027814-Keawcharoen1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Therefore, a major proportion of viral shedding occurs while birds are clinically normal and apparently able to fly, thus potentially allowing for the long-distance dispersal of HPAIV H5N1. Nevertheless, any insults to the health of migratory birds that are ready for potentially dangerous and extremely demanding long-distance migration 
 <xref rid="pone.0027814-Piersma4" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> may prevent them from undertaking migration at all 
 <xref rid="pone.0027814-Guglielmo1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. Thus, it remains to be shown in free-living migratory birds whether sub-clinical infection reduces the likelihood of taking off for long migratory journeys. Another caveat that cannot be addressed by the present study is the fact that knots under experimental settings were fed 
 <italic>ad libitum</italic>, which may differ from conditions met in nature.
</p>
