<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Studies have shown that the metabolism and elimination of AMF in rats are fast, and the bioavailability of AMF by intraperitoneal injection was 77.4%± 28%, but the oral bioavailability is very low (Liao et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Yu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Researches on the tissue distribution of AMF in rats showed that after oral administration, the drugs are mainly distributed in the small intestine and stomach, followed by the liver and large intestine, and only a small part can enter other tissues with blood circulation. And it is difficult to dissolve in water and organic solvents, so it is difficult to be absorbed by the body. To give full play to the pharmacological effects of AMF, bioavailability and solubility must be improved. The main methods to improve the bioavailability and solubility of drugs are to change the way of drug delivery, change the dosage form (Wei et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Hu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Santos et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) or modify its structure (Sen Gupta &amp; Ghosh, 
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Because it is difficult for AMF to dissolve in water and organic solvents, it is almost impossible to change the way drugs are administered. In recent years, micelle-based drug delivery systems have been widely developed because of their enhanced pharmacokinetics, biological distribution and high stability (Kesharwani et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>), and oral bioavailability has been greatly improved after the preparation of micelles (Guo et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). So in this experiment, the nanomicelle was made, and evaluated 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>.
</p>
