<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par9">The clinical presentation of COVID-19 is dominated by respiratory signs with less frequent occurrence of gastrointestinal symptoms. The virus invasion is not limited to these two organs, particularly considering that significant expression of ACE2 is detected in other tissues, including heart, kidney, endothelium and CNS
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>. Viral infection of the brain
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup> may have multiple neurological and psychiatric consequences, contributing to both the acute phase of disease and its potential sequelae Fig.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>. The neurotropism has been well documented for several β-coronaviruses including SARS-CoV-1, MERS-CoV and the HEV 67 N virus of porcine hemagglutinating encephalomyelitis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. Arguably, the primary way for SARS-CoV-2 is associated with ACE2 expressed in neurones and in neuroglia
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup> The ACE2 expressing neural cells are found in the circumventricular organs, such as the subfornical organ, the paraventricular nucleus, the solitary tract and in the rostral ventrolateral medulla
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. All these regions have little protection of the blood brain barrier (BBB) and all are involved in cardiovascular and respiratory regulation. The lack of BBB makes these CNS sites vulnerable in many pathologies, such as various types of systemic inflammation including sepsis-associated encephalopathy, neuroinfection with bacteria, viruses or parasites, stress and autoimmune encephalitis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>. Microglial cells localised in CVO seems to be in a state of chronic activation in the attempt to limit the entry of circulating neurotoxic molecules or invasive agents into the parenchyma and to preserve cerebral homoeostasis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup>. The SARS-CoV-2, similarly to other respiratory viruses, could gain access to CNS through several routes, for example by migrating through axons of the olfactory nerve
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. The intranasal infection of SARS-CoV-1 or MERS-CoV
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup> was shown to result in rapid spread of viral particles into the brain possibly through the olfactory bulb by a retrograde axonal transport; viruses replicating in the nasal cavity may utilise the direct link with the olfactory bulb to colonise the CNS. In this paradigm the virus is transported through the axons of olfactory bulb neurones with subsequent infection of the specific type of neuroglia the sustentacular cells of the olfactory bulb
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>. When the virus was administered intranasally in extremely low doses, only the CNS was disseminated
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>
 </sup>, strengthening the concept of an intrinsic neurotropism of coronaviruses. In rodents ablation of the olfactory bulb prevented viral spread following nasal infection
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup>. Further support for the role of nasal-olfactory route comes from clinical observations according to which anosmia develops early in SARS-CoV-2 infected subjects
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>. The SARS-CoV-2 RNA was present for 20 or more days in oropharyngeal and nasopharyngeal secretion samples of 30% of COVID-19 survivors, suggesting that SARS-CoV-2 can linger for a long time at both upper and lower respiratory tract
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
