<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<author-notes>
 <title>Article Information</title>
 <p>
  <bold>Accepted for Publication:</bold> May 12, 2019.
 </p>
 <p content-type="published-online">
  <bold>Published:</bold> June 28, 2019. 
  <?xpp bx;1?>doi:
  <uri content-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.6412</uri>
 </p>
 <p content-type="open-access-note">
  <bold>Open Access:</bold> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the 
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/pages/instructions-for-authors#SecOpenAccess" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">CC-BY License</ext-link>. © 2019 Orman ES et al. 
  <italic>JAMA Network Open</italic>.
 </p>
 <corresp id="zoi190254cor1">
  <bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Eric S. Orman, MD, MSCR, Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Indiana University School of Medicine, 702 Rotary Cir, Ste 225, Indianapolis, IN 46202 (
  <email xlink:href="esorman@iu.edu" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">esorman@iu.edu</email>).
 </corresp>
 <p content-type="author-contributions">
  <bold>Author Contributions:</bold> Dr Orman had full access to all of the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.
 </p>
 <p>
  <italic>Concept and design: </italic>Orman, Ghabril, Nephew, Chalasani.
 </p>
 <p>
  <italic>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</italic> Orman, Roberts, Ghabril, Desair, Patidar, Chalasani.
 </p>
 <p>
  <italic>Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Orman, Chalasani.
 </p>
 <p>
  <italic>Critical revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content: </italic>Orman, Roberts, Ghabril, Nephew, Desai, Patidar.
 </p>
 <p>
  <italic>Statistical analysis:</italic> Orman, Ghabril, Patidar.
 </p>
 <p>
  <italic>Obtained funding:</italic> Orman.
 </p>
 <p>
  <italic>Administrative, technical, or material support:</italic> Nephew.
 </p>
 <p>
  <italic>Supervision:</italic> Ghabril, Chalasani.
 </p>
 <p content-type="COI-statement">
  <bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> Dr Chalasani reported ongoing consulting activities (within the preceding 12 months) with NuSirt, Abbvie, Eli Lilly and Co, Afimmune (DS Biopharma), Allergan (Tobira), Madrigal, Shire, Axovant, Coherus, Pronova (BASF), and Genentech; and receiving research grant support from Intercept, Eli Lilly and Co, Exact Sciences, Galectin Therapeutics, and Cumberland outside the submitted work. No other disclosures were reported.
 </p>
 <p content-type="funding-statement">
  <bold>Funding/Support:</bold> This study was supported in part by the 
  <funding-source rid="sp1">Indiana Clinical and Translational Sciences Institute</funding-source>, which is funded in part by Clinical and Translational Sciences Award KL2TR001106 from the 
  <funding-source rid="sp2">National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences</funding-source>, 
  <funding-source rid="sp3">National Institutes of Health</funding-source>. This study was also supported in part by grant K23DK109202 from the 
  <funding-source rid="sp4">National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</funding-source>, 
  <funding-source rid="sp5">National Institutes of Health</funding-source>.
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>Role of the Funder/Sponsor:</bold> The funders had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>Disclaimer:</bold> The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the National Institutes of Health.
 </p>
</author-notes>
