<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Ornithodoros</italic> ticks have long lifespans, and ASFV can replicate to high titers and be maintained for long periods of time in the vector with minimal cytopathological effects or increased tick mortality (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>); although increased mortality rates have also been reported (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>–
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). A study following ASFV infection in 
 <italic>O. porcinus porcinus</italic> ticks after feeding on viremic pigs showed ASFV titers of 6 log
 <sub>10</sub> HAD
 <sub>50</sub>/tick, which were maintained at that level for at least 290 days and declined only 2 log
 <sub>10</sub> HAD
 <sub>50</sub>/tick or less after 3 years (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). ASFV was isolated from 
 <italic>O. moubata</italic> ticks from a farm in Madagascar 4 years after the culling of all pigs (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). ASFV transmission to pigs by infected the Iberian soft tick has been demonstrated up to 588 days after infection (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>) and ASFV persistence has been shown for at least 5 years in 
 <italic>O. erraticus</italic> ticks collected from infected farms in Portugal (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). However, viral clearance after one year has also been observed (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Nonetheless, virus-tick adaptation is likely necessary to achieve high virus titers since significantly lower infection rates and viral titers, and increased mortality have been observed in studies using ASFV isolates not derived from ticks, or 
 <italic>Ornithodoros</italic> species not native to Africa (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>).
</p>
