<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0055">Disruption of sewage systems and contamination of drinking water may contribute in food- borne or water related infectious diseases (
 <xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">Badparva et al., 2017</xref>). Consuming of crops which were grown in soils that were contaminated with sewage during the flood is another potential source of gastrointestinal diseases. Crops can be contaminated with bacterial and parasitic agents during the grow. It is like that soils were fertilized by animal and human feces (
 <xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">Alderman et al., 2012</xref>). Poor sanitation facilities along with overcrowding can increase fecal-oral transmission of different pathogens (
 <xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">Paterson et al., 2018</xref>). Flood water scan transport microbial agents into the aquatic environment and clean water supplies, resulting to increased incidence of waterborne diseases and post flood epidemics. However, a considerable population displacement may lead to difficult access to clean water sources (
 <xref rid="bb0170" ref-type="bibr">Okaka and Odhiambo, 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">Paterson et al., 2018</xref>). Contact with flood water is reported as an increased risk of gastrointestinal diseases during the 2002 floods in Germany (
 <xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">Alderman et al., 2012</xref>). The most common identified pathogen bacterial post flooding was 
 <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic> and enterotoxigenic 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (
 <xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">Paterson et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr">Ni et al., 2014</xref>). Also, the increased numbers of dysentery cases due to shigellosis, salmonellosis giardiosis, cryptosporidiosis, infection with 
 <italic>Entaemoeba histolytica</italic> and enteric fever cases have been reported in the resident of flood-affected communities (
 <xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">Paterson et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">Ghozy et al., n.d.</xref>).
</p>
