<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Considering live vaccines, one can anticipate that pre-existing and significant levels of serotype-specific or cross-reactive antibody responses may block their infectivity and subsequent replication, and therefore limit adaptive immune response to the vaccine. One should then wait for a certain period of time after infection to ensure a proper induction of vaccine-induced immunity. Some studies and trials can be mentioned in this regard:
 <list list-type="simple">
  <list-item>
   <label>⚬</label>
   <p>Monkey studies performed with the Sanofi Pasteur vaccine candidate have shown that in this species immune responses could benefit from a second vaccine dose administered two months after a live priming performed by a monovalent attenuated vaccine (“wild-type like” priming) or performed by a primary dose of a bivalent or tetravalent vaccine. Administering a second dose with a tetravalent or complementary bivalent vaccine two months after such monovalent, bivalent, or tetravalent priming was able to induce a strong booster effect with a broader response covering all four serotypes [
    <xref rid="B30-vaccines-08-00174" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>⚬</label>
   <p>Some of these prime/boost combinations were then further tested in clinical trials. In humans, a second complementary bivalent dose administered 3.5 months after the first bivalent one was, however, largely inefficient and apparently blocked by the pre-existing cross-neutralizing immune response induced upon the first administration [
    <xref rid="B31-vaccines-08-00174" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Therefore, the “refractory” period appears to be longer in humans as compared to monkeys, and this was also pointed out by other authors, who proposed to apply a longer interval between two live vaccine administrations, i.e., 6 months or longer [
    <xref rid="B32-vaccines-08-00174" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Such a time interval should then also be applied to a first live vaccine administration following a natural infection.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
