<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Unlike HIV-1 which has a relatively broad tropism, HCV is a bloodborne virus that primarily infects and replicates in hepatocytes. In primary hepatitis C infection, ~25% of patients naturally clear the virus and although reinfection occurs in many individuals (Grebely et al., 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), it is evident that repeated infection is associated with a reduced magnitude and duration of viraemia, and a greater likelihood of clearance (Sacks-Davis et al., 
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Thus, characterizing and eliciting the naturally-protective immune responses during primary infection and reinfection provide a rational path for the design of a prophylactic HCV vaccine (Grebely et al., 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). The immune responses that correlate best with natural protection include robust and broad CMI to conserved HCV non-structural (NS) proteins (NS3, NS4, and NS5) (Smyk-Pearson et al., 
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Baumert et al., 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) and NAb targeting conserved regions of the viral envelope (E1E2) proteins (Houghton, 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Osburn et al., 
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Bailey et al., 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Although CMI will not prevent infection, clinical data suggest that T cell responses could prevent the development of persistent infection in individuals who naturally clear the virus, which is an acceptable outcome given that primary infection is often asymptomatic and not associated with severe disease outcomes (Baumert et al., 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). After two decades of unsuccessful pre-clinical studies and Phase I HCV vaccine trials, the current lead prophylactic candidate is in an NIH-sponsored Phase IIb, placebo-controlled trial (ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: NCT01436357) in high risk people who inject drugs (PWID) (Swadling et al., 
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The candidate vaccination regimen being tested utilizes a chimpanzee adenovirus (ChAd) prime and a modified vaccinia Ankara (MVA) boost to elicit systemic T cell immunity to gt1 NS antigens (Swadling et al., 
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). However, it is not clear if this vaccination can induce robust intrahepatic T cell immunity and sufficient multi-genotypic immunity to result in significant protection in vaccinated individuals especially given the increased prevalence of multiple genotypes in HCV endemic regions.
</p>
