<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Second, relatively balanced neutralization against each of the viruses is required for an ideal tetravalent dengue vaccine or pentavalent Dengue/Zika vaccine. The majority of dengue vaccine candidates are comprised of mixed antigens representing four serotypes, and they are administered to recipients simultaneously to elicit a tetravalent response. When using attenuated viruses, however, different replicative capacity of each virus may produce interference among them, leading to imbalanced neutralizing antibody responses (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Dayan et al., 2013b</xref>). As for tetravalent protein or DNA vaccines, the immune dominance of specific antigens also affected the balance of neutralizing activities elicited by the vaccines (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Block et al., 2010</xref>). Thus, modulation of dosage of each serotype of virus or antigen is always needed to improve the relative balance of antibody responses induced. Because the correlation between neutralizing titers and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> protection varies among four serotypes of dengue viruses or Zika virus, to adjust the balance among immune responses in order to achieve broad protection becomes even more difficult. An alternative strategy is to elicit broadly neutralizing antibodies through a single antigen presenting conserved neutralizing epitopes. To this end, we obtained a consensus E80 sequence that contains epitopes conserved across all four serotype viruses through 
 <italic>in silicon</italic> calculation with a dataset composed of 3,127 published sequences of dengue viruses, and found this single consensus E80 protein was immunogenic and capable of inducing neutralizing antibodies toward all four serotypes of DENV, with less bias than conventional tetravalent E80 vaccine (
 <xref rid="B174" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2017</xref>). When administered in a DNA prime and protein boost regimen, this vaccine conferred protections against all four serotypes of viruses in a mouse model (
 <xref rid="B184" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2019</xref>). This vaccine design strategy uniformly enriched all conserved epitopes on a single E80, further incorporation of consensus E80 monomers derived from both DENV and ZIKV to a stabilized dimer might help to present most cross-neutralizing epitopes on surface.
</p>
