<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0050">The COVID-19 outbreak has led to increased efforts toward the development of more antiviral nanoagents as a reserve strategy in the fight against viral epidemics. Research thus far has mostly focused only on the development of new drugs and vaccines, or reusing approved antiviral drugs [
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], while the absence of antiviral nanoagents during this emergency is conspicuous. Moreover, despite the promising versatility of ENMs in antiviral applications, practical therapeutics are limited in terms of the development of new strategies and improvements in efficacy and safety. The following are a few such limitations:
 <list list-type="simple" id="lis0010">
  <list-item id="lsti0020">
   <label>(i)</label>
   <p id="par0055">Although most reported antiviral nanoagents exhibit outstanding performance in mammalian cell lines or rodents, they may cause adverse or more complicated responses in humans. Hence, before rushing into the clinic, more preclinical tests using promising animal models (
    <italic>e.g.</italic>, ferrets, macaques, and other primates) that better mimic human disease response must be performed to assess the health risks as well as the antiviral activity of nanoagents. More importantly, massive preclinical tests are prerequisite for the development of nanoagents with better efficacy and broad-spectrum antiviral activity than current approved antiviral drugs.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0025">
   <label>(ii)</label>
   <p id="par0060">Compared to bacteria, virus infections are more complicated, involving faster transmission and a variable incubation period. For instance, although both SARS and COVID-19 belong to the coronavirus family, they exhibit different infectious and pathogenic effects on patients [
    <xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Therefore, the design of novel antiviral nanoagents for a severe viral pandemic requires not only specific and broad-spectrum activities of antiviral nanoagents, but also a better understanding of the infection mechanisms, especially for viruses exhibiting a high mutation rate and tolerance to approved drugs or vaccine treatments [
    <xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0030">
   <label>(iii)</label>
   <p id="par0065">The envelope, capsid, and nucleic acids are the primary targets in the design of antiviral nanoagents. However, the interactions between ENMs and these targets remain unclear, which hampers a deeper understanding of the mechanisms that inhibit virus infection. Therefore, the possible interaction mechanisms, including the damage caused by the direct binding of ENMs to viruses, the disturbance of interactions between virus and host cell, or the indirect effects on the activation of innate and adaptive immunity, should be clarified.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0035">
   <label>(iv)</label>
   <p id="par0070">A viral infection involves the following stages: attachment to membrane receptors, penetration into cells, intracellular uncoating, nucleic acid synthesis, and the transfer of progeny virus between cells. Existing databases and bioinformatics should be better used to propose strategies for designing novel antiviral nanoagents that can inhibit the abovementioned processes. Furthermore, the prediction and screening of the interactions between ENMs and viruses during the infection process requires more powerful and high-throughput analytical platforms.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0040">
   <label>(v)</label>
   <p id="par0075">The antiviral nanoagent treatments may also act on the immune system. Therefore, better manipulation of the physicochemical properties (
    <italic>e.g.</italic>, surface modification) of ENMs is necessary to avoid their side effects, in addition to the well-balanced dose administration. In addition, the reasons for secondary adverse outcomes remain unclear, which can be caused by either ENM-induced nonspecific immune response or virus-incurred inflammation during treatment. Therefore, besides virus infection, the immune activation associated with the type and dosage of the applied ENMs should be considered as well.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0045">
   <label>(vi)</label>
   <p id="par0080">The controllable delivery of antiviral nanoagents to lesions is an important concern during the treatment of diverse viruses. Generally, intravenous administration may be the most commonly used clinical route, especially for treating an infection due to influenza virus. However, for gastrointestinal infections caused by rotavirus or hepatitis virus, oral administration is better, while intranodal administration may be better for treating infections caused by respiratory viruses such as SARS and COVID-19. Therefore, the stability and bioavailability of antiviral nanoagents must be carefully assessed, considering the features of both diverse administration methods and different viruses.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0050">
   <label>(vii)</label>
   <p id="par0085">The rapid increase in the variety of ENMs provides space for healthcare innovations as well as opportunities for the development of novel antiviral agents. However, both the advantages and limitations of ENMs must be well understood to avoid additional risks before practical applications. For example, owing to their high surface-to-volume ratio and modifiable surface properties, two-dimensional ENMs such as GO have been demonstrated as useful tools for anticancer drug delivery [
    <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
    <xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], although their biocompatibility remains a question. Therefore, the possible use of two-dimensional ENMs for antiviral treatments warrants further exploration in the future [
    <xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
