<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Additionally, other upper respiratory tract viruses increase the adherence ability of bacterial pathogens to primary and immortalized epithelial cells with particular differences. Such differences are determined by the types of epithelial cells and their response to parainfluenza virus‐3, respiratory syncytial virus, and/or influenza virus.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0083" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>83</sup>
 </xref> Novotny et al
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0084" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>84</sup>
 </xref> showed that adenovirus and respiratory syncytial virus stimulated the expression of intercellular adhesion molecule 1 (ICAM‐1) by primary respiratory tract epithelial cells. ICAM1 acts as a receptor for Type 4 pilus (T4P) of non‐typeable 
 <italic>H. influenzae</italic> (NTHI), thus promoting the binding of this pathogen to cells expressing this molecule. Also, respiratory syncytial virus infection increases the binding ability of 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> to normal epithelial cells, as well as cells affected by cystic fibrosis. Such phenomena have been frequently employed by other bacteria to increase their virulence to infect the cells.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>66</sup>
 </xref> Studies have indicated that, following the infection with the respiratory syncytial virus, the rate of the binding of 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> serotypes epithelial cells is increased by 2–10 folds.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0085" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>85</sup>
 </xref> Similarly, the antibody titers against 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> are elevated in the nasopharynx when the cells co‐infected with the respiratory syncytial virus, rhinovirus, and community‐acquired pneumonia.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0086" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>86</sup>
 </xref> The higher degree of colonization of nasopharynx with 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> is also found when the individuals are co‐infected with viral upper respiratory tract infection or human immunodeficiency virus infection.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0087" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>87</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
