<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Bacterial and viral co‐infection can alter some properties of the host mucosal immunity, leading to the failure in controlling the replication of bacteria in this site.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0088" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>88</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0089" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>89</sup>
 </xref> Some key findings are discussed here, including the influence of viral infection on phagocytic activity. The reduction of alveolar macrophages by the influenza virus facilitates bacterial co‐infection.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0088" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>88</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0090" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>90</sup>
 </xref> Several lines of evidence demonstrated that 90% of resident alveolar macrophages were lost in the early weeks after influenza infection through tracking dye‐labeled alveolar macrophages,
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>42</sup>
 </xref> whereas 95% of the initial bacterial inoculum was eliminated during 3 hr by alveolar macrophages in non‐influenza inoculated hosts. Notably, in those cells co‐infected with influenza virus about 50% of the bacterial inoculum remained recoverable.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>42</sup>
 </xref> Also, it has been suggested that phagocyte activity, along with the cell proliferation could be influenced by viral infection. The infection of alveolar macrophages with influenza causes a marked decrease in the level of cytokines and chemokines, leading to decreased rates of recruitment and stimulation of neutrophils.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0088" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>88</sup>
 </xref> It may also suppress the phagocytic bacterial clearance mediated to nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate (NADPH), thereby increasing the susceptibility to secondary bacterial infection.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0091" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>91</sup>
 </xref> As mentioned earlier, the dysregulation of pro‐inflammatory cytokine‐induced by viral infection has been shown to play an essential role in the susceptibility of the cells to secondary bacterial infection. It is now known that type 1 IFNs have antiviral and immune‐stimulatory properties and could have detrimental effects on human cells when their expression is inappropriate and excessive. It has been reported that IFNs play a fundamental role in the production of anti‐inflammatory cytokines, such as interleukin (IL)‐10 and IL‐6, as well as the inhibition of proinflammatory cytokines, linking the innate immunity to adaptive immune responses, such as IL‐17 and IL‐23. They also decrease the activity of macrophages, dendritic cells, natural killer cells, along with the number of CD4‐ and CD8‐positive T cells, leading to the impaired eradication of bacterial co‐infection.
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0079" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>79</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0092" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>92</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0093" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>93</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="iub2356-bib-0094" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>94</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
