<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Even though numerous studies on vector competence have been performed, results are in most cases not comparable because of the variety of the infection protocols used. 
 <italic>Culicoides imicola</italic> has been proven to be susceptible to several BTV serotypes, including BTV-2 [
 <xref rid="B43-viruses-11-00941" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], BTV-4 [
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-11-00941" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-viruses-11-00941" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], and BTV-8 [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-11-00941" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-11-00941" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Species of the Obsoletus complex, although less investigated, have been found to be susceptible to serotypes 1, 4, 8, and 9 [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-11-00941" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-11-00941" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The authors of [
 <xref rid="B43-viruses-11-00941" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] achieved low recovery rates when 
 <italic>C. imicola</italic> midges were fed with BTV-2 (0.5%), BTV-4 (0.2%), and BTV-8 (0%) infected blood through membrane. Relatively low recovery rates of either BTV-8 (&lt;1% for both European and South African strains) or BTV-4 (1.9%), using the virus isolation technique, were also achieved from 
 <italic>C. imicola</italic> fed on 1-day-old chicken membrane [
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-11-00941" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-11-00941" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-11-00941" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. There were also cases where some BTV strains (BTV-4 and BTV-2) were not even recovered from midges [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-11-00941" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Paslaru [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-11-00941" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] demonstrated the competence of the Obsoletus complex for BTV-8 and BTV-4, obtaining a dissemination rate of 2% for both serotypes. Virus detection was performed by RT-PCR on heads as in our study, but the feeding method and the length and temperature of incubation period were not the same. Thus, also in this case, the variability of important parameters makes it difficult to compare the results. 
</p>
