<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0380">Immunomodulators directly target the host rather than the pathogen (
 <xref rid="f0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7.5</xref> ). This is accomplished by targeting pattern recognition receptors, such as TLRs that are present on innate immune cells in the host to detect features of microbes known as pathogen-associated molecular patterns. Since immunomodulators target host immune cells, they are an attractive candidate for use against bacterial agents as they are unlikely to result in the development of antibiotic resistance even after repeated use. In particular, the threat of an intentional release of a highly virulent bacterial pathogen that is either intrinsically resistant to antibiotics, or has been weaponized via the introduction of antibiotic resistance, makes immunomodulation an attractive complementary or alternative strategy to directly targeting bacterial biothreat agents. For example, a synthetic TLR9 agonist, 
 <italic>5'-C-phosphate-G-3'</italic> oligodeoxynucleotide (CpG ODN), appears to be able to stimulate protective immunity against intracellular bacterial infection and/or eliminate chronic infections. Indeed, studies in mice have demonstrated that the innate immune defenses activated by CpG ODNs protect against lethal challenge with 
 <italic>B. anthracis</italic>, 
 <italic>B. mallei</italic>, and 
 <italic>F. tularensis</italic> or their surrogates 
 <xref rid="bib1020" ref-type="bibr">[203]</xref>. Similarly, human monocyte-derived macrophages treated with poly(I:C), a synthetic TLR3 agonist, showed significantly reduced intracellular 
 <italic>F. tularensis</italic> [both Schu 4 and LVS (live vaccine strains)] replication. Mice administered with poly(I:C) before or after Schu 4 or LVS infection showed reduced bacterial burden in the lungs and prolonged survival. Mice treated with poly(I:C), challenged with 
 <italic>F. tularensis</italic>, and then treated with levofloxacin showed 100% survival relative to no survival in animals receiving levofloxacin alone 
 <xref rid="bib1025" ref-type="bibr">[204]</xref>.
</p>
