<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0090">The emergence of the IoT is probably the biggest opportunity in the utilization of data for human kind safety and progress. The IoT-derived data, if obtained with the highest standards of ethics and secured with the highest standards of security, will enable us to better track and control infectious diseases globally. In most studies, the parameters that show high dependence for dissemination of infections are the role played by the individuals and their close environment. As such, social interactions are very important drivers of infectious diseases transmission. Social interactions are probably even more important for primates and other group-living animals (
 <xref rid="bb0255" ref-type="bibr">Rushmore et al., 2017</xref>). Network analysis becomes a must not only to better control zoonosis but also to understand how in a group of individuals, be it animals, the social interactions shape the infectious disease dynamics. Human studies have shown how social media data (
 <xref rid="bb0195" ref-type="bibr">Lim et al., 2017</xref>) could be used to map infectious diseases that have not yet been identified by public health institutions. Using unsupervised machine learning model (i) no name of disease and (ii) no symptoms as a bottom-up approach. Our interpretation and review of the method is that by avoiding the integration of the name of the infection and the symptoms, there is more change to cover diseases and unknown diseases and to also enrich the databased related to known infectious diseases. Because most of the terms used in social media (symptoms, body parts, and pain locations) are not the scientific/medical level often reported by health-care institution it is more likely to cover a wide range of individuals and as such outputs with a denser geographical area. Although the study was limited in time (8 months), the validation was performed with accurate (electronic medical records) from a small group of individuals (
 <italic>n</italic>  = 104), and the model was able to predict with a high precision, recall and 
 <italic>F</italic> values on average above 0.7 (
 <xref rid="bb0195" ref-type="bibr">Lim et al., 2017</xref>). This suggests that sentiments expressed in social media is still valuable information, despite their heterogeneity and better classification of sentiments should be a priority for the next generation of social media-related studies. This approach of mass data to identify specific signals may enable us to enter into the era of personalized medicine. In line with this, patient similarity using electronic medical record has been successfully used to recommend treatments (
 <xref rid="bb0330" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2015</xref>). The diagnoses, demographic data, vital signs, and structures laboratory results were used for similarity testing. The addition of an intelligence to the electronic medical record may enables us to reach a precision &gt; 0.8. This again shows that dynamic learning models can be used as assistive technology for decision-making.
</p>
