<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0030">Cross-sectional and multicenter study with the participation of a secondary-level and a primary-level hospital. The data collection period was 15 days, from 20th March to 4th April 2020. The prevalence of potential interactions in COVID-19 patients treated with LPV/r was recorded and analysed. All patients older than 18 with hospital admission diagnosed with pneumonia due to COVID-19 or with clinical suspicion, who received treatment with LPV/r, were included in the study. All cases with acute respiratory symptoms including, among other symptoms, fever, persistent cough, odynophagia or respiratory distress and that met hospital admission criteria, were considered as suspected COVID-19 patients. The diagnosis of COVID-19 pneumonia was confirmed by positive PCR in a nasopharyngeal swab sample. An interaction related to LPV/r and any prescribed or home medication was defined as the existence of any qualitative or quantitative modification in the effect of the prescribed or home medication or LPV/r, with the concomitant administration of both. A review and screening of the interactions between LPV/r, prescribed and home medication, was carried out using the following identification and consultation databases: Lexicomp® (Uptodate),
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref> HIV-
 <italic>drug interactions</italic>
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref> and COVID-
 <italic>drug interactions</italic>.
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref> Potential drug interactions were those classified according to risk level: X (avoid combination), D (consider therapy modification) and C (monitor therapy). The latter were partially recorded, that is, only risk C interactions, with a recommendation to modify the therapy, in addition to monitoring it. Subsequently, the frequency was analysed and each interaction was reported according to the mechanism, the level of risk, if it had an impact on LPV/r, on the other drug involved in the interaction or both, if it could compromise the efficacy or cause toxicity and the recommendation, in each case.
</p>
