<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A detailed comparative genomic organization of important and related 
 <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic> members, including a 
 <italic>Deltacoronavirus</italic> as well, is provided in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-09-00519-f002">Figure 2</xref>. At the genomic level, the sequence homology of SARS-CoV-2 with MERS-CoV is lower (50–51.8%) than that with SARS-CoV (79%) [
 <xref rid="B32-pathogens-09-00519" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Phylogenetically, SARS-CoV-2 is most similar to the bat SARS-like-CoVZC45 concerning most genes [
 <xref rid="B33-pathogens-09-00519" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-pathogens-09-00519" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Even at the amino acid level, SARS-CoV-2 is relatively similar to bat SARS-like-CoVZC45, although there exist certain notable differences. For example, the 6, 7b, and 10 proteins are present in SARS-CoV-2, whereas these are absent in bat SARS-like CoVZC45. Compared to SARS-CoV, the sequence for 8a is absent in the SARS-CoV-2 genome; the sequence for 3b is shorter, while that for 8b has an extra 73 amino acids in SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B29-pathogens-09-00519" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The spike protein-encoding gene in SARS-CoV-2 (1273 amino acids) is longer than those of bat SARS-like-CoVZC45 (1246 amino acids) and SARS-CoV Tor2 (1255 amino acids). Certain accessory proteins, such as the 6 and 7b proteins of SARS-CoV Tor2, are similar to those in SARS-CoV-2, except for a marginal variation in protein length, as shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-09-00519-f002">Figure 2</xref>. The majority of the accessory proteins in MERS-CoV EMC are distinctive, including a longer spike protein (1353 amino acids), compared to those in SARS-CoV-2. In comparison to SARS-CoV-2, bovine CoV ENT has the longest spike protein (1363 amino acids) and a unique hemagglutinin–esterase gene, while porcine CoV HKU15 (a delta-CoV) has the shortest spike protein (1159 amino acids) and lacks several accessory proteins. Hence, it would be interesting to characterize the spike and accessory proteins of SARS-CoV-2 and study the role of these proteins in the pathogenesis and transmissibility of the virus.
</p>
