<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227550.g007">Fig 7</xref> shows the number of DENV dengue cases by island of residence with the incidence per 1000 residents included. Efate has the largest population of Vanuatu with 86,250 residents and as would be expected also has the highest number of residents with confirmed DENV infection, with 26 cases over the period of testing. The remainder of the islands have a population of 46,078 to as low as 229 or less. In general, the number of positive DENV cases can be correlated with the island population, where for most islands, the incidence of DENV infection was not significantly different to the average national incidence (0.416 per 1000 people). However, the islands of Aniwa (
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.0035), Ambae (
 <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.00001), Tongoa (
 <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.00001), and Emae (
 <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.00001) had a higher number of positive cases than would be expected from the number of residents alone. Interestingly the island of Santo, with a population of 46, 078, showed a statistically significant decrease in the number of dengue cases recorded (0.018 per 1000; 
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.0016) compared to the national average. However, the most striking examples are the islands of Emae, Tongoa and Ambae. Ambae has a population of 11061 with 14 confirmed dengue cases while Tongoa and Emae had 2243 and 684 residents with a total of 5 and 6 cases respectively. Aniwa had 1 case of dengue and is home to only 229 inhabitants thus can be excluded as a reservoir of increased dengue infection due to the small population and only 1 case of infection. Although this study is relatively small with a total of 116 confirmed cases from the whole Vanuatu region, perhaps the islands Emae, Tongoa and Ambae had a higher number of mosquitoes harbouring DENV thus leading to the increased number of positive cases observed in residents of the island (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227550.g007">Fig 7</xref>).
</p>
