<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our study has some limitations. First, the sample size was relatively small and had low power to evaluate the significance of viral–bacterial coinfection. Even though the study period included 2 consecutive influenza seasons in Korea, the number of influenza cases was too small to analyze the synergism of influenza virus and pneumococci or 
 <italic>S aureus</italic>. Secondly, respiratory specimens obtained from children without viral infections such as influenza, adenovirus, or RSV were not included as negative controls. So, it is uncertain whether the codetection of certain bacteria in the upper respiratory tract is under the influence of each virus. And third, from the study design, we only included patients with solo—infections of adenovirus, influenza, and RSV which are known to be associated with severe LRTIs. Rhinovirus, for example, is another frequently detected respiratory virus associated with both upper and lower respiratory tract infections. It can possibly cause synergistic bacterial coinfection as shown from previous studies revealing rhinovirus with 
 <italic>S pneumoniae</italic> as the most common combination.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>–
  <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]
 </sup> By restricting the viruses of interest, the overall comprehension of distribution and dynamics of the pathogens of respiratory tract might have been precluded. In addition, the presence of bacteria in the nasopharyngeal aspirates was determined not by semiquantitative real-time PCR but conventional PCR, which leaves some uncertainty of significant bacterial abundance on viral–bacterial interaction. Furthermore, the presence of bacteria in the upper respiratory tract might not reflect the viral–bacterial interaction in lower respiratory tract infections. Finally, we did not review the individual histories of immunization including pneumococcal and 
 <italic>H influenza</italic> type b (Hib) vaccines. However, in Korea, Hib and pneumococcal protein-conjugate vaccine had been included in the national immunization programs since 2013 and May 2014, respectively, and as of 2017, the coverage rate for both vaccines is estimated to have risen up to 97% to 98%.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]
 </sup> So, the incidence of viral–bacterial codetection might not reflect the differences between vaccinated or nonvaccinated patients.
</p>
