<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Second, it has been shown that the germicidal activity of UVGI is compliant with the Bunsen–Roscoe reciprocity law, where it was established that the efficiency of inactivation is dependent on UV dose, which is the product of UV intensity (mW/cm
 <sup>2</sup>) and exposure time (seconds).
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0160" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>160</sup>
 </xref> The resulting implications in the translation into application mean that, upon a reduction of UV intensity, the virucidal action of UVGI can be compensated through the increase of exposure time.
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0161" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>161</sup>
 </xref> When tested for four different strains of airborne bacteriophages: ssRNA (MS2, ATCC 15597‐B1), ssDNA (
 <italic>Φ</italic>X‐174, ATCC 13706‐B1), dsRNA (phi 6 with envelope lipid, ATCC 21781‐B1), and dsDNA (T7, ATCC 11303‐B1), it was reported that the required UVGI dose required was approximately increased twofold when attempting to increase 90% inactivation to 99% inactivation.
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0162" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>162</sup>
 </xref> In the same study, it was also observed that certain strains of viruses were more vulnerable to UVGI than others. The UVGI doses required were, in increasing order, 339–423 µWs/cm
 <sup>2</sup> for ssRNA, 444–494 µWs/cm
 <sup>2</sup> for ssDNA, 662–863 µWs/cm
 <sup>2</sup> for dsRNA, and 910–1196 µWs/cm
 <sup>2</sup> for dsDNA.
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0162" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>162</sup>
 </xref> A similar ranking was reported when it came to observing the sensitivities of similar virus classes on a surface medium (as opposed to aerosol).
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0158" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>158</sup>
 </xref> The susceptibility of viruses to this method was thought to be dependent on several factors, such as physical size, molecular weight, DNA conformation, repair enzyme, and chromophore presence, clumping propensity, etc., which could all affect the UV dose required.
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0163" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>163</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
