<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">What can history teach us about successful responses to past infectious disease pandemics? Given the widespread implementation of social distancing (also known by the more accurate designation of “physical distancing”) in response to COVID-19 disease, public health leaders are deeply interested in the outcomes of these same so-called “nonpharmaceutical interventions” when they were deployed in response to another deadly pandemic of a respiratory virus, the influenza epidemic of 1918–1919 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Contemporary analyses support the fact that these interventions, when implemented early and in a sustained manner, were successful in mitigating the consequences of pandemic influenza in the last century [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. That valuable information is being put to good use during the current wave of SARS-CoV-2. But what can we say about the public health responses that were undertaken in the years following the 1918–1919 influenza pandemic, after the immediate threat had passed? Certainly, there was increased research interest into the causative agent of influenza, leading to the eventual isolation of influenza A from human tissue samples in 1933 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. And historians have noted that the lack of a national disease reporting system in the U.S.—which hindered a coordinated response to the influenza outbreak of 1918/1919—was rectified several years later; by 1925 all U.S. states were participating in a national system to report disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. But given the periodicity of influenza, it’s come-and-go nature, some experts have opined that our national response to pandemics typically follows a cycle of “panic–neglect–panic–neglect” [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Sadly, this supposition is supported by patterns of public health funding in the U.S. Typically, after a national disease outbreak or other disaster there is an infusion of one-time supplemental funding which generally recedes after the emergency wanes and the attention of legislators turns to other, more immediate issues [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].
</p>
