<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Yellow fever (YF) is a potentially fatal disease caused by a member of the family Flaviviridae, genus 
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic>, yellow fever virus (YFV) [
 <xref rid="B1-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The disease is endemic in equatorial Africa, tropical areas of South America, eastern Panama and Trinidad. YFV is transmitted to humans and non-human primates (NHP) by 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> spp. mosquitoes in Africa [
 <xref rid="B2-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] and 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> spp., 
 <italic>Haemagogus</italic> spp. and 
 <italic>Sabethes</italic> spp. mosquitoes in South America [
 <xref rid="B4-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. There are three transmission cycles for YFV: a sylvatic cycle involving NHP and 
 <italic>Aedes africanus, Haemagogus</italic> spp. or 
 <italic>Sabethes</italic> spp. mosquitoes in jungles with sporadic transmission to humans frequenting these areas; an intermediate cycle involving NHPs, humans and 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> spp. mosquitoes in African savannah settings; and an urban cycle involving primarily 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> mosquitoes and humans in cities. While the sylvatic and intermediate YFV transmission cycles account for most human disease, in the last decade there has been a resurgence in urban outbreaks [
 <xref rid="B6-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Many of the recent African outbreaks, including in Uganda in 2010 [
 <xref rid="B7-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], Ethiopia in 2013 [
 <xref rid="B9-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], Angola in 2015 [
 <xref rid="B10-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] and Nigeria in 2017 [
 <xref rid="B12-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], were the first YF outbreaks in these countries in more than 10 years. Moreover, the Angola outbreak resulted in spread to the Democratic Republic of the Congo (DRC)[
 <xref rid="B13-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], Mauritania and Kenya [
 <xref rid="B14-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], as well as importation of disease into China by unvaccinated Chinese nationals who were infected while working in Angola [
 <xref rid="B15-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In South America, a large urban outbreak was detected in 2016 in a non-endemic area of Brazil, and from 2016 to March of 2019 there were 2204 reported human cases or more cases than in the previous 20 years combined [
 <xref rid="B17-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-vaccines-07-00179" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. 
</p>
