<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pone-0078122-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0078122.g002</object-id>
 <label>Figure 2</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Kernel-assisted comparison of two tree shapes.</title>
  <p>For trees comprising 
   <inline-formula>
    <inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0078122.e021.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula> and 
   <inline-formula>
    <inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0078122.e022.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula> nodes, respectively, there are 
   <inline-formula>
    <inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0078122.e023.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula> pairs of nodes to evaluate. (A) Starting from a given pair of nodes (indicated in figure by circles with double-outlines), the algorithm finds the largest common subset tree rooted at these nodes. First, we find that for both nodes, neither of the branches terminate at a ‘leaf node’ (marked with ‘
   <inline-formula>
    <inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0078122.e024.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </inline-formula>‘). This match contributes a relatively small amount to our kernel score, not only because the matching subset trees (highlighted in thick blue lines) comprise only one node each, but also because their discordant branch lengths lead to a substantial penalty. (B) Next, we descend down the left branch in both trees. The current nodes (open circles) in both trees spawn one leaf node and one internal node; therefore, the subset trees continue to match. In addition, their branch lengths are similar, so their contribution to the cumulative kernel score is given greater weight. (C) Finally, we descend down the right branch in both trees and find that the subset trees no longer match beyond this point. We also proceed down the right branch of the reference nodes and find no match, so our traversal of the two trees from these nodes is complete and we restart our search at the next pair of nodes.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pone.0078122.g002" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
