<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>HIV-1 
 <italic>pol</italic> sequences from the study population were supplemented with 1664 HIV-1 
 <italic>pol</italic> sequences from patients newly diagnosed in 2013 (
 <italic>n</italic> = 655), 2015 (
 <italic>n</italic> = 456) or 2017 (
 <italic>n</italic> = 553). Sequences were generated using Sanger sequencing by either the TruGene HIV-1 genotyping kit (TruGene, Siemens Healthcare Diagnostics, Eschborn, Germany), ViroSeq HIV-1 Genotyping System (Abbott Molecular, Wavre, Belgium) or an in-house protocol. Since the length of the generated sequences slightly differed between protocols, they were trimmed to the 870 nucleotides that were covered by all methods, representing codons 9 to 99 of the protease gene and 41 to 239 of the reverse transcriptase gene. Alignments were composed in BioEdit [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-11-01096" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Gaps resulting from the insertions of three nucleotides at codon positions 33 or 35 of the protease gene were observed in less than 20 sequences and were removed. Positions associated with drug resistance, detected in 79 patients, were kept after excluding any influence on the phylogenetic tree topology. The phylogenetic tree was constructed using the maximum likelihood (ML) approach implemented in PhyML 3.0 [
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-11-01096" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] with automatic selection of the best fit evolutionary model of DNA substitution (GTR + G + I) using the Akaike information criterion. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-01096-f001">Figure 1</xref> shows the phylogenetic tree of the extended population of 2849 patients. Branch support was obtained by the approximate likelihood-ratio test (LRT) [
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-11-01096" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Identification of clustering was performed as described before [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-11-01096" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Sequences linked with at least one other sequence with an LRT of ≥0.97 and a mean pairwise distance of ≤0.015 were considered as genetically linked and classified as either paired (2 members) or clustered (≥3 members). Sequences located in a cluster but with a branch length of &gt;0.030 were considered as isolated and removed as cluster members to ensure that the cluster members identified primarily resulted from recent transmission events. 
</p>
