<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0265">Considerable progress was made in the 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> diagnostic test (IVD) for COVID-19. Real-time reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) is the basic ideology for IVD which takes a few hours for the results. Few industries have managed to reduce the test time from 3 h (Cepheid) to 5 min (Abbot). A wide array of serology immunoassays (IAs) that primarily detect IgM and IgG were also developed (automated chemiluminescence IA, manual ELISA, rapid lateral flow IA), complementing the COVID-19 diagnostic molecular assays [
 <xref rid="bb0980" ref-type="bibr">196</xref>]. The production of SARS-CoV-2 antiviral drugs remains problematic as there are no officially approved drugs and vaccines for the treatment of COVID-19. Hence, we must rely solely on implementing preventive and stringent control measures to reduce the possibility of potential transmission of diseases. Furthermore, the currently limited knowledge for therapeutic drugs must be used thoroughly to establish strategies for drug application to inhibit and manage SARS-CoV-2 transmission. While research is underway to improve COVID-19 prevention, treatment, and control, the reported clinical data on various therapeutic approaches are limited. Several preclinical trials show that S protein is a key viral antigen for vaccine development. Detailed clinical trials for already licensed products are being performed on COVID-19 affected patients since they have a well-established safety profile. Studies performed 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> for an antiviral and antimalarial drug namely remdesivir and chloroquine have shown promising results in suppressing the virus. In a recent study dated 9th April 2020, 1061 patients were treated for COVID-19 using a combination of Hydroxychloroquine-Azithromycin (HZQ-AZ) for 3 days and a follow up of 9 days. The results depict that 91.7% of the patients were cured while 4.3% required intensive care units and 0.47% of patients died. The authors reported that HZQ-AZ combination is a safe and effective treatment if begun immediately after diagnosis, and in most cases clears up the virus persistence and contiguity [
 <xref rid="bb0985" ref-type="bibr">197</xref>]. In the future, research must be carried out using an effective animal model that analyses the virus's replication, transmission and pathogenesis also integrating the imaging and molecular diagnosis will help to efficiently track and treat COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0990" ref-type="bibr">198</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0995" ref-type="bibr">199</xref>].
</p>
