<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Time-scaled phylogenies were inferred by the Bayesian Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) method using BEAST v1.82 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006827.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. A total of 129 complete viral E genes, including 104 DENV-2 sequences from RT-PCR confirmed cases obtained in this study and 25 reference sequences retrieved from GenBank, were used to construct a maximum clade credibility (MCC) tree [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006827.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0006827.s002">S2 Table</xref> lists the accession numbers of all sequences included in this study. Complete ORF sequences (10176 nt.) of 43 C6/36 isolated DENV-2 viruses were also subjected to an MCC tree construction. The best-fit DNA substitution model was determined by Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) and Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC) implemented in jModelTest [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006827.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006827.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Both AIC and BIC indicated that the TN93+G model was the best fit for the dataset, and a strict molecular clock was applied. 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0006827.s003">S3 Table</xref> lists log marginal likelihoods of various models by different methods. Two*10
 <sup>8</sup> and 1*10
 <sup>7</sup> MCMC iterations were implemented for E protein and complete ORF, respectively. Tracer v1.8 (available in BEAST package) was used to ascertain the calibration and ensure the effective sample sizes (ESS) of higher than 200 for all parameters. MCC trees were generated by TreeAnnotator v1.8.1 (available in BEAST) after removing 10% as burn-ins, visualized and summarized by FigTree v1.4.2 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006827.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] with posterior probabilities. The viral group evolutionary rates were calculated using Tracer v1.8 after being combined by LogCombiner v1.8.4 (available in BEAST) with constant population size as a tree priority. To obtain root-to-tip genetic distances, maximum likelihood phylogenetic trees were constructed with DENV-2 E and ORF genes using MEGA 6.06 software [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006827.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The genetic distances were plotted against time by R v3.30 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006827.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Phylogenetic trees were visualized with R package ggtree [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006827.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].
</p>
