<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During the viral infection, host innate and acquired immune responses can be activated by virus-derived products, accompanied by the recruitment and activation of eukocytes and other cells by cytokines, chemokines, and inflammatory mediators released from infected or resident immune cells, eliciting antiviral action (Schorey et al., 
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Innate immunity provides the first line of defense and triggers pro-inflammatory responses, while adaptive immunity eliminates the viruses during the later stages of infection (Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). The recognition and respones to viruses are very important for innate immune system. The viral components such as proteins, lipids, carbohydrates and genetic material, are generally defined as pathogen associated molecular patterns (PAMPs). PAMPs can bind with pattern recognition receptors (PRRs) on the plasma membrane of host cells or dendritic cells (DCs) and MΦ to induce cell-signaling cascades, culminating in the activation of innate immune response against the viruses (Kouwaki et al., 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). PRRs include Toll-like receptors (TLRs), RIG-I-like receptors, NOD-like receptors, and C-type lectin receptors. Interestingly, viruses have evolved special strategies to evade and/or inhibit host immune responses to promote their virulence and evade immune surveillance. Influenza viruses evolved multiple ways to escape from the host immunity, for instance, some multi-functional proteins such as non-structural protein-1 (NS1) protein and PB1-F2 protein were produced to suppress innate immune signaling pathways (Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Moreover, EVs may evoke a “Trojan horse” ploy to help influenza viruses avoid the immune surveillance and favor viral entry into the recipient cells, due to their lower immunogenicity and better biocompatibility. Notably, EVs provide shelter for host and viral proteins and genome by protecting them from DNase, RNase and proteinases in extracellular environment. Some host miRNAs with function of promoting virus replication were found in EVs during influenza virus infection (Keshavarz et al., 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). For example, miR-17-5p highly expressed in EVs derived from IAV-infected lung epithelial cells and patients' bronchoalveolar lavage fluid (BALF) can result in decreased expression of the antiviral factor Mx1 and significantly enhanced IAV replication (Scheller et al., 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Therefore, some scholars speculated that those miRNAs within EVs could also promote influenza virus replication in recipient cells (Keshavarz et al., 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Zheng et al., 
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>).
</p>
