<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In contrast, EVs also are found as an antiviral mediator participating in antiviral immunity. Virus-infected cells can release EVs with functional viral RNAs (e.g., mRNA and miRNA) to DCs and MΦ, and then the viral RNAs are internalized and recognized by PRRs to produce a large quantity of type I interferon and pro-inflammatory cytokines. For example, IAV-RNA can be recognized by TLR7 in plasmacytoid DCs (pDCs), triggering the signal to induce antiviral innate immune responses (Diebold et al., 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). Recent studies have revealed that infected epithelial cells release EVs that specifically regulate responses of neighboring epithelial cells and immune cells to limit the virus's transmission. Liu et al. (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) observed that hsa-miR-1975, a Y5 RNA-derived small RNA, was activated in the apoptosis process of influenza virus-infected human lung adenocarcinoma epithelial A549 cells. Subsequently, hsa-miR-1975 was delivered into neighbor cells by exosomes, and fused with other antiviral proteins or nucleotides to produce interferon, and thereby inhibited influenza virus replication when viruses invaded the recipient cells. Besides the infected cells, respiratory epithelial cells not only produce cytokines and chemokines that communicate with immune cells to activate and regulate antiviral responses (Miura, 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>), but also secrete EVs to induce the antiviral responses. Kesimer et al. (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) firstly observed that human tracheobronchial epithelial (HTBE) cells derived exosome-like vesicles with characteristic exosomal size (30–100 nm) and morphology (cup-shaped), and multivesicular and late endosomal membrane markers Tsg101 and CD63, can neutralized influenza viruses by mean of α-2,6 linked sialic acid on the their surface which can preferentially be bound to influenza viruses, implying an antiviral role for exosomes in mucosal innate defense. Thereafter, Maemura et al. (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>) firstly examined the presence of exosomes in BALF of influenza virus-infected mice, and found the quantity of exosomes enriched miR-483-3p was increased. Those miR-483-3p-containing exosomes might mainly derived form MΦ, but not lung tissues. After exosomal miR-483-3p transfection in lung epithelial cells, the expressions of type I interferon and proinflammatory cytokine were increased by miR-483-3p targeting negative regulators of the RIG-I signaling pathway. Besides BALF, furthermore, high levels of exosomal miR-483-3p was also found in serum of influenza virus-infected mice, and high inflammatory cytokines in vascular endothelial cells (Maemura et al., 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Meanwhile, microparticles were found in the BALF of relatively normal subjects who underwent bronchoscopy and bronchoalveolar lavage in the study by Suptawiwat et al. (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Those vesicles were originated from bronchial epithelial cells and alveolar epithelial cells, and might exert their anti-influenza activity by trapping influenza virions using their surface sialic acid. The further study have shown that transformed bronchial epithelial BEAS-2B cells enriched both a-2,6- and a-2,3-linked sialic acids, and their microparticles could combat both H1N1 and H5N1, while human lung alveolar epithelial A549 cells only enriched a-2,6-linked sialic acid and their microparticles could only combat H1N1 virus (Jantaratrirat et al., 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Additionally, EVs from immune cells are also involved in inflammatory responses to viral infection. Huo et al. demonstrated that mast cells may support the productive replication of influenza virus such as H1N1, H5N1, and H7N2 in their previous studies, however, they observed that exosomes were preferentially secreted from H1N1 or H7N2-infected mouse mastocytoma cell in follow-up study, and speculated that those exosomes were potentially pivotal in innate immunity to fight IAV infection via triggering the robust innate immunity of cells (Huo et al., 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>).
</p>
