<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We performed i.c. infection to bypass peripheral dissemination and neuroinvasion, therefore directly measuring the neurovirulence of each variant. Unlike the weak heparin binders IEE and IEQ-244E
 <sup>+</sup>, intracerebrally inoculated IEQ failed to exhibit the same neurovirulent phenotype as it did following i.p. administration, for which we propose two possible explanations. First, virus replication in brain cells may be restricted. This is supported by histopathological studies showing very few neurons in brain are infected with EV-A71 [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007863.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007863.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. IEQ viruses failed to acquire the VP1-K244E mutation, presumably due to lower infectivity of neurons and suboptimal replication following direct inoculation into brain, resulting in low virulence in mice. Secondly, viral multiplication in extraneural tissues such as hind limb skeletal muscle plays a key role in neuropathogenesis [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007863.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Mice intracerebrally inoculated with IEE showed higher viral load in hind limb muscles (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1007863.s004">S4 Fig</xref>), implying that the virus spread to peripheral tissues and underwent further extraneural replication (especially in the skeletal muscles) before re-entering the brain at high titers [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007863.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007863.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007863.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Retrograde axonal transport is the main transmission route for neuroinvasion [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007863.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007863.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. High replication will result in muscle damage that increases retrograde axonal transport and virus trafficking to the CNS [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007863.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007863.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007863.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. The weak heparin binders IEE and IEQ-244E
 <sup>+</sup> remain lethal since they disseminate effectively and establish high viremia prior to neuroinvasion. Using an 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> porcine blood brain barrier (BBB) model (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1007863.s011">S1 Text</xref>), we found no correlation between heparin-binding and neuroinvasion across the BBB through tight junction leakages, as demonstrated by IEE and IEQ which induce poorer permeability compared to wild type KEQ (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1007863.s005">S5 Fig</xref>). This suggests that hematogenous spread is not the main route of spread to brain [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007863.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]; rather, establishment of high viremia appears crucial for virus dissemination to other target organs which support high levels of replication.
</p>
