<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Three complementary mutations, VP1-L97R, VP1-N104S and VP1-E167G, were detected along with VP1-K244E from IEQ-infected moribund mice. Given that these mutations are near the VP1-244 residue site and located at loops (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1007863.s006">S6A Fig</xref>), they could be selectively utilized by the virus to stabilize the conformational structure of the VP1-K244E mutation at the five-fold axis. The VP1-N104S mutation was frequently associated with the VP1-244 variants. Root mean square fluctuation (RMSF) was measured to examine the dynamic movement of residues (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1007863.s006">S6B Fig</xref>); the RMSF value of the BC loop (where VP1-104 is located) was relatively higher in IEQ-244E compared to other virus variants. This indicates that residues within the VP1 BC loop are flexible and may bind poorly to heparin. The emergence of the VP1-N104S mutation could contribute to the conformational stability of VP1-K244E, resulting in enhanced viral infectivity [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007863.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. The VP1-L97R mutation, within the VP1 BC loop, has been reported to enhance heparin-binding [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007863.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. This mutation was first detected from EV-A71 in the blood, CSF and stool from an immunocompromised patient [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007863.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. However, we found this mutation in both the skeletal muscle and brain of an IEQ-infected moribund mouse. Similarly, the presence of the VP1-L97R could stabilize the conformational structure of VP1-244E. Interestingly, both VP1-97R and 104S did not co-exist in the same sample. The VP1-D31G [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007863.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>] and VP1-E167G [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007863.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>] mutations previously implicated in neurotropism in humans were also observed in the brain samples but at very low frequencies. Furthermore, restricting polymerase fidelity and impairing recombination rendered the virus avirulent, suggesting that restriction of population diversity alters fitness of the virus 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. The transition of different virus subpopulations is pivotal for the virus to gain fitness and adaptation 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>.
</p>
