<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Infect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Infect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Infection</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0163-4453</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-2742</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The British Infection Association. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7141704</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S0163-4453(20)30159-6</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2020.03.031</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The role of phylogenetic analysis in clarifying the infection source of a COVID-19 patient</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0001"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Jann-Tay</given-names></name><email>wang.jt1968@gmail.com</email><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0002"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>You-Yu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0003"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Sui-Yuan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0004"><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>Shiou-Hwei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Bor-Hsian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0006"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Pei-Jer</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0007"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Shan-Chwen</given-names></name><email>changsc@ntu.edu.tw</email><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">f</xref><xref rid="cor0001" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>a</label>Department of Internal Medicine, National Taiwan University Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan</aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>b</label>Department of Microbiology, National Taiwan University Center of Genomic Medicine, Taipei, Taiwan</aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>c</label>Department of Clinical Laboratory Sciences and Medical Biotechnology, College of Medicine, National Taiwan University, Taipei, Taiwan</aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>d</label>Department of Laboratory Medicine, National Taiwan University Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan</aff><aff id="aff0005"><label>e</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Hoping Fuyou Branch of Taipei City Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan</aff><aff id="aff0006"><label>f</label>Department of Internal Medicine, College of Medicine, National Taiwan University, No.7, Chung-Shan South Rd., Taipei 10002, Taiwan</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor0001"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author at:Department of Internal Medicine, National Taiwan University Hospital, No. 7, Chung-Shan South Rd., Taipei 10002, Taiwan. <email>changsc@ntu.edu.tw</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p id="notep0001">These authors contribute equally.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>8</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>81</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 The British Infection Association. Published by Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Elsevier Ltd</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p content-type="salutation"><italic>Dear Editor</italic>,</p><p id="para0003">Previous reports indicated that the emergence of the novel coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) infection (COVID-19) had raised global concern and was characterized as a pandemic event by the World Health Organization on March 11, 2020.<xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> Till March 18, 2020, it has spread to 146 countries, including Taiwan.<xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> People in Taiwan and mainland China travel frequently, which put Taiwan at a great risk of acquiring an epidemic of COVID-19. Taiwan has been on constant alert and react rapidly to epidemics change from China ever since the severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) epidemic in 2003 and has done much effort on the containment of COVID-19 with success.<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Till March 18, 2020, there are only 100 cases of COVID-19 noted in Taiwan, including 79 imported cases and 21 cases belonging to seven occasions of limited local transmission (six family clusters and two transmissions in social societies).<xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</p><p id="para0004">To contain the epidemics of COVID-19, prevention from both import and export of contagious people is an essential intervention. It is also important to clearly clarify the infection source in order to initiate an efficient and successful contact tracing for the SARS-CoV-2 infected patients, and thereafter people exposed to the contagious patients could be quarantined to avoid further disease spreading. Here we present a COVID-19 patient whose infection source could not be completely clarified initially, and later was illuminated by using the phylogenetic analysis of the isolated virus.</p><p id="para0005">This 66-year-old Taiwanese woman was well before. She traveled to Dubai from January 29 to February 10, 2020, and Egypt from February 11 to February 21, 2020. When she stayed in Egypt, she ever participated an eight-day tourism on a Nile cruise boat. She returned to Taiwan via an international airline on February 21, 2020. She began to suffer from general malaise, myalgia, cold sweating, productive cough, and sore throat since February 18, 2020. She reported that there were another 16 persons in the same tourism group had similar symptoms at that time. Her symptoms persisted despite medication, prescribed on February 21 by a local medical doctor. On February. 26, the cough exacerbated, and she developed chest tightness, abdominal upset and vomiting. She visited the Department of Emergency of a teaching hospital in Taipei on February 28. No fever was noted during her disease course. In the context of her travel history and prominent respiratory symptoms, a nasopharyngeal swab was taken for test of SARS-CoV-2 by real-time reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR), and the result was positive. She was then transferred to a negative-pressure isolation room as a case of COVID-19.</p><p id="para0006">The most interesting point of this patient is where she contracted her COVID-19. By history, she is more likely to contract SARS-CoV-2 infection while travelling abroad. However, despite that the median incubation period of COVID-19 was 5.1 days, it might be as long as more than three weeks in some extreme cases.<xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Therefore, an argument that she got the infection while she was in Taiwan couldn't be excluded completely.</p><p id="para0007">To clarify this argument, more virologic studies were conducted. Virus whole genome sequencing was conducted for the SARS-CoV-2 isolate (NTU03) from her throat swab collected on March 2, 2020. The derived NTU03 sequence was most similar to clade A2a with only 5 nucleotide differences, which included 2 synonymous mutations (Orf 1b/5410 CTA&#x0003e;TTA, and orf 3a/819 GTG&#x0003e;GTT), 2 nonsynonymous mutations (Orf 1b/799 <italic>G</italic>&#x0003e;<italic>V</italic>, and orf 3a/57Q&#x0003e;<italic>H</italic>), and a mutation within 5&#x02032;UTR (<xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table</xref>
1). An average of 12 nucleotide differences were observed between NTU03 and sequences of other clades, whereas an average of 10 nucleotide differences were observed with other previous viruses isolated from Taiwan. The phylogenetic analysis also reveals that the NTU03 belongs to clade A2a (<xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of SARS-CoV-2 alignment.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0002">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1_lrg.gif"><alt-text id="alt1">Image, table 1</alt-text></inline-graphic></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>SARS-CoV-2 genetic sequences, including NTU03, all 6 previously submitted Taiwan sequences, and representative sequences for clades A1, A1a, A2, A2a, A3, A5, B1, B2, and B4, were aligned and compared. MN908947 was used as the reference sequence, and orange shaded nucleotides indicated nucleotides different to the reference nucleotide, and gray shaded positions indicated lack of nucleotide information. The NTU01 and CDC03 are derived from the Case 3 patient, and CDC04 and CGMH1 are from the from the Case 4 patient. Sequence data were obtained from GISAID (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gisaid.org/CoV2020/" id="interref0003">https://www.gisaid.org/CoV2020/</ext-link>) . The GISAID accession number for each representative clade sequence: A1a, hCoV-19/Switzerland/1,000,477,102/2020|EPI_ISL_413,019; A1, hCoV-19/Singapore/11/2020|EPI_ISL_410,719; A2a, hCoV-19/Italy/UniSR1/2020|EPI_ISL_413,489; A2, hCoV-19/Germany/BavPat1/2020|EPI_ISL_406,862; A3, hCoV-19/Australia/NSW13/2020|EPI_ISL_413,599; A5, hCoV-19/USA/CA5/2020|EPI_ISL_408,010; B1, hCoV-19/USA/WA12-UW8/2020|EPI_ISL_413,563; B2, hCoV-19/USA/TX1/2020|EPI_ISL_411,956; B4-1, hCoV-19/South Korea/KUMC03/2020|EPI_ISL_413,513; B4-2, hCoV-19/USA/CA7/2020|EPI_ISL_411,954.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig0001"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic analysis of the full-length SARS-CoV-2 sequences. The phylogeny tree analysis was conducted to determine the clade of NTU03 (red asterisk) and its relationship to other viral sequences derived from case patients identified in Taiwan (red arrows). The phylogenetic tree was generated and modified for display purposes from Nextstrain (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nextstrain.org/ncov" id="interref0001">https://nextstrain.org/ncov</ext-link>),<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> which uses genetic sequences and metadata from GISAID (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gisaid.org/CoV2020/" id="interref0002">https://www.gisaid.org/CoV2020/</ext-link>) and sequence submission date for the horizontal axis.<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> The phylogenetic tree was generated at 2020/03/09 6PM (GMT+8) with a total of 240 viral genomes sampled (For interpretation of the references to color in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of this article.).</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0001">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p><p id="para0008">Based on the results of whole genome sequencing and phylogenetic analysis, NTU03 belongs to clade A2a, in which all other of the reported case patients were currently either from Europe or travelled to Europe recently according to the information provided by the laboratories who submitted the clade A2a sequences to the Global Initiative on Sharing All Influenza Data (GISAID). None of the previously submitted sequences of viruses isolated from Taiwan were assigned to clade A2a or A2.</p><p id="para0009">With the limited transmission clusters in Taiwan and the fact that NTU03 exhibits at least 8 unique nucleotide difference compared to other previously reported viruses from Taiwan, we conclude that it is much more probable that the present patient was infected during her travelling abroad. To our best knowledge, in late February and early March, several foreign&#x000a0;COVID-19 patients who had travel histories to Egypt were reported. Further phylogenetic analysis including viral sequences derived from the 45 confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infections on the quarantined Nile cruise boat will help to delineate the outbreak on Nile tourism boat and its impact on the COVID-19 epidemic.<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>
</p><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title><p id="para0010">None to declare.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebibl1"><title>References</title><ref id="bib0001"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0001"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tambyah</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>D.S.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emergence of a novel coronavirus causing respiratory illness from Wuhan, China</article-title><source>J Infect</source><volume>80</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>350</fpage><lpage>371</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0002"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0002"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emergence of SARS-like coronavirus in China: an update</article-title><source>J Infect</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2020.03.010</pub-id><comment>[Epub ahead of print]</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="othref0001">World Health Organization[Internet]. Statement on the second meeting of the International Health Regulations (2005) Emergency Committee regarding the outbreak of novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV). [cited 2020 Mar 18]. Available from:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/events-as-they-happen" id="interref0004">https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/events-as-they-happen</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="othref0002">Taiwan Centers for Disease Control. Situation of COVID-19 in Taiwan. [cited 2020 Mar 18]. Available from:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://sites.google.com/cdc.gov.tw/2019ncov/taiwan" id="interref0005">https://sites.google.com/cdc.gov.tw/2019ncov/taiwan</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0005"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0003"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brook</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Response to COVID-19 in Taiwan: big data analytics, new technology, and proactive testing</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.3151</pub-id><comment>[Epub ahead of print]</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0006"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0004"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Backer</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klinkenberg</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallinga</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incubation period of 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) infections among travelers from Wuhan, China</article-title><comment>20028 January 2020</comment><source>Euro Surveill</source><volume>25</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2000062</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0007"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lauer</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grantz</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>F.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meredith</surname><given-names>H.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The incubation period of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) from publicly reported confirmed cases: estimation and application</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M20-0504</pub-id><comment>[Epub ahead of print]</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="othref0003">The Washington Post. Egypt tires to reassure tourists as coronarivus spikes. [cited 2020 Mar 18]. Available from:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/middle_east/egypt-tries-to-reassure-tourists-as-coronavirus-spikes/2020/03/08/ab1dfbf6-6160-11ea-8a8e-5c5336b32760_story.html" id="interref0006">https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/middle_east/egypt-tries-to-reassure-tourists-as-coronavirus-spikes/2020/03/08/ab1dfbf6-6160-11ea-8a8e-5c5336b32760_story.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib0009"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0006"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hadfield</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Megill</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huddleston</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Callender</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nextstrain: real-time tracking of pathogen evolution</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>34</volume><issue>23</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>4121</fpage><lpage>4123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29790939</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0010"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0007"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sagulenko</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Puller</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neher</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TreeTime: maximum-likelihood phylodynamic analysis</article-title><source>Virus Evol</source><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2018</year><comment>vex042</comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0001"><sec id="sec0001"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p id="para0011">We thank all the persons involved in the response to this outbreak.</p></sec><sec id="sec0002"><title>Financial support</title><p id="para0012">This study was financially supported by grant from the &#x0201c;Center of Precision Medicine&#x0201d; from The Featured Areas Research Center Program within the framework of the Higher Education Sprout Project by the Ministry of Education (MOE) in Taiwan.</p></sec></ack></back></article>