<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">Like other viruses and bacteria, it seems that SARS-CoV-2 as well could trigger acute cerebrovascular diseases (CVD), such as ischemic or haemorrhagic stroke and cerebral venous sinus thrombosis, which have been reported in several patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Stroke incidence was reported between 2.5 and 6% in retrospective European and Chinese studies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Such complications seem to be caused by alterations in the homeostasis of coagulation. It is noteworthy that patients with severe forms of COVID-19 showed higher levels of D-dimer [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] and more serious thrombocytopenia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Nonetheless, numerous pieces of evidence have recognized the role of the inflammatory response as a contributor to the pathophysiology of cerebrovascular diseases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Consistently with this evidence, higher concentrations of C-reactive protein have been reported in patients who developed CVD [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Recently, Li and colleagues [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] further speculated that the involvement of the nervous system by SARS-CoV-2 may also play a role in the onset of respiratory failure occurring in COVID-19. ACE2 is expressed in the brainstem and the CNS replication of SARS-CoV-2 might directly involve the cardiorespiratory centre [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Additionally, the skeletal muscle injuries that have been documented in COVID-19 patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] might concur to the development of respiratory failure. Moreover, it is well known that severe hypoxia, which often presents in patients with COVID-19, can lead to brain damage with cerebral vasodilation and interstitial oedema. These effects might indeed be precipitated or worsened by an overlapping respiratory failure.
</p>
