<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The seasonality of MI, ventricular arrhythmias, and SCA/SCD has for many decades been the focus of epidemiology studies, as seasonality may suggest etiological factors.[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] Because all patients in our study had a first STEMI, we were able to examine the seasonality and relationship of viral exposure with VF independently of its association with STEMI. Most,[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] but not all,[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] studies showed a seasonal variation of SCD, with a peak in winter (December and January) and a reduction during the summer months (from June through September). A link between viral infection of the heart (myocarditis) and sudden cardiac death has long been recognized.[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] At least 20 different viruses, including EV, have been implicated in myocarditis.[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] Although most patients infected with EV remain asymptomatic or only experience flu-like symptoms, the role of EV as one of the most common causes of viral myocarditis is well-established.[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] Evidence for a role of EV infection in the modulation of cardiac electrical function and pro-arrhythmia is the fact that myocarditis is one of the most common findings at autopsy in young adults who died of SCD,[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] and patients with serious ventricular arrhythmias and survivors of SCD had prevalent detection of EV RNA in their endomyocardial biopsies, suggesting a role of EV in ventricular arrhythmias and SCD[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Although we did not find an association between influenza and VF risk during STEMI, substantial evidence has been gathered to support the effect of influenza among MI patients.[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] These findings are consistent across studies using various measures for viral exposure, such as influenza activity at the population level through surveillance data,[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] as well as at the individual level with laboratory-confirmed infection[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The latter is preferable, and Kwong et al. found in a self-controlled case-series study that laboratory-confirmed influenza in the week before MI was associated with increased risk of MI.[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] Incidence ratio for acute MI during the 7-day risk interval compared with the control interval was 6.05 (95% CI 3.86–9.50). These data suggest that influenza-like illness can cause MI.[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]
</p>
