<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One of the contributing factors to virus infectivity and virulence is a phenomenon called antibody-dependent enhancement (ADE). ADE refers to the viruses binding to specific antibodies of the surface of host cells that enhance their entry and replication. This phenomenon was observed in many viruses, including the yellow fever virus, zika virus, and coronaviruses [
 <xref rid="B33-diagnostics-10-00409" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. ADE can adversely impact the process of vaccine development because vaccines could trigger the production of antibodies that viruses could use to gain access to host cells, so the vaccine could worsen the condition that it was designed to fight. Thus, ADE is a major potential challenge for COVID-19 vaccine development, as ADE was observed in other types of coronaviruses that resulted in previous pandemics, including SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV. For example, there were several vaccine candidates for the SARS-CoV pandemic, including whole inactivated viruses, DNA, subunits, and vectored vaccines. Although these vaccines were able to halt the replication of the SARS-CoV virus in infected cells, they granted viral access to macrophages through ADE, which eventually caused serious lung infections [
 <xref rid="B34-diagnostics-10-00409" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-diagnostics-10-00409" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The SARS vaccine candidates resulted in enhanced hepatitis, increased morbidity, and stronger inflammatory responses that were attributed to ADE [
 <xref rid="B36-diagnostics-10-00409" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Similarly, the MERS-CoV virus was shown to utilize the cellular receptors that mimic viral receptors to gain access to host cells, resulting in enhanced infection [
 <xref rid="B37-diagnostics-10-00409" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Little is known about whether ADE will present a challenge to target the SARS-CoV-2 due to gained access to immune cells or due to prior coronavirus infections, and it is currently an active area of investigation [
 <xref rid="B38-diagnostics-10-00409" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].
</p>
