<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par123">In the second category of antibody drugs, additional modifications are made to the antibody in order to enhance its therapeutic value. Some general approaches include immunocytokines, antibody-drug conjugate, antibody-radionuclide conjugates, bispecific antibodies, immunoliposomes, and chimeric antigen receptor T cell (CAR-T) therapy. To create an immunocytokine, a selected cytokine is fused to an antibody to enhance delivery specificity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR259">259</xref>]. Antibody drug conjugates consist of an antibody that targets a cancer-specific marker conjugated to the small molecule drug; the antibody enhances delivery to the tumor site, increasing the efficacy of the small molecule while reducing side effects by reducing non-specific toxicity to non-target tissues [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR260">260</xref>]. The antibody may also be conjugated to a radionuclide, in order to direct radiotherapy more specifically to the tumor site [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR261">261</xref>]. For bispecific antibodies, antibodies targeting two receptors are engineered to further enhance therapeutic effects [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR262">262</xref>]. Antibody-engaged effector cell functions may enhance the therapeutic efficacy of bispecific antibodies. With regard to immunoliposomes, the binding site of the antibody (scFv or Fab) is cleaved from the constant region and subsequently conjugated to different nano-drug delivery systems, such as liposomal drugs, to provide more specific targeting [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR263">263</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR264">264</xref>]. Lastly, CAR-T involves inserting the gene for a chimeric T cell receptor-antibody targeting a specific cancer marker into T cells, such that the engineered cells target and kill cancer cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR265">265</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR266">266</xref>]. In recent years, this approach has garnered major attention from the scientific and medical community due to its significant clinical benefits to cancer patients. In many cases, patients have experienced complete remission or even been completely cured of cancer [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR267">267</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR271">271</xref>].
</p>
