<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A clearer apprehension of SARS-CoV-2 pathophysiology in humans, immunological protection correlation, and the time duration of naturally acquired immunity would benefit the development of COVID-19 vaccination approaches to limit the dissemination of the virus. Comprehensive knowledge of the SARS-CoV-2 pathogenesis, including the infection of target organs and the route and mechanism of virus propagation to these vital organs, will aid in developing vaccines for the protection of target organs. For example, if the SARS-CoV-2 causes pneumonia via upper respiratory tract infection, the use of vaccine preparations containing live replication-competent vectors or weekend viruses that are able to induce local mucosal immune response can protect both the upper as well as lower respiratory tract infections and causes a significant reduction in nasal shedding. On the other hand, if the infection occurs in the lungs or other organs through viremia, then parenteral (IM) vaccines, which provoke adequate virus-neutralizing antibodies in serum to prevent viremia. Furthermore, people who have recovered from COVID-19 infection but are again primed to the virus-like seasonal influenza, the administration of a parental vaccine (i.e., subunit S or RBD protein) may provide an effective remedy as to yearly booster vaccination.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
 </sup> These booster vaccines would augment memory T- and B-cell mediated immunity responses, and may aid in preventing viral reinfections. In some COVID-19 patients, diarrhea and fecal shedding were observed,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="cit0072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>
 </sup> and these conditions can be effectively overcome by the use of oronasal vaccines. Therefore, COVID-19 vaccination is likely to be used in three types of populations (1) naïve (susceptible) individuals with no immunity level (2) recovered individuals with different immunity levels and people having preexisting resistance to MERS-CoV or SARS-CoV. As a result, the immune reactions, defensive ability, and adverse response of candidate vaccines may differ among these populations. It will be meaningful to assess preexisting immunity levels for validating the safety and efficacy of the vaccine in each population and various range groups within these populations.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
