<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since the winter season of 2011-2012, the Influenzanet platforms share a common and standardized data collection approach throughout the nine European countries involved, namely: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.degrotegriepmeting.nl" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Belgium</ext-link> (BE), 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://influmeter.dk" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Denmark</ext-link> (DK), 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.grippenet.fr" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">France</ext-link> (FR), 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://flusurvey.ie" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Ireland</ext-link> (IE), 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.influweb.it" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Italy</ext-link> (IT), 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.degrotegriepmeting.nl" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">the Netherlands</ext-link> (NL), 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gripenet.pt" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Portugal</ext-link> (PT), 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gripenet.es" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Spain</ext-link> (ES) and 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://flusurvey.org.uk" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">the United Kingdom</ext-link> (UK). In each of the Influenzanet countries, the national platform is coordinated by a team of local researchers from Universities, Research Institutions or Public Health Institutions and consists of a website where individuals can register and have access to a personal account where they can insert and update their data. The platforms are disseminated among the general population through press releases, public media campaigns, specific dissemination events (e.g. science fairs) or word of mouth. Participation is voluntary and anonymous, and all the residents of the participating countries can enrol. Upon registration, individuals are asked to complete an online Intake Questionnaire covering basic questions such as age, gender, household size and composition, home location, workplace, etc. [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006173.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Participants can also create accounts on behalf of other members of their family or household, thus enabling, for instance, parents to record data for their children. Registered participants are then reminded weekly, via an e-mail newsletter, to fill in a Symptoms Questionnaire [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006173.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] in which they are presented with a list of general, respiratory and gastrointestinal symptoms (18 in total, reported in 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006173.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) and asked whether since the last time they visited the platform they experienced any symptoms among those listed. In this study, we employed data collected by the Influenzanet platforms in the nine European countries over the course of six influenza seasons, from 2011-2012 to 2016-2017.
</p>
