<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The use of 3D models in MBF research has facilitated the study of mechanisms of MBF infection. For example, research using neurospheres of neural progenitor cells (NPCs) and cerebral organoids has demonstrated that NPCs and radial glia are more susceptible to altered cell cycle and cell death following ZIKV infection (Cugola et al., 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Dang et al., 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Nowakowski et al., 
 <xref rid="B149" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Xu et al., 
 <xref rid="B237" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Gabriel et al., 
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Garcez et al., 
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Zhou et al., 
 <xref rid="B245" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Moreover, studies in cerebral organoids have shown that exposure to ZIKV at early stages of differentiation disrupts organoid expansion and fold formation (Li et al., 
 <xref rid="B120" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Other cerebral organoid studies have shown that ZIKV targets and replicates in proliferating ventricular zone (VZ) apical progenitors, affecting NPC differentiation and leading to progenitor depletion, disruption of the VZ, impaired neurogenesis, and cortical thinning (Cugola et al., 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Gabriel et al., 
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Organoids and neurospheres have also been used in drug development (Xu et al., 
 <xref rid="B237" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) and to explore the oncolytic potential of ZIKV (Zhu et al., 
 <xref rid="B247" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Other iPSC-derived 3D models have also incorporated primary microglia cells to study flavivirus-microglia interaction in a multicellular system (Abreu et al., 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). More complex models have the potential to better model human physiology than classical 2D 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> models. In other fields, organoids have shown to be a novel tool for drug screening development for cancer (Weeber et al., 
 <xref rid="B227" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), intestinal diseases (Liu et al., 
 <xref rid="B125" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), and others.
</p>
