<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>What is disheartening is to see children and young adolescents succumbing to stress and anxiety in the wake of this adversity.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r155" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>,
  <xref rid="r156" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>
 </sup> In view of forestalling further spread of this highly infectious disease, countries around the world have been forced to push a majority of their population into quarantine, which includes many children as well. While this has effectively slowed the progression of the disease, this dramatic change in their environment seems to have quite a distressing effect on everyone, and children are no exception. They are being exposed to widespread fear propelled by the rapid spread of the virus, compounded by constant news chatter about death and disease, which creates an environment of uncertainty around them. Million children worldwide are stuck in limbo, with their schools shut down indefinitely and outdoor activities stalled.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r155" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>
 </sup> While for those staying at home with their parents this strain may have been reduced to some extent, it is equally difficult for those separated from their caregivers/parents. Being confined to their homes for prolonged periods increases irritability, restlessness, nervousness and lack of concentrating abilities among children.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r155" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>
 </sup> High incidences of acute stress disorders, adjustment issues and grief among children isolated or quarantined during a pandemic have been reported.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="r159" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>,
  <xref rid="r160" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>
 </sup> Parental loss during childhood does go a long way in the development of mood disorders, psychosis and increased suicidal rates in the future. There are growing evidences of household violence and child abuse in view. Children with disabilities, those staying in crowded settings and living on streets are deemed particularly vulnerable. For an entire generation, to grow up in these conditions, with no clear answers for the foreseeable future, is unprecedented and will inevitably have a significant impact on their outlook.
</p>
