<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Human cell responses to DENV infection can be studied better in humanized mouse models since these models provide the opportunity to measure the contribution of host factors in an 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> system. NOD/SCID mice transplanted with human cord blood hematopoietic progenitor (CD34
 <sup>+</sup>) cells and infected with DENV mimicking natural infection conditions have been used to demonstrate the clinical symptoms of dengue with a fever, rash, and thrombocytopenia [
 <xref rid="B118-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. Antibody responses mimicking primary dengue infection have been demonstrated in RAG2
 <sup>−/−</sup>γ
 <sub>c</sub>
 <sup>−/−</sup> mice that were xenografted with human CD34+ hematopoietic stem cells [
 <xref rid="B119-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. A humanized NOD-SCID IL2rγ null mice (
 <xref rid="viruses-11-00252-t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>) model has been used to demonstrate differences in the virulence of different DENV-2 genotype strains. Southeast Asian strains produced the highest viremia, followed by Indian strains and Sylvatic strains [
 <xref rid="B120-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>]. An improved humoral response, HLA-A*02-restricted T cell response, and associated IFN-γ production were observed in BLT-NSG mice, but not in NSG mice. Therefore, BLT-NSB mice are an attractive platform for assessing human immune responses to the DENV vaccine [
 <xref rid="B121-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>,
 <xref rid="B122-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. However, humanized mice models predominantly develop IgM in response to DENV infection; only a few developed an IgG response because of inefficient class switching, and hence the kinetics of the antibody response was slow [
 <xref rid="B119-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>,
 <xref rid="B123-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>]. Research efforts are expected to lead to the development of ideal models that will show both IgM and IgG responses for studying dengue pathogenesis [
 <xref rid="B124-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]. The serum metabolomic profile of DENV-2 infected humanized mice has also been utilized to identify the prognostic markers to predict severe dengue. The results yielded a profile similar to those reported in human longitudinal studies [
 <xref rid="B125-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. Human immune system (HIS) BLT-NOD/SCID mice have also been demonstrated to be useful in preclinical testing of the efficacy of antiviral drugs against dengue [
 <xref rid="B126-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. The following future aspects can be aimed at with the observed results: (i) to test the safety of the DENV vaccine in the recipient without pathology [
 <xref rid="B120-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>,
 <xref rid="B127-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>]; and (ii) to test the immunogenicity of the DENV vaccine [
 <xref rid="B126-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>,
 <xref rid="B128-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>,
 <xref rid="B129-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>].
</p>
