<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par53">Historically, higher attack rates and more severe disease outcomes were observed among minorities since 1900s including during the 1918 influenza pandemic [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">45</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR126">127</xref>]. In an analysis of influenza 2009 H1N1 cases pooled from 19 countries, Van Kerkhove et al. (2011) reported that indigenous populations and minority groups were disproportionately represented among hospitalized influenza cases and fatalities in Canada, Australia, and New Zealand, while in Mexico and Thailand minority groups did not carry excess disease burden. In a Canadian case–control study of laboratory-confirmed pH1N1 cases, 37 % were represented by the First Nation residents. The odds ratio was 6.52 for the First Nation individuals being admitted to the ICU compared to other ethnic groups even when controlling for socioeconomic status, age, residency settings, comorbidities, and time to treatment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">45</xref>]. Similar results for influenza severity were observed in the USA where the risk for pH1N1 influenza hospitalization in New Mexico was 2.6 times higher among American Indians, 1.7 times higher for Blacks, and 1.8 times higher for Hispanics compared to non-Hispanic Whites [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">105</xref>]. Surveillance data from 12 states showed that the rate of mortality attributed to pH1N1 was four times higher among the American Indians and Alaska Natives (AI/AN ) and they had the highest rate (81.0 %) of underlying health conditions than all other ethnic groups [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127">128</xref>]. Higher proportion of pediatric hospitalizations among minorities was observed during the pre-pandemic seasons as well, including the 2000–2001 season [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">129</xref>] and 2003–2004 when influenza A/Fujiian was the prevalent circulating virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115">116</xref>].
</p>
