<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par55">Traditionally populations at the extremes of the age spectrum, young children and older adults are the most vulnerable groups during seasonal influenza epidemics while pandemics exhibit a characteristic shift towards younger adults in influenza-related deaths [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">65</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">80</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">130</xref>]. Persons younger than 65 years of age accounted for a greater proportion of deaths during all three pandemics in the twentieth century as well as during the 2009 H1N1 pandemic when young adults were at an increased risk for morbidity and mortality. Age was an independent risk factor for severe disease outcomes and death. In a study of hospitalized influenza cases in Washington State the odds of ICU admission or death were 4.4 and 5.9 times greater among adults 18–49 years and 50–64 years of age respectively compared with children younger than 18 years when controlling for other risk factors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. The lower influenza incidence rate and mortality among adults over 64 years observed during pandemics could be explained by antigen recycling mechanism, a partial protection due to earlier exposure to a similar virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">65</xref>]. However, if infected, this age group had the highest mortality rate among the hospitalized patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">99</xref>] potentially due to the presence of comorbidities, effect of medications, and bacterial coinfections. Explanations for severe disease among young adults included antibody-dependent enhanced infection and strong inflammatory response in the lungs leading to lung injury and ARDS [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Once infected with a novel influenza virus younger persons may retain long-lasting immunity better than older persons [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129">130</xref>].
</p>
