<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0105">In this study, we demonstrated variably heterogenous glycosylation patterns within a diverse panel of HAs, ranging from minor high-mannose fractions in avian HA stem domains, to near-complete oligomannose sites within the heads of human IAV HAs. Glycoproteomics analysis and structures of glycosylated HAs highlight broad conservation as to the location of many HA glycans, while occupancy of these sites with either complex or high-mannose glycoforms appears far more diverse, particularly between avian and human examples. That highly occupied oligomannose sites are almost exclusively associated with human-adapted HAs, suggests the possibility that reduced glycan processing might be selected for as part of host adaptation. Notably, glycosites with significant oligomannose content such as N94 and N289 in H1, and N165 and N286 H3, are well-conserved since the respective emergences of both H1N1 and H3N2 IAVs in humans (
 <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S4</xref>). Further glycoproteomic analysis of two early H3 HAs from A/Duck/Ukraine/1/1963 (DK/63; avian H3 precursor) and A/Hong Kong/1/1968 (HK/68; human pandemic H3) strongly supports this possibility, revealing that both H3 precursors also contain significant high-mannose fractions at N165 and N285 (
 <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref> ). Interestingly, with significant oligomannose fractions detected at all glycosites, the avian H3 pandemic precursor DK/63 appears quite distinct from contemporary avian examples profiled. Thus, appearance of high-mannose type glycans on IAV HAs may well be more complicated than simple host origin or adaptation. However, while the H5, H6, H7, and H10 HAs investigated here do reflect avian IAVs that have been able to infect humans in isolated cases, none have yet fully evolved properties to enable sustained human-to-human transmission. Comparison of glycome profiles determined here with additional examples in the literature (
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Khatri et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Mir-Shekari et al., 1997</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura et al., 1980</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Ward and Dopheide, 1981a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Ward and Dopheide, 1981b</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Ward et al., 1980</xref>) (see 
 <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S5</xref>) further supports observations that certain high-mannose glycoforms are well-conserved in fully adapted human H1 and H3 HAs, even between very early and late examples. Together these data suggest a model where IAVs carrying high-mannose glycans may be predisposed to human adaptation, or that host-adaptive pressures may instead select for strains with potential for increased high-mannose incorporation.
</p>
