<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par63">The development of new formulations against 
 <italic>Candida albicans</italic> is essential to overcome drawbacks as multiple resistance mechanisms developed by biofilms formation, which makes this pathogen resistant to drugs such as fluconazole and amphotericin B, and, consequently, making difficult to treat effectively these infections, contributing to high morbidity and mortality rates in immunocompromised patients (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR141">141</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR155">155</xref>). In light of this, Paramanantham 
 <italic>et al</italic> . (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR141">141</xref>) reported a nanosystem based on MSNs modified with Rose Bengal (RB) as photodynamic therapy (PDT) as antimicrobial alternative to treat 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> biofilms. MSNs with average pores size and diameter of 2 and 500 nm, respectively, were amino functionalized aiming to increase the conjugation capacity of RB. RB is a photosensitizer, an organic compound that absorbs light of a suitable wavelength generating singlet oxygen and reactive oxygen species (ROS), which can kill microbial systems. High values of RB EE (58.54%) was achieved by amino-modified MSNs due to the good electrostatic interaction of the positively charged MSNs surface with anionic dye RB. Taking the aforementioned into account, 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> release tests showed a slow and controlled RB release with a maximum of 66.38% after 3 h. Additionally, cellular uptake studies exhibited high MSNs-RB uptake (up to 47%) compared to the free RB (up to 10%) after 3 h. Through 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> release results, amine groups modified onto MSNs enabled a slow and controlled release, by electrostatic attraction with the RB, which is desirable and allow a good PDT action after a single administration. When associated with PDT, high values of MSNs-RB antimicrobial action were achieved for both 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> planktonic cells (up to 88.7%) and biofilms (up to 79.7%) regarding pristine MSNs and free RB. Beyond that, after light irradiation, MSNs-RB exhibited high ROS production, proteins leakage (from cytoplasm 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> cells), DNA damage and lipid peroxidation. These results confirmed the MSNs-RB as an efficient nanosystem as antimicrobial PDT against infections caused by antifungal drug resistant and biofilm forming strains, being its application extended to enhance 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> eradication on medical devices such as implants and catheters.
</p>
