<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par64">Econazole (ECO), an antifungal widely used for topical infections treatment has limited bioavailability due to its low aqueous solubility (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR156">156</xref>). Aiming to overcome ECO solubility drawbacks, Montazeri 
 <italic>et al</italic> . (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140">140</xref>) developed ECO-loaded MSNs modified with aminopropyl groups. Spherical shape and hexagonal mesopores arrays were detected for MSNs. Pristine MSNs, modified MSNs and ECO-loaded MSNs displayed average size ranging from 39 to 91 nm while the nanosystems presented average pores size up to 2.54 nm. In addition, MSNs was negatively charged (MSNs and MSNs-ECO showed -12.14 and -17.51 mV, respectively) whereas after amino modification the nanosystem showed positive surface charge (MSNs-NH
 <sub>2</sub> and MSNs-ECO-NH
 <sub>2</sub> exhibited +32.52 and +33.63 mV, respectively). MSNs and MSNs-NH
 <sub>2</sub> exhibited ECO EE of up to 42 and 63% and release rate of 29.57 and 38.65, respectively. Both MSNs and modified MSNs containing ECO were non-toxic to human dermal fibroblast strains cells. Distinct ECO/MSNs and modified MSNs ratios were evaluated being that the antifungal activity (
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>) for all nanosystems increased as drug amount loading increased. Greater antifungal activity was observed for modified nanosystems compared to the non-modified ones showing inhibition zone of up to 19.5 and 16.0 mm, respectively (at 1.2 mg mL
 <sup>-1</sup> of ECO). ECO-loaded MSNs displayed greater antifungal activity regarding to the econazole cream, confirming the nanosystem efficiency for the infectious treatment caused by fungus such as 
 <italic>C. albicans</italic>. Additionally, the developed nanosystem exhibited non induced skin irritation on rabbits, being cutaneous reaction negligible after 72 h. It is worth mentioning that the designed nanoplatform could reduce the treatment duration by increasing patient compliance, making this nanosystem desirable for fungal therapy purposes.
</p>
