<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par65">In another study, authors (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR142">142</xref>) fabricated pH-responsive gated MSNs-based nanosystem aiming to treat fungal infections such as vaginal candidiasis. The sensitive MSNs like MCM-41 nanoplatforms were loaded with tebuconazole (TEB) and modified with silane groups as 3-[2-(2-aminoethylamino)ethylamino]propyltrimethoxysilane (N3) used as gatekeepers that can avoid TEB leakage from the mesopores before the nanosystem reach the target site. Spherical-shaped silica nanoplatform with average size of 100 nm and hexagonal pores arrays with mean diameter of 2.45 nm were successfully prepared as well as the TEB loading (0.064 mmol g
 <sup>-1</sup> of MSNs) into mesopores and subsequently capping with N3 groups (2.43 mmol g
 <sup>-1</sup> of MSNs). For cellular uptake assays, fluorescein (FL, green dye) were loaded into MSNs and modified with the N3 gatekeeper. The simulated nanosystem exhibited good cellular internalization (
 <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> cells, incubated at pH 3.7) detected by fluorescence microscopy. In addition, 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> release FL tests were performed at pHs 3.7 and 5.5. Results showed that more than 95% of FL was released after 12 h whereas almost no release was detected at pH 3.7, confirming the design of pH-responsive nanosystem. At pH 3.7, the polyamines of N3 capping was more protonated than at pH 5.5, which allowed high rigid chain conformation and high interactions with anions (as SO
 <sub>4</sub>
 <sup>2-</sup>), that favor the mesopores blockage. At pH 5.5, the polyamine chains is more flexible allowing pores opening and FL release. After successful cellular uptake and FL release tests, 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> antifungal assays (
 <italic>C. albicans</italic> cells) were performed with the MSNs-TEB-N3 and free TEB. Results exhibited high antifungal activity promoting 90% of cells death by using MSNs-TEB-N3 while free TB showed only 10% of action. In this way, the designed smart nanoplatform improved TEB efficacy comprising an interesting tool to overcome side effects associated with topical therapies for vulvovaginal infection and improve its cost-effectiveness. A schematic pH-responsive nanosystem action is displayed in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>.
</p>
