<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The maximum number of midges per plains zebra (
 <italic>ψ</italic>) were extracted from records of seasonal abundance in 
 <italic>Culicoides</italic> populations (including 
 <italic>C. imicola</italic>) in the vicinity of livestock at seven sites of South Africa between October 1983 and December 1986 [
 <xref rid="pone.0222366.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. For the purpose of this study, records of only two of the seven sites were used (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0222366.g003">Fig 3A</xref>): Stellenbosch (33°56’S, 18°52’E) and Eiland (23°40’S, 30°45’E); and were chosen to characterise the seasonal midges’ activity in the WCP and in KNP, respectively. Venter et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0222366.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] reported the total number of collection events and the total number of 
 <italic>Culicoides</italic> trapped per season (spring, summer, autumn and winter) as well as the proportion of 
 <italic>C. imicola</italic> over the total number of 
 <italic>Culicoides</italic> collected. Estimates of 
 <italic>ψ</italic>, together with the activity rate 
 <italic>a</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>), were then computed from these data assuming that one light trap collection using downdraft blacklight traps mimics, when placed near host, the daily host seeking activity of 
 <italic>Culicoides</italic> toward one individual zebra as well as its seasonal variation [
 <xref rid="pone.0222366.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. We therefore translated trap data directly to vector to host ratios, identified the maximum number of 
 <italic>C. imicola</italic> per collection events to estimate 
 <italic>ψ</italic> and adjusted remaining records to compute 
 <italic>a</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>), with monthly values of 
 <italic>a</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>) ranging from 0 to 1 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0222366.g002">Fig 2B</xref>). We further account for the uncertainty in the maximum number of midges per plains zebra by randomly sampling the estimate of 
 <italic>ψ</italic> from a Poisson distribution at the start of each simulation.
</p>
