<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The quality of specimens can be affected by several steps including operation of specimen collection, transport, and storage. For URT and sputum samples, sample quality depends greatly on the operation of the collectors. Firstly, synthetic fiber swabs with plastic shafts and sterile container were recommended to use when collecting, while calcium alginate swabs or swabs with wooden shafts should not be used as they may contain substances that inactivate viruses and inhibit PCR testing.
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>27</sup>
 </xref> Secondly, to get enough virus infected cells, swabs must be inserted deep enough. In detail, nasopharyngeal (NP) swab must be inserted through the nares parallel to the palate, and oropharyngeal (OP) swab needs to be inserted into posterior pharynx and tonsillar areas.
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">29</xref> Several studies have reported that combined NP and OP specimens could increase the sensitivity of detecting respiratory viruses.
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">32</xref> As seen in Table 
 <xref rid="rmv2106-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>, although using different RT‐PCR methods targeting different genes, the threshold cycle (CT) value of NP and OP swabs was much lower than NP or OP swab alone, suggesting that in accordance with other respiratory viruses, combining NP and OP swabs together could increase viral load and the sensitivity of SARS‐CoV‐2 RNA detection. Sputum is often confused with saliva. Although SARS‐CoV‐2 could be detected in saliva,
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>33</sup>
 </xref> sputum is preferred by several guidelines.
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">34</xref> Patients should cough deeply so that sputum rather than oral secretions is collected. Dehydration may lessen the fluid in the lungs and make it hard to produce sputum, hence drinking water before collection can increase availability. To avoid contamination, all types of samples must be transported in sterile containers. To ensure sample stability, storage condition should be strictly controlled, which is summarized with other key points of specimen collection in Table 
 <xref rid="rmv2106-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>.
</p>
