<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>After specimen collection, different methods should be used to process specimens for different purposes. For isolation and culture of virus, centrifuging samples to remove cellular debris, and then inoculating the supernatant on human airway epithelial cells, Vero E6 cells or Huh‐7 cells. It took about 96 hours for SARS‐CoV‐2 to be successfully cultured in human airway epithelial cells, and took about 6 days to be cultured in Vero E6 or Huh‐7 cells.
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">22</xref> The isolation and culture should be conducted at BSL‐3, and laboratory workers should wear protective equipment, including disposable gloves, solid front or wrap‐around gowns, scrub suits, or coveralls with sleeves that fully cover the forearms, head coverings, shoe covers or dedicated shoes, eye protection, and respiratory protection.
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>35</sup>
 </xref> Inactivation of viruses without reducing detection efficiency is required for testing RNA of high pathogenic CoVs at BSL‐2 and protecting experimenters from infection. Trizol, Trizol LS (Life Technologies), and buffer AVL (Qiagen) have been standard methodology for purifying and extracting viral RNA for years. Guanidine salt in these agents can inhibit nuclease, thereby ensuring viral RNA is not degraded. Viral RNA in samples placed in buffer AVL was stable for at least 48 hours at 32°C, and at least 35 days at either 4°C or −20°C.
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>36</sup>
 </xref> In addition, the powerful denaturing activity of guanidine isothiocyanate in these reagents could denature and dissolve protein, thus effectively inactivating enveloped viruses. The phenol component of Trizol could also disrupt membranes and denature proteins. These reagents were shown to inactivate alphaviruses, flaviviruses, filoviruses, bunyaviruses, and ebola virus.
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">37</xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">39</xref> Kumar, et al. confirmed that AVL, Trizol and Trizol LS could completely inactivate MERS‐CoV within 10 minutes' room temperature incubation.
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>40</sup>
 </xref> Thus, although many methods have been verified to effectively inactivate SARS‐CoV and MERS‐CoV,
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>41</sup>
 </xref> we suggest handling samples in these reagents, as well as other virus retention reagents containing guanidine salt would be an effective way to inactivate and stabilize viruses, without affecting subsequent molecular testing of SARS‐CoV‐2. Since CoVs are sensitive to heat, heating inactivation of samples could effectively inactive virus if SARS‐CoV‐2 antibody needs to be tested at BSL‐2. However, it should be noticed that heat inactivation could significantly interfere with the levels of antibodies, and might cause false‐negative results. It was reported that the anti‐SARS‐CoV‐2 IgM levels of all samples decreased by an average level of 53.56%, and the IgG levels were decreased in 64.71% samples by an average level of 49.54% after heating at 56°C for 30 minutes.
 <xref rid="rmv2106-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>42</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
