<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The sex chromosomes X and Y, which differentiated from ordinary autosomes about 180 million years ago, show great levels of dissimilarities, except in their pseudo-autosomal regions (PAR1 and PAR2) located at the end of both chromosomes [
 <xref rid="B123-ijms-21-03474" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>]. Having two X-chromosomes, females have two different cell types in all their organs with one of the two X-chromosomes being inactivated (Xi, while the activate form is Xa), a condition that was first described by Mary F. Lyon in mice [
 <xref rid="B124-ijms-21-03474" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]. The XCI is due to epigenetic processes that randomly select and permanently silence one of the two X-chromosomes of a female individual. The process occurs at an early phase of embryonic development and is maintained during adulthood. XCI is a strategy that aims to balance the X-linked transcriptional dosage between female XX and male XY cells. In general, 50% of female cells and all cells derived from them have the maternal X-chromosome inactivated, the other 50% have the paternal X-chromosome inactivated. The knowledge of the complex mechanism of XCI and its regulation is summarized in [
 <xref rid="B125-ijms-21-03474" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. XCI results in a condition of “cell mosaicism” in a female individual, where a balanced expression of both parental X-linked genes is expected [
 <xref rid="B126-ijms-21-03474" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. This condition may provide females with greater plasticity and adaptability in the response to infectious diseases than males. When it comes to gene expression, females may compensate adverse X-linked mutations by using cells that carry the wild allele on the other X-chromosome [
 <xref rid="B124-ijms-21-03474" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]. However, it is clear that XCI is incomplete in humans [
 <xref rid="B127-ijms-21-03474" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>] and that the balance may be disrupted both by the process of skewed XCI and by genes escaping silencing [
 <xref rid="B123-ijms-21-03474" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>].
</p>
