<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are four types of seasonal influenza virus vaccines currently licensed for use in humans: inactivated, live attenuated, recombinant protein, and cell-based vaccines. A vast majority of the influenza virus vaccines administered in humans are split inactivated vaccines, which are produced in embryonated chicken eggs. For split inactivated vaccines, vaccine strains are individually grown in the allantoic cavity of embryonated chicken eggs and inactivated by treatment with formalin or β-propriolactone (
 <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Gerdil, 2003</xref>). Once purified, virus particles are then split using ether and detergent to reduce the level of viral ribonucleoproteins, which cause reactogenicity at the site of injection (
 <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Gerdil, 2003</xref>). The individual vaccine components are mixed in a standardized manner to ensure an inclusion of 15 μg of HA per strain (
 <xref rid="ref102" ref-type="bibr">Sridhar et al., 2015</xref>). Inactivated vaccine is administered intramuscularly to stimulate the systemic immune response, producing mainly IgG antibodies and low amounts of IgA antibodies (
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Clements et al., 1986</xref>). Similar to inactivated vaccines, live attenuated influenza vaccines (LAIVs) are grown in embryonated eggs. LAIV strains are generated using a reverse genetics approach to incorporate HA and NA genes from circulating influenza strains into a cold-adapted, attenuated influenza virus backbone (
 <xref rid="ref102" ref-type="bibr">Sridhar et al., 2015</xref>). Cold adaption of the LAIV backbone ensures that the replication of the vaccine strain does not occur at temperatures above 33°C, allowing for replication in the upper respiratory tract but not in the lower respiratory tract (
 <xref rid="ref102" ref-type="bibr">Sridhar et al., 2015</xref>). LAIV, which is administered intranasally to mimic natural infection, stimulates robust IgA and IgG responses in the upper respiratory tract (
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Clements et al., 1986</xref>). LAIV has also been shown to elicit T-cell mediated responses in vaccinated children (
 <xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">He et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">Hoft et al., 2011</xref>). While both inactivated vaccine virus strains and LAIV viruses are grown in embryonated eggs, this poses a challenge in the event of egg shortages and for immunization of individuals with egg allergies. Recombinant protein vaccines and cell culture-based influenza vaccines have been developed to overcome limitations of egg-based vaccines. Currently, there is only one recombinant vaccine, named Flublok
 <sup>®</sup>, approved for use by the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA). Flublok
 <sup>®</sup> still contains HA protein antigens representing the selected influenza strains for the current season, but it is produced in insect cells (
 <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Cox and Hollister, 2009</xref>). In contrast to embryonated egg-based vaccines, manufacturing of Flublok
 <sup>®</sup> takes approximately 2 months and can be administered in individuals with egg allergies, providing an advantage over traditional seasonal egg-based vaccines (
 <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Cox and Hollister, 2009</xref>). In regard to cell-based vaccines, Flucelvax
 <sup>®</sup> is a licensed quadrivalent inactivated vaccine that is grown in a mammalian cell line and can avoid any potential egg-based mutations (
 <xref rid="ref64" ref-type="bibr">Lamb, 2019</xref>). As with Flublok
 <sup>®</sup>, Flucelvax
 <sup>®</sup> can be administered to individuals with egg allergies and requires a shorter production time than egg-grown vaccines.
</p>
