<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0090">So far, most neutralizing antibodies recognize the RBD in the S protein S2 of CoVs. Compared with the high mutation rate in the S1 protein, S2 is much more conservative, thereby decreasing the off-target risk caused by amino acid replacement [
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>], and also bypassing the special epitopes that may cause ADE [
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. This means that the cocktail of monoclonal antibodies binding to different epitopes of RBD would be more desirable for therapeutic purposes [
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. For treatment, the monoclonal antibodies are from a human source or are humanized antibodies, isolated or generated with various approaches. For example, wild-type mice were immunized with soluble recombinant RBD containing the S protein. Then mouse antibodies were humanized and isolated, or transgenic mice were directly immunized, to express human versions of the antibodies [
 <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. However, direct cloning of single B cells from human survivors, used in combination with the phage-display antibody library, could provide authentic human antibodies. Until now, it should be noted that many neutralizing antibodies have been successfully discovered for treatment of SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>] and MERS-CoV infection [
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. These antibodies have all been described favorably in the literature [
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. A similar approach is known as single chain fragment variable (scFv) library screening, whereby the use of RBD as a bait protein allows some neutralizing antibodies to be screened out from non-immune humans [
 <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>].
</p>
