<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0145">According to new studies, dexamethasone was the first agent to be proven to cause ‘significant reduction in mortality’ in individuals with COVID-19 who require oxygen or ventilation. As part of the random evaluation of the Oxford University's COVID-19 treatment (RECOVERY) trial, some patients are being treated with steroids. During the trial, a total of 2104 patients were randomly assigned to receive oral or intravenous dexamethasone, 6 mg once a day for 10 days, and were randomized with 4321 patients in the control group. Dexamethasone reduced the mortality of ventilated patients by 35% (rate 0.65, 95% CI 0.48–0.88; p 0.0003), whereas it decreased by 20% among patients who received oxygen only (0.80, 95% CI 0.67–0.96; p 0.0021). No benefit was seen in patients who do not require respiratory support (1.22, 95% CI 0.86–1.75; p 0.14) The Oxford University research on various drugs that may help against COVID-19 found that dexamethasone improves the survival of patients with COVID-19 who are receiving oxygen or using ventilators. For those receiving oxygen therapy, it saved the lives of one patient among 25 patients who were treated (reducing the number of deaths by about one-fifth). For patients using a ventilator, it saved the lives of eight patients (reducing deaths by approximately one-third). In particular, it seems to help avoid the damage caused by cytokine storms in the most severely affected patients 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.recoverytrial.net" id="intref0035" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.recoverytrial.net</ext-link> [
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Physicians must ensure the laboratory-confirmed SARS-CoV-2 status of patients and their medical history, and must consult the official recommendations of WHO for dexamethasone clinical use, because from time to time drugs are suspended and new drugs are approved. It was also explained in the study that dexamethasone does not help those who are mildly infected with the virus, indicating that it works by treating specific symptoms rather than the virus itself [
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. The researchers shared preliminary observations with WHO on the test findings and look forward to completing data analysis. WHO may coordinate a meta-analysis to improve our overall understanding of the intervention. In addition, WHO clinical guidance will be updated to reflect how and when the drug should be used in COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>].
</p>
