<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In regards to the effects of HIV on DC maturation, studies show controversial data and results as well. It has been demonstrated that once immature DCs encounter HIV, DCs undergo maturation where molecules on the surface are upregulated and DCs can migrate from the periphery to secondary lymphoid organs [
 <xref rid="B48-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Upon arrival at lymphoid tissues in mucosal transmission, HIV trans-infection to CD4+ T-follicular helper cells can occur [
 <xref rid="B52-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. It has been shown that DCs can undergo maturation by viral infection or by cytokines in the microenvironment during migration and then present HIV antigens to T cells in secondary lymphoid tissues and initiate an immune response [
 <xref rid="B53-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Other studies have demonstrated that infection of HIV on DCs with different stimuli can lead to maturation in monocyte-derived DCs [
 <xref rid="B54-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. An important component of DC maturation involves DC-derived microvesicle-associated HIV particles, which are released from T lymphocytes and DCs [
 <xref rid="B55-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. It is well known that immature DCs are more susceptible to HIV infection in comparison to mature DCs likely due to CCR5 expression differences [
 <xref rid="B56-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. The presence of these microvesicles results in increased maturation of DCs, thereby reducing de novo replication of HIV [
 <xref rid="B57-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Conversely, other studies have shown partial maturation of DCs that is mediated by abnormal or partial up-regulation of cell maturation markers effecting binding of gp120 to monocyte-derived DCs [
 <xref rid="B58-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. It has also been demonstrated that HIV infection can actively suppress DC maturation by inhibiting TLR-induced maturation of DCs [
 <xref rid="B59-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. The interactions between DCs is complicated and no one DC subset behaves the same. The diversity of CLRs enables DCs to broadly capture pathogens and dictate the fates of the antigen. The interactions between DCs is complicated and no one DC subset behaves the same. The diversity of CLRs enables DCs to broadly capture pathogens and dictate the fates of the antigen [
 <xref rid="B60-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. In addition to DC-SIGN, CD207, and cDC, expression of CLRs vary among DC subtypes and have been thoroughly defined [
 <xref rid="B62-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-jcm-09-02661" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. However, further characterization of CLRs on DCs to better understand their immune function, and how they influence infection with HIV and other pathogens, may lead to novel insight to develop new strategies to prevent HIV infection of DCs.
</p>
