<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="d1e3464"> Type I IFN was used to treat MERS-CoV, SARS-CoV, and SARS-CoV-2 infection 
 <xref rid="b53" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b92" ref-type="bibr">[92]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b93" ref-type="bibr">[93]</xref>. The early treatment of MERS-CoV infection protected mice from lethal infection but late induction could result in serious pneumonia 
 <xref rid="b92" ref-type="bibr">[92]</xref>. SARS-CoV-2 was shown to be more sensitive to type-I IFN treatment than SARS-CoV 
 <xref rid="b53" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b93" ref-type="bibr">[93]</xref>. Our simulation shows that the antiviral drug efficacy needs to be close to 90% to suppress viral replication effectively. However, intensification with interferon can more effectively reduce the duration of viral plateau with a 60% efficacy of the antiviral drug. Comparison of the genomic sequences of SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV shows that some changes, such as the absence of open reading frame (ORF) 3b and a short truncation of ORF6 in SARS-CoV-2, can reduce the virus’ capacity to interfere with type I IFN 
 <xref rid="b53" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b93" ref-type="bibr">[93]</xref>. ORF3b is a 154 amino acid (AA) long protein that blocks IRF3 phosphorylation 
 <xref rid="b94" ref-type="bibr">[94]</xref>. SARS-CoV-2 ORF3b has a premature terminal codon that produces a truncated protein of 22 AA. The N-terminal domain of ORF6 can disrupt karyopherin transportation of transcriptions factors like STAT1 
 <xref rid="b53" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b95" ref-type="bibr">[95]</xref>. SARS-CoV-2 has a two amino acid truncation in its ORF6 
 <xref rid="b53" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. These alterations might make SARS-CoV-2 infection more sensitive to IFN. IFN was also administrated with other drugs to treat COVID-19 patients but the outcomes have not been available 
 <xref rid="b96" ref-type="bibr">[96]</xref>. Because IFN might activate immunity to attract more immune cells, further studies are needed to determine if IFN can exacerbate the cytokine storm and evaluate the effectiveness of using IFN with and without other antiviral drugs to treat SARS-CoV-2 infection in humans.
</p>
