<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An important question is why large human WNV outbreaks have not been detected in Latin American countries [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. The tropical and subtropical regions of the Americas have suitable conditions for the establishment of WNV, including warm temperatures, diverse avian populations, and a variety of 
 <italic>Culex</italic> mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. Moreover, SLEV, a similar flavivirus maintained by 
 <italic>Culex</italic> vectors and avian hosts is endemic throughout the Americas [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref123" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>]. Considering that the “old” NY99 genotype virus was recently detected in Brazil [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>] and serological evidence of WNV is prevalent in resident birds from Latin America [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>], it is likely that WNV is endemic throughout the Americas. Perhaps the presence of other mosquito-borne viruses has thus far masked human cases (e.g., misdiagnosed as dengue) or may convey some level of cross-protection [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. Alternatively, as WNV may have initially outcompeted SLEV in the US [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref124" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>], the presence of competitive SLEV genotypes in Central and South America may have at least temporarily slowed WNV transmission in these regions. Given these uncertainties, initiatives to introduce human and equine serosurveys and dead bird and mosquito surveillance for WNV in regions throughout the Americas are paramount for determining its true burden.
</p>
