<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par38">In general, patients with depressed immunity are at a higher risk of infectious diseases. The effect of COVID-19 on the cardiovascular system in immunocompromised patients, such as those with cancer or those who have undergone organ transplantation, is largely unknown. Heart transplantation recipients might be at higher risk of COVID-19 owing to their immunosuppressed state combined with their baseline cardiovascular disorders
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>
 </sup>. COVID-19 has been reported in two heart transplantation recipients from China, both of whom made a full recovery
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>
 </sup>. The clinical presentations of these two patients were not distinct from those of non-immunosuppressed patients. In a retrospective case series of heart transplantation recipients with COVID-19 admitted to hospitals in Michigan, USA, between 21 March 2020 and 22 April 2020, 13 patients were identified, all of whom were African American men
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>
 </sup>. Six patients required admission to the ICU and two patients died during hospitalization. Of note, the clinical presentation and laboratory markers of disease severity of these patients were not distinct from those of the general population, despite immunosuppression use to preserve allograft function. However, another case series involving 28 heart transplantation recipients with COVID-19 in New York reported higher mortality and an increased incidence of severe complications in these individuals than in the general population
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>
 </sup>. A total of 22 patients were hospitalized, of whom 7 patients required mechanical ventilation and 7 patients died (case fatality rate 25%). Moreover, 13 out of 17 patients had myocardial injury, as evidenced by elevated levels of troponin T (&gt;0.022 ng/ml).
</p>
