<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0355">Using the gene trapping approach, Carette et al. 
 <xref rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr">[76]</xref> first identified several host factors that are required for EBOV infection. These include a cholesterol transporter Niemann–Pick C1 factor involved in the fusion of endosomes and lysosomes (homotypic fusion and protein sorting complex), biogenesis of endosomes (PIKFYVE), lysosomes (BLOC1S1, BLOC1S2), and targeting of luminal cargo to the endocytic pathway 
 <xref rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr">[76]</xref>. Many of these hits reoccurred in several CRISPR and small interfering RNA (siRNA)/shRNA screenings 
 <xref rid="bib0390" ref-type="bibr">[77]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0395" ref-type="bibr">[78]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0410" ref-type="bibr">[81]</xref>. In addition, lysosomal protein (BRI3) and a GTPase involved in the regulation of vesicle trafficking (RAB39B), PI3K, calcium/calmodulin kinase-related network, and de novo pyrimidine synthesis pathway are essential for EBOV replication and transcription 
 <xref rid="bib0395" ref-type="bibr">[78]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0400" ref-type="bibr">[79]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0405" ref-type="bibr">[80]</xref>. The application of RNAi screening has been utilized for other viral pathogens such as henipavirus, JUNV, poxvirus, 
 <italic>Vaccinia virus</italic>, and VEEV 
 <xref rid="bib0380" ref-type="bibr">[75]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0415" ref-type="bibr">[82]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr">[83]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0425" ref-type="bibr">[84]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0430" ref-type="bibr">[85]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0435" ref-type="bibr">[86]</xref>. It is demonstrated that catalytic activity of fibrillarin, the enzymatic subunit of the snoRNP complex that is responsible for catalyzing the transfer of a methyl donor from a bound cofactor 
 <italic>S</italic>-adenosyl methionine to ribose sugars of the target pre-rRNA, is required for henipavirus infection 
 <xref rid="bib0415" ref-type="bibr">[82]</xref>. Voltage-gated calcium channel (VGCC) subunits were shown to be important in JUNV–cell fusion and entry into cells. Gabapentin, an FDA approved anticonvulsant drug against α
 <sub>2</sub>δ
 <sub>2</sub> subunit-containing VGCCs, inhibited replication of the vaccine strain of JUNV in mice 
 <xref rid="bib0380" ref-type="bibr">[75]</xref>. Other siRNA-based screens against 
 <italic>V. virus</italic> identified that AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK) promotes viral entry through the control of actin dynamics, and knockdown of nuclear pore protein (Nup62) arrests virion morphogenesis 
 <xref rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr">[83]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0425" ref-type="bibr">[84]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0430" ref-type="bibr">[85]</xref>. Lastly, an siRNA screen identified trafficking host factors that modulate VEEV infection 
 <xref rid="bib0435" ref-type="bibr">[86]</xref>.
</p>
