<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Drug-resistant tuberculosis (DR-TB) is defined as a case of TB excreting bacilli resistant to one or more anti-TB drugs. DR-TB exists in various forms: monodrug-resistant TB (mono-DR-TB), polydrug-resistant TB (poly-DR-TB), rifampicin-resistant TB (RR-TB), multidrug-resistant TB (MDR-TB), and extensively drug-resistant TB (XDR-TB).
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Mono-DR-TB is a case of TB showing resistance to single first-line anti-TB drugs only. Isoniazid (H) resistance is a type of mono-DR-TB and has recently become an important concern, as there is a risk of amplification of resistance involving additional drugs if left untreated. Poly-DR-TB is a case of TB resistant to more than one first-line anti-TB drug other than both rifampicin (R) and H. RR-TB is defined as a case of TB showing either resistance to R only or accompanied by resistance to other anti-TB drugs in various forms such as R mono-DR-TB, R poly-DR-TB, MDR-TB, and XDR-TB. The last two are important forms of DR-TB. MDR-TB is defined as a case of TB showing either exclusive resistance to both H and R or accompanied by resistance to other first-line anti-TB drugs. XDR-TB refers to resistance to at least one of three fluoroquinolones (FQs) and at least one of three second-line injectable drugs (SLIDs), in addition to multidrug resistance. A subset of MDR-TB patients may have additional resistance to second-line anti-TB drugs — at least one of three FQs (ofloxacin [Ofx], levofloxacin [Lfx], moxifloxacin [Mfx]) or one of three SLIDs (capreomycin [Cm], kanamycin [Km], amikacin (Am)] but not to both — also known as pre-XDR-TB. MDR-TB and XDR-TB are considered a global health problem with notoriously difficult and challenging treatment.
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> A dynamic interaction exists between TB and HIV infection. TB accelerates the progression of disease in people living with HIV (PLHIV), and PLHIV have increased susceptibility to TB infection. TB is a major cause of mortality among PLHIV, while HIV is responsible for failure of TB-control programs in achieving targets, particularly in high-burden countries. TB and HIV coinfection enhances the risk of harboring and acquiring M/XDR-TB strains.
 <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> HIV coinfection with M/XDR-TB further complicates the situation, and is considered a significant threat with challenging management. Proper adherence to treatment remains an issue, due to higher pill burden, overlapping or additive adverse drug reactions (ADRs) and drug–drug interactions. The current review addresses the relationship between HIV and M/XDR-TB, collaborative TB–HIV activities, diagnostic and clinical guidelines for management of M/XDR-TB in HIV-infected patients, potential drug interactions, ADRs and monitoring requirements in the concomitant treatment of M/XDR-TB and HIV, and infection-control implications in the context of HIV and M/XDR-TB.
</p>
