<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0290">Improvements to genetic sequencing technologies have reduced costs worldwide and advanced the field of ‘phylodynamics’, in which epidemiological dynamics are inferred from pathogen sequence data. In the early 2000s, new computational packages, including Bayesian Evolutionary Analysis Sampling Trees (BEAST), provided the capacity to infer detailed evolutionary, demographic and spatial patterns from sequence data (
 <xref rid="bib0315" ref-type="bibr">Lemey et al., 2009a</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0320" ref-type="bibr">Lemey, Rambaut et al. 2010</xref>). However, in-depth studies of influenza virus evolution require large numbers of viral sequences carefully sampled over time and space, which are unavailable in many low- and middle-income countries. To address this gap, Fogarty’s MISMS staff partnered with the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID) and National Library of Medicine (NLM), to provide whole-genome sequencing of influenza virus collections free of cost via the Influenza Genome Sequencing Program (
 <xref rid="tb0015" ref-type="boxed-text">Box 3</xref> ). When this sequencing project began in 2005, there were fewer than 100 complete influenza virus genomes available on GenBank. As of 2017, almost 20,000 influenza virus genomes have been sequenced through this project and made publicly available. A strong linkage between the Influenza Genome Sequencing Program and Fogarty’s MISMS network of global researchers, and their viral collections, has helped address important gaps in influenza sequence availability and in turn transmission dynamics. The program targeted understudied aspects of influenza virus evolution, including large regions of the viral genome not typically sequenced, under-sampled populations in tropical settings, influenza B virus, and non-human mammalian hosts (
 <xref rid="tb0015" ref-type="boxed-text">Box 3</xref>). The program fostered a global culture of data-sharing that facilitates large-scale comparative studies across subtypes, regions, and species, advancing our fundamental understanding of influenza virus evolution and ecology.
 <boxed-text id="tb0015">
  <label>Box 3</label>
  <caption>
   <title>The Influenza Genome Sequencing Project, a large-scale collaboration between NIH institutes and J. Craig Venter Institute, transforms our understanding of influenza virus evolution.</title>
  </caption>
  <p id="par0390">
   <list list-type="simple" id="lis0020">
    <list-item id="lsti0115">
     <label>1</label>
     <p id="par0125">Major ‘jumps’ in influenza antigenic space can be produced by genomic reassortment events (
      <xref rid="bib0240" ref-type="bibr">Holmes, Ghedin et al. 2005</xref>; 
      <xref rid="bib0385" ref-type="bibr">Nelson et al., 2008a</xref>).
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0120">
     <label>2</label>
     <p id="par0130">Multiple lineages of influenza virus are introduced into single geographic locations every winter and co-circulate (
      <xref rid="bib0395" ref-type="bibr">Nelson et al., 2007</xref>, 
      <xref rid="bib0405" ref-type="bibr">2008b</xref>).
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0125">
     <label>3</label>
     <p id="par0135">Influenza viruses migrate continuously between winter epidemics in Northern and Southern hemispheres, and the irregular seasonality of influenza in tropical regions may be central to the virus’s long-term persistence (
      <xref rid="bib0395" ref-type="bibr">Nelson et al., 2007</xref>; 
      <xref rid="bib0455" ref-type="bibr">Rambaut, Pybus et al. 2008</xref>).
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0130">
     <label>4</label>
     <p id="par0140">The sudden global emergence of influenza A/H3N2 viruses resistant to adamantine drugs was driven by reassortment and genetic hitchhiking, and local, but not global, drug selection pressure (
      <xref rid="bib0550" ref-type="bibr">Simonsen, Viboud et al. 2007</xref>; 
      <xref rid="bib0400" ref-type="bibr">Nelson et al., 2009</xref>).
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0135">
     <label>5</label>
     <p id="par0145">Avian influenza viruses do not transmit as conserved genome constellations, owing to ongoing genomic reassortment and shuffling of genes (
      <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">Dugan, Chen et al. 2008</xref>).
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0140">
     <label>6</label>
     <p id="par0150">Next-generation sequencing techniques reveal the extent of intra-host diversity, and how sub-populations fluctuate over the course of an infection and during transmission events. (
      <xref rid="bib0195" ref-type="bibr">Ghedin, Fitch et al. 2009</xref>; 
      <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">Hughes, Allen et al. 2012</xref>)
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0145">
     <label>7</label>
     <p id="par0155">Remarkable spatial fluidity was observed during the 2009 H1N1 pandemic, to the extent that college students with illness on the same day in the same dorm possessed genetically different viruses, highlighting the challenge of viral control during outbreaks (
      <xref rid="bib0235" ref-type="bibr">Holmes, Ghedin et al. 2011</xref>).
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0150">
     <label>8</label>
     <p id="par0160">The evolutionary history of influenza A viruses includes a selective sweep of the internal genes of avian influenza viruses during the late 1800s, which may coincide with an invasion of an H7 virus of equine origin (
      <xref rid="bib0655" ref-type="bibr">Worobey, Han et al. 2014</xref>).
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="lsti0155">
     <label>9</label>
     <p id="par0165">Decades of long-distance swine trade has spread viruses between continents, creating multiple niches with high genetic diversity where novel pandemic viruses may evolve, exemplified by Mexico, the source of the 2009 H1N1 pandemic (
      <xref rid="bib0390" ref-type="bibr">Nelson, Lemey et al. 2011</xref>; 
      <xref rid="bib0410" ref-type="bibr">Nelson, Viboud et al. 2015</xref>)
     </p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
  <notes notes-type="alt-text" specific-use="for-accessibility" id="at0035">
   <p>Alt-text: Box 3</p>
  </notes>
 </boxed-text>
</p>
