<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Surveillance is the most important preventive measure for assessment of the current contamination situation and timely discovery of virus variation, so that effective measures may be implemented to control the disease. Some researchers
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref> have reported findings from environmental surveillance. Horm
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref> found that the samples collected from farms had a higher H5N1 positive rate than those from ponds. Another study
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref> observed that the H7N9 positive rate in live poultry markets (LBMs) was higher than those on farms and in slaughter houses. Poor management, such as the absence of regular rest days to clean and disinfect the premises, causes severe hygiene problems and the spread of viruses in LBMs
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>. Of the laboratory-confirmed cases of avian influenza A (H7N9), 75% had a history of poultry exposure
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>. In addition to H7N9, LBMs are also the major source of human infections with other avian influenza subtypes, such as H10N8, H5N6, H5N1 and H9N2
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>. Zhejiang, situated in the core area of Yangtze River Delta, is an area of high incidence of avian influenza
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>. Being a province with a powerful economy, it has close trade links, including live poultry transactions, with other provinces. Thus, avian influenza viruses are easily spread across Zhejiang
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>. Shutting down the LBMs may be an ideal control measure. However, it is traditional for consumers to purchase live birds at local markets and slaughter them at home. Therefore, it is important to manage LBMs effectively with the use of environmental surveillance.
</p>
