<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During the colonial period the region was economically more dependent on the large southern cities of the Stanley Pool (Leopoldville-West, Leopoldville-East (Kinshasa), and Brazzaville) than on western Cameroon, because of the easy transportation highway provided by the Congo-Sangha river system. Local firms used the Belgian railway between Kinshasa and the Atlantic port of Matadi, available since 1898, to export their products. The French companies used the Belgian railway until 1932, when a second railway connecting Brazzaville to Pointe Noire was completed, diverting most of the region's exports from the Belgian railway [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72-viruses-04-01950">72</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B151-viruses-04-01950">151</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B156-viruses-04-01950">156</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B157-viruses-04-01950">157</xref>]. In the period 1899–1914 the German connections to Kinshasa were particularly intense. The GSK was exploiting the resources of southeast Kamerun more intensively than its French counterparts in neighboring AEF, and it had large warehouses in Moloundou [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54-viruses-04-01950">54</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B122-viruses-04-01950">122</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B151-viruses-04-01950">151</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B156-viruses-04-01950">156</xref>]. Both the GSK and the associated Kameruner Schiffahrts-Gesellschaft had steamers navigating between southeast Kamerun and Kinshasa, and Belgian archival documents refer to warehouses and other property owned in Kinshasa by these two German companies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B158-viruses-04-01950">158</xref>]. For example, on the day the First World War broke out, four German steamers were docked in Kinshasa, which illustrates the intensity of the commercial links between the city and southeast Kamerun [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B122-viruses-04-01950">122</xref>]. The German administration and enterprises in Moloundou employed men described as “Bangala” [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54-viruses-04-01950">54</xref>]. This designation could mean they belonged to the Bangala tribe from the Belgian Congo (of which our previous research revealed that many men were in Kinshasa [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16-viruses-04-01950">16</xref>]), or speakers of Lingala, a trade language by then dominant in the Congo basin's colonial posts [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B159-viruses-04-01950">159</xref>]; in either case they could well have frequented or inhabited the Pool cities.
</p>
