<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat.1007919.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007919.g002</object-id>
 <label>Fig 2</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Phylogeny of the PB2 gene in H9N2 G1-like subclades isolated in the Middle East and Central Asia.</title>
  <p>(A) Phylogenetic tree of the PB2 genes of H9N2 G1-like subclades isolated in the Middle East and Central Asia, including the G1-A/B reassortant. The tree was reconstructed from nucleotide sequences of the PB2 genes of the Middle Eastern and Central Asian reference strains and of the prototype G1/1997, EG/2013 and A/duck/Hong Kong/Y280/1997 (i.e., the prototype Y280-like clade). CK, DK, QL and TK in the virus strain names denote chicken, duck, quail and turkey hosts. Phylogeny-associated PB2 mutations acquired during the evolution of G1-A/B are shown beside each branch, with the mutations grouped in the four time periods during which they were identified (designated mutation categories a-d). The four mutations that were shown in this study to act cooperatively in expansion of the host range to humans are underlined. Virus particles are represented by ovals, with horizontal bars representing the eight gene segments (from top to bottom: PB2, PB1, PA, HA, NP, NA, M and NS). Segments in the descendent viruses are colored according to the corresponding source viruses to illustrate the gene ancestry through reassortment. Yellow in segment 1 (PB2) indicates the four phylogeny-associated mutations that contribute to the expanded viral host range to humans. (B and C) Polymerase activities of EG/2013-wt and the PB2 revertants carrying single mutations in human 293T cells at 33°C and in avian DF-1 cells at 37°C, without the PB2-V627E mutation (B) and with the PB2-V627E mutation (C). The data are expressed relative to the results for EG/2013-627V (wt) (B) and for EG/2013-V627E (C). Asterisks indicate a P value &lt; 0.01. NS indicates no statistically significant difference. Colors of the vertical bars indicate the four groups of strains based on when the mutations were identified during the evolution of G1-A/B, as shown in A.</p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1007919.g002" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
