<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0010">A life threatening infectious coronavirus [
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] started from Wuhan of China in December 2019. As of June 04, 2020, the disease has officially spread to 213 countries and territories infecting a total of 6,632,985 people causing a death of 391,136. The patients affected by this coronavirus show symptoms of pneumonia. The World Health Organization (WHO) has termed this particular virus as 
 <italic>severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2</italic> (SARS‐CoV‐2) and the associated disease as COVID‐19 [
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>]. Recently, the WHO has declared COVID-19 as a pandemic. One of the similar coronaviruses reported in the last two decades is the outbreak of Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS) in 2003 causing thousands of deaths. Another disease Middle East Respiratory Syndrome (MERS) emerged in 2012. A third virus known as Swine Acute Diarrhea Syndrome (SADS) was noted in the swine industry in 2017. These diseases originated from bats and they are pathogenic to humans or livestock [
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>]. Some of the main symptoms of this disease are the development of fever, cough, and respiratory problems including shortness of breath. According to WHO, the incubation period of this virus in most cases vary from 2 to 10 days. Unfortunately, there is no known cure for this disease, for example there is no vaccine for prevention of this disease. There is no specific antiviral treatment as well. The doctors help the patients to manage the symptoms. In many cases, the patients may develop pneumonia and experience failure of multiple organs leading to possible death. The COVID-19 is spread by respiratory droplets from the patients. In other words, the spread is severe when the infected patients cough or sneeze [
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. However, the spread can be minimized to some extent by taking hygiene measure including careful handwashing. Moreover, early detection of this disease can help in the containment of the virus. Because of the life threatening nature and no cure of COVID-19, significant research interest has been seen in this field since early January 2020. It is expected that data analytics can play an important role in investigating the salient features of COVID-19 and eventually find a vaccine for it. Therefore, this paper focuses on the application of data analytics on COVID-19. The contributions of this paper are summarized below:
 <list list-type="simple" id="olist0010">
  <list-item id="o0010">
   <label>1)</label>
   <p id="p0015">The literature has been reviewed to find the important aspects of COVID-19.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0015">
   <label>2)</label>
   <p id="p0020">Data analytics has been applied on a currently available dataset to visualize the spread of COVID-19 as of June 4, 2020.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0020">
   <label>3)</label>
   <p id="p0025">A description is provided on the feature selection, regression and classification algorithms suitable for this disease. A polynomial regression model has been used to model the number of confirmed cases in the world. Moreover, feature selection and classification algorithms are applied on a dataset for data-driven diagnosis of COVID-19.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0025">
   <label>4)</label>
   <p id="p0030">The possible applications of data analytics on the important aspects of the disease are presented.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
