<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>LAIV has been approved for clinical use in humans since 2003 and is proven effective in preventing influenza infections (Mohn et al., 
 <xref rid="B167" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). The protection of LAIV is superior to IIVs due to multifaceted immune arms including antibody responses and cell-mediated responses that operate systemically and locally (Jang and Seong, 
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">2013a</xref>,
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>; Sridhar et al., 
 <xref rid="B214" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Further, displaying a whole set of viral antigens in a native conformation into the host immune system presents a definite advantage of LAIV to generate better protective immunity than the other strategies relying on a limited set of antigens. As discussed above, T cell immunity directed to the conserved viral epitopes constitutes the cornerstone of cross-protection. A large number of researches have shown that T cell responses induced by LAIV are critical for broad protection against heterologous and heterosubtypic influenza infections in animal models (Cheng et al., 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Jang and Seong, 
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">2013a</xref>; Rekstin et al., 
 <xref rid="B202" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). In young children, only LAIVs were shown to induce durable and potent T cell responses, while developing similar levels of antibody response as compared to IIVs (Belshe et al., 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; Hoft et al., 
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Mohn et al., 
 <xref rid="B166" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B168" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Despite well-documented cross-protection, LAIV has received little attention to develop a UIV. This may be attributed to the general belief that LAIV is not effective at inducing broadly neutralizing antibodies against conserved domains in surface antigens (e.g., M2e or HA stalk). However, close attention is recently being given to LAIV as an alternative platform as a potent and cross-protective vehicle than previously thought, through inducing multifaceted immune correlates including T cell response and antibody-mediated effector functions (Jang and Seong, 
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">2013a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).
</p>
