<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float">
 <label>Table 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Core HIV and hepatitis C virus prevention and treatment interventions for people who inject drugs and indicator data collected to develop estimates of intervention coverage</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th/>
    <th align="left">
     <bold>Indicators</bold>
    </th>
    <th align="left">
     <bold>Definition used for coverage estimate</bold>
    </th>
    <th align="left">
     <bold>Coverage levels</bold>
     <xref rid="tbl1fn1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>
    </th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Needle and syringe programmes</td>
    <td align="left">Number of sites; number of clients or occasions of service in a given time period; percentage of PWID accessing NSP in a given time period; number of needle-syringes distributed in a given time period</td>
    <td align="left">Number of needle-syringes distributed per PWID per year</td>
    <td align="left">Low: &lt;100; moderate: 100 to &lt;199; high: ≥200</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Opioid substitution therapy</td>
    <td align="left">Number of sites and forms of OST provided (methadone, buprenorphine, heroin, or other); percentage of PWID accessing OST at a given point in time; number of OST clients at a given point in time</td>
    <td align="left">Number of OST clients per 100 PWID; number of OST clients per 100 primary opioid injectors
     <xref rid="tbl1fn2" ref-type="table-fn">†</xref>
    </td>
    <td align="left">Low: &lt;20; moderate: 20 to &lt;39; high: ≥40</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">HIV testing and counselling</td>
    <td align="left">Evidence of HIV testing programmes targeted to PWID; percentage of PWID receiving an HIV test in the previous 12 months (who know the result); number of PWID receiving an HIV test in the previous 12 months (who know the result)</td>
    <td align="left">Number of PWID receiving an HIV test in the past 12 months per 100 PWID</td>
    <td align="left">Low: &lt;40; moderate: 40 to &lt;74; high: ≥75</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">HIV ART</td>
    <td align="left">Presence of policy restrictions limiting access to ART on the basis of injecting drug use history or status; percentage of HIV-positive PWID receiving ART; number of HIV-positive PWID receiving ART at a given point in time</td>
    <td align="left">Number of PWID receiving ART per 100 HIV-positive PWID</td>
    <td align="left">Low: &lt;25; moderate: 25 to &lt;74; high: ≥75</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Condom programmes</td>
    <td align="left">Number of sites distributing condoms to PWID; number of PWID receiving condoms from targeted programmes; percentage of PWID receiving condoms from targeted programmes; number of condoms distributed by programmes targeting PWID</td>
    <td align="left">Number of condoms distributed by PWID-targeted services per PWID</td>
    <td align="left">Low: &lt;50; moderate: 50 to &lt;99; high: ≥100</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn>
   <p>PWID=people who inject drugs. OST=opioid substitution therapy. NSP=needle and syringe programmes. ART=HIV antiretroviral therapy.</p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn id="tbl1fn1">
   <label>*</label>
   <p id="cenpara10">Suggested targets developed by WHO, UNAIDS, and the UN Office on Drugs and Crime to assess intervention coverage.
    <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">
     <sup>5</sup>
    </xref>
   </p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn id="tbl1fn2">
   <label>†</label>
   <p id="cenpara20">Prevalence of primary opioid injecting estimated in Degenhardt and colleagues.
    <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">
     <sup>1</sup>
    </xref>
   </p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
