<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Given that TYLCV-resistant genotypes could also potentially serve as inoculum sources of the virus, their impact on viral epidemics would further depend on how they influence vector preference and performance. Results from the current study indicated that host susceptibility to the virus differentially affected vector preference, the effects varied temporally and with the infection status of whiteflies. With a TYLCV susceptible genotype, non-viruliferous whiteflies showed a significant preference for infected plants six weeks after inoculation. On the contrary, viruliferous whiteflies significantly preferred non-infected plants at three and six weeks after inoculation. Non-viruliferous vector preference towards virus-infected plants and viruliferous vector preference for non-infected hosts could, in general, favor viral epidemics [
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The cues that influence such interactions are not known in this system, but a combination of visual, volatile, and/or gustatory (nutrients) cues, as in other persistent virus pathosystems [
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], could be influencing whitefly preference as well. Availability of nutrients and defensive compounds are also altered by begomoviruses so that infected plants are more suitable for sustained whitefly feeding [
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Perhaps, such an alteration could have also influenced the increased settling of non-infected whiteflies on TYLCV-infected tomato plants in susceptible cultivars. In addition to TYLCV infection in plants, TYLCV infection in whiteflies also induced a behavioural change, as infected whiteflies preferentially settled on non-infected plants as early as 3 weeks post infection. Direct changes in behavior (i.e. feeding and locomotory activities) following begomovirus infection have already been described for the b and q biotypes of 
 <italic>B</italic>. 
 <italic>tabaci</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Another study demonstrated that viruliferous whiteflies were attracted towards green light [
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]; such an attraction could explain why viruliferous whiteflies preferentially settled on non-infected plants in this study. Such behavioural patterns modulated by the virus directly through whitefly infection or indirectly through the host plant, particularly in the early stages of the host, could have implications for viral epidemics.
</p>
