<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Following the detection of the first outbreak, a control programme, as stipulated by the European Union, was implemented. This programme consisted of stamping out of infected flocks, movement restrictions and establishment of protection and surveillance zones. Despite additional control measures such as pre-emptive culling of flocks within a radius of 1 km of an outbreak and establishment of buffer zones between defined areas by complete depopulation of poultry flocks in these zones, there was a continued spread of the virus by mechanisms which are not clearly understood 
 <xref rid="pone.0040929-Stegeman1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0040929-Boender1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0040929-Thomas1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. This spread only came to an end after the control measures had led to the culling of a large proportion of farms in the affected regions 
 <xref rid="pone.0040929-Stegeman1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. For the farmers, this meant incurring economic losses through and emotional burden of lost stock. Moreover, after a debate accruing from the 2001 Foot-and-Mouth Disease epidemic in the UK and the Netherlands, public opinion turned against the (large-scale) preventive killing of healthy animals; deeming it unethical 
 <xref rid="pone.0040929-Woods1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0040929-vanAsseldonk1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Hence the Dutch government is seeking alternative control measures to (large-scale) preventive culling, with emergency vaccination being the preferred strategy. However, in comparison with preventive culling, emergency vaccination would have the important disadvantage that its effect suffers from a 7 to 14 days protection delay 
 <xref rid="pone.0040929-vanderGoot1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. This delay would prolong the time until epidemic control is obtained especially in the high density poultry areas (de Jong and Hagenaars 
 <xref rid="pone.0040929-deJong1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref> and the references therein). Thus the identification, testing and implementation of supplementary control strategies such as improved biosecurity are required. Identification of such strategies requires us to better understand the neighbourhood transmission (i.e., the indirect spread of the virus to farms neighbouring an infectious farm) of the virus.
</p>
