<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Sensitivity to the induction of experimental models of autoimmune diseases is highly susceptible to the genetic background of the strain of animals used, often resulting in differing phenotypes which respond differently to drugs. For instance, a widely used experimental model of multiple sclerosis is experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis (EAE). This is commonly induced in C57BL/6 mice by immunological challenge with myelin oligodendrocyte glycoprotein, an important autoantigen in the CNS, administered in the immunological adjuvant, Freund's complete adjuvant (FCA, killed 
 <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> in paraffin oil), with or without pertussis toxin to make the blood‐brain barrier permeable. Animals develop a progressive form of paralysis which can be scored.
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">49</xref> A variety of active compounds and marketed drugs has been developed on the basis of their activity in this model. However, only a minority of multiple sclerosis patients exhibit a chronic progressive form of the disease. The more common relapsing‐remitting form, occurring in 85% of patients, can be better reproduced in SJL mice after challenge with myelin proteolipid protein in FCA with pertussis toxin or in Dark‐Agouti rats with rat spinal cord homogenate in FCA. We have recently shown that even when assessing established, marketed drugs, not all EAE models show similar responsiveness to already approved treatments.
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">50</xref> However, even in models which show little responsiveness in terms of clinical score assessment, the concurrent use of more clinically relevant variables, such as behavior or social interaction, uncovered unexpected efficacy. Other authors have reported that sensitivity to mechanical pain in EAE also varies between SJL and C57BL/6 mice.
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">51</xref> The lesson drawn is that the genetic and phenotypic variety in experimental models can be taken into account partially using a range of genetically sensitive strains and a selection of translationally relevant assessment methods to generate an efficacy profile that provides a more precise picture of drug efficacy.
</p>
