<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As with viral susceptibility to immune attack, epitope drift or genetic spreading also occurs during the development of autoimmunity and can complicate interpretation of drug effects. Consequently, the immune system begins to recognize antigenic molecules beyond those of the specific, external chemical determinants to which a specific immune response was initially induced.
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">52</xref> Not only does this lead to autoimmune tissue damage but also to the recruitment of a variety of different humoral, cytotoxic, and immunoregulatory mechanisms. At a later stage of many chronic autoimmune diseases it is, therefore, difficult to determine the basic underlying defect. Genetic and biomarker studies may highlight common factors in the disease, such as HLA‐DR4 variants or anti‐citrullinated protein antibodies in rheumatoid arthritis, which help to stratify patients for therapy,
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">53</xref> once again emphasizing the need for a range of disease assessments in evaluating effects of drug therapy. But epitope drift can also complicate the use of experimental models of autoimmunity. One of us (MJP) well remembers performing a series of studies years ago on the tissue injuring effects of lymph node lymphocytes from Lewis and Wistar rats with adjuvant‐induced arthritis,
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">54</xref>, 
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">55</xref> during which the reactivity of the lymphocytes was gradually lost with time, presumably due to epitope drift, and the project had to be stopped. These observations are supported by results of a study by other authors on adjuvant arthritis induced in Sprague Dawley rats from two different vendors.
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">56</xref> The rats from the two sources varied in their susceptibility to arthritis, as well as in immune (various proinflammatory cytokines) and endocrine (plasma ACTH and corticosterone) responses. The authors suggested that different types of genetic drift in the two colonies were probably responsible, a possibility raised in a previous publication.
 <xref rid="prp2532-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">57</xref> It would be well worthwhile to carry out a comparative study between different labs of the range of antigenic reactivity of lymphocytes from animals in which the same initial stimulus is used to induce the autoimmune response. One would guess that this reactivity would differ considerably, indicating that the researchers are not necessarily assessing the same response.
</p>
