<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Because zoonotic pathogens typically may cause variable clinical outcomes in human hosts that differ in age, nutritional status, genetic background, and immunological condition, deciphering the complex interactions between evolving pathogens and their hosts is a great challenge. The genome sequences of many host species have become available the last decade, and with them a range of novel tools are available to study virus–host interactions at the molecular level. This progress, together with advances in high-throughput sequencing technology and, not least, in (bio)informatics and statistics, allows us to analyze the “genome-wide” networks of gene interactions that control the host response to pathogens. By comparing and contrasting the outcomes of infection with closely related pathogens in different but related host species, we can further delineate the various host pathways involved in the different outcomes. The power of this approach was nicely demonstrated for SIV infection of various primate host species. Natural reservoir hosts of SIV do not develop AIDS upon infection, whereas non-natural hosts, such as rhesus macaques and pig-tailed macaques, when infected experimentally with SIV, develop AIDS in a similar manner to HIV-infected humans. Transcriptional profiling indicates that SIV infection of these species produces a distinctive host response 
 <xref rid="ppat.1000557-Lederer1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. SIV-infected primates with symptoms of AIDS have a high viral load, immune activation, and loss of certain types of T cells, whereas SIV-infected sooty mangabeys (the species from which HIV-2 is thought to have originated) have substantially lower levels of innate immune activation than the symptomatic primates, partly due to the production of less interferon-α by plasmacytoid dendritic cells in response to SIV and other Toll-like receptor ligands 
 <xref rid="ppat.1000557-Mandl1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Identification of host factors that restrict HIV infection may aid the development of effective intervention strategies. Below, we elaborate on two other examples of recent important zoonotic events that led to sustained virus transmission in the human host, and the role that genomics has played in the elucidation of their pathogenesis thus far.
</p>
