<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Morbillivirus antigen was detected in the mammary gland of 
 <italic>T. truncatus</italic> from the US Atlantic coast epidemic in 1987–1988 and of 
 <italic>S. coeuruleoalba</italic> from the Mediterranean Sea outbreak in 1990 [
 <xref rid="B59-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B87-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>] and in the penile and preputial epithelium of a 
 <italic>P. phocoena</italic> from the North Sea [
 <xref rid="B107-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. Furthermore, a testicular fibroma collected in a short-beaked common dolphin (
 <italic>Delphinus delphis</italic>
 <italic>ponticus</italic>) from the Black Sea was positive for morbillivirus RNA by RT-PCR [
 <xref rid="B117-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]. The first evidence that vertical transmission may occur was the detection of morbilliviral RNA in the brain, lung, spleen, lymph node, and liver from the seven-month fetus of a DMV-infected 
 <italic>G. melas</italic> stranded in the Balearic Islands in 2007 [
 <xref rid="B88-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. These data suggest that CeMV infected females may transmit the infection to their fetuses and neonates 
 <italic>in utero</italic> and during lactation, respectively. 
 <italic>In utero</italic> transmission has been reported for MV in humans. The effects on the fetus depend on the stage of pregnancy and include abortion, 
 <italic>in utero</italic> death or premature birth [
 <xref rid="B118-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. When MV infects pregnant women in the peri-natal period, neonates are at risk of congenital measles and have a higher risk of developing early and fulminant SSPE because of the incomplete transfer of protective antibodies [
 <xref rid="B96-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>,
 <xref rid="B119-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. A similar situation may have happened in a 
 <italic>S. coeruleoalba</italic> calf stranded in Italy in November 2009 with a CNS infection [
 <xref rid="B120-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>] and in a neonate sperm whale (
 <italic>Physeter macrocephalus</italic>) washed ashore in Oahu, Hawaii in May of 20l1 [
 <xref rid="B121-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>]. 
</p>
