<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since 1984, it has been known that verapamil, the blocker of VGCCs, inhibits influenza A virus (IAV) infection [
 <xref rid="B7-cells-09-00094" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Moreover, IAV infection induces Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> influx, and the elevated intracellular Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> promotes endocytic uptake of IAV [
 <xref rid="B8-cells-09-00094" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Until recently, the underlying mechanism was revealed by Fujioka et al. [
 <xref rid="B9-cells-09-00094" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. They reported that several VGCC blockers and siRNA against the Ca
 <sub>V</sub>1.2 channel (L-type channel) inhibited H1N1 and H3N2 IAV infection in multiple cell lines. IAV attaches to the target cells by the viral hemagglutinin protein (HA), which is a type I transmembrane protein embedded in the viral envelope, binding to sialic acids [
 <xref rid="B10-cells-09-00094" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Fujioka et al. showed that the virus HA binds to domain IV of Ca
 <sub>V</sub>1.2, which contains two potential sialylated asparagine residues (N1436 and N1487) [
 <xref rid="B9-cells-09-00094" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-cells-09-00094" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. When Ca
 <sub>V</sub>1.2 mutants in one or both these residues were replaced with glutamine (N1436Q, N1487Q, and N1436Q + N1487Q), the interaction between HA and the Cav1.2 was attenuated compared with the wild-type fragment. They demonstrated that a VGCC blocker, diltiazem, significantly prolonged the survival of IAV-infected mice and allowed the recovery of the survivors. Therefore, Ca
 <sub>V</sub>1.2 may serve as a host cell surface receptor that binds IAV and is critical for IAV entry (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="cells-09-00094-f002">Figure 2</xref>A). New world hemorrhagic fever arenaviruses (NWA) are another virus that is reportedly sensitive to the VGCC blocker club member [
 <xref rid="B12-cells-09-00094" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-cells-09-00094" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. An siRNA screen with Junín virus glycoprotein-pseudotyped viruses identified that VGCCs are involved in NWA entry. Treatment with the channel blocker gabapentin, an FDA (U.S. Food and Drug Administration)-approved analgesic that targets the channel α2δ2 subunit, protects against NWA infection [
 <xref rid="B13-cells-09-00094" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. This research work demonstrated that the interaction between a virus and VGCCs promotes virus entry at the virus-cell fusion step. 
</p>
