<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8">Although rotaviruses are not generally considered primary foodborne pathogens, because person-to-person transmission seems to be the main route of transmission in developed countries, contaminated water sources are considered to be an important source of rotavirus transmission in developing countries [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Rotaviruses are non-enveloped double-stranded segmented RNA viruses from the family 
 <italic>Reoviridae</italic>. The genus Rotavirus contains eight species numbered A–H of which A–C are encountered in humans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Rotavirus A infection is the most common cause of severe gastroenteritis in infants and young children worldwide. Rotavirus B has been found mainly in adults with diarrhoea in China, Bangladesh and India. The viral nucleocapsid outermost layer contains two structural proteins VP4 and VP7 that define the serotype of the virus and are considered critical in vaccine development; more than 40 serotypes have been identified [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. By the age of five nearly every child has been infected with rotavirus A at least once, the majority of which is anticipated to be symptomatic. The spectrum of rotavirus A disease ranges from mild watery diarrhoea to severe diarrhoea with vomiting and moderate fever. Infection can result in death due to dehydration and electrolyte imbalance that is profuse and life threatening amongst others due to the action of a unique virus encoded enterotoxin NSP4 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. The severe impact is primarily observed in young children &lt;2 years of age and can be treated by oral rehydration therapy. Symptoms generally resolve within 3–7 days. Subsequent infections occur from birth to old age but natural immunity renders most of these infections asymptomatic. Rotavirus A is shed in high concentrations in the stool of infected persons and is transmitted via the oral-faecal route with &lt;100 virus particles being sufficient for transmission [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Infections occur mainly in late winter or early spring in Europe and colder/drier times of the year in the tropics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Rotavirus A vaccines were introduced in 2006, but prior to vaccination policies, rotaviruses caused ~3 million disease episodes per annum in the USA, requiring 500,000 visits to physicians and 60,000 hospitalisations, leading to 20–40 deaths [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. Similar observations were done in Europe [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. In developing countries rotavirus A infections cause millions of diarrhoea cases, almost two million hospitalizations and an estimated 453,000 infections result in the death of a child younger than 5 years of age annually worldwide [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. The introduction of proper hygienic measures, clean drinking water, oral rehydration therapy and rotavirus A vaccines reduced disease burden in both developed and developing countries [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].
</p>
