<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par7">Here, using a disease system-dynamics framework (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), we develop a discrete-time, stochastic epidemiological compartmental model (Environmental-Mechanistic Model or EMM, Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) incorporating spatial environmental variability to simulate present-day spill-over and subsequent human-to-human transmission using the example of Zaire Ebola virus (EBOV) (the strain responsible for the 2013–2016 outbreak in West Africa). We run the model ~20,000 times with randomly-sampled starting conditions and critically examine the emergent patterns of infections to discover which areas of the world are most at risk, and explore currently unsampled effects of Ebola epidemiology in Africa, and potential spread of EBOV at global scale based on flight data. As our model is flexible in terms of inputs, we can then examine the possible trend of Ebola epidemiological patterns by projecting to a future time-point, 2070
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup> under a variety of integrated global change scenarios
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup>. We compare the model output from three Representative Concentration Pathways (RCP) scenarios of increasing greenhouse gas concentrations: GCAM-RCP4.5 (‘High Climate Mitigation’), AIM-RCP6.0 (‘Low Climate Mitigation’), and MESSAGE-RCP8.5 (‘Business as Usual Emissions’)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>, and three possible socio-economic development scenarios (Shared Socio-economic Pathways or SSP), ordered by increasing human population density and reduced regional socio-economic cooperation: SSP1, SSP2 and SSP3 (termed respectively ‘Sustainable’, ‘Middle of the Road’ and ‘Regional Rivalry’ Development). Using these scenarios as reasonable boundaries of possible future global change, we then identify the prevailing direction of changes to the spatial patterns of risk of EBOV outbreaks and epidemics across Africa, and subsequent importations of disease cases across the world via airlines.
</p>
