<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To our knowledge, this is the first study to investigate the spatiotemporal clusters of DF and assess the socio-environmental factors in Guangzhou city using the spatial techniques at street-level. The study provides readily accessible information on DF spread and GIS maps on high-risk areas which can be used by the local Department of Health towards prevention and control of DF in Guangzhou. There are two limitations in this study: 1) Model included few variables on socio-environmental factors, as it was difficult to obtain all other street-level data. 2) As this study is an ecological study, measurement and information biases are possible. For example, the data on the socio-demographic factors were only obtained from the 6th Nation Population Census (collected in 2010) as the national demographic census in China was only conducted once 10 years. The socio-demographic data varied by time in Guangzhou and may have little impact on our results. However, we believe that the relative changes by different street level is unlikely to change dramatically in Guangzhou. We obtained the floating population in Guangzhou between January 1st 2006 and December 31st 2014 by accessing the registers at the online Guangzhou Statistics Bureau website (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gzstats.gov.cn/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.gzstats.gov.cn/</ext-link>). In addition, under-reporting is most likely possible as people with sub-clinical symptoms usually do not seek medical attention. The biases and drawbacks of stepwise multiple regression are well established within the statistical literature, including bias in parameter estimation, inconsistencies among model selection algorithms, etc. Whittingham et, al. discussed these issue and showed that stepwise regression allows models containing significant predictors to be obtained from each year's data [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006318.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. In this study, we conducted stepwise logistic regression model as this technique was applied in the vector-borne diseases research, so as to select the main risk factors and develop predictive model. The spatial-temporal analysis presented in this paper differs from the one by explaining the observed distribution and perhaps ultimately permitting prediction.
</p>
