<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">At a within-host scale (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), models can be used to simulate cellular interactions, immunological responses and treatment pharmacokinetics
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup>. In such simulations, viral dynamics are often modelled using a compartmental structure, with the growth of one population, such as circulating virions, dependent on the size of another population, such as infected cells. For example, a seminal within-host model fit to viral load data by Perelson et al.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup> revealed high turnover rates of HIV-1, counter to what was then the prevailing assumption that HIV-1 remained dormant during the asymptomatic ‘latency’ phase. The corollary to these high rates of viral turnover was that drug resistance would likely evolve rapidly under monotherapy. Further analyses of this model indicated that a combination of at least three drugs was necessary to maintain drug sensitivity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>. Once combination therapy did become available, extension of the Perelson et al. model demonstrated that the two-phase decline in viral load observed following treatment initiation was attributable to a reservoir of long-lived infected cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup>. With this insight also came the realization that prolonged treatment would be necessary to suppress viral load. The incorporation of stochasticity into this within-host framework allowed model fitting to ‘viral blips’—transient peaks in viral load, even under antiretroviral treatment
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>
 </sup>. Analysis of this data-driven stochastic model demonstrated that homeostatic proliferation maintained the infected cell reservoir and produced these viral blips, a finding that was later confirmed experimentally
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>. The implication for clinical care was that intensified antiretroviral treatment would be unable to eliminate the latent reservoir of infected cells as had been hypothesized, sparing patients from potentially fruitless trials with such regimens.
</p>
