<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28">Among the various approaches developed to study non-stationary data, WA is one of the most efficient tools to detect periodicity in epidemiological time series
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup>. This technique is more powerful when applied to longer time-series than the one used in our study. Although our findings should be interpreted with some caution in the light of the previous statement, we are confident of the robustness of our overall results. As previously stated, other factors need to be taken into account when explaining inter-annual cycles of dengue, such as population immunity and the (re)introduction of new DENV serotypes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>. Epidemic outbreaks of dengue fever were first recorded in Venezuela in 1964 and were partly attributed to the (re-)introduction of previously non-circulating DENV serotypes/strains coinciding with increased spread and densities of 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>
 </sup>. However, from 2000 onwards, the 4 DENV serotypes co-circulate in Venezuela
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>
 </sup> and although the epidemic peak registered in 2001 can be related to the introduction of serotype 3
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>
 </sup>, this peak also coincided with La Niña event. Moreover, after 2000, at least 3 major epidemics occurred with the co-circulation of all DENV serotypes in the same period. Future research should aim to investigate how climate forcing interacts with the effects of cross-immunity and cross-enhancement between serotypes to determine the population dynamics of this arboviral disease in Venezuela. Finally, the epidemics of chikungunya (2014) and Zika (2015–2016) viruses were important epidemiological events that affected a large number of people in Venezuela. During 2014, concomitant chikungunya and dengue epidemics were recorded which may have resulted in a certain degree of misdiagnosis between the two diseases during the first two weeks of the chikungunya epidemic when health personnel were not yet acquainted with this new disease. However, the remarkable clinical picture of chikungunya was quickly recognized and properly diagnosed in the great majority of cases. Regarding the possible epidemic effect of the introduction of Zika virus in 2015, the data showed a steady increase of dengue cases since August 2015, while the first confirmed autochthonous case of Zika was reported by the end of November. Zika epidemic reached its peak in January-February 2016 lingering on during the rest of this year. Therefore, we discard any potential effect of Zika virus epidemic on the dengue time series analysed.
</p>
