<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">International societies like World Health Organization (WHO) and Centre for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) are always confirming the necessity to use Personal Protection Equipment (PPE) in addition to the restriction of outpatient and elective procedures as preventive measures against COVID-19 
 <xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. Limitations of aerosol-generating procedures like suction, endotracheal intubation, and advanced endoscopy are of major concern due to the fear of the possibility of disease transmission. Further restrictions to prevent other routes of infections like feco-oral transmission, included colorectal surgeries and colonoscopies. Currently, many interventional surgical societies, anesthesia, endoscopy, radiology, and intensive care have placed their statements, guidelines, and recommendations to adjust their practice to the current epidemic 
 <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Different reasons rationalized the delay or even cancellation of non-emergency procedures as they would consume PPE tools which are currently running short supply worldwide. The second reason that such elective procedures are postponed or canceled is to prevent unnecessary infections to medical staff and caregivers, which may be transmitted from asymptomatic COVID-19 patients or their companions. Also, they consider such procedures a further burden and workload on an already exhausted medical system. Finally, occupying the operative theatres with such cases would warranty the need for mechanical ventilators that might be more beneficial and valuable if they are directed to rescue a COVID-19 patient’s life 
 <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. Meticulous evaluation should be done before deciding for the priority of the procedure through detailed history taking, one by one consultation, temperature measurement, hand hygiene, and reporting of any suspected case of COVID-19 (even if afebrile), and finally cleaning and disinfection protocols of premises. Repeated physical examination and temperature measurement along with the revision of chest imaging like a computed tomography scan or a chest radiograph, and if COVID-19 is suspected or confirmed, all non-emergency procedures would be delayed or canceled 
 <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>.
</p>
