<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A method using a tandem SPE sample preparation clean-up combined with column-switch LC–MS/MS was developed for the analysis of seven antiviral drugs in poultry muscle, ranging from very polar to reasonably non-polar drugs, and including basic, amphoteric and neutral compounds. The removal of matrix interferences was critical for the detection and quantification of zanamivir and ribavirin in particular. Because neither compound was sufficiently retained by using reversed-phase chromatography, a column-switch LC system combining a reversed-phase and a Hypercarb column was developed. This system showed improved separation power and is relatively easy to set-up, which is of major importance in a routine situation. Furthermore, a tandem SPE procedure proved to be mandatory for additional removal of matrix constituents. The method was fully validated according to 2002/657/EC [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] at concentrations of 5, 10 and 15 μg kg
 <sup>−1</sup>. Good linearity, trueness, repeatability and within-lab reproducibility were obtained for zanamivir, ribavirin, oseltamivir, oseltamivir carboxylate, amantadine and rimantadine. For arbidol these paramaters did not comply with the established criteria because the method resulted in a severe overestimation of the concentration for 16% of the spiked samples. The selectivity and robustness proved to be sufficient to apply the presented method in a routine situation enabling parallel analysis of at least 48 samples within 1 day. It is concluded that the presented method is suitable for the quantitative confirmatory analysis of zanamivir and ribavirin at levels as low as 10 μg kg
 <sup>−1</sup> and for oseltamivir, oseltamivir carboxylate, amantadine and rimantadine at a concentration of 1 μg kg
 <sup>−1</sup>. Furthermore, the presented method is suitable for the qualitative confirmatory analysis of arbidol at a concentration of 1 μg kg
 <sup>−1</sup>.
</p>
