<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0030">If necessary, the first step of sample procession is homogenization (physical, e.g., homogenizer, mortar and pestle, freeze-thaw cycles; or enzymatic techniques, e.g., salt solution, detergents, alkaline lysis), centrifugation of the sample and filtration of the supernatant (through 0.22 and 0.45 µm pore membranes) to remove nonviral nucleic acids (i.e., host cellular debris and bacteria). The filtrates can be treated with a mixture of DNases and RNases to further reduce background nucleic acids originating from the host cells and bacteria. The method chosen in this step depends on the physical properties and other characteristics of the sample type (
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Datta et al., 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib161" ref-type="bibr">Mokili et al., 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib215" ref-type="bibr">Shah et al., 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib234" ref-type="bibr">Vo and Jedlicka, 2014</xref>). Following sample homogenization and reduction of the amount of debris and background nucleic acids, viral particles can be concentrated at various efficacies. Commonly used methods include tangential-flow filtration, polyethylene glycol precipitation, and ultracentrifugation. Density gradient ultracentrifugation using cesium chloride gradient provides highly purified virus particles. Concerning the step of viral nucleic acid extraction, the picture is more complex. Viral particles are disrupted by using “lysis buffer,” which may contain chaotropic acids (e.g., guanidine hydrochloride), detergents (sodium dodecyl sulfate, Triton X-100), and/or proteases (e.g., proteinase K). During the subsequent separation phase, the nucleic acids could be isolated from other components. This can be done by liquid–liquid extraction or liquid–solid extraction. During the liquid phase extraction different types of alcohol are used (e.g., phenol-chloroform-isoamyl alcohol, isopropanol, etc.). The solid phase extraction may include one of the following procedures: gel filtration, where nucleic acid is separated through gel matrix (e.g., Sephadex), ion exchange chromatography (e.g., anion exchange resin, DEAE-C), and affinity chromatography (silica surface, paramagnetic beads). In general, liquid–solid extraction methods use less hazardous chemicals and provide increased throughput. Various formats have been marketed providing flexible, fast, and scalable viral nucleic acid extraction (
 <xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Datta et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib225" ref-type="bibr">Thatcher, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib227" ref-type="bibr">Thurber et al., 2009</xref>).
</p>
