<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To generate a long-term dynamic process of infection, infection was initiated by randomly selected seed infections of each type and a burn-in period of 20000 years is allowed to let the system be fully developed. The time series of infection was monitored to detect the times at which the incidence rate rose above or fell below a threshold level of 42 cases per 100000 person-days (cf. [
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]) so to obtain the duration of epidemic (DE) and the inter-epidemic period (IEP). The attack rate (AR) is defined as the proportion of the population infected during the epidemic. These three characteristics were calculated only for the total number of all infections. Stochastic extinction occurs once the total number of infected people reduces to below one. Following Truscott et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], the Kullback-Leibler (KL) information distance over parameter space was calculated to measure the match between the model outputs and these three characteristic features, 
 <disp-formula id="pone.0142170.e010">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="pone.0142170.e010.jpg" id="pone.0142170.e010g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M10">
    <mrow>
     <mtext>KL</mtext>
     <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
     <mi>g</mi>
     <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
     <mi>π</mi>
     <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
     <mo>,</mo>
     <mi>f</mi>
     <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mstyle displaystyle="true">
      <mrow>
       <mi>∫</mi>
       <mrow>
        <mi>g</mi>
        <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
        <mi>π</mi>
        <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
        <mspace width="0.1em"/>
        <mtext>log</mtext>
        <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
        <mfrac>
         <mrow>
          <mi>g</mi>
          <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
          <mi>π</mi>
          <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
         </mrow>
         <mi>f</mi>
        </mfrac>
        <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
        <mi>d</mi>
        <mi>x</mi>
       </mrow>
      </mrow>
     </mstyle>
    </mrow>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
  <label>(5)</label>
 </disp-formula> where 
 <italic>f</italic> is the empirical distribution of a feature, and g(
 <italic>π</italic>) is the approximate distribution of the same feature from model simulations over 1000 consecutive epidemics under the values of a set of model parameters 
 <italic>π</italic>. As in Truscott et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], empirical patterns of seasonal influenza are assumed to be characterised by these three normally distributed features with mean (
 <italic>m</italic>) and standard deviation (SD): (
 <italic>m</italic>, SD) = (11,3) weeks for DE, (15%,5%) for AR, and (52,7) weeks for IEP. We approximate the continuous empirical distribution 
 <italic>f</italic> as 
 <italic>f</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub>, 
 <italic>i</italic> = 1,…,
 <italic>N</italic>
 <sub>bin</sub> where 
 <italic>N</italic>
 <sub>bin</sub> is the number of bins. Under the values of the model parameters 
 <italic>π</italic>, the predicted distribution is categorised as 
 <italic>g</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub> where 
 <italic>i</italic> = 1,…,
 <italic>N</italic>
 <sub>bin</sub>. The KL information distance is approximated as 
 <disp-formula id="pone.0142170.e011">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="pone.0142170.e011.jpg" id="pone.0142170.e011g" position="anchor" mimetype="image" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M11">
    <mrow>
     <mtext>KL</mtext>
     <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
     <mi>g</mi>
     <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
     <mi>π</mi>
     <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
     <mo>,</mo>
     <mi>f</mi>
     <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
     <mo>≈</mo>
     <mstyle displaystyle="true">
      <msubsup>
       <mo>∑</mo>
       <mrow>
        <mi>i</mi>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mn>1</mn>
       </mrow>
       <mrow>
        <msub>
         <mi>N</mi>
         <mrow>
          <mtext>bin</mtext>
         </mrow>
        </msub>
       </mrow>
      </msubsup>
      <mrow>
       <msub>
        <mi>g</mi>
        <mi>i</mi>
       </msub>
       <mspace width="0.15em"/>
       <mtext>log</mtext>
       <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
       <msub>
        <mi>g</mi>
        <mi>i</mi>
       </msub>
       <mo>/</mo>
       <msub>
        <mi>f</mi>
        <mi>i</mi>
       </msub>
       <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
      </mrow>
     </mstyle>
    </mrow>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
  <label>(6)</label>
 </disp-formula>
 <italic>N</italic>
 <sub>bin</sub> takes the following values: 52, 104 and 100 for DE, IEP and AR, respectively. The overall measure of goodness of fit is an unweighted sum of the information distance for DE, AR, and IEP, denoted in this paper as KL3. For convenience, acronyms that are used to describe the characteristic features of an infection time series (such as DE) are listed in 
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.
</p>
