<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0110">Virus persistence in the CNS is critical for the development of the subacute and chronic forms of MHV-, and possibly HCoV-OC43-induced demyelinating diseases. In these infections, histopathological damage appears to be mainly immune-mediated, with little or no direct cytopathic effects. In fact, while no demyelination occurs after JHMV infection in mice with defective B- and T-cell maturation, demyelinating lesions are instead observed when virus-infected splenocytes from normal mice are transferred (
 <xref rid="bb0850" ref-type="bibr">Wu and Perlman, 1999</xref>). Although JHMV viral infection may trigger the development of autoreactive T cell clones, this does not seem the major mechanism for demyelination (
 <xref rid="bb0665" ref-type="bibr">Savarin et al., 2015</xref>). Instead, persistent activation of inflammatory cells that may damage oligodendrocytes seems to play a major role. In fact, JHMV latent infection favors CNS maintenance of CD4
 <sup>+</sup> and CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T lymphocytes (
 <xref rid="bb0490" ref-type="bibr">Marten et al., 2000</xref>) which both attract macrophages through the release of the chemokine CCL5 and of IFN-
 <italic>γ,</italic> respectively (
 <xref rid="bb0400" ref-type="bibr">Lane et al., 2000</xref>). An important role in recruiting macrophages and lymphocytes in the lesions is also played by the release of CXCL10 by resident glial cells (
 <xref rid="bb0225" ref-type="bibr">Dufour et al., 2002</xref>). As a matter of fact, immunoneutralization of either CCL5 or CXCL10 significantly reduces the severity of demyelination in mice chronically infected with JHMV (
 <xref rid="bb0265" ref-type="bibr">Glass et al., 2004a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0465" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2001</xref>). Time course analysis of gene expression in different cell types infiltrating the demyelinating lesions showed that long-lasting damage is probably due to microglial cells, whereas macrophages are probably more important at earlier stages (
 <xref rid="bb0670" ref-type="bibr">Savarin et al., 2018</xref>). Glial cells may prompt tissue damage not only by releasing chemoattractant molecules, but also nitric oxide and cytokines such as TNF-α, IL-1β, IL-6 (
 <xref rid="bb0715" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 1995</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0230" ref-type="bibr">Edwards et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0285" ref-type="bibr">Grzybicki et al., 1997</xref>). An additional mechanism of damage during latent infection is the impairment of differentiation of oligodendrocyte precursors caused either directly by JHMV (
 <xref rid="bb0455" ref-type="bibr">Liu and Zhang, 2006</xref>) or indirectly through IFNγ release under CXCL10 stimulation (
 <xref rid="bb0815" ref-type="bibr">Weinger et al., 2013</xref>) (
 <xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">Chew et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0740" ref-type="bibr">Tirotta et al., 2011</xref>).
</p>
