<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Reporting variables were estimated with an experimental kernel-ABC method that combines a kernel method on tree shapes (
 <xref rid="msw217-B40" ref-type="bibr">Poon et al. 2013</xref>) with a framework for approximate Bayesian computation (ABC). The basic premise of ABC is that it is usually easier to simulate data from a model than to calculate its exact likelihood for the observed data. A model can then be fit to the observed data by adjusting its parameters until it yields simulations that resemble these data, bypassing the calculation of likelihoods altogether. We formulated a structured compartmental SI model (
 <xref rid="msw217-B32" ref-type="bibr">Jacquez et al. 1988</xref>) that was informed by the descriptions of the agent-based simulations that were distributed to all participants. Specifically, the model comprised three populations: a main local population, a second local high-risk minority population, and an external source population. Each population was further partitioned into susceptible and infected groups, where the latter was stratified into three stages of infection (acute, asymptomatic, and chronic). Mixing rates between the main and minority local populations were controlled by two parameters to allow for asymmetric mixing. Individuals with acute or asymptomatic infections migrated from the external region to the local region at a constant rate 
 <italic>m</italic>, and replaced with new susceptible individuals in the external region. One infected individual in the external source population started the simulation. Coalescent trees were then simulated based on population trajectories derived from the numerical solution of the ordinary differential equations that represent the model, using the R package 
 <italic>rcolgem.</italic> The subset tree kernel (
 <xref rid="msw217-B40" ref-type="bibr">Poon et al. 2013</xref>) was used as a distance measure between the simulated coalescent trees and the reconstructed viral phylogenies on available sequence data, or the provided phylogenies. A Markov chain Monte Carlo implementation of ABC was used to fit the model. This kernel-ABC approach was validated on simulated data from more conventional compartmental models (
 <xref rid="msw217-B39" ref-type="bibr">Poon 2015</xref>).
</p>
