<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The extraction was performed by adding 100 µL of lysis buffer, 20 µL of sera and 30 µL of magnetic beads to a 1.5 mL tube, followed by incubation at 95 °C for 10 min. After incubation, the tube was transferred to a magnetic stand for 2 min, and after sedimentation of the beads, a 150 µL volume of supernatant was collected in a new 1.5 mL tube. RNA amplification of all samples was carried out using the Tubescanner point of care device (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany), and the Twist exo RT kit (TwistDx, Cambridge, UK), using RPA amplicons designed for the detection of 5 arboviruses: dengue virus (DENV), with two sets of primers and probes (set 1 for DENV1-3 and set 2 for DENV- 4 [
 <xref rid="B10-diagnostics-10-00408" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]); yellow fever virus (YFV) [
 <xref rid="B12-diagnostics-10-00408" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]; chikungunya virus (CHIKV) [
 <xref rid="B13-diagnostics-10-00408" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]; rift valley fever virus (RVFV) [
 <xref rid="B14-diagnostics-10-00408" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]; and zika virus (ZIKV) [
 <xref rid="B15-diagnostics-10-00408" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], with analytical sensitivities of 241, 14, 10, 23, 10, 21; and RNA molecules were detected, respectively. RT-RPA reactions were performed in a volume of 50 µL. Briefly, a mix containing 29.5 μL of rehydration buffer, 7.2 μL of ddH
 <sub>2</sub>O, 420 nM of each primer, and 210 nM of a target specific RPA exo-probe, was dispensed into each of the eight 1.5 mL tubes, before adding 5 μL of RNA template. Finally, 46.5 μL of master mix/template solution was transferred to each lyophilized RPA pellet of the eight-tubes strip provided in the kit. An amount of 3.5 μL magnesium acetate (280 mM) was added into the lid of each tube, before closing it and spinning the drop into the reaction mix. For real-time fluorescence monitoring, the reaction tubes were placed in the ESE Quant Tubescanner (Qiagen Lake Con- stance GmbH, Stockach, Germany).
</p>
