<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par35">Genetic differences among HIV-1 variants have a significant impact on HIV transmission, disease progression, as well as the response to ARV therapy (see reviews, Geretti 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR177">2006</xref>; Taylor et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR502">2008</xref>; Tyor et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR516">2013</xref>; Tables 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Pre-cART studies provide substantial evidence that HIV clade differences can influence HAND (Gupta et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR194">2007</xref>; Sacktor et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR445">2009</xref>; Boivin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2010</xref>; McArthur et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR321">2010</xref>; Rao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR420">2013</xref>), with HAND severity being highest for clade D and B strains, followed by C and A clades (Tyor et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR516">2013</xref>). These findings are supported by preclinical studies in which clade B or clade C HIV-infected macrophages were intracranially injected into severe combined immunodeficient mice (SCID) mice. Exposure to clade B isolates induced more severe memory deficits, as well as greater astrogliosis and neuronal damage (Rao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR419">2008</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR420">2013</xref>). In another example, the Tat dicysteine motif (CC) at positions 30 and 31, which is commonly found in clade B isolates, appears to worsen HAND (Mishra et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR341">2008</xref>; Rao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR420">2013</xref>) and has been studied extensively in vitro (Ranga et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR418">2004</xref>; Rao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR419">2008</xref>; Zou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR560">2011</xref>; Krishnan and Chatterjee 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR262">2015</xref>). Clade B Tat is more intrinsically cytotoxic to primary neurons in vitro than clade C Tat (Li et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR282">2008</xref>; Campbell et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2011</xref>; Zou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR560">2011</xref>), resulting in increased proinflammatory cytokine production (e.g., IL-6 and TNF-α) (Gandhi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR170">2009</xref>) and monocyte recruitment/migration into the brain (Ranga et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR418">2004</xref>; Rao et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR419">2008</xref>), and increased disruption of the BBB (Gandhi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR172">2010</xref>). Similarly, the production of the inflammatory mediators prostaglandin E
 <sub>2</sub> and the thromboxane A
 <sub>2</sub> receptor by astrocytes is more significantly increased by clade B than clade C gp120 (Samikkannu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR448">2011</xref>). Sequence and structural alterations in gp120 have been demonstrated between clades B and C (Gnanakaran et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR181">2007</xref>) and potentially contribute to these observed differences.
</p>
