<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Novel SARS-CoV2 is a pathogenic strain of coronavirus that is raising major concerns over the public health around the world. Coronaviruses are spherical enveloped viruses with positive sense single stranded RNA genome having a place in the Coronaviridae family and they cause respiratory tract infections in humans, animals and birds. SARS-like CoVs isolated from bats have 95% genome sequence identity with human SARS-CoVs, allowing them to directly infect humans without any requirement for an intermediate host (Hu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). The genome of SARS coronaviruses comprise 5′ open reading frame ORF (1a and 1b coding region, S region encodes spike glycoprotein, E region encodes enveloped protein, M region encodes membrane protein, N region encodes nucleocapsid protein, six accessory proteins encoded by ORF 3a, ORF 6, ORF 7a, ORF 7b, ORF 8 and 3′ terminal non-coding region) (Rota et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). The trimeric S glycoprotein contains two S1 and S2 subunits for interaction with host cell receptor and for fusion with host cell, respectively (Wu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Fan Wu et al. revealed that the receptor-binding domain (RBD) of COVID-19 spike protein is fundamentally the same as that of SARS-CoVs (73.8–74.9% amino acid character) and SARS-like CoVs, including strains Rs4874, Rs7327 and Rs4231 (75.9–76.9% amino acid) (Wu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Yuan et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Peng Zhou et al. confirmed that SARS-CoV-2 uses human ACE2 receptor for cell entry (Q. Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; P. Zhou et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) and this receptor can turn out to be a potential target to block the attachment of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein (Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Among several viral proteins, the main protease of SARS-Cov2 (M
 <sup>pro</sup>) is more potent target due to its vital role in the virus replication and transcription inside the host cells (Jin et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). As the novel coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) have sequence homology with SARS and MERS thus the existing antiviral drugs seem effective against SARS-CoV-2. Remdesivir, a nucleotide analogue inhibitor of RdRp and antimalarial drug chloroquine effectively inhibited the SARS-CoV-2 infection 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> (M. Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Hydroxychloroquine, an analogue of chloroquine is also a drug candidate after 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> (Yao et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>) and clinical investigations (Gautret et al. 2020). Considering the increase in fatality, there is an urgent requirement to channeled approved drugs and natural active compounds towards fighting the pandemic (Y. Zhou et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). This has led to several computational studies that screened hundreds of small molecules for their binding to key proteins such as spike glycoprotein, envelop protein, membrane protein and nucleocapsid protein (Das et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Islam et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Farag et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Micael et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Pandit et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Ubani et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Tallei et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Romulo et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Liu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). As natural product repository has overwhelming number of leads that may act as both blocker of receptor mediated host cell uptake of the viral particles and inhibitor of the viral replication. In this direction, we have selected two target proteins (viral protein, M
 <sup>pro</sup> and host receptor protein, ACE2) and performed docking studies to screen potential natural products. Further, 
 <italic>in silico</italic> ADME (Absorption, Distribution, Metabolism, Excretion) analysis has been performed to understand their suitability as a drug candidate. While the top leads, Delphinidin 3,5-diglucoside, Scutellarein 7-glucoside, Avicularin and 3,5-Di-O-galloylshikimic acid show optimal binding at the active site of both SARS-CoV-2 M
 <sup>pro</sup> and ACE2, ADME calculations show that all these molecules have low bioavailability.
</p>
