<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several studies demonstrate that lytic replication contributes to viral oncogenesis through the inflammation caused by long-term persistent viral replication and cytokine production, providing a pro-tumor microenvironment for tumor initiation in a paracrine manner and the expression in cells of lytic viral gene products that manipulate cell cycle and directly regulate immune responses to avoid immunologic surveillance [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008156.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008156.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008156.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008156.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Meanwhile, case reports and retrospective studies have also pointed out the benefit of antiviral therapy, specifically targeting the KSHV lytic replication cycle in the treatment and prevention of KSHV-associated diseases [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008156.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. For example, treatment with Ganciclovir (GCV) and Foscarnet (PFA) to block the viral DNA polymerase during lytic replication were shown to prevent KS in KSHV-seropositive transplant recipients [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008156.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In addition, GCV has been reported to be effective in MCD patients with active KSHV replication [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008156.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Knowing that KSHV lytic replication is important in the development of virus-associated diseases, makes screening and identifying new antiviral agents targeting viral lytic replication critical for developing new effective therapies. Here, we sought to screen for novel anti-KSHV agents using a high-throughput screening strategy applied to a library consisting of 1280 Food and Drug Administration (FDA)-approved drugs. Our screening finally identified 15 hit compounds with significant anti-KSHV activity. Additional mechanistic studies demonstrated the involvement of histamine, histamine receptors and related signaling pathways in KSHV lytic replication and reactivation.
</p>
