<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par59">It is believed that previously healthy young adults usually have a sound immune system; thus, they can immediately and accurately respond to invading pathogens and viruses. However, the reasons they quickly develop respiratory failure or acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) after being infected with SARS-Co-2 are still unclear. We presume that the first reason is possibly attributed to the pathophysiology of the viral load. Tiny viral loads allow the immune system to produce antibodies whether any clinical symptoms are experienced by the body or not [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. However, when a significant number of viruses invade the body in a short time, the immune system will be overwhelmed, resulting in massive cytokine reaction that ultimately damages the lung’s tiny vessels. It will subsequently result in pulmonary edema, providing significant burden to the circulatory system, eventually crushing the heart and lungs as well as causing coagulation and massive tiny thromboses in the tiny vessels of the whole body. Recently, Zou et al. have proven the presence of viral load of the upper respiratory tract that was detected in the asymptomatic patient was similar to that in the symptomatic patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. According to another previous study, the lower respiratory tract specimens usually have significantly higher viral loads and genome fractions than the upper respiratory tract specimens [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. The second reason is possibly attributed to the different inflammatory responses of each individual, which also play a crucial role in coronavirus-induced lung injury and ARDS. CRP is a nonspecific marker of inflammation which was widely used as a biochemical indicator for reflecting the acute severe systemic inflammatory response caused by a viral infection, such that our research illustrated that the severe COVID-19 patients had a high value than mild ones. In 2003, corticosteroid was widely administered in the treatment of SARS to control pulmonary inflammatory edema by regulating the immunity responses toward SARS-CoV. Russell et al. announced that corticosteroids should be administered before an inflammatory storm occurs to prevent lung injury [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. However, recently, most studies have reported that corticosteroids could only delay viral clearance [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] and are insignificantly associated with the mortality rate in severe viral pneumonia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. According to Wang et al.’s study [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] in comprising 46 COVID-19 patients, low-dose and short-term administration of corticosteroids was associated with a faster improvement of clinical symptoms and absorption of lung focus. However, patients may significantly benefit when the medication is administered at the right time with a reasonable dose.
</p>
