<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The complement system consists of at least 30 serum and cell surface proteins that interact with each other through a cascade of enzymatic activation and inhibition, leading to the elimination of pathogens, while protecting the self from subsequent damage. While activation of the complement system can be initiated by three different pathways, i.e., the classical pathway, the lectin pathway, and the alternative pathway, all the three pathways share a common amplification cascade of enzymatic reaction, leading to the formation of C5b-9 membrane attack complex (MAC). The classical pathway is activated by C1q binding to antigen-antibody complexes on the surfaces of pathogens. The lectin pathway is initiated by binding of mannose-binding lectin (MBL) to microbial surface, resulting in activation MBL-associated serine proteases (MASPs). The alternative pathway is constitutively active at low levels through the spontaneous hydrolysis of C3. The complement system has a protective role in controlling WNV infection. WNV infection in mice deficient in complement receptor 1 (CR1) and CR2 developed increased CNS virus burdens, and were vulnerable to lethal infection at a low dose of WNV, and had significant deficits in IgM and IgG [
 <xref rid="B90-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. In addition, genetic deficiencies in C1q, C4, factor B, or factor D all resulted in increased mortality in mice following WNV infection. Furthermore, the lack of complement functions might also result in the deficiency of B and T cell responses to WNV [
 <xref rid="B91-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. MBL recognizes N-linked glycans on the structural proteins of WNV and DENV, resulting in neutralization through a C3- and C4-dependent mechanism that utilizes both the canonical and bypass lectin activation pathways [
 <xref rid="B92-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. Soluble and cell-surface-associated WNV NS1 has been shown to bind to and recruit factor H, resulting in decreased complement activation in solution and attenuated deposition of C3 fragments and MAC on the cell surface [
 <xref rid="B93-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. NS1 attenuates classical and lectin pathway activation by directly interacting with C4 [
 <xref rid="B94-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>,
 <xref rid="B95-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. The complement component C1q increases the potency of antibodies against WNV by modulating the stoichiometric requirements for neutralization [
 <xref rid="B96-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. However, another study reported that despite mice deficient in MBL-A and MBL-C or MASP-2 were more vulnerable to WNV infection than WT mice, they had comparable kinetics of viral burden in the CNS and B and T cell immune responses, suggesting that lectin pathway might have important yet subordinate functions in protecting against WNV infection [
 <xref rid="B97-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. In addition, using C5-depleted or -deficient human or mouse sera, one study suggested that C5 might not either contribute to protection against WNV pathogenesis or augment the neutralizing efficacy of complement-fixing anti-WNV neutralizing antibodies in mice [
 <xref rid="B98-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>].
</p>
