<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recently, Jang et al., using a previously developed ts and ca X-31 H3N2 IAV [
 <xref rid="B147-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>], analyzed the genetic signature of the virus and characterized the contribution of the identified amino acid changes in the ts, ca phenotype of the IAV X-31 [
 <xref rid="B148-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>]. This mutant virus was selected during multiple serial passages in embryonated eggs at progressively lower sub-optimal temperatures (30, 27, and 24 °C). The cold-passaged mutant exhibited both ts and ca phenotypes. Moreover, mice did not show clinical signs even at high titer infection with the generated ts and ca X-31 mutant virus [
 <xref rid="B147-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>]. X-31 is a reassortant virus carrying the HA and NA segments of A/Hong Kong/1/68 H3N2 in the genetic background of PR8 [
 <xref rid="B126-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>,
 <xref rid="B147-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>]. During the ca process, 32 nucleotide changes were introduced in all six inteRNAl viral genes. Among them, 17 nucleotide substitutions resulted in amino acid substitutions in seven viral proteins: four in PB2 (F34Y, M105I, H110Q, and I588S), three in PB1 (V91A, A240T, and G684E), two in PA (S69N and I668V), two in NP (E18G and T130M), three in M1 (F3L, A137T, and I217R), two in M2 (M42I and A86T), and one in non-structural protein 1 (NS1; M98L) (
 <xref rid="viruses-10-00560-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B147-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>,
 <xref rid="B148-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>]. Phenotypic analysis with single- and multiple-gene reassortant viruses suggests that the viral NP was the major contributor to the ts and ca phenotype of the ts and ca X-31 H3N2 IAV [
 <xref rid="B147-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>]. However, other viral genes also included mutations responsible for viral attenuation in mice [
 <xref rid="B147-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>]. The contribution of the six inteRNAl genes from most to least to the ca phenotype were NP &gt; PB1 = M &gt; PA &gt; PB2 = NS and that to the ts phenotype were NP &gt; PB2 = PA &gt; M &gt; NS &gt; PB1 [
 <xref rid="B147-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>]. In addition, multiple gene reassortant viruses containing combinations of the polymerase components (PB2, PB1, and PA) provided marginal effect to the ca or ts phenotype as compared to the ts and ca phenotype of the single NP gene [
 <xref rid="B147-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>]. Moreover, by combining the three polymerase subunits (PB2, PB1, and PA) with the NP gene, the authors observed an increase in both phenotypes (ca and ts) [
 <xref rid="B148-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>], suggesting an additive effect of several amino acid residues in the polymerase complex. However, in this study, authors did not identify the specific amino acid residues in each of the viral proteins involved in the ca, ts, and att phenotype.
</p>
