<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The Regional simulation model consists of a stochastic, individual-level epidemic transmission and intervention model, and an evolutionary model that generates viral phylogenies and sequence data to simulated transmission chains. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="msw217-F1">Figure 1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online, describe the overall simulation pipeline, model components, parameters, and parameter values. Notably, assumptions were made on: sexual risk behavior (proportion of individuals in risk groups, mixing between risk groups, partner change rates); HIV infection (relative transmission rates); interventions (population-level effectiveness of ART); within-host evolution (neutral coalescent model, no co-infection and no recombination); between-host evolution (transmission of one virion, no recombination); and sequence sampling (at time of diagnosis of randomly selected individuals). To obtain the six epidemic scenarios shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="msw217-F2">figure 2</xref>, we varied the relative transmission rate from early infections as well as parameters relating to uptake of the combination intervention respectively. The simulation algorithm is available from 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/olli0601/PANGEA.HIV.sim" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/olli0601/PANGEA.HIV.sim</ext-link> (last accessed October 14, 2016), and combines (with further code): the individual-based HPTN071 (PopART) model version 1.1 to generate transmission chains, the VirusTreeSimulator (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/PangeaHIV/VirusTreeSimulator" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/PangeaHIV/VirusTreeSimulator</ext-link>; last accessed October 14, 2016) to generate viral trees from transmission chains, and SeqGen version 1.3 (
 <xref rid="msw217-B43" ref-type="bibr">Rambaut and Grassly 1997</xref>) to simulate viral sequences along viral trees.
</p>
