<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24">Diarrhoea in neonatal piglets is a common problem in many pig herds. Usually, this condition is seen either in the offspring of gilts or as an epidemic problem affecting litters from sows of any parity. In the first case, the problem is usually attributed to an inadequate acclimation protocol for gilts while in the latter, the most often cause is the introduction of a new enteric pathogen. These patterns reflect the immune status of sows against the causing agents and the transfer of colostral and lactogenic immunity to piglets. The agents involved in neonatal diarrhoea of piglets are diverse and include bacterial (
 <italic>Escherichia coli, Clostridium perfringens</italic>, etc.) and viral pathogens (coronaviruses, rotaviruses, etc.). Less commonly neonates can suffer from diarrhoea caused by parasites [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Most of the viruses causing outbreaks of diarrhoea in neonate piglets are RNA viruses such as 
 <italic>Porcine epidemic diarrhoea virus</italic> (
 <italic>PEDV</italic>), 
 <italic>Transmissible gastroenteritis virus</italic> (
 <italic>TGEV</italic>), 
 <italic>Porcine deltacoronavirus</italic> (
 <italic>PDCoV</italic>) or 
 <italic>Rotavirus A, B, C</italic> or 
 <italic>H</italic> (
 <italic>RVA</italic>, 
 <italic>RVB</italic>, 
 <italic>RVC</italic>, 
 <italic>RVH</italic>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Among them, 
 <italic>Rotavirus A</italic>, 
 <italic>B</italic> and 
 <italic>C</italic> are a major cause of diarrhoea in pigs worldwide, having a significant impact in health and productivity, plus the potential of zoonotic transmission to humans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. The virus is transmitted by the faecal-oral route and large number of viral particles is excreted during 
 <italic>Rotavirus</italic> infection. In contrast, other RNA viruses including 
 <italic>Kobuvirus, Astrovirus, Sapovirus</italic>, 
 <italic>Sapelovirus</italic>, 
 <italic>Teschovirus,</italic> and 
 <italic>Torovirus,</italic> have been detected in pig faeces but its role as causative agents of neonatal diarrhoea has not so far been fully elucidated [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. For instance, porcine 
 <italic>Kobuvirus</italic> (
 <italic>KobuV</italic>) has been found frequently (16–99%) in faecal samples of pigs worldwide [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. In some cases, the presence of the virus was associated with diarrhoea, but in others no significant differences between infection rates in healthy or diarrhoeic animals was found. Frequently 
 <italic>KobuV</italic> were present concomitantly with other viruses making difficult a precise assessment of its role as agent of disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].
</p>
