<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">By integrating phylogenetic methods with traditional epidemiological methods, researchers are able to infer relationships between surveillance data and patterns in pathogen population dynamics, such as genetic diversity, selective pressure, and spatiotemporal distribution. Systematic investigation of these relationships, or phylodynamics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], offers a unique perspective on infectious disease epidemiology, enabling researchers to better understand the impact of evolution on, for example, spatiotemporal dispersion among host populations and transmission among network contacts, and vice versa [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The study of the interconnectedness of these pathogen characteristics was previously limited by the cost and timescale of the generation of molecular data. Recent decades have been characterized by technology with the ability to rapidly generate serial molecular data from identifiable sources for which we can obtain detailed relevant information through epidemiological surveillance, allowing for the merging of phylodynamics and epidemiology, or evolutionary epidemiology [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Hence, progress in the field of molecular evolution has provided the opportunity for real-time assessment of the patterns associated with local, national, and global outbreaks [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], cross-species transmission events and characteristics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], and the effectiveness of treatment strategies on current [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] and recurring epidemics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. These assessments are essential for monitoring outbreaks and predicting/preventing pandemic inception, a good example being the recent study of Middle East Respiratory Syndrome coronavirus global transmission [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] (Additional file 1 (Video S1)). But has the, field of evolutionary epidemiology quite reached its full potential? In this article, we systematically discuss how the application of phylodynamic methods has and will continue to impact epidemiological research and global public health to understand and control infectious diseases locally and across the globe.
</p>
