<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the Americas, CHIKV has been circulating since 2013 (Zeller 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="mve12338-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>) and ZIKV since 2013 (Ayllon 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="mve12338-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) or 2014 (Faria 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="mve12338-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Their rapid spread was possible because the region's population was immunologically naïve in urban areas with well‐established 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> populations, which previously were transmitting the DENVs. Fewer mosquitoes are needed to cause local transmission of DENV when herd immunity in the human population is low (Focks 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="mve12338-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>). In the current study, the presence of ZIKV in 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> during its emergence in Puerto Rico in 2016 was compared with the presence of CHIKV in 2014 (Barrera 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="mve12338-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) in females of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> in four communities with different mosquito densities and levels of vector control. For both CHIKV in 2014 and ZIKV in 2016, mosquito densities and rates of virus detection were significantly higher in the two communities without vector control than in the treated communities. Average mosquito densities in communities with AGO traps were lower than two females/trap/week and only a few positive pools and no virologic evidence in mosquitoes of ongoing local transmission (lack of detection in several consecutive weeks) were found. A serologic study of CHIKV antibodies in residents of the four communities showed that the prevalence of immunoglobulin G (IgG) antibodies was at least 50% lower in people with AGO traps than in those in communities without traps (Lorenzi 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="mve12338-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). A vector density threshold that seemed protective against CHIKV of less than three female 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>/SAGO trap/week was proposed (Barrera 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="mve12338-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>, 
 <xref rid="mve12338-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). Mosquito densities collected in the same treated areas in 2016 in the present study were also below that threshold and a similarly low ZIKV incidence in 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> was found. As DENVs have been circulating in Puerto Rico for decades and herd immunity is high (Arguello 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="mve12338-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>), the mosquito density threshold for local transmission may be higher than two or three females/SAGO trap/week. Thus, keeping 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> density below this threshold may also protect against dengue outbreaks.
</p>
