<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Though the role of cats as a reservoir for 
 <italic>B. henselae</italic> has long been established, the prevalence of infection or exposure of cats to other 
 <italic>Bartonella</italic> species or to other vector‐borne diseases remains unreported. Using serology and polymerase chain reaction (PCR), the prevalence of exposure and bacteremia of vector‐borne infections (
 <italic>Anaplasma</italic>spp, 
 <italic>Babesia</italic>spp, 
 <italic>Cytauxzoon</italic>spp, 
 <italic>Ehrlichia</italic>spp, 
 <italic>Rickettsia</italic>spp, 
 <italic>Piroplasma</italic>,
 <italic>Mycoplasma</italic>spp, and 
 <italic>Bartonella</italic>spp.) was assessed in a population of free‐roaming cats in a rural area of the Midwestern United States. Serum and EDTA blood samples were collected from 65 free‐roaming cats captured as part of a community spay and neuter program. Testing with PCR revealed that 9 cats (14%) were positive for 
 <italic>Bartonella</italic> species (6 for 
 <italic>B. henselae</italic>and 3 for 
 <italic>B. clarridgeiae</italic>) and 7 cats (11%) were positive for 
 <italic>Mycoplasma</italic> species (6 for 
 <italic>M. haemominutim</italic> and 1 for 
 <italic>M. haemofelis</italic>). Serological testing revealed that 50 cats (83%) were positive for antibodies against 
 <italic>Bartonella</italic> species. More specifically, 50 cats were positive for 
 <italic>B. koehlerae</italic>, 47 were positive for 
 <italic>B. henselae</italic> and 42 were positive for 
 <italic>B. vinsonii</italic> subspecies 
 <italic>berkhoffi</italic>. A significant positive correlation was identified between positive 
 <italic>Bartonella</italic> spp. PCR results and the presence of antibodies against 
 <italic>B. vinsonii berkhoffi</italic> and 
 <italic>B. henselae</italic>. All cats that were positive for 
 <italic>Bartonella</italic> by PCR had positive serologies for all three species of 
 <italic>Bartonella</italic> tested. Odds ratio analysis of age, sex and weight revealed that male cats were at increased risk for exposure to 
 <italic>B. vinsonii berkhoffi</italic>.
</p>
