<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">Viruses have high rates of mutation, possibly arising out of their complex interactions with hundreds of human host proteins
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup> during viral replication and pathogenesis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>. Viral proteins evolve either to reduce certain interactions or to maintain them as the host proteins themselves undergo mutations
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup>. There are an increasing number of studies that reveal these virus-host interactions. The focus of the present work is however, to statistically describe the viruses at the complete genome level, selecting a scale that is bigger than a single protein and smaller than the virus-host interactions. Since viruses have only around ten types of proteins, building interaction maps either at the protein level or at the domain level will have too little information to draw systems level inferences or to compare one virus with another. Since the uniqueness of viruses is their high mutation rates, fine-graining with a focus on amino acid interactions is statistically and biologically more meaningful
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>. Finer scale manifestations of protein-level interactomes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup> have been studied in the domain-level interactomes of 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>elegans</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup> as well as in the amino acid level interactions in viruses
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>. The consequences of such studies span from the potential that it may be possible to define a systems-level metric for the viral complexity to identifying suitable strategies for drug discovery by highlighting the amino acid level interactions. In this work, we explore the former aspect on how viral or viral genomic complexity may be defined, a question that has not been asked so far to the best of our knowledge.
</p>
