<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">Amino acid level covariance can arise either from structural constraints between proximal amino acids or because of functional constraints from amino acids at distal sites or other proteins or due to phylogeny
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. Several studies focused on building amino acid interaction networks, starting from the three dimensional structural data of proteins
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>. The utility of structure based methods is limited to availability of the structures, and to structurally proximal relations. Conversely, using amino acid co-evolutionary couplings from abundant homologous sequence data of multiple species
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>, bioinformatic approaches such as Statistical Coupling Analysis (SCA)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>, Direct Coupling Analysis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup> and GREMLIN
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup> could predict hotspots of proteins, active sites of enzymes, 
 <italic>de novo</italic> three dimensional structures
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>, protein-protein contacts
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup>, functionally related clusters of amino acids
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup> and the vulnerability of viruses
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>. In this study, we use amino acid covariance networks from whole genome data to study the systems level characteristics of viruses. Earlier studies had explored and identified the genome-wide amino-acid co-variational couplings in various viruses
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>. The analysis was based on the smaller data sets available then, and the mechanism underlying the observed power-law, which is different from the ones in commonly studied complex networks, was not explored. In this work, we use large-scale complete genome data obtained from thousands of sequences of each virus to build amino acid covariance networks. We further use these network characteristics to probe the systems level complexity of the interaction networks, with possible implications for defining the biological complexity of viruses.
</p>
