<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">ACE2 is found in many types of cells and tissues, including the lungs, blood vessels, heart, liver, kidneys, and gastrointestinal tract. It is also present in the epithelium lining the lung, the nose, and mouth [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. It is highly abundant in type 2 pneumocytes, the important cells located in alveoli, where oxygen exchanged with carbon dioxide [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Regulating blood pressure and inflammation are the main functions of local ACE2 via the conversion of angiotensin II (Ang II) to other molecules that neutralize the effects of Ang II. It competes with ACE (Angiotensin-converting enzyme) in hydrolyzing inactive decapeptide Ang I. ACE2 hydrolyzes Ang I into the nonapeptide Ang(1–9) and decreases the available Ang I to be converted to AngII by ACE. It also hydrolyzes Ang II and Ang(1–9) into Ang(1–7). Unlike Ang II, Ang(1–7) is a vasodilator with anti-inflammatory effects acting through Mas receptors [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Thus, ACE2 is a negative regulator of local RAS in lung and other tissues. Occupying the ACE2 receptor by SARS-CoV-2 prevents it from performing its normal function, and breaking the Ang I and Ang II peptides. Naturally, there is a high concentration of ACE in the lung tissue. Thus, in ACE2 deficiency, ACE will be more active due to more available Ang I which is changed into Ang II. Increased local Ang II levels damage blood vessel linings and cause inflammation and tissue injury. For this reason, it is claimed that the renin-angiotensin- system has a serious role in COVID-19 pathogenesis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. So it can be claimed that the main destructive factor in the patients with severe COVID-19 is abnormal and high activity of local Ang II. Drugs that inhibit ACE or ACE inhibitors (ACEI) such as ramipril, lisinopril, and enalapril may prevent the injuries caused by Ang II via inhibiting its production without blocking the actions of ACE2.
</p>
