<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the phylogenetic trees of the H5N1 virus (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029617.s003">Figures S3</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0029617.s004">S4</xref>), the process of viral evolution is composed of a set of branches, originating from a common ancestor at the root of the tree. The length of a branch describes an evolutionary stage which starts from a previous hypothesized ancestor (or a node). The taxa having a common node can be regarded as a subgroup (or a clade). By this means, a phylogenetic tree is usually divided and the taxa are grouped into different subgroups, with the members of each subgroup are phylogenetically close. In Virology, subgroups are usually determined by eye balling 
 <xref rid="pone.0029617-Li1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0029617-Smith1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. A subgroup is believed to have a strong capability of surviving if its members show a pattern of wide spatial dispersion and extensive persistence over time 
 <xref rid="pone.0029617-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. This also indicates the capability of a subgroup to spread the disease. However, for a virus, this capability can be measured by both the process of the viral evolution and the capability of the subgroups which the virus belongs to. The longer is the evolutionary process the greater is the ability of a virus to survive and the higher is the possibility of the spread of the virus. Also, a virus is believed to have a large capability if it is a member of a strong subgroup of the strains showing extensive persistence in space and time. For evaluation, it is necessary to sum up all evolutionary stages that a virus goes through. Each stage contains a branch and a node which is shared by a subgroup of the taxa. As a first approximation, 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0029617.e055.jpg" mimetype="image" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>, an estimate of the capability of a virus, can be measured by a linear sum,
 <disp-formula>
  <graphic xlink:href="pone.0029617.e056.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <label>(1)</label>
 </disp-formula>where 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0029617.e057.jpg" mimetype="image" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>, 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0029617.e058.jpg" mimetype="image" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>, and 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0029617.e059.jpg" mimetype="image" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula> are viral evolution, spatial dispersion, and time span at a stage 
 <italic>i</italic>. 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0029617.e060.jpg" mimetype="image" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>, 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0029617.e061.jpg" mimetype="image" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>, and 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0029617.e062.jpg" mimetype="image" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula> are weights for the three variables, assigned the values 0.4, 0.4, and 0.2, respectively. The lower weight for the time span is because a temporal scale of a year is coarse relative to the other two variables. The normalized values of 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0029617.e063.jpg" mimetype="image" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>, 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0029617.e064.jpg" mimetype="image" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>, and 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0029617.e065.jpg" mimetype="image" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula> can be estimated from the hierarchical structure of the tree. First, the length of the branch at a stage 
 <italic>i</italic> is used to measure viral evolution. Second, we measure how widely dispersed, geographically, members of the same subgroup are. Spatial dispersion is estimated by the total inertia (sum of the variances) of the 2
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0029617.e066.jpg" mimetype="image" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>2 covariance matrix calculated using the locations (latitude, longitude) of the members at the same stage. Third, the length of time for a subgroup is measured by the time span from early to late occurrences of virus members. The time span 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0029617.e067.jpg" mimetype="image" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula> is a ratio, including the persistence of a subgroup at stage 
 <italic>i</italic>. It is calculated as the time length 
 <italic>i</italic> divided by the time length of the whole tree. Estimates of 
 <italic>e</italic> and 
 <italic>s</italic> are normalized to avoid the effect of large values. Mathematically, the capability of a virus can be evaluated by
 <disp-formula>
  <graphic xlink:href="pone.0029617.e068.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  <label>(2)</label>
 </disp-formula>where 
 <italic>n</italic> is the number of evolutionary stages of the virus. Quantifying a phylogenetic tree enables us to estimate the capability of a virus.
</p>
