<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Human diseases are expressed by underlying complex mechanisms that can be developed or obtained from many sources such as aberrations in genetics, infectious diseases, degenerative disease and more. Diseases often involve many complex cellular pathway cascades, which can vary in certain individuals. In diverse human populations, each individual has a unique set of inherited or non-inherited genetic abnormalities that could result in certain individuals to respond less or not at all to general treatments or drugs. Approved drugs can be invalid for a specific individual if they are deficient in a particular drug target and may not respond to the common way to a particular drug. This situation entails the requirement of personalised medicine to tailor for each patient, as drug efficacy can defer substantially in different gene profiles due to heterogeneity in human disease [
 <xref rid="B109-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. To reduce the lack of drug efficacy, drug repositioning plays an important role. Together with the advancement of next-generation sequencing technologies, personalised genomic studies can be carried out with an affirmative approach. This can result in the best medicine accompanied by high efficacy at the lowest toxicity levels possible to the specific individual in contrast to conventional treatment that aims for maximum tolerated doses. For instance, non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) accounts for 85–90% of all lung cancers [
 <xref rid="B110-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]. In 2007, it was first reported that there is a fusion gene in NSCLC, which comprises portions of echinoderm microtubule-associated protein-like 4 genes (
 <italic>EML4</italic>) and anaplastic lymphoma kinase gene (
 <italic>ALK</italic>) in ∼7% of patients with NSCLC. This was different from the common NSCLC with epidermal growth factor receptor mutation. Crizotinib, a small-molecule kinase inhibitor, which was intended to treat ALK-positive anaplastic large-cell lymphoma, is now repositioned to treat this small subset of NSCLC [
 <xref rid="B81-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. Without the advance screening of biomarkers in each NSCLC individual, this small subset would not be successfully discovered, and the common EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitors would have been prescribed to all NSCLC patients albeit the limited efficacy in patients with 
 <italic>EML4-ALK</italic> alteration. Recently, the drug Crizotinib (Pfizer’s Xalkori) successfully obtained FDA approval as a treatment for patients with NSCLC with 
 <italic>MET</italic> exon 14 skipping which occurs in approximately 3% of NSCLC tumours and 
 <italic>ROS 1</italic>/anaplastic lymphoma kinase-positive resistant systemic anaplastic large cell lymphoma (
 <italic>ROS-1/ALK</italic>-ALCL) [
 <xref rid="B111-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. Hence, repositioning the drug based on stratification is important in accordance with the appropriate biomarkers for each individual.
</p>
