<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To calculate the vertebrate host competence index for RVFV, an equation describing vector competence was calculated utilizing available mosquito transmission experiments performed at 26°C as a linear function of log (host viremia). This viremia-vector competence equation (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0003163.s001">Figure S1</xref>, C) describes the fraction of mosquitoes that would become infected after feeding on a single viremic host indicating the infectiousness of a vertebrate 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003163-Kilpatrick2" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003163-Komar1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. Because of limited species-specific experimental transmission data, the viremia-vector competence equation is based on the combined experimental transmission data of 17 mosquito species (See 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0003163.s001">Figure S1</xref>). Mosquito species that demonstrated low overall vector competence in experimental transmission studies due to midgut escape barriers or salivary gland barriers or had a limited sample size as described above were not used to calculate the viremia-vector competence relationship 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003163-Turell2" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. The viremia-vector competence equation (vector competence = 0.062 (Log
 <sub>10</sub> viremia) −0.276; R
 <sup>2</sup> = 0.27; N = 27; P = &lt;0.001) was used to calculate the daily infectiousness of vertebrate hosts by inserting daily vertebrate host viremia titers into the equation. When the equation calculated a vertebrate host's infectiousness to be negative the vertebrate host's daily infectiousness was set to zero 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003163-Kilpatrick2" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. These daily values were summed over the host's viremic period and used as the vertebrate species' competence index (
 <italic>C</italic>
 <sub>i</sub>). When multiple experimental studies existed for a particular vertebrate species or taxonomic group a mean 
 <italic>C
  <sub>i</sub>
 </italic> was calculated 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003163-Kilpatrick2" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003163-Komar1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003163-PerezRamirez1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>.
</p>
