<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As mentioned earlier in this review biodiversity may influence host-pathogen interactions and thus the prevalence of infectious agents leading to the emergence/re-emergence of diseases. However, the role of biodiversity on pathogen pattern changes is actually controversially and extensively discussed (Maillard and Gonzalez, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B98">2006</xref>; Aguirre and Tabor, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">2008</xref>; Maillard and Sparagano, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B99">2008</xref>). While the hypothesis that high species diversity decreases pathogen prevalence through mechanisms such as decreased host density, reduced encounters between hosts, alterations in host behavior or reduced host survival (“Dilution Effect”) commonly exists another theory is postulated (“Amplification” or “Rescue Effect”) where increased pathogen prevalence is associated with greater species diversity through increased encounters between hosts, or through the presence of secondary hosts (Keesing et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">2006</xref>). The “Dilution Effect” has been demonstrated for pathogens other than hantaviruses, i.e., for Leptospirae it was shown that a reduced mammal species biodiversity increased its incidence (Derne et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">2011</xref>). Similar observations have been made for other rodent-borne viruses (Mills, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B113">2006</xref>) including also several New World hantaviruses. In example, for Sin Nombre, Choclo, and Laguna Negra virus a negative relationship between species diversity and hantavirus prevalence has been emphasized (Yahnke et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B170">2001</xref>; Ruedas et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B134">2004</xref>; Dizney and Ruedas, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">2009</xref>). In Belgium the PUUV prevalence in 
 <italic>M. glareolus</italic> was negatively affected by the relative proportion of the non-host 
 <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic> (Tersago et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B155">2008</xref>). Further, for Sin Nombre Virus there is also experimental evidence for the “Dilution Effect,” which has been demonstrated through manipulation of small mammal biodiversity in wild reservoir populations in Panama (Suzán et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B153">2009</xref>). In contrast to the above studies, for PUUV in Lower Bavaria, where 
 <italic>M. glareolus</italic>, 
 <italic>A. flavicollis</italic>, 
 <italic>A. sylvaticus</italic>, 
 <italic>M. agrestis</italic>, and 
 <italic>Sorex</italic> spp. are predominant, the association of reduced rodent diversity and higher prevalence of PUUV could not be confirmed (Thoma, personal communication). Here, increased species diversity was correlated with higher PUUV estimates in the host rodent, which is in line with the “Amplification Effect.” With regard to this phenomenon several hypotheses may be formulated: (i) species other than the primary host could have the ability of functioning as a further reservoir for PUUV and thus lead to an increased transmission of the virus and overall prevalence; (ii) the presence of a species with a low reservoir capability could lead to higher contact rates between the primary hosts and subsequent higher transmission of the virus (Clay et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">2009</xref>). Nevertheless, whereas biodiversity may play a key role in pathogen transmission further factors which drive regional differences must exist.
</p>
