<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our second contribution is an adaptively weighted ensemble approach to combining the output of different forecasting methods given their historical and/or cross-validation forecasts. We first implemented this method in preparation for the 2014/2015 FluSight comparison, mixing together our empirical Bayes forecasting method with two baselines (a uniform distribution and an empirical distribution for each target), and later applied it while participating in the Dengue Forecasting project [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006134.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] and following FluSight comparisons (adding up to 9 additional components including delta density based methods), and found it improved our forecasts in all cases. Other epidemic forecasting teams have also reported success with concurrently or subsequently developed stacking generalization [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006134.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006134.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] ensemble approaches to the FluSight forecasting tasks using Bayesian model averaging [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006134.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], the fixed weighting scheme that we examine below [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006134.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], and alternative adaptive weighting schemes based on gradient tree boosting [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006134.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], as well as with earlier ensemble approaches to short-term point predictions [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006134.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Methodologically, our adaptively weighted ensemble framework differs from these alternatives in that it selects a weighting over components for a particular forecast using “plug-in” statistical estimators for the optimal weights given the context of the forecast being prepared. Like the adaptive approaches presented in [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006134.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], component weights for each forecast are selected using regression, but the type of regression used and the manner of incorporating additional information, such as the forecast week, are distinct.
</p>
