<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Intercolonial relationships (e.g., colony interactions) generally play an important role in shaping the efficiency of disease transmissions in social insects [
 <xref rid="B20-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. For example, high aggression between individual workers from different colonies is believed to decrease pathogen transmissions due to the limited contact and/or high causality and mortality following hostile interactions [
 <xref rid="B22-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. We, therefore, aimed to test the pathogen infection patterns associated with intercolonial aggression by analyzing the correlation between infection status and aggressive level. Additional aggression assay was carried out on colony pairs involving colonies from different sites of the same island (hereafter referred to as between-site colony pair, n = 30; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="insects-10-00436-f002">Figure 2</xref>b; 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-insects-10-00436">Supplementary Table S1</xref>), and the data were combined with that of the within-site colony pairs to ensure the dataset is statistically robust. Not all between-site colony pairs were subjected to the aggression test, particularly those from Taiwan, due to different field collection schemes. We then categorized all the colony pairs into three groups, based on the infection status of the two colonies involved, those groups being uninfected vs. uninfected (−/−), infected vs. uninfected (−/+), and infected vs. infected (+/+). In addition, the Kruskal–Wallis rank-sum test, and the pairwise comparisons using the Wilcoxon rank-sum test with Bonferroni correction, were used to determine whether aggression levels are associated with the infection status. We conducted the non-parametric hypothesis tests and data visualization with the basic function, fitted the linear mixed model using the lme4 package, and selected the best fitted model by MuMIn package in 
 <italic>R</italic> software (version 3.5.2, 
 <italic>R</italic> Core Team, 2018) [
 <xref rid="B23-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].
</p>
