<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>CDV vaccine strains have recently been used as a vector to stably express the glycoprotein (G) of the rabies virus (RABV) within an additional transcription unit of a CDV cDNA clone. The RABV-G can be incorporated in the viral envelope of the chimeric virus to improve immunological recognition. The chimeric virus was shown to be safe for both mice and dogs and resulted in the production of long-lasting neutralizing antibodies against both CDV and rabies, and even protected mice from a lethal dose of rabies, demonstrating potential for the production of multivalent vaccines against both pathogens [
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. A recombinant avirulent CDV strain expressing 
 <italic>Leishmania</italic> antigens (leishmania homolog of receptors for activated C-kinase (LACK), thiol-specific antioxidant (TSA), or protein antigen LmSTI1 (LmSTI1), was also reported suitable for use as a polyvalent vaccine vector for 
 <italic>Leishmania</italic>, providing protection against both CDV and major infections of 
 <italic>Leishmania</italic> in dogs [
 <xref rid="B69-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. In addition, the generation of recombinant CDV expressing interleukin (IL)-18 or IL-7 also showed that they could be potentially used as molecular immunoadjuvants and agents for anticancer therapies in vivo [
 <xref rid="B70-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. These results also highlighted the requirement for evaluation of feasible intergenic regions for the insertion of a foreign gene because it was shown that the polar gradient transcription of the CDV genome could constitute a limiting factor for the expression of a foreign gene. The further upstream the additional transcription unit (ATU) cassette, the higher the amount of mRNA transcribed and higher the protein expression. However, if the encoded foreign gene product interferes with CDV replication, high levels of the encoded antigen may be detrimental [
 <xref rid="B71-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Another approach for generating a chimeric virus involves combining the replication complex of the MeV vaccine strain with the envelope glycoproteins (F and H) of wild-type CDV [
 <xref rid="B72-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. The resulting recombinant did not cause any clinical signs or immunosuppression in vaccinated ferrets and induced protective immunity from lethal challenge. In addition, several recent attempts employed CDV RGS for the study and the development of CDV vaccines based on wild-type strains (
 <xref rid="viruses-12-00339-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). One such example is the concept of rational attenuation of the CDV 5804P strain by modifying the L protein so that it expresses EGFP within its second hinge region, leading to viral attenuation in ferrets [
 <xref rid="B73-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Similarly, depleting the 
 <italic>N</italic>-linked glycosylation sites in the H protein of the virus produced a recombinant CDV with an attenuated phenotype, which was no longer able to cause disease in ferrets [
 <xref rid="B74-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. 
</p>
