<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10">Arildone is an antiviral drug of the 4-[6-(2-chloro-4-methoxy)phenoxyl]hexyl-3,5-heptanedione class, which is active against both DNA and RNA viruses (Kuhrt et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">1979</xref>). It is primarily suggested to be used as a broad-spectrum antiviral agent because it is relatively a less toxic drug and inhibits viral replication at lower concentration (Kim et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">1980</xref>). SAR studies demonstrated that omission of the lipophilic substituents of arildone diminished the antiviral activity (McSharry et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">1979</xref>). Arildone (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">22.3</xref>) inhibits replication of enterovirus, particularly poliovirus, via interaction with the viral capsid and hence blocking viral uncoating (Nikolaeva-Glomb and Galabov 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2004</xref>). Further in vitro studies provided evidence that a direct interaction of arildone with the poliovirus capsid stabilizes the virion against heat and alkaline treatment, resulting in loss of the VP4 capsid polypeptide and blocked release of viral RNA (Fox et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">1986</xref>). The uncoating inhibition action of arildone at lower dose can block replication of herpes virus at an earlier stage than the polymerase. Arildone is administered as a solution in dimethyl sulphoxide (DMSO) due to its poor solubility in water, and the solvent properties of DMSO may have augmented its antiviral action (Hutchinson 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">1985</xref>). In an animal model experiment, the ability of arildone to block the virion uncoating property to prevent paralysis and death was studied in mice intracerebrally infected with a higher dose of poliovirus type-2 (strain MEF). Moreover, IP administration of arildone suspended in gum tragacanth successfully protected the animals from paralysis and death in a dose-dependent fashion (minimal inhibitory dose = 32 mg/kg, 2X/day) (Mckinlay et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">1982</xref>). Arildone is the first of the capsid inhibitors that demonstrated in vitro inhibition of poliovirus replication and prevented paralysis and death in poliovirus-infected mice. Such compounds with better bioactivity showed potency orally in the mouse model, even when administered days after intracerebral infection (McKinlay et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2014</xref>).
</p>
