<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">The 2014 Ebola virus outbreak struck a populous region near the border of Guinea and Sierra Leone, sparking a crisis in a resource-constrained area that had no prior experience with the virus. As the caseload mounted and disseminated geographically, it became apparent that the West African outbreak would be unprecedented in its devastation. Models were developed to estimate the potential size of the epidemic in the absence of intervention, demonstrating the urgent need for expanded action by the international community
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>, and to calculate the scale of the required investment
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>. Initial control efforts included a militarily enforced quarantine of a Liberian neighbourhood in which Ebola was spreading. Modelling analysis in collaboration with the Liberian Ministry of Health demonstrated that the quarantine was ineffective and possibly even counterproductive
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup>. Connecting the microbiological and population scales, another modelling study integrated within-host viral load data over the course of Ebola infection and between-host transmission parameterized by contact-tracing data. The resulting dynamics highlighted the imperative to hospitalize most cases in isolation facilities within four days of symptom onset
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>. These modelling predictions were borne out of empirical observations. Early in the outbreak, when the incidence was precipitously growing, the average time to hospitalization in Liberia was above six days
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>. As contact tracing improved, the concomitant acceleration in hospitalization was found to be instrumental in turning the tide on the outbreak
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>. In another approach, phylogenetic analysis and transmission modelling were combined to estimate underreporting rates and social clustering of transmission
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. This study informed public health authorities regarding the optimal scope and targeting of their efforts, which were central to stemming the epidemic.
</p>
