<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig3">
 <label>Figure 3</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Identification of Most Influential Nodes in Calu-3-Specific Human-SARS-CoV-2 Interactome (CSI) Using Network Biology Framework</p>
  <p>(A) Weighted 
   <italic>k</italic>-shell decomposition identifies inner and peripheral layers of CSI. Thirty-three percent of all shells are considered as inner layers. Top 5% of the inner layer proteins are considered as significant (Red = inner layer, Blue = peripheral layer).
  </p>
  <p>(B) SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV interactome network similarity based on weighted 
   <italic>k</italic>-shell decomposition. Shells numbers were normalized to percentile and binned into 10 buckets represented as color blocks in the Sankey diagrams. The red block is for 100 to 90 percentile and percentile bucket in yellow represents 10 to zero percentile. The arrow represents the increase in the bucket shell percentile size from zero to 100 with bins of 10 percentile.
  </p>
  <p>(C and D) Correlation between information centrality and degree (C, 
   <italic>r</italic>
   <sup>2</sup> = 0.94) and PageRank and degree (D, 
   <italic>r</italic>
   <sup>2</sup> = 0.94).
  </p>
  <p>(E) Thirty-three CSI significant proteins (CSPs) that are inner layer SIPs and exhibit more than one high significant centrality measures (degree, information centrality (IC), betweenness centrality (BW), eigenvector centrality (EV), clustering coefficient (CC), load centrality (LC), harmonic centrality (HC), and PageRank). The size of the blue spot determines the significant central node in centrality indices.</p>
  <p>(F) Significantly enriched rare disease terms of 33 CSPs in SARS, Dengue fever, and Japanese encephalitis (p &lt; 0.0001) using Enrichr tool.</p>
  <p>(G) Network representation of significant SARS-CoV-2 viral protein interaction with 33 CSPs (Nodes: Red = viral proteins, Blue = CSPs significantly targeted by viral protein; edge width = MIST score, edge color = AvgSpec).</p>
  <p>“See also 
   <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S1</xref> and 
   <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S3</xref>.”
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="gr3" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
