<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract>
 <sec id="st1">
  <title>Background</title>
  <p>Universal testing and treatment (UTT) is a potential strategy to reduce HIV incidence, yet prior trial results are inconsistent. We report results from HPTN 071 (PopART), the largest HIV prevention trial to date.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st2">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>In this community-randomized trial (2013-18), 21 communities in Zambia and South Africa were randomized to Arm A (PopART intervention, universal antiretroviral therapy [ART]), Arm B (PopART intervention, ART per local guidelines), and Arm C (standard-of-care). The PopART intervention included home-based HIV-testing delivered by community workers who supported linkage-to-care, ART adherence, and other services. The primary outcome, HIV incidence between months 12-36, was measured in a Population Cohort (PC) of ~2,000 randomly-sampled adults/community aged 18-44y. Viral suppression (VS, &lt;400 copies HIV RNA/ml) was measured in all HIV-positive PC participants at 24m.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st3">
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>The PC included 48,301 participants. Baseline HIV prevalence was similar across study arms (21%-22%). Between months 12-36, 553 incident HIV infections were observed over 39,702 person-years (py; 1.4/100py; women: 1.7/100py; men: 0.8/100py). Adjusted rate-ratios were A vs. C: 0.93 (95%CI: 0.74-1.18, p=0.51); B vs. C: 0.70 (95%CI: 0.55-0.88, p=0.006). At 24m, VS was 71.9% in Arm A; 67.5% in Arm B; and 60.2% in Arm C. ART coverage after 36m was 81% in Arm A and 80% in Arm B.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st4">
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>The PopART intervention with ART per local guidelines reduced HIV incidence by 30%. The lack of effect with universal ART was surprising and inconsistent with VS data. This study provides evidence that UTT can reduce HIV incidence at population level.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="st5">
  <title>Trial registration</title>
  <p>ClinicalTrials.gov NCT01900977</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
