<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For PB1-F2 expression constructs, PB1-F2-coding sequences of A/PR/8/1934 (PR8), A/WSN/1933 TS61 (WSN), A/Vietnam/1203/2004 (H5N1) and A/Zhejiang/DTID-ZJU01/2013 (H7N9) were subcloned into pCAGEN vector to express PB1-F2 with three Flag tags at the C terminus (PB1-F2-Flag). pEF-Bos-Flag-MAVS was generated as previously described [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008611.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Aggregation-defective mutants of MAVS (E26A, W56R and R64, 65A) were generated on pEF-Bos-Flag-MAVS through site-directed mutagenesis using Q5
 <sup>®</sup> Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit (New England Biolabs). MAVS-coding sequence was subcloned into pCAGEN to generate pCAGEN-Myc-MAVS and pCAGEN-V5-MAVS. Expression constructs for RIG-IN, TRAF3, TRAF6, TBK1, IKKε, IRF3-5D and MyD88 as well as reporter constructs pIFNβ-Luc, pISRE-Luc, pIRF3-Luc, pκB-Luc and pRL-Tk were as described [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008611.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. TRIM31-coding sequence was subcloned from I.M.A.G.E. clone 3846513 into pCMV-Tag3B vector. Eight-plasmid system for recombinant influenza A virus based on pHW2000 vector have been described [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008611.ref087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. H7-2 WT and H7-2ΔF viruses were made with PB2, PB1, PA, NP, M and NS from H7N9 plus HA and NA from WSN (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat.1008611.g005">Fig 5A</xref>). H7N9 PB1-F2 knockout (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat.1008611.g005">Fig 5A</xref>) was achieved by using Q5
 <sup>®</sup> Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit. Mammalian expression constructs for ubiquitin and its mutants have been described [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008611.ref088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. The 12-plasmid reverse genetic system, including 8 pHH21 constructs for vRNA segments and 4 protein expression constructs driven by pCAGGS for PB2, PB1, PA, and NP, for production of WSN WT (A/WSN/1933 TS61) and WSN ΔF viruses, was a gift from Dr. Yoshihiro Kawaoka (University of Wisconsin, Madison, WI, USA) [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008611.ref089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. PB1-F2 knockout was achieved by using Q5
 <sup>®</sup> Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit.
</p>
