<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Life-long uninterrupted ART remains the cornerstone treatment for the HIV component. It contains at least three ART drugs from different classes.
 <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref> Various ART regimens are described in 
 <xref rid="T0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. The WHO has recommended first-line regimens comprising two nucleoside reverse-transcriptase inhibitors (NRTIs)/one NRTI and a nucleotide RTI (NtRTI), and a nonnucleoside RTI or integrase inhibitors. The currently approved regimen includes tenofovir (TDF), lamivudine (3TC), and efavirenz (Efv)/nevirapine (Nvp) or dolutegravir (Dtg), if available. Second-line regimens are indicated when there is resistance or intolerance to NRTIs. Failure of first-line ART followed by switching to second- or third-line ART is assessed by viral load testing, documentation of exposure history to drugs, enhanced adherence counseling, and also genotyping if available.
 <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref> Genotyping needs to be implemented at a programmatic level in view of early detection of probable resistance to ART drugs, including integrase inhibitors, even without previous exposure. Unnecessary switching to different regimens must be avoided. Currently recommended second-line regimens for adults include two NRTIs, such as zidovudine (Azt) with 3TC, and a boosted protease inhibitor (PI), with lopinavir/ritonavir (Lpv/r) or atazanavir/ritonavir (Atv/r) preferred. Boosted PI-based regimens are preferred in children. However, certain considerations should be kept in mind while managing these cases: ART plays a pivotal role, as mortality in M/XDR-TB in PLHIV without the use of ART is extremely high; ADRs are reported frequently in PLHIV, as multiple medications (nine or ten) are involved in M/XDR-TB with recognized high-toxicity risks and interactions, often combined with ART; some toxicities are common to both anti-TB treatment and ART, which may result in additive rates of ADRs; monitoring needs to be more intense for both response to therapy and ADRs; use of thiacetazone (T) is not routinely recommended for HIV-infected patients, as it has a propensity to cause skin rash and immunoreconstitution inflammatory syndrome (IRIS), which might complicate the therapy.
</p>
