<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Epidemiological details of dengue cases were acquired using the databases from the National Dengue Surveillance Program from 1999 to 2017. To account for comparability between previous (1993–2012, DF, DHF, DSS) and newer (2012–2017, dengue without and with warning signs, severe dengue) dengue case definitions, we used the criteria applied by MINSA to normalize the categories. Consequently, the outcome variables were reduced into two categories: (i) classic dengue, which covers dengue without warning signs; and (ii) hemorrhagic dengue, which encompasses dengue with warning signs, severe dengue, DHF, and DSS. Independent variables included were age group (0–10, 11–20, 21–30, 31–40, 41–50, 51–60, 61–70, 71–80, &gt;80), gender, and geographic regions (Panama provinces and indigenous regions). Due to the low number of dengue cases in indigenous regions, we arbitrarily included the indigenous regions within their closest provinces (Guna Yala indigenous region with Darien province, Ngöbe-Buglé indigenous region with Chiriqui province) (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-viruses-11-00764">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>). We compared those with classic dengue to those with hemorrhagic dengue using the following variables: gender, age group, and geographic region. Descriptive analysis was obtained for each variable. The association at the univariate and multivariate level between the outcome and independent variables was expressed as odds rations (ORs) using an unconditional logistic regression model. For statistical analysis, reference groups were selected using the categories with a higher number of observations, and 
 <italic>p</italic> values &lt; 0.05 were considered significant. ORs &gt; 1 indicated a higher risk compared to the reference group, ORs &lt; 1 indicated a protective factor (lower risk) compared to the reference group. All statistical analyses were conducted using STATA 14.1 (STATA Corporation, College Station, Texas, US).
</p>
