<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">Looking to understand the possible current direction of changes to Ebola burden over time, we project our models to 2070 and show that changes to SSP scenarios, which control levels of poverty and human population size in our models, will likely have a greater impact than climate and land-use change (here mediated via RCP scenarios). This is not surprising, as poverty reduction increases the presumed EVD-EBOV healthcare response in our simulations, and many of the countries in the endemic region are expected to have substantial reductions in poverty levels by 2070
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup>. Similarly, contact rates in our simulation (both between humans and between humans and wildlife) depend linearly on human population growth, whereas climate change increases EVD-EBOV cases through more complex interactions. Species distribution models indicate that the presumed wildlife hosts prefer warm and wet conditions (Supplementary Figs. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>), which are expected to increase in these regions according to the HADGem2-AO climate model
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup> (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>). This model, when compared to the predicted host change from 32 other models represents the ‘middle ground’ in terms of host spatial occurrence change (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7</xref>), but future work should further examine how climate model choice impacts future predictions. This expansion of the optimal conditions for presumed the wildlife host species effectively increases the at-risk human population by including more of the northern, eastern and southern areas of Africa (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>). Predicted future anthropogenic land-use changes, however, reduces the optimal wildlife host habitat, thereby reducing human-wildlife interactions. In terms of global socio-economic development, EVD cases numbers would appear to respond best to efforts in slowing the rate of population growth and increasing socio-economic development while mitigating climate change, such that global change most closely tracks the GCAM-RCP4.5 SSP1 scenario (High Climate Mitigation + Sustainable Development). Global binding commitments to reducing climate change may act to slow the effects, but evidence
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup> suggests a wholesale change is unlikely. Efforts to decreases poverty in Central and Western Africa with a concomitant increase in healthcare resources, therefore, would appear to be the most realistic approach to reducing future EVD disease risk globally.
</p>
