<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are several Chagas endemic areas in Mexico, including the States of Yucatán, Chiapas, Guerrero, Oaxaca, Jalisco, Veracruz, Puebla, Hidalgo, and Morelos where the disease occurs mainly in rural areas (
 <xref rid="B286" ref-type="bibr">286</xref>). The highest prevalence was observed in the Northeastern region of the country, which corresponds to the central area of a tropical region comprising the States of Hidalgo, San Luis Potosí, Veracruz, and the US neighbor State of Tamaulipas (
 <xref rid="B287" ref-type="bibr">287</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B288" ref-type="bibr">288</xref>). Recent cases of Chagas have been reported in Coahuila (
 <xref rid="B289" ref-type="bibr">289</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B290" ref-type="bibr">290</xref>) where 
 <italic>T. cruzi</italic> infection has been found also in blood donors (
 <xref rid="B290" ref-type="bibr">290</xref>). There have been new records of 
 <italic>T. gerstaeckeri</italic> and 
 <italic>T. rubida</italic> in Nuevo Leon and Coahuila (
 <xref rid="B291" ref-type="bibr">291</xref>). As in the US, 
 <italic>T. cruzi</italic> is increasingly transmitted through blood transfusions partly due to migration from rural areas toward Mexico City (
 <xref rid="B292" ref-type="bibr">292</xref>). More than 180 domestic, synanthropic, and wild species of mammals, especially rodents and marsupials, are likely to be infected with 
 <italic>T. cruzi</italic> and to be involved in the disease transmission cycle (
 <xref rid="B293" ref-type="bibr">293</xref>). In the Yucatan peninsula, the anti-
 <italic>T. cruzi</italic> antibody prevalence in dogs and cats were determined to be 14.76 and 4.21%, respectively (
 <xref rid="B258" ref-type="bibr">258</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B294" ref-type="bibr">294</xref>). In addition, an active canine 
 <italic>T. cruzi</italic> transmission cycle with severe symptoms affecting a broad range of dog breeds and age groups was observed in several counties in Texas (
 <xref rid="B295" ref-type="bibr">295</xref>). Further, in regions of Central Mexico, studies have demonstrated that canine sero-prevalence is directly correlated to human sero-prevalence, demonstrating the importance of this host as a sentinel species (
 <xref rid="B296" ref-type="bibr">296</xref>). Serosurveillance in shelter dogs was found useful as a public health tool to assess the risk for 
 <italic>T. cruzi</italic> infection (
 <xref rid="B297" ref-type="bibr">297</xref>).
</p>
