<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The isolation of DMV and PMV has been achieved using homogenates of lung tissue from 
 <italic>S. coeruleoalba</italic> and 
 <italic>P. phocoena</italic> inoculated onto monolayers of African green monkey kidney (Vero) cells following standard methodologies [
 <xref rid="B1-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Primary canine kidney epithelial cell cultures, bovine foetal lung cells and 
 <italic>T. truncatus</italic> peripheral blood mononuclear cells have also proved useful for isolation of CeMV directly or after co-cultivation with Vero cells [
 <xref rid="B1-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Primary culture of kidney cells derived from diseased 
 <italic>P. phocoena</italic> permitted direct virus isolation [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Repeated passages of the inoculated cell cultures and, consequently, several weeks are typically needed before virus growth can be detected [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Recently, Vero cells expressing the canine SLAM (Vero.DogSLAMtag cells) were shown to reduce the time necessary for PDV isolation from weeks to days [
 <xref rid="B72-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. These cells were also successfully used to grow stocks of PMV and DMV initially passaged on Vero cells and to isolate DMV from the brain of a 
 <italic>G. melas</italic> stranded in Valencia during the 2006–2008 epidemic [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. More recently, they proved useful to isolate CeMV from fresh tissues as part of the investigation into the 
 <italic>T. truncatus</italic> morbillivirus outbreak along the eastern Atlantic coast of USA in 2013 [
 <xref rid="B71-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Virus isolation has the added benefit of providing antigen necessary to carry out serological testing, as described in the serology section below. It may also provide genomic material for more complete phylogenetic analysis.
</p>
