<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0110">In Africa, where CMBs and whitefly species are found to be different from that in Asia, whiteflies of the 
 <italic>B. tabaci</italic> complex seem to play a rather important role in the CMD epidemics (
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Legg and Ogwal, 1998</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Legg et al., 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Legg et al., 2014</xref>). In a field survey conducted in Uganda in the 1990s, higher populations of whiteflies were reported in epidemic-affected than unaffected areas (
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Legg et al., 1998</xref>). Later, analysis of data from multiple regions in Africa revealed that the spread of severe CMD epidemic generally came after the appearance of ‘super-abundant’ whitefly populations (
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Legg et al., 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Also, it was established that a distinct whitefly genotype cluster is associated with the epidemic of severe cassava mosaic virus disease in Uganda (
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Legg et al., 2002</xref>). The strong association between the increase of whitefly abundance and presence of severe CMD epidemics suggested that CMD epidemics in Africa might be primarily driven by whiteflies (
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Legg and Ogwal, 1998</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Legg et al., 2002</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Legg et al., 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Legg et al., 2014</xref>). However, in Asia, whiteflies seem to play a more minor role in the epidemics of CMD. As whitefly-borne infection results in symptom appearance in young upper leaves only and cutting-borne infection results in both young and old leaves, field surveys established that whitefly-borne infection was found to account for only 9.0–37.5% and 20.6% of the total incidences observed in India and Vietnam, respectively (
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Jose et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Minato et al., 2019</xref>). The reason for the differential role of whitefly in CMD epidemics in Africa and Asia might be the differential transmission of African or Asian CMBs by local whiteflies and/or the abundance of efficient whitefly vectors in regions where CMD occurred. In this regard, a previous study using cassava mosaic geminiviruses and whitefly populations collected from India and Africa established that cassava mosaic geminiviruses from either location are transmitted efficiently only by whitefly populations from their geographical origin (
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Maruthi et al., 2002</xref>). Therefore, it is tempting to speculate that the lack of efficient CMB vector populations might account for the limited whitefly-borne infection in Asia.
</p>
