<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0120">Further, in order to explore the mechanisms underpinning the differential transmission of SLCMV by different whitefly species, we monitored virus acquisition by and virus transport inside whiteflies. Our findings revealed that the transmission efficiencies of SLCMV by different whitefly species correlated positively with quantity of virus in whitefly whole body, but negatively with that in honeydew. It was also noted that the variation of transmission efficiency was associated with the differing virus transport inside whitefly, particularly across the whitefly midgut. Interestingly, the pattern of differential transmission of SLCMV and underlying mechanisms are similar to that of CLCuMuV and tobacco curly shoot virus (TbCSV) when only Asia II 1 and MEAM1 are considered, suggesting something in common in those three viruses, probably in their coat proteins considering the function of coat proteins (
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Briddon et al., 1990</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">HöFer et al., 1997</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Czosnek et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Harrison et al., 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Pan et al., 2018</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Pan et al., 2018b</xref>). For begomoviruses, once they are acquired by insect vectors during feeding, they move long the food canal and then translocate from the gut lumen into the haemolymph and finally into the salivary glands, from where they are introduced back into the plant host during insect feeding (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Czosnek et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Hogenhout et al., 2008</xref>). Therefore, the information provided here, along with those in previous reports, offers a unique opportunity to further explore the nature of virus transport within whitefly and factors involved, e.g., the motifs of coat protein involved in whitefly-begomovirus interaction, thereby advancing our understanding of whitefly transmission of begomoviruses.
</p>
