<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0065">All samples were stored at 4 °C and shipped to the testing laboratory in ice packs within four hours of sampling to test for SARS-CoV-2. Test results were available on the same day. Quantitative analysis of the SARS-CoV-2 ribonucleic acid (RNA) genome was carried out by quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) according to the technical guidelines for laboratory detection of coronavirus infection (fifth edition) published by the National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China (
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">China, 2020a</xref>). Viral RNA was extracted using the LabServ® Prefilled Viral Total NA Kit-Flex and the Applied Biosystems 7500 System (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., Waltham, USA). qRT-PCR assays were performed on SARS-CoV-2 open reading frame 1ab (ORF1ab) and nucleocapsid protein (NP) gene fragments using China Food and Drug Administration (CFDA)-approved commercial Nucleic Acid Diagnostic Kits (PCR-Fluorescence Probing) (Daan Gene Inc., Guangzhou, China) and the Applied Biosystems 7500 System Real-Time PCR Detection System (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc., Waltham, USA). Every assay consisted of a positive control and a negative control. Data from the samples were further analysed only when both controls produced the expected results; otherwise, the data were considered invalid, and the test was repeated. A sample was considered to have tested positive if either of the two targets (ORF1ab, NP) had an apparent logarithmic phase in the amplification curve, and the cycle threshold (Ct) value was &lt; 40. Otherwise, the sample was considered to be negative if both targets had no apparent logarithmic phase or if the Ct value was ≥40 or indeterminate. In this study, an “intense positive” constituted a positive result from both the ORF1ab gene and the N gene of SARS-CoV-2. In addition, tests were repeated when a sample tested positive. The sample was confirmed to be positive when the second test was also positive.
</p>
