<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Compared to other regions in sSA, the rates of TDR in East Africa have been shown to be increasing, with a projected annual increase of 29% since ART rollout [
 <xref rid="pone.0171124.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Comparatively, the findings of this study showed a moderate level of TDR that was higher than that reported from most of the regions in East Africa [
 <xref rid="pone.0171124.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0171124.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0171124.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0171124.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0171124.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] especially in studies from rural settings [
 <xref rid="pone.0171124.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0171124.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0171124.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. This can partly be explained by the high prevalence and incidence in the study region as well as the more accurate means for assessing incidence [
 <xref rid="pone.0171124.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Among the studies compared, majority assessed TDR among persons initiating ART with unknown time of infection. Studies have shown possible archiving of TDR mutations due to comparatively higher viral fitness of the wild-type strains and it is likely that these studies may have underestimated the TDR levels as confounded by the choice of population studied [
 <xref rid="pone.0171124.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. The observed TDR in Ndhiwa was however lower than that observed in the urban settings of Mombasa (13.2%) and Entebbe (19.2%). The difference in this may be explained by the difference in the epidemic in the two regions. For example, in Mombasa HIV transmission occurs substantially through injection drug use (IDU) [
 <xref rid="pone.0171124.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] while that in Ndhiwa it is mainly heterosexual. IDU has been associated with a higher risk of primary HIV transmission in many parts of the world [
 <xref rid="pone.0171124.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. On the other hand, ART rollout in Uganda and Kenya started in 2000 and 2003, respectively [
 <xref rid="pone.0171124.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Thus, the length of ART use in Uganda is higher than that of Ndhiwa, which may partly explain the nearly 2 times TDR difference observed in the two regions, i.e., 19.2% in Entebbe (Uganda) against 9.2% in Ndhiwa [
 <xref rid="pone.0171124.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].
</p>
