<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the past century, several arthropod-borne viruses have emerged and/or re-emerged and have been associated with significant morbidity and mortality [
 <xref rid="B34-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B138-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>,
 <xref rid="B333-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">333</xref>] (Summarized in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="microorganisms-08-01167-f001">Figure 1</xref>). Among these agents, viruses within the genus 
 <italic>Alphavirus</italic> represent a significant risk to both human and animal health. In particular, CHIKV has demonstrated the substantial risk posed by Alphaviruses in the contemporary age. The single mutation, E1-A226V significantly increased the fitness of IOL strains of CHIKV in the peri-urban vector 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>, a vector known for its ability to survive in colder environments than 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>, allowing for the geographic expansion of CHIKV, and displacement of Asian lineage strains in some areas [
 <xref rid="B214-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">214</xref>,
 <xref rid="B334-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">334</xref>,
 <xref rid="B335-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">335</xref>,
 <xref rid="B336-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">336</xref>]. The Asian lineage itself expanded the geographic range of CHIKV via a series of outbreaks in the Americas beginning in 2013, which are estimated to have infected over 2.9 million individuals [
 <xref rid="B337-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">337</xref>,
 <xref rid="B338-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">338</xref>]. Given the backdrop of climate change, and human activities including global travel and commerce, destruction and encroachment of local ecologies, the emergence/reemergence of Alphaviruses and other arboviruses is not only possible but likely in coming years [
 <xref rid="B136-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>,
 <xref rid="B138-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>,
 <xref rid="B339-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">339</xref>]. With the exception of WEEV [
 <xref rid="B188-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">188</xref>], the alphaviruses highlighted here continue to have significant potential to emerge/reemerge and cause significant human and veterinary disease. Moreover, the lack of critical health care infrastructure and antiviral measures such as vaccines and antivirals remains a significant hindrance for treating future outbreaks. Therefore, enhanced virus surveillance and mosquito abatement will be critical tools to stemming potential epizootics.
</p>
