<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>SARS-CoV-2 causes various complications ranging from fever, dry cough, and pneumonia to decreased organ perfusion leading to MSOF. Early symptoms are similar to those of influenza, and the first step to differentiate COVID-19 from flu and pneumonia is a nasopharyngeal swab test (viral testing for influenza A/B).
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr77-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>
 </sup> Quantitative polymerase chain reaction-based (qPCR) methods are the major diagnostic tests for SARS-CoV-2 using nasal swab, aspirate, sputum, or blood as samples. These method have some limitations as they are time consuming and have variable sensitivity (30%–80%).
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr78-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr79-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr80-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>
 </sup> Another diagnostic method is the newly approved nucleic acid test, which is carried out based on the principle of fluorescence PCR.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr81-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>
 </sup> The main goal of SARS-CoV-2 diagnosis is to accurately detect the virus and to minimize further transmissions by timely isolation and treatment of infected patients. Other tests (not specific for SARS-CoV-2) used in conjunction with the methods above are based on clinical manifestations. These include blood tests such as complete blood count, comprehensive metabolic panels, basic metabolic panels, and assessment of liver/kidney markers and procalcitonin levels (for bacterial infections). Inflammatory markers may also be assessed including CRP, erythrocyte sedimentation rate, IL-6, lactate dehydrogenase, D-dimer, ferritin, troponin and creatine kinase-MB. Imaging investigations are typically computed tomography scans: in COVID-19 patients these often show glass opacities, areas of consolidation, and paving patterns in cases of severe and progressive disease. Ground glass opacities can also be observed on chest X-ray. Finally, ultrasound can show B-lines, pleural line thickening, and lung consolidation. Air bronchograms can also be used for assessment. These tests are non-specific but helpful to determine patients’ health status.
</p>
