<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="bullet">
 <list-item>
  <p>Equal Weight (
   <monospace>FSNetwork-EW</monospace>): This model consisted of assigning all components the same weight regardless of performance and is equivalent to an equally weighted probability density mixture of the components: 
   <italic>π</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>c</italic>,
    <italic>t</italic>,
    <italic>r</italic>
   </sub> = 1/
   <italic>C</italic>.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Constant Weight model (
   <monospace>FSNetwork-CW</monospace>): The weights vary across components but have the same value for all targets and regions, for a total of 21 weights: 
   <italic>π</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>c</italic>,
    <italic>t</italic>,
    <italic>r</italic>
   </sub> = 
   <italic>π</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>c</italic>
   </sub>. For purposes of statistical estimation, we say that the degrees of freedom (df) is (21 − 1) = 20. For each set of weights, once 20 weights are estimated the 21st is determined since they must add up to 1.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Target Type Weight model (
   <monospace>FSNetwork-TTW</monospace>): Weights are estimated separately for our two target-types (
   <italic>tt</italic>), short-term and seasonal targets, with no variation across regions. This results in a total of 42 weights (df = 40): 
   <italic>π</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>c</italic>,
    <italic>t</italic>,
    <italic>r</italic>
   </sub> = 
   <italic>π</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>c</italic>,
    <italic>tt</italic>
   </sub>.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Target Weight model (
   <monospace>FSNetwork-TW</monospace>): The weights are estimated separately for each of the seven targets for each component with no variation across regions, resulting in 147 weights (df = 140): 
   <italic>π</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>c</italic>,
    <italic>t</italic>,
    <italic>r</italic>
   </sub> = 
   <italic>π</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>c</italic>,
    <italic>t</italic>
   </sub>.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Target-Region Weight model (
   <monospace>FSNetwork-TRW</monospace>): The most complex model considered, this model estiamted weights separately for each component-target-region combination, resulting in 1617 unique weights (df = 1540): 
   <italic>π</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>c</italic>,
    <italic>t</italic>,
    <italic>r</italic>
   </sub> = 
   <italic>π</italic>
   <sub>
    <italic>c</italic>,
    <italic>t</italic>,
    <italic>r</italic>
   </sub>.
  </p>
 </list-item>
</list>
