<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pone-0087194-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087194.g005</object-id>
 <label>Figure 5</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Phylogenetic analysis of the bat gammaretrovirus-related sequence.</title>
  <p>(A) Schematic representation of the partial genome structure encompassing the pol (almost 3,580 nt encoding, the polymerase of almost 1,190 aa) gene of the porcine endogenous retrovirus (GenBank number Y17013), with black bars corresponding to the longest contig sequences (&gt;900 nt) of bat gammaretrovirus (named Sers gammaretrovirus) identified in samples from b7 (
   <italic>Eptesicus serotinus)</italic>. The genomic region amplified by PCR is represented by a dashed bar, and the sequence used for phylogenetic analysis is indicated with an asterisk. (B) Phylogenetic tree produced from the amino-acid alignment based on a selected region (155 aa) of the translated sequence obtained from the PCR product (almost 288 aa, approximate positions 173 to 423 of the pol protein of the porcine endogenous retrovirus). The bat gammaretrovirus-related sequence is indicated in bold, with circles in black indicating bat gammaretroviruses. The scale bar indicates branch length, and bootstrap values ≥70% are shown next to the relevant nodes. The tree is midpoint-rooted for purposes of clarity only. REV, reticuloendotheliosis virus; FeLV, feline leukemia virus; GALV, gibbon ape leukemia virus; F-MuLV, Friend MuLV; R-MuLV, Rauscher murine leukemia virus; M-MuLV, Moloney MuLV; M-CRV, murine type C retrovirus; PreXMRV-1/2, pre-xenotropic MuLV-related virus 1 and 2; PERV-A, porcine endogenous type C retrovirus class A; PERV-B, porcine endogenous retrovirus B; PERV-C, porcine endogenous retrovirus C; RD114, feline RD114 retrovirus; MDEV, 
   <italic>Mus dunni</italic> endogenous virus; KoRV, koala retrovirus; OOEV, 
   <italic>Orcinus orca</italic> endogenous retrovirus; BaEV, baboon endogenous virus; RpuRV, 
   <italic>Rhinolophus pusillus</italic>; RmRV, 
   <italic>Rhinolophus megaphyllus</italic>; RaRV, 
   <italic>Rhinolophus affinis</italic> retrovirus; MrRV, 
   <italic>Myotis ricketti</italic> retrovirus; PaRV, 
   <italic>Pteropus alecto</italic> retrovirus and MlRV, 
   <italic>Megaderma lyra</italic> retrovirus.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pone.0087194.g005" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
