<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract abstract-type="summary">
 <title>Author summary</title>
 <p>Dengue is one of the most important mosquito-borne diseases affecting humans, resulting in an estimated hundreds of millions of infections annually throughout the tropics. To control dengue, most public health programs use a variety of methods to kill the primary mosquito vector, 
  <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>. Water holding containers that harbor larvae (and other immature stages) are treated or eliminated. During emergencies, large insecticide spray campaigns are deployed to kill infected adult mosquitoes. Innovative interventions that are effective at targeting adult mosquitoes in sustainable ways are needed to increase the options for control of dengue and other 
  <italic>Aedes</italic> borne virus diseases. The use of insecticide-treated curtains (ITCs) has previously been shown to significantly reduce 
  <italic>Ae</italic>. 
  <italic>aegypti</italic> numbers in and around homes, but the impact of ITCs on dengue virus (DENV) transmission has not previously been quantified. Using a rigorous study design in which 10 clusters (~90 houses per cluster) were provided multiple ITCs to place in their homes was compared to 10 clusters of homes without ITCs. Assignment of which clusters received ITCs was randomized. Blood samples were obtained at 9-month intervals from residents living in all the clusters, so that people with serological evidence of a DENV infection could be identified by comparing paired samples. Seroconversion data showed that individuals living in the clusters that received ITCs were at greater risk to DENV seroconverting, with an average seroconversion rate of 50.6 per 100 person-years (PY) (CI: 29.9–71.9). Conversely, those in the control arm had an average seroconversion rate of 37.4 per 100 PY (CI: 15.2–51.7). ITCs lost their insecticidal efficacy within 6 months of deployment, necessitating re-treatment with insecticide. 
  <italic>Ae</italic>. 
  <italic>aegypti</italic> populations did not show statistically significant differences between ITC and non-ITC clusters. The reason for higher transmission in the ITC treated clusters could be attributable to failure of the curtains (loss of efficacy) and/or that the curtains were not sufficiently effective at protecting against mosquito bites. The higher risk of DENV seroconversion in ITC clusters may be due to a false sense of security that inadvertently led to less routine protective behaviors on the part of households that received the ITC.
 </p>
</abstract>
