<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p2935">Information about the pathology of HEV infection in humans is emerging,
 <xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr">58a.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib106" ref-type="bibr">61a.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib111" ref-type="bibr">63c.</xref> although many of the histological features are similar to those seen in other types of viral hepatitis or in autoimmune or drug-induced hepatitis.
 <xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr">58a.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib106" ref-type="bibr">61a.</xref> The morphology depends on the HEV viral genotype and on the clinicopathological setting
 <xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr">58a.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib109" ref-type="bibr">63a.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">64.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">65.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">66.</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">67.</xref> (see 
 <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="boxed-text">Box 6.1</xref> ). Foci of lobular necroinflammation with intrasinusoidal pigmented, ceroid-laden Kupffer cells are prominent in the acute infection (
 <xref rid="f0095" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6.18</xref> ).
 <xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr">58a</xref>
 <italic>Epidemic (genotype 1 or 2) hepatitis E</italic> is well known for its potential for severe hepatic disease, acute liver failure and massive hepatic necrosis, but some cases have shown prolonged clinical cholestasis with bile canalicular cholestasis and cholestatic rosettes on biopsy. The changes may resemble those of hepatitis A, with prominent cholestasis and a predominantly portal and periportal inflammatory infiltrate.
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref> In one study, a pregnant woman with fatal epidemic hepatitis E the liver showed little portal inflammation, much cholestasis with prominent portal vein and central vein endotheliitis and viral particles were identified in bile ductules by electron microscopy.
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>
 <italic>Cases of autochthonous hepatitis E (usually genotype 3)</italic> have shown portal lymphoid aggregates and periportal ductular reaction with neutrophilia at the edges of portal tracts.60 In immunocompromised subjects with organ transplants, immundeficiencies or corticosteroid therapy, 
 <italic>chronic hepatitis E</italic> manifests with the classical features of chronic hepatitis (i.e., interface hepatitis with variable lobular necroinflammation), but portal tract neutrophilia with bile duct damage, or even destruction, may be prominent.
 <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>
 <boxed-text id="b0010">
  <label>Box 6.1</label>
  <caption>
   <title>Major clinicopathological settings of HEV infection</title>
  </caption>
  <p id="bpar0010">
   <list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010">
    <list-item id="u0010">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="bpar0015">Acute, epidemic (genotype 1 or 2) hepatitis E</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0015">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="bpar0020">Acute autochthonous (genotype 3 or 4-7) hepatitis E</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0020">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="bpar0025">Acute hepatitis E superimposed on pre-existing chronic liver disease</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0025">
     <p id="bpar0030">(acute-on-chronic liver disease)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0030">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="bpar0035">Acute or chronic hepatitis E in immunocompromised host (e.g., organ transplant recipients; chemotherapy administration; HIV positivity)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0035">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="bpar0040">Chronic hepatitis E</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
 </boxed-text>
</p>
