<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Batches of 60 6–8 day-old female mosquitoes were isolated in feeding boxes and starved for 24 h, then exposed to the infectious blood-meal containing final viral titers of 10
 <sup>7.5</sup> PFU/mL (CHIKV_115) and 10
 <sup>6.5</sup> PFU/mL (CHIKV_SM), which correspond exactly to the same titers, passage and stocks used by Vega-Rua et al. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005698.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005698.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] to assess vector competence of American 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> populations. The infectious meal consisted of a mixture of two parts of washed rabbit erythrocytes and one part of the viral suspension. Females were fed through a pig-gut membrane and the infectious blood-meal was maintained at 37°C. Mosquito feeding was limited to 1 hour. Only fully engorged females were incubated at 28°C constant temperature, 80% RH and 14h:10h light:dark cycle, with unlimited access to 10% sucrose solution [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005698.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. As expected for sylvatic, not colonized mosquitoes, the artificial blood-feeding rates under experimental conditions here were low (&lt;10%). Thus when available, samples of around 20 mosquitoes of each species were examined at 3 and 7 days after virus exposure, abbreviated as “dpi”. Females were individually processed as follows: abdomen and thorax (herein after referred to as body) were examined to estimate viral infection rate, head for viral dissemination and saliva for viral transmission [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005698.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. For the determination of viral infection and viral dissemination rate, each mosquito body and head were respectively ground in 500 μL and 250μL of Leibovitz L15 medium (Invitrogen) supplemented with 2% fetal bovine serum (FBS; Eurobio) and centrifuged at 10,000 x 
 <italic>g</italic> for 5min at +4°C for further inoculation onto monolayers of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> C6/36 cell (Institut Pasteur, Paris) culture in 96-well plates [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005698.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005698.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. After 1 h incubation of homogenates at 28°C, 150 μL of 2.4% CMC (carboxymethyl cellulose) in Leibovitz L15 medium supplemented with 10% FBS was added per well. After 3 days of incubation at 28°C, cells were fixed with 10% formaldehyde, washed and revealed with hyperimmune ascetic fluid specific to CHIKV as the primary antibody and Alexa Fluor 488 goat anti-mouse IgG as the second antibody (Life Technologies). Presence of viral particles was assessed by detection of focus forming units (FFU). To estimate viral transmission, mosquito saliva was collected in individual pipette tips containing 5 μL FBS for 30 min as previously described [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005698.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Then, FBS containing mosquito saliva was expelled into 45 μL of Leibovitz L15 medium for titration in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> C6/36 cell culture in 96-well plates and stained as described above. Viral load in saliva was expressed as FFU/saliva.
</p>
