<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The importance of the antiviral response mediated by NK cells in humans has essentially been indicated by indirect evidence, including the following: 
 <list list-type="simple">
  <list-item>
   <label>(1)</label>
   <p>Most of the primary deficiencies in NK cell frequency or function are associated with an unusual susceptibility to herpes viruses [
    <xref rid="B23-viruses-11-00131" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
    <xref rid="B24-viruses-11-00131" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(2)</label>
   <p>KIR and HLA genotypes are associated with susceptibility or resistance to a large panel of viral infections, including arboviruses [
    <xref rid="B32-viruses-11-00131" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
    <xref rid="B33-viruses-11-00131" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
    <xref rid="B34-viruses-11-00131" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(3)</label>
   <p>NK cells can control a viral infection in the absence of a T cell response. This was shown in a 3-month-old girl with a T
    <sup>−</sup>B
    <sup>+</sup>NK
    <sup>+</sup> severe combined immunodeficiency phenotype who recovered from cytomegalovirus (CMV) infection without antiviral therapy. In this patient, the high number of NK cells (&gt;2 × 10
    <sup>10</sup>/L) present at the peak of viremia, as well as the correlation between viral load and the number of NK cells during follow-up, were suggestive of a causal relation [
    <xref rid="B35-viruses-11-00131" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(4)</label>
   <p>Adaptive NKG2C
    <sup>+</sup> NK cells can be expanded in response to different viral infections in the context of human CMV seropositivity [
    <xref rid="B36-viruses-11-00131" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
    <xref rid="B37-viruses-11-00131" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
    <xref rid="B38-viruses-11-00131" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. These hyper-reactive and long-lived NK cells have been described after certain viral infections and are able to mount stronger protective responses upon re-encounter of the same pathogen, at least in mice [
    <xref rid="B39-viruses-11-00131" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
    <xref rid="B40-viruses-11-00131" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
    <xref rid="B41-viruses-11-00131" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
    <xref rid="B42-viruses-11-00131" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], which could redefine the notion of immunological memory for NK cells. These adaptive NK cells will be discussed in further detail later, in the context of arbovirus infection.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
