<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Expanded surveillance in mammalian hosts has yielded several surprises, including divergent IAVs in bats (H17 and H18) [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008259.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], a new genus of Orthomyxovirus (influenza D) in bovines [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008259.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], and the establishment of IAV in canines (CIV) during the 2000s: CIV-H3N8 in the US [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008259.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] and CIV-H3N2 in Asia [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008259.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. An outbreak of H7N2 in felines in New York [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008259.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] suggests that other mammalian species could potentially be capable hosts for IAV transmission at certain thresholds of animal density and movement. However, IAVs have relatively low reproductive numbers (R), just above the threshold of 1 required for transmission, and require high contact rates between susceptible hosts to maintain transmission. For example, CIV in the US is maintained only in high-turnover animal shelters and dog daycares [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008259.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In contrast to swine, whose movements are tracked as livestock commodities and can be directly linked to disease spread [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008259.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008259.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], efforts to understand and predict emerging threats in companion animals are impeded by the low availability of public records and virological surveillance. Counterintuitively, shifting global attitudes towards dogs as domestic companions has facilitated the emergence of CIV. In the US, CIV-H3N2 appears to be maintained in dog daycares, which have proliferated and become mainstream. Furthermore, tThe recent introduction of CIV-H3N2 into the US spatial-temporally coincides with efforts by animal rights groups to rescue hundreds of Asian meat dogs for US adoption, although to date no direct link has been established between any rescue animals and the appearance of CIV-H3N2 in the US [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008259.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Dogs entering the US must provide documentation of rabies vaccination but otherwise require no disease testing or quarantine. The most pronounced change in attitudes towards dogs has been in China, where pet dogs are surging in popularity in urban areas after being banned for many decades. High rates of CIV have been observed in pets in Chinese cities [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008259.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. It remains unclear how populations of meat dogs, strays, and pets interact and collectively contribute to CIV emergence and transmission. A diversity of swine-origin [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008259.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], human-origin [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008259.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], and reassortant IAVs have been isolated from dogs in Asia but with unknown degrees of onward transmission. High contact rates between canines and humans provides frequent opportunities for zoonotic transmission, and further research is greatly needed to understand the extent to which Asia’s rapidly expanding dog populations present a pandemic risk.
</p>
