<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">This mapping is chosen so that it has two maxima of optimal fitness. One peak is set slightly below the critical infection probability of 0.5 so that the epidemic wave typically covers at most a small finite domain. A second peak is chosen well above the critical infection probability corresponding to a well adapted genotype of the species that may typically lead to a global epidemic wave. In keeping with the valley crossing mentioned above, the intermediate state 
 <italic>γ</italic> = 0 presents a minimum in the fitness, with which many of the nodes do not pass on the pathogen. As an initial condition we choose 
 <italic>γ</italic> = −1.0 at all network nodes and initially infect one randomly chosen node. Then the infection probability is initially below the critical value at 
 <italic>λ</italic> = 0.45. If a node 
 <italic>i</italic> is in state 
 <italic>I</italic>, the sequence variable 
 <italic>γ</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub> mutates in each iteration step with the rates given by the scheme 
 <disp-formula id="Equ2">
  <label>2</label>
  <alternatives>
   <tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$-1\underset{{\rm{\chi /2}}}{\overset{{\rm{\chi }}}{\rightleftarrows }}0\underset{{\rm{\chi }}}{\overset{{\rm{\chi /2}}}{\rightleftarrows }}1$$\end{document}</tex-math>
   <math id="M6" display="block">
    <mo>−</mo>
    <mn>1</mn>
    <munderover accentunder="false">
     <mrow>
      <mi>⇄</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">χ/2</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">χ</mi>
     </mrow>
    </munderover>
    <mn>0</mn>
    <munderover accentunder="false">
     <mrow>
      <mi>⇄</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">χ</mi>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mi mathvariant="normal">χ/2</mi>
     </mrow>
    </munderover>
    <mn>1</mn>
   </math>
   <graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_62597_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </alternatives>
 </disp-formula>where the -1, 0, 1 are the state values of 
 <italic>γ</italic>. The parameter 
 <italic>χ</italic> can be interpreted as a mutation rate parameter that quantifies the probability per time step of the respective transitions. The transmission probability 
 <italic>λ</italic>(
 <italic>γ</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub>) changes according to the table above. If a node 
 <italic>i</italic> infects one of its connected sites, the genetic variable 
 <italic>γ</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub> is inherited. This value is then, during the same iteration step, mutated. After an infected node transitions to the R-state, its 
 <italic>γ</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub> value remains unchanged.
</p>
