<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>HLA polymorphism has been well studied in worldwide populations, which makes it a genetic marker for tracing a population’s origin, migration, and admixture [
 <xref rid="B7-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Compared to HLA, KIR genes show polymorphisms, both at content and allelic levels. Among 16 identified KIR genes, 
 <italic>2DL1, 2DL2, 2DL3, 2DL5, 3DL1, 3DL2</italic>, and 
 <italic>3DL3</italic> belong to inhibitory KIR genes, while 
 <italic>2DS1, 2DS2, 2DS3, 2DS4, KIR2DS5</italic>, and 
 <italic>3DS1</italic> belong to activating KIR genes, and 
 <italic>KIR2DL4</italic> has both inhibitory and activating capacities [
 <xref rid="B9-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Four framework KIR genes—
 <italic>3DL3, 3DP1, 2DL4</italic>, and 
 <italic>3DL2</italic>—which are located from the centromeric to the telomeric region, respectively, are observed consistently in almost all individuals [
 <xref rid="B10-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. On the basis of gene content, KIRs are divided into two haplotype groups: A and B. The A haplotype has a fixed gene content (
 <italic>3DL3-2DL3-2DL1-3DP1-2DL4-3DL1-2DS4-3DL2</italic>) and an activating 
 <italic>2DS4.</italic> Four inhibitory KIRs (
 <italic>2DL1</italic>, 
 <italic>2DL3</italic>, 
 <italic>3DL1</italic>, and 
 <italic>3DL2</italic>) are specific for four major HLA class I ligands (
 <italic>C2</italic>, 
 <italic>C1</italic>, 
 <italic>Bw4</italic>, and 
 <italic>A3/A11</italic>, respectively) [
 <xref rid="B11-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In contrast, haplotype B is variable both in the numbers and combinations of KIR genes and comprises several genes (
 <italic>2DL2</italic>, 
 <italic>2DL5</italic>, 
 <italic>2DS1</italic>, 
 <italic>2DS2</italic>, 
 <italic>2DS3</italic>, 
 <italic>2DS5</italic>, and 
 <italic>3DS1</italic>) that do not exist in the A haplotype. Among them, 
 <italic>2DS1</italic> binds to 
 <italic>HLA-C2</italic> but with a low affinity; 
 <italic>3DS1</italic> may bind to the 
 <italic>HLA-Bw4</italic> allotype, especially for 
 <italic>Bw4-80T</italic>; and 
 <italic>2DS2</italic> may bind to 
 <italic>HLA-A11</italic> [
 <xref rid="B12-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. KIR genes, genotypes, haplotypes, and KIR–HLA pairs show a diverse distribution in different populations worldwide. Examination of KIR and ethnic populations may permit analysis of the evolutionary basis for KIR variation, allowing insight into the role of these receptors in health and disease.
</p>
