<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The 55 officially recognized ethnic populations of China, which contribute to about 8% of the overall Chinese population, provide abundant genetic resources for KIR–HLA studies. The ethnic groups living in the south and southwest of China can be traced back to three major ancient groups: Di-Qiang, Bai-Pu, and Bai-Yue [
 <xref rid="B15-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. According to historical records, the ancient Di-Qiang tribe migrated from northern to southern China before the Qin dynasty in 206 BC and formed several ethnic populations who spoke the language of Tibeto-Burman, which belongs to the Sino-Tibetan linguistic family [
 <xref rid="B15-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The ancient Baipu tribe settled down in the south and southwest of Yunnan Province in China and developed into the major Mon-Khmer speaking populations of the Austo-Asiatic linguistic family. Most of the Mon-Khmer ancient tribes migrated to the Indochina Peninsula by the end of 2000 BC, whereas others remained in the Yunnan Province [
 <xref rid="B15-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The ancient Baiyue tribe, which was widely distributed along the southeast coast of China, migrated to Yunnan Province and the northern part of Southeast Asia 2000–3000 years ago and then later on migrated to Northern Thailand and contributed to the ancestral gene pool of the Thais [
 <xref rid="B15-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. They formed ethnic populations who spoke a language of Daic, part of the Sino-Tibetan linguistic family [
 <xref rid="B17-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. There are several ethnic populations in northwestern China, such as the Tu and Yugu. It has been suggested that the Tu population originated from an ancient Xian-Bei tribe, who constructed the Kingdom of Tuguhun in 400 AD, and most of them live in Qinhai and Gansu Provinces. The Yugu originated from Hui-Hu in 600 AD and live only in Gansu Province now. Both the Tu and Yugu integrated with Mongolian and Han populations during the following centuries; moreover, both speak a language of Mongolian belonging to the Altaic linguistic family [
 <xref rid="B15-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].
</p>
