<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Two significant progresses in the tools to block the transmission of dengue inside vector benefit from the advances in genetic engineering technology and molecular biology. One is the discovery of cytoplasmic incompatibility (CI) induced by the intracellular bacteria 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic> (Hertig and Burt, 1924), which has enhanced replacement in the control programs [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. CI is a reproductive phenotype induced by bacterial endosymbionts in arthropods. Measured as a reduction in egg hatchability resulting from the crossing of uninfected females with bacteria-infected males, CI increases the frequency of bacteria-infected hosts by restricting the fertilization opportunities of uninfected hosts in populations [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Markedly reduced severity of dengue virus infection has been found in 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> infected with 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The other one is the introduction of genetic-based strategies, which has the goal to eliminate or reduce mosquito densities below transmission threshold through population suppression or to establish mosquito populations that are refractory to the pathogen through population replacement and/or modification [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Genetically modified 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> mosquitoes that activate the conserved antiviral JAK/STAT pathway in the fat body tissue have been developed, and the modified population inhibits infection with several dengue virus (DENV) serotypes [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], but its use encounters regulatory barriers and public opposition in some countries. Few drugs have been tested to inhibit the virus transmission inside mosquito, although some drugs against dengue virus effectively in vitro have been reported, such as quercetin [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], ivermectin [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], dasatinib [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], pyran naphthoquinones [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], mycophenolic acid [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], castanospermine [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], deoxynojirimycin [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. From these drugs, we choose ivermectin as an available compound for the investigation by considering following three facts: (i) ivermectin has been used for about 30 years for treatment of parasitic infections in human since 1988 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], and ivermectin mass drug administration (MDA) to humans has been suggested as a possible vector control method to reduce 
 <italic>Plasmodium</italic> transmission [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]; (ii) ivermectin has the ability to target exophagic and exophilic vectors [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] with a different mode of action [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] from the currently used insecticides [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], and then avoid known mosquito behavioral and physiological resistance mechanisms [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]; (iii) ivermectin is an inhibitor for the development of dengue virus in cells [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0006934.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The purpose of this investigation is to further determine ivermectin efficacy against dengue virus type-2 (DENV-2) in 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic>, and explore its potential application as an innovative vector control tool.
</p>
