<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">Dual-infection with HIV-1 and HIV-2 has been reported with a prevalence of up to 3.2% in West Africa [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>]. However, cross-reactivity in antibody testing and limited molecular testing to distinguish dual-infections have hampered the accuracy of prevalence estimates. Intriguingly, a possible protective effect of HIV-2 on subsequent incident HIV-1 infection was reported in 1995, and several studies reported that HIV-2 could alter HIV-1 infectivity and replication in vitro [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]. Moreover, HIV-2 infection has been shown to inhibit immunosuppression and simian AIDS after subsequent challenge with pathogenic SIV or SHIV in the Macaque model [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>]. In 2012, it was shown that HIV-2 could inhibit HIV-1 disease progression also in humans, resulting in almost twice as long time to AIDS and mortality among HIV-1 and HIV-2 dual-infected individuals compared with HIV-1 single-infected individuals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>]. Importantly, the results showed that the slower disease progression was determined during the establishment of infection, and that the inhibitory effect was strongest among study participants where the HIV-2 infection preceded the HIV-1 infection (indicating the importance of the order of infections, Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Moreover, in-depth analyses of CD4+ T-cell counts and HIV-1 diversity evolution indicated that the main difference between single and dual-infected individuals was determined during early HIV-1 infection. In support, results from the Bissau HIV cohort showed that the median CD4+ T-cell count was higher and the mortality lower in dual-infected individuals compared with HIV-1 single-infected individuals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>]. In contrast, a meta-analysis by Prince et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>] did not show any difference between HIV-1 single, and HIV-1 and HIV-2 dual-infected individuals. However, the data used was extracted from studies that were not designed for comparing survival between single and dual-infected individuals, and lacked information on estimated infection date and infection order among the dual-infected individuals. Most studies suffered from short periods of patient follow-up or observation time, and some were based on hospitalized patients with severe disease already at enrollment. Altogether, if identified, the determinants of the inhibition and slower disease progression in HIV-1 and HIV-2 dual-infection compared with HIV-1 single-infection could represent novel targets suitable for HIV cure strategies or vaccines. Moreover, it is possible that the viral reservoir in HIV-1 and HIV-2 dual-infected individuals is reduced compared to that in the majority of HIV-1 single-infected individuals. Cure strategies in dual-infected individuals may therefore be more successful compared with HIV-1 single-infected individuals (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).
</p>
