<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Dengue viruses include four genetically related viruses (65% genetic homology between the four) classified as ‘arboviruses’ (arthropod-borne viruses). All arboviruses involve replication through an arthropod host (usually a mosquito or tick) have a worldwide distribution and are responsible for huge periodic epidemics. Dengue viruses are in the family 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic> along with related viruses: West Nile virus, yellow fever virus and over 65 other related viruses. Arboviruses also include hundreds of agents, of which many are human pathogens in other viral families (
 <italic>Bunyaviridae</italic> and 
 <italic>Togaviridae</italic> including the alphavirus, chikungunya described below). Dengue viruses are the most important of all of these agents due to the number of human infections, clinical disease, associated deaths and ongoing expansion worldwide. It is estimated by the WHO that greater than 100 countries are endemic in the tropics and subtropics with over 2·5 billion people at risk. It is impossible to know the number of clinical cases that actually occur each year, but one estimate of the global burden of dengue during the 2010 worldwide pandemic was 390 million infections across four continents of which 96 million were symptomatic including 500 000 cases of severe dengue [
 <xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In Asia and Latin America, dengue is the leading cause of hospitalization in children. Since there is no effective vaccine or specific treatment, vector control is the only intervention. The dengue cycle involves humans and mosquitoes (primarily 
 <italic>A. aegypti</italic>), but sylvatic cycles also occur and are recently being investigated associated with preliminary reports of a new dengue virus type (DENV-5). Immunity to a given viral type is considered lifelong, but due to incomplete antibody neutralization between types, secondary infection with a different type can lead to more severe disease referred to ‘severe dengue’ including haemorrhagic fever and/or shock. The majority of clinical cases are classified as ‘fever’ defined by WHO as fever plus two other symptoms most commonly including chills, painful eyes, body aches (that can be severe, ‘break-bone fever’), rash, easily bruised or other evidence of haemorrhagic conditions. Three transfusion-transmission clusters have been reported [
 <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]; the first in Hong Kong, another in Singapore (where two clinical cases and one antibody seroconversion were documented) and lastly a case of transfusion-transmitted haemorrhagic fever in Puerto Rico [
 <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Infected individuals may donate blood since it has been estimated that 53–87% of dengue-infections are asymptomatic, and even individuals who develop symptoms will have a 1–2 day asymptomatic period. Puerto Rico, an island in the Caribbean and a US territory, experiences annual outbreaks. Research blood donation screening in Puerto Rico has documented the rate of dengue RNA in blood donors during the outbreak years of 2005, 2007, 2010, 2011 and 2012 at between 0·03% and 0·31%. The estimated number of viremic donations and the risk of dengue transfusion transmission have been modelled by the CDC. The resulting model output and the observed number of RNA-positive donors from blood donation screening show the same trend [
 <xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Although routine screening by the American Red Cross occurs in Puerto Rico, the clinical efficacy of the intervention is unknown since the number of transfusion transmissions documented has been few. It is unclear why the number of transfusion transmissions is not higher in endemic areas considering the magnitude of dengue outbreaks and high viral loads associated with infected donors. Possible theories include an absence of effective hemovigilance in many of the countries impacted by dengue, inability to differentiate mosquito versus transfusion transmission, protection of secondary infection due to heterologous antibodies present in the transfused unit, immunosuppression in many recipients and possibly different clinical outcomes dependent on the route of infection (i.e. mosquito versus transfusion) [
 <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].
</p>
