<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Angiotensin‐converting enzyme 2 gene (
 <italic>ACE2</italic>) is a metalloproteinase with 805 amino acids which is an important receptor for entry of SARS‐CoV into the host cell. Domain S1 in the SARS‐CoV spike protein binds the virus to the ACE2 cell receptor present in the host cells. Therefore understanding the association between SARS‐CoV, SARS‐CoV‐2, and ACE2 can be an effective therapeutic approach (Lin et al., 
 <xref rid="jcp29785-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). ACE2 is a homolog of carboxy peptidase that is best known for cleaving different peptides in the renin‐angiotensin system (RAS) and other substrates, such as apelin (Batlle, Wysocki, &amp; Satchell, 
 <xref rid="jcp29785-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). This enzyme is mostly present in organs such as the kidneys, gastrointestinal tract, and relatively low level in the lungs and its expression has been reported in Type 2 pneumocytes (Hamming et al., 
 <xref rid="jcp29785-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>). The extracellular domain of ACE2 acts as the SARS‐CoV and SARS‐CoV‐2 spike protein receptor. The new coronavirus also uses membrane‐bound ACE2 as the receptor. ACE2 neutralizes SARS‐CoV‐2 in vitro by combining with the Fc protein of immunoglobulin (Lei et al., 
 <xref rid="jcp29785-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). In addition, SARS‐CoV‐2 binds to ACE2 with a higher affinity than SARS‐CoV. In this context, the preparation of a soluble and recombinant form of ACE2 protein in humans could be useful as a novel biological treatment to counter or limit the progression of infection caused by coronaviruses that use ACE2 as a receptor (Wrapp et al., 
 <xref rid="jcp29785-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Thus, if ACE2 is presented as a suitable recombinant protein in its soluble form, it may be a new factor to counteract the spread of coronavirus by limiting the binding of coronavirus to the cell membrane or entry of the virus as well as its proliferation in infected individuals (Batlle et al., 
 <xref rid="jcp29785-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Viral replication in the presence of ACE2 the most efficient approach for extensive vaccine production. In addition, recently recognized early spike protein priming by transmembrane protease serine 2 is an important factor for entry/viral spread of 2019‐nCoV through interaction with the ACE2 receptor. Moreover, soluble ACE2 may competitively bind with 2019‐nCoV and survive cellular ACE2 activity which negatively normalizes the RAS to protect the lung from damage through weakening viral entry into cells also a viral expansion to protect the lung from injury. ACE2, fused to an immunoglobulin Fc domain, providing a neutralizing antibody help to avoid any viral escape, while also recruit the immune system to shape lasting immune respaces (Kruse, 
 <xref rid="jcp29785-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>; Smith, 
 <xref rid="jcp29785-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; H. Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="jcp29785-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>).
</p>
