<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One Health represents the collaborative efforts of multiple scientific and clinical disciplines working to attain optimal health for humans, animals, and the environment. My own unique perspective on this topic comes from my basic training in biochemistry and physiology. When a new pathogen is identified, biochemists and molecular biologist have a tendency to focus on genetic sequence and structure, and use comparative approaches to Study the new pathogen in the context of existing knowledge of similar pathogens. A good place to start is the genetic sequence of the virus and the amino acid sequence of its spike proteins, which may turn out to be important antigens and targets for development of vaccination strategies. After learning more about the sequence and the structure of the virus, return to immunology to look for ways to develop immunity to it. Let's begin with the sequence of the spike proteins. There is significant amino acid sequence homology between the spike protein epitopes of taxonomically-related coronaviruses (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Can this knowledge help in the development of novel treatments for COVID-19? Based on the high-homology between the spike protein epitopes it has been hypothesized that past contact with infected animals may shield some humans against the circulating SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). This is a very interesting hypothesis that requires further attention. Since other coronaviruses can infect other animals such as cats, dogs, mice, rats, cattle, and bats, their pivotal role as “virus reservoir” needs to be considered further. Co-existence between humans and animals needs to be studied more closely because animals that have been infected with other species of coronavirus, including companion animals might act as a “beneficial” source of immune-stimulating virus particles; thus shielding against the circulating SARS CoV-2 in humans (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). However, further epidemiological and experimental studies are required to test this hypothesis. This idea is not implausible and the pioneering work that Edward Jenner did two centuries ago reminds us that taking a “One Health” approach can be extremely valuable (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Jenner's discovery of the link between cowpox in cattle and smallpox in humans helped to lay the foundations of immunology and vaccinology, creating the first ever live vaccine: the smallpox vaccine (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).
</p>
