<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The present study focuses on the intra-host evolution of cell-free and cell-to-cell infection, which we refer to as global and local infection respectively, with spatial structure of target cells. Since the mode of spread of a pathogen affects the evolution of its life history traits, such as virulence [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005952.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005952.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], it is important to reveal what level of global and local infection is selected. Previous studies assumed that there is a trade-off between global and local infection [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005952.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005952.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Our present study also uses this assumption that denotes the retention of virions on the infected cell surface and polarization to the side of cell-cell contact promote the efficient local infection but interfere with global infection [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005952.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Because virions could be transmitted to different susceptible cells during global infection, local infection can “waste” some virus particles by putting them all into one cells. As an example, previous study that addressed the evolution of global versus local spread, assuming spatial host dynamics whereby reproduction of host individuals is always local and, as a result, the host population is spatially structured [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005952.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. They showed that the spatial structure is important for the evolution of local infection but this conclusion is limited to particular spatial structures generated by infection dynamics and host reproduction. Such self-organized structures are only a part of possible spatial structures; spatial distribution of target cells in a body, for example, have far more diversity than those self-organized by a particular epidemiological model. Another example of previous theoretical studies include local infection through virological synapses in retroviruses [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005952.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005952.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. These studies considered viruses that spread via cell-free and cell-to-cell infection, and viral strategy is defined as the number of viruses passed per virological synapse. Since total number of virions produced before an infected cell dies is limited, putting virions all into one cell can “waste” those virus particles. The strategy selected in evolutionary competition can be an intermediate number of viruses passed per synapse (i.e. evolved viruses make use of local infection) depending on the viral kinetics. However the effect of spatial structure was only implicitly discussed. To date, the relationship between a measure of spatial structure and an evolutionary outcome remains unclear in the literature.
</p>
