<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">Health, medical, and healing systems are especially relevant cultural adaptations that have evolved over time; an evolution that was, in fact, often in tandem with human cultural responses to infectious disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Reduction in the morbidity and mortality from SARS-CoV-2 infection requires a prevention system sensitive to the biological features of the virus previously described, in particular its easily aerosolized transmissibility, contagious symptomatic and asymptomatic carriers, and, in some, rapid progression from symptoms to systemic medical crisis. No curative treatment (tertiary prevention) exists for COVID-19, underscoring the need for screening and primary/secondary prevention with subsequent public health intervention. Identifying SARS-CoV-2 infection comprises symptomatic screening, testing for presence of viral DNA (PCR), or a serological test for presence of viral antibodies. Given the large burden of COVID-19 attributable to viral transmission by asymptomatic carriers, widespread testing and subsequent quarantine of those found positive is necessary to interrupt transmission of infection. Major challenges to symptomatic screening for COVID-19 are the ambiguities and similarities of symptoms compared to the common cold or influenza [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Widespread and timely testing varies greatly from country to country, and in the USA especially (where testing policy is not regulated nationally, and instead becomes the responsibility of local entities), from community to community local officials compete with others within their own state and across states to access supplies through undisclosed sources [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. The centralized push for testing in the USA by Centers for Disease Control and Prevention was mired in bureaucracy, manufacturing issues, quality control, and scientific standard delays [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. WHO shipped 250 000 diagnostic tests to 70 laboratories around the world while the US efforts in developing testing lagged behind [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Republic of Korea was able to offer testing kits after China shared the genomic sequence with the public and emergency approval was granted on a temporary basis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. The medical teams of Korea were able to screen patients with suspected respiratory symptoms in a time-efficient manner by donning one quarantine suit in “drive-through centers” that minimized contact between health care workers and patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].
</p>
