<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0050">To make an effective and new generation vaccine against this fast spreading virus, instead of protein, mRNA vaccination strategy can be a better approach [
 <xref rid="bb0260" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. The mRNA vaccine manifests the immune responses similar to natural infection and provides a short synthetic viral mRNA, which is then used by the host to produce the antigen proteins. Since the mRNA used in vaccine after injected can't integrate into the host's genome, they are safe to use. Furthermore, they are safer than inactivated or protein based vaccines because they are free from the risk of protein contamination or the injected virus to become active. The huge benefit of mRNA vaccine is that it can circumvent the hassle associated with the purification of viral proteins that saves the time from months to years used in standardization and scaling up the mass production [
 <xref rid="bb0260" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. So far there is no approved RNA vaccine, but are under clinical trials. The National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Disease (NIAID), USA in collaboration with Moderna have initiated a research to develop an mRNA vaccine called mRNA-1273 [
 <xref rid="bb0265" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] which produces a stable form of the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein (S). NIAID has registered a phase 1 clinical trial of the vaccine candidates on 45 healthy adults completed on 19th March 2020 in Seattle [
 <xref rid="bb0270" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0275" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], while the other clinical trials of phase 1 mRNA vaccines (mRNA-1273) and another mRNA-based vaccine candidate BNT162, currently in pre-clinical testing are expected to start in April 2020 [
 <xref rid="bb0265" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0280" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. However, the proposal of mRNA based vaccine development is not new. Since extracellular ribonucleases is everywhere in the cytoplasm, so the unprotected naked mRNA alone is not very stable to be used as a prophylactic vaccine. Due to the presence of strong net negative charge and hydrophilic nature, the RNA cannot be taken up easily by the cells during in vivo condition. Thus it requires highly efficient carriers such as new generations of liquid nano particles (LNP) to stabilize and pack the mRNA into an injectable form which is also done in the case of the mRNA-1273 vaccine being developed today.
</p>
