<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack id="ac0005">
 <title>Acknowledgments</title>
 <p>We would like to thank the governments of Liberia, Sierra Leone, and Guinea for contributing to the International Medical Corps' humanitarian response. We would also like to thank all of our generous institutional, corporate, foundation, and individual donors who placed their confidence and trust in International Medical Corps and made our work during the Ebola epidemic possible. We would also like to thank the United States Naval Medical Research Center, Public Health England, the European Union Mobile Laboratory, and the Nigerian Laboratory for providing laboratory data to our Ebola Treatment Units. We would like to further acknowledge all members of our Research Review Committee and other technical teams that contributed to this research. Finally, we would also like to thank our clinical, WASH, and psychosocial teams as well as all of our monitoring and evaluation staff, including the data collection officers at each of our ETUs. AC would like to thank Mary Lynn Baniecki and Christian Matranga for insightful discussions on the EBOV qPCR assays, and Christopher Moxon for critical feedback on the manuscript. Finally, we thank the patients included in this study whose data has and will continue to make invaluable contribution to improving future Ebola care. PCS, AF, and AC received support from 
  <funding-source id="gts0005">Howard Hughes Medical Institute</funding-source>, AC was supported by NI grants R01AI114855, U01HG007480, and U19AI110818, and 
  <funding-source id="gts0010">Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation</funding-source> grant OPP1195122. ACL, MS, and VW were fully supported by IMC for this study. MAH and TS were supported by GOAL Global and U.K. Department for International Development grant 04890. RFG was supported by 
  <funding-source id="gts0015">NIH</funding-source> grant U19AI115589. JGS was supported by 
  <funding-source id="gts0020">NIH</funding-source> grant U19AI135995. DSG was supported by 
  <funding-source id="gts0025">NIH</funding-source> contract number HHSN272201400048C.
 </p>
 <sec id="s9100">
  <title>Conflict of interest statements</title>
  <p id="p3165">RFG discloses conflicts of interest from receiving NIH grants and from the development of medical countermeasures by members of the Viral Hemorrhagic Fever Consortium that may result in royalties. The rest of the authors declare that there are no conflicts of interest associated with this research manuscript.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s9000">
  <title>Role of funding source</title>
  <p id="p2465">The funders of the research had no role in study design, data collection, data analysis, data interpretation, or writing of the manuscript. The corresponding authors had full access to all the data in the study and had final responsibility for the decision to submit for publication.</p>
 </sec>
</ack>
