<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Genome analyses have provided evidence that genetic variation in the spike gene of these viruses from civets is associated with increased transmission of the virus 
 <xref rid="ppat.1000557-Tang1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. In addition, species-to-species variation in the sequence of the gene 
 <italic>angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2)</italic>, which encodes the SARS-CoV receptor, also affects the efficiency by which the virus can enter cells 
 <xref rid="ppat.1000557-Li1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. By a combination of phylogenetic and bioinformatics analyses, chimeric gene design, and reverse genetics–aided generation of viruses that encode spike proteins of diverse isolates, researchers have reconstructed the events that led to the emergence of a virus able to spread efficiently in humans 
 <xref rid="ppat.1000557-Sheahan1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. Structural modeling predicted that the SARS-CoV that caused the epidemic had an increased affinity for both civet and human ACE2 receptors due to adaptation (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat-1000557-g002">Figure 2</xref>). Subsequent functional genomics studies of these viruses in diverse species provided further insight into the role of specific host genes involved in the pathogenic response 
 <xref rid="ppat.1000557-Rockx1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1000557-deLang1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. The pathological changes observed in the lungs are initiated by a disproportionate innate immune response, illustrated by elevated levels of inflammatory cytokines and chemokines, such as CXCL10 (IP-10), CCL2 (MCP-1), interleukin (IL)-6, IL-8, IL-12, IL-1β, and interferon-γ 
 <xref rid="ppat.1000557-Baas1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. These clinical data were confirmed experimentally by demonstrating that SARS-CoV infection of diverse cell types induces a range of cytokines and chemokines, thus providing a conceptual framework for SARS-CoV pathogenesis. Host genome expression analyses of various animal hosts and humans with different outcomes of infection indicated differential activation of innate immune genes in, for example, aged subjects compared to young subjects. Importantly, treatment of aged macaques with pegylated interferon-α (i.e. interferon-α covalently modified with polyethylene glycol polymer chains, to enhance its bioavailability) reduced SARS-CoV replication and pathogenic responses 
 <xref rid="ppat.1000557-Haagmans1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. Thus, host genomics analysis may provide markers of pathogenesis and leads for therapeutic intervention, as in this example of SARS-CoV infection.
</p>
