<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is intriguing that NP-R111E’s increased oligomerization correlated with severely defective minigenome transcription and replication (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00105-f005">Figure 5</xref>B,C), to the degree that NP-R111E trVLPs were unable to replicate over multiple passages (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00105-f005">Figure 5</xref>D). NP oligomers coat viral RNA to defend against host viral RNA sensors and nucleases; however, these oligomers also prevent the viral polymerase L from accessing viral RNA. During viral transcription and replication, accumulation of EBOV VP35 disrupts NP oligomers (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00105-f003">Figure 3</xref>C), releasing free viral RNA as a template for RNA-directed RNA synthesis [
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. One possible hypothesis is that NP-R111E stabilizes oligomers too strongly, rendering viral RNA inaccessible to L, in turn abrogating minigenome transcription and replication. Because NP-R111E trVLPs were extremely defective, charge-reversal, unsurprisingly, has never been observed in EBOV or most other ebolavirus sequences (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00105-f002">Figure 2</xref>C). Surprisingly, Sudan virus (SUDV), a replication-competent ebolavirus that is lethal in humans, does encode a charge-reversal substitution, NP-K110E (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00105-f002">Figure 2</xref>C). The secondary structure of an SUDV NP monomer is quite similar to that of EBOV NP [
 <xref rid="B87-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>], and residues 109–111 are positioned in the same β-strand in both. However, SUDV NP oligomers have not yet been characterized, so one of the many other amino acid differences between SUDV and EBOV could counteract the effect of NP-K110E in SUDV. Future study is required to better understand how EBOV NP oligomerization affects viral RNA synthesis, and how SUDV NP promotes viral transcription and replication despite a charge-reversal substitution.
</p>
