<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Testing whether emergent mutations like NP-R111C affect fitness of live virus brings additional challenges because different viral stocks and cultured cells versus animal models can cause discordant results. For example, the GP-A82V substitution has been shown numerous times to enhance EBOV infectivity in cell culture [
 <xref rid="B15-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], using multiple EBOV surrogate systems (e.g., EBOV VLPs, retroviral particles pseudotyped with EBOV GP, and recombinant live virus [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]) and multiple cell types (e.g., human monocyte-derived dendritic cells [
 <xref rid="B15-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]). However, a recent study using immunocompromised laboratory mice and non-human primates [
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] indicated that EBOV Makona viral isolates encoding GP-A82V lead to modestly decreased viral load compared those without the GP-A82V mutation. A second recent study found that GP-A82V may induce slightly more morbidity and fatality in immunocompromised laboratory mice but not in domestic ferrets [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The discrepancies between the in vitro and in vivo studies could be due to the use of clinical EBOV isolates [
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] that contain multiple additional mutations versus live EBOV generated from recombinant DNA plasmids [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Limited recombinant live EBOV studies have been performed to test the impact of the NP-R111C substitution specifically. One study showed that EBOV with GP-A82V and NP-R111C outcompetes ancestral EBOV Makona in a head-to-head format in cultured cells, but did not measure the impact of NP-R111C alone [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Another study found that NP-R111C alone increases viral replication in cell culture, decreases morbidity and lethality in immunocompromised laboratory mice, and does not differ from ancestral EBOV Makona in domestic ferrets [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-12-00105" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].
</p>
