<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0090">Some examples of these items include:
 <list list-type="simple" id="lis0010">
  <list-item id="lsti0025">
   <label>1</label>
   <p id="par0095">Protein energy malnutrition (PEM). The risk of developing this condition increases with age and becomes particularly high in conditions of severe illness and immobilization or significant reduction in physical activity. The presence of PEM increases the risk of frailty in the elderly and, therefore, of severe comorbidity and death. This picture is generally associated with severe alterations of the immune response that begin with a reduction in the number of white blood cells (leukopenia), which, together with serum albumin levels, is one of the main indicators of PEM; at the somatic level, the main indicator of PEM is a reduction in lean body mass, that is, muscle mass. The latter becomes particularly apparent as a reduction in the musculature of some parts of the body, such as the muscles of the leg and in particular of the thigh or the quadriceps; also, those of the arms and trunk can rapidly suggest an onset of the phenomenon. This process denotes an alteration of the metabolic and energy management processes (metabolic reprogramming) that lead to the use of muscle and other tissue proteins as energy source rather than as functional components (for example, as a support for muscle contraction). This occurs because the physiological processes nutrient (particularly glucose) use for energy – in the presence of altered insulin function – taper off. This energy reprogramming is one of the main endocrine consequences and aging and its sequelae accelerate in case of chronic inflammation (microinflammation) and immunocompromise [
    <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0030">
   <label>2</label>
   <p id="par0100">Micronutrient and vitamin deficiency. The importance of nutritional factors and, in particular, of some micronutrients to guarantee an optimal function of the immune system is well known [
    <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Specific deficiencies of vitamins and trace elements with a marked immunomodulatory action are observed in Western countries and, in particular, in the elderly. In Spain and Italy, one of the countries that should theoretically follow ideal lifestyles (those part of the Mediterranean Diet), the same deficiencies of other Western countries are now observed, consequent to the globalization of food production and supply systems [
    <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
    <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. These unavoidable developments reduce the consumption of nutritional factors with a positive action on the immune system, while providing an excess of caloric intake and, therefore, higher risk of developing overweight, obesity, and metabolic diseases that, in turn, promote secondary immunodeficiency conditions. In summary, the Mediterranean and Western diets are now often high in calories and low in micronutrients, a condition that can lead to malnutrition, similar to that described above for protein [
    <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Vitamins such as A, B
    <sub>6</sub>, B
    <sub>12</sub>, C, D, E and folic acid and minerals like zinc, iron, selenium, magnesium and copper are factors and cofactors of many enzymes involved in immune processes. In addition, they participate in the production of antimicrobial proteins and in the activity of cells such as neutrophils and macrophages. Fatty acids of the omega 3 series, which are essential, are the precursors of many molecules, e.g. resolvins, proteins and maresins, that accelerate the resolution of inflammatory processes [
    <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0035">
   <label>3</label>
   <p id="par0105">Sedentary lifestyle, overweight/obesity, and metabolic diseases. Sedentary lifestyles and obesity are important risk factors for the development of cardiometabolic diseases and for an accelerated decrease in immunoinflammatory homeostasis in all age groups, particularly in the elderly. The last phenomenon - called immunosenescence - is responsible for the increased susceptibility to infectious diseases seen in those over 65 years of age [
    <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0040">
   <label>4</label>
   <p id="par0110">Exposure to environmental immune interference. There are numerous environmental factors responsible for immunosuppression, whose actions add to those of aging, and which might lead to the so-called forms of secondary immunodeficiency [
    <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Recently, the importance of epigenetic factors is emerging, in particular, in their relevance to the susceptibility to viral infections.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0045">
   <label>5</label>
   <p id="par0115">Intestinal dysbiosis. A healthy microbiota contributes to the maintenance of the immune system, much of which contributes to the immune response through B and T cells. To corroborate this theory, 2 to 10% of Chinese SARS-Cov patients experienced gastrointestinal symptoms at start [
    <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Coronaviruses, including Covid-19, bind to the angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) from the intestinal epithelium and use it as a receptor. The intensity of this link seems to be related to the state of health of the intestinal microbiota. Physicians should be aware that provision of selected probiotics might strengthen the immune response, although full confirmation by human trials is still needed [
    <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
    <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0050">
   <label>6</label>
   <p id="par0120">Parallel to the development of precision therapies in medicine, precision nutrition is an emerging science that is based on well-established factors such as genetic, epigenetic, and microbiome individual variations [
    <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Numerous molecular studies are providing mechanistic insight into precision nutrition. As very specific therapeutic objectives must be achieved, precision nutrition must be based on food products with well-established mechanisms of action at the molecular level in terms of gene expression and modulation, and signaling pathways. This includes modulating the response of the immune system through activation of innate immune responses, considering that personal genetic profiles affect immune variables.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
