<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig1">
 <label>Figure 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Zika Virus Production in SK-N-SH and VeroE6 Cells is Similar to C6/36 Cells which Resist Cell Death. Astrocytes Exhibit Higher Zika Virus Production than Neurons and Maintain Higher Viability. (
   <bold>a</bold>) Graphs represent ZIKV infectious virus particles in the supernatants at different hpi, as measured with the plaque assay. Trend in the production of infectious virus particles are similar in SK-N-SH, VeroE6, C6/36 cells (
   <bold>a</bold>
   <sub>
    <bold>i</bold>
   </sub>) and in astrocytes (
   <bold>a</bold>
   <sub>
    <bold>ii</bold>
   </sub>), while in neurons are lower in all three strains. The increase in infectious ZIKV-FP virus particles was the lowest in all cell types. ZIKV-FP viral particles, collected in the supernatant at 12 hpi did not produce countable plaques. (
   <bold>b</bold>) Cell survival plots for SK-N-SH, Vero E6, and mosquito C6/36 cells (
   <bold>b</bold>
   <sub>
    <bold>i</bold>
   </sub>) and for astrocytes and neurons (
   <bold>b</bold>
   <sub>
    <bold>ii</bold>
   </sub>) infected with ZIKV-UG, ZIKV-BR, and ZIKV-FP at an MOI 0.1. (
   <bold>c</bold>) Cell survival plots for SK-N-SH, Vero E6, and mosquito C6/36 cells (
   <bold>c</bold>
   <sub>
    <bold>i</bold>
   </sub>) and for astrocytes and neurons (
   <bold>c</bold>
   <sub>
    <bold>ii</bold>
   </sub>) infected with ZIKV-UG, ZIKV-BR, and ZIKV-FP at an MOI 1. Cell survival data shown in panels b and c was determined with Reliablue reagent. Noticeable cell death of all cell types, except C6/36 cells, was observed. Survival of astrocytes was higher than of neurons. Data represent means ± SEM of two independent experiments performed in triplicates in panel a, one experiment performed in triplicates in panels b
   <sub>i</sub> and c
   <sub>i</sub> and one experiment performed in triplicates in panels b
   <sub>ii</sub> and c
   <sub>ii</sub> (a total of 10
   <sup>4</sup> cells were plated per well).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_44559_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e505" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
