<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Has this increase in ZIKV-interest been translated into practical solutions? In our opinion, the answer is yes. For instances, the catalogue of options for molecular diagnostic and reliable serological tests has been greatly expanded after the ZIKV uprising in Brazil [
 <xref rid="B13-jcm-08-00369" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Moreover, important milestones of ZIKV research were rapidly achieved. One of them was the development of amenable animal models. Although non-human primates are naturally susceptible to ZIKV infection, ethical, financial, and operative concerns limited their utilization in ZIKV-research. The utilization of immuno-deficient mice solved the problems with the “resistance” to peripheral ZIKV infection in adult mice and provided useful animal models for ZIKV infection [
 <xref rid="B14-jcm-08-00369" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. These mice models have contributed to the advancement of the understanding of the pathology of ZIKV, antiviral testing, and vaccine evaluation. The utilization of 3D culture systems (brain organoids) also contributed to the understanding of ZIKV pathology [
 <xref rid="B15-jcm-08-00369" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. On combining clinical findings, animal, organoid, and cell culture results, ZIKV-induced microcephaly was found to be the result of the marked neurotropism of ZIKV. This pathogen is able to cross the placental barrier and infect neural progenitor cells and neurons, causing premature differentiation, inducing apoptosis, and thus reducing brain size. In addition to this “direct effect”, placental insufficiency and inflammatory responses during the infection would also contribute to intrauterine growth restriction [
 <xref rid="B16-jcm-08-00369" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. However, it should be highlighted that critical questions about ZIKV biology and its pathogenesis are not yet fully understood and although there are working hypotheses to explain the development of microcephaly, the complete puzzle has not been totally solved. Regarding therapeutic approaches, a wide panel of substances with antiviral activity against this virus was rapidly identified [
 <xref rid="B17-jcm-08-00369" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and is still growing day by day. One of the most promising approaches for the rapid identification of drugs effective against ZIKV was carried out by drug repositioning studies screening libraries of drugs approved for human use, a methodology that brings the advantage of the identification of compounds with documented security. Additionally, the search for novel and specific drugs has already identified a wide variety of cellular and viral targets suitable for pharmacological intervention. The structure of some of the ZIKV proteins has been solved, which probably accelerates both drug discovery and vaccine design [
 <xref rid="B18-jcm-08-00369" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. This search for antivirals is also contributing to the identification of broad-spectrum antiviral candidates that could be effective against other medically relevant flaviviruses like DENV or WNV, and could even help to combat other still undefined future arboviral threats [
 <xref rid="B19-jcm-08-00369" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Notwithstanding, we have to be still cautious when thinking in antiviral prescription against ZIKV, because there is yet no specific antiviral drug licensed to combat any flavivirus. Moreover, antiviral therapies against ZIKV will have to face extra challenges such as safety in pregnant women or its ability to cross the blood–brain barrier to inhibit virus infection in nervous tissues [
 <xref rid="B20-jcm-08-00369" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. In this scenario, vaccination appears to be the most feasible control strategy in the short term. In fact, there are already multiple vaccine candidates that have undergone phase I clinical trials, and even one DNA vaccine that has entered into Phase II trials [
 <xref rid="B21-jcm-08-00369" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The good results obtained with vaccination for the control of other flaviviral diseases like yellow fever, Japanese encephalitis, or tick-borne-encephalitis invite optimism. However, the experience with DENV vaccination indicated that vaccine performance may depends on serostatus, showing that vaccination against certain flaviviruses is not a bed of roses [
 <xref rid="B22-jcm-08-00369" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Results from animal experimentation suggest that the immunological crosstalk between ZIKV and other flaviviruses (i.e., DENV) could complicate massive utilization of some of these vaccines [
 <xref rid="B23-jcm-08-00369" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-jcm-08-00369" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In fact, there are experimental evidences of ZIKV-vaccine candidates that induce a generation of cross-reactive antibodies that may enhance DENV infection, although there are promising approaches to minimize this possibility [
 <xref rid="B25-jcm-08-00369" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Additionally, there is anecdotal evidence showing that neutralizing antibodies if induced against ZIKV and DENV at high titers could potentially prevent enhancement of infection [
 <xref rid="B26-jcm-08-00369" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-jcm-08-00369" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Thus, in order to develop safe ZIKV vaccines, an important effort is urgently required to assess the real potential of antibody-dependent enhancement of infection within the populations suitable for ZIKV-vaccination [
 <xref rid="B28-jcm-08-00369" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].
</p>
