<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">Plant pathogens and pests are responsible for up to 40% of maize, potato, rice, soybean, and wheat crop yield losses worldwide (
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Savary et al., 2019</xref>). Plant diseases caused by bacteria, fungi, nematodes and viruses cost the global economy USD220 billion annually (
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Savary et al., 2019</xref>). Viruses make up almost half of the plant disease-causing pathogens, at an annual global cost of more than USD30 billion (
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Nicaise, 2014</xref>). Rice is cultivated in 100 countries, supporting nearly half the world's population, and is at risk from multiple vector-transmitted viruses, at a cost of USD1.5 billion annually. In 2019, the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses recognized 1484 plant viruses. Like animal viruses, plant viruses are grouped on the basis of viral genomic structure. There are 26 families of plant viruses, although only those infecting cash crops are investigated (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Sastry et al., 2018</xref>). Belonging to the economically important DNA virus family, Geminiviridae
 <italic>, Cassava mosaic begomovirus</italic> infection results in an annual crop loss of 25 million tons. With half a billion people relying on this staple for a source of calories, epidemics of this virus directly lead to famine. As a member of Caulimoviridae
 <italic>, Cacao swollen shoot badnavirus</italic> (CSSV) has become endemic in Ghana, Nigeria, and Togo. West African cacao production accounts for 70% of the world's cacao supply. The loss of cacao plantations would devastate the local economy and lead to global cacao shortages. With 200 million trees dead due to CSSV infection, expensive eradication programs have been established to save the cacao industry (
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Nicaise, 2014</xref>). Members of the Bromoviridae, Closteroviridae, Luteoviridae, and Potyviridae families are all positive-sense single-stranded RNA viruses, like SARS-CoV-2, and are the most economically damaging group of plant viruses. Bromoviruses cause disease epidemics in fruits, vegetables, and animal feed. Citrus, an internationally high-value fruit crop, is at risk from 
 <italic>Citrus tristeza closterovirus</italic>, a member of Closteroviridae that has caused the loss of 100 million citrus trees worldwide (
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Nicaise, 2014</xref>). Unfortunately, quarantine measures are only effective in areas with a low infection rate. The most widely distributed viral disease of cereals, 
 <italic>Barley yellow dwarf luteovirus</italic>, of the Luteoviridae family, infects barley, maize, rice, oat, and wheat crops that sustain the world's population. 
 <italic>Potato leafroll polerovirus</italic> is responsible for the annual loss of 20 million tons of potato, at a cost of USD100 million. The estimated cost for the management of the Potyviridae family member, 
 <italic>Plum pox potyvirus,</italic> exceeds USD10 billion (
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Nicaise, 2014</xref>). The more famous Potyviridae family member, 
 <italic>Papaya ringspot virus,</italic> devastated the papaya industry and could have led to the extinction of the species in Hawaii.
</p>
