<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0025">Vaccination is economically sound and less labor-intensive than screening and quarantine measures. Although plants do not have an adaptive immune system like that of humans, the expression of weaker related viruses or viral proteins leads to disease resistance. Innate immunity in plants, as in humans, protects against pathogens. Antiviral Resistance (R) genes prevent systemic spread by eliciting programmed cell death, and RNA silencing prevents viral replication (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Soosaar et al., 2005</xref>). Traditional methods of breeding and grafting can confer such pathogen resistance, but in response to the 
 <italic>Papaya ringspot virus</italic> epidemic, the first virus-resistant papaya was obtained through bioengineered expression of viral protein, successfully demonstrating plant vaccination (
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Ferreira et al., 2002</xref>). Since then, successful RNA silencing-based genetic resistance has been demonstrated in bean, papaya, pepper, plum, potato, squash, and tomato, although the application of biotechnology is underutilized (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Khalid et al., 2017</xref>). Bioengineering pathogen resistance could control plant pandemics, reduce yield loss, and promote food security; however, limited funding and negative public opinion about genetically modified crops are obstacles to their development and subsequent cultivation and consumption. Eradication of emerging or reemerging infectious diseases requires fast affordable testing and universal vaccination programs. Bioengineered expression of antiviral proteins in 
 <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> could provide fast and inexpensive diagnostic reagents and vaccine candidates against SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Capell et al., 2020</xref>). With this in mind, perhaps a positive outcome of COVID-19 could be a change in public attitude toward the application of biotechnology to fight diseases of both plants and people.
</p>
