<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>VLPs are multimeric nanostructures composed of viral structural proteins with inherent self-assembly properties. Morphologically, VLPs resemble the authentic viruses but are devoid of viral genetic materials, rendering them non-replicative and non-infectious. Attributed to their intrinsic adjuvanticity, several VLPs were reported to be capable of inducing strong B-cell and T-cell responses even in the absence of adjuvants [
 <xref rid="B31-vaccines-07-00091" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In an attempt to produce a universal influenza A vaccine, we previously constructed chimeric VLPs derived from NvC that were genetically fused with three copies of the M2e epitope at its C-terminal region [
 <xref rid="B26-vaccines-07-00091" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Although NvC-M2ex3 was demonstrated to be immunogenic, its protective efficacy has not been investigated in vivo. Therefore, in the present study, we investigated the protective efficacy of NvC-M2ex3 against H1N1 and H3N2 infections. BALB/c mice were immunized subcutaneously with NvC-M2ex3 three times at three-week intervals. After the primary injection, the anti-M2e antibody response was insignificant and indistinguishable from the control group. However, a spike of anti-M2e antibody titer was detected three weeks after a booster was administered and a further increase was observed one week after the second booster. In our previous study, we administered NvC-M2ex3 into BALB/c mice in the presence of a complete Freund’s adjuvant using the same dose and same immunization schedule as in this study. Our previous results demonstrated a significant increase in anti-M2e antibody titer just three weeks after the primary injection and a maximum titer was achieved after the first booster, indicating that the maximum antibody response could be attained with a lower injection number in the presence of adjuvants [
 <xref rid="B26-vaccines-07-00091" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Although a complete protective mechanism of M2e-based vaccine remains poorly understood, passive transfer of the anti-M2e antibody was demonstrated to be able to protect the recipients against viral infection, suggesting the importance of this antibody [
 <xref rid="B32-vaccines-07-00091" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Furthermore, the anti-M2e antibody was also reported to confer protection against influenza virus infection via antibody-dependent cytotoxicity and antibody-mediated phagocytosis in Fcγ receptor knockout mice [
 <xref rid="B33-vaccines-07-00091" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-vaccines-07-00091" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. In the present study, a higher titer of anti-M2e antibody corresponded well with increased survival, reduced immunopathology, and morbidity of IAV-infected mice.
</p>
