<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The mice immunized with NvC-M2ex3 demonstrated distinct cytokine profiles when they were challenged with different strains of IAV. Upon infection with H1N1, the mice immunized with NvC-M2ex3 exhibited a higher level of IFN-γ and IL-12 in the lungs compared to the control groups. Positive correlation between IL-12 and IFN-γ in influenza infection was also reported by Monteiro et al. [
 <xref rid="B40-vaccines-07-00091" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. IL-12 enhanced IFN-γ secretion which reduced pathogenesis and replication of IAV at the early stages of the viral infection [
 <xref rid="B41-vaccines-07-00091" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-vaccines-07-00091" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Intriguingly, when the mice that had been vaccinated with NvC-M2ex3 were challenged with H3N2, a lower concentration of IFN-γ was observed compared to the control groups, despite a higher level of IL-12 also being detected, suggesting dysregulation of IFN-γ. The balance of inhibitory and stimulatory signals directed to IFN-γ-producing cells along with IL-12 could be the underlying cause that leads to this outcome. Similar cytokine profiles were observed in the peripheral blood mononuclear cells of patients infected with multidrug-resistant tuberculosis and cord blood-derived mononuclear cells of neonates stimulated with 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B43-vaccines-07-00091" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-vaccines-07-00091" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Although IL-6 was demonstrated to correspond with the lung pathogenesis and disease severity induced by IAV in mice, it was also reported to promote neutrophil survival, virus clearance, and mitigated lung inflammation [
 <xref rid="B45-vaccines-07-00091" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-vaccines-07-00091" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-vaccines-07-00091" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. In the present study, the mice immunized with NvC-M2ex3 exhibited a lower level of IL-6 in the lungs compared to the control group when challenged with H3N2, but no significant difference was observed after H1N1 infection. On the other hand, histopathological analysis of the lungs of infected mice also suggests a reduced immunopathology in the mice immunized with NvC-M2ex3 after IAV challenges, but did not correspond with the mentioned pro-inflammatory cytokine levels in the lungs, indicating that other cytokines might have played dominant roles in mediating the immunopathology. Secretion of pro-inflammatory cytokines potentially confers early protection against IAV infections, but excessive activation could lead to massive tissue damage.
</p>
