<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with OASIS Tables with MathML3 v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archive-oasis-article1-mathml3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jpoasis-nisons2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Soc Anthropol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Soc Anthropol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1111/(ISSN)1469-8676</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SOCA</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Social Anthropology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0964-0282</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1469-8676</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7276731</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1469-8676.12849</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">SOCA12849</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Special Section Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Special Section Articles</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Covid&#x02010;19 Forum</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Viral living</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">FORUM</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">TIMOTHY GITZEN</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="soca12849-cr-0001" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Gitzen</surname><given-names>Timothy</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6148-7463</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="soca12849-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><address><email>tgitzen@hku.hk</email></address></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="soca12849-aff-0001">
<label><sup>1</sup></label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Society of Fellows in the Humanities</named-content>
<institution>University of Hong Kong</institution>
<city>Hong Kong</city>
</aff><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><elocation-id>10.1111/1469-8676.12849</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><!--<copyright-statement content-type="issue-copyright"> &#x000a9; 2020 European Association of Social Anthropologists <copyright-statement>--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2020 European Association of Social Anthropologists</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This article is being made freely available through PubMed Central as part of the COVID-19 public health emergency response. It can be used for unrestricted research re-use and analysis in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source, for the duration of the public health emergency.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:SOCA-9999-na.pdf"/><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><page-count count="2"/><word-count count="651"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>edited-state</meta-name><meta-value>corrected-proof</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:5.8.4 mode:remove_FC converted:08.06.2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body id="soca12849-body-0001"><p>As much of the world has gone into complete lockdown, woefully unprepared, many countries have turned to South Korea for answers, given its handling of COVID&#x02010;19. Rapid and widespread testing, expansive surveillance assemblage and selected quarantine practices are upheld by many countries and public health professionals as superb, a model to adopt. But this is not South Korea&#x02019;s only lesson. Indeed, the world is on edge, scrambling in the here and now, but trying to figure out what happens to sociality going forward.</p><p>Five years prior, South Korea found itself mid&#x02010;epidemic, facing a different coronavirus. In the aftermath of the 2015 Middle East Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus (MERS&#x02010;CoV) outbreak in South Korea, queer and HIV/AIDS activists gathered to reflect on the government&#x02019;s and society&#x02019;s treatment of infected individuals as vectors of disease rather than as people. Activists demonstrated how this viropolitical stance mirrored the treatment of people living with HIV/AIDS in South Korea: they became more disease than person, threatening South Korean bodies and making South Korea itself impure.</p><p>One particular activist at the gathering stated that South Korea should <italic>not</italic> aim for purity or absolute cleanliness to keep citizens safe. That&#x02019;s impossible, and results in catastrophic social and psychological effects for those deemed impure and unclean. Rather, the activist claimed, we need to find ways for infected and non&#x02010;infected individuals to live together, both socially and spatially. When kinship and social relations are predicated on consanguine purity, the mere presence of a virus can potentially upend an entire social and affective system of belonging. For activists, that epidemic embodied, quite literally, fundamental problems in South Korean kinship, social relations and belonging.</p><p>The problems of sociality and belonging are now front and centre in the current pandemic, as quarantines, isolation and social distancing have blanketed much of the world. The Herculean global effort of viral containment and cleanliness &#x02013; discourses of face masks and social distancing &#x02013; though undeniably important, will have lasting effects on how we live with one another. This was the fear of those South Korean activists after the MERS&#x02010;CoV outbreak, as what underlined public health discourse and practice were stigmas of impurity.</p><p>Living together, then, confronts stigmas of impurity, and purity&#x02019;s embeddedness in sociality and belonging. The virus, facilitating for many a reprioritisation of one&#x02019;s life, allows a broader reassessment of social relations. If purity is impossible, sociality must start someplace else. For those South Korean activists, sociality begins with the virus itself, finding ways of living together with the virus. South Korea offers a view at how this dialectic has played out, between the abysmal government response to viral outbreak and the activist solution of living with the virus.</p><p>Disease experts warn that thousands of viruses lie in wait; the frequency of novel viruses that caused the likes of MERS, SARS and Ebola virus disease has increased in recent years. We are living in the time of viruses, not pandemic times: the normalcy of the virus rather than the normalcy of panic and fear. Sooner or later we will have to find ways of living with viruses.</p></body><back><ack id="soca12849-sec-0002"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Special thanks to Elliott Prasse&#x02010;Freeman for reading drafts of this contribution.</p></ack></back></article>