<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par36">Stimulated cells were washed in FACS staining buffer (D-PBS with 0.5% FBS) and incubated in 200 µl 0.02% EDTA (UltraPure EDTA, 0.5 
 <sc>m</sc>. pH 8.0, Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA) in D-PBS (Quality Biological) for 15 min at 37 °C to disengage interactions of the cells with the cross-linked co-stimulatory antibody. Subsequently, cells were washed in staining media, transferred into a 96 deep-well plate, and stained for 10 min at RT in the dark with 0.5 µl of a fixable Live/Dead cell discrimination fluorochrome (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA) in 1 ml. Cells were washed in FACS staining buffer, then surface stained for 30 min at RT in the dark with 100 µl of a cocktail containing antibodies targeting CD3 (BD Biosciences, clone SP34-2, catalog number 557917, 1 µl), CD4 (BD Biosciences, catalog number 562843, clone L200, 0.5 µl), CD8 (BD Biosciences, catalog number 557834, clone SK1, 5 µl), CD28 (BD Biosciences, clone L293, catalog number 337181, 20 µl), and CD95 (clone DX2, catalog number 561978, 20 µl). Cells were then washed in FACS staining buffer, fixed, and permeabilized with Caltag Fix &amp; Perm solutions (Life Technologies), and incubated with 130 µl of a cocktail containing antibodies targeting CD69 (Beckman Coulter, clone TP1.55.3, catalog number 6607110, 5 µl), IL-2 (BD Biosciences, clone MQ1-17H12, catalog number 560702, 10 µl), IFNγ (BD Biosciences, clone B27, catalog number 560924, 5 µl), and TNFα (BD Biosciences, clone Mab11, catalog number 552889, 10 µl) for 20 min at 4 °C in the dark, then washed in FACS staining buffer, and fixed in 200 µl freshly prepared PBS with 0.1% paraformaldehyde (Alfa Aesar, Haverhill, MA). Uncompensated flow cytometric events were acquired on a Beckton-Dickinson LSR-II flow cytometer (BD Immunocytometry Systems, San Jose, CA) 1–24 h after fixation. BD CompBeads (Anti-Mouse IgGκ and Anti-Rat IgG/Negative Control (FBS) compensation particles, BD Biosciences) stained separately with the individual monoclonal antibodies used in the test samples, were used as a basis for electronic compensation. Samples were analyzed in one single technical replicate.
</p>
