<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para30">Initial findings for convalescent plasma therapy for the treatment of COVID-19 are encouraging but have so far only come from two small studies done in China; a 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/2763983" id="interrefs40" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">case series of five patients</ext-link> with critical COVID-19 receiving mechanical ventilation, and a 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/content/early/2020/04/02/2004168117" id="interrefs50" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">pilot study done in ten patients</ext-link> with severe COVID-19. In both studies, convalescent plasma therapy was shown to be safe and clinical outcomes improved, including fever, Sequential Organ Failure Assessment score, and respiratory symptoms, in some cases within 1–3 days of treatment. The 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/vaccines-blood-biologics/investigational-new-drug-ind-or-device-exemption-ide-process-cber/revised-information-investigational-covid-19-convalescent-plasma" id="interrefs60" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has approved</ext-link> the use of convalescent plasma under compassionate use rules, but randomised controlled trials are now needed to provide clinical evidence. Three trials initiated by the 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ccpp19.org/index.html" id="interrefs70" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">US National COVID-19 Convalescent Plasma Project</ext-link> are currently being evaluated by the FDA to test the activity and safety of convalescent plasma in three groups of patients: people who have been exposed to the virus and are at high risk of developing severe COVID-19 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04323800" id="interrefs80" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04323800</ext-link>); hospitalised patients with acute respiratory symptoms (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04325672" id="interrefs90" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04325672</ext-link>); and patients with severe COVID-19 who are mechanically ventilated. Other trials are also planned or underway in China, Colombia, Iran, Mexico, and the Netherlands.
</p>
