<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are several additional considerations that may improve upon our efforts. Many disease models include exposed compartments (e.g., malaria 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1003668-Mandal1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>) in the host and/or vector population that can delay the onset of infectiousness once bitten. This may lead to additional possibilities in the switch time analysis that we did not consider. For example, if a host population is initially infected but has a long exposed period then there may be a quick switch to sampling the vector population followed by switches at longer time scales back to the host population. Additional important developments include treating the initial conditions and transmission process as random variables. This will likely lead to a distribution of optimal strategies rather than a single, fixed strategy 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1003668-Kendrick1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. Recognizing uncertainty in the initial conditions may be especially important when the source of infection is unclear given the potential sensitivity of the sampling process to the initial infections. We also did not consider the possibility of testing for multiple pathogens in this analysis. For example in Florida, mosquito control agencies regularly screen for malaria, West Nile virus, and dengue fever among others 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1003668-Connelly1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Applying a mixed sampling strategy may allow managers to hedge their bets because the optimal strategy for West Nile virus may not necessarily translate to the early detection of other pathogens. Finally, our assumption that diagnostic tests for pathogen or antibodies provide perfect indicators of an individual's state may be violated by several factors. First, immunological dynamics can lead to low viral or antibody levels even when individuals have been infected, which may lead to low test reliability 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1003668-Paweska1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Extending the approach to coupled immunological-epidemiological models may account for this source of uncertainty. Second, and perhaps more importantly, imperfect diagnostic test reliability can arise due to stochastic factors that cannot be accounted for in conventional lab techniques. These effects can be incorporated into a sampling model by multiplying the economic efficiency by a random variable representing the test sensitivity and specificity 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1003668-Donald1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>.
</p>
