<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34">Infectious diseases are one of the most hazardous enemies mankind has faced as these are capable of destroying all his economic strengths by affecting their pets, domesticated animals and themselves. For profitable animal husbandry practices, prevention and control of diseases should be considered on cost–benefit ratio basis. The colossal losses are incurred during disease outbreaks like FMD, IBR, PPR, bluetongue, sheep pox, goat pox in livestock and IBD, MD, IB, EDS, CIA and avian influenza in poultry. Vaccines and judicial vaccination procedures are only ways to prevent and control such diseases in a cost-effective manner. The concept of vaccination was first popularized by Edward Jenner in 1798 as a method to fight against the deadly human small pox disease. However, prior to it, Chinese people were practicing a form of vaccination called ‘ovination’ where virulent sheep pox virus was inoculated in sheep to generate immunity against further infection with sheep pox virus. Similarly, in FMD, in the absence of a vaccine, ‘apthization’ (deliberately rubbing the infected fluid or lesions of diseased animals into the healthy animals of the farm/herd) was practiced with the objective of reducing the time, labour and cost towards the management of the outbreak in one go at the farm. The ILT virus, a herpes virus which causes respiratory disease in poultry, was recommended to be inoculated in the cloacal region to impart immunity in want of vaccine availability. However, now with the availability of dependable vaccines against most of the infectious diseases it is not advisable to use such methods as it has the risk of spreading the virulent virus to susceptible animals. After the successful initial approaches by Jenner using cow pox virus as vaccine against small pox in human, the concept of killed vaccine was made into use by Louis Pasteur in 1885 to prevent post-bite rabies disease in man. The mid-1940s designated as ‘the era of cell culture’ made a revolution in vaccine research to develop more attenuated live organisms as vaccine. Vaccine research has moved from the application of whole organism approach (inactivated or live attenuated) to synthetic antigenic peptide-based or gene-based vaccine approaches for man and animals against a number of infectious diseases.</p>
