<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par42">Azithromycin is safe and well tolerated. Even in long-term administration (500 mg thrice weekly for 48 weeks), there was no increase in serious adverse events besides mild increase in diarrhoea [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. The main adverse event of concern in this trial would be potential cardiovascular toxicity. Although macrolides have a class warning for potential cardiac QT prolongation, azithromycin does not show this effect under experimental conditions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Only a few cases of QT prolongation have been reported for patients treated with the drug [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>], mainly because azithromycin, unlike other macrolide antibiotics, does not interact with CYP3A4, despite a minor interaction with the anti-coagulant warfarin [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. In the large AMAZES RCT, there was no increase in QTc prolongation, although this study excluded participants with QTc&gt;480 ms [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Recently, a large study of Medicaid prescriptions reported an additional risk of cardiovascular death of 47 extra deaths/million compared with amoxicillin (relative risk (RR) for cardiovascular death 2.49 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>], and a meta-analysis of 20 million patients suggested a RR for cardiac death or ventricular tachycardia of 2.42 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. However, these effects are very small and subject to confounding and at odds with more recent studies: in a review of 185,000 Medicare patients, odds ratio for CV death was only 1.35, and after controlling for covariates decreased to 1.01 (0.95–1.08) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>], whilst a large Cochrane review of 183 trials found no evidence of an increase in cardiac disorders with macrolides (OR 0.87) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. Overall, the risk to a patient treated would be low compared with the considerable mortality of COVID-19, particularly if patients with QTc&gt;480 ms were excluded.
</p>
