<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0235">The integration of research activities in the response to outbreaks has led to a prompt research response in terms of R&amp;D activities on drug and vaccine development, and treatment. The next step is to consider other factors conducive to research innovation, such as fostering an innovative atmosphere in pharmaceutical R&amp;D and focusing on research coordination to develop effective solutions. There is no approved drug therapy for SARS-CoV-2 or any other coronaviral infection at this time, as development efforts have been closely linked to free market dynamics. Thus, it is imperative to accelerate the improvement of innovative R&amp;D of antiviral drugs. In the global market, public and private sectors must cooperate toward the development of a new regulatory category of broad-spectrum drugs for the treatment of coronaviral infections.
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>74</sup>
 </xref> For China in particular, acceleration of research aimed at the clinical isolation of dangerous pathogens is necessary, as well as improvement of the existing R&amp;D facilities for the development of anti-coronaviral therapies. Advanced technologies have been applied in epidemic surveillance and control, and pandemic prevention and control strategies have been optimized in a timely manner. However, prevention and control measures taken by the international community have exposed shortcomings related to various aspects such as emergency reserve supplies as well as fundamental disease prevention and control systems in response to public health emergencies. It is suggested that the construction of advanced institutional mechanisms to reform the public health response in addition to an increased focus on coordination and cooperation among scientists, public health professionals, entrepreneurs, and government officials would be conducive to global joint defense against pandemics in the future. In addition to the above general suggestions, there are some other specific efforts that China must undertake. Regional differences in previous studies reflect the importance of developing an equitable health system and accelerating the construction of modern information systems to improve governmental coordination for effective pandemic preparedness and response.
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>
</p>
