<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The history of virus lineage dispersal in Yunnan was recovered from geo-referenced phylogenies, which were estimated using the continuous phylogeographic method [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007392.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] implemented in BEAST 1.8. A separate continuous phylogeographic analysis was performed for each gene and each Yunnan clade identified by the preliminary discrete phylogeographic analyses; however, the nucleotide substitution and molecular clock models were linked across the clades to avoid over-parameterisation. For these models, we used the same models as described above, together with a relaxed random walk model for inference of the continuous spatial locations. This relaxed random walk model assumed a log-normal probability distribution among phylogeny branches of diffusion rate scalars. The spatiotemporal information contained in inferred phylogenetic trees was extracted with the R package “seraphim” [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007392.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1007392.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. For the present study, we extracted spatiotemporal information from a subset of 1,000 trees sampled at regular intervals from the posterior distribution of trees (after burn-in had been removed). This was done for each gene and for each Yunnan clade. After this extraction step, each phylogeny branch is represented as a distinct movement vector [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007392.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. “seraphim” was also used to estimate statistics of spatial dispersal based on these extracted movement vectors. We estimated the mean branch velocity, the weighted dispersal velocity, the diffusion coefficient (as originally defined in Pybus 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007392.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]) and the weighted diffusion coefficient (as defined by Trovão 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007392.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]). Further details regarding these statistics can be found in the “seraphim” package [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007392.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].
</p>
