<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0044">The approach utilizes a vector, such as plasmids, replication-deficient adenoviruses, lentiviruses, or replication-competent vesicular stomatitis virus, to transfer a SARS-CoV-2 gene and express a viral protein, typically the S protein, to elicit immunogenicity. DNA vaccines have many characteristics of desirable vaccine as they are relatively easy to manufacture in large and high quality at a relatively low cost, relatively safe, and stable at room temperature. The DNA vaccines could be delivered by intramuscular or intradermal inoculation and even electroporation. DNA vaccines have been developed for several infectious diseases and have been shown to be well-tolerated and immunogenic. They are also being tested for safety and immunogenicity against SARS-CoV-2. Preliminary studies in rhesus macaques upon expression of several viral S immunogens have shown have humoral and cellular responses, including production of neutralizing antibodies and IFN-g producing CD4+ and CD8+ T cells 
 <xref rid="bib0077" ref-type="bibr">[77]</xref>. The immune response following DNA vaccination was effective in reducing viral RNA levels upon inoculation of the immunized monkeys with SARS-CoV-2 virus 
 <xref rid="bib0077" ref-type="bibr">[77]</xref>. Likewise, vaccination with a recombinant adenovirus that expressed the full-length S protein led to dose-dependent antibody and T cell responses in the majority of the vaccinated individuals, which were peaked at ~ 4 weeks 
 <xref rid="bib0078" ref-type="bibr">[78]</xref>. No serious side effect was reported, but mild to moderate side effects were common 
 <xref rid="bib0078" ref-type="bibr">[78]</xref>. A phase 2 study with this vaccine is planned. One caveat with the vector-based vaccines is immunogenicity of the vectors. Replication-deficient adenoviruses are known to be immunogenic and elicit host-immune reaction and shutdown of the transgene expression, which were amply demonstrated in the early days of gene therapy [
 <xref rid="bib0079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>].
</p>
