<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">The spatial transmission pattern of a virus is very important for epidemic control and potential vaccine design. Viruses like H3N2 seasonal influenza virus are highly transmissible, and a new adaptive variant can rapidly spread globally after its emergence
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, in the phylogeny of H3N2, it is rare to have a genetic cluster that is persistent and limited in a specific region. A sink-source model of H3N2 viral ecology is suggested in which new variants are seeded from the tropics (mainly East and Southeast Asia) to sink populations in temperate regions
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup>. In contrast, viruses like enterovirus A 71 (EVA71) are more endemic, and different genetic subtypes circulate and persist in different regions. For instance, the C4a sub-genotype of EVA71 mainly circulates in mainland China, while the C5 genotype of EVA71 is mainly detected in Vietnam
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. The establishment and prevalence of the specific sub-genotype of a viral species could be determined by environment factors, population immunity, and/or the genetic background of hosts in this region. Here, we trace the global as well as local hMPV distribution and transmission by integrating publicly available sequences and newly generated sequences. We find that hMPV was endemic in America before 1990, indicating the possible origin of currently circulating hMPV lineages. Notably, this could be the case because hMPV was limited to circulating in America or could be caused by sampling bias as there were few samplings on other continents before 1990 (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Further retrospective study of hMPV in other continents would improve our understanding of the origin of hMPV. Between 1990 and 2000, transmissions from America to other continents were observed. However, most of these introductions were transient since the local phylogenetic clusters of hMPV were not sustained in the phylogeny, indicating hMPV was still not well established in the regions. After 2005, clusters of hMPV mainly composed by strains in A2b and A2c lineages became dominant in Asian countries. Thereafter, transmissions from Asia to other continents were frequently identified through the phylogenetic trees (Figs 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). These results suggest the establishment of A2b and A2c lineages in Asia after 2005, and more Asian countries became epicenters for hMPV. In this scenario, it is reasonable to have novel variants of hMPV first identified in Asian regions. The 180-nt and 111-nt duplicates of hMPV in the G gene were first reported in Japan in 2016 and 2017, and these newly emerged variants caused an increasing epidemic in Japan
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>. In Guangzhou, the duplicate variant was also detected and closely related with the strains identified in Japan with nucleotide identity at 99.3% (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). A2c was the predominant lineage identified in hMPV epidemics in Guangzhou, China 2013–2015. However, the increasing epidemic of hMPV infection in Guangzhou in 2017 was mainly caused by the B1 strains which were closely related viruses circulating in Japan in 2016 (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). These results suggest the predominant hMPV lineage is varied among Asian countries in the same epidemic season, and rotation of these predominant lineages may be observed among these countries due to frequent viral transmissions.
</p>
