<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The genetic analyses suggest that CHIKV is a conserved virus, with over 95% nucleotide/amino acid similarity across the genome. Previous studies based on partial genomes and individual genes yielded similar results [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006670.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Codon 148 in the nsp1 coding region was identified as undergoing positive selection pressure. Given that this position is located in a nonstructural protein and is not present in any currently known B-cell epitopes, it is possible that this residue plays a role in modulating intracellular interactions and/or the host T-cell immune response. Insertion/deletion regions in the CHIKV 3’UTR are associated with genotype/subtype classification and most likely occurred as a founder effect due to their adaptation to mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006670.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Since insertion/deletion does not count as “substitution” in viral evolution, we did not include 3’UTR region in our BEAST analysis. The substitution rate of CHIKV was estimated to range from 4E-4 (Asian genotype) to 6E-4 (ECSA genotype) substitutions/site/year by our temporal phylogenetic analysis, consistent with previous studies based on fewer numbers of CHIKV genome sequences [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006670.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006670.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. The substitution rate is lower than human influenza A virus (3E-3 substitutions/site/year) and Zika virus (1E-3 substitutions/site/year) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006670.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006670.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], but similar to other RNA viruses, such as human respiratory syncytial virus A (5E-4 substitutions/site/year) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006670.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], West Nile virus (5E-4 substitutions/site/year) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006670.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], and Ebola virus (8E-4 substitutions/site/year) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006670.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].
</p>
