<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Epidemic history of the CHIKV Asian genotype reconstructed by phylogenetic analyses showed a significant temporal-spatial evolutionary pattern, especially among non-CO strains, and indicated that the CHIKV Asian genotype diverged about 50–60 years ago. Long internal branches of non-CO sequences in the phylogenetic trees indicated extensive genetic diversity and suggested that the non-CO viruses have been circulating for many years prior to being detected or sampled. Significant geographical clustering of non-CO strains reflected limited viral transmission between regions, with a previous study showing similar results [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006670.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In contrast, due to the rapid spread and explosive transmission of the CO viruses, the CO clade showed distinct bush-like patterns with several polytomies. Furthermore, there was more viral transmission between different regions in the CO clade than in non-CO strains. A previous study suggested an intertwined transmission network among different countries and regions [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006670.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. However, with the large number of newly-acquired sequences during the 2014–2015 Caribbean/Americas epidemic, the CO clade presents significant phylogeographic clustering as well. In particular, our Florida sequences with recent travel history available enabled robust interpretations regarding distinct virus introductions and co-circulating virus strains in different regions. However, a lack of such metadata for many previously-published sequences may prevent us from gaining a complete picture of international virus transmission. In Nicaragua, the geographic enrichment analysis revealed a higher-than-expected presence of strains belonging to the CO1.4 subclade in both Managua and Nueva Segovia, which are located relatively far apart (~300 km = 186 miles). This finding could indicate either co-circulation or separate introductions of this virus subclade into two geographic regions.
</p>
