<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Understanding the incredibly complex biology of the HIV virus is essential for building effective diagnostics and drugs. HIV belongs to a class of viruses known as retroviruses because it contains ribonucleic acid (RNA) as its genetic material. After the HIV virus infects a cell, it uses an enzyme called reverse transcriptase to convert its RNA into DNA so that it can replicate itself using the host cell’s own replication machinery. The HIV replication cycle begins with fusion of the virus to the host cell surface, which begins the influx of viral proteins into the host cell. After viral DNA is formed by reverse transcription and integrated into the host DNA, new viral RNA is used as genomic RNA to make viral proteins, which travel to the cell surface to form a new HIV virus. This vicious cycle rapidly produces several billion new viruses every day in persons infected with HIV and is further complicated by the ability of reverse transcriptase to mutate, causing new strains of HIV to develop in infected individuals. HIV targets the immune system directly by infecting CD4+ lymphocytes, which also leads to the systematic degradation of the immune system because CD4+ cells are pivotal in helping immune responses (Blum 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2005</xref>). The constant process of evolution and replication in the HIV virus creates incredible stress for the immune system and has been one of the reasons why HIV has been especially difficult for medical researchers to combat. Drugs against HIV are called antiretroviral drugs because HIV is considered a retrovirus as previously described and the drugs fall into three classes consistent with the underlying biology of the virus: (1) nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NRTIs), (2) nonnucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NNRTIs), and (3) protease inhibitors (PIs) (Pirmohamed 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137">2001</xref>). Reverse transcriptase inhibitors directly inhibit the reproductive capacity of the HIV virus because of the mandatory role the reverse transcriptase enzyme plays in viral reproduction. NRTIs contain faulty versions of the nucleotides used by reverse transcriptase to convert RNA to DNA, causing improper build of the new DNA so that HIV’s genetic material cannot be incorporated into the healthy genetic material of the host cell. On the other hand, NNRTIs work by attaching themselves to reverse transcriptase and prevent the enzyme from converting RNA to DNA. After viral RNA is translated into a polypeptide sequence, the sequence is assembled into a long chain that includes the proteins like reverse transcriptase and protease.
</p>
