<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During the SARS and MERS pandemics, CP had provided several satisfactory and successful therapeutic outcomes (
 <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). In a meta-analysis from 32 studies conducted on SARS-CoV infection, the mortality rate was significantly decreased when compared to their placebo group (
 <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Since there is a high sequence as well as virological homology between the SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2, the CP therapy could be a promising therapy to treat the severely affected COVID-19 patients (
 <xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). In CP therapy the antibody-rich plasma will be isolated from the COVID-19 recovered patients using an apheresis machine; the plasma-rich antibody against the SARS-CoV-2 would be injected, which could neutralise the viral load in the severely affected COVID-19 patients. For this procedure, around one litre of plasma will be collected, where approximately only 250 mL of plasma is required for one patient (
 <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). According to a recent study in China, the researchers found that CP therapy could rescue COVID-19 patients from disease severity. During this experimental assay, one dose of 200 ml CP transfusion was readily accepted, which also reduced several symptomatic conditions of the COVID-19 patients. The researchers found that after the introduction of CP therapy, the patients showed negative for the SARS-CoV-2 nucleic-acid test, increased the oxygen saturation levels and lymphocyte counts, and also improved the functions of organs (
 <xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). These studies demonstrate that CP therapy could be a promising therapy to improve the clinical outcomes of COVID-19 patients. Since this therapy is in its pipeline stage, more investigations are required in larger cohorts to make it a global and standardised therapy to treat COVID-19 infection.
</p>
