<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Additionally, in the H1N1 pandemic, patients with severe disease had high rates of venous thromboembolism (VTE) and many patients with thromboembolism did not have evidence of systemic DIC.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr36-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr37-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr"/>
  <xref rid="bibr38-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr39-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>
 </sup> Patients with ARDS from H1N1 infection had a greater than 20-fold increase in risk of pulmonary embolism compared to patients with ARDS unrelated to H1N1.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr39-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>
 </sup> Empiric therapeutic anticoagulation in patients with ARDS was associated with decreased rates of VTE in patients with ARDS from H1N1, but had no effect on VTE rates in patients with ARDS unrelated to H1N1 infection. There are reports of VTE in patients with COVID-19, despite concerns regarding underdiagnosis given baseline elevations in D-dimer, as well as pragmatic challenges in diagnostic imaging while in isolation, including use of personal protective equipment and longer duration of exposure of health care workers.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr40-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr41-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>
 </sup> Although data remain scarce, there are increasing reports of arterial thrombotic events including ischemic strokes in patients with COVID-19.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr41-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr42-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr43-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>
 </sup> Myocardial injury, defined by elevations in cardiac troponin levels, is common in patients hospitalized with COVID-19 and is associated with severe disease and high risk of mortality.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr44-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr45-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>
 </sup> Myocardial injury may result from systemic inflammatory response syndrome (SIRS) and inflammation as well as due to acute thrombotic events.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr46-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr47-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>
 </sup> Similar observations of myocardial injury have been found in patients with other viral infections.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr48-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr49-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
