<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Regarding drug design, NS1 is a target to be considered due to its involvement in multiple essential pathways in influenza’s biology [
 <xref rid="B135-ijms-21-01511" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>]. NS1 was initially identified as a viable target through yeast-based screening assays with 2000 compounds. Of these, four compounds emerged capable of inhibiting NS1 activity. Initially, Basu and coworkers [
 <xref rid="B136-ijms-21-01511" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>] conducted a study aiming at identifying compounds able to block NS1 activity without having repercussions on the hosts’ proliferation. As NS1 is toxic to yeast, the NS1 inhibitor is as successful as the yeast cells regain their normal growth [
 <xref rid="B137-ijms-21-01511" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>]. It was found that three compounds (NSC128164, NSC109834, and NSC95676) decreased the levels of NS1-specific viral RNAs. Another compound (NSC125044), although not interfering with the viral RNAs levels, increased IFN’s induction. These four compounds seem to act on two different antiviral mechanisms. This yeast-based assay showed that it is possible to target accurately NS1 and that the action on NS1 decreased the virus load. The action of these compounds is restricted to specific interactions with influenza’s NS1, as activity in other viruses has not been inhibited. These results proved that NS1 may be a target for small molecule inhibitors with clinical applicability. Walkiewicz and coworkers [
 <xref rid="B138-ijms-21-01511" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>] pursued one of these four compounds to further investigate how it modulates NS1’s action, optimizing the prior hits. One of these compounds—JJ3297—was shown to inhibit viral replication by shifting the IFN signaling cascade into regaining its normal function. This is important if the infection is in its early stages because JJ3297 is effective in restoring the IFN cascade, preventing the spread of the infection to neighboring cells. However, the compound is less effective if the infection has already spread to a high cell number. The mechanism of action of JJ3297 remains unclear, but it seems to be related to the essential presence of RNAse L.
</p>
