<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="viruses-12-00581-f002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Inhibition of influenza virus infection by nylidrin. (
   <bold>A</bold>) Western blot analysis showing the dose-dependent decrease in viral proteins by nylidrin. Madin-Darby canine kidney (MDCK) cells were mock-infected (no virus) or infected for 24 h with the PR8 virus at a multiplicity of infection (MOI) of 0.001 in the presence of dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO; 0.2%, a delivery vehicle), nylidrin (1, 10 or 100 μM), oseltamivir carboxylate (OSV-C; 10 μM), or ribavirin (RBV; 100 μM). Each viral protein and α-actin, as a loading control, are marked on the right side of the gels. (
   <bold>B</bold>) Plaque reduction assay. Viral titers were determined using culture supernatants from the same samples as in (A). This represents one of the three independent experiments. Statistical comparisons were performed using a two-tailed unpaired 
   <italic>t</italic>-test. 
   <italic>n</italic> = 2; **, 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01. n.d., not detected. (
   <bold>C</bold>) Time-of-addition experiment. Nylidrin or (−)-epigallocatechin gallate (EGCG; an entry blocker) was administered during virus adsorption at 4 °C for 1 h (0~1 h) or at the indicated time points post-infection (p.i.) (0, 1, 2, and 4 h). At 5 h p.i., the supernatants were removed and replaced with an overlay medium for incubation at 35 °C. The percentage plaque number was determined by crystal violet staining on day 3. This represents one of the three independent experiments. Statistical significance was assessed using a two-way ANOVA with Dunnett’s multiple comparisons tests. 
   <italic>n</italic> = 2; **, 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01; ****, 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001. (
   <bold>D</bold>) Confocal microscopy. MDCK cells were infected with PR8 (MOI, 1) at 37 °C for 5 h in the presence of DMSO (delivery vehicle) or nylidrin (100 μM). Viral NP (green) and cellular nuclei (blue) were detected using NP-specific antibody and DAPI, respectively. Original magnification, 400×.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="viruses-12-00581-g002" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
