<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13">To overcome the further spread of SARS-CoV-2, precautions and preventions are highly recommended i.e. to restrict traveling to affected areas, direct personnel exposure to a diseased individual, use of disinfectants in routine, and least exposure of human to human. Since no completely effective treatment is available for COVID-19, but in this regard, China has approximately two thousand old histories of using traditional Chinese medicines (TCM) against most of the viral infections including large-scale cold outbreaks being effective since Zhong-Jin Zhang (AD150- 219) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. So TCM could be a better hope in the recent outbreak as well as in future such epidemics, a generic drug screening and selection process are shown in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. Few examples relevant to respiratory viral infections e.g. Yin-Qiao-San and Jing-Fang-Bai-Du-San dispelling wind and cold, Ma-Xing-Shi-Gan-Tang can remove toxic heat obstruction in the lungs so has been effective in past [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], Further investigation and research in TCM can also contribute in providing therapies for COVID-19. TCM is not only effective indirect inhibition of virus attachment and internalization in cell thus prevent their replication and further spread but also boost up host immune response [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] and can enhance T cell proliferation, antibody production, expression of pathogen-specific CD8 +  and CD4 + response, the release of IgA, IgG2 and IgG1, increase Th1 type cytokine secretion, activation of alveolar macrophages, suppress Th2/Th17-responses and keep Th1 and Th2/Th17 cells balanced thus preventing further severity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. From the available reports SARS-CoV-2 outbreak has infected thousands of individuals with high mortality rate due to unavailability of effective therapies, with this in mind we aimed to summarize some important therapeutic strategies to enhance host immune response with the help of traditional Chinese medicine, which are observed quite effective against viral epidemics in past before effective vaccines were developed for the complete virus elimination so the implementation could be a hopeful contribution in COVID-19 therapeutic strategies.
</p>
