<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0045">The ability of CoVs to enter the primary infection site and to later spread to distant sites including the CNS, relies on their interaction with specific receptors located on the host cells. A large body of experimental work firmly points to the spike (S) protein as the main determinant of cell tropism and pathogenicity of CoVs (
 <xref rid="bb0810" ref-type="bibr">Walls et al., 2020</xref>). The S protein, which forms heavily glycosylated transmembrane trimers in the viral envelope, mediates CoVs entry into susceptible host cells via the interaction with specific cellular receptors represented by aminopeptidase N (APN) for the α-CoV HCoV-229E (
 <xref rid="bb0870" ref-type="bibr">Yeager et al., 1992</xref>), angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) for SARS-CoV (
 <xref rid="bb0425" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2003</xref>) and SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="bb0325" ref-type="bibr">Hoffmann et al., 2020</xref>), and dipeptidyl-peptidase 4 (DPP4) in the case of MERS-CoV (
 <xref rid="bb0620" ref-type="bibr">Raj et al., 2013</xref>). Instead, the immunoglobulin-like CEACAM1a protein is the receptor for MHVs (
 <xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">Bergmann et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0840" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al., 1990</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0845" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al., 1991</xref>). It is important to note that these receptors are also expressed in CNS neurons, glial and endothelial cells, where they could mediate cell-specific targeting (
 <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">Baig et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">Bender et al., 2010</xref>). The S protein has the structure of class I fusion proteins, consisting of two functional subunits contained in the same protein, the N-terminal surface subunit (S1) responsible for receptor binding, and the C-terminal transmembrane subunit (S2) that mediates viral internalization (
 <xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr">Bosch et al., 2003</xref>). Upon binding to its receptor, the S protein is cleaved by specific proteases, thereby allowing the release of the S2 subunit, initiating membrane fusion and virus internalization (
 <xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr">Bosch et al., 2003</xref>). Cleavage of SARS-CoV (
 <xref rid="bb0275" ref-type="bibr">Glowacka et al., 2011</xref>) and SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="bb0325" ref-type="bibr">Hoffmann et al., 2020</xref>) S protein is mediated by the Transmembrane Serine Protease 2 (TMPRSS2); pharmacological inhibition of TMPRSS2 significantly reduces infection with SARS-CoV-2, representing therefore a potential strategy for the treatment of COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="bb0865" ref-type="bibr">Yamaya et al., 2020</xref>).
</p>
