<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite the limitations, the present study allows the benefits and costs of DAA treatments to be examined in connection with statutory accident insurance-financed services. It must be taken into consideration that the costs recorded are not standardised costs, but actual costs incurred for the study cohort. The costs of the 20-year projection relate to this study cohort comprising patients with therapy experience. Due to the declining incidence of HCV infections among HP, it is expected that the overall cost for treating occupational HCV infections will also fall for statutory accident insurance [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-17-00440" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Following an increase in the number of patients treated with DAAs in 2015, this figure declined again and is now largely stable [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-17-00440" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The retrospective cost analysis in the present study supports this assumption. The overall cost for occupational CHC cases has fallen in recent years. Kruger et al. [
 <xref rid="B8-ijerph-17-00440" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] estimated in a real-world setting study using data from the German Hepatitis C Registry that costs per SVR12 for second-generation DAA treatments are comparable to those for first-generation DAAs, due to the fact that the costs for the currently used treatment regimens have declined. Additionally, the high SVR12 rates involved in DAA treatment resulted in a lower RWA for most insured persons in our study. In the long term, this will be positively reflected in the cost structure, especially in terms of the expenditure for pension benefits. The results of the sensitivity analysis show that prompt administration of therapy is desirable for cost reasons. Treatment with interferon-free therapies reduces the number of patients with advanced liver diseases and increases life expectancy. Newly introduced treatment regimens such as Epclusa (SOF + velpatasvir), Zepatier (elbasvir + grazoprevir), or Maviret (glecaprevir + pibrentasvir) allow lower-cost alternatives to be offered for newly infected patients than DAA regimens with SOF [
 <xref rid="B50-ijerph-17-00440" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-ijerph-17-00440" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. In particular, the very well tolerated ribavirin-free DAA regimen pibrentasvir/glecaprevir achieves an overall SVR12 rate of 98% with a short treatment duration and a high barrier to resistance. It is the only pangenotypic therapy regimen for patients with severe-to-terminal renal dysfunction, including dialysis patients, and is also well suited for patients following liver transplantation [
 <xref rid="B51-ijerph-17-00440" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-ijerph-17-00440" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. When the patent for the costly DAA regimen (e.g., SOF) expires, cheaper generic drugs will be available in future to treat CHC. To regulate treatment costs, it is advisable to prioritise individual DAA treatment regimens based on their cost effectiveness. Alongside the economic perspective, ethical concerns are also of importance.
</p>
