<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Differences in reproductive behavior, or behavior due to age or sex, vertical transmission, heterogeneity in host response and time since infection may impact the disease dynamics and deserve further study, particularly in wildlife disease modeling (
 <xref rid="b37" ref-type="ref">Busenberg and Cooke [1993]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b176" ref-type="ref">Woolhouse et al. [1997]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b70" ref-type="ref">Galvani and May [2005]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b12" ref-type="ref">Allen et al. [2006]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b99" ref-type="ref">Klein and Calisher [2007]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b4" ref-type="ref">Adler et al. [2008]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b26" ref-type="ref">Banerjee et al. [2008]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b94" ref-type="ref">Keeling and Rohani [2008]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b103" ref-type="ref">Laverty and Adler [2009]</xref>). Reproductive differences between species can be introduced through the birth rates, that is, births can occur at a constant rate through the year, as is often modeled for human populations (
 <xref rid="b19" ref-type="ref">Anderson and May [1992]</xref>), or as a seasonal pulse, which is often more probable in animal populations (
 <xref rid="b94" ref-type="ref">Keeling and Rohani [2008]</xref>). The former case will provide (assuming no vertical transmission) a constant stream of new susceptibles into the population, whereas seasonal births will provide an influx of new susceptibles at a given time each year. The implications can be a sudden change in the 
 <inline-graphic xlink:href="NRM-25-5-e059.jpg" xlink:title="inline image" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/> value for the population with a corresponding change in the level of vaccination required for herd immunity. Behavioral differences in the sexes where male rodents’ aggressive behavior when infected with hantavirus (
 <xref rid="b99" ref-type="ref">Klein and Calisher [2007]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b100" ref-type="ref">Klein et al. [2004]</xref>) and vertical transmission when infected with arenavirus were modeled in (
 <xref rid="b12" ref-type="ref">Allen et al. [2006]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b26" ref-type="ref">Banerjee et al. [2008]</xref>). Analyses of the models revealed distinct thresholds that depend on these sexual differences. Age structure or age since infection can be accounted for in models through either discrete or continuous ages and through multiple infectious stages indicating time since infection (
 <xref rid="b94" ref-type="ref">Keeling and Rohani [2008]</xref>). Models with juveniles and adults whose behavioral differences may affect the disease dynamics have been considered in wildlife diseases, e.g., spread of rabies (
 <xref rid="b157" ref-type="ref">Suppo et al. [2000]</xref>) but data are limited on age‐structure or times since infection in wildlife populations. Addressing the heterogeneity in the host population has not been well studied but it clearly has implications for the maintenance and spread of viral pathogens. The best illustration of the importance of heterogeneity in host response to pathogens is the incidence of superspreaders (
 <xref rid="b176" ref-type="ref">Woolhouse et al. [1997]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b70" ref-type="ref">Galvani and May [2005]</xref>), in which 20% of a host population contributes to 80% of transmission (20/80 rule). Vertical transmission, virus spread from mother to offspring, has been included in models by assuming infectious females give birth to infectious offspring with a given probability (
 <xref rid="b37" ref-type="ref">Busenberg and Cooke [1993]</xref>).
</p>
