<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Eight to ten years after ART roll out in 2003 we found a moderate level of TDR in Gondar which is in agreement with observations of increased TDR prevalence after roll-out of ART from different world regions [
 <xref rid="pone.0205446.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0205446.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0205446.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. The overall prevalence of TDR (6%), found in this study is comparable to the 5.6% prevalence in sub-Saharan Africa 6–8 years after ART roll-out, and the 7.4% prevalence estimate in East Africa, eight years after ART roll-out [
 <xref rid="pone.0205446.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0205446.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0205446.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Two previous studies conducted in Gondar in 2009–2010, and in the country 2009–2011, 6–8 years after ART roll out showed DRM levels of 4–6% [
 <xref rid="pone.0205446.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0205446.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0205446.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Despite long term ART administration in the area there was not a significant difference in the DRM level. A direct comparison of the temporal DRM levels presented here is not possible, since the former studies targeted older age groups as opposed to our threshold study that included a younger population of HIV infected individuals. Thus, in Gondar the DRM prevalence among different age groups were not different although TDR differences between age groups and gender has been reported from other sub Saharan countries [
 <xref rid="pone.0205446.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0205446.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. However, even moderate levels of TDR among young sexually active individuals should raise concerns as it may result in less effective ART in a considerable proportion of recently HIV-1 infected individuals.
</p>
