<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0300">
 <list list-type="simple" id="lis0025">
  <list-item id="lsti0050">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="par0305">Inhibitors of flaviviral proteases, such as the dengue virus NS3, block replication without causing cellular toxicity, suggesting that they are specific for the viral target (
    <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">Lescar et al., 2008</xref>). The small-molecule BILN 2061, which binds to the active site of the hepatitis C virus NS3, was effective in reducing viral load in patients (
    <xref rid="bib0340" ref-type="bibr">Lamarre et al., 2003</xref>). Although its development was halted by evidence of cardiotoxicity, this would not necessarily prevent the compound from being used at low dosage as an imaging probe.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0055">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="par0310">Drugs that directly inhibit the virus-encoded methyltransferase are currently under development for dengue, West Nile and other flaviviruses (
    <xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">Dong et al., 2008</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0060">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="par0315">Non-nucleoside molecules have been identified that inhibit the RNA-dependent RNA polymerase of bovine pestivirus (
    <xref rid="bib0410" ref-type="bibr">Paeshuyse et al., 2009</xref>). Others are now under evaluation for the treatment of hepatitis C.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0065">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="par0320">The C-terminal portion of the flavivirus NS3 molecules is a helicase, which is essential for replication. Inhibitors have been identified for hepatitis C and other flaviviruses (
    <xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">Leyssen et al., 2008</xref>, 
    <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">Lescar et al., 2008</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0070">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="par0325">The hepatitis C virion surface glycoproteins E1 and E2 are expressed on the surface of infected cells, making them potential targets for antibody-dependent cellular cytotoxicity and for imaging by a radiolabeled antibody fragment or a labeled DNA aptamer (
    <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">Drummer et al., 2003</xref>, 
    <xref rid="bib0405" ref-type="bibr">Nattermann et al., 2005</xref>, 
    <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2009a</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
