<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The treatment of chronic HCV infection began with the administration of interferon (INF) mono therapy, and until a few years ago the recommended therapy available for HCV treatment was pegylated-interferon (PEG-IFN) alpha, plus ribavirin (RBV) with an administration of about 24 weeks (genotypes 2–3) or 48 weeks (genotype 1) (Reddy et al., 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Li et al., 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Inati et al., 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Ricchi et al., 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Aminizadeh et al., 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Risoluti et al., 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2016a</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Catauro et al., 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). This treatment produced important side effects, such as irritation at the injection site, febrile influenza-like manifestations, mental disorders, thyropathy, neutropenia, and hemolytic anemia. Eradication of the infection did not reach the expected results, due to the presence of subjects who did not respond to therapy or developed recurrences. Infection is assumed eradicated when there is a sustained virological response (SVR), defined as the lack of HCV RNA in serum by a sensitive test performed 24 weeks after completion of antiviral therapy. PEG-IFN plus RBV obtained SVR rates of 25–64% in patients with thalassemia and HCV infection (Inati et al., 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Harmatz et al., 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Di Marco et al., 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), and demonstrated an improvement of patient survival due to a reduction in the risk of cirrhosis and hepatocellular carcinoma (Ray and Thomas, 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). However, this treatment was not well-tolerated by thalassemic and SCD patients and the use has been severely reduced because ribavirin (RBV) proved to cause hemolytic anemia and to increase blood transfusions, in addition to interferon side effects, such as influenza-like symptoms, depression and cytopenias (Materazzi et al., 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2014a</xref>; Origa et al., 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Di Marco et al., 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Moon et al., 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). More recently, the use of Direct-acting Antiviral Agents (DAAs) demonstrated to be suitable in HCV management in patients with thalassemia and sickle cell disease for whom previous regimens gave restrictions (Materazzi et al., 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2017a</xref>; Di Marco et al., 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Moon et al., 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Origa et al., 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Premkumar et al., 
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Mehta et al., 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>).
</p>
