<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to the effects of bloodmeal conditions and mosquito behavior on vector competence assessments, environmental factors also have major impacts. The role of ambient temperature on both vector competence and vectorial capacity (e.g., survival, and adult density via the effect on larval development [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]), is well documented. For example, an analysis of field-derived 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> exposed to ZIKV and reared at 16 °C, 20 °C, 24 °C, 28 °C, 32 °C, 34 °C, 36 °C, or 38 °C ± 0.5 °C showed differences in infection, dissemination, and transmission rates [
 <xref rid="B130-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>]. Infection was least affected by temperature, with at least minimal rates observed at 16 °C (6%) and 38 °C (7%), with the highest efficiency in the 24–34 °C range (75–89%). Dissemination had a more limited optimal range with minimal efficiencies observed at 16–20 °C (3–4%) and 38 °C (5%), while maximum efficiency was observed between 28–34 °C (65–77%). Transmission capability demonstrated the narrowest range of efficiency with minimal rates observed between 16–24 °C (0–4%) and 36–38 °C (5–0.4%) and maximum efficiency within the 28–34 °C range (19–23%) [
 <xref rid="B130-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>]. Compared to ZIKV, CHIKV demonstrated an increased infectivity of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> Liverpool when mosquitoes were maintained at 18 °C compared to 28 °C, while YFV demonstrated increased infectivity in field-derived 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> when the mosquitoes were maintained at 18 °C compared to 28 °C [
 <xref rid="B159-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>]. Conversely, DENV-2 is more infectious for two populations of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> (Nairobi and Kilifi) when the mosquitoes are held at a higher temperature range (29–31 °C compared to 25–28 °C), although the effect is more pronounced in the Nairobi population [
 <xref rid="B160-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>], indicating the possibility that the effect exerted by temperature may interact with the mosquito population or possibly the viral strain as well [
 <xref rid="B161-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>]. These varied results underscore the difficulty in predicting precisely the effects of climate change on the vector competence of natural mosquito populations.
</p>
