<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Sex distribution was equal between the two groups (
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.250). In both groups the mixed breed was overrepresented. Besides furosemide and torasemide, other medications used to control the cardiac disease were comparable. At admission there was no difference between groups regarding age (
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.956), body weight (
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.543), left ventricular diastolic internal diameter normalized for body weight (LVIDDn) (
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.331), left atrial to aortic ratio (LA:Ao) (
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.959), tricuspid regurgitation peak velocity (
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.838), creatinine (
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.433) and potassium (
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.230) serum levels. There was no difference in prevalence of atrial fibrillation between groups (
 <italic>P</italic> = 1.000). The overall number of decompensations experienced by each dog was higher for the study group (4.4 ± 1.9) compared to the control group (2.9 ± 1) (
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.001). At last examination only LA:Ao was higher in the study group compared to controls (
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.035). The total maximal dose of furosemide was 6.1 ± 3 mg/kg/day for the study group and 5.6 ± 2.1 mg/kg/day for the control group (
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.475). While the initial dose of torasemide used was 0.7 ± 0.4 mg/kg/day. When comparing the first and last examinations within the two groups, body weight reduced in the study group (
 <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), while LA:Ao (P &lt; 0.001), and creatinine (P &lt; 0.001) increased. The number of decompensations recorded before (2.9 ± 1.1) and after (1.5 ± 1.5) torasemide initiation reduced significantly (
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.001). Within the control group only creatinine increased (
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.013). Thirty‐six dogs died of cardiac related causes. There was no difference in survival between the two groups (
 <italic>P</italic> = 0.413), with a median survival of 523 days for the study group and of 383 days for the control group.
</p>
