<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>EVs play a role in cell-to-cell communication by transferring biologically active molecules into target cells while regulating NASH pathogenesis and progression. The fatty liver disease-related liquid biomarkers are listed in 
 <xref rid="ijms-21-03732-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Macrophage activation and influx in the liver are important for the progression of NAFLD because hepatic macrophages promote NASH development via cytokines IL-1, IL-6, and TNFα [
 <xref rid="B67-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. A model comprising Mlk3−/− mice fed a diet that was high in fats and carbohydrates exhibited suppressed cytokine expression and macrophage infiltration compared to wild-type (WT) mice [
 <xref rid="B68-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. This indicates that non-parenchymal cells and infiltrated inflammatory cells are optional yet important sources of EVs that perpetuate liver injury. The TLR9 is facilitated by the chemotaxis of neutrophils and M1 macrophages—proves that TLR9 is a pro-inflammatory activator in NASH [
 <xref rid="B69-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. The production of Hep-EVs increases in hepatocytes treated with palmitic acid (PA), and hepatic stellate cells (HSCs) are stimulated when treated with exosomes from PA-treated hepatocytes in a cell culture model [
 <xref rid="B70-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Exosomes released by healthy or compromised hepatocytes and Hep-EVs are crucial in cell-to-cell communication, especially in hepatocytes and hepatocyte-to-HSC signaling. EVs derived from hepatocytes containing excessive levels of lipids promote liver fibrosis through pro-inflammation, which directly affects immune cells. Kornek et al. reported increased numbers of EVs derived from invariant natural killer T cells and CD14+ monocytes—which are associated with alanine transaminase (ALT)—in plasma samples from NAFLD patients [
 <xref rid="B32-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. There is an increase in inflammatory cell-derived Hep-EVs in NAFLD patients and in patients with either or both of alcohol-related cirrhosis and chronic hepatitis C-related cirrhosis [
 <xref rid="B32-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Immature myeloid cells (CD11b
 <sup>+</sup>, Ly6C
 <sup>hi</sup>, Ly6G
 <sup>-</sup>) have also been detected in a high-fat diet mouse model of NASH [
 <xref rid="B72-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Furthermore, mesenchymal stem cell (MSC)-derived EVs are linked to liver inflammation and NASH progress, and are associated with increased proinflammatory markers (TNF-α, IL-1β, IL-6, and IL-12) [
 <xref rid="B73-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Mouse obesity models have been used to demonstrate that levels of circulating adipocyte-derived microparticles are high in stressed adipocytes, which secrete chemoattraction “find-me” signals to recruit macrophages and monocytes [
 <xref rid="B74-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Notably, palmitate-stimulated EVs are enriched in ceramide (C16:0). EVs chemoattract macrophages via ceramide-derived sphingosine 1 phosphate (S1P), which leads to macrophage activation [
 <xref rid="B75-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. This result also indicated that the amino acid metabolomics also can be detected by the liquid biopsies and significantly associated with the progression of liver fibrosis [
 <xref rid="B76-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. To date, the literature indicates that the EVs secreted by various cells play a crucial role in inflammatory regulation in advanced steatosis. However, the major components of EVs that are involved in cell or cytokine activation require further investigation. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-21-03732-f002">Figure 2</xref> is an illustration of the NAFLD/NASH effects on the liver driven by lipid accumulation and their effects.
</p>
