<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>These data, coupled with the temporal increase in the number of small and larger clusters, confirms the role of undiagnosed, recently infected individuals in fuelling of the current HIV epidemics in Poland, similarly to Canada, UK, Netherlands or France [
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Our study is expanding the evidence on the enlarging MSM epidemics in Poland with the increasing importance of transmission networks and shows that current molecular dynamics of HIV spread reflects that of the West-European countries. One of the consequences of expanding transmission networks may be the increase in frequency of primary drug resistance [
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], however, we have shown previously that trends in drug resistance were stable over time, with infrequent transmission within clusters and median prevalence of 8.3% [
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Given the fact that estimated tMRCA infection times are within the timeframe of increased frequency of sexually-driven HIV infections observed over the last 10 years we suggest that clustered transmissions may significantly contribute to the current increase in the prevalence of HIV in Poland. These data are relevant for the design of prophylactic interventions and emphasize the need for prevention programs to focus on early detection and treatment among MSMs as it may reduce the frequency of onward transmissions within the networks [
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Of note, prevention campaigns targeted to MSM in Poland are currently limited to anonymous counseling and testing, with no pre-exposure prophylaxis available. Scarce programs such as "Test and Keep in care"–program targeted at identification and referral to care for the newly diagnosed patients—do not seem sufficient as testing rates among populations at risk remain low [
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. The strategy should be "Seek, Test, Link, Treat, and Retain” as suggested by Hull at al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0172473.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] and may be implemented across all populations, not only MSM.
</p>
