<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ferrets are widely used animal models of human influenza, justified by the similar distribution of SA receptors in the upper respiratory tract to humans. They also exhibit similar clinical signs when infected with influenza [
 <xref rid="B76-viruses-12-00673" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>,
 <xref rid="B77-viruses-12-00673" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,
 <xref rid="B78-viruses-12-00673" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,
 <xref rid="B79-viruses-12-00673" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Unlike for other zoonotic avian influenza subtypes, such as H5N1 [
 <xref rid="B80-viruses-12-00673" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>], formal risk assessments based on ferret experimentation are not publicly available for H6Nx viruses. However, several ferret experiments for H6Nx infections have been conducted. In China, in recent years, frequent reassortments between influenza A(H1N1)pdm09 and other endemic SIVs have been observed. The internal genes of the influenza A(H1N1) pdm09 virus, which is prevalent in swine worldwide, increases the replication efficiency of H6N6 IAV in the lower respiratory tract of ferrets but not its transmissibility between ferrets. Experiments have shown that the virus has limited transmissibility through direct contact or through inhalation of infectious aerosolised droplets [
 <xref rid="B81-viruses-12-00673" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. The aims of the study conducted by Sun et al. were to understand the impacts of mutations in HA of the endemic H6N6 virus on its receptor-binding properties and also to assess the transmission potential and potential risks posed by reassortants of H6N6 with the A(H1N1)pdm09 virus. Such reassortants have the potential to emerge naturally due to both viruses currently circulating in the swine population [
 <xref rid="B82-viruses-12-00673" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. These findings suggest H6N6 swine IAV (SIV) currently poses a moderate risk to public health, but its evolution and spread should be closely monitored.
</p>
