<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Lancet Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Lancet Public Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Lancet. Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2468-2667</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7252171</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2468-2667(20)30112-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2468-2667(20)30112-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>COVID-19: a public health approach to manage domestic violence is needed</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au10"><name><surname>Chandan</surname><given-names>Joht Singh</given-names></name><email>joht.chandan@nhs.net</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au20"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>Julie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au30"><name><surname>Bradbury-Jones</surname><given-names>Caroline</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au40"><name><surname>Nirantharakumar</surname><given-names>Krishnarajah</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au50"><name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>Eddie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au60"><name><surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname><given-names>Siddhartha</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>College of Medical and Dental Sciences, University of Birmingham, Birmingham B15 2TT, UK</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Centre for Crime, Justice, and Policing, University of Birmingham, Birmingham B15 2TT, UK</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>College of Social Sciences, University of Birmingham, Birmingham B15 2TT, UK</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Institute for Global Innovation, University of Birmingham, Birmingham B15 2TT, UK</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Centre for Health and Justice, University of Nottingham, Nottingham, UK</aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e309</fpage><lpage>e309</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an Open Access article under the CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 license</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p id="para10">The negative consequential effects of the measures adopted by the UK and other countries to tackle the spread of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) on society are beginning to unfold. An area of concern is the impending crisis of domestic violence&#x02014;gender-based violence and child abuse and neglect, due to movement restrictions, loss of income, isolation, overcrowding, and stress and anxiety, all which put women and children at a disproportionally increased risk of harm.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> This increased risk is not surprising. Previous epidemics, such as the Ebola virus disease outbreak in west Africa,<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> but also cholera and Zika virus disease outbreaks, led to regional environments where domestic violence became more prevalent; there were reductions in funding for specialist gender-based violence public health services; and, for survivors of gender-based violence, there was reduced access to health-care services. Although we are not aware of published studies to date that have tracked the national trends in gender-based violence related to COVID-19, initial reports from UK support services such as the National Domestic Abuse helpline have already shown increases in service use, a pattern seen elsewhere (with notable examples in China, Spain, and France).<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</p><p id="para20">In the UK, before the coronavirus crisis, gender-based violence was already deemed as highly prevalent, associated with substantial negative downstream social, psychological, and physical outcomes.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> Therefore, any resultant increases in the rates of domestic violence would not only be a further travesty of human rights but also be associated with further long-term costs to society, which might be irreparable beyond the immediate threat of COVID-19. It has never been more important than now to implement a public health approach to gender-based violence in the UK.</p><p id="para30">Similar to an approach that has been put in use to improve the management of physical violence in cities such as Cardiff, Glasgow, and London, the principles of a public health approach should be implemented to support survivors of gender-based violence. The WHO public health approach consists of four steps, which we have suggested the adaptation of to aid in the prevention of domestic violence during this pandemic (<xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">appendix</xref>).<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>
</p><p id="para40">Without adequate surveillance, it is not possible to capture the burden of domestic violence during this pandemic. Because of selection biases, administrative datasets have consistently shown underestimates in the expected rates of domestic violence.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> Potential approaches to improve the surveillance of domestic violence could include the routine inquiry (feasibly integrated into remote primary care consultations or active syndromic surveillance from local health protection teams) and the urgent implementation of linked datasets between police and health records datasets to identify individuals at risk. Enhancing surveillance would also provide the opportunity to offer targeted support and interventions. Though formal evaluations of current interventions have not yet taken place during the pandemic, national charities (such as, but not limited to, Women's Aid, Safelives, and the National Society for the Prevention of Cruelty against Children) have produced guidance for how survivors can both report violence, abuse, and neglect and keep themselves safe, including information on remote reporting and support mechanisms.</p><p id="para50">There are substantial gaps in the literature relating to the surveillance and evaluation of effective interventions to support those at risk of domestic violence, child abuse and neglect during this pandemic. The medical profession has a duty to provide support in overcoming these problems&#x02014;to provide a public health approach to supporting those most vulnerable in society.</p></body><back><ref-list id="bibl10"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>WHO</collab></person-group><article-title>Joint Leader's statement - Violence against children: a hidden crisis of the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/08-04-2020-joint-leader-s-statement---violence-against-children-a-hidden-crisis-of-the-covid-19-pandemic" id="interrefs10">https://www.who.int/news-room/detail/08-04-2020-joint-leader-s-statement---violence-against-children-a-hidden-crisis-of-the-covid-19-pandemic</ext-link><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>International Rescue Committee</collab></person-group><chapter-title>Everything on her shoulders: rapid assessment on gender and violence against women and girls in the Ebola outbreak in Beni</chapter-title><year>March 15, 2019</year><publisher-name>DRC</publisher-name><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.rescue.org/report/everything-her-shoulders-rapid-assessment-gender-and-violence-against-women-and-girls-ebola" id="interrefs20">https://www.rescue.org/report/everything-her-shoulders-rapid-assessment-gender-and-violence-against-women-and-girls-ebola</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taub</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>A new COVID-19 crisis: Domestic abuse rises worldwide</chapter-title><year>April 6, 2020</year><publisher-name>The New York Times</publisher-name><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/06/world/coronavirus-domestic-violence.html" id="interrefs30">https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/06/world/coronavirus-domestic-violence.html</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandan</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gokhale</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nirantharakumar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The burden of mental ill health associated with childhood maltreatment in the UK, using The Health Improvement Network database: a population-based retrospective cohort study</article-title><source>Lancet Psychiatry</source><volume>6</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>926</fpage><lpage>934</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31564467</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Violence Prevention Alliance</collab></person-group><chapter-title>The public health approach</chapter-title><year>2011</year><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/violenceprevention/approach/public_health/en/" id="interrefs40">https://www.who.int/violenceprevention/approach/public_health/en/</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref60"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Everson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussey</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Concordance between adolescent reports of childhood abuse and child protective service determinations in an at-risk sample of young adolescents</article-title><source>Child Maltreat</source><volume>13</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18174345</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="sec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p id="para70">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ecomp10"><caption><title>Supplementary appendix</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.pdf"/></supplementary-material>
</p></sec><ack><p>KN reports grants from the Medical Research Council, the National Institute for Health Research, Health Data Research UK, AstraZeneca, and College of Policing; and personal fees from Merck Sharp &#x00026; Dohme and Sanofi, outside the submitted work. All other authors declare no competing interests.</p></ack></back></article>