<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0045">The majority of available studies concerning the presistance of 
 <italic>Coronavirus</italic> species in animated environments and surfaces were conducted on a surrogate human 
 <italic>Coronavirus</italic> strain, HCoV-229E (
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kampf et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization, 2020a</xref>): on different surfaces of various materials, such as plastic, metal, or glass, the virus is able to survive from 2 h to 9 days. Temperatures ranging from 30 °C to 40 °C are able to substantially reduce the persistance of highly pathogenic viruses, such as the Middle East Respiratory Syndrome 
 <italic>Coronavirus</italic> (MERS-CoV), the Transmissible Gastroenteritis Virus (TGEV) and the Mouse Hepatitis Virus (MHV). A higher viral load of SARS-CoV is capable to survive for longer time. The same study demonstrated, using carrier tests, that the HCoV-229E is effectively inactivated in 1 min on stainless steel, employing the most common biocides, such as ethanol 70% w/v or 0.1% sodium hypochlorite (
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kampf et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization, 2020a</xref>). Studies aimed to verify the survival of SARS-CoV, sharing high phylogenetic similarities with SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Forster et al., 2020</xref>), showed the survival of a 10
 <sup>5</sup> viral titre of the pathogen on aluminium, plastic, metal, wood, and paper, of 4–5 days at room temperature (
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kampf et al., 2020</xref>). The main results of the researches conducted on SARS-CoV-2 surrogate strains (SARS-CoV, and H–CoV-229) are showed in 
 <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. The COVID-19 is caused by SARS-CoV-2: recent researches supposed that the probable ecological reservoirs could be the bats, which allegedly transmitted the virus to humans through an intermediate host. Based on previous epidemics from the past 20 years, caused by species from 
 <italic>Coronavirus</italic> genus, such as the Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS) and the Middle East respiratory Syndrome (MERS), cases of viral infection transmission through food were never registered, and, until now, no SARS-CoV-2 infections transmitted via food were reported: studies in progress aim to evaluate the mode and time of survival of the virus in food matrices. For examples, it has been demonstrated that, at 4 °C, MERS-CoV is able to survive up to 72 h in food (
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization, 2020b</xref>). A study conducted in 2013 regarding the survival of human 
 <italic>Coronavirus</italic> 229E (H–CoV 229E) in different food matrices (fruit and vegetables) describes the lower persistance of the virus on lettuce stored at 4 °C, compared to 
 <italic>Poliovirus</italic> 1 (PV-1). In particular, H–CoV 229E on lettuce registered a log
 <sub>10</sub> reduction &gt;1.31 after 8 days, with respects to the 0.36 log
 <sub>10</sub> reduction of 
 <italic>Poliovirus</italic> 1. H–CoV 229E was not detectable on lettuce samples after 4 days of storage and no viral loads were detected after spiking H–CoV 229E on strawberries samples (
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Yepiz-Gomez et al., 2013</xref>). It is needed to specify that the starting viral loads from the 3 pathogens were different: in fact the overall recovery of H–CoV 229E on lettuce, at the time of virus spiking, resulted lower (3.99 ± 0.25 log
 <sub>10</sub>), compared to 
 <italic>Poliovirus</italic> 1 (7.14 ± 0.10 log
 <sub>10</sub>) and 
 <italic>Adenovirus</italic> 2 (9.15 ± 0.19 log
 <sub>10</sub>) (
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Yepiz-Gomez et al., 2013</xref>). It may be therefore possible that the faster die-off of H–CoV 229E could be linked to the lower viral load, in spite of 
 <italic>Poliovirus</italic> 1 
 <italic>Adenovirus</italic> 2, whose loads were respectively 3 and 5 log
 <sub>10</sub> higher. The recent evidences regarding monitorings conducted on further 
 <italic>Coronavirus</italic> strains demonstrate that, although these pathogens result stable at low temperatures for a defined period of time, the application of the proper measures to ensure food hygiene and safety are able to prevent the virus shedding. In particular, species from 
 <italic>Coronavirus</italic> genus are thermolabile, thus susceptible to traditional heat treatments (e.g., 70 °C cooking): it would be indeed sufficient avoiding to consume uncooked food of animal origin. It is furthermore important to underline that SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV in general are extremely susceptible to detergency and disinfecting treatments, and there are not evidences showing higher resistance of SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organzation, 2020b</xref>), allowing to consider appropriate the periodic cleaning of surfaces, and the sanitation of food, employing food-contact approved disinfecting agents (e.g., sodium hypochlorite, and hydrogen peroxide).
</p>
