<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0095">Convalescent plasma has also been used as a last resort to improve the survival rate of patients with various viral infections, such as SARS, H
 <sub>5</sub>N
 <sub>1</sub> avian influenza, pandemic 2009 influenza A H
 <sub>1</sub>N
 <sub>1</sub> (H
 <sub>1</sub>N
 <sub>1</sub> pdm09), and severe Ebola virus infection.
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>55</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>56</sup>
 </xref> One possible explanation for the efficacy of convalescent plasma therapy is that the immunoglobulin antibodies in the plasma of patients recovering from viral infection might suppress viremia. Shen et al. (2020) reported on five critically ill patients with laboratory-confirmed COVID-19 and acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) who received transfusion with convalescent plasma with a SARS-CoV-2–specific antibody (binding titer &gt;1:1000 and neutralization titer &gt;40). The convalescent plasma was obtained from 5 patients who recovered from COVID-19 and it was administered to the five enrolled patients between 10 and 22 days after admission. Antiviral agents and methylprednisolone were also administered. Following plasma transfusions, improvements in clinical condition were observed, including normalization of body temperature within 3 days (in 4/5 patients), decrease in Sequential Organ Failure Assessment score, rise in PaO
 <sub>2</sub>/FiO
 <sub>2</sub>, resolution of ARDS (4 patients at 12 days after transfusion), a success of weaning from mechanical ventilation (3 patients within 2 weeks of treatment), and decline in viral loads (became negative within 12 days) and increase in SARS-CoV-2–specific ELISA and neutralizing antibody titers. Of the 5 patients, 3 were discharged from the hospital (lengths of stay: 53, 51, and 55 days), while 2 were in stable condition at 37 days after transfusions.
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>56</sup>
 </xref> The authors concluded that use of convalescent plasma transfusion is beneficial among patients infected with SARS-CoV-2, even though the sample number in this study is small.
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>56</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
