<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10">Since 2008, HFMD has regularly captured wide attention owing to both its high incidence and potential health hazards for millions of children, along with substantial losses to economy every year in mainland China
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. It is imperative that specific control and intervention planning be introduced and set by the related public health agencies to handle such a wide-ranging issue. However, vital to any initiation planning of HFMD is an accurate prediction of its future temporal patterns. Early detection of HFMD epidemics based on models such as SARIMA and NAR has been a profitable technology for facilitating prevention strategies more effectively
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, in view of the LSTM model’s flexible capacity to learn what to store and what to abandon during information-processing
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup>, to the best of our knowledge, this attempt is the first using an LSTM approach to model the long trajectory behaviors of HFMD incidence in mainland China. Our results imply that the LSTM method has the potential to obtain a clearer perspective of epidemic trends than the SARIMA and NAR models built on the specified predictive horizons. Notably, the LSTM method can make the outcome measurements of MAE, MAPE and RMSE markedly drop by 31.993%, 30.182% and 39.154%, respectively, in the training dataset, and can make their counterparts in the testing dataset decrease by 21.883%, 28.415% and 16.607%, respectively, compared to the SARIMA model. In contrast to the NAR model, the decreased percentages in the training subset for the three indices listed above are 0.310%, 29.091% and 13.001%, respectively, and their counterparts in the testing subset are 69.035%, 30.328% and 128.304%, respectively. Likewise, according to Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>, it was found that the upward or downward trend simulated and forecasted by the LSTM model provides a more reasonable approximation to the reported points, especially for the identification of high incidence peaks, indicating that the LSTM model can adequately capture the essence of the dependence hidden behind the notified case series of HFMD. Similarly, in the two datasets used to account for the uncertainty in the model, the accuracy measurement indices in the LSTM approach also display the lowest error rates among these chosen, optimal methods, particularly in the 18-step ahead predictions, and the performances are as good as can be expected. The scale-dependent measure of MAE showed a lower value in the simulated stage of the NAR method than in the LSTM technique in the 6-step predictions; this result mainly arises from the fact that there are several simulated values that are far away from the observed values. Moreover, it was confirmed that the NAR model is effective in capturing the short-term dynamics of the data. In short, in comparison with the SARIMA and NAR models, the established LSTM approach not only can better explain the seasonal and trend characteristics of HFMD but also is robust with respect to medium-term and long-term forecasts. Apparently, this network can act as an effective tool for recognizing the temporal levels of HFMD incident cases in mainland China in upcoming years. Similar to the recent literature, which has also found that the LSTM method provides good forecasting power for air pollutant concentrations
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>, financial time series
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup> and harmful algal blooms in rivers
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>. From this point of view, our LSTM technique appears to be worthy of being popularized for forecasting the incidence case series of HFMD in other settings in China and even a wide range of simulation applications, such as for all types of contagious diseases or in all time series analyses; however, this conclusion requires further verification. It should, however, be noted that with the increasing development of hybrid techniques, numerous combined methods incorporating linear approaches such as the SARIMA method
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>, the gray GM(1,1) model
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup>, the error-trend-seasonal model
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup> and the exponential smoothing model
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup> and nonlinear techniques such as the back propagation neural network approach
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>, the generalized regression neural network method
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup> and the radical basis function technique
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup> have already been adopted to serve as early warning tools for infectious diseases, and most have obtained satisfactory results. Consequently, much work will be required to explore the preferred models for detecting and analyzing HFMD morbidity cases in mainland China. In addition, in terms of the modeling measures (MAE, MAPE and RMSE), we found that the simulating and forecasting efficacies of the NAR method were slightly superior to the SARIMA method in the short-term (6-step) predictions, which is consistent with the earlier studies performed by Zhou 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>, yet is incongruous with the study involving modeling the prevalence of schistosomiasis in Qianjiang
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>; in the medium-term (12-step) and long-term (18-step) prediction stages, the NAR method underperforms the SARIMA model in the testing dataset, but this result is not in line with previous work predicting the morbidity of hemorrhagic fever with renal syndrome
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup> and the daily number of new admission inpatients
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>. It seems possible that these contrasting results are due to the following: the various characteristics of infectious diseases from different regions and the NAR approach suffer from overfitting, which is a defect inherent in the ANN methods. However, during MATLAB training, a default technique of early stopping was adopted to improve generalization and avoid overfitting. Therefore, being further suggestive of the necessity of constructing forecasting techniques for different infectious diseases in various settings and at different time periods, it is superior to the NAR technique in short-term forecasting.
</p>
