<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">It is well established that accurate identification of high-risk seasonality plays a pivotal role in timely implementation of prevention strategies and the reasonable allocation of resources for HFMD
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup>. In our report, HFMD could occur throughout the year, and larger epidemics could be regularly found every 2 to 3 years. Similar trajectory behaviors were also reported in the studies involved in the regions of Vietnam
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>, Malaysia
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup>, Hong Kong
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>, Taiwan
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup> and Singapore
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>, but the underlying drivers fail to be fully elucidated. In our study, evident seasonal and cyclical components were observed with the aid of the HP method; for example, every year from April until July, there was peak activity accounting for 59.581% of all notified cases, among which May and June were of particular concern, as they accounted for 60.952% of cases occurring in high-risk seasons. However, between January and February annually, there was a dramatic decline in the reported cases. A similar seasonal distribution was also revealed in recent years in other countries, including Singapore
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>, Malaysia
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup> and most regions of China
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup>, containing Hong Kong, Taiwan, Shenzhen, Ningbo, Shandong, Zunyi, Guangdong and Guangzhou
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup>. Moreover, outbreaks commonly occurred during the 4 months as well
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup>. Additionally, two peaks could be noted in our data from June 2008 to June 2018, the first and stronger peak primarily occurred during the high-risk season, and the weaker peak was chiefly observed from August to November annually; the appearance of the two peaks was also reported in another study of southern China
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup>. This seasonal pattern is consistent with that of Hong Kong
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>, Taiwan
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup> and Vietnam
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>
 </sup>. The single peak was customarily observed in northern China
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>, and earlier studies on the temporal characteristics of HFMD in Japan
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>
 </sup> and Malaysia
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup> matched that in northern China. This may be pertinent to the different viruses, geographical differences or changing risk (e.g., school attendance, temperature, humidity or other meteorological drivers). Furthermore, in studies of particular regions of China, the leading agents (EV71 and CVA16) are also distributed in various peaks
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>, where the pathogenic agent EV71 is predominant in the stronger peak months. By contrast, CVA16 is more inclined to circulate in the more vulnerable population. These two etiologic factors are notably attenuated in January and February. Regarding the seasonal variations, climatic factors are possibly responsible for such a discrepancy (e.g., the ability of the causative agents to survive outside the host, the variability in the behavior and immune level of the host by climatic factors, and the inclination of people to go outdoors in summer rather than in winter increases the chances of person-to-person contact causing the etiologic agents to more easily achieve transmission among humans by virtue of spreading-factors)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
