<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0130">Among the many molecules synthesized and tested by the DeGrado group, compounds 
 <bold>3</bold> and 
 <bold>4</bold> emerged as the first promising candidates of M2 Ser31Asn inhibition. TEVC experiments revealed 50% inhibitory concentration (IC
 <sub>50</sub>) values of 14 and 16 μM for 
 <bold>3</bold> and 
 <bold>4</bold>, respectively, against the Ser31Asn form of M2, which was comparable to amantadine's inhibition of WT M2 in the authors' hands (16 μM; 
 <xref rid="bib142" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2013a</xref>). Moreover, compound 
 <bold>4</bold> bound to Ser31Asn M2 with such high affinity that structure determination by solution NMR was possible. In their structure model (PDB: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="pdb:2LY0" id="intref0055" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">2LY0</ext-link>), 
 <bold>4</bold> was found to be clamped between the side chains of three Asn31 residues while having its amine group pointing towards the M2 N-terminus (
 <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>B). The adamantane cage fit within the hydrophobic pocket between Asn31 and Gly34, and the positively charged ammonium group of the adamantane formed hydrogen bonds via water molecules with two asparagines, while the third asparagine and the nitrogen of isoxazole of 
 <bold>4</bold> formed a bidentate interaction. The side-chain carbonyl of Asn received a hydrogen bond from the ammonium group, and the carboxamide of the same Asn donated a hydrogen bond to the endocyclic nitrogen of isoxazole. On the other end of compound 
 <bold>5</bold>, the thiophene moiety sit against four methyl groups of Val27 and was stabilized by hydrophobic interactions. Notably, this distal hydrophobic group could be substituted by other similar moieties such as benzene (
 <bold>3</bold>) and cyclopropane (
 <bold>5</bold>) without substantially compromising efficacy. Molecular dynamics experiments also supported the potential drug-protein interactions observed in NMR experiments. Numerous additional inhibitors of M2 Ser31Asn have since been reported by the DeGrado and Wang laboratories: for example, compound 
 <bold>6</bold> inhibited 74.4% of M2 Ser31Asn activity by TEVC and virus replication with a 50% effective concentration (EC
 <sub>50</sub>) of 1.7 μM (
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2016a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">2016b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) in PRA. Notably, compound 
 <bold>6</bold> also inhibited 12% of WT M2 channel activity by TEVC at 100 μM (
 <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2016a</xref>).
</p>
