<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Virus isolates sequenced in our analysis were derived from a wide range of mosquito vector species. RRV is a vector generalist and has been isolated from over 40 unique species of mosquito across Australia (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). The diverse climates, landscapes, and weather patterns among the southern, central, and northern regions of Western Australia result in different mosquito breeding conditions and species distributions. For example, in the tropical northern regions of WA, where freshwater breeding sites associated with floodplains are plentiful, 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">Culex annulirostris</named-content> is generally the dominant vector species. In the south, specifically along the Swan Coastal plan, saltwater marsh mosquitoes such as 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">Aedes vigilax</named-content> and 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">Aedes camptorhynchus</named-content> dominate (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). In general, a greater diversity of mosquito species is observed in WA’s north than in the south. The genetic diversity among the distinct RRV genotypes characterized in this study may have some impact on vector competence, and it is possible that mosquito ecology may potentially influence the distribution and evolution of RRV in WA. Our preliminary analysis has not identified any unique or characteristic genetic features that are shared among viruses derived from specific mosquito species, but this will be investigated further in the future. The northern G2A lineage was observed in our study to be more genetically diverse than the southern G2B lineage. Genetic diversity of G2A may be driven by the greater diversity of mosquito species present in the north or potentially by the likely greater transmission that occurs among potentially larger populations of amplifying hosts in the state’s rural north. Long-term endemicity of G2A in the state’s north may also explain the genetic variability between isolates. The near identical clusters of sequences sampled in the south may indicate continual seeding of virus from other locations, possibly, the north of WA or interstate.
</p>
