<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As for host susceptibility, environmental conditions can impact the host immune response and increase cells' susceptibility to infection [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007327.ref082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>] or pose seasonal challenges (such as food limitations) that leave hosts vulnerable to infection or pathology [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007327.ref083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>], which has been proposed to influence disease progression in individuals infected with HIV [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007327.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. For directly transmitted infections, environmental conditions can be major drivers of cycles in incidence, with influenza and cholera transmission being notable examples (e.g., see [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007327.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1007327.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]). The effects of climate on flu transmission have been studied using population-level data coupled with transmission models, as well as empirical animal studies [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007327.ref084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>], to demonstrate the effects of temperature and humidity on transmission. Although climate conditions undoubtedly play a direct role in several directly transmitted infections, they may play a more nuanced role in vector-borne disease systems in which they modulate vector population dynamics and subsequently disease transmission. For example, in the case of African sleeping sickness (
 <xref rid="ppat.1007327.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), the rainy season is hypothesized to modify tsetse fly distribution, which results in changes in human–tsetse fly contact and subsequently African sleeping sickness incidence; in this case, we can classify the seasonal driver as (1) vector seasonality alone or as (2) seasonal climate influencing vector seasonality and vector seasonality having a downstream effect on seasonal exposure. Abiotic and biotic seasonal drivers are therefore interconnected and not mutually exclusive.
</p>
