<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While AIV primarily infect gastrointestinal epithelial cells of aquatic birds, human influenza viruses primarily infect respiratory epithelial cells. In these studies, we used fully differentiated NHBE cells which closely emulate the human upper respiratory tract epithelium 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Rose1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. NHBE cell cultures are recognized as a good 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> correlate to evaluate respiratory virus infection and the host response to infection 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Kogure1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Ilyushina1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Oshansky1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. HA receptors on human influenza viruses have a preference for cell surface glycans terminating in sias linked to galactose by an α2,6 linkage 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Shinya1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Plant lectins have been used to detect α2,3 or α2,6 linkages, which specifically bind to glycolipids and glycoproteins containing sia α2,6 or α2,3 configurations. These sias are expressed on respiratory epithelial cells lining the respiratory tract, e.g. nasal mucosa, trachea, bronchi, bronchioles, and alveoli; however, their abundance varies by tissue location 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Shinya1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref> and, at least in culture, by cellular differentiation status 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Chan1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. In the tracheal-bronchial tree, human influenza viruses attach predominantly to ciliated epithelial cells 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Shinya1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Thompson1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Nicholls2" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Matrosovich3" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, but the virus may also attach to non-ciliated cells 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Matrosovich2" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Thompson1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Tateno1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. At least one explanation for these differences is the MAA preparation used to stain for sias. MAAI and MAAII are both isoforms derived from 
 <italic>Maackia amurensis</italic>, however, MAAI has a greater affinity for SAα2-3Galβ1–4GlcNAc and MAAII has greater affinity for SAα2-3Galβ1–3GalNAc 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Knibbs1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Konami1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Imberty1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. Binding profiles also showed that MAAI binds to non-sialic acid-containing residues 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Nicholls2" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>.
</p>
