<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The characteristic indications of uncomplicated influenza infection are often nasal obstruction, cough, sore throat, headache, fever, and myalgia which are due to cellular damage at the site of virus replication, and to the cytokines, chemokines, and other inflammatory mediators expressed at the sites of infection 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Hayden1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. Studies of humans infected with highly pathogenic H5N1 virus who had severe disease showed that these individuals also had high serum levels of IP-10 and monokine-induced by IFNγ (MIG) 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Peiris1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, and H5N1 viruses induced higher levels of TNFα and IP-10 in human macrophages compared to H1N1 viruses 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Cheung1" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>. Furthermore, H5N1 virus has been shown to induce IP-10, IFNβ, RANTES and IL-6 mRNA in human primary alveolar type II epithelial and NHBE cells 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Chan2" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>. Interestingly, a recent study showed that viruses with a predilection for sia α2,3 induced higher levels of proinflammatory cytokines than viruses with sia α2,6 binding specificity 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Ramos1" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>, and studies with Calu-3 cells (derived from human bronchial epithelium) have shown that H5N1 infection results in a weak anti-viral response characterized by little interferon regulatory factor (IRF)-3 nuclear accumulation, reduced IFNβ production and limited interferon stimulated gene (ISG) induction compared to H3N2 infection 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Zeng1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. In accordance with a recent study that showed robust induction of IP-10, RANTES, and IL-6 production following infection with HPAI H5N1 in alveolar epithelial cells 
 <xref rid="pone.0021183-Chan3" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>, we show in this study that fully differentiated NHBE cells infected with LPAI H5N1, H5N2 and H5N3 induce robust IP-10 and RANTES responses early during infection compared to human H3N2 infection. Moreover, our results show that the origin of the virus isolates e.g. wild bird vs. poultry, or AIV vs. human, differentially affects chemokine expression. NHBE cells infected with H5N2 and H5N3 viruses of chicken origin induced a more potent chemokine response than H5N1 isolated from a mute swan, where for example, apical IP-10 expression was differentially induced by AIV infection. Similarly, NHBE cells infected with A/NY expressed low levels of apical IP-10 relative to AIV infection. Of note, NHBE cells infected with AIV significantly inhibited basolateral MCP-1 secretion relative to mock-infected NHBE cells. Taken together, these findings indicate that human and AIV induce different patterns of chemokine expression following infection of fully differentiated NHBE cells, suggesting that this may contribute to differences in disease pathogenesis between avian and human influenza virus infections in humans.
</p>
