<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Medications for treatment of opioid use disorder (MOUDs, which is now the preferred term to medication-assisted therapy) are recognized as the most effective treatments for OUD [
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. There are 3 Food and Drug Administration-approved MOUDs—methadone, buprenorphine, and extended-release naltrexone (XR-NTX). Methadone is a full opioid agonist and buprenorphine is a partial opioid agonist, while XR-NTX is an opioid antagonist. All are successful in treating OUD and in decreasing mortality. All reduce illicit opioid use, opioid craving, overdose, and HIV and HCV transmission [
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]; and buprenorphine and XR-NTX also improve HIV viral suppression in people living with HIV, the gold standard of care in treatment of HIV that is associated with reduced mortality and reduced transmission [
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Of the 3 MOUDs, access to methadone and buprenorphine are limited by regulations. Prescribing requires special training outside postgraduate programs and either a waiver from the Drug Enforcement Agency in the case of buprenorphine or treatment in a federally certified opioid treatment program in the case of methadone. Unfortunately, many clinical settings lack physicians trained in OUD treatment. Only about 5% of the nation’s physicians have waivers to prescribe buprenorphine and most substance use treatment programs do not have opioid treatment programs, which makes methadone treatment challenging to obtain [
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Therefore, the prevailing care for these patients typically consists of withdrawal management or detoxification and referral to outpatient resources for follow-up treatment. This asks patients with severe OUD to tolerate withdrawal symptoms, risking premature exit from hospital, and relapse to opioid use after failure to connect with OUD treatment referrals. Such inadequate care results in prolonged hospitalizations due to concern about relapse and nonadherence if patients leave the hospital, readmissions after OUD relapse, and, if concomitant infection is present, lack of antibiotic adherence and reinfection. Ultimately, this cycle leads to poor clinical outcomes, high health care costs, and excess deaths. Infectious disease specialists are at the frontlines in many hospitals treating infectious diseases in people who use drugs and have an opportunity to screen and treat co-occurring SUDs.
</p>
