<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Similar studies need to be carried out now on all subtypes of pandemic potential. However, we cannot do so without choosing priorities, given restrictions of time and resources. Choices must be made on the basis of historic and current observations. At one time, a closed, fixed cycle of type A subtypes was thought to exist, with one following the other, each producing a pandemic (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">
  <italic>5</italic>
 </xref>). This theory predated molecular analysis of the hemagglutinin of the viruses and was based as a classification system derived from their epidemiologic characteristics. As shown in the 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table</xref>, the concern that swine influenza would appear in 1976 was supported by seroarcheology, evidence in serum samples collected before, for example, 1968 that an A (H2) and A (H3) virus had previously circulated (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">
  <italic>6</italic>
 </xref>). Few currently believe this theory in its entirety, since it would require that a subtype remain undetected in a host, perhaps in humans, for a long period of time. However, the determination, using molecular techniques unavailable until well after the pandemics had occurred, that the A (H2N2) and A (H3N2) viruses were reassortants between previous human and avian strains suggested a different origin for these viruses (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">
  <italic>7</italic>
 </xref>
 <italic>,</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">
  <italic>8</italic>
 </xref>). The avian predecessors of these 2 new viruses were not highly pathogenic, and the resultant pandemics showed a typical U-shaped death rate, highest in the very young and old. The 1918 virus had a different derivation and was apparently not a reassortant but a mutant. It also had an avian origin, but the progenitor virus has not yet been identified, so its pathogenicity in birds is unknown (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">
  <italic>9</italic>
 </xref>). However, its epidemiologic signature in humans was high case fatality in young adults (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">
  <italic>10</italic>
 </xref>).
</p>
