<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our parameterization of the ratio 
 <italic>c</italic>/γ equaled the integral of the non-normalized HMTP curve describing the infectiousness of humans to mosquitoes over time [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005797.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], as noted in the section describing the generation interval. The parameter 
 <italic>b</italic> did not appear in our description of the generation interval, because it affects only the magnitude of transmission (i.e., 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub>) rather than its timing (i.e., generation interval). This parameter is poorly understood empirically, so we chose a value of 
 <italic>b</italic> = 0.4 consistent with a previous model [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005797.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. We described biting rate 
 <italic>a</italic> as a function of temperature 
 <italic>T</italic> (i.e., 
 <italic>a</italic>(
 <italic>T</italic>)) using two temperature-dependent estimates based on the average duration of the 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> gonotrophic cycle [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005797.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005797.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], similar to how gonotrophic period was incorporated into the generation interval. This process involved weighting the temperature-dependent length of the first cycle and the temperature-dependent length of each subsequent cycle based on the probability of the mosquito surviving to a given number of cycles (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0005797.s001">S1 Appendix</xref> for mathematical derivation). To capture one potential effect of temperature on the ratio of mosquitoes to humans 
 <italic>m</italic>, we assumed that 
 <italic>m</italic>(
 <italic>T</italic>) = λ / 
 <italic>μ</italic>(
 <italic>T</italic>) consistent with equilibrium assumptions of a mosquito population with adult mortality rate 
 <italic>μ</italic>(
 <italic>T</italic>) and constant parameter λ, which is the ratio of the daily rate of adult female mosquito emergence and the number of humans subject to feeding by the mosquitoes represented by 
 <italic>m</italic>(
 <italic>T</italic>) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005797.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Because values of λ are highly variable in space and time for reasons other than temperature variation, we examined the sensitivity of the value of λ across a range of values 0.0–0.5. We arrived at 0.5 as an upper limit for λ by dividing an upper limit for 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> based on independent estimates (maximum of 7.8 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005797.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]) by all other terms on the right-hand side of 
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pntd.0005797.e001">Eq 1</xref> (19.73 at 32.5°C). This is equivalent to assuming that one new adult female mosquito emerges from larval habitats every other day for each human at risk of biting within a given population.
</p>
