<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To account for uncertainty associated with values of 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> that we calculated, we generated 1,000 Monte Carlo samples from the uncertainty distributions of each model parameter as described in each of the references [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005797.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005797.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005797.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] in which those parameters were originally described. For 
 <italic>μ</italic>(
 <italic>T</italic>) and 
 <italic>n</italic>(
 <italic>T</italic>), we took random draws of their parameters consistent with published descriptions of uncertainty in the parameters of these functions from their original sources [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005797.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005797.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. For 
 <italic>a</italic>(
 <italic>T</italic>), we used nonlinear least-squares estimates of the first gonotrophic period’s 
 <italic>ρ</italic> parameter in the model by Focks et al. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005797.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] by refitting it to their data, resulting in mean 8.83x10
 <sup>-3</sup> and standard deviation 3.8x10
 <sup>-4</sup>. We assumed similar uncertainties (standard deviation) around the 
 <italic>ρ</italic> parameter for the second gonotrophic period proposed by Otero et al. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005797.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. We then took random draws from normal distributions describing uncertainties in these two parameters and weighted the resulting two temperature-dependent biting rates (inverses of the gonotrophic periods) according to the probability of the mosquito surviving to a given number of gonotrophic cycles, as described in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0005797.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>. A summary of parameters and their default values is available in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0005797.s022">S4 Table</xref>.
</p>
