<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0020">The medical community has been mindful of infection origination and pathogen transfer for centuries. As surgeons, we meticulously exercise the necessary steps to decrease the possibility of pathogen transfer and are acutely aware of the consequences of infection affecting our patients. Societies also have considerable knowledge regarding the importance of “breaking the chain of pathogen transfer”. In the middle of the 19th century, Ignac Semmelweis, known as the Savior of Mothers [
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], recognized the personal chain of pathogen transfer and mandated hand-washing to disrupt this process. Quarantines have an even more remote history, dating back to 14th century [
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In an effort to protect the coastal cities from diseases arriving on incoming boats, passengers were placed in isolation for a period of time and monitored for the presence of disease before being allowed to interact with the local community. All of the measures implemented to address the COVID-19 pandemic, which have been in practice in the medical and surgical community for centuries, are intended to break the chain of pathogen transfer. There is no doubt that this pandemic shall also pass and we will return to our “normal” lives. Many, however, believe that the new normalcy will have different features than what was present before COVID-19. Our profession will also witness changes in everyday routines that will be necessary to overcome the issues with the current pandemic and diminish the scale and gravity of future epidemic/pandemics. As we prepare to emerge from this pandemic and contemplate resuming our practices, we are faced with the ever-pertinent question of what changes will we need to implement in our daily routines. This article is written, with reliance on available evidence from the past and the current events, to provide some guidance on strategies that may need to be implemented to disrupt the chain of pathogen transfer. These strategies may also translate to a reduction in the rate of surgical site infections in the future.
</p>
