<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The incubation periods of COVID‐19 were 1 to 14 days, and the mean has been estimated to be 5.2 days (95% confidence interval [CI]: 4.4‐6.0) and 97.5% of those who develop symptoms will do so within 10.5 days (95% CI: 7.3‐15.3) of infection.
 <xref rid="jmv25740-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref> From the first confirmed child case who was reported in Shenzhen on 20th January 2020 to 6 February 2020, at least 230 COVID‐19 cases in children (≤18 years) have been reported in China. The SARS‐CoV‐2 rapid spread in children suggests that it has a strong transmission capacity in the special population (neonate, children). SARS‐CoV‐2 infection can range from asymptomatic infection to severe respiratory distress in neonates and children. However, Respiratory distress occurs in children with underlying conditions. One patient had severe malnutrition and survived surgery for congenital heart disease, the other had bilateral hydronephrosis and left‐kidney calculi. The clinical course of COVID‐19 was generally milder in children than adults.The most common clinical symptoms of COVID‐19 included fever, fatigue, and dry cough. A few patients showed upper respiratory symptoms such as nasal obstruction, nasal discharge, and sore throat. Gastrointestinal symptoms such as abdominal discomfort, vomiting, abdominal pain, and diarrhea may also occur. C‐reactive protein was normal or temporary upregulation, ALT levels and myocardial enzyme were not obviously abnormal changes. Chest imaging normalities were present in asymptomatic infected patients. SARS‐CoV‐2 can be mixed to different pathogen including mycoplasma pneumonia, influenza A, influenza B, RSV, and EB virus. The clearance time of SARS‐CoV‐2 nucleic acid from nasopharyngeal swab was recorded in three children, 9 days in two patients, 12 days in one patient.
 <xref rid="jmv25740-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref> Thus far, no deaths have been reported in the children which are similar to SARS.
 <xref rid="jmv25740-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv25740-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref> Three newborns have been diagnosed up to date who mainly belonged to family cluster cases. One 17 days old neonate diagnosed as COVID‐19 infection had a fever, cough, and vomiting milk. In his family, the housemaid was the earliest case, subsequently, the mother was infected.
 <xref rid="jmv25740-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref> The second newborn appeared fever on 5 days after birth whose mother also confirmed infected. The third one who was born by the infected mother was silent and diagnosed on 30 hours after birth by the viral nucleic acid test. Short breath, vomiting milk, cough, and fever were present in neonates. The vital signs of those neonates were stable, there is no severe emergency case until now.
 <xref rid="jmv25740-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv25740-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv25740-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv25740-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv25740-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
