<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par59">Proteins that selectively bind m6A sites are defined as m6A “readers”, which exert regulation by influencing the recognition of methylated RNA. It has been established that the YTH N6-methyladenosine RNA-binding protein family comprising YTHDF1, YTHDF2, YTHDF3, YTHDC1, and YTHDC2 is the major protein family among all “readers”. In general, YTHDF1 directly enhanced translation through binding with the m6A modification in 3’UTR region [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]; YTHDF2 recruited CCR4-NOT de-adenosine complexes to promote mRNA decay [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]; YTHDF3 acted as a helper of YTHDF1 and YTHDF2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. YTHDF1, 2, and 3 are dominantly located in the cytoplasm, while YTHDC1 is mainly localized in the nucleus where it regulates mRNA export from nucleus to cytoplasm and induce exon inclusion [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. YTHDC2 modulates the translation of RNA by interacting with the 40-80S subunit in the cytoplasm [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Recently, Huang et al. identified a new family- the insulin-like growth factor 2 mRNA-binding proteins (IGF2BPs, including IGF2BP1/2/3) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. In contrast to YTH domain family, IGF2BPs bind to m6A-modified mRNAs through GG(m6A)C, a typical m6A motif, to promote mRNA stability. Moreover, other proteins have been found to recognize m6A, such as eIF3 and HNRNP2AB1. eIF3, as part of the 43S pre-translational initiation complex, promotes protein translation by binding to the m6A site of mRNA 5’UTR region [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Therefore, m6A is dynamically regulated by writers, erasers, readers and other potential proteins associated with these regulators (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). 
</p>
