<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Roots of the syndemic among MSM have been posited to lie in early experiences of stress and stigma, which in turn increase the likelihood of mental health problems, substance misuse, sexual risk behavior, and difficulty forming/maintaining healthy intimate relationships (or dissolving unhealthy intimate relationships), all of which in turn increase or exacerbate the presence of the other components of the syndemic [
 <xref rid="pone.0206746.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Childhood sexual abuse (CSA) is not only a developmentally early stressor, much research has documented the link to subsequent problems like HIV, substance misuse, mental health problems, and IPV among many populations [
 <xref rid="pone.0206746.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0206746.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0206746.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. CSA has also garnered attention as a precursor to increased risk for HIV, especially given some evidence of elevated rates of experiencing CSA among MSM (for a review, see Llyod &amp; Operario [
 <xref rid="pone.0206746.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] and Schafer 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0206746.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]). Some studies focused on the syndemic among MSM have also suggested that CSA may be a salient factor to consider [
 <xref rid="pone.0206746.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0206746.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0206746.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. None of these studies specifically focused on prevalence of CSA among Black MSM, and though they may have reported some estimates, they are limited by small sample sizes for Black MSM. There has been one published one multi-site study examining CSA among Black MSM, but the sample size in any one of the cities was capped at about 225 individuals; moreover, the sampling plan weighted very heavily (~20:1) towards Black MSM who believed they were not living with HIV; that is, Black MSM living with HIV were heavily undersampled, making it unclear how generalizable the observed associations between CSA and syndemic factors may be to the larger population of Black MSM that has a high prevalence of HIV. Consequently, using a relatively large (
 <italic>N</italic> = 1,002) sample of Black MSM from the New York City area—where HIV prevalence rates among Black MSM have been estimated to exceed HIV rates in many countries in Sub-Saharan Africa [
 <xref rid="pone.0206746.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]—recruited without regard to perceived HIV status, this study addresses the following research questions:
</p>
