<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13">At present, number of laboratory based diagnostic techniques is used to detect Chikungunya virus infection. This includes conventional culture based identification, immunological detection through direct ELISA and molecular detection by end point RT-PCR, qRT-PCR and RT-LAMP
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. The conventional culture method is tedious and time consuming and also need expertise with well established cell culture facilities. Though serological techniques are frequently used but still suffer from false positivity due to circulation of cross reactive viruses. Therefore detection based on molecular assay is widely preferred throughout the world for confirmatory diagnosis. Polymerase spiral reaction is a recently reported field compatible onsite isothermal rapid molecular detection platform. PSR is a novel isothermal method that fulfils the requirements of World Health Organization (WHO) guidelines for development of diagnostic systems. The current objectives of developing diagnostic by research laboratories mainly lies in “ASSURED” (affordable, sensitive, specific, user friendly, robust and rapid, equipment free and deliverable) philosophy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup>. The aim is now shifting towards development of onsite point of care diagnostics. The main reason behind this is the revolution in molecular biology detection platforms including various isothermal diagnostic assays. PSR method has advantages over traditional PCR methods in comparison to time, cost, specificity, sensitivity; omit the gel electrophoresis, need for high end equipment and onsite detection capabilities. Specific nucleic acids can be amplified and detected in isothermal conditions, without need of any costly equipment. A positive reaction results in accumulation of large amount of pyrophosphate so that turbidity can also be recorded for quantification purpose. Primer designing for RT-PSR is very simple and similar to conventional end point PCR (i.e. identification of a conserved gene revealed through multiple sequence alignment). Further, sequence from an unrelated species that is an exogenous or from a botanical origin is appended at the 5′ end of the primer sequence at the target region. In contrast, LAMP, another isothermal technique requires complicated primer designing tool. Therefore the PSR method has the potential to be setup in rural settings as per requirements.
</p>
