<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Due to the novelty of this disease, there is a lack of understanding of the SARS-CoV-2 replication process in host cells. The general mechanisms of entry into the host cell, replication, and release follow characteristics that have been described for other CoVs and have been partially confirmed for SARS-CoV-2. To date, it is known that the SARS-CoV-2 virion entries the host cells by the attachment of the S protein with angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 receptor (ACE2), defining SARS-CoV-2 tropism for cells that express this receptor, such as pulmonary, hepatic, gastrointestinal, and renal human cells (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Chu et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">Hoffmann et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B210" ref-type="bibr">Tai et al., 2020</xref>). The interaction of ACE2 with the receptor-binding domain (RBD) of the S protein triggers virion endocytosis and the formation of an endosome (
 <xref rid="B175" ref-type="bibr">Rabi et al., 2020</xref>). The S protein possesses two subunits, S1 and S2 (
 <xref rid="B230" ref-type="bibr">Walls et al., 2020</xref>). During endocytosis, an acid-dependent proteolytic cleavage of the S1 protein by cellular proteases, like cathepsin, TMPRRS2, and trypsin, exposes the S2 subunit, a fusion peptide that allows the fusion of the viral envelope with the endosome membrane, and consequently, releases the capsid into the cell cytoplasm (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Belouzard et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B143" ref-type="bibr">Matsuyama et al., 2020</xref>). In the cytoplasm, the CoV viral genome is uncoated, and the viral RNA is released. The positive-sense RNA viral genome is translated to produce nonstructural proteins (nsps) from two open reading frames (ORFs), ORF1a and ORF1b. The ORF1a encodes the polyprotein pp1a that is cleaved in 11 nsps, while the ORF1b encodes the polyprotein pp1ab, which is cleaved into 15 nsps. The proteolytic cleavage is performed by viral proteases nsp3 and nsp5 (
 <xref rid="B252" ref-type="bibr">Yogo et al., 1977</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B123" ref-type="bibr">Lai and Stohlman, 1981</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B114" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2020</xref>). The nsps assemble to form a replicase-transcriptase complex (RTC) responsible for RNA synthesis, replication, and transcription of nine subgenomic RNAs (sgRNAs) (
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Fehr and Perlman, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Chen W.-H. et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B114" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2020</xref>). The sgRNAs act as mRNAs for structural and accessory genes localized downstream of the replicase polyproteins. SARS-CoV-2 has six accessory proteins: 3a, 6, 7a, 7b, 8, and 10 (
 <xref rid="B114" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2020</xref>). The structural proteins S, E, and M are translated from the sgRNAs and forwarded to the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) and are subsequently inserted into an intermediate compartment of ER with Golgi (ERGIC). There, viral genomes are encapsulated by N proteins and assembled with the structural proteins to form virions (
 <xref rid="B204" ref-type="bibr">Siu et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Fehr and Perlman, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B132" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020</xref>). The M proteins bind to E protein and nucleocapsid, and then, the S protein is incorporated, forming a complete virion. Finally, the virions are transported to the cell surface in vesicles and released in a pathway mediated by exocytosis (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Fehr and Perlman, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B114" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B132" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020</xref>).
</p>
