<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Chikungunya virus (CHIKV) is a re-emerging pathogen responsible for causing outbreaks of febrile disease accompanied with debilitating joint pain. CHIKV was first discovered in Tanzania in 1952, but outbreaks became more widespread, encompassing countries in Africa, Asia, Europe, and islands of the Pacific and Indian Oceans before emerging in the Americas in 2013 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. More recently, in 2016–2017, there has been a resurgence of autochthonous CHIKV transmission in India [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], Pakistan [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], and Italy [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The virus is transmitted to humans through the bite of 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> mosquitoes. Chikungunya infection results in illness, in which fever and joint polyalrthralgia, are typically reported symptoms [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Acute symptoms persist for two weeks, but more chronic arthralgias may persist for months to years in a subset of subjects. More severe and/or chronic chikungunya illnesses were first widely reported in retrospective studies of the chikungunya epidemics of Reunion Island [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] and India [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Following infection, patients experience renal, respiratory, hepatic, and cardiovascular system failures. In addition, diseases of the central nervous disease and encephalitis are major areas of concerns [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. People over 60 years of age are at particular risk for severe chikungunya-associated illnesses, with case fatalities reported [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. However, the incidence of CHIKV infection in this population is not remarkable in comparison to other age groups [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The specific mechanisms that lead to increased severity of CHIKV illness in the elderly are not known, but increased understanding could lead to better treatments and vaccines for this at-risk population.
</p>
