<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0055">Remdesivir, a monophosphate prodrug of an adenosine analog, was originally developed to combat the Ebola outbreak in 2014. It has been highly touted as a potential antiviral drug for COVID-19. It has been shown to have potent in-vitro activity against SARS-CoV-2 (EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 0.77 μM 
 <xref rid="b0170" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>), SARS-CoV-1 and MERS-CoV 
 <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. Because of its high selectivity for viral polymerases, Remdesivir is less likely to cause toxicity in humans. The drug also exhibits a high genetic barrier to resistance in coronaviruses and its long intracellular half-life is conducive for once-a-day dosing 
 <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. There are currently 38 registered trials listed on ClinicalTrials.gov for investigating the efficacy of this drug. Preliminary results from a small cohort show clinical improvement in 68% of hospitalized patients 
 <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref> on administration of Remdesivir. However, the small sample size and the lack of a control group limit its significance. Wang et al. reported that in a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, multicentre trial of 237 participants (NCT04257656), Remdesivir did not exhibit significant clinical benefits 
 <xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. On April 29, the US NIH reported that in a high powered RCT of 1063 participants, patients in the Remdesivir group had shown a 31% faster time to recovery (median 11 days) 
 <xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref> than those in the placebo group (15 days) (p &lt; 0.001). Even though the findings do not definitively reveal whether the drug is curative, Remdesivir is slated to be the new standard of care 
 <xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref> for COVID-19 patients in the United States. It has also been approved for therapeutic use in COVID-19 patients by the regulatory bodies of Japan, Australia, Singapore, and Europe 
 <xref rid="b0205" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. The use of Remdesivir might prove to have a measurable impact on healthcare capacity by minimizing the length of hospital stay and reducing the overall severity of the illness. In a comparative analysis of the Phase 3 SIMPLE-severe trial and a retrospective cohort study of severe COVID-19 patients, Remdesivir has recently shown a 62% reduction in the risk of mortality as opposed to the standard of care and an improvement in clinical recovery 
 <xref rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. The drug is also being tested on outpatients as an inhaled, nebulised form in a Phase 1a trial 
 <xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>.
</p>
