<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Prior to rotavirus vaccination, RVGE showed a winter-spring seasonality and geographic patterns that begin in the southwest in December-January, extending across to the U.S. and ending in the northeast during April-May. In the post-vaccine era, the rotavirus season was shorter, delayed and of smaller magnitude compared to seasons in the pre-vaccine era, but a biennial pattern of RVGE incidence emerged [
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. This RVGE reduction was accompanied by biennial patterns with higher seasonal peak in 2009, 2011, and 2013 compared to lower seasonal peak in 2008, 2010, and 2012 [
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In general, biennial patterns of RVGE could be induced by factors that govern the rate of new susceptibles. These include incomplete vaccine coverage rates, imperfect vaccine efficacy, and birth rates [
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In one study, a RVGE transmission model predicted that biennial patterns of RVGE emerge after the introduction of vaccines when birth rates are low, while an annual pattern of RVGE was predicted when birth rates are high [
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In the U.S, birth rates have remained fairly stable in the pre and post-vaccine era. Thus, birth rate is likely not a significant driver of the biennial pattern of RVGE in the U.S. Incomplete vaccination coverage that leads to a build-up of susceptible children may be driving this biennial pattern [
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Unvaccinated children drive the higher rotavirus hospitalizations in the biennial patterns [
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In contrast, other developed countries with high coverage of rotavirus vaccination (&gt;85%), such as Belgium, Austria, Australia, Finland, and Germany, did not have the biennial epidemic patterns after the introduction of vaccines [
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0228942.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].
</p>
