<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A limitation of many vaccines is the poorly immunogenic response they evoke. Thanks to the advances in the knowledge of mechanisms underlying innate immunity, effective vaccine adjuvants have been developed to enhance the immune systems' response. (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>). These compounds are able to improve the speed, potency, and persistency of the immune response to vaccination. While aluminum was the first and only adjuvant routinely used in human vaccines for more than 50 years, novel adjuvanted system (AS) composed of the combination of two or more different immunostimulants were developed to achieve the desired response. For example, one of them, namely AS04, was used in 2005 for the hepatitis B (HBV) vaccine and in 2007 for the human papillomavirus HPV-16/18 vaccine (
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>). More recently, AS01, an adjuvant composed by two immunostimulants, (saponin QS21 and monophosphoryl lipid A, targeting TLR4), has been licensed for a vaccine against malaria and herpes zoster vaccine. Also, it is currently used in clinical trials for vaccines designed to prevent reactivation of tuberculosis, and for a vaccine against non-typeable 
 <italic>H. influenzae</italic> and 
 <italic>Moraxella catarrhalis</italic>, aimed to prevent exacerbation in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. The TB vaccine phase 2b trial conducted in Kenya, South Africa, and Zambia provided 54.0% protection in 
 <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> infected adults against active pulmonary tuberculosis disease. This vaccine is composed of the M72 recombinant fusion protein including two immunogenic 
 <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> antigens (Mtb32A and Mtb39A), combined with the AS01
 <sub>E</sub> adjuvant system (
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>). Additional adjuvants targeting the innate immune receptors TLR9 (DNA oligonucleotides), TLR5 (Flagellin), TLR7, surface-exposed (TLR1/2), endosomal (TLR3), or cytoplasmic (RIG I, DNA sensors) innate immune receptors have been successfully tested (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>).
</p>
