<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Statins have proven to be beneficial as an add-on therapy in patients with different autoimmune inflammatory conditions (e.g. systemic lupus erythematosus, rheumatoid arthritis, multiple sclerosis, and graft-versus-host disease).
 <xref rid="pvaa042-B2" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>2</sup>
 </xref> Statins have also been evaluated as an immunomodulatory treatment in various infectious diseases. Although observational studies have reported improved outcomes in patients with community-acquired pneumonia or sepsis receiving statins,
 <xref rid="pvaa042-B3" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="pvaa042-B4" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref> most RCTs on inpatient statin treatment in sepsis or ventilator-associated pneumonia failed to demonstrate a beneficial effect.
 <xref rid="pvaa042-B4" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref> On the other hand, statin therapy appears promising in the context of viral infections. Avian influenza viruses induce an intense host response characterized by a cytokine storm, which can sometimes lead to ARDS.
 <xref rid="pvaa042-B3" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> Few large observational studies have reported the effectiveness of statin treatment in reducing influenza-related hospitalizations and deaths.
 <xref rid="pvaa042-B3" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> Further, a recently completed RCT (ClinicalTrials.gov number, NCT02056340) showed a significant improvement of symptoms in statin-naïve patients hospitalized for seasonal influenza receiving atorvastatin 40 mg compared with placebo. An association between outpatient statin use and reduction in disease severity among patients hospitalized during the 2009 H1N1 pandemic has also been demonstrated.
 <xref rid="pvaa042-B3" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> Some authors have therefore advocated statin use as an immunomodulatory therapy for viral infections with potential for epidemics and pandemics.
 <xref rid="pvaa042-B3" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> Although no RCT has yet investigated this hypothesis, statins [together with angiotensin receptor blockers (ARBs)] were effective in targeting the host response and preventing endothelial barrier damage in patients infected with Ebola virus during the recent Ebola outbreak in West Africa.
 <xref rid="pvaa042-B5" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
