<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack id="ceack10">
 <sec>
  <title>Acknowledgments</title>
  <p>This work was provided with some funding support from the Open Society Foundations, The Global Fund, WHO, UNAIDS, and UN Office on Drugs and Crime. The Australian National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre, UNSW Sydney, provided some funding towards the costs of this systematic review. LD, AP, RPM, and JG are supported by Australian National Health and Medical Research Council Fellowships. EBC is supported by a CanHepC PhD scholarship. MH is an NIHR Senior Investigator and acknowledges support from NIHR Health Protection Research Unit in Evaluation. PV acknowledges support from the Health Protection Research Unit in Blood-borne and Sexually Transmitted Infections and National Institute for Drug Abuse (grant number R01 DA037773-01A1). JS is an NIHR Senior Investigator and is supported by the NIHR Biomedical Research Centre in Mental Health at South London and Maudsley NHS Foundation Trust/Kings College London. The National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre and the Kirby Institute are funded by the Australian Government Department of Health and Ageing. The views expressed in this publication do not necessarily represent the position of the Australian Government. Thanks to the research assistants who assisted with searches for and extraction of data from the eligible papers in this review: Griselda Buckland, Gabrielle Gibson, Inbar Millo, Laura Sergeant, Julia Stadum, Harriet Townsend, and Foong Chin Yong (National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre, UNSW Sydney), and Diana Sergiienko (Ukrainian Institute of Public Health Policy). Thanks to Mary Kumvaj (librarian) who provided specialist advice on our search strategy and search strings for the peer-reviewed literature searches. Thank you also to the individuals who provided encouragement and support in various ways throughout the conduct of this review, including circulating requests for data, provision of contacts in countries and assistance with locating data: Annette Verster (WHO), Daniel Wolfe (Open Society Foundations), Andre Noor (EMCDDA), Eleni Kalamara (EMCDDA), Mauro Guarinieri (Global Fund), Christoforos Mallouris (UNAIDS), Susie McLean, Catherine Cook (Harm Reduction International [HRI]), Maria Phelan (HRI), Katie Stone (HRI), Riku Lehtovuori (UNODC), Keith Sabin (UNAIDS), Jinkou Zhao (Global Fund), and Vladimir Poznyak (WHO). Assistance in sourcing and verifying data was provided by many individuals from government, non-government, and research organisations around the world, for which we are thankful. These individuals are listed in the 
   <xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">appendix</xref>.
  </p>
 </sec>
</ack>
