<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <title>Declaration of interests</title>
 <p>SL has received investigator-initiated untied educational grants from Indivior. LD has received investigator-initiated untied educational grants for studies of opioid medications in Australia from Reckitt Benckiser, Indivior, Mundipharma, and Seqirus. AP has received investigator-initiated untied educational grants from Mundipharma and Seqirus. JG is a consultant and advisor for, and has received research grants from, Abbvie, Cepheid, Gilead Sciences, and Merck/MSD. MH reports honoraria for speaking at meetings from Gilead, Abbvie, and MSD. JM is supported by research grants from the Department of Health, National Institute for Health Research (NIHR), and the NIHR Biomedical Research Centre for Mental Health at King's Health Partners; he has part-time employment as Senior Academic Advisor for the Alcohol, Drugs and Tobacco Division, Health and Wellbeing Directorate, Public Health England; he declares grant funding for an investigator-led, educational grant from Indivior (administered by Action on Addiction) for a study of adjunctive, personalised psychosocial intervention for non-response to opioid agonist treatment (The ARC Trial), and grant funding at IoPPN and South London and Maudsley NHS Mental Health Foundation Trust from NIHR (Health Technology Assessment) for a trial of extended-release naltrexone (investigational medicinal product supply from iGen). In the past 3 years, JM has received honoraria from Merck Serono (2015; clinical oncology medicine), Martindale Pharma (2017; treatment for opioid use disorder), and Indivior (via PCM Scientific) as co-chair and chair (2015–17) for the Improving Outcomes in Treatment of Opioid Dependence conference; these companies had no role in the design, conduct, interpretation, or publication of findings. 
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.kcl.ac.uk/ioppn/depts/addictions/people/hod.aspx" id="interrefs30" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">JS</ext-link> is supported by the NIHR Biomedical Research Centre for Mental Health at South London and Maudsley NHS Foundation Trust and King's College London and is an NIHR Senior Investigator. JS's employer (King's College London) has received, connected to his work, project grant support, honoraria, and consultancy payments from Department of Health, National Treatment Agency, Public Health England, Home Office, National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence, and European Monitoring Centre for Drugs and Drug Addiction (EMCDDA) as well as research grants from (last 3 years) the NIHR, Medical Research Council, and Pilgrim Trust. JS has also worked with WHO, United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime, EMCDDA, US Food and Drug Administration, US National Institute on Drug Abuse, and other international government agencies. JS's employer (King's College London) has registered intellectual property on an innovative buccal naloxone with which JS is involved, and JS has been named in a patent registration by a pharmaceutical company as inventor of a potential concentrated naloxone nasal spray. JS's employer (King's College London) has also received, connected to his work, research grant support and payment of honoraria, consultancy payments, and expenses from pharmaceutical companies (including, past 3 years, Martindale, Indivior, MundiPharma, and Braeburn/Camurus) and trial medication supply from iGen and Braeburn and also discussions with various companies about medications potentially applicable in the treatment of addictions and related problems. SC, JL, LH, EBC, RPM, KVD, ML, PG, and PV declare no competing interests.
 </p>
</ack>
