<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Interestingly, SARS and MERS zoonotic CoVs have probably originated from bats and then moved into other mammalian hosts—the Himalayan palm civet for SARS-CoV and the dromedary camel for MERS-CoV—before spilling over humans [
 <xref rid="B17-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The SARS epidemic was the first human pandemic to break out in the 21
 <sup>st</sup> century and emerged through recombination of bat SARS-related coronaviruses [
 <xref rid="B20-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Transmission of SARS-CoV-1 occurred from the bat to humans and the palm civets served as a secondary host and reservoir for the continuation of the infection and then the SARS emergency [
 <xref rid="B21-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The SARS epidemic, which started in 2002 and ended in 2003, lasted about 1 year and has so far caused 8098 cases in 26 countries in 2002–2003, with 774 deaths (estimated mortality rate of 10%). No other cases have been detected since 2004. Uncertainty remains as to the epidemiology and ecology of the infection. The virus reservoir has been detected in bats, but the passage to humans took place through an intermediate host, civet, which is considered a food delicacy in China. The main mechanism of morbidity and lethality of SARS is the so-called acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS). The virus-cell interaction occurs between the viral Spike protein, the ligand, and the human angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2), which is the membrane cellular receptor. ACE2 is a key player enzyme in the Renin-Angiotensin system and a target for the treatment of hypertension [
 <xref rid="B22-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The Spike/ACE2 interaction triggers a violent acute inflammation of the lungs, leading to the formation of a layer of fibrin on the pulmonary alveoli, thus preventing gaseous exchange [
 <xref rid="B23-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The transmission of SARS-CoV-1 occurred mainly person-to-person through direct contact, Flügge’s large drop-to-drop contact, and indirect contact by fomites, unwashed hands, and rarely touching contaminated surfaces or air travel [
 <xref rid="B24-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. No effective drugs have been identified, although vaccination strategies have been designed to fight SARS pandemic [
 <xref rid="B26-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].
</p>
