<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">CoVs are enveloped single-stranded positive-sense RNA viruses with genomes ranging between 26.2 and 31.7 kb RNA. The genome encodes four major structural proteins: the spike (S) protein, nucleocapsid (N) protein, membrane (M) protein, and the envelope (E) protein, all required to produce the viral particle [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Sequencing analyses on RNA of SARS-CoV-2 variants isolated from COVID-19 patients show 96% homology with a bat virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>] suggesting that, as for the other coronaviruses, SARS-CoV-2 jumped from bats to humans, probably through an intermediate host, not yet identified, after the occurrence of a mutation that allowed the infection of human cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The S (spike) glycoprotein mediates the SARS-CoV-2 entry into cells following the binding to the angiotensin converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. ACE2 is highly expressed on cell surface of many tissues and organs including the lungs and the myocardium [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Of relevance, ACE2 is mainly located in the inner track of the respiratory system, thus explaining why SARS-CoV-2, differently from the flu virus which binds to the upper airways track, might cause serious respiratory insufficiency. This also explains why COVID-19 is not just a common influenza, like somebody believed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Differently from ACE1, which catalyses the formation of Angiotensin (Ang) II, the active component of renin–angiotensin system involved in blood pressure regulation and cardiorenal function, ACE2 cleaves Ang II in Ang (1–7). Thus, ACE2 antagonises ACE1 activity. Ang II receptor blockers (ARBs), which are widely used to treat hypertension and heart failure, increase the levels of Ang II [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>] and, indirectly, could activate ACE2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. It has been proposed that patients receiving ARBs have higher susceptibility to COVID-19 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] and, as a consequence, hypertensive or patients with heart failure should switch from ARBs to other drugs. This way of thinking, however, is not supported by any evidence [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Actually, there are caveats here: (1) ACE2 expression is reduced in hypertension models; (2) there is no evidence of increased ACE2 expression with ARBs in the lung; (3) hypertension and its treatment with ARBs did not affect previous coronavirus infections [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].
</p>
