<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Strongyloidiasis, caused by the threadworm 
 <italic>Strongyloides stercoralis</italic>, is another important soil-transmitted helminth infection, associated with chronic enteritis, impaired child development, eosinophilia, and hyperinfection in immunocompromised hosts 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Milder1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Siddiqui1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. The disease is under-reported partly because of the difficulty of diagnosing the infection by fecal examination 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Siddiqui1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Kitchen1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. A review of several studies conducted during the 1960s, 70s, and 80s and determined that the prevalence in Central Appalachia ranged from 0.4% (Charleston, West Virginia) to 4.0% (Harlan County, Kentucky, and Johnson City, Tennessee) 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Siddiqui1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. Based on 3,271 fecal examinations in Kentucky, Walzer et al. estimated that the overall prevalence was approximately 1% 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Walzer1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. A high percentage of the patients with strongyloidiasis were found to be older white males, most of whom had underlying chronic illnesses including chronic obstructive pulmonary disease 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Walzer1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Milder1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Siddiqui1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Berk1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. These infections may have been acquired in coal mines. Murray et al. determined that 11 million people compose the poor white Appalachians in America 4 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Murray1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, while the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) reported that the population of rural Appalachia is approximately 6.8 million 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Centers1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. Based on Walzer's prevalence determination of 1%, I estimate there are approximately 68,000 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Hotez4" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref> to 110,000 Appalachians infected with 
 <italic>S. stercoralis</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000256-t002">Table 2</xref>).
</p>
