<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0110">Hepatitis C virus (HCV) is a bloodborne positive single-stranded RNA virus, belonging to the 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic> family in the 
 <italic>Hepacivirus</italic> genus [
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. HCV causes hepatitis C that can be a mild illness lasting a few weeks (acute) or a lifelong and serious disease (chronic). Hepatitis C may degenerate into cirrhosis and HCV is the major cause of liver cancer. Worldwide 71 million people have chronic HCV infection [
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. HCV exists in seven genotypes and more than 80 subtypes, which differ in the pathogenesis and response to treatments. Because of its high genetic variability, due to a high replication rate and lack of proofreading activity by the HCV RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (vRdRp), so far there is no effective vaccine against hepatitis C, and new antivirals able to overcome the drug-resistance and to reduce the side effects in the long treatment are needed [
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. HCV infection starts with HCV nanoparticles attachment to the liver cells through a multistep-process involving the viral glycoproteins E1 and E2 and cellular receptors. Then, HCV particles internalization occurs by clathrin-mediated endocytosis. Upon the release of the RNA into the cytoplasm, the viral RNA is translated as a single polypeptide that undergoes co- and post-translational processes by viral and cellular proteases to yield structural (Core, E1, E2) and seven non-structural (NS) proteins. The NS proteins include NS5B (vRdRp), key enzyme in RNA synthesis and one of the main targets of the direct-acting antivirals (DAAs). The other NS proteins are fundamental in the formation of the replication complex and virus assembly. In particular, HCV NS3 protein plays a significant role in the viral life cycle [
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].
</p>
