<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The sites of interaction between NP and PB2 are poorly mapped. Three independent regions of NP (amino acids 1–161, 255–340, 340–465) were found to bind PB2, while the C-terminus of NP (amino acids 465–498) inhibits the interaction [
 <xref rid="pone.0191226.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. On the other hand, two fragments of PB2 (amino acids 1–269 and 580–683) were shown to interact with NP [
 <xref rid="pone.0191226.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. However, these sites of interaction were mapped by deletion mutagenesis and cover a significant portion of both proteins (75% of NP and 50% of PB2). Several studies reported reduced interaction between NP and PB2 of avian influenza viruses in mammalian cells that can be restored by the E627K adaptive mutation [
 <xref rid="pone.0191226.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0191226.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0191226.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. This led to the hypothesis that PB2 amino acid 627 is involved in NP-PB2 interactions. However, another report suggested that the apparent stronger binding of NP with PB2 observed in co-immunoprecipitation with a PB2 E627K mutant is a consequence of increased polymerase activity instead of higher binding affinity between NP and PB2 [
 <xref rid="pone.0191226.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In addition, PB2 627E was found to restrict polymerase activity in mammalian cells in an NP-independent manner suggesting that reduced binding between avian PB2 and NP in mammalian cells is not the primary reason for the low activity of avian influenza virus polymerase in mammalian cells [
 <xref rid="pone.0191226.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. To gain a better insight into the interplay between NP and PB2 here we investigate the interaction between NP and the PB2 ‘627’ domain further and identify amino acids 605 and 606 of PB2 that is involved in an interaction with amino acid region of 146–185 of NP.
</p>
