<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The information presented here indicates that helminth infections, especially the three major STH infections, schistosomiasis, LF, and onchocerciasis, account for up to 85% of the disease burden caused by NTDs in SSA (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000412-t006">Table 6</xref>). Given that NTDs may be responsible for as much as one-half and one-third of the region's malaria and HIV/AIDS disease burden, respectively, helminth control should continue to be prioritized by public health experts, health ministries, and global policy makers. In addition, based on revised estimates for schistosomiasis that fully consider the morbidities of chronic infection including effects on anemia, malnutrition, growth stunting, and diminished child development 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-King1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-King2" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, and the observation that many of these same sequelae occur for STH and other helminth infections 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Brooker1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Brooker2" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Stephenson1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Stephenson2" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Hotez4" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Crompton1" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>, the possibility remains that maternal and child helminthiases may increase even further in their disease control priority rankings. There is an urgent need for better direct or indirect methods of estimating the disease burden for the NTDs and other conditions. Disease burden estimates for the major helminthiases and other NTDs (based on DALYs as the major metric) are currently being re-evaluated in an initiative led by the Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation at the University of Washington and supported by the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Mathers1" ref-type="bibr">[143]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Stein1" ref-type="bibr">[145]</xref>. Another high priority is to begin obtaining prevalence, incidence, and disease burden estimates for many of the non-helminth NTDs. Amebiasis and toxoplasmosis stand out as both common and serious protozoan infections for which we have very little information. Similarly, the data available for human 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> and tick-borne zoonotic bacterial infections are minimal even though some reports suggest they be enormously important. Stepped-up surveillance measures for some of Africa's arboviral infections may provide timely and useful data in the coming years. A full analysis of all Africa's NTDs is an essential step towards prioritizing these conditions relative to ongoing HIV/AIDS and malaria control efforts supported by private foundations and the Group of Eight nations.
</p>
