<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0085">Next, using the dataset in Ref. [
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], a number of illustrations are shown. 
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> shows the bar chart of confirmed cases and death cases in different countries. It indicates that the number of confirmed cases and death cases of the disease are significantly higher in the USA than any other countries. Spain has the second and Italy has the third highest confirmed cases, while Italy has the second and the UK has the third highest death cases. An important point to note here that although China experienced the most number of confirmed cases up to February 16, 2020 [
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], it is now in the 18th position in the world in terms of the number of confirmed cases and death cases. 
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> shows the bar chart of death rate across the globe. In this case, death rate is represented as the ratio of number of deaths to number of confirmed cases. The largest death rate is in Yemen being 22.74%. The Belgium, France and Italy have the 2nd, 3rd and 4th highest death rates being 16.25%, 15.33% and 14.40%, respectively. 
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> shows the plots of death rate and recover rate across the globe for a time span ranging from January 22, 2020 to June 04, 2020. In this case, recovery/death rate is defined as the ratio of recovery/death to confirmed cases. It can be seen that the recovery rate has significantly increased from January to first week of March, however, it decreased from second week of March to first week of April 2020. The recovery rate has increased since early April 2020 which indicates that the number of active cases has reduced as many active patients have recovered. On the other hand, the death rate has increased from below 3% in Mid-February 2020 to around 6.0% in June 2020. 
 <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> presents graphs showing the death cases, recovered and active cases over time in the world. It can be seen from 
 <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>(a) that the death case has a significantly sharp increment since the first week of March 2020. From 
 <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>(b) it can be seen that the recovery cases have been steady with linear increment over time, but the active cases have experienced sharp increase after first week of March 2020. 
 <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> illustrates the number of currently active cases of COVID-19. 
 <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>(a) is a pie chart indicating that the percentage of active cases in the world is currently 42.20% of the total confirmed cases. At the same time the recovered cases is 51.90% of the total confirmed cases. 
 <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>(b) is a bubble graph showing the number of active cases in the world in different countries. In the graph, the larger the bubbles, the higher the number of active cases. It can be seen that currently the USA has far more active cases than any other country.
</p>
