<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0030">It is well established that the gut microbiota has a critical role in intestinal homeostasis and that changes in its composition and function activity are involved in local inflammation (
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Blander et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Lavelle and Sokol, 2020</xref>). A lack of ACE2 leads to substantial alteration in the composition of the gut microbiota in mice; this partly results from reduced production of the antimicrobial peptides that control the gut’s microbial community (
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hashimoto et al., 2012</xref>). Moreover, disruption of the ACE/ACE2 axis during pulmonary hypertension (loss of ACE2) is associated with alteration of the gut microbiota in humans (
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Santisteban et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2020</xref>). One can speculate that the decrease in ACE2 availability during SARS-COV-2 infection is enough to alter the composition of the gut microbiota. Recent pilot studies suggest gut microbiota alterations during SARS-CoV-2 infection (
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">Yu et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Gu et al., 2020b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Zuo et al., 2020</xref>). In a cohort of 30 COVID-19 patients (fecal sample analysis using 16S rRNA gene sequencing), infection was associated with a significant decrease of bacterial diversity and abundance (
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Gu et al., 2020b</xref>). Significant changes in gut microbial communities were noticed, including lower relative abundance of beneficial (butyrate-producing) bacteria, such as several genera from the 
 <italic>Ruminococcaceae</italic> and 
 <italic>Lachnospiraceae</italic> families. However, significantly higher relative abundance occurred of opportunistic pathogens, including 
 <italic>Streptococcus</italic>, 
 <italic>Rothia</italic>, 
 <italic>Veillonella</italic>, and 
 <italic>Actinomyces</italic>. Of interest, the gut microbial signature of patients with COVID-19 was different from that of H1N1 patients (
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Gu et al., 2020b</xref>). Enrichment of opportunistic pathogens and depletion of beneficial commensals was also observed in a (longitudinal) study using deep shotgun metagenomics (15 COVID-19 patients) (
 <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Zuo et al., 2020</xref>). In particular, enrichment of opportunistic pathogens known to cause bacteremia, including 
 <italic>Clostridium hathewayi</italic>, 
 <italic>Actinomyces viscosus</italic>, and 
 <italic>Bacteroides nordii</italic>, was observed. Lower relative abundance of beneficial commensals, including the anti-inflammatory bacterium 
 <italic>Faecalibacterium prausnitzii</italic>, 
 <italic>Alistipes onderdonkii</italic>, 
 <italic>Roseburia</italic>, and 
 <italic>Lachnospiraceae taxa</italic>, was also noticed. The authors found a correlation between rise or drop of these bacteria and disease severity. Of note, altered microbiota composition persisted after clearance of SARS-CoV-2 and resolution of respiratory symptoms, indicating that resiliency is long lasting (
 <xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr">Zuo et al., 2020</xref>). Hence, SARS-CoV-2 infection modifies the composition of the gut microbiota in humans. It is possible that reduced levels of commensal bacteria with important physiological functions, such as butyrate producers, may promote the overgrowth of intestinal conditional pathogenic bacteria. Whether these changes increase intestinal mucosal permeability and endotoxin concentrations in the blood, ultimately triggering inflammation and cytokine release exacerbation, remains to be investigated (
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> ). Further analyses are urgently needed in larger human cohorts to confirm and detail gut microbiota alterations in COVID-19 patients. Studies should prospectively include asymptomatic COVID-19-confirmed subjects and patients at disease onset, during disease course, and over the long term after discovery to delineate the role of microbiome changes in SARS-CoV-2 infection and post-infection recovery. It will be critical to consider patients treated or not with antibiotics (and other medications) and the comorbidity status of those patients. The consequences of SARS-CoV-2 infection on the gut microbiota should also be investigated in relevant animal models of COVID-19. Possible models include non-human primates, ferrets, human-ACE2-expressing mice, and hamsters (
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Callaway, 2020</xref>). The impact of SARS-CoV-2 on the gut microbiota’s metabolic output also remains to be defined. This aspect is of particular importance because in a mouse model, the altered gut microbiota associated with ACE2 deficiency (1) favors intestinal inflammation and (2) confers susceptibility to colitis when transferred to wild-type animals (
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hashimoto et al., 2012</xref>). In parallel, it remains to be determined whether alterations in the microbiota influence the extraintestinal outcomes of COVID-19. Altogether, direct enterocyte infection, disruption of the enteric ACE2 axis (and interference with nutrient absorption), hypoxia, alterations of the enteric nervous system and local immune response, and changes in inflammatory cytokine levels might lead to adverse intestinal outcomes (including dysbiosis) in patients with COVID-19.
</p>
