<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0140">Early studies verified high enteropathogenicity of the G1a CV777 in nursing pigs (
 <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">Coussement et al., 1982</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0565" ref-type="bibr">Pensaert and Martelli, 2016</xref>). The S1 of the S protein and the rest of the genome of the S INDEL PEDV (G1b) was genetically closest to that of G1a and the highly virulent G2 PEDV, respectively (
 <xref rid="bib0395" ref-type="bibr">Lee, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0565" ref-type="bibr">Pensaert and Martelli, 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0695" ref-type="bibr">Vlasova et al., 2014</xref>), the strain was initially thought to be virulent. However, during the initial outbreaks by S INDEL PEDV in the US and Europe, the low to zero mortality rates of pigs in the field were distinct from those of US non-S INDEL infections with up to 100 % mortality rates in nursing pigs (
 <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">Boniotti et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0205" ref-type="bibr">Goede et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0655" ref-type="bibr">Stevenson et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0715" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2014b</xref>). Nevertheless, difference in virulence of the two types of strains in the field was not often observed (
 <xref rid="bib0220" ref-type="bibr">Grasland et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0515" ref-type="bibr">Mesquita et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0645" ref-type="bibr">Stadler et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0650" ref-type="bibr">Steinrigl et al., 2015</xref>). A study using a wild-type strain of S INDEL PEDV reproduced as severe PED in infected sows and their piglets as that observed in the field (
 <xref rid="bib0405" ref-type="bibr">Leidenberger et al., 2017</xref>). Other studies showed generally milder pathogenicity of S INDEL PEDV in 3−7-day-old conventional pigs, compared with non-S INDEL PEDV (
 <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2016a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0440" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2015a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0750" ref-type="bibr">Yamamoto et al., 2015</xref>). However, the virulence of S INDEL PEDV was increased in the PEDV challenged suckling piglets when the mothers became sick, corresponding to poor immune, nutritional or health conditions (
 <xref rid="bib0440" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2015a</xref>). The mortality rates of piglets increased from 0% to 75 %, and the peak fecal PEDV RNA titers shed were also as high as those of non-S INDEL strain.
</p>
