<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Finally, we found that the degradation-resistant cortactin D93E and D116E mutants interfered with the amount of IAV progeny released from infected cells that was enhanced by the cleavage-sensitive cortactin WT. These data further supported our hypothesis that cortactin likely has a dual, but contrasting role during IAV infection. Cortactin, in association with Arp2/3 complex and N-WASP, promotes and stabilises the branching of filamentous actin [
 <xref rid="B30-viruses-12-00087" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], which regulate both clathrin-dependent and clathrin-independent endocytosis [
 <xref rid="B11-viruses-12-00087" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The IAV is known to use receptor-mediated endocytosis to enter the host cell [
 <xref rid="B33-viruses-12-00087" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Hence, we believe that in the early stages of infection intact cortactin is required for IAV entry to maintain dynamic branched filamentous actin network for efficient endocytosis of incoming virions [
 <xref rid="B7-viruses-12-00087" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. However, during the late stages of IAV infection intact cortactin is potentially deleterious due to the same branched filamentous actin-associated function. The late stages of IAV infection, assembly, budding, and release of viral progeny from the plasma membrane microdomains (lipid rafts) potentially require a less dynamic and unbranched filamentous actin network. This argument finds support in earlier observations where filamentous actin was found to be re-organised close to the IAV assembly sites [
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-12-00087" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Further, such re-organised filamentous actin promotes the clustering of viral proteins close to the IAV assembly sites and was important for efficient IAV assembly and budding [
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-12-00087" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Furthermore, the disruption of filamentous actin dynamism by drugs that either inhibit actin polymerization or enhance actin depolymerization led to an increase in the amount of IAV progeny released from infected cells [
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-12-00087" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Potentially, the degradation-resistant cortactin mutants interfered with such filamentous actin reorganization and/or dynamism and consequently in the IAV progeny assembly and release. Nevertheless, further molecular and microscopic investigations are needed to elucidate such dual role of cortactin during IAV infection. 
</p>
