<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with OASIS Tables with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archive-oasis-article1-mathml3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.2?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jpoasis-nisons2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Ecol Epidemiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Infect Ecol Epidemiol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Infection Ecology &#x00026; Epidemiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2000-8686</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Taylor &#x00026; Francis</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7480504</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/20008686.2020.1792620</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1792620</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" vocab-term="Version of Record" article-version-type="VoR">Version of Record</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinical Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Role of Environmental Temperature on the Attack rate and Case fatality rate of Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) Pandemic</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">M. M. HASSAN ET AL.</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">INFECTION ECOLOGY &#x00026; EPIDEMIOLOGY</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6495-4637</contrib-id><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>Mohammad M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="bio" rid="b0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1056-4761</contrib-id><name><surname>El Zowalaty</surname><given-names>Mohamed E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002"><sup>b</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0003"><sup>c</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/><xref ref-type="bio" rid="b0002"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Shahneaz A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="bio" rid="b0003"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9210-3351</contrib-id><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>Ariful</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0004"><sup>d</sup></xref><xref ref-type="bio" rid="b0004"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nayem</surname><given-names>Md. Raihan K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="bio" rid="b0005"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7075-1059</contrib-id><name><surname>J&#x000e4;rhult</surname><given-names>Josef D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0005"><sup>e</sup></xref><xref ref-type="bio" rid="b0006"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>a</label>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, <institution-wrap><institution>Chattogram Veterinary and Animal Sciences University</institution></institution-wrap>, <country>Bangladesh</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>b</label>Zoonosis Science Center, Department of Medical Biochemistry and Microbiology, <institution-wrap><institution>Uppsala University</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Uppsala</city>, <country>Sweden</country></aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>c</label>Department of Clinical Sciences, College of Medicine, <institution-wrap><institution>University of Sharjah</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Sharjah</city>, <country>UAE</country></aff><aff id="aff0004"><label>d</label>Centre for Integrative Ecology, School of Life and Environmental Science, <institution-wrap><institution>Deakin University</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Geelong</city>, <country>Australia</country></aff><aff id="aff0005"><label>e</label>Zoonosis Science Center, Department of Medical Sciences, <institution-wrap><institution>Uppsala University</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Uppsala</city>, <country>Sweden</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">CONTACT Mohamed E. El Zowalaty <email xlink:href="mailto:elzow005@gmail.com">elzow005@gmail.com</email>; Josef D. J&#x000e4;rhult <email xlink:href="mailto:josef.jarhult@medsci.uu.se">josef.jarhult@medsci.uu.se</email> Zoonosis Science Center, Department of Medical Biochemistry and Microbiology, Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id seq="15">1792620</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 The Author(s). Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &#x00026; Francis Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="ZIEE_10_1792620.pdf"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>SARS-CoV-2 is a zoonotic <italic>Betacoronavirus&#x000a0;</italic>causing the devastating COVID-19 pandemic. More than twelve million COVID-19 cases and 500 thousand fatalities have been reported in 216 countries. Although SARS-CoV-2 originated in China, comparatively fewer people have been affected in other Asian countries than in Europe and the USA.&#x000a0;This study examined the hypothesis that lower temperature may increase the spread of SARS-CoV-2&#x000a0;by comparing attack rate and case fatality rate (until 21 March 2020) to mean temperature in&#x000a0;January&#x02013;February 2020. The attack rate was highest in Luxembourg followed by Italy and Switzerland. There was a significant (p = 0.02) correlation between decreased attack rate and increased environmental temperature. The case fatality rate was highest in Italy followed by Iran and Spain. There was no significant correlation between the case fatality rate and temperature. This study indicates that lower temperature may increase SARS-CoV-2 transmission (measured as an increased attack rate), but there is no evidence that temperature affects the severity of the disease&#x000a0;(measured as case fatality rate). However, there are clearly other factors that affect the transmission of SARS-CoV-2,&#x000a0;and many of these may be sensitive to interventions, e.g. through increased public awareness&#x000a0;and public health response.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>KEYWORDS</title><kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd><kwd>coronaviruses</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>environmental temperature</kwd><kwd>pandemic</kwd><kwd>attack rate</kwd><kwd>case fatality rate</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="1"/><ref-count count="31"/><page-count count="6"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001" disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Emerging infectious diseases, including infections caused by coronaviruses, continue to pose a threat to public health globally in recent years. Severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) and Middle East respiratory syndrome (MERS) are two coronaviral diseases with demonstrated potential to generate significant outbreaks [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In particular, MERS continues to pose a significant threat in the Middle East since its emergence in Saudi Arabia in 2012. SARS-CoV-2 is a&#x000a0;zoonotic&#x000a0;<italic>Betacoronavirus</italic>, which likely originated from bats and is now transmitted between humans. It emerged in late December&#x000a0;2019 in Wuhan in China and causes COVID-19 pandemic which is the first coronavirus&#x000a0;pandemic causing global challenges. SARS coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) emerged in Wuhan, China, in late December 2019. A cluster of patients reported and presented with a common link in a seafood wholesale market (fish market with live animals of different species, including wildlife being sold) in Wuhan (Hubei, China), with pneumonia of initially unknown origin, and the etiologic agent was quickly identified as a novel coronavirus [<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], which was later designated as SARS-CoV-2 [<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. SARS-CoV-2 causes Coronavirus disease-2019 (COVID-19), an acute respiratory disease, and represents the most recent introduction of a high pathogenic coronavirus into the human population. SARS-CoV-2 is the seventh coronavirus known to infect humans. The emergence of SARS-CoV-2 as a human coronavirus came after the emergence of MERS-CoV in less than a 10-year period. This recent emergence of a previously unknown coronavirus in China has led to huge impacts on humans globally. SARS-CoV-2 and the subsequent COVID-19 pandemic resulted in devastating health and economic impacts on humans [<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. SARS-CoV-2 has caused more than twelve million reported and confirmed cases and more than 500 thousands fatalities in 216 countries around the globe, with more than three million reported cases in the USA as of 9 July 2020 [<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p>Despite recent efforts in basic and translational influenza and coronavirus research, there is still no vaccine against coronavirus for use in humans including SARS and MERS [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. COVID-19 now reached the required epidemiological standards for a pandemic [<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. To mitigate an emerging pandemic infectious disease like COVID-19, assessing transmissibility is crucial. The large movement of people in the Asian region and between China and globally due to the lunar new year celebrated in China likely increased the rapid geographical dispersal of infection during the initial outbreak [<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Relatively low environmental temperature may have increased the spread of the virus in China. Similarly, countries with relatively low environmental temperature may be more affected than high environmental temperature countries during the recent outbreak due to better viral survival. There are few studies available on global risk factors of COVID-19 transmission and pattern of spread [<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Rigorous testing and case-based interventions have so far formed key pieces of successful control efforts, e.g. in Singapore and Hong Kong [<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Many other countries are adopting measures termed &#x02018;social distancing&#x02019; or &#x02018;physical distancing&#x02019;, including closing schools and workplaces, limiting gatherings, using face masks, avoiding physical contact when greeting, and implementing cough etiquette. In the initial phase, the infection was epidemic with an estimated basic reproduction number (<italic>R<sub>0</sub></italic>) of 2.2 and the case number doubled on average every 7.4&#x000a0;days [<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. China was able to reduce the cases more than 90% by implementing strict containment measures. Other affected countries like Italy, Spain, and Iran have not been able to successfully replicate this containment strategy [<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. To further test the hypothesis of temperature affecting the transmission rate, the present study aimed to investigate the correlation of environmental temperature to attack rate and case fatality rate of COVID-19.</p></sec><sec id="s0002" disp-level="1"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s0002-s2001" disp-level="2"><title>Data</title><p>We extracted population data (total population in 2019) for the affected countries from the world population review database. We extracted COVID-19 data regarding new cases, total cases, and total deaths from the World Health Organization (WHO) database [<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. We included WHO data from January 2020 (beginning of the outbreak) until 21 March 2020. Furthermore, we extracted weather data (temperature) from the Trading Economics (monthly average temperature data by country). We used the mean temperature of January and February 2020 for each country as a measure of environmental temperature during the study period. There are variations in data recording and disease-tracking systems in different countries, which we consider a limitation of the study.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2002" disp-level="2"><title>Assessment of attack rate and case fatality rate</title><p>Attack rate and case fatality rate were calculated using the formulae [<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] described below:
<disp-formula-group><disp-formula id="um0001"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="ZIEE_A_1792620_UM0001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="d1e351"><mml:mtext>AR</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">n</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow/></mml:mfrac></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula></disp-formula-group></p><p>Here, AR is the attack rate, <italic>n</italic> is the number of new cases among the population during the period, and <italic>N</italic> is the population at risk at the beginning of the period.</p><p>and case fatality rate was calculated using the formula: <disp-formula-group><disp-formula id="um0002"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="ZIEE_A_1792620_UM0002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="d1e383"><mml:mtext>CFR</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext mathvariant="italic">n</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow/></mml:mfrac></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula></disp-formula-group></p><p>Here, CFR is the case fatality rate, <italic>n</italic> is the number of death due to the particular disease, and <italic>N</italic> is the total number of cases due to the same disease.</p><p>The attack rate was multiplied by 1000 to be expressed as cases per 100,000 population, while the case fatality rate was expressed as percent as per the output from the formula.</p></sec><sec id="s0002-s2003" disp-level="2"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Pearson&#x02019;s coefficient was calculated using the &#x02018;PEARSON&#x02019; formula in Excel. The <italic>t</italic>-statistic was calculated using the formula:<disp-formula-group><disp-formula id="um0003"><graphic xlink:href="ZIEE_A_1792620_UM0003.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula></disp-formula-group></p><p>where <italic>t</italic> =&#x000a0;<italic>t</italic>-statistic, <italic>r</italic> =&#x000a0;absolute value of Pearson&#x02019;s coefficient, and <italic>n</italic> =&#x000a0;number of observations. The <italic>p</italic>-value was calculated from the <italic>t</italic>-statistic in Excel using the &#x02018;TDIST&#x02019; function and a two-tailed test.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0003" disp-level="1"><title>Results</title><p>The environmental temperature varied markedly by country based on their geographical location. Some of the Asian countries and most of the European countries and North America experienced low environmental temperatures during the study period. The attack rate (in 100,000 population) of COVID-19 in China was 5.67. However, outside of China, there were countries with markedly higher attack rates: 78.60 in Luxembourg followed by 77.65 in Italy, 56.33 in Switzerland, 42.75 in Spain, 32.38 in Norway, 29.58 in Austria, 23.69 in Iran, 21.93 in Germany, 21.74 in Denmark, 19.55 in Belgium, 19.36 in France, 17.51 in the Netherlands, and 17.17 in South Korea. It was found that the attack rate decreased significantly with increased temperature (<italic>p</italic> =&#x000a0;0.02, <italic>r</italic> =&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.36, <italic>t</italic> =&#x000a0;2.35, DF&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;37) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1</xref>).</p><p>Mean temperature during January and February 2020, attack rate until March 21, and case fatality rate until March 21 are given in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The case fatality rate was highest in Italy (8.57%) followed by Indonesia (8.09%), Iran (7.29%), Iraq (7.25%), Spain (5.01%), the UK (4.44%), China (4.00%), France (3.56%), and the Netherlands (3.54%) (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).
<fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>The correlation between environmental temperature and attack rate in different countries. <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;coefficient of determination.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="ZIEE_A_1792620_F0001_OC"/><graphic specific-use="print-only" content-type="black-white" xlink:href="ZIEE_A_1792620_F0001_PB"/></alternatives></fig>
<table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Attack rates and case fatality rates of countries of the continents.</p></caption><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col width="1*" align="left"/><col width="1*" align="left"/><col width="1*" align="char" char="."/><col width="1*" align="left"/><col width="1*" align="char" char="."/><col width="1*" align="char" char="."/><col width="1*" align="char" char="."/><col width="1*" align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left">Continent</th><th align="center">Countries</th><th align="center" char=".">Mean Temp (<sup>&#x000b0;</sup>&#x000a0;C) of January and February 2020</th><th align="center">Population<break/>in 2019</th><th align="center" char=".">Total cases</th><th align="center" char=".">Total deaths</th><th align="center" char=".">AR</th><th align="center" char=".">CFR</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="11" align="left">Asia</td><td align="left">China</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;2.285</td><td align="left">1,433,783,686</td><td align="char" char=".">81,416</td><td align="char" char=".">3261</td><td align="char" char=".">5.678</td><td align="char" char=".">4.006</td></tr><tr><td align="left">India</td><td align="char" char=".">20.485</td><td align="left">1,366,417,754</td><td align="char" char=".">231</td><td align="char" char=".">4</td><td align="char" char=".">0.017</td><td align="char" char=".">1.732</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Indonesia</td><td align="char" char=".">26.48</td><td align="left">270,625,568</td><td align="char" char=".">309</td><td align="char" char=".">25</td><td align="char" char=".">0.114</td><td align="char" char=".">8.091</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Iran</td><td align="char" char=".">9.205</td><td align="left">82,913,906</td><td align="char" char=".">19,644</td><td align="char" char=".">1433</td><td align="char" char=".">23.692</td><td align="char" char=".">7.295</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Iraq</td><td align="char" char=".">12.565</td><td align="left">39,309,783</td><td align="char" char=".">193</td><td align="char" char=".">14</td><td align="char" char=".">0.491</td><td align="char" char=".">7.254</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Japan</td><td align="char" char=".">6.67</td><td align="left">126,860,301</td><td align="char" char=".">1007</td><td align="char" char=".">35</td><td align="char" char=".">0.794</td><td align="char" char=".">3.476</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Lebanon</td><td align="char" char=".">10.815</td><td align="left">6,855,713</td><td align="char" char=".">163</td><td align="char" char=".">4</td><td align="char" char=".">2.378</td><td align="char" char=".">2.454</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Malaysia</td><td align="char" char=".">25.885</td><td align="left">31,949,777</td><td align="char" char=".">1030</td><td align="char" char=".">2</td><td align="char" char=".">3.224</td><td align="char" char=".">0.194</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pakistan</td><td align="char" char=".">13.46</td><td align="left">216,565,318</td><td align="char" char=".">495</td><td align="char" char=".">3</td><td align="char" char=".">0.229</td><td align="char" char=".">0.606</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Philippines</td><td align="char" char=".">26.025</td><td align="left">108,116,615</td><td align="char" char=".">230</td><td align="char" char=".">18</td><td align="char" char=".">0.213</td><td align="char" char=".">7.826</td></tr><tr><td align="left">South Korea</td><td align="char" char=".">4.8</td><td align="left">51,225,308</td><td align="char" char=".">8799</td><td align="char" char=".">103</td><td align="char" char=".">17.177</td><td align="char" char=".">1.171</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Australia</td><td align="left">Australia</td><td align="char" char=".">27.505</td><td align="left">25,203,198</td><td align="char" char=".">874</td><td align="char" char=".">7</td><td align="char" char=".">3.468</td><td align="char" char=".">0.801</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Eurasia</td><td align="left">Turkey</td><td align="char" char=".">4.71</td><td align="left">83,429,615</td><td align="char" char=".">670</td><td align="char" char=".">9</td><td align="char" char=".">0.803</td><td align="char" char=".">1.343</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="18" align="left">Europe</td><td align="left">Austria</td><td align="char" char=".">3.15</td><td align="left">8,955,102</td><td align="char" char=".">2649</td><td align="char" char=".">6</td><td align="char" char=".">29.581</td><td align="char" char=".">0.227</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Belgium</td><td align="char" char=".">9.04</td><td align="left">390,353</td><td align="char" char=".">2257</td><td align="char" char=".">37</td><td align="char" char=".">19.559</td><td align="char" char=".">1.639</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Bulgaria</td><td align="char" char=".">5.31</td><td align="left">7,000,119</td><td align="char" char=".">127</td><td align="char" char=".">3</td><td align="char" char=".">1.814</td><td align="char" char=".">2.362</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Denmark</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;2.34</td><td align="left">5,771,876</td><td align="char" char=".">1255</td><td align="char" char=".">9</td><td align="char" char=".">21.743</td><td align="char" char=".">0.717</td></tr><tr><td align="left">France</td><td align="char" char=".">8.675</td><td align="left">65,129,728</td><td align="char" char=".">12,612</td><td align="char" char=".">450</td><td align="char" char=".">19.364</td><td align="char" char=".">3.568</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Germany</td><td align="char" char=".">7.245</td><td align="left">83,517,045</td><td align="char" char=".">18,323</td><td align="char" char=".">45</td><td align="char" char=".">21.939</td><td align="char" char=".">0.246</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Greece</td><td align="char" char=".">8.895</td><td align="left">10,473,455</td><td align="char" char=".">495</td><td align="char" char=".">8</td><td align="char" char=".">4.726</td><td align="char" char=".">1.616</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ireland</td><td align="char" char=".">8.11</td><td align="left">4,882,495</td><td align="char" char=".">683</td><td align="char" char=".">3</td><td align="char" char=".">13.989</td><td align="char" char=".">0.439</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Italy</td><td align="char" char=".">8.295</td><td align="left">60,550,075</td><td align="char" char=".">47,021</td><td align="char" char=".">4032</td><td align="char" char=".">77.656</td><td align="char" char=".">8.575</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Luxembourg</td><td align="char" char=".">1.25</td><td align="left">615,729</td><td align="char" char=".">484</td><td align="char" char=".">5</td><td align="char" char=".">78.606</td><td align="char" char=".">1.033</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Netherlands</td><td align="char" char=".">2.45</td><td align="left">17,097,130</td><td align="char" char=".">2994</td><td align="char" char=".">106</td><td align="char" char=".">17.512</td><td align="char" char=".">3.540</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Norway</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;1.89</td><td align="left">5,378,857</td><td align="char" char=".">1742</td><td align="char" char=".">7</td><td align="char" char=".">32.386</td><td align="char" char=".">0.402</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Poland</td><td align="char" char=".">4.895</td><td align="left">37,887,768</td><td align="char" char=".">425</td><td align="char" char=".">5</td><td align="char" char=".">1.123</td><td align="char" char=".">1.176</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Portugal</td><td align="char" char=".">11.9</td><td align="left">10,226,187</td><td align="char" char=".">1020</td><td align="char" char=".">6</td><td align="char" char=".">9.974</td><td align="char" char=".">0.588</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Spain</td><td align="char" char=".">9.79</td><td align="left">46,736,776</td><td align="char" char=".">19,980</td><td align="char" char=".">1002</td><td align="char" char=".">42.750</td><td align="char" char=".">5.015</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sweden</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;1.845</td><td align="left">10,036,379</td><td align="char" char=".">1623</td><td align="char" char=".">16</td><td align="char" char=".">16.171</td><td align="char" char=".">0.986</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Switzerland</td><td align="char" char=".">3.23</td><td align="left">8,591,365</td><td align="char" char=".">4840</td><td align="char" char=".">43</td><td align="char" char=".">56.336</td><td align="char" char=".">0.888</td></tr><tr><td align="left">UK</td><td align="char" char=".">7.565</td><td align="left">67,530,172</td><td align="char" char=".">3983</td><td align="char" char=".">177</td><td align="char" char=".">5.898</td><td align="char" char=".">4.444</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left">North America</td><td align="left">Canada</td><td align="char" char=".">&#x02212;15.08</td><td align="left">37,411,047</td><td align="char" char=".">971</td><td align="char" char=".">12</td><td align="char" char=".">2.595</td><td align="char" char=".">1.236</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Costa Rica</td><td align="char" char=".">24.865</td><td align="left">5,047,561</td><td align="char" char=".">113</td><td align="char" char=".">2</td><td align="char" char=".">2.239</td><td align="char" char=".">1.770</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mexico</td><td align="char" char=".">18.095</td><td align="left">127,575,529</td><td align="char" char=".">203</td><td align="char" char=".">2</td><td align="char" char=".">0.159</td><td align="char" char=".">0.985</td></tr><tr><td align="left">USA</td><td align="char" char=".">0.515</td><td align="left">329,064,917</td><td align="char" char=".">19,624</td><td align="char" char=".">260</td><td align="char" char=".">5.964</td><td align="char" char=".">1.325</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left">South America</td><td align="left">Argentina</td><td align="char" char=".">18.79</td><td align="left">44,780,677</td><td align="char" char=".">158</td><td align="char" char=".">3</td><td align="char" char=".">0.353</td><td align="char" char=".">1.899</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Brazil</td><td align="char" char=".">24.47</td><td align="left">211,049,527</td><td align="char" char=".">904</td><td align="char" char=".">11</td><td align="char" char=".">0.428</td><td align="char" char=".">1.217</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ecuador</td><td align="char" char=".">21.375</td><td align="left">17,373,662</td><td align="char" char=".">426</td><td align="char" char=".">7</td><td align="char" char=".">2.452</td><td align="char" char=".">1.643</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Peru</td><td align="char" char=".">20.925</td><td align="left">32,510,453</td><td align="char" char=".">263</td><td align="char" char=".">3</td><td align="char" char=".">0.809</td><td align="char" char=".">1.141</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p>Total populations and total cases and total deaths in COVID-19 as of 21 March 2020. The mean temperature of January and February 2020 is included. Only countries with population more than 50,000 and at least 100 total cases with at least two total deaths are included.</p></fn><fn id="tfn0002"><p>AR: attack rate; CFR: case fatality rate.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>The present analysis showed no significant correlation between case fatality rate and environmental temperature (<italic>p</italic> =&#x000a0;0.27, <italic>r</italic> =&#x000a0;0.18, <italic>t</italic> =&#x000a0;1.11, DF&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;37) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2</xref>).
<fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>The correlation between environmental temperature and case fatality rate in different countries. <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;coefficient of determination.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="ZIEE_A_1792620_F0002_OC"/><graphic specific-use="print-only" content-type="black-white" xlink:href="ZIEE_A_1792620_F0002_PB"/></alternatives></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0004" disp-level="1"><title>Discussion</title><p>SARS-CoV-2 which caused the COVID-19 pandemic originated in China, but interestingly, the neighboring countries with relatively high environmental temperature (Taiwan, Thailand, Myanmar, Nepal, Sri Lanka, and Bangladesh) were relatively less affected than the neighboring countries with low environmental temperature (South Korea, Iran, and Japan). Understanding the stability and transmissibility of viruses in different environmental temperature conditions is critical to recognize the transmission dynamics of a novel infectious agent including SARS-CoV-2 which caused the COVID-19 pandemic. Temperature along with other environmental factors including humidity and ultraviolet radiation is known to affect the transmission of infectious diseases (including viruses) within the community [<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. There are also differences in human behavior that likely contribute to the transmission of viruses; for example, spread is more likely in crowded indoor environments [<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Further, the human immune system may become slightly impaired in cold weather as both vitamin D and melatonin are depleted due to shorter daylight [<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p><p>Early in the COVID-19 outbreak, Asian countries with relatively lower environmental temperature (e.g. South Korea, Japan, Indonesia, and Iran) had more severe outbreaks than warmer countries (e.g. Singapore, Taiwan, Malaysia, Nepal, Bangladesh, and Thailand). In the further spread of COVID-19 also, other countries with low environmental temperature were severely affected in Europe (including Luxembourg, Italy, Spain, Germany, Belgium, the Netherlands, and the UK). Our study demonstrated a significant correlation between environmental temperature and attack rate, where a higher environmental temperature is correlated to a lower COVID-19 attack rate. However, the relatively low <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> value indicates that there are also other factors substantially affecting transmission. Temperature is a strong predictor of influenza seasonality in high latitudes, suggesting that cold temperatures may drive seasonal epidemics in these regions [<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Individuals in temperate regions spend the majority of their time indoors where the temperature is managed and does not correlate well with outdoor temperatures. Nevertheless, temperature may affect the timing of influenza epidemics through mechanisms independent of virus survival; for example, low outdoor temperatures may promote indoor crowding, thereby increasing person-to-person contact rates. As the temperature is now increasing in temperate countries in the Northern Hemisphere, and decreasing in the Southern, it will be interesting to follow SARS-CoV-2 transmission over time.</p><p>The distance droplets travel depends on the velocity and mechanism by which respiratory droplets are propelled from the source (coughing or sneezing), the density of respiratory secretions, environmental factors such as temperature and humidity, and the ability of the pathogen to maintain infectivity over that distance. The interaction between temperature and humidity on viral activity is challenging to assess [<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. The human coronavirus associated with the common cold was reported to remain viable only for 3&#x000a0;h on environmental surfaces after drying. However, it remains viable for many days in liquid suspension [<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. In aerosolized form, human coronavirus 229E is generally less stable in high humidity [<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The virus is stable for 3&#x000a0;weeks at room temperature in a wet environment, but it is easily killed by heat at 56&#x000b0;C for 15&#x000a0;min [<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. SARS-CoV-2 may retain its infectivity up to 2&#x000a0;weeks at low temperatures and low humidity environment. This indicates that SARS CoV-2 may be a stable virus transmittable by indirect contact or fomites [<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Thus, contaminated surfaces may play a significant role in the transmission of infection in the hospital and the community [<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p><p>Importantly, environmental temperature is not a driver of COVID-19 transmission that is possible to influence, and thus, it is necessary for governments to focus on the implementation of public health interventions in a timely manner. Due to the lack of vaccines and specific antiviral drugs against SARS-CoV-2, the implementation of handwashing and other hygiene-related interventions, restrictions of movements in and between countries [<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], and avoiding mass gatherings are plausible measures. The implication of such basic strategies to mitigate SARS-CoV-2 spread may also reduce the significant burden on the economy created by the pandemic [<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s0005" disp-level="1"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In our study, the lower environmental temperature of a country was correlated to a higher attack rate of SARS-CoV-2. This may explain some of the variations of COVID-19 burden seen in different countries. The environmental temperature had no significant correlation to case fatality rate in our study, suggesting that environmental temperature affects transmission rather than disease severity. As the environmental temperature is not possible to affect transmission, other public health measures are imperative to mitigate the COVID-19 pandemic. Public awareness including personal interventions (movement restriction, social and physical distancing, and hygiene) and increased public health response including case detection, isolation, and contact tracing may help reduce the spread of the virus and decrease the fatalities due to this pandemic.</p></sec></body><back><bio id="b0001"><p><bold><italic>Mohammad M. Hassan, PhD</italic></bold> is a professor and epidemiologist, with research interests in Virology, Immunology, Microbiology, Therapeutic interventions, Epidemiology, Ecology of infectious diseases, Emerging zoonotic pathogens and One Health.</p></bio><bio id="b0002"><p><bold><italic>Mohamed Ezzat El Zowalaty, PhD,</italic></bold> is an associate professor affiliated to Zoonosis Science Center,&#x000a0;Uppsala University, Sweden, an adjunct faculty at the Department of Clinical Sciences, College of Medicine, University of Sharjah, UAE, and an International Research Collaborator at Duke One Health, Duke University, North Carolina, USA. Dr. ME El Zowalaty is&#x000a0;a virologist and microbiologist researching emerging infectious diseases, zoonotic viruses and bacteria, antimicrobial resistance at animal-human-environmental interface, and One Health.</p></bio><bio id="b0003"><p><bold><italic>Shahneaz A. Khan, PhD</italic></bold> is an associate Professor and molecular biologists, with&#x000a0; research interests in Biochemistry, Molecular biology, Immunology, Microbiology,&#x000a0; Molecular epidemiology, and Emerging zoonotic pathogens.</p></bio><bio id="b0004"><p><bold><italic>Ariful Islam</italic></bold>, DVM is a veterinary epidemiologist and disease ecologist, working as a senior scientist in Bangladesh field program in EcoHealth Alliance. His research focuses on understanding zoonotic disease emergence and the ecology and evolution of bats and their associated viruses such as Nipah and Ebola viruses, along with SARS, Midde East Respiratory Syndrome (MERS), and other pathogens at the animal, human, and ecosystem.</p></bio><bio id="b0005"><p><bold><italic>Md. Raihan K. Nayem,</italic></bold>&#x000a0; is a postgraduate student at Faculty of Veterinary Medicine; Chattogram Veterinary and Animal Sciences University, Bangladesh, working on infectious disease epidemiology, AMR and One Health.</p></bio><bio id="b0006"><p><bold><italic>Josef J&#x000e4;rhult, MD, PhD,</italic></bold> is a Consultant, Associate Professor, and Senior Lecturer in Infectious Diseases at Uppsala University/University Hospital. His main research interests are zoonotic diseases and antimicrobial drug resistance in the human-animal-environment interface.</p></bio><sec id="s0006" disp-level="1" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Disclosure statement</title><p>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the authors.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdirizak</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chowell</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Evaluating the potential impact of targeted vaccination strategies against severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) and Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) outbreaks in the healthcare setting</article-title>. <source>Theor Biol Med Modell</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>16</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>A novel coronavirus from patients with pneumonia in China, 2019</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>382</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>727</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31978945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Detection of Covid-19 in children in early January 2020 in Wuhan, China1</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>382</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<page-range>1370&#x02013;1371</page-range>. .</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">Gorbalenya A, Baker S, Baric R et al</person-group>
<article-title>The species severe acute respiratory syndrome-related coronavirus: classifying 2019-nCoV and naming it SARS-CoV-2</article-title>. <source>Nat Microbiol</source>. <year>2020</year>;536&#x02013;544 (2020). doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41564-020-0695-z</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El Zowalaty</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>J&#x000e4;rhult</surname><given-names>JD.</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Environmental impact of the COVID-19 pandemic &#x02013; a lesson for the future</source>. <publisher-name>Taylor &#x00026; Francis</publisher-name>; <year>2020</year>. Infec Ecol Epidemiol 10 (1):1768023. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/20008686.2020.1768023</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><article-title>Coronavirus COVID-19 Global Cases by Johns Hopkins, The Center for Systems Science and Engineering (CSSE)</article-title>; <year>2020</year> [<date-in-citation>cited 09 July 2020</date-in-citation>]. <comment>Availabe from:</comment>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://gisanddata.maps.arcgis.com/apps/opsdashboard/index.html#/bda7594740fd40299423467b48e9ecf6">https://gisanddata.maps.arcgis.com/apps/opsdashboard/index.html#/bda7594740fd40299423467b48e9ecf6</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>An interactive web-based dashboard to track COVID-19 in real time</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>533</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>534</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32087114</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Time to use the p-word? Coronavirus enter dangerous new phase</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>579</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/d41586-020-00551-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32132700</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Yang Z, Gao W, Zhao X, Hao C, Xie X (2020) Spatiotemporal Patterns of Population Mobility and its Determinants in Chinese Cities Based on Travel Big Data. Sustainability 2020; 12 (10):4012;&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su121040121</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Nowcasting and forecasting the potential domestic and international spread of the 2019-nCoV outbreak originating in Wuhan, China: a modelling study</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>395</volume>(<issue>10225</issue>):<fpage>689</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>697</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32014114</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bogoch</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas-Bachli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Potential for global spread of a novel coronavirus from China</article-title>. <source>J Travel Med</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>2</issue>). doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jtm/taaa011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="newspaper">Chinazzi M, Davis JT, Gioannini C, et al. <article-title>Preliminary assessment of the International Spreading Risk Associated with the 2019 novel Coronavirus (2019-nCoV) outbreak in Wuhan city</article-title>. <source>Lab. Model. Biol. Soc.&#x02013;Techn. Syst</source>; <year>2020</year> Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.mobs-lab.org/uploads/6/7/8/7/6787877/wuhan_novel_coronavirus__6_.pdf">https://www.mobs-lab.org/uploads/6/7/8/7/6787877/wuhan_novel_coronavirus__6_.pdf</ext-link> (accessed on 5 April 2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haider</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yavlinsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Passengers&#x02018; destinations from China: low risk of novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) transmission into Africa and South America</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Infect</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>148</volume>:<fpage>e41</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32100667</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heesterbeek</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klinkenberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>How will country-based mitigation measures influence the course of the COVID-19 epidemic?</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>395</volume>(<issue>10228</issue>):<fpage>931</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>934</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32164834</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Early transmission dynamics in Wuhan, China, of novel coronavirus&#x02013;infected pneumonia</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>382</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<page-range>1199&#x02013;1207</page-range>. .</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Remuzzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Remuzzi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>COVID-19 and Italy: what next?</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>395</volume>(<issue>10231</issue>):<page-range>1225&#x02013;1228</page-range>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">Ritchie H, Coronavirus source data.&#x000a0;Available at&#x000a0;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ourworldindata.org/coronavirus-source-data">https://ourworldindata.org/coronavirus-source-data</ext-link>. Accessed 22 March 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanchan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Unnikrishnan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<chapter-title>Mortality: statistics</chapter-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Payne-James</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Byard</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group>, editors. <source>Encyclopedia of forensic and legal medicine</source>. <edition>2nd</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>; <year>2016</year> p. <fpage>572</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>577</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fares</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Factors influencing the seasonal patterns of infectious diseases</article-title>. <source>Int J Prev Med</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>128</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>132</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23543865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernstrom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldblatt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Aerobiology and its role in the transmission of infectious diseases</article-title>. <source>J Pathog</source>. <year>2013</year>;<fpage>2013:</fpage>493960. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2013/493960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinter-Wollman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jeli&#x00107;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The impact of the built environment on health behaviours and disease transmission in social systems</article-title>. <source>Phil Trans Royal Soc London Series B Biol Sci</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>373</volume>(<issue>1753</issue>):<fpage>20170245</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrillo-Vico</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lardone</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>&#x000c1;lvarez-S&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Melatonin: buffering the immune system</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>8638</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8683</lpage>. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23609496</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamerius</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Correction: environmental predictors of seasonal influenza epidemics across temperate and tropical climates</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<comment>e1003194-e1003194</comment>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/annotation/df689228-603f-4a40-bfbf-a38b13f88147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lowen</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Steel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz-Cherry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Roles of humidity and temperature in shaping influenza seasonality</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>88</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>7692</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7695</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24789791</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marr</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mechanisms by which ambient humidity may affect viruses in aerosols</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>6781</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6788</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22820337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>[26]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">Chan K-H, Peiris JM, Lam S, et al</person-group>
<article-title>The effects of temperature and relative humidity on the viability of the SARS coronavirus</article-title>. <source>Adv Virol</source>. <year>2011</year>;2011:734690, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2011/734690</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>[27]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Geller</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Varbanov</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duval</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Human coronaviruses: insights into environmental resistance and its influence on the development of new antiseptic strategies</article-title>. <source>Viruses</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3044</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3068</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23202515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>[28]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pirtle</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beran</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Virus survival in the environment</article-title>. <source>Rev Sci Tech</source>. <year>1991</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>733</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>748</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1782426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0029"><label>[29]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>VCC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>SKP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>PCY</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus as an agent of emerging and reemerging infection</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>660</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>694</lpage>. .<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17934078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0030"><label>[30]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Otter</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yezli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>French</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group>
<chapter-title>The role of contaminated surfaces in the transmission of nosocomial pathogens</chapter-title> In: <source>Use of biocidal surfaces for reduction of healthcare acquired infections, edited by Borkow G</source>. <publisher-name>Springer, Springer International Publishing, USA</publisher-name>; <year>2014</year> p. <fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>58</lpage>. Available at: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-08057-4_3</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0031"><label>[31]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Interventions to mitigate early spread of SARS-CoV-2 in Singapore: a modelling study</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>678&#x02013;688</page-range>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>