<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An important role in the pathogenesis of respiratory infections is being played by the virus-induced oxidative stress (Schwarz 
 <xref rid="bib236" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>; Lin 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib159" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Liu 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib162" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Khomich 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib134" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Xanthine oxidoreductase has an important role in the appearance of the symptoms and complications of virus-associated pneumonias. Xanthine oxidoreductase is a cytosolic enzyme of purine catabolism (Frederiks and Vreeling-Sindelarova 
 <xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Agarwal, Banerjee and Banerjee 
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) and its activity strongly increases in hypoxic conditions (Poss 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib216" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>; Terada 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib275" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>; Linder 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib160" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>) as well as under the influence of proinflammatory mediators and cytokines (Page 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib206" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>; Brandes 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>). In pathological conditions, xanthine oxidoreductase is released from the cells to the blood (predominantly in oxidase form; Spiekermann 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib259" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>) and fixates at the luminal surface of the plasma membrane of endothelial cells in the area of the inflammation by physical/chemical interaction with glycosaminoglycans (Akaike 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>; Adachi 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>; Rouquette 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib229" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>). Xanthine oxidoreductase located on the cytoplasmic membrane of endothelial cells produces a superoxide anion radical in the process of purine oxidation, and at the same time may redux nitrite and nitrate anions to the nitrogen oxide (NO
 <sup>•</sup>) at another active site (Jansson 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib118" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Cantu-Medellin and Kelley 
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), i.e. it can recycle this vasodilating agent. Local production of the prooxidative complex (O
 <sub>2</sub>
 <sup>–•</sup>, H
 <sub>2</sub>O
 <sub>2</sub>, NO
 <sup>•</sup>, ONOO
 <sup>–</sup>) is potentially very dangerous, especially in the vascular bed of the lungs. Nevertheless, the attempts of using allopurinol, an inhibitor of xanthine oxidoreductase (Pacher, Novorozhkin and Szabo 
 <xref rid="bib205" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; George and Struthers 
 <xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), for the treatment of influenza A virus-induced pneumonia in daily doses of 5–50 mg/kg have failed. Allopurinol has not shown any effects on the evolution and outcomes of the viral infection (Dolganova and Sharonov 
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>). Lack of therapeutic effect in this case is associated with the fact that after the inhibition of (Mo-Co)-containing center of the enzyme by allopurinol, the NADH-oxidative and nitrite-/nitrate-reductive activities of xanthine oxidoreductase, which are realized at the FAD-dependent site of the enzyme, were not affected (Harris and Massey 
 <xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>; Doel 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Boueiz, Damarla and Hassoun 
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). As there are still no approved medications able to inhibit the FAD-dependent activity of xanthine oxidoreductase, administration of heparin seems feasible as prophylaxis of pulmonary embolism with the objective of the desorption of xanthine oxidoreductase from the cytoplasmic membrane of endothelial cells (Povalyaev 
 <xref rid="bib218" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Obi 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib197" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>).
</p>
