<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During recent years, our groups, together with several others worldwide, demonstrated the ability of nutritionally derived bioactive compounds to suppress inflammatory cytokine release (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>–
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). In particular, the administration of several plant-derived polyphenols to 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> cultured immune cells suppressed the release of inflammatory cytokines (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Traditional Chinese herbal medicines for influenza treatment demonstrated potential antiviral activity (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). Polyphenol bioavailability has been long discussed, as many have observed health benefits, but few have observed circulating traces of bioactive compounds (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Nonetheless, exposure of the epithelial barrier to a polyphenol-rich environment can efficiently activate local immune suppression and tissue repair mechanisms (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>), and systemic benefits may be related to the release of circulating microRNA, defined as small non-coding RNA molecules, with anti-inflammatory effects (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). Indeed, even if orally introduced, bioactive dietary factors induce miRNA synthesis, these are packaged into exosomes and released into the bloodstream to act systemically (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Dietary factors are emerging as anti-inflammatory miRNA promoters able to regulate metabolic functions, inflammation, and oxidation systemically (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>–
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). Furthermore, herb extracts may combine antiviral, anti-inflammatory, and antioxidant activity, and tissue-repair properties (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>).
</p>
