<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig fig-type="Scheme" xml:lang="en" id="feb213784-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Scheme 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Genetic relationship of the SARS‐CoV‐2 spike (S) protein to bat and pangolin sequences as well as SARS‐CoV‐1. The scheme highlights the recombination breakpoint in the S protein gene of SARS‐CoV‐2. SARS‐CoV‐2 is ‘very’ similar to the Bat CoV RaTG13 S protein gene, except for the ACE‐2 RBD, which is more sililar to the pangolin CoV (analyses by Simplot). (A) Schematic representation of the SARS‐CoV‐2 genome, which is a single‐stranded (ss) RNA of positive polarity (+) around 30 kb, and codes for six open reading frames (ORFs) and accessory proteins. (B) Similarity plot analyses of different CoV S protein coding sequences. The SARS‐CoV‐2 NCBI reference nucleotide sequence (NC045512) was used as query. Sequences of the S protein from different CoVs are indicated in brackets with their respective animal origin, strain name and NCBI accession numbers. The ACE‐2 RBD coding region is framed with dotted lines. The pairwise similarity between all sequences in a multiple sequence alignment (
   <sc>clustalw</sc>; 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mbio.ncsu.edu/bioedit/bioedit.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.mbio.ncsu.edu/bioedit/bioedit.html</ext-link>) [
   <xref rid="feb213784-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">20</xref>] was calculated with a 200‐nt window moved along the sequence in 10 nt steps using the software 
   <sc>simplot</sc> v3.5.1 [
   <xref rid="feb213784-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">21</xref>]. (C) Neighbour joining analysis of the RBD coding region. Evolutionary distances were calculated by the Kimura two‐parameter method, with 1000 bootstrap replications to estimate node consistencies. The length of the branch is proportional to the number of nucleotide divergences. Sequences are labelled with their respective accession number, animal origin, coronavirus strain and location/date of isolation. The sequence of pangolin CoV has been derived from [
   <xref rid="feb213784-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">19</xref>]. The scheme was conceived and crafted by Dr. Romain Volle, Department of Molecular Life Sciences, University of Zurich, Switzerland.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic id="nlm-graphic-1" xlink:href="FEB2-594-1127-g001" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
