<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="Tab2">
 <label>Table 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Asthma-specific recommendations from Global Initiative for Asthma (GINA) as reported on GINA website [
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]
  </p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">People with asthma should continue all of their inhaled medication, including inhaled corticosteroids, as prescribed by their doctor</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">In acute asthma attacks patients should take a short course of oral corticosteroids if instructed in their asthma action plan or by their healthcare provider, to prevent serious consequences</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">In rare cases, patients with severe asthma might require long-term treatment with oral corticosteroids (OCS) on top of their inhaled medication(s). This treatment should be continued at the lowest possible dose in these patients at risk of severe attacks/exacerbations. Biologic therapies should be used in severe asthma patients who qualify for them, in order to limit the need for OCS as much as possible</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <p>Nebulizers should, where possible, be avoided for acute attacks due to the increased risk of disseminating COVID-19 (to other patients AND to physicians, nurses and other personnel)</p>
     <p> Pressurized metered dose inhaler (pMDI) via a spacer is the preferred treatment during severe attacks. (Spacers must not be shared at home)</p>
     <p> While a patient is being treated for a severe attack, their maintenance inhaled asthma treatment should be continued (at home AND in the hospital)</p>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Patients with allergic rhinitis should continue to take their nasal corticosteroids, as prescribed by their clinician</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Routine spirometry testing should be suspended to reduce the risk of viral transmission, and if absolutely necessary, adequate infection control measures should be taken</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
