<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The ability to predict disease outbreaks will provide a mechanism for policymakers and health-care services to respond to epidemics in a timely manner, reducing the impact and maximizing the limited resources available to be deployed[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The timing and severity of infectious disease outbreaks, two matters of considerable public-health relevance, are the main challenges when attempting to predict disease outbreaks[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Attempts to set up prediction frameworks for anticipating epidemics for other diseases such as dengue and influenza were pursued in the recent past with different degree of success, but clear added value[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. These systems proved effective to better anticipate future outbreaks and increase our understanding on mechanisms driving disease variability. To this end, a threshold quantity that is most important to anticipate the risk of future outbreaks is the basic reproduction number (
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub>). There are quite a few studies that estimated 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> for the current MERS-CoV outbreak. Majumdar et al.[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] for instance, estimated 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> for Jeddah and Riyadh using a function called Incidence Decay with Exponential Adjustments (IDEA). They found that the estimate of 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> in Jeddah and Riyadh are in the ranges (3.5–6.7) and (2.0–2.8), respectively. A stochastic epidemiological model of MERS-CoV with zoonotic and human-to-human transmission was considered by Poletto et al.[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] to quantify the rates of generation of cases from those two transmission routes. They found that spring 2014 cases led to the increase in transmission rates, which brings 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> to values above unity. Heishet al.[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] used a simple mathematical model to trace the temporal course of South Korea MERS-CoV outbreak. They estimated 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> to be in the range of 7.0 to 19.3. Instead, Nishiura 
 <italic>et</italic> al.[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] estimated the expected number of secondary cases following the importation of an index case (countries other than KSA, Qatar and UAE), using a branching process type modelling approach. They also suggested that even if 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> is below unity, a large cluster of cases with multiple generations might occur. The aforementioned studies indicated that the basic reproduction number is above unity, although there are few studies that suggest 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> is less than one[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. However, at the same time, intriguing differences in observed and predicted scenarios clearly suggested other important factors might be missing in previous models built for these MERS-CoV case studies. For instance, in a recent survey for Mers-CoV in over 1300 Saudi Arabian camels, Sabiret al.[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] found that camels share three coronaviruses (CoV) species with humans. Among them, one has been dominant in the region since December 2014 and led to the human MERS-CoV outbreaks occurring in 2015. The wide species range of CoVs and their propensity to cross species boundaries suggest that more MERS-CoV uncontained outbreaks may likely occur in the future. Zumlaet al.[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] also suggested that MERS-CoV species can mutate to have increased inter-human transmissibility. Cottenet al.[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] used MERS data from the period May to September 2013. They found four Saudi Arabia MERS-CoV phylogenetic clades, with 3 clades apparently no longer contributing to current cases, therefore not appearing in the saliva of camels. They also show that the ancestors of most of the viral clades originated in Riyadh (See Cotten et al.[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]). Recently, strain variability in MERS-CoV infection was confirmed in 51 respiratory samples from 32 patients, confirming that more than one strain of human MERS-CoVis present[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The fact that more than one MERS-CoV strain is currently circulating in Saudi Arabia should be properly accounted for as this presence may have substantially contributed to amplify the transmission intensity producing repeated MERS-CoV changes in incidence through their periodic reintroduction into human populations[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Furthermore, Chan et al.[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] characterized MERS-CoV viruses from dromedaries in Saudi Arabia and Egypt and compared them with a human MERS-CoV reference strain. They isolated three dromedary strains, two from Saudi Arabia and one from Egypt. The human and dromedary MERS-CoV strains had similar viral replication competence in Vero-E6 cells and respiratory tropism in ex-vivo cultures of the human respiratory tract. They also suggested that dromedary viruses from Saudi Arabia and Egypt are probably infectious to human beings[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008065.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].
</p>
