<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="editorial"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BMJ-UK</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">bmj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The BMJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0959-8138</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1756-1833</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7202944</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">Roesch280420</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.m1712</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorials</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Violence against women during covid-19 pandemic restrictions</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Roesch</surname><given-names>Elisabeth</given-names></name><role>consultant</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>Avni</given-names></name><role>technical officer</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>Jhumka</given-names></name><role>associate professor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2 </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Moreno</surname><given-names>Claudia</given-names></name><role>acting unit head</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>Department of Sexual and Reproductive Health, World Health Organization, Geneva, Switzerland</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>Department of Global and Community Health, College of Health and Human Services, George Mason University, Fairfax, VA, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Correspondence to: C Garc&#x000ed;a-Moreno <email xlink:href="garciamorenoc@who.int">garciamorenoc@who.int</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>369</volume><elocation-id>m1712</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>Published by the BMJ Publishing Group Limited. For permission to use (where not already granted under a licence) please go to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://group.bmj.com/group/rights-licensing/permissions">http://group.bmj.com/group/rights-licensing/permissions</ext-link></copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>BMJ</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/igo/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution IGO License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/igo/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/igo/</ext-link>), which permits use, distribution, and reproduction for non-commercial purposes in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bmj.m1712.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Protections for women and girls must be built into response plans</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>As the covid-19 pandemic intensifies, its gendered effects have begun to gain attention. Though data are scarce, media coverage and reports from organisations that respond to violence against women reveal an alarming picture of increased reports of intimate partner violence during this outbreak, including partners using physical distancing measures to further isolate affected women from resources.<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> In Jianli County, Hubei province of China, a police department reported a tripling of domestic violence cases in February 2020 compared with February 2019, estimating that 90% were related to the covid-19 epidemic.<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> In the UK, a project tracking violence against women noted that deaths from domestic abuse between 23 March and 12 April had more than doubled (to 16 deaths) compared with the average rate in the previous 10 years.<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>
</p><p>These reports are disturbing yet predictable. Globally, 30% of women experience physical or sexual violence by an intimate partner in their lifetime.<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Such violence can increase during humanitarian crises, including conflict and natural disasters.<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> The gendered impacts of infectious disease epidemics are less understood and acknowledged.</p><p>Past epidemics, including Ebola<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> and Zika,<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> suggest violence against women may shift in nature and scale as outbreaks affect social and economic life.<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Half of the world&#x02019;s population is being asked to stay at home to slow the spread of covid-19.<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> For women already in abusive relationships, or at risk of such abuse, staying at home increases their risk of intimate partner violence. Children may also be exposed to intimate partner violence or be abused themselves.<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Urgent steps must be taken to address the risks of violence faced by women and children during pandemic restrictions. </p><sec sec-type="other1"><title>Pathways of risk</title><p>Household stress can increase the likelihood of intimate partner violence.<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> As people stay at home, families spend more time in close contact, including in cramped conditions. Simultaneously, the disruption of livelihoods and the ability to earn a living reduces access to basic needs and services, causing additional stress. Perpetrators of partner violence may also restrict access to money or health related items such as hand sanitiser, soap, medications, and access to health services. </p><p>The disruption of social and protective networks may further exacerbate intimate partner violence and its consequences. Women may have less contact with family and friends who provide support and protection from violence by a partner. Perpetrators may further restrict access to services, help, and psychosocial support from formal and informal networks. </p><p>As health and other support services, including sexual and reproductive health services, are scaled back, women subjected to violence may have less opportunity for receiving support and referrals from the health sector. Other essential support services such as hotlines, crisis centres, shelters, legal aid, and protection and counselling services may also be scaled back, further reducing access to help for women in abusive relationships.</p></sec><sec sec-type="other2"><title>How to respond</title><p>Although the health system is under enormous burden as covid-19 stretches the capacity of hospitals and clinics, the health sector can take steps to mitigate the risk of violence against women during the pandemic restrictions and help reduce its effects (<xref ref-type="boxed-text" rid="box1">box 1</xref>). Governments must include essential services to deal with violence against women in covid-19 response plans, resource them, and identify strategies to make them accessible during physical distancing measures. Health facilities should identify locally available support services for survivors (such as hotlines, shelters, rape crisis centres, counselling) and refer women when they seek health services.</p><boxed-text id="box1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Box 1</label><caption><title>Resources on violence against women</title></caption><list list-type="bullet" id="L1"><list-item><p>Covid-19 and violence against women: What the health sector/system can do (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/vaw-covid-19/en/">https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/vaw-covid-19/en/</ext-link>)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Violence against women during covid-19: Q&#x00026;A (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/q-a-detail/violence-against-women-during-covid-19">https://www.who.int/news-room/q-a-detail/violence-against-women-during-covid-19</ext-link>)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Health care for women subjected to intimate partner violence or sexual violence: a clinical handbook (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/violence/vaw-clinical-handbook/en/">https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/violence/vaw-clinical-handbook/en/</ext-link>)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Strengthening health systems for women subjected to intimate partner violence or sexual violence: a health manager&#x02019;s manual (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/violence/vaw-health-systems-manual/en/">https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/violence/vaw-health-systems-manual/en/</ext-link>)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Caring for women subjected to violence: a WHO curriculum for training health-care providers (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/caring-for-women-subject-to-violence/en/">https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/caring-for-women-subject-to-violence/en/</ext-link>)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Clinical management of rape and intimate partner violence survivors: developing protocols for use in humanitarian settings (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/rape-survivors-humanitarian-settings/en/">https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/rape-survivors-humanitarian-settings/en/</ext-link>)</p></list-item></list></boxed-text><p>Health providers should be aware of the risks and consequences of violence against women and provide those affected with support and relevant medical treatment.<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> It is important to ensure the maintenance of essential medical services, such as for post-rape care, including availability of the necessary medicines and other supplies. Older women, women with disabilities, women living in humanitarian crises contexts, poor women living in crowded conditions, and ethnic minorities may be disproportionately affected and have additional needs. The use of mobile health and telemedicine to safely support those experiencing violence against women must be explored urgently, as well as other means to reach women in settings where access to mobile phones or the internet is limited or lacking.<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
</p><p>Importantly, the world&#x02019;s most vulnerable populations will be affected as this pandemic reaches countries with high levels of poverty, displacement, and conflict. Humanitarian organisations need to make services available for women experiencing violence and collect data on reported cases.</p><p>We must learn lessons from past epidemics about the failures to recognise and address gender related effects of outbreaks. As the global health community grapples with how best to halt the spread of covid-19, the ongoing epidemic of violence against women cannot be ignored.</p></sec></body><back><notes><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><?igo-nc?>Competing interests:<?igo-nc?>We have read and understood BMJ policy on declaration of interests and have no interests to declare. The authors are employed by WHO. The views are those of the authors and do not represent WHO policy.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>Provenance and peer review: Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></fn></fn-group></notes><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gupta A, Stahl A. For abused women, a pandemic lockdown holds dangers of its own. <italic>New York Times</italic> 2020 Mar 24. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/03/24/us/coronavirus-lockdown-domestic-violence.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2020/03/24/us/coronavirus-lockdown-domestic-violence.html</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Graham-Harrison E, Giuffrida A, Smith H, Ford L. Lockdowns around the world bring rise in domestic violence. <italic>Guardian</italic> 2020 Mar 28. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.theguardian.com/society/2020/mar/28/lockdowns-world-rise-domestic-violence">https://www.theguardian.com/society/2020/mar/28/lockdowns-world-rise-domestic-violence</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Allen-Ebrahimian B. China&#x02019;s domestic violence epidemic. <italic>Axios</italic> 2020 Mar 7. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.axios.com/china-domestic-violence-coronavirus-quarantine-7b00c3ba-35bc-4d16-afdd-b76ecfb28882.html">https://www.axios.com/china-domestic-violence-coronavirus-quarantine-7b00c3ba-35bc-4d16-afdd-b76ecfb28882.html</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web">Grierson J. Domestic abuse killings &#x02018;more than double&#x02019; amid covid-19 lockdown. <italic>Guardian</italic> 2020 Apr 15. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.theguardian.com/society/2020/apr/15/domestic-abuse-killings-more-than-double-amid-covid-19-lockdown">https://www.theguardian.com/society/2020/apr/15/domestic-abuse-killings-more-than-double-amid-covid-19-lockdown</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>WHO</collab></person-group>
<source>Global and regional estimates of violence against women: prevalence and health effects of intimate partner violence and non-partner sexual violence.</source>
<publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>, <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zara</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The hidden disaster: domestic violence in the aftermath of natural disaster</article-title>. <source>Aust J Emerg Manag</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>28</fpage>-<lpage>35</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>UNDP</collab></person-group>
<source>Ebola recovery in Sierra Leone: tackling the rise in sexual and gender-based violence and teenage pregnancy during the ebola crisis.</source>
<publisher-name>UNDP</publisher-name>, <year>2015</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Oxfam International</collab></person-group>
<source>Dominican Republic gender analysis: study of the impact of the Zika virus on women, girls, boys and men.</source>
<publisher-name>Oxfam International</publisher-name>, <year>2017</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Erika F. Impact of covid-19 pandemic on violence against women and girls, VAWG Helpdesk Research Report No 284. VAWG Helpdesk, 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sandford A. Coronavirus: half of humanity now on lockdown as 90 countries call for confinement. Associated Press, 3 Apr 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guedes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bott</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Moreno</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Colombini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Bridging the gaps: a global review of intersections of violence against women and violence against children</article-title>. <source>Glob Health Action</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>31516</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/gha.v9.31516</pub-id>&#x000a0;
<?supplied-pmid 27329936?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27329936</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buller</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranganathan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bleile</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hidrobo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Heise</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A mixed-method review of cash transfers and intimate partner violence in low- and middle-income countries</article-title>. <source>World Bank Res Obs</source>
<year>2018</year>;<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>218</fpage>-<lpage>58.</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/wbro/lky002</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web">WHO. Health care for women subjected to intimate partner violence or sexual violence: a clinical handbook. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/violence/vaw-clinical-handbook/en/">https://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/violence/vaw-clinical-handbook/en/</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erskine</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Not just hotlines and mobile phones: gender-based violence service provision during covid-19.</source>
<publisher-name>Unicef</publisher-name>, <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>