<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this work we demonstrate, for the first time, that the human MDV A/AA/6/60 LAIV has both active PA-X and NS1 proteins that can inhibit host gene expression (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-09-00086-f001">Figure 1</xref>). Building on our previous work, we also showed that the effects of these two viral proteins is additive in a reporter assay (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-09-00086-f002">Figure 2</xref>). We also demonstrate the feasibility of generating recombinant MDV A/AA/6/60 LAIVs with altered PA-X and/or NS1 proteins (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-09-00086-f003">Figure 3</xref>). Removing PA-X, however, showed to be detrimental for viral replication and resulted in a smaller plaque phenotype in cultured cells (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-09-00086-f004">Figure 4</xref>). Conversely, removing the inhibitory function of NS1 did not adversely affect viral replication of the MDV A/AA/6/60 LAIV (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-09-00086-f004">Figure 4</xref>). These trends were also seen in vivo. While all the MDV A/AA/6/60 LAIVs were still fully attenuated and did not result in any weight loss in mice, viruses lacking PA-X showed reduced viral replication in lungs and nasal turbinate, while those lacking a functional NS1 resembled the parental WT MDV A/AA/6/60 LAIV (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-09-00086-f005">Figure 5</xref>). Even with the reduced replication seen in some of these viruses, all of them were able to induce similar protective antibody responses (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-09-00086-f006">Figure 6</xref>) that provided full protection against a lethal homologous challenge with pH1N1 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-09-00086-f007">Figure 7</xref>). However, while all of the MDV A/AA/6/60 LAIVs were protective against weight loss and mortality, there were differences in the amount of pH1N1 detected in the lungs of challenged mice at Days 2 and 4 p.i., with the parental WT MDV A/AA/6/60 LAIV showing the least amount of virus in the lungs and the double mutant MDV A/AA/6/60 LAIV (PA
 <sub>MT</sub>
 <sup>−</sup>/NS1
 <sub>MT</sub>
 <sup>−</sup>) showing the most pH1N1 viral replication (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-09-00086-f007">Figure 7</xref>).
</p>
