<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0130">Melatonin was found to exhibit effective inhibition of pathological manifestations in cases with viral infections in humans (
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Reiter et al., 2020</xref>) and plants (
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2020</xref>). As SARS-CoV-2 is a newly discovered virus, there is a shortage of research in the literature, which delays the development of effective treatment strategies and in particular the potential effects of melatonin in human or experimental animals against this deadly pathogen. However, melatonin exerts remarkable antiviral effects on several viruses in humans and animals. An early work reported that encephalomyocarditis virus or the Semliki Forest virus causes severe inflammation in the nervous tissue and result in a high mortality rate. Melatonin when administered at the pharmacological dose successfully attenuated the inflammation parameters and reduced the number of deaths (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Ben-Nathan et al., 1995</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Maestroni et al., 1988</xref>). A recent report on Ebola infection demonstrated that the virus hampers the immune system and initiates blood coagulation with significant inflammation reaction that induces an overwhelmed generation of toxic free radicals and the development of oxidative stress and severe damage in cells and tissue. This eventually causes organ and system dysfunction and failure (
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Reiter et al., 2020</xref>). In this regard, these authors reported that melatonin can prevent hemorrhagic shock syndrome, a major pathological parameter, associated with Ebola virus infection. This action is mediated primarily by the reduction of circulating proinflammatory cytokines. Melatonin also upregulates heme oxygenase-1 (HO-1), which obstructs the replication of the Ebola virus (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Anderson et al., 2015</xref>). Recently, a research group confirmed that melatonin is an effective, safe, and low-cost therapeutic option for Ebola virus (
 <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Junaid et al., 2020</xref>).
</p>
