<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">Almost all the index patients of the 2019-nCoV outbreak were either sellers or visitors at the Huanan seafood market in Wuhan where besides aquatic animals even mammals and snakes were sold. It is speculated that the zoonosis of the virus happened from an intermediate host animal being sold at the market. However, no bats were being sold. It is similar to how Himalayan civets (
 <italic>Paguma larvata</italic>) acted as the intermediate host for the zoonosis of SARS CoV in 2002–03 although horseshoe bats (belonging to genus 
 <italic>Rhinolophus</italic>) were primary hosts coronaviruses are positive-sense single-stranded RNA viruses enclosed in a solar corona shaped envelope (hence the name). They belong to the sub-family 
 <italic>Coronavirinae</italic> of the family 
 <italic>Coronaviridae</italic> of the order 
 <italic>Neovirales</italic>. They are further divided into four genera—
 <italic>Alphacoronavirus, Betacoronavirus, Gammacoronavirus and Deltacoronavirus. Alphacoronavirus</italic> and 
 <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic> infect only mammals, whereas the 
 <italic>Gammacoronavirus</italic> and 
 <italic>Deltacoronavirus</italic> mostly infect birds. The 2019-nCoV along with the SARS and MERS CoV belongs to the genus 
 <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic>. Data from the phylogenetic analysis show that 2019-nCoV is distantly related to SARS CoV (with less than 79% sequence identity at genome level) or MERS CoV (less than 50% sequence identity). This proves that the 2019-nCoV is novel and distinct from the previously reported pathogenic coronaviruses. The 2019-nCoV is further classified under the sub-genera Sarbecoviruses along with two closely related (about 88% identity) bat-derived SARS-related coronaviruses (SARSr-CoV) designated as SL-CoVZC45 and SL-CoVZXC21. This throws light on the fact that 2019-nCoV like all previously reported pathogenic coronaviruses (SARS and MERS CoV) has its ancestry to coronaviruses with bats as the primary host. However, the ancestry of 2019-nCoV is not directly linked to the two bat-derived coronaviruses and homologous recombination events in an intermediate host have played a key role in the evolution of this novel strain.
</p>
