<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21">The HA protein of avian H5N1 IAVs has been reported to require both human-type Q226L and G228S mutations to bind to both α-2,3 and α-2,6 SAs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR186">186</xref>], and that of avian H7N9 IAVs only needs the Q226L mutation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">122</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR187">187</xref>]. Interestingly, a H7N9 human isolate was contact transmissible in pigs, regardless of PB2 E627 or K627, but only in the acquisition of human-type HA Q226L determinant, which indicates the importance of the acquisition of human-type receptor specificity for the avian IAV transmission in pigs, potentially also in humans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR188">188</xref>]. However, as demonstrated in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b and c, the acquisition of human-type PB2 K627 would have been more critical due to the presence of SAα-2,3 glycans in the upper respiratory tract of pigs. Avian IAVs with the PB2 E627K mutation should be able to replicate in the upper respiratory tract of humans and may be transformed to be transmissible between humans (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c). However, they were poorly transmissible in ferrets (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>d). There have been no reports that investigated the transmissiblity of avian IAVs with the PB2 E627K mutation between humans. All the first three human isolates of avian H7N9 IAVs, which contained the human-type PB2 E627K and HA Q226L mutations, showed approximately 30% airborne transmissibility in ferrets [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">122</xref>]. These appear to match with the conceptualized transmission in ferrets of Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>d. The H7N9 isolates with PB2 K627 and HA L226 would have replicated in the upper respiratory tract of ferrets, but their replication might have been inefficient since the receptor binding of the H7N9 Q226L HA was still weaker to α-2,6 SA than to α-2,3 SA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR187">187</xref>]. Airborne transmission of the H7N9 virus in ferrets lacking α-2,6 SA might be explained by the overflow of the virus replicating in the lower respiratory tract, since ferrets poorly express α-2,3 SA in the upper respiratory tract [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR189">189</xref>]. This model also indicates similar level of transmission of avian IAVs in ferrets without any human-type determinants. Therefore, the conceptual model of IAV transmission based on the receptor distribution appears to agree only with the ferret experiments, and probably only with H7N9 transmission in ferrets, since avian H5N1 IAVs were not transmissible in ferrets [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR190">190</xref>]. This conceptual model is apparently an oversimplification. There may be more factors involved in the transmission of IAVs, such as the functional balance between the HA and NA proteins and inherent replicability of IAVs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR191">191</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR192">192</xref>]. The problem is, due to the discrepancy between what is expected in humans by the conceptual model and the reality, how to translate the results of transmission experiments evaluated in animal models to the natural transmission environments between humans. We may compare the transmissibility of certain viral isolates to that of CA04 in ferrets, but it is difficult to determine what the level of the transmissibility of these viruses indicate in terms of the pandemic potential of the viruses. The reports on the α-2,3 SA expression status in the upper respiratory tract of ferrets, pigs, and humans appear to be inconclusive [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. Determination of IAV receptor distributions in humans and animal models appears critical for the interpretation of pathogenicity and transmission experiments assessed in animal models.
</p>
