<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ZIKV belongs to the 
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic> genus (family 
 <italic>Flaviridae</italic>), along with DENVs and WNV, and is primarily transmitted to humans through the bite of an infected female 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> or 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> mosquito. Both species are principal vectors of DENVs and chikungunya virus (CHIKV). The former species is established in north Queensland and present in some towns in central and southern Queensland [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The latter species is not yet established in mainland Australia but is present on many Torres Strait islands [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] and is detected occasionally at Australia’s international air and seaports by the Department of Agriculture and Water Resources [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In addition to vector-borne transmission, sexual contact,[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] perinatal transmission,[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and blood transfusion [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] are alternative transmission pathways for ZIKV. Symptomatic infection with ZIKV is usually characterized by mild, self-limiting febrile illness with low-grade fever, arthralgia, myalgia, headache and conjunctivitis [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], although as many as 80% of cases may be asymptomatic [50–80%][
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. When acquired during pregnancy, ZIKV can cause miscarriage or neurological birth defects (e.g. microcephaly) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. In addition, ZIKV may also cause Guillain-Barré syndrome [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].
</p>
