<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>First isolated in Uganda in 1947, ZIKV was relatively unknown until an outbreak in Yap, Federated States of Micronesia, in 2007 and then in French Polynesia in 2013–2014. Outbreaks of ZIKV occurred throughout the Americas and the Pacific in 2015–2016. Local transmission has been reported in, at least, 87 countries and from 2015 to 2
 <sup>nd</sup> July 2019 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], and more than 33 million travel-associated cases of ZIKV have been reported from 2015 to week 4 2019 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Vector competence of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> mosquito populations for ZIKV varies substantially depending on the origin of the virus strain and mosquito population [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The vector competence of Australian 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> has been established experimentally for African, Cambodian, Western Pacific and Brazilian virus strains [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Hugo, Stassen 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] recently showed that Australian 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> can transmit a Brazilian epidemic ZIKV strain with more efficiency than 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic>. More than 140 cases of confirmed or probable ZIKV infection have been reported in travelers to Australia since 2012 as of 23 March 2019,[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] with the highest number of notifications reported in the areas of north Queensland where 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> is present and abundant [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Areas of north-eastern Australia could sustain local transmission of ZIKV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] in wild-type 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic>, although the recent and expanding implementation of 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-based control strategies in the region may reduce future risk of potential transmission in locations where 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic>-infected 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> persist in high relative densities [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008438.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>].
</p>
