<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0035">
 <label>Table 7.6</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Combination therapies for biothreat bacterial pathogens.</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th colspan="2" valign="bottom" align="left">Combination therapeutics
     <hr/>
    </th>
    <th valign="bottom" align="left">Notes
     <hr/>
    </th>
    <th valign="bottom" align="left">References
     <hr/>
    </th>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <th colspan="4" valign="bottom" align="left">
     <italic>Bacillus anthracis</italic>
    </th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Antibiotics</td>
    <td align="left">AIGIV</td>
    <td align="left">Combination therapy with antibiotics and AIGIV is more effective than antibiotics alone in a rabbit model of inhalational anthrax and improved survival compared to the antibiotic treatment alone</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0780" ref-type="bibr">[155]</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Ciprofloxacin</td>
    <td align="left">Clindamycin</td>
    <td align="left">Treatment of rabbits with systemic anthrax with clindamycin and ciprofloxacin had improved efficacy compared to monotherapy and could be used to prevent relapse of infection</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0785" ref-type="bibr">[156]</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Ciprofloxacin</td>
    <td align="left">PA IgG antibodies</td>
    <td align="left">Combination therapy for anthrax, including antiprotective antigen (PA IgG) antibodies and ciprofloxacin in a rodent anthrax model increased survival significantly compared to ciprofloxacin treatment alone</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0790" ref-type="bibr">[157]</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Levofloxacin</td>
    <td align="left">Raxibacumab</td>
    <td align="left">Combination therapy with raxibacumab, an IgG1 monoclonal antibody that binds protective antigen, and the antibiotic levofloxacin provides protection in rabbits late in the disease course</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0795" ref-type="bibr">[158]</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Oligochlorophen</td>
    <td align="left">Antibiotics</td>
    <td align="left">Targeting cytoskeletal proteins such as FtsZ with oligochlorophen analogs is a promising new treatment method that has a 10-fold lower development of resistance compared to antibiotics used for anthrax treatment in humans</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0800" ref-type="bibr">[159]</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Penicillin, meropenem, or rifampin</td>
    <td align="left">Linezolid</td>
    <td align="left">Treatment of antibiotic-resistant inhalation anthrax with linezolid and penicillin, meropenem, or rifampin had the inhibitory effect on mean lethal factor levels compared to the control groups and successfully treated fluoroquinolone-resistant 
     <italic>B. anthracis</italic> infection
    </td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0805" ref-type="bibr">[160]</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Rifampin</td>
    <td align="left">Clindamycin</td>
    <td align="left">Combination therapy for anthrax with rifampin and clindamycin was shown to be synergistic in vitro</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0810" ref-type="bibr">[161]</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="4" align="left">
     <italic>Brucella</italic> spp.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Doxycycline</td>
    <td align="left">Rifampin</td>
    <td align="left">Successful combination therapies used to treat pulmonary brucellosis in humans is doxycycline and rifampin for 6 weeks</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0815" ref-type="bibr">[162]</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="4" align="left">
     <italic>Burkholderia mallei</italic>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Antibiotic</td>
    <td align="left">Heat-killed vaccine</td>
    <td align="left">Combination of an antibiotic moxifloxacin, azithromycin, or sulfamethoxazole-trimethoprim, and vaccination using heat-killed 
     <italic>B. mallei</italic> can protect BALB/c mice from lethal glanders infection, potentially by stimulating immune responses, such as gamma interferon, which acts synergistically with antibiotic therapy to inhibit bacterial growth
    </td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0820" ref-type="bibr">[163]</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Enrofloxacin, trimethoprim, and sulfadiazine</td>
    <td align="left">Doxycycline</td>
    <td align="left">Successful 12-week combination treatment of parenteral administration of enrofloxacin and trimethoprim with sulfadiazine followed by oral administration of doxycycline eliminated 
     <italic>B. mallei</italic> from glanderous horses during an outbreak
    </td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0825" ref-type="bibr">[164]</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="4" align="left">
     <italic>Burkholderia pseudomallei</italic>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Antibiotics</td>
    <td align="left">Farnesol</td>
    <td align="left">Combination therapy with farnesol a sesquiterpene alcohol that damages biofilm matrix and interferes with cell wall and peptidoglycan biosynthesis, facilitates antimicrobial penetration, and reduces the minimum biofilm eradication concentration for ceftazidime, amoxicillin, doxycycline, and sulfamethoxazole-trimethoprim in vitro</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0830" ref-type="bibr">[165]</xref>, 
     <xref rid="bib0835" ref-type="bibr">[166]</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Ceftazidime</td>
    <td align="left">Avibactam</td>
    <td align="left">Avibactam restores susceptibility to ceftazidime for genetically diverse extremely drug resistant isolates of 
     <italic>Burkholderia</italic> from cystic fibrosis patients by binding PenA and the combination treatment significantly improved survival of larvae infected with the drug resistant isolates
    </td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0835" ref-type="bibr">[166]</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Ceftazidime</td>
    <td align="left">IFN-γ</td>
    <td align="left">Interferon gamma–induced reactive oxygen species with ceftazidime leads to synergistic killing of intracellular 
     <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> and markedly increases the effectiveness of antimicrobial therapy for the treatment of 
     <italic>B. pseudomallei</italic> infection in mice
    </td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0840" ref-type="bibr">[167]</xref>, 
     <xref rid="bib0845" ref-type="bibr">[168]</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="4" align="left">
     <italic>Clostridium botulinum</italic>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Antibody cocktail</td>
    <td/>
    <td align="left">BoNT serotypes and subtypes differences present a significant challenge for creating monoclonal antibody treatments for neutralization, by diversifying the V-regions of mAbs and selecting cross reactivity, a combination treatment of three antibodies neutralized BoNT/F1, F2, F4, and F7 in mice and was 150 times more potent than equine antitoxin</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0850" ref-type="bibr">[169]</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="4" align="left">
     <italic>Coxiella burnetii</italic>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Doxycycline</td>
    <td align="left">Chloroquine</td>
    <td align="left">Combination therapy of doxycycline and hydroxychloroquine combination shortened the duration of therapy and reduced the number of relapses in patients with Q fever endocarditis. And a case of Q fever endocarditis with biological prosthetic aortic valve and aortic homograft was successfully treated with doxycycline and chloroquine combination therapy</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0855" ref-type="bibr">[170]</xref>, 
     <xref rid="bib0860" ref-type="bibr">[171]</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="4" align="left">
     <italic>Francisella tularensis</italic>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Antibiotics</td>
    <td align="left">Uptake inhibitors and inflammatory inhibitors</td>
    <td align="left">Cytochalasin B, LY294002, wortmannin, nocodazole, MG132, and XVA143 inhibitors reduce 
     <italic>F. tularensis</italic> update and reduce inflammatory cytokine production and can be used in combination with antibiotics to improve survival of infected mice
    </td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0865" ref-type="bibr">[172]</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Gentamicin</td>
    <td align="left">Membrane antigen immunization</td>
    <td align="left">Postexposure immunization with membrane protein fraction antigens and treatment with low-dose gentamicin increased survival of mice and significantly reduced bacterial burdens in the liver and spleen</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0870" ref-type="bibr">[173]</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="4" align="left">
     <italic>Yersinia pestis</italic>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Antibiotics</td>
    <td align="left">Efflux pump inhibitor</td>
    <td align="left">Combination therapy, including antibiotics with an efflux pump inhibitor, would be a novel mechanism to restore the efficacy of the antibiotic in resistant strains of 
     <italic>Y. pestis</italic>
    </td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0875" ref-type="bibr">[174]</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Antibody therapy</td>
    <td align="left">Corticosteroid</td>
    <td align="left">The addition of antiinflammatory methylprednisolone, a corticosteroid, in combination with antibody therapy correlates with improved mouse survival, with reduction in neutrophil and matrix metalloproteinase 9 in the tissue, and the mitigation of tissue damage</td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0880" ref-type="bibr">[175]</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">Ciprofloxacin</td>
    <td align="left">L-97-1</td>
    <td align="left">A novel postexposure medical countermeasure 
     <sc>l</sc>-97-1, an A
     <sub>1</sub> adenosine receptor antagonist blocks LPS-induced activation of immunomodulatory cytotoxic substance accumulation to prevent acute lung injury, and in combination with ciprofloxacin improves survival of rats following infection with 
     <italic>Y. pestis</italic>
    </td>
    <td align="left">
     <xref rid="bib0885" ref-type="bibr">[176]</xref>
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn>
   <p>
    <italic>AIGIV</italic>, anthrax immune globulin intravenous; 
    <italic>IFN</italic>, interferon; 
    <italic>LPS</italic>, lipopolysaccharide; 
    <italic>PA</italic>, protective antigen.
   </p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
