<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Exhaustion of T lymphocytes is the most important factor contributing to weakened T cell activity against both cancer and infectious agents. Notably, T cell exhaustion is a distinguishing feature of many chronic viral infections such as HIV and hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection. Indeed, T cell exhaustion was first described in the context of chronic infections.
 <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7 8</xref> In the following, T lymphocytes with a similar phenotype were also detected in the tumor microenvironment.
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2 7–9</xref> Exhausted T lymphocytes are functionally characterized by a loss of interleukin 2 (IL-2) production, impaired proliferation, diminished cytotoxicity, and altered production of proinflammatory cytokines.
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2 7–9</xref> Moreover, the overexpression of immune checkpoint receptors, including PD-1 and CTLA-4, is a characteristic. Given the similarities between the immune response to cancer and chronic infections, one may hypothesize that the use of ICI should not be harmful for tumor patients with infections or may even provide a benefit. However, as of yet, tumor patients with existing viral infections are excluded from participation in many treatment protocols for ICI.
 <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7 8</xref> With respect to acquired infectious diseases during ICI treatment, no increased risk was observed in clinical studies.
 <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1–4 7 8</xref> However, ICI treatment frequently results in activation of autoreactive T lymphocytes and disturbances in immune tolerance thereby causing autoimmune‐like/inflammatory side effects. These are summarized as immune‐related adverse events (irAEs) and include autoimmune colitis, pneumonitis, hypophysitis, hepatitis, thyroiditis and so on.
 <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10–12</xref> Since irAEs may require immunosuppressive therapy, including high-dose corticosteroids and/or tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-α blockers, the risk of infection or reactivation of chronic or latent viral infections (eg, HBV or hepatitis C virus (HCV)) may be secondarily increased.
 <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10–12</xref> In this respect, it should also be noted that much of the morbidity of persistent viral diseases is caused by collateral damage caused by the chronic reactive inflammation associated with the inability of viral clearance; both may be boosted by ICI therapy. In this review, we present information on the pros and cons of using ICI in patients with viral infections including COVID-19.
</p>
