<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although human MBCs have been characterized for many important viral pathogens, including HIV (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), RSV (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), influenza (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), human DENV MBC derived antibodies were not fully characterized until 2010 (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Mosquito-transmitted DENV is responsible for ~100 million symptomatic cases and 35,000 deaths annually (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) making it the most common and serious vector-borne disease affecting humans. DENV is an enveloped positive sense RNA virus, that circulates as four distinct serotypes (DENV 1-4), with 60–85% shared sequence homology (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Repeat infections often occur in DENV endemic regions–Asia, Latin America, Africa, and parts of Oceana. Population growth, increased global travel, and spread of the vector have led to increasing epidemics. DENV infection causes symptoms that include high fever and rash. A portion of patients (~500,000 per year) develop severe dengue—referred to as dengue shock syndrome (DSS) or dengue hemorrhagic fever (DHF)—which can further progress to organ failure and death. First (1°) infection with one serotype is thought to provide life-long protection against that serotype, but only short-lived protection against heterologous infection (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Secondary (2°) infection with a different serotype can lead to broader protection, up to all four serotypes, but comes at a greater risk of serious disease during acute infection, through a process of antibody dependent enhancement (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), which occurs when sub-neutralizing antibodies bind to virus and facilitate uptake into cells via Fc receptors (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). The mechanism by which subsequent broader immunity develops is incompletely understood: while it is known that immediately following second infection the antibody response contains a large proportion of cross-reactive antibodies that can neutralize both viruses (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) the relative contribution of type specific, weakly cross-neutralizing and broadly neutralizing antibodies to long-term immunity is unclear, and may depend on virus maturation state (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Further complicating the hypothesized role of broadly cross-neutralizing antibodies is the recent finding by Raut et al. (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) that 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> neutralization assays using mature and partially mature tissue-culture derived DENV1 over-estimated by almost 15-fold the potency of heterotypic neutralizing antibodies when compared to neutralizing potency against the same fully mature DENV1 circulating in humans. Deeper understanding of the diversity and epitope-specificity of 1° MBCs could lead to the development of subunit vaccines that preferentially elicit potently neutralizing antibodies against all 4 DENV serotypes while avoiding potentially enhancing antibodies.
</p>
