<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Though WNV transmission is consistently detected throughout the continental US, its burden is not uniform, with a large variation in year-to-year human cases and the highest incidence rates often occurring in the central great plains (e.g., Wyoming, South Dakota, and North Dakota) [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Dynamic extrinsic factors, such as rainfall and temperature, that influence mosquito and bird populations can be predictive of WNV intensity [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref094" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>], yet the contributions of these extrinsic factors vary across the US due to differences in regional ecology [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref095" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. This is supported by the nonuniform abundance of 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>tarsalis</italic>, 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>pipiens</italic>, and 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>quinquefasciatus</italic> across the US [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref097" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>], where the presence or absence of these primary mosquito vectors in a given location is mediated by many factors including human land use, elevation, and winter temperatures. Together, these ecological differences create unique transmission networks at the local and regional levels that can significantly influence the likelihood of human disease risks [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. These ecological barriers may further influence mosquito genetic diversity [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>], causing potential differences in their efficiency for WNV transmission [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref095" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. Combined with varied avian ecology and migratory bird flyways across the US [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>], these data suggest that WNV is maintained in regional transmission networks with unique selective pressures that influence the stability and emergence of new WNV strains [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>].
</p>
