<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The impact of current COVID‐19 outbreak and the likelihood of future CoV epidemics strongly advocate for rapid development of new treatments and fast intervention protocols. Few research groups have already suggested potential repurposing strategies for clinically approved drugs
 <xref rid="minf202000028-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="minf202000028-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="minf202000028-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">26</xref> or proposed de novo agents
 <xref rid="minf202000028-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">27</xref> as therapeutic solutions for SARS‐CoV‐2. However, previously reported docking (virtual screening) campaigns with Mpro targets were able to process only few millions or even thousands compounds.
 <xref rid="minf202000028-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="minf202000028-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="minf202000028-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="minf202000028-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">30</xref> The main reason for that is that conventional docking is too computationally expensive and slow, while the libraries of available chemicals are growing exponentially.
 <xref rid="minf202000028-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">31</xref> To address this general challenge, we have recently developed a novel deep learning‐based approach for accelerated screening of large chemical libraries, consisting of billions of entities. This Deep Docking (DD) platform utilizes quantitative structure‐activity relationship (QSAR) models trained on docking scores of database subsets to approximate in an iterative manner the docking outcome of the remaining entries. Importantly, DD does not provide any novel scoring function for docking, thus its accuracy relies completely on the docking program that is used. The development of deep learning scoring functions has been already attempted, but results have shown various degrees of success which could be due to a lack of appropriate datasets.
 <xref rid="minf202000028-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="minf202000028-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">33</xref> Likely, as the very nature of docking is approximate, the improvements are likely to come from better approximation of physical‐chemical processes, including solvation, enthalpic and entropic factors, rather than from a better training base and procedures.
 <xref rid="minf202000028-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="minf202000028-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">35</xref> Thus, our method represents not just feasible, but also practical options for utilizing deep learning in virtual screening. Herein we have used DD for large‐scale virtual screening against the SARS‐CoV‐2 Mpro active site.
</p>
