<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza virus, a single-stranded negative-sense RNA virus, belongs to 
 <italic>Orthomyxoviridae</italic> family, and can infect the nasal and tracheal airways, and then spread throughout the upper and lower respiratory tract (Tumpey and Belser, 
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Influenza virus infection usually causes various syndromes such as fever, cough, headache, body ache, runny nose and even severe pneumonia depending largely on the health status and immunologic function of the patient and virus pathogenicity. Seasonal influenza and pandemic influenza are manifestations of influenza virus infection in human beings, moreover, avian-origin influenza virus occasionally jumped species and spread to human successfully, leading to limited, non-sustained human-to-human avian influenza virus transmission, and the mortality is high (Malik et al., 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). During the influenza season, according to statistics, 5–15% of the human population could be infected, causing 250,000–500,000 deaths a year worldwide (Ginsberg et al., 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Goeijenbier et al., 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Since 2010, 140,000–710,000 inpatients of the United States were infected with influenza viruses, and 12,000–56,000 deaths each year (McGowan et al., 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Most seasonal influenza virus infections are self-limiting, however, they can cause serious or fatal pulmonary dysfunction and even acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) (Khatri et al., 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Meanwhile, the oversecretion of inflammatory cytokines (known as “cytokine storm”) induced by the immune or inflammatory response, aggravate the damage degree of ARDS, even induce many organs failures and finally raise the death risk (Tisoncik et al., 
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Moreover, during or shortly after influenza virus infection, patients usually face increased risk of thrombosis-related cardiovascular events, such as myocardial infarction and stroke (Warren-Gash et al., 
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Antoniak et al., 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Dreadfully, a new strain or variant of influenza virus might result in a pandemic with millions of fatalities.
</p>
