<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>According to the different antigenicity of the nucleoprotein (NP) and matrix protein (M), influenza viruses are usually classified into three different serotypes: influenza A virus (IAV), influenza B virus (IBV), and influenza C virus (ICV) (Zheng et al., 
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). IAV has genetically distinct subtypes based on 18 hemagglutinin (HA) and 11 neuraminidase (NA) surface glycoproteins. Some subtypes of IAV have established stable transmission profiles among birds, swine, and humans (Huo et al., 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). In particular H5N1 and H7N9 are highly pathogenic subtypes of avian origin, and directly transmitted from birds to humans with highly contagious and widespread outbreak patterns (Li et al., 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). H1N1 is the earliest emerging subtype with available genomic sequences, has caused several pandemics and seasonal epidemics, resulting in millions of deaths and enormous economic losses (Yin et al., 
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Once influenza virus settle in the respiratory tract of humans, the virus can break the mucus barriers and rapidly infect the primary host cells (i.e., epithelial cells) to release the genome segments into the cell to start virus transcription and replication. First of all, influenza viruses bind to sialic acid receptor on the surface membrane of the epithelial cells using HA, and then enters into host cells via viropexis and/or receptor-mediated endocytosis process. Viropexis is the predominant metabolical activity-independent mechanism of influenza viruses attachment envelopment and the subsequent formation of virus-containing intracellular vacuoles for entry into the host cell (Patterson et al., 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">1979</xref>). The virus particles are encapsulated into endosomes, and transported to locations near the cell nucleus. After the viral membranes fused with endosomes, viral ribonucleoprotein complex (vRNPs) as the templates are released into the cell nucleus to synthesize messenger RNA (mRNA) and complementary RNA (cRNA) for viral translation and replication. Newly synthesized vRNPs are assembled and exported from the cell nucleus and then directed to the plasma membrane. Finally, vRNPs are incorporated into budding virions and released into extracellular environment (Keshavarz et al., 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), and then spread to uninfected cells or local immune cells such as macrophages (MΦ), which are the principal effector cells of the innate immune system (Cypryk et al., 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). The intercellular transfer of viral materials released from infected cells to neighboring and distant recipient cells affect virus spread and pathogenesis. Importantly, this kind of cell- cell communication can directly activate host response to influenza virus infection, and modulate the host homeostasis (Assil et al., 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>).
</p>
