<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">COVID-19 has a capacity for human-to-human transmission, the public has no hard immunity against it, a high mortality rate, which makes it suitable agents for pandemic potential and the modern transport system also helps in its rapid expansion. Easy mode of transmission, nature of the virus, population density, environmental condition, social culture (like handshaking, etc.) are major contributors to its rapid spreading. Therefore, COVID-19 turned into a global health concern since its inception from Wuhan, China. Like other respiratory viruses, coronavirus is also contagious and easily spread from one person to another. Many viruses produced similar clinical symptoms; therefore COVID-19 cannot be differentiating on the basis of their clinical symptoms, for its accurate diagnosis a sensitive and specific assay always required. Unfortunately, only a few countries have a capacity for proper viral diagnosis or surveillance by laboratory assays. Without laboratory-confirmed assay or under the capacity of viral diagnosis or surveillance system can decreases the authenticity and accuracy of data. The Basic Reproductive Number (R
 <sub>0</sub>) can be utilized to calculate averaging the number of infections produced by infected individuals in susceptible populations. Basic Reproductive Number (R
 <sub>0</sub>) is for the SARS-CoV (1.4–5.5), MERS–CoV (&lt; 1), COVID-19 (2.2–2.6) and Influenza viruses (5–25). The members of the 
 <italic>coronaviridae</italic> are less contagious than influenza viruses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Although, COVID-19 is a slow virus than influenza viruses, but even then spread in the 210 countries within 120 days and caused a large number of infections. In these hundred days, COVID-19 causes the 15, 21, 966 laboratories confirmed cases and 88, 659 (5.82%) deaths worldwide till 09 April 2020. The USA (4, 35, 160), Spain (1, 48, 220), Italy (1, 39, 422), Germany (1, 13, 296) and France (1, 12, 950) are top five infected countries have 9, 49, 048 (62.35%) of total laboratories confirmed cases of COVID-19. Italy (17, 669), USA (14, 797), Spain (14,792), France (10, 869) and United Kingdom (7097) are the top five affected countries have 65, 224 (73.56%) of total deaths due to COVID-19. The mortality rate (%) of top ten countries on the basis of their laboratory-confirmed cases are Italy (12.67%), UK (11.68%), Spain (9.98%), France (9.62%), Belgium (9.57%), Iran (6.18%), China (4.07), USA (3.40%), Turkey (2.12%), and Germany (2.07%) 
 <italic>(</italic>
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/seen" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/seen</ext-link> on 09 April 2020).
</p>
