<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0245">One of the most significant and most efficient measures in the suppression of COVID-19 pandemic is increasing social distancing. In order to increase social distancing in a patient to patient and patient to healthcare worker relationship, additional modules in MIS MEDIS.NET were developed. The additional modules enabled the implementation of social distancing within healthcare institutions, where at the same time the concentration of viral pathogen is high, as well as the probability of infection during the COVID-19 pandemic. By reducing contacts, the quality of medical services provided to patients was not impacted, on the contrary, the quality was increased since medical staff was able to dedicate more time to the patients who came to examinations (the number of patients in the HCN decreased). The decreased number of patients at the HCN, which represents the primary healthcare institution, enabled the medical staff to engage in special COVID-19 hospitals and infirmaries on the territory of the city of Nis as a medical support. In this way the healthcare capacity during the combat against the COVID-19 disease increased, where each physician and nurse represented a valuable resource during the new pandemic. The module developed for triage enabled fast detection of infected patients by the novel virus and prompt actions in order to provide quick and quality medical care. Besides that, more difficult cases of the coronavirus infection were transported into the specialized COVID-19 hospitals. Certain reports from MIS MEDIS.NET enabled the Crisis Staff in the city of Nis to efficiently trace potentially infected persons and medical staff, which was an important measure during the pandemic to avoid having a huge number of infected healthcare employees by the novel virus. In the continuation of discussion, it is presented how MIS MEDIS.NET with additionally developed modules during the COVID-19 pandemic responded to the combat against the pandemic from the perspective of increasing the degree of social distancing.</p>
