<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27">Sheep and goats are vital for more than 330 million poor subsistence and marginal farmers in Africa and Asia a home to more than 1.7 billion sheep and goats, where over 80% of the world’s small ruminants occur and here PPR causes food insecurity and contributes to poverty [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. The clinical signs elicited by PPRV may vary depending on the breed of the affected animal species and/or the strain of virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Besides, other factors such as the resilience of the population, nutrition, co-infection and other stressors contribute to the pathogenesis of PPRV infection. The severity of disease depends on the immune status of the animal; for example, newborn animals become susceptible to PPRV infection at three to 4 months of age following natural decline in colostral antibodies. Early and accurate diagnosis of PPRV infection is important for prompt control and this can be facilitated by pen-side diagnostics (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The availability of simple cost-effective pen-side diagnostics and laboratory based tests would aid in the prevention and control of PPR in low-income countries. However, these tests should be performed in reference with OIE prescribed tests for confirmation of clinical cases using immunocapture enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (IC-ELISA) and reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) and for certification of population freedom from infection by competitive enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (C-ELISA) and virus neutralization test (VNT) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Thus, the use of automated assays that do not require supplementary multiple reagents and lateral flow diagnostic strips technologies based on low cost immunoreagents such as nanobodies may accelerate the development of powerful diagnostic assays. In addition, lack of validated tests amongst wildlife species creates uncertainties in the interpretation of surveillance data. 
</p>
