<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0065">One of the greatest challenges in emerging epidemics is uncertainty amongst HCW about transmission risks, and fear of becoming a victim of the outbreak disease. ICU is a high-risk area where a larger number of “high transmission risk” procedures are performed. Clear concise communication and leadership are critical to tackle stress, fear, fake news and mistrust during the crisis 
 <xref rid="bib0355" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. Staff morale is vulnerable and emotional support should be proactively made available. Frontline staff must be made to feel safe by constant exposure to clear protocols and rigorous training. Expansion of critical care beds to cope with increased numbers of patients by opening more ICU beds, and converting wards and other monitored areas for ICU provision is often recommended in outbreak disaster plans. However, experience from SARS-CoV showed that rapid and excessive expansion may overwhelm staff, lead to excess infections in HCW, and compromise care 
 <xref rid="bib0360" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. Thus, expansion should be matched by safe staffing to guarantee an appropriate quality of care and staff safety, which necessarily limit expansion. It has been suggested by an expert consensus group with first-hand experience of outbreak expansion that this is realistically limited to a maximum of 50-100% of baseline capacity 
 <xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. Alternatively, restricting normal critical care to provide only core and essential provisions, may allow greater expansion and more patients to have limited life sustaining interventions under conditions of limited resources 
 <xref rid="bib0370" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. Should these measures be overwhelmed, individual patient triage and appropriate rationing of ICU care will be required to provide greatest benefit for the greatest number of patients 
 <xref rid="bib0375" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0380" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. A structured triage approach incorporating triage admission criteria that can adapt to the scale of crisis, are fluid and adaptable depending on the evolution of the outbreak and change in response to resource pressures is necessary. A process of development and implementation that provides transparency, an appeal mechanism, documentation of decisions and that is culturally and socially sensitive is recommended 
 <xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>.
</p>
