<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The effects of vaccination on distribution patterns of co-circulating RV strains have been investigated. A previous study in Australia reported that the introduction of RV vaccines affected the ecology of RV by increasing diversity and differences in genotype predominance. Increased prevalence of 
 <italic>G12P[8]</italic> across states was observed following the use of RotaTeq and 
 <italic>G2P[4]</italic> and DS-1-like 
 <italic>G3P[8]</italic> with the use of Rotarix [
 <xref rid="pone.0235280.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Another study in Japan showed that the dominant genotype shifted from 
 <italic>G3P[8]</italic> to 
 <italic>G1P[8]</italic> and 
 <italic>G2P[4]</italic> after vaccine introduction [
 <xref rid="pone.0235280.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. In the previous report in Thailand [
 <xref rid="pone.0235280.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0235280.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], RV with DS-1-like backbone (
 <italic>G1</italic>,
 <italic>3</italic>,
 <italic>4</italic>,
 <italic>9P[8]I2</italic>) has been prevalent in children and adults since 2013, with a trend of continued significant increase until 2016 in distinct provinces. In the present study, unusual DS-1-like 
 <italic>G3P[8]</italic> was identified as the major strain in Thailand. The sequences of 
 <italic>VP7</italic> and 
 <italic>VP4</italic> genes displayed high percentage nucleotide identity to the Australian unusual DS-1-like 
 <italic>G3P[8]</italic> strains circulating between 2006 and 2011 [
 <xref rid="pone.0235280.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. This unusual DS-1-like 
 <italic>G3P[8]</italic> strain has been identified in several countries with a range of vaccine coverage, with different rates of infection depending on geographic and temporal patterns, including Australia, Germany, Hungary, USA, Brazil, Japan, and Thailand [
 <xref rid="pone.0235280.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0235280.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0235280.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0235280.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0235280.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0235280.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0235280.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], indicating that the DS-1-like backbone is derived from a globally circulating pool of RV. Studies on children infected with the unusual DS-1-like 
 <italic>G1P[8]</italic> strain revealed no significant differences in clinical severity relative to disease caused by Wa-like 
 <italic>G1P[8]</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0235280.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0235280.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. However, these strains contain several different amino acids, especially in the antigenic region, which may affect vaccine efficacy, as shown previously for unusual DS-1-like 
 <italic>G1P[8]</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0235280.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. This reassortment has a considerable impact on communities, potentially conferring some advantage to viral propagation and survival, although severity of diarrhea may not be affected. While no data on effectiveness of vaccines against unusual DS-1-like 
 <italic>G3P[8]</italic> are available at present, the efficacy of the RV vaccine against Wa-like 
 <italic>G1P[8]</italic>, unusual DS-1-like 
 <italic>G1P[8]</italic>, 
 <italic>G2P[4]</italic> and Wa-like 
 <italic>G9P[8]</italic> strains has been confirmed based on mean Vesikari score and distribution of Vesikari score [
 <xref rid="pone.0235280.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0235280.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>].
</p>
