<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mosquito species, time, location, and species by time interaction effects on transmission were analyzed using maximum likelihood categorical analyses of contingency tables (PROC CATMOD, SAS 2002) based on the number of mosquitoes categorized for the presence or absence of CHIKV on the filter paper (first time point) and in capillary tubes (second and third time points). When significant treatment effects were found, follow-up analyses included pairwise comparisons of treatments, correcting for multiple comparisons using the sequential Bonferroni method. We chose this analysis for consistency and improved comparison to other CHIKV studies [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005724.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005724.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005724.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005724.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005724.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Separate analyses of transmission were performed for the first time point and combined for the second and third time points because different methods were used to collect saliva. Also, separate analyses were performed for each of the CHIKV lineages since these experiments were performed at different times. Maximum likelihood categorical analyses of contingency tables were used to test for treatment effects (see salivary infection methods) on viral dissemination efficiencies to gauge barriers to transmission (midgut escape barrier). Each infection experiment with 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> and CHIKV was conducted only once. Individual mosquitoes are the unit of replication and we analyzed infection responses by analysis of frequency distribution [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005724.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Analysis of variance was used to test for differences in virus titers in the legs and saliva of the individual mosquitoes. Significant effects were followed by Tukey-Kramer multiple comparisons among treatment least-squares means for pairwise comparisons.
</p>
