<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Rabies is caused by neurotropic viruses in the genus 
 <italic>Lyssavirus</italic>, family 
 <italic>Rhabdoviridae</italic>, and is transmissible to all mammals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Dogs are the main hosts responsible for human rabies in Africa, Latin Americas and Asia, especially in China [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>], where rabies is re-emerging as a major public health threat, and its severity is only second to HIV and tuberculosis (TB) among all reportable infectious diseases. From the annual ~3000 human deaths, southeast China counts for most cases, with more than 90% attributed to rabid dog bites [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Notably, both human population and dog density are high in the region with low rabies vaccination coverage in dogs. Given that the program of dog rabies elimination has not been listed in the priority of governmental agenda, it is possible that long term dog rabies enzootics will lead to spillover events of dog-associated rabies into wildlife species. In addition to rabies transmitted by rabid dogs, other sources of rabies exposure to humans, such as cats, ferret badgers (FB), and pigs, have been continuously reported in China [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>-
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Interestingly, in provinces like Zhejiang, Jiangxi and Anhui, the percentage of dog-associated human rabies is relatively low. Meanwhile, up to 80% of the reported human rabies cases were inferred to be caused by FB bites in some districts in Zhejiang province from 1994 to 2004 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Although rabies in badgers was previously recorded in other countries [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>], FB-associated human rabies has never been reported except in China [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. The frequent occurrence of FB-associated human rabies cases in southeast China highlights the lack of laboratory-based surveillance and urges revisiting the potential importance of this animal in rabies transmission. Nevertheless, management of such animal bites in humans needs a clear guideline on post-exposure prophylaxis (PEP) for rabies. Currently, FB trading and its meat consumption are common in the related areas, resulting in a frequent source of FB bite to humans. Similar to severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) outbreaks through consumption of civet in south china, the close and frequent contact of FB by humans could be an important factor in human rabies cases in southeast China.
</p>
