<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Total RNA (≥ 50 ng/μl) was extracted from a ToCV positive sample using a Quick-RNA MiniPrep kit (Zymo Research, USA) and sequenced using an Illumina HiSeq 2500 Ultra-High-Throughput Sequencing System (Illumina Inc. USA) at the Agricultural Research Council Biotechnology Platform [ARC-BTP (Pretoria, South Africa)]. A paired-end library was generated using the platforms’ sequencing by synthesis technology (SBS). FastQC [
 <xref rid="pone.0220298.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] was used to determine the read quality of NGS data generated from the HiSeq platform. The raw data was trimmed using Trimmomatics version 0.36, (parameters: Leading:14, Trailing:14, sliding window:4:15 minlen:70), where the low-quality sequence regions and Illumina universal adapter sequences were trimmed and removed. To remove the host sequence reads, the trimmed data were mapped against the reference genome: 
 <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> strain: Heinz 1706 (accession: GCF_000188115), where the whole genome sequence of 
 <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> strain: Heinz 1706 was downloaded from NCBI. Using the reference genome assembler: Bowtie2 version2.3.4 [
 <xref rid="pone.0220298.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], an index reference database was constructed, and the sequence reads that did not align to the reference genome was collected for meta-assembly. The meta-assembly was done using the metaSPAdes pipeline within the de novo assembler: SPAdes version 3.11.1 [
 <xref rid="pone.0220298.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Contigs were identified using Blast against the NCBI nucleotide database. ORF Finder (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/orffinder/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/orffinder/</ext-link>) was used to identify ORFs and translate proteins. Nucleotide and amino acid similarities of coding and non-coding regions were generated using the sequence identity and similarity tool SIAS (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://imed.med.ucm.es/Tools/sias.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://imed.med.ucm.es/Tools/sias.html</ext-link>). Phylogenetic analysis was conducted using MEGA 6 software. A best-fit model was generated from multiple sequence alignments for each RNA segment of the ToCV bipartite genome.
</p>
