<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The various classes of disinfectants/sanitizing agents inactivate viruses via different mechanisms and their potency against viruses is highly dependent upon the type of virus and application conditions such as concentration, exposure duration, temperature, pH, and organic load. Therefore, knowledge of the target virus and careful control of the application conditions are crucial to achieve effective disinfection. In general, it is observed that disinfectants/sanitizing agents like povidone‐iodine, aldehydes, and oxidizing agents that inactivate viruses by chemically modifying their surface groups are fast‐acting and highly potent towards most viruses but their application is also often limited by their higher toxicity and damaging effects to surfaces
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0101" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>101</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0103" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>103</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0118" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>118</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0123" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>123</sup>
 </xref>. On the other hand, disinfectants like alcohols and surfactants that mostly rely on dissolving the lipid envelopes tend to only show potency towards a narrower range of viruses and may require longer exposure durations, but are often more biocompatible
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>32</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>42</sup>
 </xref>. An ideal disinfectant/sanitizer would be one that is effective towards a broad range of viruses with fast‐action and high potency but still suitable for long‐term use, exhibiting good biocompatibility and mild effects towards surfaces. A potential direction may be to develop potent disinfectant agents from natural compounds
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0218" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>218</sup>
 </xref> as they may have less toxicity allowing the product to be child‐safe
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0219" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>219</sup>
 </xref> and also safe for long‐term usage. New generation sanitizers with viral inactivation mechanisms that can enhance and balance broad disinfection efficacy with biocompatibility are thus likely to have good potential in becoming the preferred choice of consumers.
</p>
