<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0065">Animal studies on remdesivir efficacy against CoVs have utilized transgenic mice and rhesus macaques [
 <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. For example, using a mouse model with a Ces1c-knockout (which better emulates human metabolism of remdesivir compared to wild-type mice) and a humanized MERS-CoV receptor, Sheahan et al. found that both prophylactic and therapeutic remdesivir had protective effects against MERS-CoV replication and associated pathology, generally resulting in less lung damage and better pulmonary function compared to controls [
 <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Interestingly, among mice that were infected with a higher virus quantity (
 <italic>i.e.</italic>, more plaque-forming units), those receiving prophylactic remdesivir one day before infection had significantly better 6-day survival than infected control mice that did not receive remdesivir. However, the mice were sacrificed before longer follow-up data could be obtained. Similarly, in a rhesus macaque model of MERS-CoV pathogenesis, prophylactic and therapeutic administration of remdesivir demonstrated favorable results, reducing respiratory tract viral titers and pulmonary pathology [
 <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Prophylactic use was initiated 24 h prior to viral challenge, whereas therapeutic use was initiated 12 h after challenge. While respiratory rate was not substantially different between the prophylactic, therapeutic, and control groups, x-ray scores, representing the severity of pulmonary infiltrates, were significantly better in the prophylactic and therapeutic groups, comparing each to controls [
 <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Incidentally, remdesivir has also been associated with beneficial effects, including reduced severity of respiratory signs and improved survival, against challenge with Nipah virus, which is a non-CoV virus in the 
 <italic>Paramyxoviridae</italic> family, in African green monkeys [
 <xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].
</p>
