<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="brief-report"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?OLF?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Microbes Infect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Microbes Infect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Microbes and Infection</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1286-4579</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1769-714X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7102648</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S1286-4579(20)30048-4</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micinf.2020.03.002</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Molecular basis of COVID-19 relationships in different species: a one health perspective</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Tilocca</surname><given-names>Bruno</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Soggiu</surname><given-names>Alessio</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Musella</surname><given-names>Vincenzo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Britti</surname><given-names>Domenico</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Sanguinetti</surname><given-names>Maurizio</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Urbani</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name><surname>Roncada</surname><given-names>Paola</given-names></name><email>roncada@unicz.it</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Health Science, University &#x0201c;Magna Gr&#x000e6;cia&#x0201d; of Catanzaro, Viale Europa, 88100 Catanzaro, Italy</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Veterinary Sciences, University of Milano, Via Celoria n10, 20133 Milano, Italy</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Basic Biotechnological Sciences, Intensivological and Perioperative Clinics, Universit&#x000e0; Cattolica del Sacro Cuore, Largo S. Vito n1, 00168 Rome, Italy</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Dipartimento Scienze di Laboratorio e Infettivologiche, Fondazione Policlinico Universitario Gemelli IRCCS, Largo S. Vito n8, 00168 Rome, Italy</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. <email>roncada@unicz.it</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><elocation-id/><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Institut Pasteur. Published by Elsevier Masson SAS. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Institut Pasteur</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p>Outside the Hubei province, China, the mild form of infection and the progressive recover of the COVID-19 patients suggest the intervention of &#x0201c;unconventional&#x0201d; biological mechanisms worthy of attention. Based on the high-homology between the Spike protein epitopes of taxonomically-related coronaviruses, we hypothesized that past contact with infected dogs shield humans against the circulating SARS-CoV-2. Elseways, the recurrent virus exposure over a short time-lapse might result in the Antibody Dependent Enhancement, triggering the violent immune reaction responsible for the severe clinical outcomes observed in the Hubei province. Nevertheless, further experimental studies are desired for a confidential evaluation of the postulated hypotheses.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>Coronavirus</kwd><kwd>Canine respiratory coronavirus</kwd><kwd>Immunization</kwd><kwd>One health</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="p0010">Since late December 2019, the world is facing a novel outbreak of an infectious disease, known as COVID-19, caused by an unidentified viral agent. Examination of patients cases reports clinical picture comparable to this observed in the SARS outbreak of 2003. This evidence is also supported by the early identification of the etiologic agent as a novel Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) and the molecular investigations describing a high percentage of sequence homology between SARS-CoV-2 and the previous SARS-causing virus (SARS-CoV) [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Coronaviruses are viruses with single-strand positive-sense RNA genome of approximately 30 kilobases [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. They have been commonly found in a wide array of host spectrum including avian, camels, bats, masked palm civets, mice, dogs, and cats [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Since its early identification, in the very begin of 2020, several nucleotides-based surveys and sequence homology-based alignments have been carried out with the focus to elucidate the viral origin and delineate cell- and host-tropism of the viral agent on the attempt to guide better management and control of the virus diffusion [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Sequence similarity alignments have reported SARS-CoV-2 being highly similar to several wildlife animals such as bats, pangolins and masked palm civets [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Controversial results have been reported concerning the snake coronavirus [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Nevertheless, the sole investigation of the genetic sequences might result in a biased and/or incomplete depiction of the virus source, biology and its pathogenetic mechanism [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In the Hubei province, where the outbreak originated, severe cases or deaths attributed to SARS-CoV-2 infections are predominantly arising from patients suffering from one or more previous pathological conditions such as diabetes, cardiovascular and cerebrovascular disease leading to sequelae, sometimes fatal, such as cellular immune deficiency, coagulation activation, myocardia injury, hepatic and kidney injury, and secondary bacterial infection [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p id="p0015">Although featured by a higher fatality rate when compared with the virus of the seasonal influenza (3.4%, WHO Situation Report-37, 25/02/2020), outside the primordial outbreak site, much less warning clinical signs have been registered in the SARS CoV-2 infected patients manifesting a mild form of the disease that is not evolving into severe stages and can, in some cases, recover without medical intervention [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Altogether this suggests the important contribution of the biological mechanisms that cannot be explained by the sole investigation of the genetic sequences.</p><p id="p0020">Protein repertoire of the coronaviruses consists of four main structural and approximately 16 major non-structural proteins [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Among the four structural proteins, the Spike protein (also known as S-protein) is involved in host tropism by means of recognition and attachment to the angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) receptor exposed in the outer layer of the host cell membrane [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. A very recent amino acid sequence alignment of ACE2 from different animal species including humans, pets and the major domestic animals highlighted high protein sequence similarity between the tested animal species, suggesting a potential&#x000a0;interaction of the viral particles with a wider array of host cells [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p id="p0025">In accordance with the hypothesis of interspecies transmission of the beta coronaviruses [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], we performed sequence homology analysis of the aminoacidic sequence of the Spike protein from SARS CoV-2 against taxonomically related coronaviruses with tropism for other animal species. Although the low homology scored while comparing the whole protein sequence (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>
), particular interest was dedicated to the canine respiratory coronavirus, the bovine coronavirus revealing and the human enteric coronavirus 36.93%, 38.42% and 37.68% sequence homology to SARS CoV-2 spike protein, respectively.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Amino acid sequence alignment of SARS CoV-2 Spike protein (GI QHR63290) against betacoronavirus database. The table display alignment relative to taxonomically-related coronavirus having a tropism for other hosts than humans.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Table&#x000a0;1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Protein Accession</th><th>E-value</th><th>Organism</th><th>NCBITax ID</th><th>% identity</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>AGO98871</td><td>1e-154</td><td>Bovine Coronavirus</td><td>11128</td><td>38.42%</td></tr><tr><td>QAY30020</td><td>3e-152</td><td>Canine respiratory coronavirus</td><td>215681</td><td>36.93%</td></tr><tr><td>ACJ35486</td><td>3e-150</td><td>Human enteric coronavirus</td><td>166124</td><td>37.68%</td></tr><tr><td>ACT10865</td><td>2e-105</td><td>Feline coronavirus</td><td>12663</td><td>32.26%</td></tr><tr><td>ABQ57216.1</td><td>4e-100</td><td>Bat coronavirus</td><td>693998</td><td>31.23%</td></tr><tr><td>AID16631</td><td>1e-145</td><td>Mouse coronavirus</td><td>1508222</td><td>36.56%</td></tr><tr><td>AID16649</td><td>8e-149</td><td>Rat coronavirus</td><td>1508223</td><td>37.60%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0030">A previous study of Hua and colleagues on the amino acid sequence of SARS CoV spike protein identified six epitopes based on the hydrophilicity, surface probability, antigenic index, and secondary structure [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>
).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Epitope details of the Spike glycoprotein of diverse coronaviruses.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Table&#x000a0;2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Protein GI</th><th>Epitope AAs</th><th>Epitope sequence</th><th>Organism</th><th>NCBI TaxID</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>QHR63290</td><td/><td/><td>SARS coronavirus 2</td><td>2697049</td></tr><tr><td/><td>424&#x02013;437</td><td>KLPDDFTGCVIAWN</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>447&#x02013;458</td><td>NYNYLYRLFRK</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>560&#x02013;571</td><td>LPFQQFGRDIAD</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>754&#x02013;764</td><td>LQYGSFCTQLN</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>789&#x02013;799</td><td>YKTPPIKDFGG</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>1139&#x02013;1152</td><td>DPLQPELDSFKEEL</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>QAY30020</td><td/><td/><td>Canine respiratory coronavirus</td><td>215681</td></tr><tr><td/><td>424&#x02013;437</td><td>SGYTVAATFASLFP</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>447&#x02013;458</td><td>FYLNVQYRINGI</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>560&#x02013;571</td><td>QLSDSTLVKFSA</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>754&#x02013;764</td><td>TYEYYVKWPWY</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>789&#x02013;799</td><td>CGTSCFKKCGG</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>1139&#x02013;1152</td><td>DPLQPELDSFKEEL</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>AHA50776</td><td/><td/><td>Bovine coronavirus</td><td>11128</td></tr><tr><td/><td>424&#x02013;437</td><td>ATSCQLYYNLPAAN</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>447&#x02013;458</td><td>TWNRRFGFTEQS</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>560&#x02013;571</td><td>EHCSGLAIKSDH</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>754&#x02013;764</td><td>SGYCVDYSTKR</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>789&#x02013;799</td><td>DSLEPVGGLYE</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>1139&#x02013;1152</td><td>NGNHIISLVQNAPY</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>ACJ35486</td><td/><td/><td>Human enteric coronavirus</td><td>166124</td></tr><tr><td/><td>424&#x02013;437</td><td>ATSCQLYYNLPAAN</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>447&#x02013;458</td><td>TWNRRFGFTEQS</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>560&#x02013;571</td><td>EHCSGLAIKSDH</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>754&#x02013;764</td><td>SGYCVDYSTKR</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>789&#x02013;799</td><td>DSLEPVGGLYE</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>1139&#x02013;1152</td><td>NGNHIISLVQNAPY</td><td/><td/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0035">The sequence homology analysis restricted to the epitope sequences of the SARS CoV-2 revealed instead high percentage homology towards taxonomically related coronaviruses. Of these, we retain it is worth of note the high similarity occurring among 4 epitope sequences of canine respiratory coronavirus (Canine respiratory CoV BJ 232) and the circulating SARS CoV-2 (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;3</xref>
).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Epitope sequence alignment. The table summarizes results from the alignment of SARS CoV-2 spike protein epitopes against the spike protein epitopes of other coronaviruses with known tropism for other animals than humans.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Table&#x000a0;3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Epitope</th><th>Organism</th><th>% identity</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3">424&#x02013;437</td><td>Bovine Coronavirus</td><td>80,00</td></tr><tr><td>Canine respiratory coronavirus</td><td>80,00</td></tr><tr><td>Human enteric coronavirus</td><td>80,00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">447&#x02013;458</td><td>Bovine Coronavirus</td><td>75,00</td></tr><tr><td>Canine respiratory coronavirus</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Human enteric coronavirus</td><td>75,00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">754&#x02013;764</td><td>Bovine Coronavirus</td><td>83,33</td></tr><tr><td>Canine respiratory coronavirus</td><td>83,33</td></tr><tr><td>Human enteric coronavirus</td><td>83,33</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">789&#x02013;799</td><td>Bovine Coronavirus</td><td>57,14</td></tr><tr><td>Canine respiratory coronavirus</td><td>57,14</td></tr><tr><td>Human enteric coronavirus</td><td>57,14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">1139&#x02013;1152</td><td>Bovine Coronavirus</td><td>70,00</td></tr><tr><td>Canine respiratory coronavirus</td><td>100,00</td></tr><tr><td>Human enteric coronavirus</td><td>70,00</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0040">Highlighting the similarity at the epitope level opens new avenues in understanding the biological mechanisms undertaken during viral infection. Before the current outbreak, several studies witness the common identification of coronavirus infection in dogs [<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Previous studies performed by Szczepanski and colleagues report the possibility to grow both bovine and canine coronavirus on human cells lines such as the Human Rectal Tumor cells (HRT-18G) and Human Airway Epithelium (HAE) although featured by a strongly reduced replication efficiency [<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In this view, a previous &#x0201c;contact&#x0201d; with the canine virus might provide at least a partial/basal immunization that shields humans against the circulating SARS CoV-2. This would partially explain the mild symptoms registered among patients outside the Hubei province and without previous co-morbidities. Accordingly, high similarity percentage have also been observed between SARS CoV-2 spike proteins epitopes and bovine coronavirus, which genome and proteins appear among those included in the patented vaccinal formulation released against coronavirus.</p><p id="p0045">With regard to the most severe cases of infection registered both outside and within the Hubei province, it is most likely that these individuals have been primed by one or more coronavirus exposure within a narrow time window, leading to the effects of Antibody-Dependent Enhancement (ADE) [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Such a hypothesis is in line with the previous observations dating back to the previous SARS outcome in 2003 when human coronaviruses, known to cause mild infections, were hypothesized of priming the high mortality scored in China. Here, anti-Spike protein antibodies were indicated as potentially involved in the enhancement mechanism [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>]. In this view, it is plausible that Hubei province patients are featured by a more severe clinical picture, since more likely to be recurrently exposed to the coronavirus.</p><p id="p0050">To summarize, animals have (had) a critical role in this outbreak onset and evolution. Acknowledged their pivotal role as virus reservoir, they might act in the first instance as &#x0201c;beneficial&#x0201d; source of immune-stimulating virus particles; thus, providing a shield against the circulating SARS CoV-2. However, the recurrent exposure within a narrow time-lapse might results in the detrimental triggering of violent immune responses and the evolution towards a more severe, or even fatal, clinical picture.</p><p id="p0055">Above hypotheses are based on the assumption that sufficient viral titer of the SARS CoV-2 is transmitted from patient to patient [<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The previous investigation on animal betacoronavirus such as the canine coronavirus have demonstrated a high transmission efficiency through direct contact between infected animals, acknowledged the high viral titers found in the aerosols of respiratory secretions [<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Novel investigations to assess the transmission rate of the canine respiratory coronavirus to humans are needed to better suit the above hypotheses. Also, care should be taken while evaluating the data on the sole basis of sequence homology and further studies employing purified forms of the spike proteins and/or its epitopes are desired.</p><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title><p id="p0060">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic characterisation and epidemiology of 2019 novel coronavirus: implications for virus origins and receptor binding</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>395</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>565</fpage><lpage>574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32007145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jalava</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First respiratory transmitted food borne outbreak?</article-title><source>Int J Hyg Environ Health</source><volume>226</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>113490</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32088598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emerging coronaviruses: genome structure, replication, and pathogenesis</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Med Virol</source><volume>92</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>418</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31967327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tetro</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is COVID-19 receiving ADE from other coronaviruses?</article-title><source>Microb Infect</source><year>2020</year><comment>online ahead of print</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zai</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Homologous recombination within the spike glycoprotein of the newly identified coronavirus may boost cross-species transmission from snake to human</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Med Virol</source><volume>92</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31967321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poon</surname><given-names>L.L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>I.H.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luk</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sia</surname><given-names>S.-F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M.H.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytokine responses in severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-infected macrophages in&#x000a0;vitro: possible relevance to pathogenesis</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Virol</source><volume>79</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>7819</fpage><lpage>7826</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15919935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghani</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>N.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiological and genetic analysis of severe acute respiratory syndrome</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><volume>4</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>672</fpage><lpage>683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15522679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) from different species sheds some light on cross-species receptor usage of a novel coronavirus 2019-nCoV</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Infect</source><year>2020</year><comment>online ahead of print</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of two antigenic epitopes on SARS-CoV spike protein</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><volume>319</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>929</fpage><lpage>935</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15184071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Decaro</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Desario</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elia</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mari</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucente</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cordioli</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serological and molecular evidence that canine respiratory coronavirus is circulating in Italy</article-title><source>Vet Microbiol</source><volume>121</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17215093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tennant</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaskell</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaskell</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on the epizootiology of canine coronavirus</article-title><source>Vet Rec</source><volume>132</volume><year>1993</year><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8382389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szczepanski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Owczarek</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Milewska</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baster</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajfur</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Canine respiratory coronavirus employs caveolin-1-mediated pathway for internalization to HRT-18G cells</article-title><source>Vet Res</source><volume>49</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>55</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29970183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szczepanski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Owczarek</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bzowska</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gula</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Drebot</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ochman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Canine respiratory coronavirus, bovine coronavirus, and human coronavirus OC43: receptors and attachment factors</article-title><source>Viruses</source><volume>11</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>328</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>W.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Traggiai</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanzavecchia</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evasion of antibody neutralization in emerging severe acute respiratory syndrome coronaviruses</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>102</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>797</fpage><lpage>801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15642942</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Di</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neutralizing antibody response and SARS severity</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><volume>11</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>1730</fpage><lpage>1737</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16318725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>N.H.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.H.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Da&#x000eb;ron</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibody-dependent infection of human macrophages by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus</article-title><source>Virol J</source><volume>11</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>82</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24885320</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaume</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>H.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kien</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus spike antibodies trigger infection of human immune cells via a pH- and cysteine protease-independent Fc R pathway</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Virol</source><volume>85</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>10582</fpage><lpage>10597</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21775467</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsao</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibody-dependent SARS coronavirus infection is mediated by antibodies against spike proteins</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><volume>451</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25073113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>D.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Presumed asymptomatic carrier transmission of COVID-19</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2020</year><comment>online ahead of print</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buonavoglia</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Decaro</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martella</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elia</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campolo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Desario</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Canine coronavirus highly pathogenic for dogs</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><volume>12</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>492</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16704791</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgement</title><p>None.</p></ack></back></article>