<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A growing body of evidence points to an intricate functional interplay between IAV infection and the cellular RNA decay machineries (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25–28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Our systematic screening strategy further highlights a specific targeting of RNA degradation pathways shared by different H1N1 IAV strains. Furthermore, the detection of an effect on the viral life cycle for eight of 19 interactors identified among the 75 tested from the original ExoRDec library, underscores the performance of the stringent protein-protein interaction screen applied here for the identification of functionally relevant factors. Some of the identified factors have been previously reported to be essential for IAV replication, such as the Double-stranded RNA-specific adenosine deaminase ADAR and the U6 snRNA phosphodiesterase USB1 (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>), or to be important for the replication of other RNA viruses, such as the Apoptosis-Enhancing Nuclease AEN and the DNA-(apurinic or apyrimidinic site) lyase APEX1 (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54–56</xref>). Interestingly, redundant targeting was observed in most instances, with factors targeted by three (ADAR, HMGA2) or even four (ADARB1, EXOSC6, ERI1) viral proteins. This redundant targeting may reflect the importance for the virus to target those specific pathways. Remarkably, our study identifies the exosome subunit EXOSC6, found by others to interact with PA, as an interactor of PB2, PB1, NS1 and NEP (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Such broad targeting of the RNA exosome by viral proteins further highlights its crucial requirement in the IAV life cycle. A more extensive comparative screening with proteins from a wider range of IAV strains will however be required to further generalize these observations. It is interesting to note that the viral protein PA-X was not included in our initial screening of the ExoRDec library because of technical constraints related to the PCA design. As PA-X is known to be tightly associated to RNA decay (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>), its screening against the ExoRDec library could also be of great interest.
</p>
