<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the cell, ERI1 has multiple roles both in the cytoplasm and in the nucleus. In the latter, ERI1 mostly plays a role in histone mRNA maturation, while in the cytoplasm, it is involved in histone mRNA decay, 5.8S rRNA maturation and miRNA homeostasis (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29–36</xref>). A common feature of all these processes is the prime role of ERI1 in RNA 3′ end trimming. Trimming of histone pre-mRNA by ERI1 requires the recognition of the 3′ stem loop upstream of the processing site. However, ERI1 trimming of other RNA species does not seem to require a specific RNA sequence nor structure aside from the existence of a 3′ ssRNA overhang. Various RNA species can thus be potential substrates for ERI1, but whether these include viral mRNAs is not known. Our data uncovered a role of ERI1 in promoting viral transcription of influenza A viruses, mostly evident during the early stages of the viral life cycle, for which both ERI1 activities - RNA binding and 3′-5′ exoribonuclease activities - were shown to be required. The RNA binding activity requirement could at least be explained by the recruitment of ERI1 when it is stably bound to histone pre-mRNAs in association with SLBP, as supported by our results showing an RNA dependency in an infectious context. Since ERI1 seems also able to directly interact with IAV viral RNA, one could envision that ERI1, recruited as part of the histone processing complex, could then directly interact with the viral proteins of the vRNPs in order to be loaded onto viral RNAs. The role of the exonuclease domain is also not clear at this stage. Interestingly, the exonuclease domain of ERI3 was not shown to be required for its role in promoting Dengue virus 2 mRNA synthesis (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), suggesting that the mechanisms involved in promoting viral transcription, which are also still unknown for Dengue virus, might differ. We observed a clear enrichment in viral mRNAs co-purified with ERI1. Since ERI1 is known to play a role in the maturation of cellular RNAs, one could envisage that ERI1 contributes to the maturation of IAV mRNAs during synthesis, which is necessary for their efficient translation. RNA-seq methodology might be an interesting tool to test this hypothesis.
</p>
