<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>MNV-1 is an important norovirus model system since it can be propagated in a cell culture system, aspects of its pathogenesis and the host immune response can be examined in an animal model, large amounts of virus can be readily produced, neutralizing monoclonal antibodies have been isolated, and an infectious clone has been developed [
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-11-00235" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Therefore, in spite of the fact that structures of a number of other members of the 
 <italic>Caliciviridae</italic> family had been determined (e.g. Norwalk virus, NV [
 <xref rid="B11-viruses-11-00235" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], and San Miguel sea lion virus, SMSV [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-11-00235" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]), it was necessary to determine the structure of MNV-1 for comparison. Surprisingly, even from the initial examination of the MNV-1 electron density (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00235-f002">Figure 2</xref>), it was quite apparent that the structure of MNV-1 was significantly different than the NV virus like particle (VLP) crystal structure [
 <xref rid="B14-viruses-11-00235" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-11-00235" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. While the P domains of NV VLPs rest upon the shell domain, there was a large gap in the electron density between the shell and protruding domains of MNV-1 (see mauve arrows in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00235-f002">Figure 2</xref>). When the NV VLP structure was overlaid onto the MNV-1 density, it was clear that the entire P1 domain lies in that gap between the P and S domains and that the electron density for the MNV-1 protruding domains extended far beyond the outer extents of the P2 domains. This gives the appearance that the MNV-1 P domains lift up off the shell (S domains) to form a second proteinacous layer. The two conformations represented by NV (compressed) and MNV (expanded) is further exemplified by the atomic models of the two viruses (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-11-00235-f003">Figure 3</xref>). As shown in this figure, there is a linker region between the S and P domains in both viruses but is coiled up in NV and extended in MNV.
</p>
