<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14">Zika virus (ZIKV, genus 
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic>, family 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic>) was isolated for the first time in the Zika forest near Entebbe, Uganda, in 1947 from a febrile sentinel Rhesus monkey (
 <italic>Macaca mulatta</italic>). One year later the virus was isolated from 
 <italic>Aedes africanus</italic> in the same area [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The first human case was reported in 1952 in Nigeria [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Subsequently, serological and virological studies showed the circulation of ZIKV in several other African [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] and Asian countries [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The virus was almost silent for 60 years until its reemergence in 2007 with the Yap Island and Gabon outbreaks [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. It is during the last decade that the Asian genotype of ZIKV has experienced significant geographic expansion causing major epidemics in the Pacific Islands [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] and in America [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Indeed, phylogenic studies on sequenced ZIKV strains isolated from Brazil, Puerto Rico and Guatemala indicated that they were all within the Asian genotype and closely related to the French Polynesia strain [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. ZIKV is known to cause several debilitating neurological complications, including microcephaly in newborns and Guillain Barré Syndrome in adults, described in both Latin America and the Pacific Islands [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. In the urban cycle, ZIKV is mainly transmitted by 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>, but cases of non-vector transmission like sexual transmission, blood transfusion, or other fluid transmissions were reported [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. In West Africa, ZIKV has a sylvatic cycle (described in southeastern Senegal) involving mainly non-human primates and arboreal 
 <italic>Aedes (Ae. furcifer, Ae. luteocephalus, Ae. africanus, Ae. vittatus, Ae. dalzieli and Ae. taylori),</italic> while 
 <italic>Ae. africanus</italic> plays this role in Central and Eastern Africa [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. In this cycle, humans are rarely infected when entering in forest or by 
 <italic>Ae. furcifer</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae. vittatus</italic> in villages [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].
</p>
