<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">ZIKV is the most frequently amplified arbovirus in Senegal [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Indeed, it was detected in mosquitoes during 21 of the 44 years of monitoring between 1972 and 2015 in the southeastern part of the country. However, ZIKV prevalence and vector density drop dramatically beyond detection by current methods each year during the dry season, generally between January and May. These data suggest that in southeastern Senegal, vectors and ZIKV are maintained locally in nature during adverse conditions corresponding to the dry season and the years when the virus is undetectable by current methods. Since the vectors belong mainly to the 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> genus, their maintenance in nature is probably done through their desiccation-resistant eggs in larval breeding sites. The presence of eggs of 9 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> species from dry tree holes from one forest-gallery has already been demonstrated by Diallo and others in 1999–2000 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. However, the relative importance of tree holes for the dry season maintenance of these 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> eggs compared to the others breeding sites [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] has not yet been investigated. The same is true of forests compared to other land covers. The detection of the virus in a pool of male 
 <italic>Ae. furcifer</italic> in 2011 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] suggests that vertical transmission, from infected females to its progeny via eggs, may be an important mechanism for local virus maintenance. In addition, there is currently no data on the mechanisms and vertical transmission rates in nature. There is also no data on species and breeding sites involved and their levels of participation in this mechanism. Our first objective was to identify the vector species in which Zika virus is maintained during dry season, and their specific infection rates, using genetic testing methods. Our second objective was to identify if vector species are more likely to use certain combinations of breeding site types and land cover classes than others to lay their eggs, using mainly a qualitative statistical approach on vector species occurrence. We expected that Zika virus would be maintained through certain mosquito species, and these mosquito species preferentially use certain combinations of breeding site types and land cover classes to lay their eggs.
</p>
