<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pgen.1008850.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1008850.g001</object-id>
 <label>Fig 1</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Phylogenetic relationship of the ST19 
   <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium phylogroup.
  </title>
  <p>(A) Maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree and based on sequence variation (SNPs) in the core genome with reference to 
   <italic>S</italic>. Typhimurium strain SL1344. The root was identified using 
   <italic>S</italic>. Heidelberg (accession number NC_011083.1) as the outgroup. 1
   <sup>st</sup> (α and β) and 3
   <sup>rd</sup> (α11–19 and β1–7) are indicated (vertical bars). Phage type complexes associated with the third-level clusters are indicated (bold type) colour coded with the lineages and representative strains from third level clusters (italicized type). The source of each isolate in the tree is indicated by filled boxes colour coded as indicated in the inset key (arrow). The presence of replicon sequence (grey box), antimicrobial resistance genes (blue box) and hypothetically disrupted coding sequence (HDCS) of virulence related genes (red box) in short read sequence data are indicated. HDCS in 
   <italic>nfsA</italic> and 
   <italic>nfsB</italic> resulting in resistance to nitrofuran antibiotics and ns SNPs resulting in substitutions in the QRDR of GyrA are indicated (light blue boxes). (B) Bars indicate the number of ancestral (black), phage or insertion sequence elements (grey), chromosomal gene (colour coded with lineages in 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008850.g001">Fig 1A</xref>) HDCS in the genome of representative strains from each third level clade. (C) Box plots indicate the mean Δbitscore (DBS: bitscore SL1344 –test strain bitscore) of proteomes in third level clades. (D) Box plot indicates the percentage of the proteome of the proteome of isolates from each third level clade with a non-zero bitscore (bitscore SL1344 –test strain bitscore &gt;0 or &lt;0) as an estimate of function divergence. (E) Box plots indicate the mean invasiveness index per genome, the fraction of random forest decision trees voting for an invasiveness phenotype based on training on the DBS of a subset of the proteome of ten gastrointestinal and extraintestinal pathovar serotypes.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pgen.1008850.g001" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
