<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0055">Rhinoviruses (RVs) are positive-sense, single-stranded RNA viruses belonging to the Picornaviridae family and Enterovirus genus. Although generally mild and self-limiting, RVs have been implicated in the induction of upper RTIs, including asthma, bronchiolitis, and common colds, in infants and the deterioration of airways in elderly people and immunocompromised patients [
 <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. In many RV strains, antigenic diversity and phenotype characteristics can affect disease severity and are significant obstacles to vaccine development [
 <xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. Human rhinovirus (HRV) represents one of the most significant etiological agents of upper respiratory illnesses, particularly common cold. Although mild to indistinguishable, HRV infection can lead to severe health complications and severe exacerbation of asthma [
 <xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. When the antiviral activities of PT-type ginsenosides (Re, Rf, and Rg2) and PD-type ginsenosides (Rb1, Rb2, Rc, and Rd) on RV infection were examined, PT-type ginsenosides protected HeLa cells from HRV3-induced apoptosis. However, PD-type ginsenosides activated HRV3-induced apoptosis and did not show any preventive effect, suggesting a structure-dependent effect of ginsenosides on HRV3 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5052424/" id="intref0085" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5052424/</ext-link> [
 <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Furthermore, PT-type ginsenosides showed noticeable antiviral effects against coxsackievirus B3 and HRV3 when administered at 100 mg/mL for 48 h. Among the PT-type ginsenosides, Rg2 exhibited significant antienterovirus 71 effects, with no cytotoxic activity at 100 mg/mL. However, PD-type ginsenosides did not display any antiviral effect against coxsackievirus B3, enterovirus 71, and HRV3, and showed cytotoxic activity in virus-infected cells [
 <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>].
</p>
