<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <bold>MARV</bold>: 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="viruses-06-02084-t002">Table 2</xref> shows a summary of reported testing for MARV in bat species. There are several studies reporting the prevalence of MARV in bats in caves in Africa including the countries of Gabon, Uganda and the Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC) [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B72-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,
 <xref rid="B75-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>,
 <xref rid="B76-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. MARV is now considered endemic in 
 <italic>R. aegyptiacus</italic> bats in Gabon [
 <xref rid="B76-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>] and, in general, those bat species which serve as potential reservoirs for MARV are endemic to regions of Central Africa. There is little evidence for the potential of MARV to occur outside Africa at this point, although there are few published reports of testing for this virus on other continents; a study in India showed that none of 140 bats tested, including 
 <italic>P. giganteus</italic> (
 <italic>n</italic> = 31), 
 <italic>Cynopterus sphinx</italic> (
 <italic>n</italic> = 30) and 
 <italic>Megaderma lyra</italic> (
 <italic>n</italic> = 79), were positive by PCR for MARV RNA [
 <xref rid="B66-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Within Africa, there are also reports of antibody or RNA evidence of MARV infection in bat species other than 
 <italic>R. aegyptiacus</italic>, such as 
 <italic>Rhinolophus eloquens</italic>, 
 <italic>Miniopterus inflatus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and 
 <italic>Hypsignatus monstrosus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B75-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>], but reports are less frequent. This highlights the importance of knowledge on the exact species of bats for the purpose of risk assessment, suggesting the main zoonotic risk is likely from 
 <italic>R. aegyptiacus.</italic> In an experimental study, MARV was found to be present in the blood and saliva of viraemic 
 <italic>R. aegyptiacus</italic> bats but not in their faeces or urine [
 <xref rid="B56-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>], suggesting that close contact between adjacent bats of the same species within the roost may be important for MARV transmission. MARV RNA has also been reported in a pooled liver, spleen, lung extract from a female 
 <italic>R. aegyptiacus</italic> fruit bat in Kenya in 2007, although tissues from other bats including 75 
 <italic>R. aegyptiacus</italic> from two locations were negative [
 <xref rid="B77-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. From an EU perspective, 
 <italic>R. aegyptiacus</italic> are known to be present in Cyprus [
 <xref rid="B78-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>] and Turkey [
 <xref rid="B79-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>] and populations were found in the wild in Tenerife in the early 2000s, as a result of escaped captive animals [
 <xref rid="B80-viruses-06-02084" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>], before being effectively eradicated by 2009. There is no reported evidence to suggest presence (or absence) of MARV in these populations.
</p>
