<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0050">The seminal studies by 
 <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">Mauck et al. (2010)</xref> and later work (
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">Carmo-Sousa et al., 2014</xref>), which investigated the interactions of aphids (
 <italic>Myzus persicae</italic> and 
 <italic>Aphis gossypii</italic>) with CMV-infected cucurbit hosts, showed that CMV manipulated its own transmission in two ways. Firstly, CMV engenders the emission by the plant of increased levels of aphid-attracting volatile organic compounds (VOCs), and secondly the virus induces synthesis of anti-feedant compounds in plant tissue (antixenosis). These virus-mediated changes in plant phenotype cause aphids to be at first attracted by the VOCs to feed upon CMV-infected plants and acquire viral inoculum, only to be subsequently repelled by the taste of the antixenotic compounds (
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">Carmo-Sousa et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr">Mauck et al., 2010</xref>) (
 <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). CMV has similar effects on interactions between 
 <italic>M. persicae</italic> and 
 <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and between aphids and tomato (Arinaitwe W., unpublished data; Bravo-Cazar A., unpublished data; 
 <xref rid="bib0270" ref-type="bibr">Westwood et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0285" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2017</xref>). In CMV-infected 
 <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, antixenosis results from increased accumulation of 4-methoxy-indol-3-yl-methylglucosinolate (4MI3M), especially within the phloem tissue, and electrical penetration graph analysis showed that ingestion of phloem sap by 
 <italic>M. persicae</italic> is consequently discouraged (
 <xref rid="bib0270" ref-type="bibr">Westwood et al., 2013</xref>). The virally-modified host phenotypes seen in CMV-infected cucurbits and 
 <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, in which plants first attract aphids and then deter them from settling (‘attract and deter’), are likely to encourage the spread of viral inoculum by aphids from infected plants to neighbouring uninfected hosts (
 <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">Donnelly et al., 2019</xref>) (
 <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).
</p>
