<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ribavirin is a guanosine nucleoside analog and antiviral compound used to treat various viral infections, such as RSV, hepatitis C virus, bunyavirus, herpesvirus, adenovirus, poxvirus, and some viral hemorrhagic fevers. Ribavirin was first used in 1980 to treat the RSV in children. The antiviral activity of ribavirin is by intracellular guanosine depletion through inhibition of the inosine monophosphate dehydrogenase enzyme, which disrupts guanosine synthesis, it also has an indirect effect on virus replication by increasing 
 <italic>IFN</italic> gene expression and modulating immune responses. Ribavirin is an inhibitor of RNA synthesis by viral RdRp as well as an inhibitor of mRNA capping (Graci &amp; Cameron, 
 <xref rid="jcp29785-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>; Martinez, 
 <xref rid="jcp29785-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). In animal studies of coronaviruses, ribavirin, although weakly inhibitory, can reduce the release of macrophage proinflammatory cytokines in mice and alter the Th‐2 response to Th‐1 response and act as an immunomodulator (Ning et al., 
 <xref rid="jcp29785-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">1998</xref>). In most cases, ribavirin is combined with IFN, and although the results of ribavirin and IFNα‐2b in a MERS‐CoV rhesus macaque model were promising, with the results of the trial and the effect of ribavirin and IFN (either α2a or β1) on MERS‐CoV infected patients it was different, however, ribavirin lowers hemoglobin concentrations in respiratory patients and therefore reduces its potential as an antiviral against SARS‐CoV‐2 (Arabi et al., 
 <xref rid="jcp29785-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Falzarano et al., 
 <xref rid="jcp29785-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). IFNα‐2b and ribavirin, when used for MERS‐CoV treatment, showed that they were 8‐fold and 16‐fold reduced in their single‐dose regimen, respectively and they further stimulate cytokine release and immune responses, reducing viral replication, modulating host response, and improving clinical outcomes. Studies using ribavirin plus lopinavir/ritonavir on patients with SARS have reduced ARDS and mortality. There was also a significant decrease in ARDS and mortality in patients with SARS‐CoV who received corticosteroids with ribavirin, lopinavir/ritonavir (Chu et al., 
 <xref rid="jcp29785-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>; Zheng &amp; Wang, 
 <xref rid="jcp29785-bib-0068" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>).
</p>
