<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Under the experimental conditions tested, CSBV Cefas W054 showed low pathogenicity in two UK fish species: common carp and pre-smolt Atlantic salmon; however, further trials mimicking different environmental conditions (e.g., higher temperatures) are recommended to fully understand the potential threat of this exotic virus to the UK. Under the conditions evaluated in this study, mild pathological changes were observed in challenged common carp and high levels of antibodies were measured in those animals, indicating that common carp is susceptible to CSBV infection and that the viral replication triggers a specific immune response. There are not many reports about fish nidovirales’ host range and pathogenicity. CSBV HB93, YCBV and WBV DF24/00 were isolated from fish showing no clinical signs of disease [
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-12-00578" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-12-00578" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-viruses-12-00578" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] but the pathogenic FHMNV caused mortalities in fathead minnows [
 <xref rid="B42-viruses-12-00578" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] and, under experimental infections, in other cyprinid species, such as spotfin shiner 
 <italic>Cyprinella spiloptera</italic> [
 <xref rid="B56-viruses-12-00578" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. In susceptible fish species challenged using the IP route of infection, both CSBV Cefas W054 and FHMNV presented similar clinical signs and histopathology, with the appearance of petechial haemorrhages and oedematous changes in the liver and multifocal areas of necrosis in internal organs. However, FHMNV showed higher pathogenicity than CSBV W054 at a similar viral dose (~10
 <sup>4</sup> TCID
 <sub>50</sub> mL
 <sup>−1</sup>), with a mortality rate of 60% in susceptible fish via the immersion route. There are no published data about seroconversion in FHMNV-susceptible fish or other fish exposed to nidoviruses. Thus, this is the first report showing neutralising antibodies in common carp and goldfish exposed to a piscanivirus, which can aid in developing serology-based surveillance programs. 
</p>
