<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Corticosteroids, such as methylprednisolone, have been proposed as adjunctive therapy, albeit with concerns about their use for novel coronavirus patients. Corticosteroids are widely used to treat severe community‐acquired pneumonia to prevent lung damage because they have suppressive effects of severe and systemic inflammation. But numerous studies show evidence of the ineffectiveness of corticosteroid treatment on viral pneumonia such as SARS‐CoV, MERS‐CoV, and H1N1 virus. Long‐term administration of high doses of corticosteroids in the early stages of treatment also has negative effects (Arabi et al., 
 <xref rid="jcp29785-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Jiang et al., 
 <xref rid="jcp29785-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>). Low or physiological doses of corticosteroids do not reduce the mortality caused by septic shock following primary pulmonary infection; but it can also have benefits, such as an earlier reversal of shock, a shorter time for the patient to exit the ICU and mechanical ventilation (Rhodes et al., 
 <xref rid="jcp29785-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Corticosteroid therapy for severe patients with ARDS can reduce pulmonary fibrosis and prevent the progression of serious pathological conditions; Also, the use of low doses can lead to a severe reduction in H1N1 mortality All of these results suggest that the appropriate use of low‐dose corticosteroids may lead to recovery and treatment for patients with 2019‐nCoV infection; however, this treatment should be performed following the guidelines recommended for patients with novel coronavirus pneumonia (NCP) who have specific clinical symptoms, such as ARDS or septic shock Systematic corticosteroids treatment in the first 3–5 days could increase oxygen saturation and arterial oxygen tension/inspiratory oxygen fraction, however, corticosteroids do not affect the recovery and survival of NCP patients with ARDS and shock. There are no specific and consistent clinical guidelines for the therapeutic use of corticosteroids in patients in intensive care units. Generally, corticosteroids should be avoided unless the patient has symptoms such as moderate or severe ARDS, sepsis, or septic shock until used following recommended WHO clinical guidelines. Corticosteroids are also not recommended for mild or early ARDS, because early corticosteroids can delay the clearance of the virus and increase the risk of death (Zhou et al., 
 <xref rid="jcp29785-bib-0069" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>).
</p>
