<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="discussion"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?OLF?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Lancet HIV</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Lancet HIV</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Lancet. HIV</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2405-4704</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2352-3018</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7402651</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2352-3018(20)30195-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2352-3018(20)30195-8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Control of epidemics by jails: lessons for COVID-19 from HIV</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au10"><name><surname>Ohuabunwa</surname><given-names>Tochi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au20"><name><surname>Spaulding</surname><given-names>Anne C</given-names></name><email>aspauld@emory.edu</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Epidemiology, Rollins School of Public Health, Emory University, Atlanta, GA 30322, USA</aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>4</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Elsevier Ltd</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article related-article-type="article-reference" id="d33e184" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/S2352-3018(20)30188-0"/></article-meta></front><body><p id="para10">Of the 10&#x000b7;2 million people incarcerated worldwide, an estimated 3&#x000b7;8% of individuals are HIV-positive, a proportion that varies widely by region.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> To achieve the ambitious UNAIDS 90-90-90 target,<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> strategies must address incarcerated people with HIV, as well as those at liberty. Universal test-and-treat (UTT) interventions represent an important step towards achieving these goals; through earlier linkage to antiretroviral therapy (ART) and wider ART coverage among people with HIV, the spread of HIV could be prevented and potentially, the HIV/AIDS epidemic could be ended.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> However, progress towards the HIV/AIDS 90-90-90 targets has not been equally distributed across subpopulations, demographics, or regions. Incarcerated people are especially disadvantaged and at risk.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</p><p id="para20">In <italic>The Lancet HIV</italic>, Michael Herce and colleagues<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> report the clinical outcomes of a prospective cohort study at three correctional facilities in South Africa and Zambia, which show that UTT implementation is feasible and effective in prison settings. Over a 1 year period, the authors introduced a UTT intervention in adult correctional facilities and tracked time to ART initiation and viral load suppression at 6 months and 12 months follow-up visits. Herce and colleagues found rapid HIV testing could be followed by on-site, rapid initiation of ART care. 835 (86%) of 975 eligible participants enrolled initiated ART with a median time from enrolment to ART initiation of 0 days (IQR 0&#x02013;8). The high rates of loss to follow up at the correctional facilities was a major limitation of the study. 415 (50%) of the 835 participants who initiated ART had left their initial facility at 6 months. However, 327 (95%) of 346 participants who remained incarcerated at 6 months were retained in care. Furthermore, of the 269 participants eligible for the 6 month follow-up analysis who had at least one viral load result documented, 262 (97%) had achieved viral suppression (&#x0003c;1000 copies per mL) at 6 months. Through early linkage to ART and high retention in care, the proportion of the prison cohort who achieved viral load suppression was similar to that observed in other African community-based trials for treatment-as-prevention (up to 88% of individuals achieved suppression).<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>
</p><p id="para30">Our own experience has shown that rapid testing for HIV can also be successfully implemented in US jails. Our study done in Atlanta (GA, USA), using routine, rapid opt-out screenings at a county jail, showed that the strategy was both feasible and cost-saving compared with sporadic, laboratory-based tests. A higher number of individuals received new HIV diagnoses in the rapid screening group than did those who had sporadic laboratory-based screening (89 <italic>vs</italic> 15). All individuals who had rapid screening received their test result; and most could start treatment in jail.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Compared with the sporadic, laboratory-based screening, rapid screening resulted in a reduction of US$2&#x000b7;8 million in US health-care costs, when considering HIV diagnoses averted when a higher number of people were aware of their HIV status.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Rapid ART initiation, which Herce and colleagues achieved, was not part of the Atlanta jail programme. The findings from Herce and coauthors might lead to replication of rapid UTT implementation in jails globally. Despite the evidence that UTT can be feasible and effective, such measures to end the HIV epidemic are rarely implemented in correctional facilities, often as a result of prejudice, disdain, and ignorance,<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> whereby the needs of incarcerated people are often overlooked. When will the health and wellbeing of incarcerated people no longer be ignored?</p><p id="para40">The COVID-19 pandemic first affected incarcerated individuals in China, and now the same pattern has been observed globally, including in the USA.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Herce and colleagues implemented the same standard of HIV care practised in the community into correctional facilities.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> In the same way, as new approaches for managing the coronavirus epidemic in the community are developed&#x02014;aggressive testing of symptomatic and asymptomatic people with contact tracing&#x02014;the same standard of care will be needed in correctional facilities. Only by doing so can the role of prisons and jails as reservoirs of viral infection be minimised. Failure to control and prevent the spread of viruses within prisons and jails will undermine population-level targets, which could cost lives and result in health-care costs similar to that observed with COVID-19 disease in the past 3&#x02013;4 months and the ongoing HIV epidemic for the past 3&#x02013;4 decades. The idea of health for all must be adopted universally to prevent disease and to uphold human rights to health and dignity for individuals within and outside of prison walls.</p></body><back><ref-list id="bibl10"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirtz</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Moazen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global burden of HIV, viral hepatitis, and tuberculosis in prisoners and detainees</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>388</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1089</fpage><lpage>1102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27427453</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>UNAIDS</collab></person-group><chapter-title>Global AIDS update 2018: Miles to go</chapter-title><year>2018</year><publisher-name>UNAIDS</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.unaids.org/sites/default/files/media_asset/miles-to-go_en.pdf" id="interrefs10">https://www.unaids.org/sites/default/files/media_asset/miles-to-go_en.pdf</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baggaley</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollingsworth</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How universal does universal test and treat have to be?</article-title><source>Lancet HIV</source><volume>7</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>e306</fpage><lpage>e308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32061316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beyrer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamarulzaman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McKee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prisoners, prisons, and HIV: time for reform</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>388</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1033</fpage><lpage>1035</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27427447</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herce</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fielding</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Universal test-and-treat in Zambian and South African correctional facilities: a multisite prospective cohort study</article-title><source>Lancet HIV</source><year>2020</year><comment>published online Aug 4.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2352-3018(20)30188-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref60"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdool Karim</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HIV-1 epidemic control-insights from test-and-treat trials</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>381</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>286</fpage><lpage>288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31314975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="oref10">Hutchinson AB, MacGowan R, Margolis A, Adee MG, Bowden CJ, Spaulding AC. Costs and outcomes associated with discontinuing a routine HIV screening program in a high volume jail. Annual Meeting of the Society for Medical Decision Making; Portland; Oct 20&#x02013;23, 2019 (abstr PS 1&#x02013;31).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="oref20">Spaulding AC, Adee MG, Bowden CJ, et al. Routine, rapid HIV screening of jail entrants in Fulton County (GA, USA) not only links more people to care but also is cost-saving. Adherence 2019&#x02013;International Association of Providers of AIDS Care; Miami; June 17&#x02013;19, 2019 (abstr).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref70"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawks</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolhandler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 in prisons and jails in the United States</article-title><source>JAMA Intern Med</source><year>2020</year><comment>published online April 28.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2020.1856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref80"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Spaulding</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flattening the curve for incarcerated populations&#x02013;Covid-19 in jails and prisons</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>382</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>2075</fpage><lpage>2077</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32240582</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack><p>ACS reports grants and personal fees from Gilead, has served on an advisory board for Gilead Sciences, reports honoraria through third parties funded by Gilead, AbbVie, and Merck, personal fees from National Commission on Correctional Health Care, National Sheriff's Association, and Harris County Sheriff's Office, travel expenses from bioLytical Sciences and Guardian, during the conduct of the study; and research funding from Cellex. TO declares no competing interests.</p></ack></back></article>