<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The mechanism of action of ribavirin against HCV 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> and the mechanism of resistance to ribavirin by HCV ribavirin resistant mutants has not been completely elucidated. The differential sensitivity observed for HCV-RR2 to 5-Fluorouracil and 2′-C-Methylcytidine when compared to parental J6/JFH1 virus indicates that mechanisms and/or viral RNA sequences implicated in the antiviral activity of these drugs could be involved in mechanism and/or viral RNA sequences of the antiviral activity of ribavirin. This is supported by the fact that 5-Fluorouracil is a pyrimidine analog and 2′-C-Methylcytidine and ribavirin are both nucleoside analogs. Given the nature of these drugs, it is tempting to speculate that ribavirin acts on HCV at the RNA replication level, as it has been shown for 2′-C-Methylcytidine 
 <xref rid="pone.0074027-LePogam1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. We previously showed that an HCV ribavirin resistant mutant has mutations in different positions of its genome including the RNA dependent RNA polymerase 
 <xref rid="pone.0074027-Feigelstock1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, and others found that the RNA dependent RNA polymerase from HCV can use ribavirin triphosphate as a nucleotide substrate. Once ribavirin monophosphate has been incorporated in the nascent chain, it can reduce or even block RNA elongation 
 <xref rid="pone.0074027-Maag1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0074027-Vo1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. As noted above, mutagenic activity of ribavirin on HCV has been observed 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> and 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>
 <xref rid="pone.0074027-Brochot1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0074027-Kanda1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>
 <xref rid="pone.0074027-Hofmann1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0074027-Lutchman1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>
 <xref rid="pone.0074027-Dietz1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>.
</p>
