<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The engagement of receptors or agonist binding to the cell surface receptors activate phospholipase C (PLC), which hydrolyses phosphatidylinositol-4,5-biphosphate (PIP
 <sub>2</sub>) to produce IP
 <sub>3</sub>. The activation of IP
 <sub>3</sub>R triggers Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> release from stores and further increases IP
 <sub>3</sub>R’s sensitivity to Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>. Targeting IP
 <sub>3</sub>Rs is more universal among different virus types. In turn, this process generates a more profound effect on host cell physiology, including metabolic stress, neurotoxicity, and enterotoxicity. Modifying IP
 <sub>3</sub> and directly interfering with IP
 <sub>3</sub>R are the main ways in which viruses affect calcium release through IP
 <sub>3</sub>R. For example, human cytomegalovirus (HCMV) UL37x1 protein interacts with the host P2Y2 purinergic receptor to increase intracellular Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> levels via the PLC–IP
 <sub>3</sub> pathway, and this activity is important to viral replication [
 <xref rid="B61-cells-09-00094" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. HIV-1 Gp120 and Tat upregulate intracellular IP
 <sub>3</sub> [
 <xref rid="B37-cells-09-00094" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-cells-09-00094" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>], while HIV Nef [
 <xref rid="B63-cells-09-00094" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-cells-09-00094" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>] and p12(I) human T-cell lymphotropic virus type 1 (HTLV-1) [
 <xref rid="B65-cells-09-00094" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>] activate IP
 <sub>3</sub>R directly as an agonist. Glycoprotein E of HSV redistributes the density of IP
 <sub>3</sub>Rs within infected cells [
 <xref rid="B66-cells-09-00094" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Some virus proteins activate IP
 <sub>3</sub>R through both ways. Enterotoxin NSP4 of RV and HCMV UL37x1-encoded protein increases the basal permeability of the ER as IP
 <sub>3</sub> diffuses and binds to IP
 <sub>3</sub>Rs to stimulate Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> release. These virus proteins deplete ER Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> storage during early stages of viral infection to increase the replication ability of viruses. On the other hand, the depletion of ER calcium storage triggers the calcium influx through SOCs (STIM1/ORAI1).
</p>
