<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Experimental investigations of several disease models confirm that higher levels of systemic estrogens promote anti-inflammatory responses. 17-β-estradiol is the predominant estrogen during the reproductive years, both in its total serum concentration and in overall estrogenic activity. Estradiol down-regulates immune functions in endothelial cells, including the stimulation of leukocyte adhesion and migration to infected tissues (
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>-
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>). It is known that estrogen plays a protective role in endothelial function (
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>), activating the generation of nitric oxide (NO) via endothelial nitric oxide synthase (eNOS), which is mediated by mechanisms that lead to an increase in NO bioavailability through the induction of gene transcription and activation of eNOS via phosphatidylinositol-3-kinase/serine-threonine kinase (PI3K/AKT) (
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>). Still, studies by our group using an aortic occlusion model in male rats indicate that previous treatment with estradiol has a beneficial effect on the course of mesenteric ischemia and intestinal injury, preventing mortality due to systemic inflammation (
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>). Additionally, in an intestinal ischemia and reperfusion (I/R) model, results indicate that female sex hormones, notably estradiol, exert a protective effect on preventing/reducing lung and intestinal injuries caused by systemic inflammation after ischemic trauma (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>-
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>). Proestrus or estradiol-treated females showed reduced lung damage and inflammation in ischemia and reperfusion models (
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>,
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>) and in a hemorrhagic shock model (
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>). In addition, treatment with estradiol showed anti-inflammatory action similar to that of glucocorticoids, with reduced expression of transcription factors involved in the inflammatory response and reduced recruitment of neutrophils by decreasing the production of interleukins, such as IL-8, in addition to chemokines and adhesion molecules (
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>).
</p>
