<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since the beginning of the 21st century, Asian countries have been significantly prone to endemic diseases. This has been particularly true in India due to its increasing population, with the country having faced more than 10 outbreaks, such as Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS), Zika virus (ZIKV) disease, and Nipah virus (NiV) disease in the last two decades. A detailed timeline of the outbreaks in India since 21st century is provided in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>. At the beginning of the previous decade (2003–2004), over 8,000 people were infected with Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus (SARS-CoV), and the death toll had increased to nearly 800 worldwide. At the end of the current decade (2020), the outbreak of the novel and lethal severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), causing symptoms similar to SARS, has become a pandemic and is threatening humankind. SARS did not spread much in India (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). As per the WHO-Epidemic and Pandemic Alert and Response (EPR) report, only three cases were reported as of July 31, 2003. These cases were reported from the Infectious Diseases Hospital, Kolkata, the Christian Medical College and Hospital (CMCH), Vellore, and Siddhartha Hospital in Pune. No other cases have been reported since then. Notably, reports have stated that 30% of medical doctors and staff from Infectious Diseases Hospital, Kolkata did not work due to fears over infection caused by a lack of sufficient protection (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). All immediate precautionary measures were taken to combat the SARS outbreak in India. Concerning the ZIKV outbreak of 2017, there have been no documented cases of ZIKV infection in India; however, antibodies to ZIKV have been detected in healthy people in India (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). This might have occured as a result of past exposure, although the possibility of cross-reaction with other flaviviruses cannot be denied. The most recent outbreak that India faced was that of NiV disease during mid-2018. As of July 17, 2018, a total of 19 NiV cases, including 17 deaths, had been reported in Kerala State (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Eighteen of the cases were laboratory-confirmed, and the deceased index case was suspected of having NiV but could not be tested. The outbreak was located in two Kerala districts, Kozhikode and Malappuram. As of July 30, 2018, no new confirmed cases or deaths were reported; NiV transmission from human to human was contained in Kerala.
</p>
