<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Within a relatively short time frame, the policy targets were incorporated into relevant donor and national strategies, policies and operational plans in both countries to varying degrees. Concerns have been raised previously about the slow pace of policy translation in many sub-Saharan African countries, whereas we demonstrate evidence of effective and diverse health networks in both settings that utilize modified framing strategies to encourage relatively fast transfer of these targets to their national setting (
 <xref rid="czx132-B34" ref-type="bibr">Tumwesigye 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2013
 </xref>). However, given the timeframe for 90–90–90 is very short (5 years), it could be argued that 2 years is too slow for updating national strategies and policy guidelines. Experience from the response to the Millennium Development Goals found efforts to mobilize domestic resources in order to meet the targets was insufficient across many countries (
 <xref rid="czx132-B16" ref-type="bibr">Ooms 
  <italic>et al.</italic> 2010
 </xref>). In this analysis we find evidence of concerted efforts to mobilise domestic revenue and to increase efficiency in the programme response. Estimates for resource needs for the response in both countries, however, indicate that despite these efforts, significant resource gaps remain (
 <xref rid="czx132-B7" ref-type="bibr">Ghana AIDS Commission 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="czx132-B35" ref-type="bibr">Uganda AIDS Commission 2016</xref>). In Ghana and Uganda, it is not apparent that MOH budgets for the HIV programme have changed as a consequence of the targets or that resources have been reallocated from other disease areas specifically to meet these targets. While more investigation is needed, this finding could alleviate concerns that targets displace funding from other parts of the health budget. Instead, we indicate that these targets have resulted in a renewed interest and focus on domestic resource mobilization mechanisms. The adoption of novel domestic resource mobilization strategies is likely influenced by a number of factors and not wholly attributable to the 90–90–90 targets, such as the Abuja Declaration, which both countries studied still fall short of. Whether other sub-Saharan African countries exhibit similar responses is yet to be seen.
</p>
