<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to having a higher detection rate, the VP1-CODEHOP test could be completed within 2–3 days, which is much shorter than the VI-IFA (7–14 days). Moreover, the VP1-CODEHOP test could further identify novel enterovirus genotypes based on phylogenetic analysis of partial VP1 gene sequences. As shown in this study, variant CVA2, CVA6, and EV71 viruses were identify using the VP1-CODEHOP test. Recently, variant CVA2 caused four complicated cases in Hong Kong in 2012 and two of them died [
 <xref rid="pone.0167532.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Interestingly, we also detected 5 variant CVA2 strains in northern Taiwan but these 5 cases only developed mild symptoms. Similar results were also observed in the National Enterovirus Surveillance Database managed by Taiwan CDC (Dr H-S Wu unpublished data). Further studies are desirable to elucidate the epidemiological differences between Taiwan and Hong Kong. In addition, variant CVA6 caused unique clinical presentation in Finland in 2008 and we also detected this variant CVA6 causing similar symptoms in Taiwan in 2010 [
 <xref rid="pone.0167532.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0167532.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. EV71 seems to evolve quicker in the past 15 years and different EV71 genotypes have caused large-scale epidemics in tropical and subtropical Asia since 1997. Moreover, antigenic variations among different genotypes were observed based on serum neutralization test using rabbit and human antisera [
 <xref rid="pone.0167532.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0167532.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Based on the VP1-CODEHOP test, we found that multiple EV71 genotypes co-circulated in 2008–2012 but EV71 sub-genotypes B5b and B5c caused large-scale epidemics in 2008 and 2012, respectively, which are consistent with other studies analyzing full VP1 sequences and complete genomes [
 <xref rid="pone.0167532.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0167532.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Although a degenerate primer set targeting conserved region of enteroviruses (5’-UTR) had been widely used on molecular diagnostic systems, the 5’-UTR-based molecular diagnosis cannot precisely identify serotypes of human enteroviruses [
 <xref rid="pone.0167532.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0167532.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].
</p>
