<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0250">In view of environmental protection, novel environmentally friendly decontamination methods are needed. We suggest that CP should replace current chemical decontamination practices because it does not produce excessive waste and can efficiently inactivate viruses in or on different media and surfaces. CP usage will likely spread in different directions to help in coping with upcoming global challenges such as the scarcity of clean water and the detrimental effects of future viral epidemics or pandemics such as COVID-19. CP in combination with other existing technologies could help to improve virus inactivation through synergistic effects, thus providing an ultimate decontamination tool.
 <boxed-text id="b0020">
  <label>Outstanding Questions</label>
  <p id="p0255">What CP source conditions will enable optimal efficiency of targeted virus inactivation in terms of the required treatment times and energy consumption?</p>
  <p id="p0260">Which types of RONS are the most relevant for inactivation of a given virus in a given matrix, how can we optimize production of such relevant RONS, and which methods should be used for their accurate determination?</p>
  <p id="p0265">Does UV radiation have a synergistic effect with RONS in virus inactivation?</p>
  <p id="p0270">What are the main viral components that are affected by different CP-mediated virus inactivation strategies, and which viral characterization methods should be used in each experiment to get a precise answer? Should a standardized protocol be developed for this purpose?</p>
  <p id="p0275">What is the scale-up potential of CP treatments?</p>
  <p id="p0280">Could CP cause cytotoxic or genotoxic damage when used for virus inactivation in specific matrices that will come in contact with human, plant, and animal tissues?</p>
  <p id="p0285">Would the combination of CP with already established methods, such as chlorine treatment, or new environmentally friendly methods such as cavitation, have a synergistic effect on virus inactivation? Would such synergy contribute to shorter treatment times, lower energy consumption, and decreased environmental burden?</p>
  <notes notes-type="alt-text" specific-use="for-accessibility" id="al0035">
   <p>Alt-text: Outstanding Questions</p>
  </notes>
 </boxed-text>
</p>
