<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0165">MAYV was originally isolated in Trinidad in 1954 from the serum of febrile patients. MAYV affects people who work or reside in contact with the natural environment. However, outbreaks have also been reported in large cities. The disease caused by MAYV takes 3–5 days and includes fever, headache, myalgia, rash, and arthralgia of large joints, and occasionally, arthritis; the convalescence of this disease could require several weeks. MAYV remains in the wild as a zoonosis of primates that are infected by the bite of 
 <italic>Haemagogus</italic> mosquitoes that live in the canopies. A study of 335 blood samples from indigenous communities in the Rio Negro region, Brazil, indicated that 41.5% had antibodies against MAYV, which shows that it is a common infection in this region. During 2007, cases of Mayaro fever have also been presented in large cities such as Manaus, the capital of the state of Amazonas. In that city, IgM antibodies against MAYV were detected by immunoassay in the serum of 33 patients, the MAYV genome was identified in one of these sera. The patients had fever, headache, arthralgia, eye pain, and rash. Evidence of the migration of MAYV to other parts of Brazil has also been reported. In 2000 three patients who had Mayaro fever and most likely acquired it in the city of Camapuã, located in the center-west of the country, traveled to the city of São Paulo, where they were diagnosed. Therefore MAYV is an emerging virus that affects humans, including individuals who live in the large cities of the Amazon region. This virus could spread to other regions of Brazil, as well as other tropical countries of America, as it is introduced by sick travelers or migratory birds. MAYV and CHIKV could also be transmitted by 
 <italic>A. aegypti.</italic> This background makes it possible to imagine a future scenario in which MAYV, after adapting to the urban cycle, could be the cause of major epidemics (
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Garcia and Moraes, 2014</xref>). 
</p>
