<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par9">Preliminary health advice when spreading epidemics is to observe hand hygiene and use PPE. Some of the reasons for not following the recommendations occur at the individual, group, and community levels. At the time of the epidemic, such issues are particularly well addressed among medical staff. Nevertheless, some hand disinfectants are not effective in eliminating the pathogen (Pittet 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2001</xref>). In other words, a disinfectant should be used that will affect the pathogen and the virus in question. At the same time as the COVID-19 pandemic, the effectiveness of hand sanitizers can prevent the virus from spreading, because the main way to prevent the transmission of pathogens is body contact. Lack of public access to such materials is also a significant issue at this time. The effectiveness of home disinfectants has been investigated by WHO (Seymour et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2020d</xref>). Its main ingredients are alcohol, glycerin, and hydrogen peroxide. After that, spray on the hands and drying is done automatically by exposing it to the air. Lack of hand disinfection and contact with parts of the body (ears, eyes, nose, and mouth) can cause COVID-19. In one study, alcohol-based hand rubs, or soap and water hand wash, were shown to be effective in preventing COVID-19. Sequentially, if the disinfectant dries, the above-mentioned items should be used again before contact with the patient or any use of the hand (Malhotra et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2020</xref>). Although there is evidence that hand hygiene can reduce respiratory illness, it has not yet been proven that it can reduce the transmission of SARS-CoV-2 (Yang 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2020</xref>). So far, no eye infections have been reported in patients with the SARS-CoV-2, but very few viruses have been seen in tears and conjunctival discharge. It can be seen that the eye may not be the main entrance of SARS-CoV-2 into the body and cause respiratory infections (Sun et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2020</xref>). However, eye infections can be caused by respiratory and nasopharyngeal infections. It can be very efficient, especially during close contact between the patient and the clinical staff. The use of masks and goggles, along with hand disinfection, has shown a significant reduction in person-to-person transmission (Yang 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2020</xref>). Also, since SARS-CoV-2 is not only transmitted through the air and can survive on the surface for a while, the importance of hand disinfection cannot be ignored (Otter et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2016</xref>). Besides, infected people can contaminate the surface they touch, which may include a large number of household items and appliances (WHO 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2020a</xref>). In this way, even infected people should disinfect their hands.
</p>
