<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The IDSA guidelines recommend that clinicians use rapid molecular assays, that is, nucleic acid amplification tests (NAAT), rather than RIDTs for the testing of outpatients in order to improve the detection of influenza virus infection [
 <xref rid="pone.0231217.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. According to the meta-analysis [
 <xref rid="pone.0231217.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], the pooled sensitivity and specificity of rapid molecular tests for influenza A were 87.4% (95%CI: 71.1–95.6) and 99.0% (95%CI: 93.2–99.5), respectively, in adults. The sensitivity and specificity of a rapid molecular test, ID NOW2 (Abott Diagnostics, USA), for influenza A were reported to be 95.9% (95%CI: 89.9–98.9) and of 100% (95%CI: 98.1–100), respectively [
 <xref rid="pone.0231217.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], which was reported from Japan, and most patients—mainly children—were tested within 48 hours after the onset of illness. In our study, in which patients were tested within 48 hours after the onset of ILI, the sensitivity of ImunoAce Flu in the detection of influenza A was as high as the sensitivity of rapid molecular tests [
 <xref rid="pone.0231217.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. However, the specificity of ImunoAce Flu within 48 hours after the onset of illness was 90.4% (
 <xref rid="pone.0231217.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), which was lower than the specificity of rapid molecular assays [
 <xref rid="pone.0231217.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] [
 <xref rid="pone.0231217.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Similarly, in a report from Japan [
 <xref rid="pone.0231217.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], sensitivity and specificity of an RIDT, QUICKNAVI (Otsuka Pharmaceutical Co, Japan) were comparable to the sensitivity and specificity of a rapid molecular assay, ID NOW2. Based on the Japanese experience, RIDTs are sufficiently sensitive and highly useful if patients are tested within 48 hours after the onset of illness. Thus, in countries where an early diagnosis and treatment are possible, an RIDT is probably one of the most useful alternatives for diagnosing influenza. For example, in Israel, &gt;50% of patients with ILI visited clinics at 0–1 days after the onset of ILI [
 <xref rid="pone.0231217.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].
</p>
