<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Group B Coxsackievirus (CVB) is a 
 <italic>Picornaviridae</italic> enterovirus, with which infection during pregnancy causes serious and sometimes fatal outcomes for the fetus [
 <xref rid="B53-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Infections with Coxsackievirus B3 (CVB3) during late pregnancy and delivery have been reported to have significant effects on the fetus, including neurological defects, encephalitis, myocarditis, meningitis, and even death [
 <xref rid="B55-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. According to Hwang et al., when cases of early pregnancy loss were analyzed for the prevalence of enterovirus infection using RT-PCR and immunohistochemistry, the rate of CVB3 infection in cases of abortion was 57.1% [
 <xref rid="B58-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Despite the high rate of fetal death associated with CVB infections, there are limited data regarding the outcome of infection during early pregnancy, since early maternal infections are commonly asymptomatic and therefore undetected. Coxsackievirus and adenovirus receptor (CAR) expression at the host cell surface is essential for viral entry and internalization of CVB3, and the receptor is not only highly expressed in the fetal brain, but also a crucial factor in embryonic development of the heart [
 <xref rid="B59-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Hwang et al. investigated the outcomes of early CVB3 infection during pregnancy in ICR mice, demonstrating the vertical transmission of CVB3 enabled by the high expression level of CAR in the uterus and embryo of the pregnant mice [
 <xref rid="B61-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. CVB3 replication, as analyzed by RT-PCR and plaque assays, was confirmed in the embryos and placentas of the CVB3-infected mice, whose embryos were particularly fragile in the brains and hearts [
 <xref rid="B61-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Furthermore, Euscher et al. showed localization of CVB RNA and protein in HCs, STBs, and CTBs of human placental tissue harvested from newborn infants [
 <xref rid="B62-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>].
</p>
