<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to ZIKV, Ebola virus has also caused recent outbreaks that caused a public health emergency. Ebola virus infection during pregnancy threatens the fetus: in nearly all cases, Ebola infection in pregnant women has resulted in miscarriage, stillbirth, or neonatal death [
 <xref rid="B75-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Given that Ebola virus research has to be done in a biosafety laboratory level 4 facility, the pathophysiology or maternal fetal transmission mechanisms are yet to be identified. Meanwhile, studies involving immune correlates of protection or transmission at the placenta for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) have been somewhat established. It is known that HCs are key mediators of HIV transmission, limit HIV-1 replication, and potentially offset mother to child transmission by induction of immunoregulatory cytokines [
 <xref rid="B76-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. Furthermore, many host restriction factors expressed by HCs or trophoblasts have been identified, including APOBEC3G and ISGs [
 <xref rid="B77-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,
 <xref rid="B78-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Despite this, the detailed mechanisms underlying HIV’s strategies to evade the protective role of placenta are poorly understood. In to the same Filoviridae family, Marburg virus can also infect the placenta and result in similar complications for the fetus as Ebola virus [
 <xref rid="B79-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Lassa virus is a member of the 
 <italic>Arenaviridae</italic> family, and an infection with Lassa virus manifests as similar symptoms to an infection with Ebola virus, due to the similar cellular targets that are shared between the two viruses [
 <xref rid="B80-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Lassa fever is a hemorrhagic disease caused by Lassa virus, and the increasing occurrence of this disease has highlighted Lassa virus as an important pathogen that can lead to 90% perinatal mortality when infection occurs during pregnancy [
 <xref rid="B81-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>].
</p>
