<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par90">The PB1-F2 protein is expressed from the PB1 gene of most IAVs, which is localized in mitochondria. It commits apoptosis by interacting with two mitochondrial proteins in host cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. The Ser residue, but not the Asn residue, at position 66 of PB1-F2 is critical for the high pathogenicity of an H5N1 in mice [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. The 1918 pandemic IVs carried the mutation of the Asn residue at position 66 to Ser in the PB1-F2 protein. The replacement of Ser with Asn attenuated the strong infectivity of the 1918 IVs, which pinpointed the PB1-F2 protein as a critical determinant of viral pathogenicity. PB1-F2 interacts with PB1 and affects the shuttling of this protein between the nuclei and cytoplasm [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], this shuttling ability might be affecting virulence. Thus, the shuttling ability seems to be critical in this context. IAVs attach to host cells via the binding of the hemagglutinin (HA) protein to the sialosaccharides of glycoproteins on the cell surface. The binding specificities of HAs in IVs derived from different host species are different. For example, HAs of human IAVs recognize sialic acid (SA)-α-2,6-Gal-terminated saccharides (α-2,6-SA) mainly, whereas HAs of avian IVs preferentially select to bind SA-α-2,3-Gal-terminated saccharides (α-2,3-SA). The horizontal avian-to-human transmission of IVs was abolished by mutations of two amino acids in HA that produced a switch in preferential binding from avian α-2,3-SA to human α-2,6-SA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. The pattern of virus attachment of the two subtypes of human IAVs (H3N2 and H1N1) and low pathogenic avian IVs (H5N9 and H6N1) was compared with the pattern of viral attachment of avian H5N1, which is highly pandemic [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Thus, the recognition pattern of IAVs to HAs might be critical for determining the degree of pathogenicity. However, the sugar-mediated binding specificity of IAVs to HAs varies according to specific viruses, which might hamper the development of new anti-IAV drugs.
</p>
