<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">Potential contamination was excluded by comparing all sequence segments with all of the known sequences in the HIV database by BLAST search (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hiv-web.lanl.gov/content/index" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://hiv-web.lanl.gov/content/index</ext-link>). All of the sequenced fragments were amended, and 
 <italic>gag</italic> and 
 <italic>pol</italic> genes from the same patient were assembled based on the overlapping sequences. In the current study, bidirectional sequencing was performed, and the background noise was very clear/minimal. When a secondary peak of &lt; 30% was observed, this peak was excluded. Once the secondary peak was &gt; 30%, we considered this position as an ambiguous base. Finally, the consensus sequences from one patient were obtained. We were very cautious on the identification of URFs. No breakpoints within URFs were identified at the joint sites of the 
 <italic>gag</italic> and 
 <italic>pol</italic> genes. Finally, the consensus sequence per patient was obtained. HIV sequence quality was determined using an online Quality-Control software (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.hiv.lanl.gov/content/sequence/QC/index.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.hiv.lanl.gov/content/sequence/QC/index.html</ext-link>). HIV genotype was determined by submitting genes to the NCBI viral genotyping tool (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nih.gov/projects/genotyping/formpage.cgi" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ncbi.nih.gov/projects/genotyping/formpage.cgi</ext-link>). HIV genotypes were determined by combining the results of the two regions and further confirmed by phylogenetic analysis. For phylogenetic analysis, all our assembled 
 <italic>gag</italic> and 
 <italic>pol</italic> sequences were aligned to the reference sequences separately using MSCLE software.. The final alignment was checked visually and edited manually using the BioEdit software package (version 7.0.0; T. Hall, North Carolina State University, Raleigh, NC, USA). Evolutionary distances were computed using the Kimura 2 parameter method, including both transitions and transversions. Phylogenetic trees were generated using the neighbor-joining method with MEGA6.06 software package and maximum likelihood methods with PhyML3.0 software package. Detailed information on the references used in the current work is provided in Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1. The reliability of topologies was estimated by performing bootstrap analysis with 1000 replicates. Possible intertype recombination events were further proven using the online Recombination Identification Program (RIP; version 3.0; 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hiv-web.lanl.gov" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://hiv-web.lanl.gov</ext-link>) and confirmed by jpHMM online software (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jphmm.gobics.de/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://jphmm.gobics.de/</ext-link>). The gene sequences were deposited to GenBank as accession numbers MH635658 - MH636002, MH632305 - MH632713.
</p>
