<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0140">In research carried out by Wang et al. in 2004, has shown that RNA interference (RNAi) activators are effective against SARS-CoV on Vero cells by inhibiting the replication of SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="bib125" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. In the study, the effect of six different vector-based siRNAs was analyzed for the inhibition of replication of SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="bib125" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. It was found that only two of them efficiently blocked the viral replication in Vero cells by targeting the RNA polymerase, thus suggesting that anti-SARS agents could have developed by using the siRNA [
 <xref rid="bib125" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. In another study, several potential inhibitors that target particular steps of the life cycle of the coronavirus were tested in order to investigate the therapeutic options [
 <xref rid="bib126" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. The specific steps of the life cycle of the coronavirus that was target by these potential inhibitors were membrane fusion, binding to the receptor, translation, post-translation processing, transcription, and release of the virus [
 <xref rid="bib127" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>]. HCoV-NL63 S glycoprotein, a viral entry protein, was found to be the target site of designed siRNA. In virus-infected cells, these designed siRNAs significantly inhibited the infection [
 <xref rid="bib128" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. In another study, the synthesis of chimeric RNA-DNA hammerhead ribozyme targeting SARS-CoV was done. In order to ensure its activity, in vitro cleavage reactions were performed using the synthesized ribozyme. The results suggested that ribozymes (Rz) were found to be useful in inhibiting viral replication up to 60% by using chimeric DNA-RNA hammerhead ribozyme. 3T3 cells (fibroblast cell line) transfected with a recombinant plasmid when targeted using chimeric construct significantly reduced the expression of SARS-CoV RNA. Thus found to be a potent and feasible treatment option for SARS [
 <xref rid="bib129" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>].
</p>
