<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Table 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Key barriers and proposed solutions relating to EIDs</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="bottom" style="background-color:#D9D9D9;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Key barriers</td>
    <td align="left" valign="bottom" style="background-color:#D9D9D9;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposed solutions</td>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rapid loss of interest after a crisis is resolved</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Health security to be given standing priority.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Ensure that the lessons learnt from EID crises/scares are reviewed and appropriate actions implemented; create national expert body to facilitate this.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Continuous education of politicians and the general public.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Politicians hearing many different voices</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Scientists to consolidate messaging (national expert body).</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Package scientific findings into effective messages.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Communication of uncertainty</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Work with politicians and the public to view EID preparation and scenario planning as an insurance policy.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Refine scenario planning and improve preparedness at all levels (public health officials, researchers, professional groups and policymakers).</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Work with the public and the media to optimise communication.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delay in getting research proposals approved during an outbreak</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Consider important research questions (national expert body).</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Prepare generic research proposals in advance.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Fast-track ethics approval processes during epidemic outbreaks.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weak EID surveillance and response systems within the Asia Pacific region</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Comprehensive assessment of regional IHR-2005 implementation.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Improved laboratory/diagnostic capacity and reporting structures.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Increased domestic funding, as well as international aid, with a specific focus on regional health security.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Expand IHR-2005 to include focus on livestock and wildlife disease surveillance or integrate with complimentary processes such as the OIE’s Evaluation of Performance of Veterinary Services.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Remunerate farmers for losses incurred as a result of disease detection to secure their cooperation in surveillance efforts.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Separation of animal and human disease data, research and policy</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Identify overlapping issues in human and animal health; understand and respect each other’s perspectives.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Funding agencies to encourage and support joint research opportunities that links human, animal and environmental health.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Create national oversight body containing human, animal and environmental health experts.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Separate government structures for human and animal public health</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Encourage cross-discipline collaboration at Commonwealth and State levels; regular meetings between human and animal public health officials (including wildlife).</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Increase cross-ministerial interaction at Cabinet and senior government official level.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Restrictive discipline focus in academic institutions</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Broaden undergraduate exposure to the ‘natural sciences’.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Encourage multidisciplinary perspectives and complex systems awareness at under and post-graduate levels, for example, joint One/Eco/Planetary Health training between medical and veterinary schools; Master degrees in One/Eco/Planetary Health, Health Security or Complex Systems.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn id="T2_FN1">
   <p>EID, Emerging Infectious Disease; IHR, International Health Regulations; OIE, World Organisation of Animal Health.</p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
