<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Table 3</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Responses to open-ended questions on antimicrobial resistance (AMR)</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="bottom" style="background-color:#D9D9D9;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Question</td>
    <td align="left" valign="bottom" style="background-color:#D9D9D9;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Responses</td>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>Nightmare scenario</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Global spread and dominance of totally antimicrobial resistant pathogens—returning to the preantibiotic era</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>Priorities for future research/policy</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Environmental impact of antimicrobial use in humans, animals and crops</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Emerging bacterial resistance to biocides and disinfectants.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>AMR transmission from and to companion animals.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Balancing food production capacity with AMR concerns.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Need for comprehensive AMR surveillance; understanding the selection, expansion and spread of multidrug-resistant mobile genetic elements (mapping the mobile gene pool).</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Antibiotic stewardship—understanding why doctors prescribe and patients demand, antimicrobials inappropriately.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Better infection control within health and aged care facilities.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Point-of-care diagnostics (including rapid species identification and drug susceptibility testing).</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Use of highly selective bacteriophage therapy.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Adaptive clinical trial designs for rapid assessment of multidrug regimens</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Alternative drug development funding models that considers the public good.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Non-antimicrobial approaches to controlling infections.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>Most important research question</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Are there effective treatment strategies that will reduce selective pressure and on-going evolutionary ‘escape’, such as increasing bacterial susceptibility to immune attack or reducing the risk/impact of invasive bacterial infection only?</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>What are the key characteristics of a healthy microbiome and the short and long term impacts of antimicrobial induced changes?</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <bold>Issues that require public consultation</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Restricting antimicrobial access to reduce inappropriate use, for example stronger regulation or increases in price</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>How best to educate the general public and prescribers about the dangers (personal and environmental) of inappropriate antimicrobial use.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Balancing animal and human welfare considerations.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Balancing distributive justice and community versus individual cost–benefit.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn id="T3_FN1">
   <p>AMR, antimicrobial resistance.</p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
