<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="T4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Table 4</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Key barriers and proposed solutions relating to AMR and antimicrobial use</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="bottom" style="background-color:#D9D9D9;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Key barriers</td>
    <td align="left" valign="bottom" style="background-color:#D9D9D9;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proposed solutions</td>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potentially divisive arguments of human versus animal use</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Develop joint National AMR Strategy with input from all sectors.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Restrict use of antimicrobials in agriculture to those with limited cross-over resistance.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Companion animals to have the same access as humans.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Companion animals are excluded from agriculture and health portfolios</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Provide a ‘home’ for companion animal health within the Commonwealth government structures.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Provide AMR prescribing guidelines for companion animals, including antimicrobial stewardship programmes and improved infection control.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Problem of attribution</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Elucidate sources of AMR organisms including in humans (hospital vs community), animals (companion vs livestock vs wildlife) and environment (eg, water or soil).</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Provide research funding for negative impacts on ecosystems and animal health, irrespective of human health.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limited funding for multidisciplinary research</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Provide funding avenues for multidisciplinary research, especially those combining human, animal and environmental health.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Consider dedicated funding provision from the new MRFF.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Global/regional rather than a national problem</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Focus on AMR (including growing drug resistance in tuberculosis and malaria) as part of the DFAT regional Health Security agenda.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Strengthened international/regional AMR legislation, improved governance and stewardship should be key international development outcomes.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>WHO to develop better global AMR accountability measures.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spread of mobile resistance elements</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Understand and monitor the mobile genetic pool, including spread by wild animals and bird populations.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Support regional/global strategies.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimicrobials are cheap and easily available</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Restrict prescribing of certain antimicrobials.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Consider deferred prescribing if uncertain diagnosis and not acutely ill.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Consider ways to make antimicrobials more expensive,* without restricting access for people who need them.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unnecessary supply and perceived public demand</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Educate children and the public about responsible antimicrobial use.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Institute effective antimicrobial stewardship programmes.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Make institutional antimicrobial use and drug resistance profiles public.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inadequate infection control leading to transmission of AMR organisms</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Improved sanitation and environmental hygiene.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Better infection control practice in hospitals and other healthcare settings.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Better infection control awareness in the general community and targeted measures in congregate settings.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor communication and collaboration between states</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Standard approach taken across states and territories.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Standardise susceptibility testing, surveillance, governance and antimicrobial stewardship procedures.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Consider routine reporting of drug-resistant infections as good clinical practice (laboratory accreditation requirement).</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antimicrobial development deliver poor return on investment</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <list list-type="bullet">
      <list-item>
       <p>Recognise the failure of standard market mechanisms</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Advocate for the development of alternative funding models, including consideration of public–private partnerships or a health insurance model.</p>
      </list-item>
      <list-item>
       <p>Develop less expensive adaptive trial strategies.</p>
      </list-item>
     </list>
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn id="T4_FN1">
   <p>*There was concern that an imposed AMR tax may limit or distort appropriate use in people who really need antibiotics.</p>
  </fn>
  <fn id="T4_FN2">
   <p>AMR, antimicrobial resistance; DFAT, Australian Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade; MRFF, Medical Research Futures fund.</p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
