<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0110">We constructed a comprehensive and robust CSI, a human-viral interactome that displayed scale-free properties (
 <italic>r</italic>
 <sup>2</sup> = 0.92; 
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>D). We also showed that the SARS-CoV-2-interacting proteins (SIPs) exhibit increased average centrality indices compared with the remaining proteins in the network (
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>, and 
 <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S1</xref>A and S1B). Numerous human-viral interactomes have previously been generated to uncover global principles of viral entry, infection, and disease progression. These include human T cell lymphotropic viruses, Epstein-Barr virus, hepatitis C virus, influenza virus, human papillomavirus, dengue virus, Ebola virus, HIV-1, and SARS-CoV (
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Ackerman et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Becerra et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Bosl et al., 2019</xref>), and all of these interactomes exhibited a power-law distribution. Another significant tenet of interactomes is the existence of modular units or modules, defined as sets of densely connected clusters within a network that exhibit heightened connectivity among nodes within a module. Such nodes within a module have previously been deemed to possess similar biological functions or belong to the same functional pathways (
 <xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr">Vlaic et al., 2018</xref>). Since nodes in CSI form protein complexes to coronavirus infection, we extracted several functional modules from our network (
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>E–L). Nuclear transport machinery is an attractive target of a wide spectrum of viruses to facilitate the transport of viral RNAs by interfering with host nucleocytoplasmic trafficking and thereby averting the host immune responses (
 <xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr">Yarbrough et al., 2014</xref>). In our viral infection/mRNA transport module, SARS-CoV-2 was shown to target two nucleoporins, NUP98 and NUP214 (
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>H). A question still to be addressed is how SARS-CoV-2 mechanistically targets these nucleoporins to enhance its virulence. Recently, the global posttranslational modification landscape in response to SARS-CoV-2 infection indicated an increase in the phosphorylation of NUP98, a significant CSP in our study (
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Bouhaddou et al., 2020</xref>) (
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>E). Given that ORF6 of both SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 interact with NUP98 and SARS-CoV blocks the transport of STAT1 to the nucleus (
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Frieman et al., 2007</xref>), it is highly likely that SARS-CoV-2-mediated NUP98 posttranslational modification would lead to the inhibition of host mRNAs export including STAT1 translocation through the nuclear pore. Another significant CSP in this pathway is UBE2I (
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>E), ubiquitin-conjugating enzyme E2I that constitutes the core component in the cell's sumoylation pathway. Because the sumoylation of the nucleoporins is necessary for their functions (
 <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">Texari and Stutz, 2015</xref>), we hypothesized that interferences in the host nucleocytoplasmic trafficking of mRNAs/proteins are partially dependent on the SARS-CoV-2 interaction with UBE2I.
</p>
