<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous studies evaluated the vector competence of 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> vectors for ZIKV belonging to both lineages. Mosquitoes from Africa [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006637.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], Asia [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006637.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006637.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] and America [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006637.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006637.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] were infected by ZIKV strains belonging to the African lineage and showed various results. The vector competence for ZIKV belonging to the Asian lineage was also evaluated with vectors from America [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006637.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006637.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] Australia [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006637.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] and Europe [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006637.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. However, the ability of the vectors from the Pacific to transmit ZIKV has been poorly studied. 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>hensilli</italic> from Yap island, appeared to be able to disseminate African ZIKV strain but the transmission has not been evaluated. However this mosquito was the most collected species in Yap island, Federated States of Micronesia, during the ZIKV outbreak in 2007 (41%) supporting its possible role as a vector during the outbreak [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006637.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Laboratory strains of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>polynesiensis</italic> from French Polynesia were shown to be able to get infected and disseminate an Asian/Pacific ZIKV strain isolated in French Polynesia in 2013. Furthermore, infectious ZIKV particles have been found in saliva of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> from French Polynesia as soon as 6 days post-infection [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006637.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].
</p>
