<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are several limitations in the study. Many studies include influenza as a single variable across all years, but in this study we included a separate influenza variable for each year, to avoid the problem of increased testing over time. This markedly reduces the statistical power to detect an association between the influenza and hospitalisation time series. A further challenge of this approach is that the influenza A and B time series in a year may be strongly correlated (collinear) thus reducing the ability of the model to resolve each type’s relative contribution to hospitalisations. Therefore, some type-specific results may not be accurate. There are limitations of notifications data in Australia. NNDSS received only laboratory-confirmed cases reported across the country, but laboratories do not report on number of patients tested so proportion positive cannot be obtained. This would avoid the problem of increased testing over time if a proportion was available. Testing and reporting of influenza infection is conducted at the discretion of the medical practitioners or according to local health facility policy. Evidence suggests an increase in testing or reporting after the 2009 pandemic [
 <xref rid="pone.0230705.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] and notification counts have increased year by year. The reason for increased testing is unknown, but may be due to increased awareness of infection by GPs and the public as well as availability of improved diagnostic tools in recent years. Variation in testing practices across the studied years might have influenced our results through varying population biases. However, use of annual variables for influenza may have limited this effect. Another limitation in the study was presence of some negative estimates from the influenza A and B model, which are difficult to interpret. Nevertheless, we included all estimates in the calculation of averages to avoid positive bias in our results. In the majority of years studied, influenza A predominated, which may have led to poor model fit for influenza B. From the sensitivity analysis comparing the use of a proportional allocation of total influenza based on the proportion of influenza detections in year, the difficulty in resolving influenza B’s contribution to hospitalisations was more of a problem in 2008. Influenza B predominated in 2008, but the type-specific model attributed all influenza-attributable hospitalisations to type B. While the proportional approach may be attractive, it may lead to inaccurate conclusions because it does not take account of varying virulence of the virus circulating in a year, or varying susceptibility of the population.
</p>
