<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Infection control is one of the essential components of management of patients with TB with or without HIV coinfection. It restricts the transmission of infection from patients to high-risk groups, especially health-care workers. There is an increased risk of transmission of infection, even for PLHIV harboring DR strains, although evidence is sparse. Such factors as delayed diagnosis of M/XDR-TB causing prolonged duration of infectiousness leading to increased exposure, overcrowding of wards, and merging of patients with TB and HIV are responsible for nosocomial transmission. These practices enhance infection epidemics or outbreaks, particularly in HIV-endemic settings. Implementation of adequate infection-control measures at health centers or hospitals significantly reduces nosocomial transmission.
 <xref rid="CIT0106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref> Interventions for infection control should be adopted at three levels: administrative, environmental/engineering, and personal respiratory protection. Administrative controls include patient screening, cough hygiene, segregation and fast-tracking of symptomatics, and education of patients and their relatives. Environmental controls include indoor patient segregation, adequate bed spacing, and ensuring effective ventilation, either natural or mechanical, including negative-pressure rooms, with a focus on high-risk areas. Ultraviolet germicidal irradiation devices could be an alternative option for ventilation, which are effective but complex and costly. Personal respiratory protection including N95 particulate respirators, is indicated when the risk to health-care workers is especially high. The feasibility of these interventions is yet to be determined by robust randomized controlled trials, so the existing recommendations are based on consensus. Community-based treatment programs should implement these measures on a larger scale. Home-based measures, such as separate living quarters, personal respiratory protection for visitors, and adequate ventilation, have also been devised.
 <xref rid="CIT0107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>
</p>
