<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">A especial attention was given to the ability of the described sensors to segregate DENV-infected patients from ZKV-infected ones. As demonstrated in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>, the GNR-DENV sensors were efficiently able to distinguish DENV-positive sera from ZIKV-positive samples. As mentioned before, ZIKV is a clinically relevant flavivirus that has been associated with important neurological malformations and stillbirths in women infected during pregnancy
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>. Nonetheless, the vast majority of infections in healthy adults result either on the absence of disease or in a clinical syndrome that is practically indistinguishable from dengue fever
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup>. In addition, the serological differentiation between ZIKV and DENV infections is complicated by extensive cross-reactivity between these two viral agents because of their genetic proximity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, traditional diagnostic methods based in antibody detection are severely compromised when it comes to distinguish patients that were infected with one virus or the other
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>
 </sup> and, as a result, the PRNT remains as the gold standard for ZIKV diagnosis. Nonetheless, adding to the fact that the method is labor-intensive and not universally available, it has been suggested that even PRNTs may culminate in dubious results when applied to the sera of patients that have been infected with other flavivirus prior to ZIKV exposition, which is a common reality in the geographical areas where ZIKV circulates
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>. Molecular tests that detect the presence of ZIKV RNA are a viable and highly specific alternative; however, viremia is notably short during this virus’ infection
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>
 </sup>, leaving serology as a needed ZIKV diagnostic tool, despite its limitations. The development of sensors that could improve serological specificity and differentiate DENV from ZIKV has been described, including a microsphere immunoassay employing Luminex technology
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup> and electrochemical impedance spectroscopy coupled to square wave voltammetry
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>
 </sup>. However, the production of a nanosensor that is not dependent on specific and not thoroughly available reading equipment, as the one presented here, could be a real breakthrough for medical personal and public health authorities dealing with the problem in areas with limited access to highly specific technologies.
</p>
