<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">Although DENV and ZIKV are not in the same serocomplex within the 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic> family, they share approximately 53–57% amino acid sequence identity in their E proteins, to which most abundant and neutralizing antibodies are elicited during infection
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>
 </sup>. The four DENV serotypes, on the other hand, share 63–78% amino acid identity in their E proteins
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>
 </sup>, enough to confer short-lived cross protection in secondary infections caused by a different DENV serotype. Due to this intense antigenic resemblance, the serologic differentiation of DENV serotypes during infections is considered impracticable. Nevertheless, when we tested highly diluted sera samples from DENV-seropositive individuals, each sensor was able to specifically recognize the correspondent anti-sera with accuracy (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). Importantly, the human sera used to validate this aspect of the sensor were characterized by immunochromatography, ELISA and PRNT, adding the necessary confidence to the obtained results
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>. Although some samples were apparently identified by the non-correlated sensor on panels GNR-DENV1E, GNR-DENV2E and GNR-DENV3E (single dots on rows DENV2, DENV3 and DENV1, respectively), we considered these as outliers. Indeed, despite the outliers, the mean values (larger horizontal lines in each row) for the non-correlated samples on panels GNR-DENV2E and GNR-DENV3E remained within the shaded cutoff area. Moreover, it is not possible to rule out that these specific outlier patients have been previously exposed to a different DENV serotype, and in that case the sensors could have picked up this serological signal. To our knowledge, this is the first description of a serological method capable to identify efficiently which DENV serotype was responsible for the latest (primary or secondary) infection based solely on the serum sample of a given patient.
</p>
