<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">There is no doubt that nanotechnology has the disruptive power to affect our way of life in many ways, being incorporated from the concrete in the walls of our houses, in the micro-circuits of the TV remote, to the quality assessment of the food we eat. When it comes to biotechnology, the possibility of using nanomaterials to different ends is practically unlimited. Biosensors are amongst the most promising of all nanomaterial applications, bringing cheaper, more sensitive and more reliable detection platforms for an enormous number of completely different bioanalytes, from environmental samples to metabolic specimens and disease-related biomarkers
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>
 </sup>. Despite their many advantages over more traditional screening, sensing and diagnostic methods, the use of nanosensors are still not as widespread as it could be. In a quite provocative article, Vikesland
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>
 </sup> suggest that although nanosensors present inherent capabilities of being highly sensitive, highly flexible, and have multiplex-prone functionalities, they are still not as consumer/operator-friendly as they should be in order to become more accessible. Many nanosensors depend on the use of uncommon electronic/optical devices to perform and cannot operate by using equipments that are immediately available in most diagnostic laboratories. Moreover, many such nanosensors may require specifically trained personnel either to operate the reading devices or to interpret the readouts
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>
 </sup>. Although the sensitivity and specificity of many published nanosensors are spectacular, those mentioned constraints might represent significant barriers to the sensors’ use, especially in developing and under-developed countries where they are frequently so desperately needed. Localized surface plasmon resonance-based nanosensors, on the other hand, are frequently based on optical readouts that can be obtained by simple UV–Vis spectrometry
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>
 </sup>. Refractive index changes induced by the binding of a molecule to the surface of functionalized metal nanoparticles result in spectral shifts that can be detected by a common spectrophotometer with UV–Vis capabilities, which are specifications frequently present in most ELISA plate readers. Because ELISA is a widespread diagnostic tool, this basic equipment is available in most diagnostic laboratories, even the humblest ones. Taking advantage of this potential for immediate applicability independently of the acquisition of specific reading devices, we developed a LSPR-based gold nanosensor for the differential immune diagnostic of DENV infections.
</p>
