<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In patients with pulmonary manifestations, bronchioloalveolar lavage at bronchoscopy may show a lymphocyte-rich effusion. Such effusions may also be seen in autoimmune diseases and viral pneumonias. Desquamated balls of reactive type II pneumocytes may be abundant with large nuclei with increased nuclear to cytoplasmic ratios, prominent clumped chromatin and large round to irregular nucleoli, and eosinophilic inclusions (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">16.1</xref>). The lungs may show classic changes of diffuse alveolar damage with hyaline membranes, reactive type II pneumocytes, and lymphocytic infiltrates (Beske et al 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2007</xref>). In acute presentations, the lungs may show intra-alveolar hemorrhage due to weakened and damaged intraseptal capillaries. Viral inclusions are extremely difficult to find except in rare patients who are immunocompromised. Immunohistochemistry is however helpful highlighting infected cells (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">16.2</xref>). The diagnosis is based on serological rise of PV IgM and DNA evidence of PV from lung biopsy or cytologic specimens (Berjaoui et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2006</xref>). The exact pathogenesis of severe pulmonary complications by B19 is not understood but may be related to a cytotoxic effect of the virus directly or indirectly on the interstitial endothelial cells. An aberrant host immune response triggered by B19 may also contribute to the pulmonary pathology (Magro et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2006</xref>). The lung tissues are not the preferred site for virus replication in humans or other mammals. This is why PV B19 pneumonia is very rare or unrecognized. B19 DNA may persist perpetually in human tissues such as skin, synovial cells, and hepatocytes. The significance of a positive PCR for PV B19 may be related to the amount observed. Since it may be harbored in healthy tissues, PCR detection of PV B19 during an illness may not be definitive proof that PV is the cause of the lung injury unless other causes are excluded. In immunocompromised patients with PV B19 pneumonia, it is difficult to determine if it is a new infection associated with viremia or a reactivation of virus dormant within the lung tissues. In fact, simultaneous infection with two pathogens often results in enhanced morbidity and mortality, in particular in immunocompromised patients (Broliden 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2001</xref>). 
</p>
