<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The nucleic acid written in the first and third place in each of the four schemes is the one found in the parental and progeny viral particles. The nucleic acid in the middle position indicates the type of nucleic acid that acts as replicative intermediate (not the transcripts involved in gene expression that participate in the infectious cycle). The presence or not of RNA in the scheme determines the potential of genetic variation of the virus. RNA viruses and DNA viruses that have RNA as replicative intermediate (that is, viruses that follow replicative schemes 2, 3 and 4) display elevated mutation rates that have been estimated in 10
 <sup>−3</sup> to 10
 <sup>−5</sup> misincorporations per nucleotide copied [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>]. The molecular basis for high mutation rates is the absence of a proofreading-repair activity in the viral RNA-dependent RNA polymerases (RdRp) and RNA-dependent DNA polymerases (RdDp) (also termed reverse transcriptases (RT)), evidenced by functional and structural studies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R79">79</xref>]. There appear to be some exceptions to this rule, as suggested by the capacity of the influenza virus polymerase to remove excess GMP residues added to a capped oligonucleotide primer [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>], a 3′-end repair mechanism described in a satellite RNA of a plant virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref>], and a 3′-5′ exonuclease activity encoded by some coronaviruses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref>]. However, it has not been established whether the decrease in mutation rate promoted by such mechanisms has a major consequence for the biology of the corresponding viruses. In addition to the general absence of proofreading-repair activities in RdRps and RdDps, the cellular post-replicative-repair pathways that act to correct mismatches in double-stranded DNA are not effective in repairing either double-stranded RNA or RNA-DNA hydrids [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>]. Lack of proofreading-repair and post-replicative repair activities contributes decisively to high mutation rates of riboviruses, retroviruses and hepadnaviruses, a feature that has a profound influence in their biology [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>].
</p>
