<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0060">Among the many antigens [
 <xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>] found in blood, Carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA) can be used as oncological biomarkers which is one the most widely used tumor marker in the clinical diagnosis of colorectal, gastric, pancreatic and cervical carcinomas [
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. CEA levels directly correspond to the stage of the tumor, the outcome of therapy and the prognosis. In 2016, Wang et al developed a highly sensitive label-free paper-based electrochemical immunosensor employing a screen-printed working electrode (SPWE) which was modified with graphene nanocomposite for detection of CEA [
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. It demonstrated high efficiency and high sensitivity to the samples it was tested against. Hence, it could provide a low-cost, sensitive Point-Of-Care diagnosis. However, in 2017, Fan et al demonstrated the detection of Neuron-specific Enolase (NSE), a tumor marker essential for monitoring effect and judging prognosis and diagnosis of small cell lung cancer using a wireless POCT (Point-Of-Care-and-Testing) device comprising of a μPAD-based measuring system [
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The detection results of NSE were comparable to those measured by a commercial electrochemical workstation. The data generated were hence, transmitted over to the smartphone using Bluetooth and displayed in real-time. Again in 2018, Draz et al. developed a hybrid Paper-Plastic Microchip (PPMC) for flexible and High-Performance Point-Of-Care (POC) Diagnostic device, which was tested for the detection of alpha-fetoprotein (AFP) and CEA as biomarkers of hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) and colorectal cancer (CRC), respectively [
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The microchip comprised of three-layer hybrid substrates made of cellulose paper substrate assembled with a transparent plastic sheet using double-sided adhesive. The fabrication process of the microchip took &lt;1h and leveraged the advantages of layer-by-layer assembly. The PPMC had electrodes printed within the cellulose paper, which had better signal resolution compared to the common protocol of screen-printing electrodes on the surface of the chip. The results showed a good correlation between the expected and measured values with a maximum error of &lt;7% (see 
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> ).
</p>
