<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0035">To stop world circulation of SARS-CoV-2, we have only basic protective measures recommended by the World Health Organization (WHO) [
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], as in the case of SARS-CoV. The phase “Using barrier precautions, the transmission of SARS-CoV can be prevented” was written in 2004 [
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], and moreover, experts warned that sooner or later a new outbreak might occur [
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. This event occurred in 2019, but no one expected that it would cover the entire world, i.e., growing to pandemic size, and the pharmaceutical industry was taken by surprise. To date (June 04, 2020), more than 11million worldwide cases of infection and 525.491 deaths have been attributed to the novel coronavirus, SARS-CoV-2, since its emergence in December 2019. To cure hundreds of thousands of infected people, it is necessary to develop effective specific and selective antiviral drugs. The truth is that to date, there are no safe and specific antiviral agents against SARS-CoV-2, and the current methods for treatment of COVID-19 are still controversial. Fortunately, after analyzing the complete genome of SARS-CoV-2 from Wuhan, China [
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], important structural and biochemical details are now available on this coronavirus and its clinical features:
 <list list-type="simple" id="olist0010">
  <list-item id="o0010">
   <label>1.</label>
   <p id="p0040">The viral genome consists of more than 29,000 bases and encodes nonstructural 29 proteins, including RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp), coronavirus main protease (3CLpro), and papain-like protease (PLpro) [
    <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, 
    <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, 
    <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>];
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0015">
   <label>2.</label>
   <p id="p0045">The SARS-CoV-2 virus, similar to its cousin SARS-CoV, uses a glycosylated spike protein S1 that binds the virion to a receptor protein known as angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) located on the surface membrane of the host [
    <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, 
    <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, 
    <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, 
    <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>], whereas the MERS-CoV binds to the human dipeptidyl peptidase 4 (DPP4) receptor through its spike glycoprotein [
    <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Viral spike glycoproteins (SARS-CoV-2 virus) can also bind to the serine protease TMPRSS2, another host cell surface receptor that uses the SARS-CoV virus [
    <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>];
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0020">
   <label>3.</label>
   <p id="p0050">Although both SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV are close relatives (79.5–82% identity) and are highly comparable at the amino acid level, they are not identical, especially with respect to the spike proteins that might be the reason for the higher binding affinity of the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein to the human ACE2 receptor, which is abundantly present in the lungs. This feature apparently gives the virus its high ability to cause pneumonia [
    <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
    <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>];
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="o0025">
   <label>4.</label>
   <p id="p0055">Upon entering the host cells, in the cytoplasm, the viral genome is released as a positive sense single-stranded RNA, and its antigens are detected by the antigen-presenting cells (APCs), which are the major cells of the immune system (dendritic cells or macrophages, especially alveolar macrophages) involved in protection against invading antigens. This detection triggers a downstream cascade of many T-cell stimulators and inflammatory molecules, the so-called cytokine storm, leading to activation of transcription factor nuclear factor-κB (NF-κB) and interferon regulatory factor 3 (IRF3), with the subsequent production of type I interferons (IFN-α/β) and a series of pro-inflammatory cytokines including interleukin (IL)-1β and IL-6 [
    <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, 
    <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, 
    <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, 
    <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>]. The cytokine storm produces a violent attack on the body by the immune system, initiating acute respiratory distress syndrome and multiple organ failure.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
