<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Pretreatment HIV drug resistance (HIVDR) to first-generation NNRTIs has consistently increased in different regions across Mexico during the last decade.
 <xref rid="dkz502-B1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> A nationally representative survey performed in 2015 showed efavirenz/nevirapine pretreatment drug resistance prevalence approaching 10%,
 <xref rid="dkz502-B2" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>2</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="dkz502-B3" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> a threshold defined by the WHO at which to recommend urgent public health action.
 <xref rid="dkz502-B4" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="dkz502-B5" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref> A more recent regionally representative survey showed a similar NNRTI pretreatment HIVDR level in the central subregion including the Mexico City metropolitan area.
 <xref rid="dkz502-B6" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref> This rate of HIVDR is especially relevant in Mexico (and many other Latin American countries), as the preferred first-line ART regimens were efavirenz based until modification of national ART guidelines in late 2018.
 <xref rid="dkz502-B7" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref> The Mexico City metropolitan area (including Mexico City and some municipalities of the neighbouring Mexico State) includes over 15% of the nearly 250 000 persons estimated to be living with HIV (PLWH) in Mexico
 <xref rid="dkz502-B8" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="dkz502-B9" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref> and is a major hub for viral dissemination within the country.
 <xref rid="dkz502-B10" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref> The Condesa Clinic in Mexico City is the largest HIV care provider in Mexico, with more than 14 000 active clients (of an estimated 37 000 PLWH in Mexico City).
 <xref rid="dkz502-B8" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref> The Condesa Clinic is also a key HIV detection centre, performing ∼35 000 HIV tests, and diagnosing ∼4000 new infections annually (according to the Condesa Information System), which represent over a quarter of all HIV diagnoses in Mexico and ∼70%–80% of all annual diagnoses in Mexico City metropolitan area.
 <xref rid="dkz502-B8" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref> Due to its size and HIV testing volume, the Condesa Clinic is an ideal site for molecular surveillance in Mexico. Combining HIV molecular data and epidemiological information might help not only to understand HIVDR transmission dynamics locally, but also to design more efficient, cluster-informed, early detection and prevention strategies.
</p>
