<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The absences of both virus isolation and observation of clinical disease in wildlife species in Africa is surprising given the increasingly visible epidemics in wildlife in Asia [
 <xref rid="B5-viruses-12-00293" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-viruses-12-00293" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-viruses-12-00293" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-viruses-12-00293" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Both absences could reflect facts (absence of viral excretion and disease expression in African wildlife) but could also be due to imperfect datasets constrained by the difficulty to survey disease in wildlife. Mortalities seen in phylogenetically closely related species to the abundant wildlife in East Africa (e.g., saiga antelope (
 <italic>Saiga tatarica mongolica</italic>)) are not dissimilar to that experienced with RP in wildlife, historically with high morbidity and mortality, in the case of saiga approaching 100% and 80%, respectively [
 <xref rid="B5-viruses-12-00293" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The closest African relatives of the saiga antelope, Thomson’s gazelle (
 <italic>Eudorcas thomsoni</italic>), are well represented in Kenya and Tanzania, and no sign of disease in PPRV prevalent areas was seen or reported by wildlife or veterinary authorities, or even anecdotally by local communities. This apparent absence of disease in most populations of free-ranging African wildlife is consistent across all species shown to be exposed to PPRV by this study or previous serological studies [
 <xref rid="B14-viruses-12-00293" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], whilst PPR syndromes in captive African species in the Middle Eastern collections are reported [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-12-00293" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. A recent outbreak of PPR in dorcas gazelle in Dinder National Park, Sudan is the first verifiable report of disease in free-ranging antelope in sub-Saharan Africa, but more pathological and epidemiological data are needed to confirm the laboratory findings [
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-12-00293" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. A shift in PPR epidemiology as wildlife becomes increasingly stressed by rising human and livestock numbers and associated loss of forage and disturbance, could be a concerning development for wildlife economies in East Africa that need to be vigilant [
 <xref rid="B4-viruses-12-00293" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-12-00293" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. This is certainly the characteristic of the Asian ecosystems where PPR is readily expressed in wildlife. To explain this phenomenon, more research on the pathogenesis of PPR in wildlife species is needed; in addition, the role of infective strains, nutrition, stress, co-infections, environmental factors, and other ecological aspects need to be better explored to understand the PPR disease ecology. While there is a possibility that wildlife can maintain and bridge viruses between populations of wildlife and livestock [
 <xref rid="B63-viruses-12-00293" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], attempts at elimination of PPRV might be frustrated. Both livestock and wildlife components should be considered in further field studies to clarify PPR epidemiology, and eco-region level approaches should be implemented to better understand PPR dynamics at a relevant landscape level.
</p>
