<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Whatever the context, all these diseases would be positively impacted by the availability of efficacious and approved vaccines. However, to a greater or lesser extent they are all niche diseases with no major commercial incentives to drive vaccine development programmes. This is a space that non‐governmental organizations (NGOs) such as the Coalition of Epidemic Preparedness Innovations (CEPI) 
 <xref rid="cei13284-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">58</xref> and Global Vaccine Alliance (GAVI) 
 <xref rid="cei13284-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">59</xref> have entered and they are supporting vaccine efforts for some of the diseases listed above. Additionally, philanthropic funders such as the Gates Foundation are supporting vaccine R&amp;D efforts 
 <xref rid="cei13284-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">60</xref>. In the United Kingdom, and subsequent to the Ebola outbreak in West Africa, vaccine networks for human and veterinary vaccines have formed to prioritize vaccine efforts in these respective contexts 
 <xref rid="cei13284-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">61</xref>, while the Department of Health, together with Innovate UK, has supported R&amp;D of vaccine candidates for the prioritized pathogens 
 <xref rid="cei13284-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">62</xref>. As a result of these global initiatives, a number of candidate vaccines are being developed for emerging bacterial and viral pathogens, examples of which, although by no means exhaustive, are cited here 
 <xref rid="cei13284-bib-0063" ref-type="ref">63</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cei13284-bib-0064" ref-type="ref">64</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cei13284-bib-0065" ref-type="ref">65</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cei13284-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">66</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cei13284-bib-0067" ref-type="ref">67</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cei13284-bib-0068" ref-type="ref">68</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cei13284-bib-0069" ref-type="ref">69</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cei13284-bib-0070" ref-type="ref">70</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cei13284-bib-0071" ref-type="ref">71</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cei13284-bib-0072" ref-type="ref">72</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cei13284-bib-0073" ref-type="ref">73</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cei13284-bib-0074" ref-type="ref">74</xref>. WHO reports ongoing global vaccine R&amp;D efforts 
 <xref rid="cei13284-bib-0075" ref-type="ref">75</xref> and also tracks the progress of clinical trials for emerging pathogens 
 <xref rid="cei13284-bib-0076" ref-type="ref">76</xref>.
</p>
