<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The first adenovirus based vaccine against Ebola, replication defective Ad5 expressing EBOV GP, was described in 2000 and tested in combination with DNA vector vaccination in non-human primates (NHPs). Vaccination was found to be protective but required long vaccination schedules (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). This vaccine was further developed by generating a vector expressing both GP and the nucleoprotein (NP) to enhance T cell responses. Indeed, vaccination with this vector resulted in complete protection in NHPs upon a single vaccination. Protection was found to correlate with both the generation of specific CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cell and antibody responses (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). Further studies employed an Ad5 vector developed by Crucell Holland BV that expressed GPs from two Ebolavirus subspecies [Ebola virus (EBOV) and Sudan Ebolavirus (SUDV)] featuring a point mutation that reduced protein cytotoxicity. The vaccine was found to be protective in NHPs while allowing deletion of NP from the construct as well as dose sparing (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). Given these encouraging results, a clinical trial (NCT00374309) was initiated in 2006 (Table 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). This study showed safety as well as the induction of antibody and T cell responses, but no significant generation of virus neutralizing titers (
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). Importantly, this study also demonstrated that the induction of antibodies was reduced in participants with pre-existing immunity against Ad5. Given the high prevalence of 60–90% of Ad5 in the human population, this finding might compromise the use of Ad5 for the development of human vaccines. Upon the outbreak of the Ebola pandemic in 2014, a new Ad5 based vaccine was developed in a joint effort by the Beijing Institute of Biotechnology and Tianjin CanSino Biotechnology Inc. This vaccine was the first to incorporate the GP of the 2014 epidemic Ebola strain and was produced as a lyophilized powder that facilitated vaccine transport and storage by allowing storage at 2–8°C. A phase I clinical trial initiated at the end of 2014 (NCT02326194), showed no serious adverse events, although higher incidences of injection-site reactions were associated with higher Ad5 doses (Table 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Importantly, this study showed that high doses of Ad5 vector were able to overcome the negative effects of pre-existing immunity, as participants with a high baseline concentration of Ad5 neutralizing antibodies still induced robust GP-specific antibody and T cell responses (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). A phase II clinical study (NCT02575456) testing the Ad5 viral vector was initiated in Sierra Leone in October 2015 (Table 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), results are not yet publicly available.
</p>
