<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>rVSV-ZEBOV currently represents the most promising candidate for the development of an effective vaccine against Ebolaviruses. This vaccine consists of a live attenuated VSV in which the VSV glycoprotein is removed and replaced with the GP from a 1995 EBOV strain. rVSV-ZEBOV was developed by the Canadian National Microbiology Laboratory and is now licensed to Merck. Preclinical studies published in 2004 and 2005, respectively, demonstrated complete protection from a lethal EBOV challenge infection in mice using a mouse-adapted strain (
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>) and NHPs with a single injection (
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>). rVSV-ZEBOV was demonstrated to be fully protective in NPHs when the vaccine was applied only seven days before challenge (
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>) and showed promise as a post-exposure prophylaxis in NHPs: injection with one or two doses of vaccine 1 or 24 h after EBOV exposure resulted in 33–67% protection (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>). The vaccine was tested in ten completed phase I clinical trials with the earliest study having been initiated in October 2014 (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>). First results from clinical studies (NCT02283099, NCT02287480, and NCT02296983) published in 2016 (
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>) showed robust and persistent induction of GP specific antibody responses as well as virus neutralizing titers with higher titers elicited in higher dose groups (Table 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). However, these studies also raised safety concerns: doses of 1 × 10
 <sup>7</sup> PFU or higher were associated with the development arthritis lasting a median of 8 days. In addition, some participants experiencing arthralgia developed a maculopapular rash indicative of VSV replication and dissemination. Following this, the study was suspended and resumed one month later using a lower dose of 3 × 10
 <sup>5</sup> PFU (NCT02287480). Reduction of viral titers employed for vaccination yielded reduced adverse events. However, while the frequency of GP specific antibody induction remained similar to cohorts vaccinated with higher doses (94%), levels of antibody responses were reduced.
</p>
