<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Infection-reinfection or sequential infection experiments attempt to recapitulate influenza seasonality using animal models. The host is primed with an initial influenza virus before a challenge with a secondary infection following a recovery period. From infection-reinfection studies, it is clear that re-challenge with the same or a similar pathogen invokes memory activation of the humoral and cellular arms of the adaptive immune system [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00122" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-11-00122" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-viruses-11-00122" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-viruses-11-00122" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Antibodies directed toward the HA molecule can block viral entry into cells if the host is re-exposed to the same virus strain [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00122" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Above we defined the exposure permutations in terms of influenza virus antigenicity as monosubtypic homologous, monosubtypic heterologous, heterosubtypic, and heterotypic reinfection relationships [
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-11-00122" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In immunocompetent individuals, sterilizing immunity is achieved via antibody-dependent virus neutralization during a homologous reinfection [
 <xref rid="B69-viruses-11-00122" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. By contrast, heterologous reinfection, whether monosubtypic heterologous, heterosubtypic, or heterotypic is often non-sterilizing since viral antigenic sites has changed [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00122" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-11-00122" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Non-sterilizing events involve cellular CD8
 <sup>+</sup> responses that target viral internal proteins (as defined above) [
 <xref rid="B54-viruses-11-00122" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. There is limited information regarding the involvement with other aspects of adaptive immunity such as memory NK cells during a heterologous reinfection event. Virus exposure following a primary infection most often occurs during the memory phase, not the expansion or contraction phase of the primary adaptive immune response. For the influenza virus-host interaction, the interval of time between a primary and secondary exposure is yearly due to virus seasonality and vaccination programs [
 <xref rid="B70-viruses-11-00122" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>].
</p>
