<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Examination of the proportion of potato VOCs by ROC curve analysis showed that onion thrips preference traits, plant age and cultivar identity had volatiles that were important predictors of these factors. Previous studies have shown the role of individual or VOC cocktails from potato in altering behaviour response of insects. Analysis of antennal activity in Guatemalan moth females of individual potato volatiles showed significant activity with several volatiles of which β-myrcene, β-carophyllene, (
 <italic>E</italic>)-β-farnesene (
 <italic>T</italic>. 
 <italic>tabaci</italic> preference), and δ-cadinene were also identified in our study [
 <xref rid="pone.0181831.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. There are also specific effects of VOC blends from potato that are known to affect aphid choice and it may be the relative concentration of chemicals within a mixture that serve as cues [
 <xref rid="pone.0181831.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Indeed it has been shown that VOCs responsible for host-cues in a blend can become non-host cues when presented individually [
 <xref rid="pone.0181831.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Certain plant volatiles may also mask attractive compounds when present in abundance. For example, (
 <italic>E</italic>)-2-hexen-1-ol and (
 <italic>E</italic>)-2-hexenal, whilst showing no repellent activity themselves, reduced the attraction of Colorado potato beetle to potato odours [
 <xref rid="pone.0181831.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Thus interpretation of our results on thrips preference requires recognition that important VOCs identified may require other compounds for activity. Of the compounds identified with significant association to 
 <italic>T</italic>. 
 <italic>tabaci</italic> repellency, β-elemene has been identified as a major constituent in the essential oil from 
 <italic>Cinnamomum myrrha</italic> that was repellent to Legume flower thrips [
 <xref rid="pone.0181831.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], and isoamyl alcohol is known to attract hornets [
 <xref rid="pone.0181831.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Similarly, of those compounds that were associated with 
 <italic>T</italic>. 
 <italic>tabaci</italic> attraction, 
 <italic>(E</italic>)-β-farnesene is well known as a repellent of aphids [
 <xref rid="pone.0181831.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0181831.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], but has been previously shown to attract western flower thrips [
 <xref rid="pone.0181831.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Zingiberene in a cocktail mix has been shown to attract the two-spotted stink bug [
 <xref rid="pone.0181831.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>].
</p>
