<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During the processes of genome replication and transcription, bunyavirus L protein synthesizes three distinct RNA species: (i) antigenomic 
 <underline>c</underline>omplementary RNA (cRNA), (ii) genomic 
 <underline>v</underline>iral RNA (vRNA) and (iii) capped, mostly non-polyadenylated viral mRNA. Whereas genome replication is believed to be initiated 
 <italic>de novo</italic> by the L protein, viral transcription is dependent on short, capped RNA primers derived from cellular RNAs by a mechanism called cap-snatching (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), which involves cap binding and endonuclease functions. The part of bunyavirus L protein that has been most characterized, both structurally and functionally, is the ∼20 kDa endonuclease domain (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7–9</xref>), which is generally located at the N terminus. Its metal-dependent RNA cleavage activity is required for the cap-snatching mechanism to steal 5′ cap structures from cellular RNA and attach these fragments to the viral mRNA in order to be processed by the cellular translation machinery at the ribosome. For Rift Valley Fever virus (RVFV), a bunyavirus of the 
 <italic>Phenuiviridae</italic> family, the C-terminal region of the L protein has been shown to contain a cap-binding domain (CBD), the second activity needed for the cap-snatching mechanism. This CBD is structurally similar to that of influenza virus but with distinct differences in its mode of cap-recognition (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). The third important activity is the RdRp, which is needed for both transcription and genome replication. To date, only for one bunyavirus L protein, that of La Crosse virus (LACV, 
 <italic>Peribunyaviridae</italic> family), is more extensive high-resolution structural information available. The LACV structures with viral RNA contain ∼77% of the L protein sequence including the endonuclease, RdRp domain and important protein–RNA interaction sites but are entirely missing the C-terminal domain (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Even though further structural insights into distinct functional states of bunyavirus L protein are still lacking, these structures were a milestone on the path to a complete structural understanding of bunyavirus transcription and replication. In terms of functional data, biochemical characterization of Lassa and Machupo viruses (
 <italic>Arenaviridae</italic> family) (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13–16</xref>) as well as LACV (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) L proteins have been published. Specific to each bunyavirus family, the 3′ and 5′ termini of the genomic RNA segments are highly conserved and almost fully complementary in sequence and are denoted as the conserved promoter regions. For influenza virus and LACV, the RNA 5′ end forms a hook-like secondary structure that is bound in a specific pocket adjacent to the RNA synthesis active site of the L protein (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). The presence of a hook-conformation and its importance for robust RdRp activity have also been proposed for arenaviruses (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Furthermore, for arenaviruses, it was shown that the L protein initiates genome synthesis 
 <italic>de novo</italic> by a prime-and-realign mechanism (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) similar to the initiation of influenza virus vRNA synthesis from cRNA and Hantaan virus genome replication (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19–22</xref>).
</p>
