<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We consider a normalized version of the 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> equation such that it is rescaled to range from zero to one with the value of one occurring at the unimodal peak. Although absolute values of 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> that are used to determine when transmission is stable depend on additional factors not captured in our model, the minimum and maximum temperatures for which 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> &gt; 0 map exactly onto our normalized equations, allowing us to accurately calculate whether or not transmission should be possible at all. Empirical estimates of absolute values of 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> are difficult to obtain in any case, but it is much easier to determine whether transmission is occurring and for how long. While different model formulations for predicting 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> versus temperature can produce results with different magnitudes and potentially different overall shapes [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], the temperatures for which 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> is above or below zero (or one) are mostly model independent. For instance, two competing models differ only by whether or not the formula in Eq (
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pntd.0005568.e001">1</xref>) is squared, but the square of a number (e.g., an absolute 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> value) greater than one is always greater than one, and the square of a number less than one is always less than one. Therefore, the threshold temperatures at which absolute 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> &gt; 0 or absolute 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> &gt; 1 will be exactly the same for either choice of formula (Fig F in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0005568.s001">S1 Text</xref>). Similarly, because different expressions for 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub>, including the square of Eq (
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pntd.0005568.e001">1</xref>), map monotonically onto our function, they will produce identical estimates for the temperatures at which transmission declines to zero and peaks (Fig F in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0005568.s001">S1 Text</xref>). Consequently, our use of relative 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> adequately describes the nonlinear relationship between mosquito and virus traits and transmission.
</p>
