<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Following Johnson 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], we fit a thermal response for each trait using Bayesian models. We first fit Bayesian models for each trait thermal response using uninformative priors (
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> ~ Uniform (0, 24), 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>m</italic>
 </sub> ~ Uniform (25, 45), 
 <italic>c</italic> ~ Gamma (1, 10) for Brière and 
 <italic>c</italic> ~ Gamma (1, 1) for Quadratic fits) chosen to restrict each parameter to its biologically realistic range (i.e., 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> &lt; 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>m</italic>
 </sub> and we assumed that temperatures below 0°C and above 45°C were lethal). Any negative values for all thermal response functions were truncated at zero, and thermal responses for probabilities (
 <italic>p</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>EA</italic>
 </sub>, 
 <italic>b</italic>, and 
 <italic>c</italic>) were also truncated at one. We modeled the observed data as arising from a normal distribution with the mean predicted by the thermal response function calculated at the observed temperature, and the precision 
 <italic>τ</italic>, (
 <italic>τ</italic> = 1/
 <italic>σ</italic>), distributed as 
 <italic>τ</italic> ~ Gamma (0.0001, 00001). We fit the models using Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) sampling in JAGS, using the R [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] package 
 <italic>rjags</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. For each thermal response, we ran five MCMC chains with a 5000-step burn-in and saved the subsequent 5000 steps. We thinned the posterior samples by saving every fifth sample and used the samples to calculate 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> from 15–40°C, producing a posterior distribution of 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> versus temperature. We summarized the relationship between temperature and each trait or overall 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> by calculating the mean and 95% highest posterior density interval (HPD interval; a type of credible interval that includes the smallest continuous range containing 95% of the probability, as implemented in the 
 <italic>coda</italic> package [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005568.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]) for each curve across temperatures.
</p>
