<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although RVF causes human infections as well, we do not consider humans directly in our single patch model. Infected humans will not transmit the RVFV to other humans or back to vectors, as they are the dead end of the pathogen transmission. Adding human compartments increases the total number of infected individuals, but it does not change the transmission dynamics of RVFV between mosquitoes and livestock. On the other hand, human movement and behavior do affect the disease dynamics by regulation of livestock importation level, movement speed, and death rates (including the rate of slaughter) in each patch. Therefore, we incorporate human activities via the periodic parameters for import level, movement speed, and death rate of livestock. The spread of RVFV is also believed to link with regional human dispersal in Egypt. To model the spread of the disease along the Nile or the coastline of Red Sea (from southern Egypt to the Nile Delta and near the Suez Canal) 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003388-Illustrated1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, we adopt a directional three-patch model (refer to 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0003388-g001">Fig. 1 (b)</xref>), similar to the idea of the three-patch model for RVFV studied in 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003388-Gao1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, and further extend the model by adding exposed classes for both host and vector population in each patch. Patch 1 represents region from the boarder between Sudan and Egypt to Aswan, patch 2 consists the land of the long region along the Nile (Aswan to Cairo) or the long coastline of Red Sea, and the last patch covers the region of the Nile Delta (shaded area in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0003388-g001">Fig. 1 (a)</xref>). Denote by 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003388.e051.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>, the movement speed of livestock in all groups, regardless of infectiousness, from patch 1 to 2 and 2 to 3. As the Nile Delta is modeled by the last patch, the death rate 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003388.e052.jpg" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula> is periodic in patch 3. In particular, there is barely any outflow of livestock from patch 3, as Mecca is a city whose economy has been heavily dependent on the annual pilgrimage 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003388-Bearman1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref> and thus export few livestock. Therefore, we ignore the movement of livestock and consider only a periodic death rate in patch 3. In this paper, we use only a three-patch model, but the number of patches can be increased based on geographic divisions. However, since the overall qualitative behavior of the system does not change by adding more patches, without loss of generality, we present a three-patch model in the paper.
</p>
