<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="Tab1">
 <label>Table 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Ten critical issues for intensive care medicine</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th/>
    <th>Current situations or problems</th>
    <th>Suggestions or solutions</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td>1</td>
    <td>Severe shortage of critical medical resources including physicians, nurses, and ICU beds in China.</td>
    <td>Increase financial and staff investment, value the training of intensive care physicians and intensivists, and increase the ratio of ICU beds to hospital beds nationwide.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>2</td>
    <td>The levels of intensive care medicine in different provinces are uneven.</td>
    <td>Strengthen training to achieve the homogeneity of clinical cognition and management capabilities of intensive care physicians in different provinces.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>3</td>
    <td>To focus medical resources on rescuing large numbers of Covid-19 patients, many non-Covid-19 patients are unable to receive effective treatment.</td>
    <td>Establish a professional agency for the integration and optimization of the allocation of critical medical resources.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>4</td>
    <td>Medical staffs in Wuhan City from other provinces or cities were unfamiliar with the local conditions and the early phage of rescuing was in unordered states.</td>
    <td>Set up standardized operating procedures for ensuring the refined risk stratification and subsequent refined management of critically ill patients.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>5</td>
    <td>Lack protection awareness and equipment early, many physicians or nurses were infected by SARS-CoV-2.</td>
    <td>Strengthen occupational protection training and develop special standardized protection procedures during epidemics.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>6</td>
    <td>The continuous recognition of Covid-19 by Chinese intensive care physicians is a long and deepening process.</td>
    <td>Develop the ability of intensive care physicians to quickly analyze and respond to a new disease.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>7</td>
    <td>Covid-19 patients usually are complicated with multiple organ failure.</td>
    <td>More cooperation between intensive care medicine and other disciplines to deal with the rapid development of Covid-19.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>8</td>
    <td>The timing, dose, and duration of many therapies or life support for Covid-19 still remain controversial.</td>
    <td>More training to improve the research ability of intensive care physicians.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>9</td>
    <td>The published studies mostly are single-centered and retrospective. It is difficult to integrate clinical, basic and public health data.</td>
    <td>Establish a national special disease database, specimen bank and share research data from different medical centers.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>10</td>
    <td>Critical patients obtain multi-disciplinary expert team consultations through a national video remote consultation platform during Covid-19.</td>
    <td>Promote ICU informatization construction. The successful experience should be extensively extended to the cure of other critical patients.</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
