<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par87">When the Spanish flu began spreading to other countries such as the U.S., finding a vaccine became a tantamount goal for scientists and clinicians alike. During the peak of this epidemic Spanish flu “vaccines” were developed and distributed throughout the U.S. Health officials informed the public that these vaccines would protect from the influenza. However, the specific cause of influenza was yet to be discovered [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>]. These vaccines targeted multiple types of bacteria that had been isolated from victims of the Spanish flu, suggesting that influenza was a bacterial disease. These Spanish Flu vaccines were widely used but still had little to no supporting evidence for their benefits. Only a few attempts to test their effectiveness were made once the vaccines were distributed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]. Eventually, the Surgeon General, American Public Health Association, and editors of the Journal of the American Medical Association made a public statement that there was currently no serum or any means of curing influenza and that there was no vaccine to prevent it. They informed the public that all claims made by newspapers and other sources were unofficial and experimental. This editorial warned health officials and physicians to stop making false promises without evidence to support them. Without knowing the causative agent of the Spanish flu there was no evidence to suggest the effectiveness of a vaccine [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]. The scientific community was failing to find the cause of the influenza which led researchers to believe that influenza was a viral disease. Virology was still in its early stages during this time. However, by the 1930 s there was an improvement in the process of isolating and identifying pathogens [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>]. These research advances aided in the search for the Spanish Flu vaccine.
</p>
