<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>PLHIV are vulnerable to infection with TB bacillus, including DR ones. The annual risk of developing TB infection in the HIV-infected population is ten times that of the uninfected.
 <xref rid="CIT0098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0099" ref-type="bibr">99</xref> Screening is required for ruling out not only active infection but also latent infection. Chemoprophylaxis is indicated if the latent infection is detected by immunologic testing, such as tuberculin skin test or IFNγ-release assay. Appropriate chemoprophylaxis has been reported to reduce the risk of TB infection by 35%, with larger benefit in the skin test–positive population (risk reduction of 52%), with the risk of mortality reduced by 35%.
 <xref rid="CIT0100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>–
 <xref rid="CIT0102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref> It has also been observed to reduce the risk of HIV disease progression by 31%. Therefore, chemoprophylaxis is an important preventive therapy in DS-TB and HIV coinfection. Limited evidence is available regarding the role of chemoprophylaxis in preventing active disease among people with or without HIV infection havin contacts with M/XDR-TB patients.
 <xref rid="CIT0103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref> People in whom latent infection is diagnosed are often infected with the same strain as the index case. Prompt treatment of the index case with DR-TB should be the priority. If contact is asymptomatic, no prophylactic treatment is recommended, and the patient should be placed under clinical follow-up. The follow-up duration for close contacts of M/XDR-TB patients is not defined, but should be at least 2 years.
 <xref rid="CIT0105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref> Children &lt;3 years of age suspected of contact with patients with M/XDR-TB can be given chemoprophylaxis to prevent progression of disease. If the contact is symptomatic, presumptive TB infection should be suspected and investigated further with the CBNAAT or appropriate investigation. Prompt initiation of treatment with a regimen designed to treat the index case is recommended in cases of development of active disease till DST results are collected. There is a lack of consensus on designing standardized chemoprophylaxis regimens related to the selection of second-line anti-TB drugs, dosages, and duration of therapy. The proposed recommendation is to use two to three oral drugs (FQs, E, Z, high-dose H, Eto, and Cs) for 6–12 months, based on the susceptibility pattern of the index case of DR-TB. The reduction of risk of developing infection has been reported to be 37%–90%.
 <xref rid="CIT0100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref> These regimens are also associated with ADRs. FQs are included in all regimens with fewest ADRs. However, preventive therapy containing FQs can be ineffective in particular settings where probability of baseline resistance to FQs remains high.
 <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> Various clinical trials are ongoing for effective preventive therapy for DR-TB with FQs' (TB CHAMP and VQUIN trials) and even with newer drugs like Dlm (PHOENIXMDR-TB trial).
 <xref rid="CIT0078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref> National programs should emphasize chemoprophylaxis in preventing latent infection among HIV-endemic areas where the probability of DR-TB coinfection remains high. Further research is required to prove the efficacy of chemoprophylaxis in the prevention of infection in PLHIV with contacts with M/XDR-TB.
</p>
