<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Infections due to mosquito-borne viruses have become a global health problem during the past two decades, due to their wide geographic spread and high human disease burden. This is directly associated with their widespread distribution and ecological changes related to vector mosquitoes as well as increases in international trade and travel [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007334.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007334.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Any list of the mosquito-borne viruses with significant impact that have emerged or re-emerged would include dengue virus (DENV), yellow fever virus (YFV), chikungunya virus (CHIKV) and recently, Zika virus (ZIKV) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007334.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007334.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. These viruses are transmitted to susceptible vertebrates with varying degrees of vector competence via the globally invasive 
 <italic>Aedes (Stegomyia) aegypti</italic> (L.) and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. (
 <italic>Stg</italic>.) 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> (Skuse) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007334.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. In Europe, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> is the most prolific invasive mosquito species, having greatly expanded its range across many countries since its original introduction to Albania in 1979 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007334.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007334.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Despite a more constrained geographical distribution, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> has significantly recolonized parts of southern and southeastern Europe with populations found in Portugal and the Black Sea coast of Russia, Republic of Georgia and, most recently, in northeastern Turkey [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007334.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007334.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Risk mapping efforts have identified 215 countries or territories to be potentially suitable for the survival and establishment of invasive 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> species, with disease outbreaks from more than half of the target regions [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007334.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Therefore, concerns of virus transmission that could initiate and sustain epidemics in countries infested by these mosquitoes have been raised, requiring vector and pathogen surveillance [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007334.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007334.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].
</p>
