<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Birds serve as both reservoirs and amplifying hosts of the virus of SINV. Studies highlight migratory birds in the redistribution of SINV from enzootic regions into non-endemic areas, as the differences between genotypes of SINV are associated with the geographic patterns of these birds [
 <xref rid="B258-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">258</xref>,
 <xref rid="B280-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">280</xref>]. Additionally, birds might have been spreading SINV mainly through north–south axis migratory routes, rather than east–west axis flyways [
 <xref rid="B257-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">257</xref>]. Although studies of experimental infection of different birds and their potential role as SINV amplifying hosts are currently scarce [
 <xref rid="B281-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">281</xref>], studies of anti-SINV antibodies detection and viral isolation from birds collected in the wild suggest a relatively wide spectrum of potential amplifying hosts of SINV. Lundström et al. [
 <xref rid="B33-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] detected neutralizing antibodies against SINV in birds from three orders, Anseriformes (waterfowl), Galliformes, and Passeriformes in Sweden. Fourteen species of these orders can also be experimentally infected with SINV, producing sufficient viremia titers to infect enzootic cycle mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="B282-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">282</xref>]. Furthermore, increased seropositivity in fieldfares (
 <italic>Turdus pilaris</italic>), redwings (
 <italic>Turdus iliacus</italic>), and of song thrushes (
 <italic>Turdus philomelos</italic>) suggests that these birds, which are common in Northern and Central Europe, might be the main amplification hosts in Sweden [
 <xref rid="B283-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">283</xref>,
 <xref rid="B284-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">284</xref>]. A study in Finland detected antibodies anti-SINV mainly in two 
 <italic>Tetrao</italic> spp., black grouse (
 <italic>Tetrao tetrix</italic>) and capercaillies (
 <italic>Tetrao urogallus</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B264-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">264</xref>]. The SINV has also been isolated from hooded crow (
 <italic>Corvus corone cornix</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B281-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">281</xref>] and from a wild, common wood pigeon (
 <italic>Columba palumbus</italic>) in Germany, which is also common in Central Europe [
 <xref rid="B285-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">285</xref>] and others [
 <xref rid="B258-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">258</xref>]. Therefore, monitoring studies of birds, mosquitoes, and other potential hosts are warranted in order to continue evaluating the risk of SINV outbreaks.
</p>
