<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Host cell nucleoside biosynthesis inhibitors</italic>: Nucleoside analogs have been commonly used as antiviral agents for human viral infections for many years [
 <xref rid="B124-pharmaceuticals-12-00157" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]. Nucleosides from the host cell are essential for maintaining adequate RNA replications in viruses. Inhibition of nucleoside biosynthesis is believed to trigger the activation of antiviral interferon-stimulated genes in human cells [
 <xref rid="B125-pharmaceuticals-12-00157" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>]. Ribavirin, one of the first clinically used broad-spectrum antivirals and a few other known broad-spectrum antivirals were found to inhibit the virus-induced cytopathic effects (CPE) of several flaviviruses, including ZIKV (EC50 = 142.9 mg/mL) [
 <xref rid="B126-pharmaceuticals-12-00157" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. However, poor inhibition of ribavirin as shown in the above virus-induced CPE study indicates that it is not a suitable candidate as a ZIKV drug [
 <xref rid="B111-pharmaceuticals-12-00157" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. Other tested nucleoside biosynthesis inhibitors showed better results, such as MPA (EC50 = 0.11 mM), brequinar (EC50 = 0.08 mM), and 6-azauridine (EC50 = 0.98 mM) [
 <xref rid="B127-pharmaceuticals-12-00157" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>]. However, a recent study indicates several new promising lead candidates for further development particularly as antivirals against ZIKV [
 <xref rid="B127-pharmaceuticals-12-00157" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>]. BCX4430 an adenosine nucleoside analog has shown EC50 values in the low μg/mL range (3.8–18.2 μg/mL) in vitro, with favorable selective index values and found to be a selective inhibitor of viral RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp). The compound has also shown in vivo efficacy in AG129 mouse model of ZIKV. Treating the animals with BCX4430 (300 mg/kg/d) protected seven of eight mice from mortality induced by a Malaysian strain (P 6–740) of ZIKV [
 <xref rid="B128-pharmaceuticals-12-00157" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. This protective efficacy of BCX4430 encourages its further development on the basis of safety and better efficacy evaluations. Another RdRp inhibitor, NITD008, an adenosine nucleoside analog, has also exhibited antiviral activity against ZIKV in vitro with EC50 at the sub-micro molar range (0.28–0.95 μM). Although when NITD008 was treated with 50 mg/kg in the A129 mouse model, it protected 50% of the infected mice from death without symptoms of neurological disorder [
 <xref rid="B129-pharmaceuticals-12-00157" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>], the compound was discarded to other undesirable toxic effects in clinical testing [
 <xref rid="B99-pharmaceuticals-12-00157" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>].
</p>
