<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Relevance screening was conducted in two stages. The first screening tool comprised of two questions to determine whether the citation could potentially be relevant to the review based on the title and abstract. We erred on the side of inclusiveness by including citations whenever their relevance remained unclear. Full-text articles of citations that passed through the first relevance screening stage were procured and assigned to a second level of relevance screening. The purpose of this step was to exclude articles after full text assessment, so that only relevant articles in full alignment with the research question remained for further characterization. At the second level of relevance screening, articles were excluded after full text assessment if they did not report on: 1) the impact of CHIKV on humans, hosts or vectors, 2) CHIKV studies including phylogeny and molecular characterization of genetic determinants for fitness and other evolutionary markers, CHIKV pathogenesis and infection mechanisms, 3) mitigation strategies to prevent and control CHIKV infections including strategies for CHIKV vector prevention and control, 4) clinical aspects of CHIKV infection and risk factors contributing to such infections, and 5) vector competence parameters—both behavioural and physiologic, as well as environmental factors associated with CHIKV transmission, 6) economic burden of chikungunya disease, or 7) modeling studies on chikungunya or CHIKV vectors. Articles that did not meet the inclusion criteria for language and primary data were also excluded at this stage. For articles that met the inclusion criteria, questions were answered at this level to broadly categorize articles by publication period, study location, study population (stratified as human and non-human hosts, vectors and/or virus) and research focus. This stage in the ScR process allowed us to gauge the quantity and breadth of research within the different focus areas and ensure that the data characterization and utility (DCU) tool would adequately capture relevant data from all studies.</p>
