<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8">As the first step in our analysis, S and N protein sequences will be analyzed to identify their immunogenic regions. Algorithms which can predict immunogenicity, secondary structure analysis, protein topology features and hydrophobicity will be studied to design peptides for further testing. Immunogenic viral peptides could be identified based on the algorithm developed by Kolaskar and Tongaonkar. This method makes use of the physicochemical properties of amino acid residues and its frequencies of occurrence in experimentally identified epitopes which are developed to identify antigenic determinants in proteins (Kolaskar and Tongaonkar 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">1990</xref>). These epitopes are the short residue set of peptides with antigenicity. IEDB (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://tools.iedb.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://tools.iedb.org</ext-link>) is one of the tools using this algorithm, which is mainly used to determine the antigenic sites with a default threshold value of 1.024. The prediction algorithm works as follows based on the paper published by Kolaskar and Tongaonkar in 1990.The algorithm is as follows.
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par9">Calculate the average propensity values (Ap) for each peptides from N terminus to C terminus of the protein and assign the result to the fourth (i + 3) residue in the segment.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par10">The average antigenic propensity of the protein will be determined</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par11">If the Ap of the protein is above 1.0 then all residues are potentially antigenic.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par12">If the average for the protein is below 1.0 then all residues having above the average for the protein are potentially antigenic.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par13">To select the antigenic determinant as a condition, six consecutive residues must satisfy step 3</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
