<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0085">HIV-1 and HIV-2 can infect human beings and cause severe immunosuppression through decline of CD4
 <sup>+</sup> cells [
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. So far, over 30 antiretroviral drugs were on the market for the treatment of HIV infection and divided into six main groups: integrase inhibitors, protease inhibitors, non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors, nucleoside/nucleotide reverse transcriptase inhibitors, and entry inhibitors [
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. However, in the United States, the annual cost of the drugs per individual can be as high as $24,000 relying on the types of anti-HIV medicines [
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Two undescribed isoprenylated, truncateols O (
 <bold>2</bold>, 
 <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>) and P (
 <bold>65</bold>, 
 <xref rid="fig13" ref-type="fig">Fig. 13</xref> ) were collected from the sponge-derived fungus 
 <italic>Truncatella angustata</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Compounds 
 <bold>2</bold> and 
 <bold>65</bold> showed anti-HIV effects by blocking HIV replication in one-cycle infection assay with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 39.0 and 16.1 μM, respectively [
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Moreover, though efavirenz (positive control) displaying stronger activity than the data raising from the isolated compounds, the lower cytotoxicity of the collected compounds (IC
 <sub>50</sub> &gt; 100 μM) in comparison with efavirenz (IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 40.6 μM) suggested that these compounds were worthy for further observation as anti-HIV leads [
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Chemical investigation of the extract of marine-derived fungus 
 <italic>Penicillium</italic> sp. IMB17-046 isolated from marine sediments collected from a mangrove swamp in Sanya, Hainan province, China, resulted in the isolation of trypilepyrazinol (
 <bold>66</bold>, 
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="fig13" ref-type="fig">Fig. 13</xref>
 <italic>β</italic>-hydroxyergosta-8,14,24 (28)-trien-7-one (
 <bold>67</bold>, 
 <xref rid="fig13" ref-type="fig">Fig. 13</xref>) [
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. These compounds exhibited broad-spectrum inhibitory activities against different types of viruses, including human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), and hepatitis C virus (HCV) [
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Compound 
 <bold>66</bold> showed inhibitory activities against HIV-1 and HCV with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 4.6 and 7.7 μM, respectively. Compound 
 <bold>67</bold> displayed anti-HIV-1 activity with IC
 <sub>50</sub> value of 3.5 μM [
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. The marine derived 
 <italic>Aspergillus niger</italic> SCSIO Jcsw6F30 was associated with a marine algae 
 <italic>Sargassum</italic> sp. collected in Yongxing Island, South China Sea, in July 2012, and produced a novel 2-benzylpyridin-4-one containing metabolite, aspernigrin C (
 <bold>68</bold>, 
 <xref rid="fig13" ref-type="fig">Fig. 13</xref>) and malformin C (
 <bold>69</bold>, 
 <xref rid="fig13" ref-type="fig">Fig. 13</xref>) [
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. These compounds exhibited obvious anti-HIV-1 activities with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 4.7 ± 0.4, 1.4 ± 0.06 μM, respectively (abacavir as a positive control, IC
 <sub>50</sub> = 0.8 ± 0.1 μM)[
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>].
</p>
