<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this part of the upstream process, the goal is to optimize conditions that permit the maximal production of leaf biomass and VLPs per square meter of green house space. Studies by our group and others demonstrated that temperature, light source and intensity, plant age, and incubation time after leaf infiltration all have significant impacts on biomass generation and VLP accumulation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR0008126">126</xref>]. For example, 
 <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> grown under nature light produces more biomass, but accumulates much less NVCP VLPs than plants grown under artificial light (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig00084" ref-type="fig">8.4a</xref>). Furthermore, leaves grown under natural-light also produce more solid debris during VLP extraction, causing problems for VLP purification [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR0008126">126</xref>]. Our data also indicate that a 16-h light/8-h dark cycle at 25 °C is the optimal condition to generate biomass under such artificial lighting [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR0008126">126</xref>]. When 
 <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> plants were grown under these conditions and sampled at various ages for NVCP VLP expression, it was founded that 5-week-old plants provided the optimal material for VLP production, because they already accumulated an adequate amount of biomass and produced the highest level of VLPs (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig00084" ref-type="fig">8.4b</xref>). Younger plants produce insufficient biomass, and older plants are too tall for infiltration and start to produce more secondary metabolites that complicate VLP purification. Consequently, 5-week-old 
 <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> optimally balance the combined need for biomass generation, filtration operation, and VLP accumulation. Our data demonstrated that under these optimized conditions, biomass for producing sufficient amount of purified NVCP VLPs for a Phase I clinical trial can be generated in 5.6 square meters of green house space in a 5-week period [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR0008126">126</xref>]. The horizontal space requirements for this type of production could be significantly reduced by vertically stacking layers of growth trays vertically.
</p>
