<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although dengue, chikungunya and Zika viruses share the same vector, there was not a perfect overlap of their spatial and temporal distributions in Brazil. Several factors could lead to the observed distribution, such as herd immunity, vector competence for the different viruses, the proportion of asymptomatic cases and under notification of cases. The Center-West region has the highest reported cases of dengue and Zika virus infections, whereas chikungunya reported infection is much higher in the Northeast region compared to the rest of the country. Chikungunya transmission efficiency seems to be lineage specific. Studies on 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> from Florida have shown differences in vector competence depending on the chikungunya strain. 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> were more susceptible to infection with the La Réunion strain than sympatric 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>Aegypti</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0201452.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. A more recent study showed that the chikungunya Asian strain is better transmitted by 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> species than by 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic>, whereas the Indian Ocean strain leads to higher body infection and transmission in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="pone.0201452.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. In addition, virus mutations can interfere with the transmission rate, for instance, an alanine-valine substitution at position 226 of the E1 envelope glycoprotein (E1-A226V) can improve transmission by 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0201452.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0201452.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>] Comparative genome studies on the chikungunya virus circulating in different Brazil regions could provide insights on the higher number of chikungunya cases found in the Northeastern Brazil.
</p>
