<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F8" position="float">
 <label>FIGURE 8</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Impact of non-structural (NS) on viral genome activity. 
   <bold>(A)</bold> Evaluation of the effect of non-structural protein 1 (NS1) on RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp) activity by mini-genome reporter assay. HEK293T cells were transfected with constructs expressing the viral RdRp complex (PA, PB1, PB2) and NP proteins, as well as a reporter plasmid pPol I-Flu-Rluc and internal control plasmid expressing firefly luciferase. At 24 h post transfection, luciferase activity and the expression of NS1 and NP of whole-cell lysate were monitored by luciferase assay and Western blot analysis, respectively. The Renilla luciferase expression level was initially normalized with firefly luciferase in the same group, and then the relative expression level was obtained by comparison with EV transfection, which was arbitrarily set as 1. The experiment was conducted in triplicate. *Indicates 
   <italic>p</italic>-value &lt;0.05. 
   <bold>(B)</bold> Effect of NS1 on expression of a heterogeneous gene in cells. The individual NS1 was transiently co-expressed with a green fluorescent protein (GFP) fusion protein in HEK293T cells. Overall GFP signal was recorded by fluorescent microscopy (the top panel) and Western blot analysis (bottom, left panel); and the expression level, relative to that without NS1 protein, was measured and plotted (bottom, right panel). 
   <bold>(C)</bold> Localization of ribonucleoprotein (RNP). Madin–Darby canine kidney (MDCK) cells were infected by individual avian influenza viruses engineered by reverse genetics (RG-AIVs) at a multiplicity of infection (MOI) of 1 for 24 h followed by immunofluorescent assay using antibodies against NP protein and DAPI to indicate the localization of RNP and the nucleus, respectively. The images were taken under confocal microscopy (400× magnification).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="fmicb-11-00280-g008" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
