<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Three to five millilitres of blood were obtained from all suspected cases of MVD for laboratory testing using real time RT-PCR and ELISA at the UVRI VHF laboratory according to established protocols [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007257.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007257.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Briefly, RNA was extracted from whole blood using 5X Magmax™ 96 Viral Isolation kit (Applied Biosystems Inc., Vilnius, Lithuania) according to manufacturer’s instructions. Subsequent RT-PCR assays targeted the VP40 viral gene. ELISA for anti-Marburg IgM and IgG detection was performed using 96-well plates. Unless otherwise stated, all ELISA procedures used 100μl test volume per well format; plates were washed 3 times using 0.1% Tween-20 in PBS (v/v) between all procedures; and all incubation temperatures were at 37°C for 1h. In addition, all reagents used in all procedures were diluted in PBS containing 5% skimmed milk (also called serum diluent). To perform ELISA, all plates were pre-coated overnight at 4°C with Marburg antigens (for IgG) and an anti-human IgM (mu) antibody (for IgM) in physiological buffered solution (PBS). Samples were pre-diluted to 1:100 in serum diluent before their addition onto pre-coated plates. For IgM, the addition of samples onto plates was followed by the addition of a positive antigen (1:2 dilution) on one (upper) half of the plate and a mock antigen (1:2) on the other half (lower) of the plate. This was followed by the addition of a primary antibody, a rabbit anti-Marburg antibody (in a dilution of 1:1500) and then a secondary, horseradish peroxidase conjugated, antibody (in a dilution of 1:8000). The substrate used was 2,2′-azino-bis (3-ethylbenthiazoline-6-sulfonic acid (Kirkegaard and Perry Laboratories, Gaithersburg USA) read at 410nm. For IgG antibody detection, samples were added to precoated plates followed directly by an anti-human IgG conjugate. Similarly, to IgM, the substrate used was 2,2′-azino-bis (3-ethylbenthiazoline-6-sulfonic acid (Kirkegaard and Perry Laboratories, Gaithersburg USA) read at 410nm.
</p>
