<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">A number of randomized controlled trials (RCTs) has also addressed this issue in healthcare settings. Loeb et al. conducted a randomized trial during the winter season of 2008–2009, comparing N95 to plain masks for prevention of influenza among 446 nurses in 8 medical centers in Ontario, Canada. There was no difference between the interventions regarding the probability of laboratory-confirmed influenza, other viral infection or febrile influenza-like illness (ILI), and a pre-specified non-inferiority criterion between mask types was met [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Furthermore, in a cluster randomized trial, McIntyre et al. compared the efficacy of simple medical masks with fit- and non-fit-tested N95 for the prevention of viral illness during a single winter season among 1441 HCWs. After 4 weeks of intervention and an additional observatory week, N95 were reported to be more effective than simple masks for prevention of clinical respiratory illness (CLI, broadly defined as two respiratory or one respiratory and one systemic symptom) but not of ILI or laboratory proven influenza or other viral infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. In another trial of identical design by the same investigators, an additional arm of intermittent N95 usage (when performing AGMPs or barrier nursing) was included; results showed a scaled increase of the probability of CLI for constant N95, intermittent N95 and plain mask usage, but no difference regarding proven viral infection, proven influenza infection or ILI [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Nonetheless, essential concern arises regarding the methodology of the latter two studies, as significant differences in baseline characteristics between the study groups indicate imperfections in the randomization procedure and probable contribution of confounders-recognized and not-to the reported results. In the largest and most recent cluster randomized trial among seven healthcare systems in the US. Radonovic et al. compared the efficacy of the two mask types among HCWs working in outpatient settings over four consecutive viral respiratory seasons. There were no ascertained differences regarding the primary outcome of laboratory-confirmed influenza or the secondary outcomes of proven or CLI and ILI [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].
</p>
