<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1">
 <label>Table 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Effect of ginseng on respiratory virus infections</p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text id="alttext0020">Table 1</alt-text>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th>Ginseng type</th>
    <th>Virus type</th>
    <th>model</th>
    <th>Dosage</th>
    <th>Results</th>
    <th>Ref</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td>Polysaccharide, saponin, and total extract</td>
    <td>Influenza (H1N1 subtype)</td>
    <td>BALB/c mice</td>
    <td>Orally 250 μg/kg/d for two weeks before virus challenge</td>
    <td>Reduced TNF-α, iNOS-producing dendritic cells (tipDCs) in the lungs and body weight loss after treatment with the polysaccharide fraction.</td>
    <td>[
     <xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <italic>P. ginseng</italic> aqueous extract powdered capsules
    </td>
    <td>Inactivated influenza virus A PR8 (25 mg)</td>
    <td>Female inbred BALB/c mice</td>
    <td>200 mg/kg for 14 days intranasally</td>
    <td>Increased levels of IgA and cytokines (IFN-g, IL-2, IL-4, IL-5, IL-6). Elevated CD69 expressing leukocytes, inducing protective immunity.</td>
    <td>[
     <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Ginsenoside Re + inactivated H3N2</td>
    <td>Inactivated influenza virus (H3N2)</td>
    <td>Female ICR mice</td>
    <td>25, 50, or 100 μg Re for 21 days subcutaneously</td>
    <td>Co-administration amplified IgG isotype responses, HI titers, lymphocyte proliferation, IL-5, and IFN-γ secretion.</td>
    <td>[
     <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>RG extract or RG saponin</td>
    <td>Influenza A/PR/8/34</td>
    <td>Balb/c mice</td>
    <td>0.25 mg/kg/d orally for 14 d prior to the primary immunization and 21 days until secondary immunization</td>
    <td>Elevated serum IgG titers and survival rates. Increased cell-mediated immunity associated with tissue repair and healing.</td>
    <td>[
     <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <italic>P. ginseng</italic>
    </td>
    <td>H1N1, and H3N2 (A/Philippines/82)</td>
    <td>BALB/c mice</td>
    <td>10 to 100 mg/kg for 14 days by oral route</td>
    <td>Lower levels of lung viral titers and IL-6, but higher levels of IFN-γ</td>
    <td>[
     <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>RGE</td>
    <td>HP H5N1 influenza virus</td>
    <td>Female mice</td>
    <td>50 mg/kg body weight) for up to 80 days</td>
    <td>Antiviral cytokines INF-α and -γ were induced</td>
    <td>[
     <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Polysaccharide</td>
    <td>H1N1 (A/PR8) and H3N2 viruses</td>
    <td>BALB/c mice</td>
    <td>25 mg/kg or IV 10 g/kg doses by i.n route</td>
    <td>Enhanced survival rate and lower levels of lung viral titers and IL-6.</td>
    <td>[
     <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>GSLS</td>
    <td>Inactivated ND and AI vaccines</td>
    <td>Hy-Line White layer chickens (male)</td>
    <td>2.5, 5, 10, and 20 mg/kg of BW for 7 days</td>
    <td>Enhanced the HI response against inactivated ND and AI vaccines in chickens</td>
    <td>[
     <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>GSLS</td>
    <td>Newcastle disease</td>
    <td>Hy-Line White layer chickens (male)</td>
    <td>2.5, 5, 10, and 20 mg/kg by oral route 7 days</td>
    <td>GSLS increased serum HI titer, lymphocyte proliferation, intestinal mucosal IgA + cells and iIELs.</td>
    <td>[
     <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>GSLS</td>
    <td>Inactive ND and AI</td>
    <td>Specific pathogen–free (SPF) chickens</td>
    <td>2.5, 5, and 10 mg/kg body weight by oral route for 7 days</td>
    <td>Improved splenocyte proliferation induced by ConA, LPS and IgA + cells and iIELs. Improved systemic and mucosal specific antibody responses</td>
    <td>[
     <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>RGE</td>
    <td>influenza A H1N1 (A/PR8) and A/WSN/1933 viruses</td>
    <td>BALB/c mice</td>
    <td>25 mg/kg/day by oral route for 30 days (500 μg/mL)</td>
    <td>RGE reduced influenza A virus-induced CPE formation and blocked the induction of influenza A virus pro-inflammatory gene expression. Anti-oxidative and immunomodulatory effects</td>
    <td>[
     <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <italic>P. ginseng</italic>
    </td>
    <td>RSV A2 strain</td>
    <td>BALB/c, C57BL/6 mice (MHCII KO) HEp2 cells</td>
    <td>25 mg/kg/day for 80 or 130 days by oral route</td>
    <td>Increased IgG2a isotype antibody response. Increased IFN-γ with modulation of CD3 T-cell populations. Decreased IL-4 production and diminished weight loss.</td>
    <td>[
     <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>RGE</td>
    <td>RSV</td>
    <td>HEp2 cells</td>
    <td>Direct mixing in medium</td>
    <td>Partially protected HEp2 cells from RSV-induced cell death and viral replication. Inhibited TNF-α in murine dendritic and macrophage-like cells.</td>
    <td>[
     <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>RGE</td>
    <td>RSV</td>
    <td>Female BALB/c mice</td>
    <td>500 μg/mL</td>
    <td>Partial inhibition of viral replication, preventing body weight loss, improving cell survival, viral clearance, and modulation of TNF-α, and producing IFN-γ in bronchoalveolar lavage cells. Increased CD8+ T and CD11c + populations in dendritic cells.</td>
    <td>[
     <xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <italic>P. ginseng</italic>
    </td>
    <td>RSV A2 strain</td>
    <td>Female BALB/c mice</td>
    <td>Oral administration of 25 mg/kg/day for 60 days (250 and 500 μg/ml)</td>
    <td>Modulation of host cellular phenotypes, producing cytokines and ROS and improving cell survival. Suppressed IL-6 and IL-8.</td>
    <td>[
     <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <italic>P. ginseng</italic>
    </td>
    <td>RSV A2 strain</td>
    <td>Human lung epithelial cells (A549 cell)</td>
    <td/>
    <td>KRGE-mediated inhibition of RSV replication, lowering lung viral loads, enhancing level of IFN-γ, reducing ROS and proinflammatory cytokine production, and improving cellular survival.</td>
    <td>[
     <xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Ginsenosides Re, Ref and Rg2</td>
    <td>HRV3</td>
    <td>Human cervix epithelial cell line (HeLa, CCL-2)</td>
    <td>Direct mixing in medium as 0.1, 1, 10, and 100 mg/mL</td>
    <td>PT-type ginsenosides (Rf and Rg2) increased cell viability and decreased susceptibility to viral infection.</td>
    <td>[
     <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn>
   <p>Abbreviations: AI, Avian Influenza; BW, Body weight; CPE, Cell Viability and Cytopathogenic Effect; Cy, cyclophosphamide; GSLS, Ginseng Stem-Leaf Saponins; HEp2, Human Epithelial; IFN-γ, Interferon-Gamma; IgA + cells, Immunoglobulin A-secreting cells; iIELs, Intestinal Intraepithelial Lymphocytes; MHCII KO, Major Histocompatibility Class II Knockout mice; ND, Newcastle Disease; ROS, Reactive Oxygen Species; RSV, Respiratory Syncytial Virus; sIgA, Secretory Immunoglobulin A; TNF-α, Tumor Necrosis Factor-alpha; LPS, lipopolysaccharide; HRV3, human rhinovirus 3; RGE, Red Ginseng extract; BALB, Bagg Albino (inbred research mouse strain); ICR, Institute of Cancer research.</p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
