<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Viral shedding was measured with quantitative RT-PCR on nasopharyngeal swabs taken through the calves’ nostrils. For this purpose, calf nasal swabs collected before infection and daily after infection were extracted in 400 μl of RNALater Stabilization solution (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA). The cell suspension was spun into a pellet in a microcentrifuge at maximum speed for 5 min, the supernatant was removed, and the cell pellet resuspended in 350 μl of Buffer RLT—lysis buffer (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany). Total RNA was extracted from the cell lysate using the RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany), according to the manufacturer’s directions as described elsewhere. [
 <xref rid="pone.0230245.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] Extracted RNA was stored at -80°C until used for further procedures. 10 μl of viral RNA from each sample was used for reverse transcription. cDNA was synthesized using the SuperScript VILO Master Mix (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA), according to the manufacturer’s directions. The reverse transcription thermocycling program consisted of 10 minutes at 25°C, 60 minutes at 42°C, and a termination cycle of 85°C of 5 minutes. Synthesized cDNA was stored at -20°C. The Q-RT-PCR was performed in duplicates on a 384-well plate, in a 20 μl reaction volume. The reaction mixture contained 10 μl PowerUP SYBR Green qPCR master mix (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA), 4 μl of cDNA, 2uL nuclease free water, and 2 μl of each primer in 5 μM concentration, specific to BRSV nucleoprotein: forward primer—
 <monospace>GCAATGCTGCAGGACTAGGTATAAT</monospace> and reverse—
 <monospace>ACACTGTAATTGATGACCCCATTC</monospace>. The RT-PCR thermocycling program consisted of one cycle of 50°C for 2 min and 95°C for 10 minutes, followed by 40 cycles of 95°C for 15 seconds and 60°C for 1 minute. RT-PCR performed using ViiA 7 Real-Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA). As a quantification standard, a supernatant from BRSV-infected bovine turbinate cell culture with virus concentration of 83.5 x10
 <sup>4</sup> plaque-forming units (PFU) per 1 ml was used. RNA from the virus supernatant was extracted using E.Z.N.A. Viral RNA Kit (Omega Bio-tek, Norcross, GA) according to manufacturer’s directions. cDNA synthesis was performed as described above. Five serial 10x dilutions of standard viral cDNA was prepared and PCR amplification was performed together with the test samples as described above. Standard curve fitting and virus quantification was performed using ViiA 7 software (ThermoFisher Scientific, Waltham, MA).
</p>
