<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Both visceral and cutaneous forms occur in SSA, with the former producing serious disease associated with high mortality. Most of the cases of visceral leishmaniasis (VL) occur in the Horn of Africa, i.e., the East African countries of Sudan, Eritrea, Ethiopia, Kenya, and Somalia 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Bern1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, with most of them caused by 
 <italic>Leishmania donovani</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000412-t003">Table 3</xref>), although some cases are caused by 
 <italic>L. infantum</italic>
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Reithinger1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. Because many cases occur in areas of conflict and forced human migrations, the exact number occurring in East Africa is not well established, nor is the disease burden. During the 1980s, an estimated 100,000 people died as a result of VL epidemics 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Reithinger1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. In Sudan alone, as a result of long-standing civil war, hundreds of thousands of cases occurred with death rates exceeding 50% in some areas 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Bern1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. Today, the continuing widespread conflict in these countries has destroyed housing and health care infrastructure, and the resultant forced migrations to endemic areas still promote the emergence of VL 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Reithinger1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. Adding to the problem is widespread malnutrition as a result of drought, which increases susceptibility to infection and contributes to the progression of disease 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Reithinger1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. The highest incidence of the disease occurs in Sudan (especially near part of its border with Ethiopia, where 15,000–20,000 new cases occur annually), followed by Ethiopia with approximately 4,000 new cases (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000412-t002">Table 2</xref>) 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Alvar1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Bern1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. The Pokot territory of Kenya and Uganda is also endemic 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Kolaczinski1" ref-type="bibr">[102]</xref>. In these areas VL is considered primarily an anthroponotic infection 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Alvar2" ref-type="bibr">[103]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Kolaczinski2" ref-type="bibr">[104]</xref>. VL is also an important opportunistic infection associated with HIV/AIDS in East Africa 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Alvar1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, especially in the Tigray region on the Sudan–Eritrea border where soldiers and seasonal workers sleep outdoors in sandfly-infested areas 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Bern1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. Cutaneous leishmaniasis caused by infection with 
 <italic>Leishmania major</italic> is also endemic in parts of SSA including West Africa, where there has been a major increase in the number of cases near Ougadougou, the Burkina Faso capital 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Alvar1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, and in Sudanese refugee camps in Chad 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000412-Bern1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>.
</p>
