<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In general, it is believed that sufficient contact rates between hosts and vectors are required to maintain enzootic transmission of 
 <italic>Y. pestis</italic> and these contact rates are often dependent on host and flea abundances 
 <xref rid="pone.0035598-Eisen6" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. With one exception (
 <italic>M. minutoides</italic>), host abundance was similar between high and low elevation sites. It is unlikely that this difference accounts for significant differences in risk because these mice harbor extremely low numbers of fleas and the diversity of fleas hosted appears to be quite low. Similar abundances were noted both inside and outside the plague focus for at least three small mammal species (
 <italic>R. rattus</italic>, 
 <italic>A. niloticus</italic>, and 
 <italic>Mastomys spp.</italic>) that are known to be susceptible to 
 <italic>Y. pestis</italic> and believed to be important in 
 <italic>Y. pestis</italic> transmission in this and other parts of Africa 
 <xref rid="pone.0035598-Amatre1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0035598-Hopkins3" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0035598-Isaacson1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0035598-Kilonzo2" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0035598-Msangi1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0035598-Njunwa1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0035598-Velimirovic1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. Despite similar abundances of fleas inside and outside the focus, inside the focus, flea diversity was significantly higher than outside, which suggests that increased flea diversity may be important for the maintenance of 
 <italic>Y. pestis</italic> transmission cycles or may be important for transmission to humans. Having multiple species of fleas within a site that are capable of transmitting 
 <italic>Y. pestis</italic> (i.e., 
 <italic>X. cheopis</italic>, 
 <italic>X. brasiliensis</italic>, 
 <italic>C. cabirus</italic>, 
 <italic>S. torvus</italic>, and 
 <italic>D. lypusus</italic>
 <xref rid="pone.0035598-Eisen5" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0035598-Velimirovic1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0035598-Bacot1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0035598-Gratz1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0035598-Pollitzer1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0035598-Davis2" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0035598-Kilonzo3" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>) and that infest hosts that are susceptible to plague infection could increase the likelihood of pathogen persistence during periods when the abundance of any particular host or flea species decreases below levels where persistence would be possible when only a single vector species was present 
 <xref rid="pone.0035598-Laudisoit1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. In other words, the presence of multiple vector species that will infest multiple susceptible host species creates a more connected host network. It is also possible that off-host adult populations of some flea species are able to survive infected for relatively long periods in burrows or nests, thus contributing to the persistence of plague in this region. Alternatively, it is possible that increased flea diversity creates greater connections between zoonotic hosts and humans. Long-term animal-based surveillance could reveal that 
 <italic>Y. pestis</italic> persists in zoonotic cycles at low elevations, most likely in the sylvatic areas outside of our sampling area, but lack of a bridging vector could result in enzootic maintenance of 
 <italic>Y. pestis</italic> but an absence of human plague cases.
</p>
