<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">Yet, pandemics such as COVID-19 are not entirely new phenomena. 
 <italic>Newly emerging</italic> (and 
 <italic>re-emerging</italic>) 
 <italic>infectious diseases</italic> have been threatening humans since the neolithic revolution, 12,000 years ago, when human hunter-gatherers settled into villages to domesticate animals and cultivate crops (
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Dobson and Carper, 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Morens et al., 2020b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Morens et al., 2008a</xref>). These beginnings of domestication were the earliest steps in man’s systematic, widespread manipulation of nature. Ancient emerging zoonotic diseases (see 
 <xref rid="tbox1" ref-type="boxed-text">Box 1</xref> ) with deadly consequences include smallpox, falciparum malaria, measles, and bubonic/pneumonic plague. Some, e.g., the Justinian plague (541 AD) and the Black Death (1348 AD), killed substantial proportions of humans in the “known” world, i.e., the world known to those whose recordings of it survive, predominantly in Asia, the Middle East, and Europe.
 <boxed-text id="tbox1">
  <label>Box 1</label>
  <caption>
   <title>Terms Related to Emerging Infectious Diseases</title>
  </caption>
  <p id="p0300">
   <list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010">
    <list-item id="u0010">
     <p id="p0305">
      <bold>Antigenic immunodominance:</bold> Ability of a protein epitope to elicit an immune response greater than the response to one or more adjacent epitopes
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0015">
     <p id="p0310">
      <bold>Cell tropism:</bold> Ability of a pathogen to infect a particular cell type
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0020">
     <p id="p0315">
      <bold>Endemic:</bold> Noun and adjective denoting prevalence of human infection
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0025">
     <p id="p0320">
      <bold>Enzootic:</bold> Noun and adjective denoting prevalence of animal infection
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0030">
     <p id="p0325">
      <bold>Epidemic, Pandemic:</bold> Noun and adjective denoting highly incident disease (epidemic) or spread that is global or covers very large geographic areas (pandemic)
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0035">
     <p id="p0330">
      <bold>Epizootic, Panzootic:</bold> Noun and adjective analogous to epidemic and pandemic, but with respect to animal diseases
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0040">
     <p id="p0335">
      <bold>Fomite:</bold> An inanimate object that transmits infection, e.g., a towel or doorknob
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0045">
     <p id="p0340">
      <bold>Host-Switching, Spillover:</bold> Process by which a pathogen adapted to one host species becomes adapted to another host species
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0050">
     <p id="p0345">
      <bold>Disease emergence:</bold> Appearance of a disease in a new host
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0055">
     <p id="p0350">
      <bold>Zoonosis:</bold> A human infection caused by an animal pathogen that may be either a dead-end infection or that may initiate person-to-person spread
     </p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
 </boxed-text>
</p>
