<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3394769</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22808012</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-11-12693</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038665</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Computational Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Sequence Analysis</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Origin of Life</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Population Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic Drift</subject><subject>Mutation</subject><subject>Natural Selection</subject><subject>Neutral Theory</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Virology</subject><subj-group><subject>Viral Evolution</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Infectious diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Viral Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Influenza</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Zoonoses</subject><subj-group><subject>Avian influenza A viruses</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Veterinary Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Zoonotic Diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Influenza</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evolutionary History and Phylodynamics of Influenza A and B Neuraminidase (NA) Genes Inferred from Large-Scale Sequence Analyses</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Evolutionary Dynamics of Influenza Neuraminidase</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Jianpeng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>C. Todd</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Christman</surname><given-names>Mary C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rivailler</surname><given-names>Pierre</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Haizhen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Donis</surname><given-names>Ruben O.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Guoqing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>&#x0002a;</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Biology, University of Nebraska at Omaha, Omaha, Nebraska, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Influenza Division, Molecular Virology and Vaccines Branch, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, Georgia, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Chemistry, University of Nebraska at Omaha, Omaha, Nebraska, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Dong-Yan</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Hong Kong, Hong Kong</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>glu3@unomaha.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: GL ROD. Performed the experiments: JX. Analyzed the data: JX CTD HZ PR. Wrote the paper: JX GL ROD MCC CTD HZ PR.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>7</issue><elocation-id>e38665</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>7</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Xu et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Influenza neuraminidase (NA) is an important surface glycoprotein and plays a vital role in viral replication and drug development. The NA is found in influenza A and B viruses, with nine subtypes classified in influenza A. The complete knowledge of influenza NA evolutionary history and phylodynamics, although critical for the prevention and control of influenza epidemics and pandemics, remains lacking.</p></sec><sec><title>Methodology/Principal findings</title><p>Evolutionary and phylogenetic analyses of influenza NA sequences using Maximum Likelihood and Bayesian MCMC methods demonstrated that the divergence of influenza viruses into types A and B occurred earlier than the divergence of influenza A NA subtypes. Twenty-three lineages were identified within influenza A, two lineages were classified within influenza B, and most lineages were specific to host, subtype or geographical location. Interestingly, evolutionary rates vary not only among lineages but also among branches within lineages. The estimated tMRCAs of influenza lineages suggest that the viruses of different lineages emerge several months or even years before their initial detection. The <italic>d</italic>
<sub>N</sub>
<italic>/d</italic>
<sub>S</sub> ratios ranged from 0.062 to 0.313 for influenza A lineages, and 0.257 to 0.259 for influenza B lineages. Structural analyses revealed that all positively selected sites are at the surface of the NA protein, with a number of sites found to be important for host antibody and drug binding.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions/Significance</title><p>The divergence into influenza type A and B from a putative ancestral NA was followed by the divergence of type A into nine NA subtypes, of which 23 lineages subsequently diverged. This study provides a better understanding of influenza NA lineages and their evolutionary dynamics, which may facilitate early detection of newly emerging influenza viruses and thus improve influenza surveillance.</p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="15"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Influenza virus belongs to the viral family Orthomyxoviridae and has a segmented negative-sense RNA genome in an enveloped virion <xref rid="pone.0038665-Smith1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. According to the antigenic properties of nucleoproteins (NP) and matrix proteins (MP), influenza viruses are classified into three types - A, B and C. The microscopic structural features and genome organization of influenza A, B and C viruses suggest that they descended from a common ancestor <xref rid="pone.0038665-Webster1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. The influenza A virus infects a wide variety of bird and mammalian species and can cause moderate to severe epidemics annually and catastrophic pandemics sporadically <xref rid="pone.0038665-Webster1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Nelson1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. The influenza B and C viruses are considered less pathogenic compared with influenza A and are found mainly in humans, although there is increasing evidence that B and C viruses can also infect other species <xref rid="pone.0038665-Osterhaus1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>.</p><p>Genetic mutation is considered one of the most important molecular mechanisms in the evolution of influenza virus <xref rid="pone.0038665-Webster2" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Like most RNA viruses, the influenza virus has low fidelity RNA synthesis, which results in a high mutation rate - around one mutation per genome per replication <xref rid="pone.0038665-Drake1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, several orders of magnitude higher than those in most DNA-based organisms <xref rid="pone.0038665-Holmes1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Evolutionary forces such as natural selection acting upon rapidly mutating viral populations could shape the genetic structure of influenza viruses in different hosts, geographic regions and periods of time <xref rid="pone.0038665-Ghedin1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Ferguson1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Importantly, rapid evolution could partially facilitate the ability of influenza viruses to cross host species barriers and successfully emerge in new hosts with often important public health and/or veterinary health implications. One such example is the Eurasian avian-like H1N1 swine virus, which was first detected in pigs in Belgium in 1979, with all of the eight segments found to be derived from a Eurasian avian H1N1 virus, presumably following adaptive mutation <xref rid="pone.0038665-Pensaert1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>.</p><p>Influenza virus has also shown the propensity to escape immunity because of continuous antigenic drift, i.e., mutation at the epitope positions of HA and NA segments <xref rid="pone.0038665-Bush1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Smith2" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Antigenic drift may often result in structural changes in antigenic sites, which must be recognized by the host immune system in order to suppress viral infection <xref rid="pone.0038665-Plotkin1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. This antigenic drift often requires the update of annual influenza vaccines to assure a match between the vaccine and currently circulating viral strains <xref rid="pone.0038665-Schwartz1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Additionally, influenza viruses undergo more dramatic antigenic changes, known as antigenic shifts, which occur following reassortment between different subtypes of influenza viruses within a single host <xref rid="pone.0038665-Webster1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>.</p><p>Each of the influenza viral genes is thought to be important in viral replication and interaction with host cells; therefore, understanding the evolutionary tempo and mode of each viral gene can provide new insight into the epidemiology of influenza viruses <xref rid="pone.0038665-Fourment1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Furuse1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Among the eight segments, neuraminidase (NA) is of particular significance. NA is a major surface glycoprotein of influenza A and B, but does not occur in influenza C <xref rid="pone.0038665-Nerome1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. It plays a key role in virus replication by removing sialic acids from the host cell surface and thus releasing newly formed virions <xref rid="pone.0038665-Palese1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. Drugs that inhibit this NA activity, known as neuraminidase inhibitors, are often used for the treatment of influenza <xref rid="pone.0038665-Bloom1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. However, drug resistance mutations (e.g., H275Y) have been broadly observed in epidemic viruses <xref rid="pone.0038665-RameixWelti1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>.</p><p>Influenza A viral neuraminidases are classified into nine subtypes (N1&#x02013;N9) according to their antigenic properties, whereas influenza B neuraminidases are classified into two lineages <xref rid="pone.0038665-Chi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. Previous phylogenetic analyses of influenza viral NA sequences have provided important insight into understanding the evolution of influenza viruses; however, these studies mainly focused on either specific types or subtypes <xref rid="pone.0038665-Fourment1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Reid1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Xu1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. A global perspective of the evolutionary history of influenza NA genes and their spatial, temporal, and host associations remain lacking. In addition, evolutionary rates of influenza viral genes were estimated (&#x0223c;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> substitution/site/year) in previous studies <xref rid="pone.0038665-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Vijaykrishna1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Chen2" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>; however, only the average values across all branches were presented. It is unlikely the evolutionary rates are the same in all branches within a phylogenetic tree. The investigation of rate variations among different branches is thus of significant importance in understanding the interior evolutionary behavior of the influenza virus. Moreover, selection pressure and positive/negative selection sites were described in previous studies <xref rid="pone.0038665-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Chen2" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, but only a small number of representative sequences were selected for the estimations. Finally, the structural analysis of positively selected amino acid sites, although essential for the development of antiviral drugs and vaccines, has largely been neglected in previous studies. In this study, we employed all influenza NA sequences available in public repositories and conducted large-scale evolutionary, phylodynamic and structural analyses to address the above issues.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Global Picture of Evolutionary Relationships of Influenza A and B Neuraminidase (NA) Genes</title><p>The Maximum Likelihood (ML) and MCMC Bayesian analyses demonstrate that the influenza NA gene diverged first into A and B (Group I and Group II), followed by the division of influenza A subtypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g001">Figure 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038665.s018">File S1</xref>). The monophylic origin of influenza A and influenza B was strongly supported by the bootstrap values (100&#x00025;). Within influenza A, two subgroups were found, one consisting of subtype N2, N3, N6, N7 and N9 (Subgroup I) and the other consisting of the remaining four subtypes, N1, N4, N5 and N8 (Subgroup II) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Each subgroup consists of viruses independently adapted to the avian, human, equine and swine hosts, indicating that parallel evolution occurred in these two subgroups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g001">Figure 1</xref>). In addition, each of the nine influenza A NA subtypes was found to form a distinct cluster with a high bootstrap support value (&#x0003e;90&#x00025;), indicating a monophyletic origin for each subtype.</p><fig id="pone-0038665-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038665.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Phylogeny of influenza A and B neuraminidase (NA) genes.</title><p>Influenza NA genes form two groups (Group I and Group II), which correspond to influenza A and B, respectively. Influenza A NA is further classified into two subgroups (Subgroup I and Subgroup II). The viral strains are colored for different hosts: human in green, swine in blue, avian in red and equine in purple. The bootstrap support values are indicated at major nodes. The scale bar at the bottom indicates the numbers of nucleotide substitutions per site.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0038665.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Phylogeny of Neuraminidase (NA) Genes within Influenza A and B Viruses</title><p>A total of 23 lineages, two to three lineages for each subtype, were identified within influenza A viruses, while two lineages were classified within influenza B (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038665-t001">Table 1</xref>). Lineages 1A and 2A were further divided into five and three sublineages, respectively. Human lineages were found in influenza A N1 and N2 subtypes and influenza B, swine lineages in N1 and N2, equine lineages in N7 and N8, and avian lineages in all influenza A subtypes. In addition, avian lineages were found to have more combinations of HA and NA compared with mammalian lineages.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0038665-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038665.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>The annotations, isolation periods, representative sequences and subtypes for the NA lineages.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0038665-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0038665.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Influenza</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subtype</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lineage/Sublineage</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annotation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isolationperiod</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Representative sequence</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Main virus subtypes</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>A</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1A.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H5N1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1996&#x02013;2010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/Goose/Guangdong/1/96(H5N1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H5N1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1A.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eurasian avian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1934&#x02013;2009</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/fowl/Rostock/45/1934(H7N1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H1N1, H3N1, H5N1, H6N1, H7N1,H9N1, H11N1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1A.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pandemic H1N1 2009</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2009&#x02013;2010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/Texas/05/2009(H1N1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H1N1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1A.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eurasian (avian-like) swine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1979&#x02013;2010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/swine/Belgium/WVL1/1979</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H1N1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1A.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North American avian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1969&#x02013;2008</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/duck/PA/486/1969(H6N1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H1N1, H3N1,H4N1, H5N1, H6N1,H10N1, H12N1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North American swine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1930&#x02013;2009</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/swine/Iowa/15/1930(H1N1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H1N1, H3N1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major human</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1918&#x02013;2009</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/Brevig_Mission/1/18(H1N1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H1N1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2A.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H9N2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1994&#x02013;2009</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/chicken/Guangdong/SS/94</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H9N2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2A.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eurasian avian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1977&#x02013;2008</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/duck/Hokkaido/5/1977</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H3N2, H5N2, H6N2, H7N2, H9N2, H11N2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2A.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North American avian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1966&#x02013;2008</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/turkey/Wisconsin/1/1966(H9N2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H3N2, H4N2,H5N2, H6N2, H7N2, H9N2, H11N2, H10N2, H13N2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Major human and swine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1957&#x02013;2009</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/Japan/305/1957</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H3N2, H2N2, H1N2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North American avian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1971&#x02013;2010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/turkey/Oregon/1971(H7N3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H7N3, H4N3, H1N3, H10N3, H11N3,H6N3, H5N3, H3N3, H2N3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eurasian/Oceanian avian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1959&#x02013;2009</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/shearwater/Australia/751/1975(H5N3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H1N3, H5N3, H4N3, H3N3, H8N3, H12N3, H7N3, H2N3, H10N3, H11N3, H9N3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other avian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1975&#x02013;2009</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/sabines gull/Alaska/296/1975(H5N3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H7N3, H16N3, H3N3, H13N3, H5N3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North American avian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1967&#x02013;2010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/turkey/Ontario/6118/1967(H8N4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H3N4, H8N4, H12N4, H4N4, H2N4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eurasian/Oceanian avian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1979&#x02013;2008</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/gray teal/Australia/2/1979(H4N4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H4N4, H8N4, H9N4,H10N4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North American avian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1976&#x02013;2009</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/mallard duck/ALB/60/1976(H12N5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H12N5, H1N5, H11N5, H3N5, H6N5,H4N5, H5N5, H2N5, H9N5, H10N5, H7N5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eurasian/Oceanian avian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1972&#x02013;2009</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/shearwater/Australia/1/1972(H6N5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H6N5, H1N5, H3N5, H8N5, H10N5,H12N5, H4N5, H14N5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North American avian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1976&#x02013;2010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/mallard duck/ALB/20/1976(H4N6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H3N6, H4N6, H10N6, H6N6, H1N6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eurasian/Oceanian avian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1956&#x02013;2010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/duck/Czech Republic/1/1956(H4N6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H4N6, H3N6, H5N6, H9N6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North American avian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1977&#x02013;2010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/mallard duck/ALB/302/1977 (H10N7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H4N7, H10N7, H3N7, H2N7, H7N7,H5N7, H8N7, H13N7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eurasian/Oceanian avian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1902&#x02013;2008</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/chicken/Brescia/1902(H7N7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H7N7, H10N7, H5N7, H11N7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Equine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1956&#x02013;1977</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/equine/Prague/1/1956(H7N7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H7N7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North American avian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1963&#x02013;2010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/turkey/Canada/1963(H6N8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H3N8, H4N8, H6N8, H7N8, H2N8, H10N8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Equine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1963&#x02013;2010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/equine/Miami/1/1963(H3N8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H3N8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eurasian/Oceanian avian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1963&#x02013;2010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/duck/Ukraine/1/1963(H3N8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H3N8, H10N8, H11N8, H6N8, H7N8,H2N8,H4N8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North American avian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1966&#x02013;2008</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/turkey/Ontario/7732/1966 (H5N9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H11N9, H13N9, H12N9, H5N9, H10N9,H3N9, H2N9, H1N9, H7N9, H4N9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eurasian/Oceanian avian I</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1996&#x02013;2010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/duck/Siberia/700/1996(H11N9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H11N9, H5N9, H7N9, H6N9, H2N9, H1N9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eurasian/Oceanian avian II</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1978&#x02013;2004</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A/duck/Hong Kong/278/1978(H2N9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H11N9, H5N9, H15N9, H10N9, H2N9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>B</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yam88</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B/Yamagata/16/88-like</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1988&#x02013;2009</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B/Yamagata/16/1988</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vic77</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B/Victoria/2/87-like</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1987&#x02013;2002</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B/Victoria/2/1987</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><sec id="s2b1"><title>Lineage analyses of influenza A N1 genes</title><p>Three lineages, 1A, 1B and 1C, were identified based upon strong bootstrap support values (100&#x00025;) of the phylogenetic tree, which was generated from 4,146 sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g002">Figure 2</xref>-A, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038665-t001">Table 1</xref>). The genetic distances between lineages ranged from 0.191 to 0.238. Lineage 1A is a major avian lineage, which is further divided into five sublineages: 1A.1 (H5N1), 1A.2 (Eurasian avian), 1A.3 (Pandemic H1N1 2009), 1A.4 (Eurasian avian-like swine) and 1A.5 (North American avian).</p><fig id="pone-0038665-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038665.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Maximum-likelihood (ML) tree of influenza A NA subtypes.</title><p>A: N1; B: N2; C: N5; D: N8. The annotation for each lineage was labeled on the trees. Three lineages in N1 (1A, 1B and 1C), two lineages in N2 (2A and 2B), two lineages in N5 (5A and 5B), and two lineages in N8 (8A and 8B) were classified. The bootstrap values supporting the corresponding lineages are shown to the left of the major nodes. Scale bars indicate the numbers of nucleotide substitutions per site.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0038665.g002"/></fig><p>Sublineage 1A.1 originated from the recent highly pathogenic H5N1 avian influenza epizootic that started in Asia around 1996 and has spread throughout the Eastern Hemisphere. The viruses in 1A.1 are mostly from birds (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;1,031), but some are from humans (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;164), swine (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;8), tigers (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2) and mink (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;1). Sublineage 1A.2 is composed of mostly Eurasian avian influenza viruses (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;230), whereas some human highly pathogenic H5N1 influenza viruses (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;24) sampled in 1997 in Hong Kong were also found in 1A.2. Sublineage 1A.4 consists of Eurasian swine influenza viruses which were originally derived from Eurasian avian viruses and first detected in Belgium in 1979. Not surprisingly, 1A.3 (Pandemic H1N1 2009) is grouped together with Eurasian swine, which confirms previous findings that the NA segment of pandemic H1N1 2009 viruses originated from the Eurasian swine influenza viruses. Sublineage 1A.5 is composed of viruses mainly from North American avian species (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;162), with a few exceptions: 1 viral sequence from human and 3 from environmental samples.</p><p>Lineage 1B consists of mainly North American swine influenza viruses, while 1C is a human lineage, consisting mainly of H1N1 human influenza viruses. The viruses in 1B correspond mostly to the classical H1N1 isolates from swine (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;126), but include 9 isolates from humans and 9 from birds, indicating sporadic interspecies transmissions of influenza viruses from swine to humans or birds. Lineage 1C consists predominantly of human viruses (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;1204), with a few exceptions, namely, swine (4 isolates) and birds (2 isolates). Within the influenza A N1 subtype, avian influenza viruses include sequences from multiple HA subtypes (e.g., H1N1, H3N1, H5N1, H6N1, H7N1, H9N1, and H11N1), whereas human and swine viruses have limited HA subtypes (human: H1N1; swine: H1N1, H3N1).</p></sec><sec id="s2b2"><title>Lineage analyses of influenza A N2 genes</title><p>The N2 sequences (3,754 in total) were classified into two major lineages, 2A and 2B (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g002">Figure 2</xref>-B, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038665-t001">Table 1</xref>). The genetic distance between lineages 2A and 2B was estimated to be 0.204. Lineage 2A is a major avian lineage whereas 2B consists of mainly mammalian (i.e., human and swine) influenza viruses. Three sublineages were further classified in 2A, 2A.1 for H9N2, 2A.2 for Eurasian avian, and 2A.3 for North American avian.</p><p>The 2A.1 is a subtype-specific sublineage consisting of mainly H9N2 avian influenza viruses, with the majority from birds (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;412), but with 24 sequences from swine and 4 from humans, which indicates the occurrence of interspecies transmissions. The 2A.2 and 2A.3 correspond to Eurasian and North American avian viruses, respectively. The viruses of 2A.2 are mainly from birds (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;342), but a few are from swine (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;7) and humans (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2). A similar result was also found in 2A.3, which includes 291 avian viruses, 1 H7N2 human virus, and 29 viruses isolated from environmental samples.</p><p>Within 2B, most of the influenza viruses are from human H2N2 and H3N2 influenza viruses (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2,340) and swine H3N2 and H1N2 viruses (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;214). However, avian influenza H3N2 viruses (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;11) were also found in this lineage. Interestingly, there were five major clades of swine influenza viruses scattered within lineage 2B, suggesting these viruses originate from human viruses through either genome reassortment or direct transmission events. It is also noted that the branch lengths of the swine clusters are much longer as compared to those of the closely related human viruses, indicating extensive evolution of the N2 gene in swine viruses after transmission from humans to swine.</p></sec><sec id="s2b3"><title>Lineage analyses of influenza A N3&#x02013;N9 genes</title><p>Three lineages, 3A, 3B, and 3C, were found in N3, with genetic distances between lineages ranging from 0.173 to 0.349 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038665-t001">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038665.s001">Figure S1</xref>). Lineage 3A consists mainly of North American avian viruses (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;173), but includes several avian strains from South America (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;8). In addition, within lineage 3A, 166 sequences were isolated from avian, 4 from swine, 1 from human, and 9 from environmental samples. Lineage 3B is a Eurasian/Oceanian avian lineage, while 3C is also an avian lineage, but does not show any geographical pattern. Lineage 3B and 3C were all composed of avian influenza viruses.</p><p>The N4, N5 and N6 subtypes were each classified into two lineages, one corresponding to North American avian (4A, 5A and 6A) and the other Eurasian/Oceanian avian (4B, 5B and 6B) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038665-t001">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038665.s002">Figure S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g002">Figure 2</xref>-C, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038665.s003">Figure S3</xref>). The genetic distance between lineages was estimated to be 0.198 for N4, 0.254 for N5, and 0.250 for N6 viruses, respectively. All N4 and N5 viruses are from avian species. Lineage 6A is composed mainly of North American avian viruses (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;336), with a few exceptions (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2) from Asia avian viruses. Lineage 6B consists mainly of Eurasian/Oceanian avian viruses (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;121), but contains 6 avian viruses from North America.</p><p>Three lineages were identified in N7 and N8, which correspond to North American avian (7A, 8A), equine (7C, 8B) and Eurasian/Oceanian avian (7B, 8C), respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038665-t001">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038665.s004">Figure S4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g002">Figure 2</xref>-D). For N9, 3 lineages were identified: 9A, 9B and 9C, which correspond to North American avian, Eurasian/Oceanian avian I and Eurasian/Oceanian avian II, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038665-t001">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038665.s005">Figure S5</xref>). The genetic distances between lineages were found in the range from 0.297 to 0.320 for N7, from 0.269 to 0.298 for N8, and from 0.117 to 0.224 for N9, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s2b4"><title>Lineage analyses of influenza B neuraminidase (NA) genes</title><p>The NA genes of influenza B viruses were divided into two distinct lineages, B/Victoria/2/87-like (Vic87) and B/Yamagata/16/88-like (Yam88) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g003">Figure 3</xref>). All influenza B viruses were found from humans, with no obvious geographical separation in either lineage. The genetic distance between Vic87 and Yam88 lineages was estimated to be 0.06.</p><fig id="pone-0038665-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038665.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Maximum-likelihood (ML) tree of influenza B NA genes.</title><p>Two lineages, Yam88 and Vic87, were classified. The bootstrap values supporting the corresponding lineages are shown on the major nodes. The scale bars indicate the numbers of nucleotide substitutions per site.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0038665.g003"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Substitution Rates and Times of Most Recent Common Ancestor (tMRCAs) of Influenza A and B NA Lineages</title><p>Outliers were identified and removed before the estimation of substitution rate and tMRCA for each lineage (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038665.s017">Table S1</xref>). The mean substitution rate and 95&#x00025; HPD range for each lineage are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038665-t002">Table 2</xref>. Our results demonstrated that the mean substitution rates estimated under random local clock (RLC) model were generally lower than the corresponding rates estimated under uncorrelated exponential relaxed clock (UCED) model (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038665-t002">Table 2</xref>). In the following, we present the results based upon the RLC model, a new model that can reveal the rate heterogeneity among branches.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0038665-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038665.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Substitutions rates and tMRCAs of different lineages for influenza A and B NA genes<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">&#x0002a;</xref>.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0038665-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0038665.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Influenza</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subtype</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lineage/Sublineage</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Substitution rate (&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> subs/site/year)</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">tMRCA (calendar year)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95&#x00025;HPD lower</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95&#x00025; HPD upper</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95&#x00025; HPD lower</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95&#x00025; HPD upper</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>A</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1A.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.06/3.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63/3.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48/4.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1988/1992</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1984/1987</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1992/1996</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1A.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.42/4.07</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.03/3.43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.79/4.74</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1927/1931</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1922/1923</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1931/1934</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1A.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.83/3.58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63/2.52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.96/4.67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19-Nov-08/</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7-June-08/</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16-Mar-09/</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7-Dec-08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12-Jun-08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30-Mar-09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1A.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.62/3.96</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.23/3.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.99/4.58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1978/1977</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1977/1974</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1979/1979</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1A.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00/4.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.69/3.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.36/4.99</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1921/1950</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1911/1920</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1934/1967</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.55/2.97</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25/2.58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.83/3.37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1929/1927</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1928/1923</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1930/1930</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79/2.44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42/2.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14/2.89</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1898/1910</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1882/1896</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1909/1918</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2A.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.45/4.61</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.07/3.98</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.89/5.24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1990/1989</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1989/1984</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1991/1993</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2A.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.53/2.81</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25/2.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.81/3.26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1974/1972</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1971/1963</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1976/1977</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2A.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.96/3.19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.66/2.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.26/3.68</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1951/1954</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1945/1937</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1957/1965</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.05/3.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.74/2.91</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.89/3.75</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1956/1956</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1955/1954</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1957/1957</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.92/3.23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6/2.61</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.27/3.83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1954/1959</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1944/1941</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1963/1971</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.67/2.96</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39/2.43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.04/3.47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1955/1950</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1950/1933</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1957/1959</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.22/3.91</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63/1.78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.85/5.96</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1955/1956</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1949/1926</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1961/1975</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.37/4.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.82/3.39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.93/5.27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1964/1966</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1962/1962</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1967/1967</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.78/4.42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.09/2.75</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5/5.98</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1970/1970</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1966/1956</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1973/1978</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.88/3.63</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.47/2.92</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.27/4.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1971/1972</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1968/1965</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1975/1976</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.68/3.61</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.07/2.21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.34/4.81</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1953/1964</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1941/1945</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1963/1972</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1/2.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.88/1.86</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3/2.79</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1960/1955</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1956/1934</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1963/1970</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.69/3.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39/2.55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97/3.63</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1943/1940</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1940/1920</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1946/1952</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8/4.87</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.33/4.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.33/5.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1975/1975</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1974/1972</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1976/1977</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.99/3.97</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.52/2.94</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46/4.91</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1892/1899</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1882/1892</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1901/1901</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.65/3.13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08/1.90</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.88/4.43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1952/1955</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1940/1952</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1956/1956</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54/2.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36/1.93</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73/2.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1930/1956</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1915/1941</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1940/1963</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;/1.68</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;/1.37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;/2.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;/1954</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;/1945</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;/1961</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1/2.13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86/1.52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35/2.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1921/1946</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1904/1923</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1937/1961</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8/3.36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.49/2.77</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.13/3.92</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1960/1961</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1957/1952</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1962/1966</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.75/3.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.19/2.41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.39/4.21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1994/1995</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1992/1992</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1996/1996</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;/2.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;/0.24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;/3.95</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;/1948</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;/1890</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;/1977</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>B</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yam88</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30/2.47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.99/2.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.62/2.85</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1986/1986</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1985/1982</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1987/1988</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vic87</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90/2.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50/1.65</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3/2.62</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1985/1985</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1983/1982</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1987/1987</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>&#x0002a;</label><p>Values calculated based upon the random local clock model/values calculated based upon the uncorrelated exponential relaxed clock model; Dash signs (-) indicate missing data.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The Bayesian consensus tree for each lineage, along with posterior mean branch lengths scaled in real time, is depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g004">Figure 4</xref>. To reflect the rate variation, we colored branches by their posterior mean relative rate of nucleotide substitution. Blue branches reflect a slow substitution rate, whereas red branches indicate rapid change. For H5N1, the mean substitution rate was estimated to be 3.06&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> subs/site/year (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038665-t002">Table 2</xref>), with a low rate (1.5&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>) found in earlier branches (blue) and a high rate (4.20&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>) in later branches (red) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g004">Figure 4</xref>-A). In contrast, N1 genes of North American swine viruses have a mean rate of 2.55&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>, with a decrease in rates during evolution: a high rate (3.2&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>) in earlier branches (red) and a low rate (0.9&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>) in later branches (blue) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g004">Figure 4</xref>-B). It is noted that human H1N1 viruses were found to evolve at two different rates in two circulation periods, with a low rate (1.3&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>) during 1918&#x02013;1957 (blue) and a high rate (2.9&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>) after 1977 (red) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g004">Figure 4</xref>-C).</p><fig id="pone-0038665-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038665.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Bayesian inferences of random local clocks on influenza NA genes.</title><p>A: H5N1 (1A.1), B: North American swine N1 (1B), C: Human H1N1 (1C), D: H9N2 (2A.1), E: Equine N7 (7C), F: Yama88 influenza B NA (Yama88). Branch coloring indicates inferred rates of nucleotide substitution from blue (slow) to red (fast). The scale bar indicates the number of years before the present.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0038665.g004"/></fig><p>The H9N2 lineage was found to have a mean substitution rate of 4.45&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038665-t002">Table 2</xref>), with a constant rate of 4.9&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> in the majority of branches (red) and a low rate (2.6&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>) in a small number of branches (blue) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g004">Figure 4</xref>-D). The substitution rates with the equine N7 lineage decreased from earlier branches (red) (3.4&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>) to late branches (blue) (1.6&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>) and averaged at 2.65&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g004">Figure 4</xref>-E). The influenza B Yama88 viruses has a mean substitution rate of 2.3&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038665-t002">Table 2</xref>), with a consistent rate of 2.4&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> in the majority of branches (red) and a rate of 1.5&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup> in a small number of branches (blue) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g004">Figure 4</xref>-F). Different rate heterogeneity patterns were also found in other lineages (Data available from authors on request).</p><p>The time of most recent common ancestor (tMRCA) varies from lineage to lineage (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038665-t002">Table 2</xref>). The tMRCA for human H1N1 (1C), which includes viruses causing the 1918 Spanish Flu, was dated to 1898 and the 95&#x00025; HPD interval was between 1882 and 1909. The tMRCA of H5N1viruses (1A.1) was estimated to be at 1988 (95&#x00025; HPD: 1984&#x02013;1992), eight years before the outbreak of H5N1 avian virus in 1996 in Asia. For 1A.2 (Eurasian avian in N1), the tMRCA was estimated to be at 1927 (95&#x00025; HPD: 1922&#x02013;1931), with the earliest sampling time being 1934. For the pandemic H1N1 2009 (1A.3), it can be dated back to Nov 19, 2008 (95&#x00025; HPD: June 7, 2008&#x02013; Mar 16, 2009). The most recent common ancestor of the Eurasian (avian-like) swine (1A.4) can be dated back to 1978 (95&#x00025; HPD: 1977&#x02013;1979), one year earlier than the first detection of this lineage in 1979. For lineage 2B, the tMRCA was dated to 1956 (95&#x00025; HPD: 1955&#x02013;1957), one year before the occurrence of human H2N2 in 1957. The tMRCAs for other lineages are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038665-t002">Table 2</xref> and the MCC trees are available from the authors upon request. The above results suggest that pandemic or epidemic viruses emerged several months or several years before their initial detection, indicating the crucial role for enhanced surveillance of newly emerging viruses.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Selection of Influenza A and B Neuraminidase Lineages</title><p>Different selection pressures were revealed in different lineages as indicated by the ratio of non-synonymous (<italic>d</italic>
<sub>N</sub>) to synonymous (<italic>d</italic>
<sub>S</sub>) substitutions per site (<italic>d</italic>
<sub>N</sub>
<italic>/d</italic>
<sub>S</sub>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038665-t003">Table 3</xref>). Within influenza A, the highest <italic>d<sub>N</sub>/d<sub>S</sub></italic> ratio was observed in 2B - human N2 lineage (0.313), which was slightly higher than that of 8B - equine N8 lineage (0.281), 1C - human N1 lineage (0.261), 1A.1 - H5N1 (0.274) and 2A.1- H9N2 (0.252), most likely reflecting host immune selection pressure, as a result of continuous circulation within the respective hosts and/or vaccination. The lineages under the most purifying selection were lineage 9C (0.068), 4B (0.062) and 5B (0.078). In comparison, the <italic>d<sub>N</sub>/d<sub>S</sub></italic> ratios for influenza B lineages were comparable: 0.259 for Yam88 and 0.257 for Vic87.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0038665-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038665.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Evidence of positive selection using the SLAC, FEL and IFEL methods with a significance level of 0.05.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0038665-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0038665.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Influenza</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subtype</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lineages/Sublineage</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. ofsequences</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SLAC</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FEL</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IFEL</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>d</italic>
<sub>N</sub>
<italic>/d</italic>
<sub>S</sub>(95&#x00025; CI)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>A</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1A.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1241</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16, 46, 83, 313, 340, 365</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8, 339, 434</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8, 16,46, 76, 339</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.274 (0.262&#x02013;0.286)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1A.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">263</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">460</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20, 105, 460</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20, 105, 454</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.202 (0.186&#x02013;0.219)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1A.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">794</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53, 388, 452</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.227 (0.206&#x02013;0.249)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1A.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.180 (0.163&#x02013;0.197)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1A.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">449</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95, 449</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.148 (0.135&#x02013;0.162)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46, 53, 75, 81, 339</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46, 53, 339, 453</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.174 (0.158&#x02013;0.192)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1210</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84, 222, 248</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19, 84, 151, 222, 248, 319, 365</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59, 222, 248, 344, 365</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.261 (0.249&#x02013;0.274)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2A.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">586</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9, 43, 50, 141, 199, 356</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20, 43, 141, 199, 356</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20, 43, 141, 199, 356</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.252 (0.240&#x02013;0.264)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2A.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.174 (0.162&#x02013;0.186)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2A.3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">328</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">356, 416</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113, 356, 414, 416</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">356, 414, 416</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.218 (0.204&#x02013;0.233)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2169</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5, 43, 56, 120, 126,148, 151, 370, 434</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5, 43, 44, 56, 120, 126, 147,148, 151, 370, 434</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43, 56, 127, 147, 267, 332,358, 370, 392, 455</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.313 (0.301&#x02013;0.326)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">413, 432, 457</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">413</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.130 (0.115&#x02013;0.146)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">413</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52, 413</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.161 (0.145&#x02013;0.178)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.092 (0.074&#x02013;0.113)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.081 (0.065&#x02013;0.100)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062 (0.047&#x02013;0.080)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30, 282</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30, 282</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.140 (0.122&#x02013;0.160)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.078 (0.061&#x02013;0.097)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">172</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.111 (0.100&#x02013;0.123)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.114 (0.100&#x02013;0.129)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.153 (0.132&#x02013;0.176)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.092 (0.079&#x02013;0.107)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.135 (0.091&#x02013;0.191)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">265</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">265</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">265, 376</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.128 (0.118&#x02013;0.138)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.281 (0.242&#x02013;0.323)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35, 41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.129 (0.114&#x02013;0.145)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.095 (0.082&#x02013;0.109)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.106 (0.081&#x02013;0.136)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9C</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.068 (0.047&#x02013;0.095)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>B</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yam88</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">565</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42, 65, 248, 373</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65, 248, 345, 373, 395</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42, 65, 248, 373, 389, 436</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.259 (0.238&#x02013;0.281)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vic87</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">345</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106, 345</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.257 (0.215&#x02013;0.305)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>Position relative to the start codon.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Human lineages were found to have the largest numbers of positively selected sites, with 16 sites for the human N2 lineage (2B), 9 sites for human H1N1 lineage (1C), and 8 sites for Yam88 lineage (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038665-t003">Table 3</xref>). In addition, H5N1 (1A.1) and H9N2 (2A.1), have 10 and 7 positively selected sites, respectively. No positive selection sites were detected in lineages 3C, 6B, 7A, 7C, 8B, and 9A&#x02013;9C. Other lineages were found to have one to six sites under positive selection.</p><p>Protein structure analyses revealed all the positively selected sites were located at the surface of the NA protein and pertained to antibody binding and/or interactions with the sugar molecules of host cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g005">Figure 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038665.s006">Figures S6</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038665.s007">S7</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038665.s008">S8</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038665.s009">S9</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038665.s010">S10</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038665.s011">S11</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038665.s012">S12</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038665.s013">S13</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038665.s014">S14</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038665.s015">S15</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038665.s016">S16</xref>). In addition, a number of positively selected sites reside in regions of the NA protein where neuraminidase inhibitors have been known to bind, indicating strong selection in influenza viruses with molecular markers predictive of antiviral resistance.</p><fig id="pone-0038665-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038665.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>The structures and positive selection sites of human influenza neuraminidase.</title><p>A: Influenza A human N1 neuraminidase (1C) (A/Brevig Mission/1/18 H1N1, 1918 &#x0201c;Spanish flu&#x0201d;, PDB ID: 3B7E); B: Influenza A human N2 neuraminidase (2B) (A/Tokyo/3/67 H2N2, 1967, PDB ID: 1IVG); C: Influenza B viral neuraminidase for Yam88 (B/Perth/211/2001, PDB ID: 3K36); D: Influenza B viral neuraminidase for Vic87 (B/Perth/211/2001, PDB ID: 3K36). The positive selection sites are denoted as green balls. Structural regions are denoted in different colors: yellow for alpha-helices, red for beta sheets, and blue for loops.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0038665.g005"/></fig><p>In the human H1N1 lineage (1C), amino acid positions 151, 222 and 344 were found to be under a strong positive selection, and the amino acids in these appear to interact with the NA inhibitor &#x02013; zanamivir, a drug molecule according to the NA structure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g005">Figure 5</xref>-A). In addition, positively selected sites 344 and 365 are located in the B-cell antigenic regions. The amino acid position 319 in human H1N1 lineage, identified to be under positive selection, forms a hydrogen bond with position 379, whose backbone carbonyl is involved in interactions with calcium ions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g005">Figure 5</xref>-A). This Ca<sup>2&#x0002b;</sup> ion interacts with positions 379, 389, 387, 382, and 381, forming H-bonds with position 385 and position 383. These interactions are crucial in protein folding to create the appropriate tertiary structure for sialic acid binding (which allows the NA to cleave the sialic acid) or for NA inhibitor binding.</p><p>With regard to another human lineage (2B), positions 126 and 127 were found to be within the binding pocket of influenza A virus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g005">Figure 5</xref>-B). These two residues, along with residues 120 and 151 were found to be under positive selection. All these sites fold in close proximity to each other, providing a hydrogen-bond network that is essential for NA inhibitor binding. Specifically, position 151 forms a hydrogen bond to position 75, which itself is predicted to bind to zanamivir.</p><p>For human influenza B, positions 42, 65, 248, 345, 373, 389, 395, and 436 were found to be under positive selection (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038665-t003">Table 3</xref>). The crystal structure of the B/Perth/211/2011 virus NA region with zanamivir, oseltamivir, or peramivir showed that residues 373 and 374 participated in drug binding, while residue 345 is involved in calcium binding and dimerization of two NA monomers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g005">Figure 5</xref>-C, D).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Evolution of Influenza Viral NA Genes - Types, Subtypes and Lineages</title><p>The ML and Bayesian MCMC analyses revealed that the divergence of influenza A and B NA genes occurred earlier than the divergence of influenza A NA subtypes. Similar findings were reported for the hemagglutinin (HA) genes <xref rid="pone.0038665-Suzuki1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, in which influenza A and B HA genes were found to diverge first, followed by the division of influenza A HA subtypes. Interestingly, within influenza A, both subgroups (I and II) consist mainly of human, swine, avian, and equine viruses and show similar patterns of host-specific lineage composition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g006">Figure 6</xref>). This strongly supports the hypothesis that subgroup I and II viruses experienced parallel evolution due to similar rates of genetic mutation and adaption to host environments <xref rid="pone.0038665-Webster1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Holmes1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>.</p><fig id="pone-0038665-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038665.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>The evolutionary dynamics of influenza neuraminidase (NA) over time.</title><p>The lineages from different hosts are colored, with the emergence times of the lineages represented by the horizontal positions of squared boxes and the mean substitution rates depicted by the degree of line thickness. Note that within 2A there are five swine clusters.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0038665.g006"/></fig><p>In this study, 23 NA lineages were determined within influenza A based upon both theoretical (e.g., phylogenetic tree topology) and empirical criteria (e.g., pandemic events). The majority of lineages were found to be specific in hosts, or geographical locations, with a genetic distance around 0.2, ranging from 0.117 to 0.349. These results are generally consistent with previous findings <xref rid="pone.0038665-Webster1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Brown1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, but our study relies on a much larger dataset (focusing on the NA segment) and illustrates more detailed evolutionary dynamics of the influenza A NA lineages.</p><p>Classification and designation of the lineages and sublineages within the influenza A virus are essential for studies of viral evolution, ecology and epidemiology. However, how to accurately identify an evolutionary lineage of influenza A viruses is challenging. Whether the naming system will be accepted and used by influenza researchers is even more challenging. To trace the evolutionary change of highly pathogenic avian influenza (HPAI) viruses, a hierarchical nomenclature system for HPAI hemagglutinin clades and sub-clades has been implemented by the WHO/OIE/FAO H5N1 Evolution Working Group and widely adapted by the research community <xref rid="pone.0038665-Group1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. The work presented here is one of the first steps toward the development of a nomenclature system for influenza A virus lineages (at the segment level) and genotypes (at the genome level). We will incorporate the findings of lineages and genotypes into our FluGenome database for the detection of newly emerging viral lineages and genome reassortment, which will improve influenza surveillance <xref rid="pone.0038665-Lu1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Substitution Rate Heterogeneity within Influenza NA Lineages</title><p>It is notable that substitution rates are not the same across all branches within a phylogenetic tree. The relaxed clock model was developed to cope with this issue. An average rate across all branches in the tree is estimated under relaxed clock model in BEAST with 95&#x00025; HPDs summarized from average rates, which are estimated from the sampled trees <xref rid="pone.0038665-Drummond1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. The 95&#x00025; HPDs thus reflect the topological uncertainty among the sampled trees, but do not show the rate variation across different branches within a tree. In previous studies, the relaxed clock model was used to estimate the substitution rate and 95&#x00025; HPDs and the resulting values were used for comparison <xref rid="pone.0038665-Fourment1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Vijaykrishna1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Chen2" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. In fact, such comparison is less accurate. For example, if a phylogenetic tree is mixed with branches of very high and low rates, it might result in an average rate that is similar to that from another tree with branches of a constant rate. We cannot simply conclude the two virus lineages evolve at the same rate. Using the random local clock (RLC), we not only computed the mean substitution rate and 95&#x00025; HPDs but also estimated rate heterogeneity among different branches of a phylogenetic tree, which reflects evolutionary dynamics of influenza viruses with a given lineage.</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Evolutionary Dynamics of Human Influenza NA Lineages</title><p>This study demonstrated that human influenza viruses were shown to have little geographical restriction, indicating that human viruses were transmitted globally and probably rapidly as well <xref rid="pone.0038665-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. In addition, this study provides new insights into the emergence time of the human pandemic influenza virus because of the employment of the new random local clock model. This model takes into account the rate variation among different branches within lineage and has been considered superior to other models. For the H1N1 human lineage (1C), which includes the sequences from the 1918 Spanish Flu, the tMRCA under the random local clock model was estimated to be 1898 (95&#x00025; HPD: 1882&#x02013;1909), which is earlier than the years previously reported. Using the uncorrelated exponential relaxed clock model, the tMRCA of pandemic 1918 H1N1 viruses was estimated to be 1905&#x02013;1918 <xref rid="pone.0038665-Smith3" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref> and 1910&#x02013;1915 <xref rid="pone.0038665-Reid1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>.</p><p>Lineage 2B includes human influenza viruses isolated from two different subtypes, H2N2 between 1957 and 1968 and H3N2 after 1968, which share the same N2 gene maintained in human influenza virus after the antigenic shift from H2 to H3 occurred in 1968 <xref rid="pone.0038665-Guan1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. The tMRCA of lineage 2B was estimated to be 1956, which is six years later than the tMRCA of 1950 estimated by Smith et al. (2009a), but further supporting the hypothesis that emerging lineages circulate years prior to their initial detection in humans. Furthermore, the human lineages have relatively high non-synonymous to synonymous (<italic>d</italic>
<sub>N</sub>/<italic>d</italic>
<sub>S</sub>) ratios (1C: 0.263, 2B: 0.313, Yam88: 0.259, and Vic87: 0.257), suggesting strong immune selection in viruses persistently circulating in humans <xref rid="pone.0038665-Ferguson1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>.</p><p>In addition to the above discussed human lineages, pandemic H1N1 2009 influenza viruses are believed to have arisen from a reassortment between North American and Eurasian swine lineages, and as expected, the pandemic H1N1 2009 viruses grouped with the Eurasian swine lineage <xref rid="pone.0038665-Smith4" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Garten1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Christman1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. The substitution rate for NA genes of pandemic H1N1 2009, estimated using sequences from the entire pandemic period (as of March 2011), was found to be very close to the substitution rate estimated in the early outbreak period <xref rid="pone.0038665-Smith4" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. In addition, the <italic>d</italic>
<sub>N</sub>
<italic>/d</italic>
<sub>S</sub> ratio of the NA genes of pandemic H1N1 2009 was 0.226, which was higher than the ratio of the closely related swine NA genes (0.100) <xref rid="pone.0038665-Smith4" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. This increase could be attributed either to the adaptations of pandemic H1N1 2009 viruses to humans or to intensive sampling (more frequent mutations detected) <xref rid="pone.0038665-Smith4" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. Immune pressure from a previously infected and/or vaccinated population may also account for the differences observed.</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Evolutionary Dynamics of Avian Influenza NA Lineages</title><p>Influenza viruses circulating in non-human species have evolved in association with their various hosts on different continents for extended periods of time <xref rid="pone.0038665-Olsen1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. Avian influenza viruses were usually classified into Eurasian and North American lineages in the past, which was attributed to confinement of birds to distinct flyways in each hemisphere <xref rid="pone.0038665-Macken1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Wahlgren1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>.This phylo-geographic pattern is evident in the lineages designated for N4&#x02013;N9 subtypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g006">Figure 6</xref>). We also found that the viruses isolated from Oceania were grouped together with Eurasian viruses. Therefore, we expanded our geographic designation and used Eurasian/Oceanian to define theses lineages. Avian lineages were found in all nine subtypes, whereas the mammalian lineages occurred in only four subtypes, providing support for the hypothesis that wild aquatic avian viruses are considered the natural reservoir of all influenza viruses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g006">Figure 6</xref>) <xref rid="pone.0038665-Webster1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Widjaja1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. In addition, the avian lineages from N3 to N9 appeared to be under strong purifying selection pressures as suggested by the low <italic>d</italic>
<sub>N</sub>
<italic>/d</italic>
<sub>S</sub> ratios. Similar observations were also described in a previous study <xref rid="pone.0038665-Obenauer1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>.</p><p>The two subtype-specific avian sublineages, 1A.1 for H5N1 and 2A.1 for H9N2, are considered to have pandemic potential and were found to evolve relatively faster compared with other avian lineages from multiple subtypes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038665-t002">Table 2</xref>). In addition, these two sublineages were found to be relatively young (23 years for H9N2 and 17 years for H5N1), indicating a more recent emergence likely indicative of their adaptation from a wild bird reservoir to domestic poultry and their ensuing establishment in poultry populations. Together, the higher substitution rates and contemporary divergence of sublineages, 1A.1 (H5N1) and 2A.1 (H9N2) may be attributable to the rapid geographical dissemination of these viruses in wild birds and poultry, followed by the establishment of endemicity in poultry-dense regions and consistent transmission and outbreaks <xref rid="pone.0038665-Vijaykrishna1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Butt1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. It will be interesting in future studies to determine if sampling biases (over-sampling in the case of H5N1 and H9N2) may also play a role in the higher substitution rates and recent divergence times observed compared to other avian influenza virus lineages. Nonetheless, it is important to continue systematic surveillance of these high-risk viruses in both birds and humans to better understand these processes.</p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title>Evolutionary Dynamics of Equine Influenza NA Lineages</title><p>Two lineages, H7N7 (7C) and H3N8 (8B), were revealed in equine influenza viruses. The H7N7 equine influenza viruses have not been detected since the late 1970s <xref rid="pone.0038665-Webster3" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>, whereas H3N8 was first isolated in 1963 <xref rid="pone.0038665-Waddell1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref> and is still circulating in equine populations throughout most of the world. Lineage 8B (H3N8) is composed predominantly of equine viruses, but canine influenza viruses are also found in this lineage. This observation is consistent with the fact that equine influenza virus has crossed the species barrier and become established as a respiratory pathogen of dogs <xref rid="pone.0038665-Crawford1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. The equine influenza viruses share ancestors with avian viruses in the same subtype, indicating their possible avian origin.</p></sec><sec id="s3f"><title>Evolutionary Dynamics of Swine Influenza NA Lineages</title><p>Two major swine virus groups, Eurasian (avian-like) swine (1A.4) and North American swine (1B), were found within N1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g006">Figure 6</xref>). Our observation of geographic separation of swine lineages agrees with previous findings <xref rid="pone.0038665-Fourment1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. Our tMRCA analysis of the Eurasian (avian-like) swine lineage revealed that an avian virus crossed the species boundary from birds to pigs in 1978, which is seven years later than previously described <xref rid="pone.0038665-Fourment1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref> but just one year earlier than the first detection of these viruses in 1979. Similar <italic>d</italic>
<sub>N</sub>
<italic>/d</italic>
<sub>S</sub> ratios were observed in both swine lineages, suggesting comparable selection pressures occurred in both lineages <xref rid="pone.0038665-Smith4" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. Interestingly, amino acid positions 46, 53, and 453 in North American swine (1B), which were found to be under positive selection, are located in the T-cell antigenic regions, while position 339 lies in the B-cell antigenic region <xref rid="pone.0038665-Tamuri1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, indicating a strong immune selection occurred on these positions.</p><p>Complicated evolutionary dynamics were observed in lineage 2B. Within this major human lineage, five separate sub-clusters of swine viruses occurred in North America and Eurasia, suggesting that human-origin N2 genes were transmitted to swine in at least five separate instances (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0038665-g002">Figures 2</xref>-B and 6). Between the 1970s and 1980s, human-origin H3N2 influenza viruses circulated in Eurasia <xref rid="pone.0038665-Miwa1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Tumova1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. Reassortment events between human-origin H3N2 and avian-like H1N1 swine influenza virus resulted in the emergence of H3N2 viruses, with HA and NA from human viruses and all six internal genes originally from birds <xref rid="pone.0038665-Madec1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. These viruses eventually superseded the former human-origin H3N2 viruses in swine around 1984. In 1994, a further swine reassortant H1N2 virus was identified in the United Kingdom <xref rid="pone.0038665-Brown2" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>. Phylogenetic analyses revealed that the HA gene of this virus was derived from a human-like H1N1 virus, whereas the NA and internal genes were derived from the European swine reassortant H3N2 <xref rid="pone.0038665-Brown1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>.</p><p>In addition to the complexity found in Eurasian swine N2 viruses, similarly, in North America in 1998 there were outbreaks of influenza observed in swine herds in Minnesota, Iowa, and Texas. The outbreaks were caused by a triple-reassortant H3N2 virus which contained genes from human (HA, NA, and PB1), swine (NS, NP, and M), and avian (PB2 and PA) influenza viruses <xref rid="pone.0038665-Zhou1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. An additional important reassortment event in North American swine resulted in an H1N2 reassortant between classical H1N1 swine (contributing only HA) and H3N2 swine (contributing the other seven segments) <xref rid="pone.0038665-Christman1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. These reassortment events, coupled with interspecies transmission between swine and humans, have led to the complexity seen within lineage 2A.</p><p>
<bold>In summary</bold>, we analyzed 14,328 influenza A and B NA sequences and studied the evolutionary history and phylodynamics of the influenza NA gene. The divergence of influenza NA into influenza A and B NA occurred first, and nine NA subtypes further diverged within influenza A, with two to three lineages identified within each NA subtype. The analyses of substitution rates, <italic>d</italic>
<sub>N</sub>
<italic>/d</italic>
<sub>S</sub> ratio, selection sites and protein structures revealed important associations between mutations and antiviral drug resistance/vaccine escape. Further analyses of other influenza segments are needed in order to obtain a comprehensive understanding of influenza virus evolution, which will facilitate influenza surveillance and control.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Sequence Data</title><p>A total of 14,328 neuraminidase (NA) nucleotide sequences longer than 1330 nts, excluding laboratory recombinant sequences, were downloaded from the Influenza Virus Resource at NCBI <xref rid="pone.0038665-Bao1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. Their host distributions are detailed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0038665-t004">Table 4</xref>. A Perl script (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sysbio.harvard.edu">http://sysbio.harvard.edu</ext-link>) was used to remove identical sequences, which resulted in 10,679 NA sequences, including 10,001 influenza A and 678 influenza B sequences. The influenza A NA sequences were divided into nine datasets (one for each subtype) that consist of 4146, 3754, 351, 85, 128, 488, 189, 684, and 176 sequences respectively for N1&#x02013;N9.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0038665-t004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038665.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Host distribution of neuraminidase (NA) sequences in influenza A and B viruses.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0038665-t004-4" xlink:href="pone.0038665.t004"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Influenza</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subtype</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Human</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Avian</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Swine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Equine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Others</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>A</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3810</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1853</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">243</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5956</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3378</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1215</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">258</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4932</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">412</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">443</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">583</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">610</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">219</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">235</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">568</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">783</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">194</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>B</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">911</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">911</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Recombination Test</title><p>Homologous gene recombination was identified using the 3SEQ algorithm under RDP3 <xref rid="pone.0038665-Martin1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>. Ideally, all influenza sequences are analyzed in a single run. However, because of computational limitations to the program when a large data set is used, we examined our dataset for gene recombination within each influenza A subtype and within influenza B. Sequences with mosaic recombination signals were identified using a cutoff p-value 0.05 <xref rid="pone.0038665-Boni1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>.</p><p>The SeqMat program was used to collapse similar sequences from the same location and the same year, which results in &#x0223c;1500 representative sequences, respectively, for N1 and N2 <xref rid="pone.0038665-Attaluri1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>. For other subtypes, we used all available sequences to detect recombination. Fourteen influenza A N1, 14 N2, two N3, one N4, five N6, three N8, and one influenza B NA sequences were identified to have mosaic recombination signals and thus were excluded from the analyses. No mosaic recombination signals were found in N5, N7 or N9.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Sequence Alignment and Phylogenetic Analysis</title><p>Influenza A and B NA sequences are remotely related with around 40&#x00025; nucleotide sequence similarity. We thus conducted both protein and nucleotide sequence alignments using Expresso - a program based upon protein structural information for alignment and TranslatorX - a program referring to the corresponding protein sequence alignment to align nucleotide sequences, respectively <xref rid="pone.0038665-Notredame1" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0038665-Abascal1" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>. The resulting alignment between influenza A and B sequences was considered to be of good quality, which assured the reliability of the downstream analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0038665.s019">File S2</xref>). MAFFT and MUSCLE were used to align sequences from each of the nine influenza A NA subtypes and the influenza B NA sequences, respectively <xref rid="pone.0038665-Edgar1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0038665-Katoh1" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>. The alignment results from MAFFT and MUSCLE were compared and adjusted accordingly.</p><p>Phylogenetic analysis was conducted using the Maximum-likelihood (ML) method in RAxML <xref rid="pone.0038665-Stamatakis1" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>. RAxML uses rapid algorithms for bootstrap and maximum likelihood searches and is considered one of the fastest and most accurate phylogeny programs. Two hundred independent inferences starting from random MP trees were performed, and the tree with the highest likelihood score was selected as the representative. The GTRGAMMA model was employed to correct the biases of multiple substitution and rate heterogeneity in sequences. All the analyses were conducted on the supercomputing clusters at the Holland Computing Center (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hcc.unl.edu/main/index.php">http://hcc.unl.edu/main/index.php</ext-link>). The trees were visualized and color-coded using FigTree (version 1.3.1) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/</ext-link>) to demonstrate tree topologies and corresponding hosts, subtypes and geographic locations.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Identification of Lineage and Sublineage</title><p>Lineages were determined based upon the topology of phylogenetic trees and strong bootstrap support values (100 for influenza A and approximately 90 for influenza B). The genetics distances between lineages were calculated using the Kimura-2-Parameter (K2P) distance matric under MEGA 5.0 <xref rid="pone.0038665-Tamura1" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>. Additional information such as the distribution of viruses in hosts and geographic regions were also considered in the classification. The aim was to identify the lineages of clearly related sequences, which might interest the virology-epidemiology community and could be used for further evolutionary dynamics analyses. The lineage and sublineage were named according to the following notations: a single digit is used to represent one of the nine influenza A NA subtypes and a letter is used to represent a lineage. A sublineage is also represented using a digit. A dot is used to separate a lineage and a sublineage. For example, 1A.2 means N1 subtype, lineage A, and sublineage 2. For influenza B, two lineages were assigned and named following the conventions well-accepted by the influenza research community. To make our lineage assignment scheme justifiable and extensible, we use alphabetic letters to represent lineages in the order of avian, swine, human, and equine for hosts and in the order of the North America followed by Eurasian/Oceanian in geography.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Substitution Rate and Time of Most Recent Common Ancestor (tMRCA)</title><p>The substitution rate and the time of most recent common ancestor (tMRCA) were estimated for each lineage/sublineage using the Bayesian Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) method available in the BEAST package <xref rid="pone.0038665-Drummond1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. Prior to the MCMC analysis, the linear regression and residual analyses for each lineage were performed using Path-O-Gen <xref rid="pone.0038665-Drummond2" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>; significant outliers identified were then removed. To reduce excessive computational load, we followed the common strategy that achieves computer tractability while preserving the accuracy of the estimates <xref rid="pone.0038665-Felsenstein1" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>. We wrote a Java program to select around 120 sequences from each lineage or sublineage, which represent viruses sampled from different locations and at different time points. In all cases, the data were analyzed under the GTR (General Time Reversible) &#x0002b; <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0038665.e001.jpg" mimetype="image"/></inline-formula> nucleotide substitution model, as this model was consistently found to be the best by Modeltest <xref rid="pone.0038665-Posada1" ref-type="bibr">[65]</xref>.</p><p>Three clock models were compared statistically for each dataset using a Bayes factor test in the Tracer program <xref rid="pone.0038665-Suchard1" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref>: a strict clock, an uncorrelated lognormal relaxed clock (UCLD) and an uncorrelated exponential relaxed clock (UCED) <xref rid="pone.0038665-Drummond3" ref-type="bibr">[67]</xref>. The UCED model was found to provide the best fit for all lineages. In addition, we used the newly developed random local clock model (RLC) that takes into account the rate variation among different branches within lineage by applying a series of local molecular clocks, each extending over a subregion of the overall phylogeny. All estimates also incorporated a different substitution rate for each codon position and a Bayesian skyline coalescent prior <xref rid="pone.0038665-Rambaut1" ref-type="bibr">[68]</xref>. For each dataset, two independent Bayesian MCMC runs were conducted for 30 million generations to achieve convergence, with uncertainty in parameter estimates reflected in the 95&#x00025; highest probability density (HPD). The Maximum Clade Credibility (MCC) tree across all plausible trees was then computed from the BEAST trees using the TreeAnnotator program, with the first 10&#x00025; of trees removed as burn-in.</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>Measurement of Selection Pressures</title><p>The ratio of non-synonymous (<italic>d</italic>
<sub>N</sub>) to synonymous (<italic>d</italic>
<sub>S</sub>) substitutions per site (ratio <italic>d</italic>
<sub>N</sub>
<italic>/d</italic>
<sub>S</sub>) were estimated using the single likelihood ancestor counting (SLAC) method available in the HYPHY package <xref rid="pone.0038665-Pond1" ref-type="bibr">[69]</xref>. Positively selected codons were detected using the single likelihood ancestor counting (SLAC), fixed effects likelihood (FEL) and internal fixed effects likelihood (IFEL) methods with a significance level of 0.05. In the SLAC method, the nucleotide and codon model parameter estimates are used to reconstruct the ancestral codon sequences at the internal nodes of the tree. The single most likely ancestral sequences are then fixed as known variables, and applied to infer the expected number of non-synonymous or synonymous substitutions that have occurred along each branch, for each codon position. The FEL method is based on maximum-likelihood estimates. The FEL method estimates the ratio of non-synonymous to synonymous substitutions on a site-by-site basis for the entire tree or only the interior branches (IFEL). In all cases, <italic>d</italic>
<sub>N</sub>/d<sub>S</sub> estimates were based on Maximum-likelihood trees under the GTR &#x0002b; &#x00413; substitution model. Protein structures of template NAs used in structural analyses were downloaded from the Protein Data Bank (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pdb.org">www.pdb.org</ext-link>). Positively selected sites were mapped on the structure of the protein using Molecular Operating Environment (MOE) <xref rid="pone.0038665-Ye1" ref-type="bibr">[70]</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038665.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Maximum-likelihood (ML) tree of influenza A N3 genes.</bold> Three lineages, denoted 3A, 3B and 3C, were classified. The bootstrap values supporting the corresponding lineages are shown on the major nodes. The scale bars indicate the numbers of nucleotide substitutions per site.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038665.s001.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038665.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p>
<bold>Maximum-likelihood (ML) tree of influenza A N4 genes.</bold> Two lineages, denoted 4A and 4B, were classified. The bootstrap values supporting the corresponding lineages are shown on the major nodes. The scale bars indicate the numbers of nucleotide substitutions per site.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038665.s002.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038665.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p>
<bold>Maximum-likelihood (ML) tree of influenza A N6 genes.</bold> Two lineages, denoted 6A and 6B, were classified. The bootstrap values supporting the corresponding lineages are shown on the major nodes. The scale bars indicate the number of nucleotide substitutions per site.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038665.s003.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038665.s004"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p>
<bold>Maximum-likelihood (ML) tree of influenza A N7 genes.</bold> Three lineages, denoted 7A, 7B and 7C, were classified. The bootstrap values supporting the corresponding lineages are shown on the major nodes. The scale bars indicate the number of nucleotide substitutions per site.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038665.s004.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038665.s005"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><p>
<bold>Maximum-likelihood (ML) tree of influenza A N9 genes.</bold> Three lineages, denoted 9A, 9B and 9C, were classified. The bootstrap values supporting the corresponding lineages are shown on the major nodes. The scale bars indicate the number of nucleotide substitutions per site.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038665.s005.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038665.s006"><label>Figure S6</label><caption><p>
<bold>The structure of 1A.1 influenza neuraminidase, with positive selection sites denoted as green balls.</bold>
</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038665.s006.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038665.s007"><label>Figure S7</label><caption><p>
<bold>The structure of 1A.2</bold>
<bold>influenza neuraminidase, with positive selection sites denoted as green balls.</bold>
</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038665.s007.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038665.s008"><label>Figure S8</label><caption><p>
<bold>The structure of 1A.3 influenza neuraminidase, with positive selection sites denoted as green balls.</bold>
</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038665.s008.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038665.s009"><label>Figure S9</label><caption><p>
<bold>The structure of 1A.4 influenza neuraminidase, with positive selection sites denoted as green balls.</bold>
</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038665.s009.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038665.s010"><label>Figure S10</label><caption><p>
<bold>The structure of 1A.5 influenza neuraminidase, with positive selection sites denoted as green balls.</bold>
</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038665.s010.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038665.s011"><label>Figure S11</label><caption><p>
<bold>The structure of 1B influenza neuraminidase, with positive selection sites denoted as green balls.</bold>
</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038665.s011.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038665.s012"><label>Figure S12</label><caption><p>
<bold>The structure of 2A.1 influenza neuraminidase, with positive selection sites denoted as green balls.</bold>
</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038665.s012.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038665.s013"><label>Figure S13</label><caption><p>
<bold>The structure of 2A.3 influenza neuraminidase, with positive selection sites denoted as green balls.</bold>
</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038665.s013.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038665.s014"><label>Figure S14</label><caption><p>
<bold>The structure of 5A influenza neuraminidase, with positive selection sites denoted as green balls.</bold>
</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038665.s014.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038665.s015"><label>Figure S15</label><caption><p>
<bold>The structure of 6A influenza neuraminidase, with positive selection sites denoted as green balls.</bold>
</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038665.s015.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038665.s016"><label>Figure S16</label><caption><p>
<bold>The structure of 8A influenza neuraminidase, with positive selection sites denoted as green balls.</bold>
</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038665.s016.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038665.s017"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>The number of sequences of each lineage and the number of outliers identified by residual analysis.</bold>
</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038665.s017.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038665.s018"><label>File S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>The phylogenetic tree of influenza A and B neuraminidase sequences.</bold>
</p><p>(TREE)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038665.s018.tree"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0038665.s019"><label>File S2</label><caption><p>
<bold>The alignment of influenza A and B neuraminidase sequences.</bold> The quality of the alignment is indicated by different colors.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0038665.s019.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are grateful to the Holland Computing Center (HCC) at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln (UNL) for the computing support. We specially thank our UNL colleagues: David Swanson, Ashu Guru, and Jun Wang and our UNO students and colleagues: Pavan Attaluri, Santosh Servisetti, Thaine Rowley and Mohammad Shafiullah for their help. We particularly thank the Academic Editor: Dr Dong-Yan Jin and four anonymous reviewers for their helpful comments and constructive suggestions.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>This publication was made possible by National Institutes of Health grant numbers R01 LM009985-01A1. The authors also acknowledge continuous funding support from The University Committee on Research and Creative Activity (UCRCA), University of Nebraska at Omaha, for this research program. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0038665-Smith1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrewes</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Laidlaw</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1933</year>
<article-title>A virus obtained from influenza patients.</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>
<fpage>66</fpage>
<lpage>68</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Webster1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bean</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorman</surname><given-names>OT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawaoka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Evolution and ecology of influenza A viruses.</article-title>
<source>Microbiol Rev</source>
<volume>56</volume>
<fpage>152</fpage>
<lpage>179</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1579108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Nelson1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>The evolution of epidemic influenza.</article-title>
<source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>196</fpage>
<lpage>205</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17262054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Osterhaus1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osterhaus</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rimmelzwaan</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Martina</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bestebroer</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fouchier</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Influenza B virus in seals.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>288</volume>
<fpage>1051</fpage>
<lpage>1053</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10807575</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Webster2"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bean</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group>
<year>1978</year>
<article-title>Genetics of influenza virus.</article-title>
<source>Annu Rev Genet</source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>415</fpage>
<lpage>431</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">371528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Drake1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1993</year>
<article-title>Rates of spontaneous mutation among RNA viruses.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>90</volume>
<fpage>4171</fpage>
<lpage>4175</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8387212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Holmes1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Evolution in health and medicine Sackler colloquium: The comparative genomics of viral emergence.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>107</volume>
<fpage>1742</fpage>
<lpage>1746</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19858482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Ghedin1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghedin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sengamalay</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shumway</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaborsky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldblyum</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Large-scale sequencing of human influenza reveals the dynamic nature of viral genome evolution.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>437</volume>
<fpage>1162</fpage>
<lpage>1166</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16208317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Ferguson1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Galvani</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Ecological and immunological determinants of influenza evolution.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>422</volume>
<fpage>428</fpage>
<lpage>433</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12660783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Pensaert1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pensaert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ottis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandeputte</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachmann</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1981</year>
<article-title>Evidence for the natural transmission of influenza A virus from wild ducts to swine and its potential importance for man.</article-title>
<source>Bull World Health Organ</source>
<volume>59</volume>
<fpage>75</fpage>
<lpage>78</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6973418</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Bush1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Subbarao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitch</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Predicting the evolution of human influenza A. Science</article-title>
<volume>286</volume>
<fpage>1921</fpage>
<lpage>1925</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Smith2"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lapedes</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bestebroer</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rimmelzwaan</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Mapping the antigenic and genetic evolution of influenza virus.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>305</volume>
<fpage>371</fpage>
<lpage>376</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15218094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Plotkin1"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plotkin</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dushoff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Hemagglutinin sequence clusters and the antigenic evolution of influenza A virus.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>99</volume>
<fpage>6263</fpage>
<lpage>6268</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11972025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Schwartz1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wortley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Mass vaccination for annual and pandemic influenza.</article-title>
<source>Curr Top Microbiol Immunol</source>
<volume>304</volume>
<fpage>131</fpage>
<lpage>152</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16989268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Fourment1"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fourment</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Evolutionary dynamics of the N1 neuraminidases of the main lineages of influenza A viruses.</article-title>
<source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source>
<volume>56</volume>
<fpage>526</fpage>
<lpage>535</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20434570</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Furuse1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furuse</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamigaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Oshitani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Evolution of the M gene of the influenza A virus in different host species: large-scale sequence analysis.</article-title>
<source>Virol J</source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>67</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19476650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Nerome1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nerome</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1976</year>
<article-title>Absence of neuraminidase from influenza C virus.</article-title>
<source>Arch Virol</source>
<volume>50</volume>
<fpage>241</fpage>
<lpage>244</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">56930</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Palese1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palese</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Compans</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1976</year>
<article-title>Inhibition of influenza virus replication in tissue culture by 2-deoxy-2,3-dehydro-N-trifluoroacetylneuraminic acid (FANA): mechanism of action.</article-title>
<source>J Gen Virol</source>
<volume>33</volume>
<fpage>159</fpage>
<lpage>163</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">978183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Bloom1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name><name><surname>Baltimore</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Permissive secondary mutations enable the evolution of influenza oseltamivir resistance.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>328</volume>
<fpage>1272</fpage>
<lpage>1275</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20522774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-RameixWelti1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rameix-Welti</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Enouf</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuvelier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeannin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Werf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Enzymatic properties of the neuraminidase of seasonal H1N1 influenza viruses provide insights for the emergence of natural resistance to oseltamivir.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>e1000103</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18654625</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Chi1"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolar</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rappaport</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Cocirculation and evolution of two lineages of influenza B viruses in europe and Israel in the 2001&#x02013;2002 season.</article-title>
<source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>5770</fpage>
<lpage>5773</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14662979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Reid1"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fanning</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Janczewski</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Taubenberger</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Characterization of the 1918 &#x0201c;Spanish&#x0201d; influenza virus neuraminidase gene.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>97</volume>
<fpage>6785</fpage>
<lpage>6790</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10823895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Chen1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>The evolutionary dynamics of human influenza B virus.</article-title>
<source>J Mol Evol</source>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>655</fpage>
<lpage>663</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18504518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Xu1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwek</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Structural characterization of the 1918 influenza virus H1N1 neuraminidase.</article-title>
<source>J Virol</source>
<volume>82</volume>
<fpage>10493</fpage>
<lpage>10501</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18715929</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Vijaykrishna1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vijaykrishna</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Evolutionary dynamics and emergence of panzootic H5N1 influenza viruses.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>e1000161</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18818732</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Chen2"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Avian influenza virus exhibits rapid evolutionary dynamics.</article-title>
<source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>2336</fpage>
<lpage>2341</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16945980</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Suzuki1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Origin and evolution of influenza virus hemagglutinin genes.</article-title>
<source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>501</fpage>
<lpage>509</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11919291</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Brown1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>McCauley</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Multiple genetic reassortment of avian and human influenza A viruses in European pigs, resulting in the emergence of an H1N2 virus of novel genotype.</article-title>
<source>J Gen Virol 79 (Pt</source>
<volume>12)</volume>
<fpage>2947</fpage>
<lpage>2955</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Liu1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tai</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Panorama phylogenetic diversity and distribution of Type A influenza virus.</article-title>
<source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>e5022</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19325912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Group1"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>Group WOFHNEW</collab>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Continued evolution of highly pathogenic avian influenza A (H5N1): updated nomenclature.</article-title>
<source>Influenza Other Respi Viruses</source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>5</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Lu1"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowley</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Garten</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Donis</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>FluGenome: a web tool for genotyping influenza A virus.</article-title>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>35</volume>
<fpage>W275</fpage>
<lpage>279</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17537820</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Drummond1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>BEAST: Bayesian evolutionary analysis by sampling trees.</article-title>
<source>BMC Evol Biol</source>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>214</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17996036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Smith3"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijaykrishna</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Poon</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Dating the emergence of pandemic influenza viruses.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>106</volume>
<fpage>11709</fpage>
<lpage>11712</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19597152</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Guan1"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijaykrishna</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>The emergence of pandemic influenza viruses.</article-title>
<source>Protein Cell</source>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>9</fpage>
<lpage>13</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21203993</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Smith4"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijaykrishna</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lycett</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Worobey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Origins and evolutionary genomics of the 2009 swine-origin H1N1 influenza A epidemic.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>459</volume>
<fpage>1122</fpage>
<lpage>1125</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19516283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Garten1"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garten</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindstrom</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Antigenic and genetic characteristics of swine-origin 2009 A(H1N1) influenza viruses circulating in humans.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>325</volume>
<fpage>197</fpage>
<lpage>201</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19465683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Christman1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christman</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kedwaii</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Donis</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Pandemic (H1N1) 2009 virus revisited: An evolutionary retrospective.</article-title>
<source>Infect Genet Evol</source>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Olsen1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Munster</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallensten</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Waldenstrom</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Osterhaus</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Global patterns of influenza a virus in wild birds.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>312</volume>
<fpage>384</fpage>
<lpage>388</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16627734</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Macken1"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Macken</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Genotype turnover by reassortment of replication complex genes from avian influenza A virus.</article-title>
<source>J Gen Virol</source>
<volume>87</volume>
<fpage>2803</fpage>
<lpage>2815</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16963738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Wahlgren1"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wahlgren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Waldenstrom</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahlin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Haemig</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fouchier</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Gene segment reassortment between American and Asian lineages of avian influenza virus from waterfowl in the Beringia area.</article-title>
<source>Vector Borne Zoonotic Dis</source>
<volume>8</volume>
<fpage>783</fpage>
<lpage>790</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18637721</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Widjaja1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Widjaja</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Krauss</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Webby</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Matrix gene of influenza a viruses isolated from wild aquatic birds: ecology and emergence of influenza a viruses.</article-title>
<source>J Virol</source>
<volume>78</volume>
<fpage>8771</fpage>
<lpage>8779</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15280485</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Obenauer1"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Obenauer</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Denson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukatira</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Large-scale sequence analysis of avian influenza isolates.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>311</volume>
<fpage>1576</fpage>
<lpage>1580</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16439620</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Butt1"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Butt</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddique</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Idrees</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Avian influenza A (H9N2): computational molecular analysis and phylogenetic characterization of viral surface proteins isolated between 1997 and 2009 from the human population.</article-title>
<source>Virol J</source>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>319</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21078137</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Webster3"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1993</year>
<article-title>Are equine 1 influenza viruses still present in horses?</article-title>
<source>Equine Vet J</source>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>537</fpage>
<lpage>538</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8276003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Waddell1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waddell</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Teigland</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigel</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1963</year>
<article-title>A New Influenza Virus Associated with Equine Respiratory Disease.</article-title>
<source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source>
<volume>143</volume>
<fpage>587</fpage>
<lpage>590</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14077956</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Crawford1"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubovi</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Castleman</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephenson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Transmission of equine influenza virus to dogs.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>310</volume>
<fpage>482</fpage>
<lpage>485</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16186182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Tamuri1"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamuri</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name><name><surname>Dos Reis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Identifying changes in selective constraints: host shifts in influenza.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>e1000564</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19911053</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Miwa1"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miwa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Piao</surname><given-names>FZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Noro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>Isolation of human (H3N2) influenza virus and prevalence of the virus-antibody in swine.</article-title>
<source>Nippon Juigaku Zasshi</source>
<volume>49</volume>
<fpage>1168</fpage>
<lpage>1170</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2828738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Tumova1"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tumova</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Stumpa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mensik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1980</year>
<article-title>Surveillance of influenza in pig herds in Czechoslovakia in 1974&#x02013;1979. 2. Antibodies against influenza A (H3N2) and A (H1N1) viruses.</article-title>
<source>Zentralbl Veterinarmed B</source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>601</fpage>
<lpage>607</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6258361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Madec1"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madec</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gourreau</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinat-Botte</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1989</year>
<article-title>Pathologic consequences of a severe influenza outbreak (swine virus A/H1N1) under natural conditions in the non-immune sow at the beginning of pregnancy.</article-title>
<source>Comp Immunol Microbiol Infect Dis</source>
<volume>12</volume>
<fpage>17</fpage>
<lpage>27</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2550169</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Brown2"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>Serological studies of influenza viruses in pigs in Great Britain 1991&#x02013;2.</article-title>
<source>Epidemiol Infect</source>
<volume>114</volume>
<fpage>511</fpage>
<lpage>520</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7781739</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Zhou1"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name><surname>Senne</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Landgraf</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Swenson</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Emergence of H3N2 reassortant influenza A viruses in North American pigs.</article-title>
<source>Vet Microbiol</source>
<volume>74</volume>
<fpage>47</fpage>
<lpage>58</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10799777</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Bao1"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolotov</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dernovoy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiryutin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaslavsky</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>The influenza virus resource at the National Center for Biotechnology Information.</article-title>
<source>J Virol</source>
<volume>82</volume>
<fpage>596</fpage>
<lpage>601</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17942553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Martin1"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lott</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moulton</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>RDP3: a flexible and fast computer program for analyzing recombination.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>2462</fpage>
<lpage>2463</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20798170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Boni1"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boni</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>An exact nonparametric method for inferring mosaic structure in sequence triplets.</article-title>
<source>Genetics</source>
<volume>176</volume>
<fpage>1035</fpage>
<lpage>1047</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17409078</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Attaluri1"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Attaluri</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Christman</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>SeqMaT: A sequence manipulation tool for phylogenetic analysis.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformation</source>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>400</fpage>
<lpage>401</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21383910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Notredame1"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Notredame</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Heringa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>T-Coffee: A novel method for fast and accurate multiple sequence alignment.</article-title>
<source>J Mol Biol</source>
<volume>302</volume>
<fpage>205</fpage>
<lpage>217</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10964570</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Abascal1"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abascal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zardoya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Telford</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>TranslatorX: multiple alignment of nucleotide sequences guided by amino acid translations.</article-title>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>38</volume>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Edgar1"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput.</article-title>
<source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>32</volume>
<fpage>1792</fpage>
<lpage>1797</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15034147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Katoh1"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Asimenos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Toh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Multiple alignment of DNA sequences with MAFFT.</article-title>
<source>Methods Mol Biol</source>
<volume>537</volume>
<fpage>39</fpage>
<lpage>64</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19378139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Stamatakis1"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stamatakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>RAxML-III: a fast program for maximum likelihood-based inference of large phylogenetic trees.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>456</fpage>
<lpage>463</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15608047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Tamura1"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>MEGA5: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methods.</article-title>
<source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>2731</fpage>
<lpage>2739</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21546353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Drummond2"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pybus</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Inference of viral evolutionary rates from molecular sequences.</article-title>
<source>Adv Parasitol</source>
<volume>54</volume>
<fpage>331</fpage>
<lpage>358</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14711090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Felsenstein1"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Accuracy of coalescent likelihood estimates: do we need more sites, more sequences, or more loci?</article-title>
<source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
<volume>23</volume>
<fpage>691</fpage>
<lpage>700</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16364968</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Posada1"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Using MODELTEST and PAUP&#x0002a; to select a model of nucleotide substitution.</article-title>
<source>Curr Protoc Bioinformatics Chapter 6: Unit 6 5</source>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Suchard1"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suchard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinsheimer</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Bayesian selection of continuous-time Markov chain evolutionary models.</article-title>
<source>Mol Biol Evol</source>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>1001</fpage>
<lpage>1013</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11371589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Drummond3"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Relaxed phylogenetics and dating with confidence.</article-title>
<source>PLoS Biol</source>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>e88</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16683862</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Rambaut1"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pybus</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Viboud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Taubenberger</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>The genomic and epidemiological dynamics of human influenza A virus.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>453</volume>
<fpage>615</fpage>
<lpage>619</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18418375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Pond1"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pond</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Muse</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>HyPhy: hypothesis testing using phylogenies.</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>676</fpage>
<lpage>679</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15509596</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0038665-Ye1"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Krug</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>The mechanism by which influenza A virus nucleoprotein forms oligomers and binds RNA.</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<volume>444</volume>
<fpage>1078</fpage>
<lpage>1082</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17151603</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>