<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par58">Size-dependent interactions of AgNPs with HSV-1, HSV-2, and human parainfluenza virus type 3 resulting in reduced viral infectivity or in inhibition of the infectivity of the viruses by smaller-sized NPs that was caused probably by blocking interaction of the virus with the cell was described by Gaikwad et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2013</xref>). AgNPs applied at nontoxic concentrations administered prior to viral infection or soon after initial virus exposure were capable to inhibit HSV-2 replication, suggesting that the AgNPs acted during the early phases of viral replication (Hu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">2014</xref>). Tannic acid-modified AgNPs of 13, 33, and 46 nm showed antiviral activity and reduced both infection and inflammatory reaction in the mouse model of HSV-2 infection, when used at infection or for a postinfection treatment (Orlowski et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR163">2014</xref>), and antiviral activity of such NPs with a size of 33 nm applied upon the mucosal tissues caused activation of immune response in vaginal HSV-2 (Orlowski et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR162">2018a</xref>). Multifunctional tannic acid/AgNPs-based mucoadhesive hydrogel for effective vaginal treatment of HSV-2 genital infection was also reported (Szymanska et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR213">2018</xref>). Investigation of the ability of tannic acid-modified Ag and Au NPs to induce dendritic cells maturation and activation in the presence of HSV-2 antigens, when used at nontoxic doses, showed that both types of these metal NPs were good activators of dendritic cells, albeit their final effect upon maturation and activation may be metal and size dependent and can help to overcome virus-induced suppression of dendritic cells activation (Orlowski et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR164">2018b</xref>). AuNPs of the size of 7.86 nm surface-conjugated with gallic acid showed the antiviral efficacy against HSV infections in Vero cells with EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 32.3 μM in HSV-1 and 38.6 μM in HSV-2 (Haider et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">2018</xref>). AuNPs capped with mercaptoethanesulfonate (MES) strongly inhibited HSV-1, whereby they interfered with viral attachment, entry, and cell-to-cell spread, thereby preventing subsequent viral infection in a multimodal manner (Baram-Pinto et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2010</xref>). However, the antiviral effect of MES-capped AgNPs against HSV-1 was found to be imparted by their multivalent nature and spatially directed MES on the surface (Baram-Pinto et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2009</xref>). An overview related to application of AgNPs in inhibition of HSV was presented by Akbarzadeh et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2018</xref>).
</p>
