<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The activity of AS on the replication of HCMV was demonstrated in different in vitro cell models, such as fibroblasts [
 <xref rid="B11-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] and tumor cells [
 <xref rid="B25-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Compared to other ART derivatives, AS had the highest activity [
 <xref rid="B16-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] and an activity comparable to or even higher than that of classical antiviral drugs, such as ganciclovir [
 <xref rid="B16-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The antiviral effect was confirmed against different, multidrug-resistant strains [
 <xref rid="B10-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] and with different methods, such as the plaque assay and luminescent/fluorescent methods based on the use of transgenic viral strains [
 <xref rid="B24-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In some cases, the effect of AS was synergistic with antiviral drugs such as maribavir [
 <xref rid="B27-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], lamivudine [
 <xref rid="B17-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], ganciclovir [
 <xref rid="B34-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], foscarnet, cidofovir, letermovir [
 <xref rid="B33-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. However, in vitro data regarding synergism are not always confirmed in other experimental conditions, as for the case reported by Morère, where synergism between maribavir and AS was not confirmed in an ex vivo placenta model [
 <xref rid="B32-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Moreover, few data obtained with animal models are available. In the rat CMV/rat model, AS demonstrated antiviral activity, measured as the dissemination of virus to the salivary glands, the number of viral genome copies, and virus titers in salivary glands. This activity was exerted only when AS was coadministered with iron in the Ferrosanol™ formulation [
 <xref rid="B11-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. AS in association with valacyclovir was tested in a murine model of herpes simplex virus encephalitis (HSE) to evaluate not only the antiviral but also the immunomodulating activity, which would be beneficial in this disease model. The survival rates of mice treated with both drugs were higher than those of mice treated with valacyclovir alone, but no significant difference was observed in the brain viral loads. Levels of cytokines such as Interleukine (IL)-1β, IL-2, IL-6, Interferon (IFN)-γ, and CCL2 were reduced in mice treated with valacyclovir combined with ART versus those in mice treated with valacyclovir alone [
 <xref rid="B35-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].
</p>
