<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>I believe, that to improve the education about containment of infectious diseases, dental schools should consider adopting a high standard infection control‐monitoring policy by establishment of infection control committees and units. These committees, with active involvement from the faculty and school deans, are likely to lead to improved sanitation, asepsis, biohazard control, and biohazard waste disposal.
 <xref rid="jdd12174-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref> An exemplary display of infection control measures by the dental school faculty will work as a guideline for students to assimilate such practices, even in resource‐constrained countries. Student immunization against infectious diseases before they enroll into dental schools might further strengthen the efforts to protect the students. Dental schools ought to include infection control teaching either as an independent course or as a significant part of other courses. The students should be taught about basic principles of infection epidemiology, susceptibility, modes of transmission, risk factors, signs and symptoms of infection, laboratory diagnosis, preventive measures including droplet and airborne precautions, eye protection, and health promotion. Students need to be educated not only by lectures and demonstrations but activities, such as workshops, skits, and training camps may also add an extra dimension to student education in infection control measures. Dental schools may launch online courses for basic infection control or smart phone applications, which may keep the students updated with latest information about infectious diseases and the preventive methods. Dental schools should start evaluating students for their infection control practices; grade, mark, and monitor the students according to their infection control practices. A faculty may be put in‐charge of the appropriate implementation of school guidelines, and students should face the consequences in case they fail to implement them.
</p>
