<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34">RSV is commonly implicated in viral-bacterial co-infections with reported co-infection rates of up to 17.5–44% in RSV-infected children [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">108</xref>]. In children with severe bronchiolitis studied by Thorburn et al., bacteria were isolated from 42% of lower airway secretions from infants with RSV using culture methods [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>]. 
 <italic>H. influenzae</italic> and 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> were the most common bacteria identified and furthermore, the study reported that children with bacterial co-infection were at increased risk for bacterial pneumonia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>]. In serological study of children with community-acquired pneumonia, 39% of children had viral-bacterial co-infections, of which RSV and 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> was the most common combination, accounting for 33% of cases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">109</xref>]. Like influenza, both RSV and 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> infection peaks during the winter months [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">110</xref>] and RSV has also been linked to seasonal increases in 
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>pneumoniae</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">111</xref>]. In a case-control study by Benet et al., co-infection of RSV and 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> was more common in cases than in controls but co-infection of RV and 
 <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> was not different between cases and controls [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112">112</xref>]. RSV-bacterial co-infection has also been associated with increased disease severity compared with RSV alone including longer hospital stays and more frequent admission to pediatric intensive care unit [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">108</xref>] and longer ventilator support [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>]. However, associations identified in clinical studies are often weak and only occasionally reach statistical significance. Additionally, some studies have reported bacterial co-infection rates below 2% in children with RSV [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116">116</xref>]. In a study of infants hospitalized with RSV, bacterial co-infection was found in only 0.6% of children hospitalized for RSV-associated LRI [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116">116</xref>].
</p>
