<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0040">It is important to focus that coronaviruses mainly infect epithelial cells of the upper respiratory tract and pulmonary pneumocytes but also other types of epithelial cells such as endothelial cells of arteries and veins, smooth muscle cells, intestinal epithelium cells and immune cells [
 <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] (1112). The RNA genome is released into the cytoplasm of the cells through the fusion of the capsid with the cell plasma membrane. After interaction with its proposed receptors angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2), genomic RNA accompanied by envelope glycoproteins and nucleocapsid proteins forms virion-containing vesicles, which then fuse with the plasma membrane to release the virus [
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Physiologically, ACE2 counters renin–angiotensin–aldosterone system (RAAS) activation by the degradation of angiotensin II to angiotensin which attenuates its effects on vasoconstriction, sodium retention, and fibrosis. ACE2 also cleaves angiotensin I to angiotensin and participates in the hydrolysis of other peptides and may be up-regulated in certain clinical states [
 <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>] The interaction between SARS viruses and ACE which is localized above all on the endothelium of the pulmonary capillaries, causes alterations of the circulation with the variation of the pressure levels (
 <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> ). On the other hand, SARS-Cov-2 also generates interference in the native immune response (Toll-like receptors (TLRs), RIG-I-like receptors (RLRs) and NOD-like receptors (NLRs), which trigger the expression of interferon (IFN) and activation of anti-viral effectors such as Natural Killer cells, T CD8+ cells, and macrophages); generates interference in the recruitment of inflammatory cells, in the regulation of host DNA replication with transcription anomalies and with triggering of the apoptotic pathways, and in dysregulation of the renin-angiotensin system [
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] (
 <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).
</p>
