<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">The S protein of SARS-CoV-2 contains two distinctive features that are not present in the S protein of SARS-CoV
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. First, the S protein of SARS-CoV-2 maintains a high binding affinity to human ACE2 even though five of the six residues present in the SARS-CoV receptor binding motif that are critical for binding to human ACE2 are mutated in the S protein of SARS-CoV-2 (L455, F486, Q493, S494 and N501)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. Cryogenic electron microscopy studies have demonstrated that the S protein of SARS-CoV-2 can bind directly to human ACE2 with a similar or even higher affinity than that of SARS-CoV
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>. This high binding affinity is likely to be related to the high transmissibility of SARS-CoV-2 and the severity of COVID-19. Second, the S protein of SARS-CoV-2 has an insertion of four amino acid residues (12 nucleotides) at the boundary between the S1 and S2 subunits, which introduces a novel 
 <xref rid="Glos7" ref-type="list">furin cleavage site</xref>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. This novel cleavage site has not been observed in SARS-CoV or other SARS-related coronaviruses originating from bats and seems to facilitate the processing of S protein at the S1 and S2 subunit boundary by ubiquitously expressed furin-like proteases for preliminary activation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>. Although the function of this novel cleavage site is unknown, similar cleavage sites have been described in highly pathogenic avian influenza viruses and the Newcastle disease virus
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. This notable feature has been proposed to have a role in expanding cell or tissue tropism of SARS-CoV-2 (ref.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>
 </sup>), contributing to the multiorgan effects of COVID-19 (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>).
</p>
