<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although the role of diet in the etiology of hepatocellular carcinoma is unclear, evidence suggests that dietary intake of particular food groups may have a favorable or adverse association with the risk of HCC [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. For example, consumption of vegetables and fruits may have an inverse connection, while consumption of red meat can increase the risk of HCC. Not many studies have been evaluated to explore the link between food intake and liver cancer, either in our country or globally. In our study, analysis of dietary habits of HCC patients and controls indicated that diet has a relevant role in HCC risk. Rice is the staple food of the Bangladeshi population. Our study found a significant association of high rice intake with increased HCC risk. Previously, there was no evidence of association of rice intake with HCC risk; however, one study found null association between total carbohydrate intake and HCC risk [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. As Bangladeshi people are more likely to eat rice frequently, it is relevant that rice may play a role as a dietary risk factor for HCC. Red meat has long been recognized as a dietary risk factor for HCC and significantly it has been proven that it has a positive relation with increased HCC risk. Huang et al. (2003) suggested that red meat intake may increase the risk of HCC. The polymorphism of the N-acetyltransferase 2 (NAT2) gene plays a role increasing the susceptibility of the effect of red meat in HCC development [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Cross et al. (2007) found that, red meat intake was associated with an elevated risk for liver cancer [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Red meat is the main source of heme iron and may increase HCC risk via the possible effect of iron such as hepatocyte injury and death and DNA damage in tissues by catalyzing lipid peroxidation [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. In the current scenario, the red meat consumption in Bangladesh is limited due to its very high price and most poor people’s intake of red meat is in moderate or low amounts. The amount of consumption and also the frequency of consumption may play an important role for being a significant dietary factor for HCC development. In the perspective of our study, red meat has no association with increased risk of HCC. In our study, higher egg consumption was found to have significance for increased risk of HCC. However, two Italian studies suggested an inverse association between higher egg consumption and increased HCC risk [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The study by Bamia et al. (2014) found an inverse association of tea intake with HCC risk, which was attributed to the presence of polyphenols as an antioxidant, especially in green tea [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Our study was unable to retrieve any significant association between tea intake and HCC risk. Roti is also consumed in Bangladesh as a primary source of carbohydrates. The present study found no significant association of roti intake and risk of HCC. Leafy vegetables are group of crop plants that are grown for their edible leaves. Examples of leafy vegetables are various types of spinach, cabbage, parsley, and lettuce. However, the distinction between leafy and non-leafy vegetables is not always clear. Non leafy vegetables are potato, cucumber, tomato, eggplant, cauliflower, etc. While investigating the association of vegetables, we classified them as the above mentioned two groups. Surprisingly, we found significant association of lower intake of leafy vegetables with higher HCC risk. In other words, an increased intake of leafy vegetables might decrease the risk of HCC. We found no significant association between non-leafy vegetables and HCC risk. A prospective cohort study in Japan showed inverse associations between the consumption of vegetables, green–yellow and green leafy vegetables and HCC risk [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. An association of overall vegetable consumption with reduced HCC risk was also found in studies conducted in China [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], Serbia [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], Japan [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>], and Italy [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. It is also noteworthy that another study conducted in Greece found no association of vegetable intake with risk of HCC [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Our study found that higher consumption of fruits is significantly associated with decreased HCC risk. The role of fruit consumption in HCC risk is not properly established as there is substantial evidence of both association and no association. Talamini et al. (2006) and Vecchia et al. (1988) suggested a positive association of higher fruit intake with lower HCC risk [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. In contrast, Yang et al. (2014) and Bamia et al. (2015) found no significant association [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. The major fact is that vegetables and fruits are major sources of vitamins, minerals, antioxidants, and many bioactive compounds which are major effectors against cancer [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. That’s why vegetable and fruit intakes are more likely to contribute to the prevention of cancer. Vegetables and fruits are also a major source of dietary fiber. The association of dietary fiber with decreased risk of HCC was found in a study conducted by Fedirko et al. (2012) [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. In the case of fish and milk, we found that, increased consumption of these food items may reduce the risk of HCC. In other words, lower consumption of fish and milk have positive association with HCC risk. Higher consumption of white meat is evident in several studies to have a positive impact on reduced HCC risk [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] and no other studies have reported results dissimilar to these studies. Fish intake is also proven to have an inverse association with increased HCC risk in previous studies [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. The supporting factor is that a diet rich in linoleic acid in foods such as white meats and fish, was inversely related to HCC risk [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. White meat and fish have less saturated fat and are rich in polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFA) [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. HCC prevention is attributed to the function of n-3 PUFA, which possesses anti-inflammatory activity by inhibiting interleukin-1 and tumor necrosis factor [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Milk consumption is not widely studied. However, there is also supporting evidence of higher milk consumption with reduced HCC risk in a previous study [
 <xref rid="pone.0232121.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].
</p>
