<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For the most sensitive detection of SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV, and SARS-CoV-2, the collection and testing of both upper and lower respiratory samples [sputum, bronchoalveolar lavage fluid (BAL)] is recommended [
 <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. However, the collection of sputum and particularly BAL via bronchoscopy increases biosafety risk to healthcare workers through the creation of aerosol droplets. Proper use of personal protective equipment (PPE) by healthcare workers is important. Bronchoscopy is a highly technical procedure requiring well-trained staff and may not be available in many parts of the world. Upper respiratory specimens are easy to collect, thereby increasing access to testing for patients with mild symptoms, and in the resource limited settings. SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV RNA are also detected from stool, urine and blood specimens, although generally less reliably than from respiratory specimens [
 <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26–28</xref>]. An exception is SARS-CoV RNA which is consistently detected in feces at about two weeks after symptom onset [
 <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. For the most sensitive detection of endemic HCoVs, upper respiratory specimens should be collected within the first few days of symptom onset. The dynamics of RNA shedding in MERS and SARS patients may reflect the specimen source, severity of illness, as well as underlying risk factors. Among hospitalized patients who did not require ventilator support, MERS-CoV RNA levels in the upper respiratory tract usually peaked in the first week after symptom onset. Among eventual fatal cases requiring ventilation, RNA levels in lower respiratory tract specimens peaked between weeks 2 and 3 [
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Similar shedding patterns were seen for SARS-CoV: RNA positive rates peaked in upper respiratory tract specimens at 7–10 days after symptom onset and then steadily declined after that, while RNA positive rates in lower respiratory tract specimens remained higher throughout 3 weeks after onset of illness [
 <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. In one study, diabetes was associated with prolonged MERS-CoV RNA shedding in the respiratory tract [
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].
</p>
