<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite extensive research, the etiology of KD is far to be unraveled, and no single pathognomonic clinical or laboratory finding for diagnosis has been identified. Indeed, the occurrence of KD in epidemics, as shown by nationwide epidemiologic surveys conducted with biennial frequency since 1970, reveals a potential relationship of KD with an infectious disease. A number of infectious agents, both bacterial and viral, have been isolated from patients with KD through the years,
 <xref rid="b15-mjhid-12-1-e2020039" ref-type="bibr">15</xref> but also non-infectious triggers are presumed to cause the disease.
 <xref rid="b16-mjhid-12-1-e2020039" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Further KD characteristics such as high-grade fever, elevated acute-phase reactants, and elevated white blood cell count strongly suggest an infectious cause, and in particular, some characteristics may suggest a viral etiology, such as the self-limited course of KD, skin rash and conjunctivitis. A host of reports have clarified the distinct seasonality of KD in geographically distinct regions of the northern hemisphere, revealing that various triggers may be operating at different times of the year in various geospatial clustering of KD cases:
 <xref rid="b17-mjhid-12-1-e2020039" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> the seasonality of KD, with winter peaks in Japan and winter-spring predominance in the USA or in many other temperate areas, is highly suggestive of a viral etiology.
 <xref rid="b18-mjhid-12-1-e2020039" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> Shimizu et al. found a seasonal effect also on the response to IVIG treatment, with more patients manifesting resistance to IVIG in the warm seasons from May to October, but no differences in the general outcome of CAA.
 <xref rid="b19-mjhid-12-1-e2020039" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Several epidemiological studies have also demonstrated that KD is frequently associated with a previous respiratory illness; however, no differences have been found in children stratified according to positive or negative respiratory viral testing; in fact, a positive test for respiratory viruses at the time of presentation should not be used to exclude the diagnosis of KD.
 <xref rid="b20-mjhid-12-1-e2020039" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
</p>
