<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
 <label>FIGURE 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Plasma membrane SM depletion suppresses IAV replication 
   <italic>in vitro</italic>. 
   <bold>(A,B)</bold> The effect of exogenous bSMase on ceramide accumulation was studied using confocal microscopy. A549 cells were treated with 0.1 U/ml bSMase or with the vehicle (HBSS
   <sup>+</sup>) for 2 h at 37°C. Cells were then washed, fixed, and stained with mouse anti-ceramide antibody followed by Alexa Fluor 488 conjugated anti-mouse antibody (green). The cell nuclei were stained with DAPI (blue). The images were taken using confocal microscopy with a 40x oil objective lens 
   <bold>(A)</bold>. Fluorescent intensities of confocal images were measured, as shown in 
   <bold>(B)</bold> using ZEN software. 
   <bold>(C)</bold> Cytotoxicity of exogenous bSMase on A549 cells was assessed using the MTT assay. A549 cells were treated with increasing concentrations of bSMase for 2 h, washed with PBS
   <sup>+,</sup> and incubated with VIM for 24 h. MTT assay was then performed at 24 h post-treatment to determine cell viability in treated and untreated cells. 
   <bold>(D–G)</bold> The effect of SM depletion on IAV infection was determined by the plaque assay 
   <bold>(D–F)</bold> or RT-PCR 
   <bold>(G)</bold>. A549 cells were pretreated with increasing bSMase concentrations or vehicle for 2 h followed by infection with either PR8 at 1 MOI 
   <bold>(D,G)</bold> and 0.01 MOI 
   <bold>(E)</bold> or Cal07 at 1 MOI 
   <bold>(F)</bold>. Viral titers were then determined using the plaque assay at the indicated time points 
   <bold>(D)</bold> or at 24 hpi 
   <bold>(E,F)</bold> and plotted relative to the vehicle-treated cells. Variation in PR8 total viral RNA in the supernatant of bSMase-treated and untreated cells was assessed at 24 hpi by RT-PCR using One-Step RT-PCR AgPath-ID 
   <bold>(G)</bold> and plotted relative to the vehicle-treated cells. The results shown are representatives of two independent experiments. Means ± SD are shown. Statistical significance between untreated and bSMase-treated cells was assessed using the 
   <italic>t</italic>-test (
   <sup>∗</sup>corresponds to a 
   <italic>P-</italic>value &lt; 0.05, and 
   <sup>∗∗∗</sup>corresponds to a 
   <italic>P-</italic>value &lt; 0.001).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="fmicb-11-00612-g001" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
