<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>‘Indirect’ evidence of a possible association between influenza and AMI derives from studies showing that influenza vaccination is effective in the prevention of ischaemic heart disease. This, in addition to strengthening the causality between the two factors, would highlight the important clinical repercussion from the association. The results of some observational studies show that the protective efficacy of influenza vaccination from new coronary events in secondary prevention is between 19% and 45%.
 <xref rid="suaa064-B6" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref> This is a range of effectiveness substantially similar to that obtained with other cardiovascular prevention measures widely accepted in clinical practice, including the cessation of smoking (range of efficacy estimated at 32–43%), anti-hypertensive therapy (range efficacy from 17% to 25%) and the use of statins (efficacy range from 19% to 30%).
 <xref rid="suaa064-B16" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref> In a meta-analysis of case–control studies published in 2015, Barnes 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <xref rid="suaa064-B17" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>17</sup>
 </xref> estimated the association between influenza vaccination and occurrence of AMI. A total of eight studies were identified in which the cases were subjects with first MI or recurrent MI. The results showed a protective efficacy of influenza vaccination against AMI equal to 29% (95% CI: 9–44%). However, only two small randomized clinical trials have evaluated the protection provided by the influenza vaccine against cardiac events in subjects with pre-existing cardiovascular disease, the FLU vaccination in ACSs and planned percutaneous coronary interventions (FLUVACS)
 <xref rid="suaa064-B18" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref> and the influence vaccination study in secondary prevention from coronary ischaemic events in coronary artery disease (FLUCAD).
 <xref rid="suaa064-B19" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
