<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0110">HCV genotypes display antigenic variability and viral genetic diversity is geographically structured: in sub-Saharan Africa and South-East Asia highly divergent subtypes of the same genotype dominate transmissions across contiguous areas (
 <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>A). These subtypes are referred to as “endemic” 
 <xref rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0320" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref> and their presence is consistent with a long-standing association of HCV with populations living in these regions. Because parenteral exposure became common only in the relatively recent past, several hypotheses were formulated to account for the maintenance of endemic HCV transmission. Some authors proposed that traditional practices such as circumcision, tattooing, piercing or acupuncture facilitated and maintained HCV infection among human populations 
 <xref rid="b0320" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0345" ref-type="bibr">[69]</xref>. Others indicated that sexually transmitted infections (STIs) that disrupt mucosal integrity are responsible for increased sexual HCV transmission 
 <xref rid="b0350" ref-type="bibr">[70]</xref>. This was indeed shown to be the case in modern high-risk populations 
 <xref rid="b0355" ref-type="bibr">[71]</xref> and STIs have probably been common throughout human history 
 <xref rid="b0360" ref-type="bibr">[72]</xref>. An alternative scenario is that the bite of arthropods, especially those taking large blood meals, can mechanically transmit HCV, possibly from other animal reservoirs such as horses 
 <xref rid="b0365" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0370" ref-type="bibr">[74]</xref>. HCV infection is in fact restricted to our species but, thanks to extensive field work, a number of hepaciviruses have been described in domestic and wild mammals, as well as in reptiles and fish 
 <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0375" ref-type="bibr">[75]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0380" ref-type="bibr">[76]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0385" ref-type="bibr">[77]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0390" ref-type="bibr">[78]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0395" ref-type="bibr">[79]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0400" ref-type="bibr">[80]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0405" ref-type="bibr">[81]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0410" ref-type="bibr">[82]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0415" ref-type="bibr">[83]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0420" ref-type="bibr">[84]</xref> (
 <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>B). At present, the largest diversity of hepacivirus species seems to be hosted by rodents and bats (
 <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>B). Instead, as previously noted 
 <xref rid="b0375" ref-type="bibr">[75]</xref>, the lowest genetic diversity is observed for hepaciviruses that infect cattle and horses (
 <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>B), suggesting that husbandry practices may have resulted in the artificial selection of specific viral strains or facilitated recent viral transmission from some other animal source (e.g., commensal rodents). Non-human primates also host hepaciviruses, but these are highly divergent from HCV. Overall, the phylogenetic relationships among hepaciviruses poorly mirror those among their hosts (
 <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>B), suggesting several cross-species and cross-order host switches during viral evolution. Up to now, the closest relatives of HCV were identified in horses/donkeys (equine hepacivirus, EHV) and dogs (canine hepacivirus, CHV) (
 <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>B). Because CHV is less genetically diverse than EHV, the canine virus possibility originated as a recent cross-species transmission from horses 
 <xref rid="b0425" ref-type="bibr">[85]</xref>, hinting at the ability of hepacivirus to shift among genetically distant hosts. Despite these advances, the events that led to the origin of HCV are still unknown. Taking as a fact the relatedness of the human virus to EHV/CHV, possible scenarios include that: i) HCV originated from a cross-species transmission of EHV, ii) that EHV was transmitted to horses by humans infected with HCV, which leaves the question on HCV origin open; iii) that HCV and EHV originated from the cross-species transmissions of the same (or similar) virus, with subsequent host adaptation and divergence. If this were the case, multiple cross-species transmission events may have originated distinct HCV genotypes 
 <xref rid="b0425" ref-type="bibr">[85]</xref>.
</p>
