<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0025">The sixth mass extinction of species is underway with the current extinction rate for mammals, amphibians, birds and reptiles being faster than any rate recorded over the last million years (
 <xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">Barnosky et al., 2011</xref>). The major anthropogenic drivers of biodiversity loss are habitat destruction, climate change, and wildlife trade (
 <xref rid="bb0475" ref-type="bibr">Travis, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0455" ref-type="bibr">Symes et al., 2018</xref>). The global trade for wildlife, including the bushmeat and the exotic pet trade, is not only responsible for a decline in biodiversity, it also represents a growing risk for public health (
 <xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">Chomel et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0225" ref-type="bibr">Karesh et al., 2007</xref>). The current SARS-CoV-2 outbreak which originates from bushmeat wet markets in China, dramatically illustrates the risk for public health of not controlling the illegal wildlife trade (
 <xref rid="bb0250" ref-type="bibr">Lam et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0270" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al., 2020</xref>). Other epidemics such as the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) (
 <xref rid="bb0365" ref-type="bibr">Pike et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0415" ref-type="bibr">Sharp and Hahn, 2010</xref>), Ebola (
 <xref rid="bb0260" ref-type="bibr">Leroy et al., 2004</xref>), monkeypox (
 <xref rid="bb0255" ref-type="bibr">Lebreton et al., 2006</xref>), simian T-cell lymphotropic virus (STLV) (
 <xref rid="bb0515" ref-type="bibr">Wolfe et al., 2005a</xref>), SARS-CoV-1 (
 <xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">Bell et al., 2004</xref>) were all fostered by consuming wild species. The large scale of the bushmeat trade combined with the ease and speed with which people and goods travel across continents, poses serious challenges for the control of emerging infectious diseases (EID; 
 <xref rid="bb0520" ref-type="bibr">Wolfe et al., 2005b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">Chapman et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0365" ref-type="bibr">Pike et al., 2010</xref>). Recent epidemics have reminded us how uncertain it is to predict future EID and how complex it is to mitigate them (
 <xref rid="bb0365" ref-type="bibr">Pike et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">Bloom et al., 2017</xref>). Current efforts, financed with billions of USD, still focus mainly on post-emergence outbreak control (
 <xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">Allen et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">Bloom et al., 2017</xref>) while little funding is allocated to prevent the emergence of new zoonotic diseases (
 <xref rid="bb0220" ref-type="bibr">Jones et al., 2008</xref>). Highlighting the considerable risks for public health and the global economy can be an alternative way to engage decision makers into the monitoring of illegal wildlife trade, particularly when they pay only little attention to demands from the scientific community and the public opinion to protect biodiversity. The socioeconomic costs of zoonotic diseases are so considerable that it undoubtedly justifies the means engaged to tackle the illegal trade for wildlife. The latter is often considered to only concern developing countries but it is first and foremost a global business with a trade flow from developing to developed countries (
 <xref rid="bb0485" ref-type="bibr">van Uhm, 2016</xref>). EU, as a major hub of the wildlife trade, has a pioneering role to play into the battle against this illegal activity. In light of recent renewed evidence that zoonotic diseases originated from wildlife represent a massive threat to global health, security, and economic growth, it is concerning that European decision makers are not more effective at preventing illegal bushmeat and exotic live animals importation into the EU. Beside enforcing policies and implementing stricter protectionist measures toward wildlife importation, EU should urgently strengthen investments into wildlife forensic science. Developing a network of forensic laboratories in Europe should be part of the EU's plan to address wildlife trafficking within the EU. If decision makers do not stick to this proactive strategy with the will of mitigating the international wildlife trade, they should at least incorporate these measures into the framework of public health politics. Ultimately, this opinion proposes an alternative approach to conservation that has the potential to mobilise the necessary funding to curb the decline of biodiversity and to offer endangered species a brighter future than their impending extinction.
</p>
