<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0165">TLR9 recognizes unmethylated cytosine-phosphate-guanine (CpG) motifs that are commonly found in bacterial and viral DNA, and then mediates the antiviral response of type I IFN 
 <italic>via</italic> the TLR9-MyD88 pathway
 <xref rid="bib119" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>119</sup>
 </xref>. CpG-containing oligodeoxynucleotides (CpG ODN) sequence 1018, as an adjuvant for immunization against hepatitis B virus (HBV), has been proven to significantly increase neutralizing antibody titers in clinical trials
 <xref rid="bib120" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>120</sup>
 </xref>. Recently it has been approved for adults in the United States
 <xref rid="bib121" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>121</sup>
 </xref>. A novel CpG ODN (BW001) has been shown to effectively activate B and NK cells and stimulate the body to secrete high level of IFN-a and IFN-
 <italic>γ</italic>, thereby producing strong anti-SARS-CoV activity
 <xref rid="bib122" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>122</sup>
 </xref>. Furthermore, CpG have been identified to be superior to other TLR agonists (TLR3 agonists: PolyI:C; TLR7/8 agonists: R848) in the secretion of inflammatory cytokines and activation of SARS-CoV S peptide specific CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cell response
 <xref rid="bib123" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>123</sup>
 </xref>. Due to the strong ability of CpG to induce cellular immunity, it is often used in combination with alum to supplement the defects of alum in inducing cellular immunity. For instance, mice immunized with SARS-CoV S protein amino acids 318–510 (S318–510) together with alum and CpG ODN show higher humoral and cellular immune responses than those immunized with S318–510 antigen and alum alone (
 <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> )
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>30</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib124" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>124</sup>
 </xref>. The above findings suggest that CpG can be used as a potent adjuvant for coronavirus vaccines.
</p>
