<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Chloroquine, also a small molecule, is a quinine analog used to prevent and treat malaria. Similar to umifenovir, chloroquine exhibits its inhibitory effect on influenza by pH stabilization. Chloroquine is a weak base and becomes protonated intracellularly in a manner described by the Henderson-Hasselbalch law [
 <xref rid="B129" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>]. It can raise lysosomal pH to facilitate autophagy intracellularly [
 <xref rid="B130" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>–
 <xref rid="B132" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>]. Chloroquine also alters the signaling pathway of enzymes, causing enzyme glycosylation, ultimately inhibiting viral replication in host cells [
 <xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B134" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>]. Liu et al. claimed that chloroquine could inhibit SARS-CoV entry by changing glycosylation of the ACE2 receptor and S protein [
 <xref rid="B135" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>]. Chloroquine's effective inhibition of SARS-CoV was demonstrated 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> on primate cells and human rectal cells [
 <xref rid="B136" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B137" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>]. Hydroxychloroquine is a derivative of chloroquine with an additional hydroxyl group. These two chloroquines share similar structures and mechanisms. Both have shown 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> antiviral activities toward 2019-nCoV [
 <xref rid="B138" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>–
 <xref rid="B140" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>]. Hydroxychloroquine was more effective than chloroquine in inhibiting 2019-nCoV 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> on primate cells [
 <xref rid="B141" ref-type="bibr">141</xref>]. Until now, chloroquine has shown apparent efficiency and safety against 2019-nCoV in clinical trials conducted in China [
 <xref rid="B139" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>]. Currently, chloroquine or hydroxychloroquine has been administered to hospitalized 2019-nCoV patients on an uncontrolled basis in various countries, including China and the USA [
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. However, it must be noted that chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine cause ocular toxicity [
 <xref rid="B142" ref-type="bibr">142</xref>]. Hydroxychloroquine is reportedly less toxic than chloroquine, making it more attractive as a prescription drug [
 <xref rid="B135" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B143" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>]. Nevertheless, more investigation and clinical trials are needed to evaluate further their efficacy and safety in treating 2019-nCoV.
</p>
