<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>ACE-2 has been identified as the functional receptor for SARS-CoV-2. It is an outer membrane enzyme expressed in vascular endothelial cells, the renal tubular epithelium, and Leydig’s cells of the testes, lungs, heart, kidney, and gastrointestinal tract.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr59-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr103-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>
 </sup> It is a type-II transmembrane metallocarboxypeptidase with its enzymatically active domain exposed at the cell surface.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr104-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>
 </sup> ACE-2 is a key player in the renin-angiotensin system (RAS) and a target for treatment of hypertension.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr105-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>
 </sup> ACE-2 catalyzes the cleavage of angiotensin II, a vasoconstrictor, into angiotensin 1–7, a vasodilator, thereby lowering blood pressure by negatively regulating RAS.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr106-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>
 </sup> ACE-2 is a promising drug target for treating CoV infection as well as other cardiovascular diseases.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr5-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
 </sup> ACE-2 confers a protective effect against lung injury induced by viruses by increasing the production of angiotensin 1–7. The virus presumably causes lung damage by reducing ACE-2 levels on cells through the process of degradation and internalization.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr107-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr108-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>
 </sup> Because studies have shown that ACE inhibitors and angiotensin II receptor blockers could be used to up-regulate the expression and activity of ACE-2 in hypertensive patients, similar strategies might reduce the severity of COVID-19.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr109-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr110-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>
 </sup> Recent studies have shown that the expression of human ACE-2 is associated with SARS‐CoV infection and that genetic variations of this receptor may contribute to susceptibility and/or resistance against infection.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr111-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>
 </sup> For instance, a single-cell RNA sequencing analysis of ACE-2 revealed that type II alveolar cells had higher expression of ACE-2 in eight individual lung tissues obtained from normal donors. ACE-2 expression was higher in the two male samples compared with the six female samples. Additionally, ACE-2 expression was higher in the only Asian male in the study compared with Caucasian and black Americans,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr59-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>
 </sup>which might explain why the four German cases showed mild clinical symptoms with no severe illness.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr112-0300060520949077" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>
 </sup> This implies that variation in ACE-2 expression in COVID-19 patients is likely to affect susceptibility, symptoms and intervention outcomes following SARS-CoV-2 infection.
</p>
