<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Two 
 <italic>D. delphis ponticus</italic> that stranded during an outbreak of mortality in Crimea in August and September 1994 had broncho-pneumonia, syncytia and lymphoid depletion [
 <xref rid="B117-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]. Morbillivirus antigen was observed by IHC in the lungs, cerebrum, spleen and lymph nodes. However, morbillivirus RNA could only be detected in a formalin-fixed sample of a testicular fibroma by RT-PCR. There was no evidence of morbillivirus in the frozen tissues using either virus isolation or an antigen capture ELISA that had proven useful during other mortality events [
 <xref rid="B3-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]. As virus isolation was negative and sequencing of the PCR products was not performed, it is unclear which morbillivirus caused the death of these dolphins. The last 
 <italic>S. coeruleoalba</italic> reported to die of acute DMV infection in Greek waters was found in the spring of 1992, two years before the 
 <italic>D. delphis ponticus</italic> mortality in the Black Sea. 
 <italic>S. coeruleoalba</italic> are not known to enter the Turkish Strait Systems (Bosphorus, Marmara Sea and Dardanelles) where 
 <italic>D. delphis</italic>
 <italic>ponticus</italic> are commonly seen, and are absent from the Black Sea [
 <xref rid="B147-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>]. 
 <italic>D. delphis ponticus</italic> have also not been reported in Aegean waters [
 <xref rid="B147-viruses-06-05145" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>]. Thus, a link between the 1990–1992 morbillivirus outbreak in Mediterranean 
 <italic>S. coeruleoalba</italic> and the morbillivirus infection in the two 
 <italic>D. delphis ponticus</italic> stranded in Crimea is unclear. Whether the morbillivirus was in fact CeMV, originating in the Mediterranean, or another morbillivirus should be further examined.
</p>
