<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig4">
 <label>Figure 4</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Dynamic Gene Regulation Modeling of Transcriptional Signatures Pertinent to SARS-CoV-2 Infection</p>
  <p>(A) Heatmap of 1,199 differentially expressed genes (DEGs) in COVID-19 patients derived bronchoalveolar lavage fluid (BALF) cells transcriptome and Calu-3-specific human-SARS-CoV-2 interactome (CSI). The heatmap was clustered based on 
   <italic>k</italic>-mean with upregulated cluster (570 DEGs) with maximum genes enriched in eIF2 signaling/translation pathways and viral transcription. Downregulated cluster (629 DEGs) is enriched in dampening the immune response and vesicle-mediated transport. P and N denote patients and controls, respectively.
  </p>
  <p>(B) Heatmap of 397 DEGs common between transcriptome of peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PMBC) derived from P (patients) and N (controls) and Calu-3-specific human-SARS-CoV-2 interactome (CSI). The heatmap was clustered based on 
   <italic>k</italic>-mean with upregulated cluster maximum genes (47 and 155) enriched in protein ubiquitination, cell cycle, and apoptosis.
  </p>
  <p>(D) Venn diagrams illustrating common and unique significant regulators SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV.</p>
  <p>(C) Dynamic regulatory event mining of 5,495 cumulative DEGs in SARS-CoV-2 across 24 h of infection reconstructed by incorporating static protein-DNA interaction, microRNA (miRNA)/target interaction data with time series proteomics, and miRNAs expression (
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-geo:GSE148729" id="intref0045" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">GSE148729</ext-link>). The regulators only differentially expressed in Calu-3 SARS-CoV-2 temporal transcriptomes are highlighted. Significant regulators (transcription factors; TFs/miRNAs) control the regulation dynamics (P &lt; 0.001 for TFs, P &lt; 0.05 for miRNAs). Major highlighted pathways are cytokine storm, interferon signaling, eIF2 signaling/protein ubiquitination, and apoptosis, and hypoxia response occurs during 24 h with a total of 63 regulators (TFs/miRNAs) involved in dynamic modulation.
  </p>
  <p>(E and F) Shared and unique significant regulators (TFs, miRNAs) identified in SARS-CoV-2- and SARS-CoV-infected Calu-3 cells. Unique significant differentially expressed regulator (MAX, BRF2, ZNF263, ESR1, FOS, SREBF1, TFAP2C, TFAP2A, and hsa-miR-429) in SARS-CoV-2-infected Calu-3 cells involved in C-Myc pathway, transcription, anticoagulation, estrogen signaling, lipid biosynthesis, ciliary landscape, nasal septum abnormality, and hypoxia (E) shared significant regulators with differential transcriptional amplitude in response to SARS-CoV-2 compared with SARS-CoV over time (F).</p>
  <p>(G) The average expression of target genes of SARS-CoV-2 unique regulator across 24 h of infection in Calu-3 cells.</p>
  <p>(H) The expression patterns of hsa-miR-429 target genes in response to SARS-CoV-2 infection at the indicated time points. The enriched pathways are listed.</p>
  <p>(I) Heatmap illustrating comparative expression analysis of cytokine-storm-related genes in response to SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 infection at the indicated time.</p>
  <p>“See also 
   <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S2, S3</xref>, and 
   <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4</xref> and 
   <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S4</xref>.”
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="gr4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
