<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>IAV infection requires a fine balance between inhibiting the host cell antiviral mechanisms by shutting down translation, and allowing enough of the host machinery active to allow for viral replication [
 <xref rid="B16-pathogens-09-00086" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Since the discovery that PA-X and NS1 can both inhibit host gene expression, it has been seen that the different strains of IAV use each protein differently [
 <xref rid="B16-pathogens-09-00086" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. For example, pH1N1 uses PA-X exclusively for inhibiting host protein synthesis as its NS1 protein does not possess this function [
 <xref rid="B17-pathogens-09-00086" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-pathogens-09-00086" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Furthermore, it has been shown that removing PA-X has different effects in different virus backbones. Removing PA-X expression in 1918 H1N1 [
 <xref rid="B15-pathogens-09-00086" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], pH1N1 [
 <xref rid="B39-pathogens-09-00086" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], and H9N2 [
 <xref rid="B20-pathogens-09-00086" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] IAVs reduces viral pathogenicity, while removing PA-X in H5N1 IAV increases viral replication and pathogenicity [
 <xref rid="B21-pathogens-09-00086" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. These differing effects, together with our recent findings with pH1N1 [
 <xref rid="B17-pathogens-09-00086" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-pathogens-09-00086" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] led us to believe that altering PA-X and/or NS1 function in the context of the WT MDV A/AA/6/60 LAIV would be a viable option to tune the safety, immunogenicity, and protection efficacy conferred by the LAIV. However, the possible side effects linked to changes in the ability of a new MDV A/AA/6/60 LAIV to modulate host innate immune responses, such as low immunogenicity, should be evaluated in other animal models of influenza infection. For instance, the implication in virus transmission should be tested in ferrets or guinea pigs, both well-stablished animal models of influenza virus infection and transmission [
 <xref rid="B43-pathogens-09-00086" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-pathogens-09-00086" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-pathogens-09-00086" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-pathogens-09-00086" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>].
</p>
