<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To model the link between climate and incidence rates by means of regression models, we had to project the punctual station-based climate data to the same spatial level as the epidemiological data (i.e. the commune level). In order to take into account the fact that incidence rates are calculated from individual data, and the fact that the population is distributed heterogeneously within each commune, we assigned every tribe the climate index value of the closest station, assuming all people and all mosquitoes within a tribe to be exposed to the same climate conditions. We then averaged the climate index values over all tribes in the same commune, repeated the process over all towns of the same commune, and then calculated an average of the tribe and town values, weighted by the respective proportion of people living in either place, thus obtaining a mean climate index value per commune (see 
 <xref rid="pntd.0004211.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). The distance between a tribe or a town and the closest station ranges from 0 km to 27 km, with a mean of 9 km (see 
 <xref rid="pntd.0004211.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). This “projection” process was done for rainfall, minimal and maximal temperature, and for 16 other climate indices built from these three raw variables (see 
 <xref rid="pntd.0004211.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> for a complete list). The 16 climate indices we built included the key variables most explicative of the inter-annual variability of dengue epidemics in New Caledonia, i.e. the number of days when maximal temperature exceeds 32°C during January/February/March [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004211.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], and the number of days when precipitation exceeds 2 mm in January [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004211.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. They also included variables known to have an influence on biological processes (see all other climate indices in 
 <xref rid="pntd.0004211.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0004211.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. 
 <xref rid="pntd.0004211.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref> shows maps of three of the climate indices built: the mean temperature (
 <xref rid="pntd.0004211.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2A</xref>), the average daily rainfall (
 <xref rid="pntd.0004211.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2B</xref>) and the average daily rainfall during the wettest quarter of the year (
 <xref rid="pntd.0004211.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2C</xref>). Mean temperature as experienced by people during epidemic years ranges from 22°C to 25°C over the territory. Globally, mean temperature experienced by people is higher in the Northern part of New Caledonia than in its Southern part. People living on the East coast are receiving more rainfall (up to 8 mm/day on average over the epidemic years) than people living on the West coast (barely more than 5 mm/day on average over the epidemic years). On the East coast, there are two “hotspots” of heavy rainfall: communes of Touho, Poindimié and Ponérihouen, in the middle-North of the East coast, and Yaté in the South. All observed climate variables and those built from these observed variables are referred to as "observed data" in the article.
</p>
