<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig3" fig-type="figure" position="float">
 <label>Figure 3</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Signatures of HIV-1 subtype reconnection events on the Site Frequency Spectrum (SFS). Results are presented for China (left major panel) and for South America (right major panel). Two time points of HIV-1 sequences sampled are considered in China (Table B in 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.115.024208/-/DC1/FileS1.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">File S1</ext-link>) and in South America (Table C in 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.115.024208/-/DC1/FileS1.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">File S1</ext-link>) (see method section ‘HIV-1 genome analysis’). The total (pooled) SFS is presented in the first row following representation of 
   <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Nawa and Tajima (2008</xref>), the joint SFSs of each pairwise group of HIV subtypes are presented in the second, third, and fourth row and, in the fifth row, the Principal Component Analyses (PCAs) are presented. Subtype J is used as an outgroup (see Figure K in 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.115.024208/-/DC1/FileS1.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">File S1</ext-link>, results for alternative outgroups). Original subtypes (subtypes found early in the epidemics in Africa; at the corners) are used to define a triangle in the PCA space. The position of the HIV-1 genomes on the straight edges of the triangle suggests strong admixture between subtypes. For the total and joint SFS, we consider the mean value of 500 random samples of sequences in each subtypes cluster (see Figure J in 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.115.024208/-/DC1/FileS1.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">File S1</ext-link> for the different clusters). A sample of 16 sequences per subtype cluster is considered in China, and of eight sequences per subtype cluster in South America. The significance of the trends in the dynamics is tested using the optimal test statistic 
   <inline-formula>
    <math id="me49">
     <mrow>
      <msub>
       <mi>T</mi>
       <mi>Ω</mi>
      </msub>
     </mrow>
    </math>
   </inline-formula> derived in the SI (Figure L in 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.g3journal.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/g3.115.024208/-/DC1/FileS1.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">File S1</ext-link>).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="107f3" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
