<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>MV outbreaks usually occur in late winter/early spring, and transmission is via aerosolized droplets (Hayward 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">1826</xref>; Rall 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2003</xref>). MV is one of the most highly contagious infectious agents, and outbreaks can occur in populations in which less than 10 % of individuals are susceptible. Before the introduction of measles vaccine, over 90 % of persons would become immune by age 15 as a result of naturally acquired infection. The 1933 studies of Hedrich in Baltimore showed that measles epidemics were related to small fluctuations in the susceptible population under the age of 15 years of age. Epidemics occurred when the susceptible population reached 45–50 % and ceased when the levels were reduced to 30–35 %. A level of herd immunity protected the population from epidemics when it reached 65 % of the children under age 15, but it guaranteed a reservoir of susceptible individuals for endemic measles (Schaffner et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">1968</xref>). It is estimated that 90 % of nonimmune people exposed to an infected individual will become infected. Moreover, infected individuals are contagious for 3–4 days before and after the appearance of the characteristic rash, increasing the risk of transmission. The contagiousness of MV is best expressed by the basic reproductive number (Ro), which is the mean number of secondary cases that would arise if an infectious agent were introduced into a completely susceptible population. The estimated Ro for MV is generally assumed to be 12–18, in contrast to only 5–7 for smallpox virus and 2–3 for SARS coronavirus (Rima and Duprex 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2006</xref>; Monto 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">1998</xref>; Moss and Griffin 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2006</xref>). The high infectivity of MV implies that a high level of population immunity (approximately 95 %) is required to interrupt MV transmission (Monto 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">1998</xref>). The virus remains transmissible in the air or on infected surfaces for up to 2 h, obviating the need for direct person-to-person contact (Monto 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">1998</xref>).
</p>
