<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="brief-report"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Dis Poverty</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Infect Dis Poverty</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Infectious Diseases of Poverty</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2095-5162</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2049-9957</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">673</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40249-020-00673-8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Opinion</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Brucellosis in China: history, progress and challenge</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Hai</given-names></name><address><email>jianghai@icdc.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Callaghan</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><address><email>david.o-callaghan@umontpellier.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Jia-Bo</given-names></name><address><email>dingjiabo@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.198530.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8803 2373</institution-id><institution>State Key Laboratory for Infectious Disease Prevention and Control, Collaborative Innovation Center for Diagnosis and Treatment of Infectious Diseases, </institution><institution>National Institute for Communicable Disease Control and Prevention, Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention, </institution></institution-wrap>Beijing, China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>VBMI, Universite de Montpellier, INSERM, UFR Medecine, 186, Chemin du Carreau de Lanes, 30908 Nimes Cedex 2, France </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411165.6</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0593 8241</institution-id><institution>Centre National de Reference Brucella, CHU de Nimes, </institution></institution-wrap>Nimes, France </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.418540.c</institution-id><institution>Department of Diagnostic Technology, </institution><institution>China Institute of Veterinary Drug Control, </institution></institution-wrap>Beijing, China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>24</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>55</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Brucellosis is a neglected zoonosis. It causes acute febrile illness and a potentially debilitating chronic infection in humans, and livestock infection has substantial socioeconomic impact. Over the past two decades, improvements have been made to better understand the various aspects of human and animal brucellosis. Meanwhile, especially in the developing world, immense challenges that remain in controlling and eradicating brucellosis are novel diagnostics tools and efficacious vaccines. Here, we will focus on the remarkable issues on epidemiological survey, as well as the priority and challenge of brucellosis in China. Brucellosis will be controlled with meaningful collaboration between local and public partnerships effectively applying a One Health framework.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Brucellosis</kwd><kwd>Neglected zoonosis</kwd><kwd>One health</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100013076</institution-id><institution>National Major Science and Technology Projects of China</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>2018ZX10101002,2018ZX10201002</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Hai</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par14">Brucellosis remains a serious public health issue, and more efforts are needed to reach the goal of controlling human and animal brucellosis in China. For human brucellosis, a total of 12.5 million persons were examined from 1950 to 1990 with 444&#x02009;900 sero-positives (positive rate: 3.56%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. In 1993, there were 326 brucellosis cases, with the incidence of 0.028/100&#x000a0;000, which was the lowest in the history. However, the incidence continued to increase since 1995, and brucellosis expanded to all provinces. In 2019, there were 44&#x02009;036 cases, with the incidence of 3.2513/100&#x000a0;000 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). This may be due to the dynamic growth of animal husbandry in China, which enhances the chance of human infection. In order to grasp the epidemic situation and develop measures for the prevention and control of brucellosis, activities for prevention and control of brucellosis have been gradually introduced. Vaccination for animals and humans was implemented as the main control measure during 1964&#x02013;1976 in regions with severe epidemics, such as Inner Mongolia, Xinjiang, Qinghai, Ningxia, and Henan provinces [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. During 1977&#x02013;1988, a national program for brucellosis control was conducted with the introduction of diagnostic criteria, treatment protocols, and control measures, and vaccination of domestic animals was used as the main control measure. National sentinel surveillance was established in 1990 to monitor the sero-prevalence of brucellosis in humans and animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Over the past two decades, improvements have been made to better understand the various aspects of humans and animals brucellosis in China. However to control the high endemic will entail enormous challenges, as it has been highlighted by the active discussion around brucellosis intervention strategies in this paper.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Aggregated number of cases (blue bars) and annual incidence rate (orange line) per 100&#x02009;000 residents, 1950&#x02013;2019</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40249_2020_673_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>History and evolution of brucellosis in China</title><p id="Par15">Brucellosis incidence in China is divided into three stages: high incidence (1950s&#x02013;1960s), decline (1970s&#x02013;1980s), and re-emergence (1990s&#x02013;) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. At the re-emergence stage, brucellosis incidence grew exponentially and spreads to all 32 provinces. During the past decade, outbreaks of human brucellosis have been reported in increasing numbers and with an apparent geographic expansion from the historically affected north of China to southern provinces because of the increasing movement of humans, animals, and animal food products from brucellosis-endemic regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Remarkable issues on epidemiological survey of brucellosis</title><p id="Par16">The disease is transmitted to humans mainly by contact with infected animals and the ingestion of infected meat or unpasteurized dairy products [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. According to the annual brucellosis surveillance report, there were 56 public health emergencies of brucellosis in 2019. These events were mainly related to animal husbandry (33), raw milk (8), or processing and marketing of animal products (8). In 2017, the human brucellosis outbreak (122 cases in Hezhou, Guangxi) was caused by drinking unpasteurized ewe&#x02019;s milk. Foodborne transmission was a serious risk factor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Although abortion in ruminants is a classical symptom of brucellosis, it is only in recent years that it has been fully recognized that brucellosis in pregnant women is associated with obstetric complications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In 2019, we first reported a case of likely mother-to-child transmission of <italic>Brucella</italic> in Hunan Province, China [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Although these events are rare, this report highlighted the importance of improving clinical awareness. Brucellosis should be considered for pregnant women presenting with fever, fatigue, and joint-muscle pain not associated with other infections.</p><p id="Par17">In 2019, we described a case to raise the brucellosis clinical diagnosis awareness among clinicians [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Brucellosis concomitant with HIV infection are rarely reported. We suggest that there is a need of a prospective investigation on the incidence of brucellosis in HIV patients in the provinces with high incidence of AIDS and brucellosis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Genomic-based surveillance of brucellosis</title><p id="Par18">The genus <italic>Brucella</italic> is considered as the most important zoonotic pathogens. Over the last decade, a vast number of <italic>Brucella</italic> genomes have been sequenced allowing us to decipher the evolutionary path of the genus from a soil bacterium to a stealth pathogen. The genus is composed of two groups of strains; the classical <italic>Brucella</italic> including the historical (usually zoonotic) species (<italic>B. melitensis, B. abortus, B. suis. B. ovis, B. canis and B. neotomae)</italic> as well as more recently isolated species (<italic>B. ceti, B. pinnepedialis, B. microti</italic> and <italic>B. papionis</italic>) and a group of atypical strains, which are much older in evolutionary terms. The classical strains are highly conserved at the DNA sequence level, however multilocus sequence typing (MLST) has been used to follow <italic>Brucella</italic> evolution and multiple loci VNTR Analysis (MLVA) has offered the possibilities to follow trace strains at the outbreak level. With the reduced costs and increased speed of next generation sequencing (NGS) technology, new typing methods are being developed to directly exploit whole-genome shotgun (WGS) data.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Clinical diagnosis</title><p id="Par19">According to the World Health Organization (WHO) factsheet, although approximately 500&#x02009;000 brucellosis cases are reported annually, the true incidence is always much higher than the reported number of cases. Up to now, there is no distinct and clear guideline for brucellosis diagnosis, with different countries having their own rules. Serologic tests play a fundamental role in the diagnosis of this disease. All of the standard serological tests are based on the detection of antibodies recognizing the O antigen of the <italic>Brucella</italic> lipopolysaccharide (LPS). The interpretation of these tests is usually difficult, particularly in patients with chronic brucellosis, reinfection, and relapse states and in endemic areas where a high frequency of positive serology are observed. Neither the US Center for Disease Control (CDC) nor the WHO offers a specific definition for chronic brucellosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Lateral flow assays do not require extensive laboratory infrastructure or technical expertise, and compared to the standard of serum tube agglutination (SAT) and/or culture, the sensitivity and specificity were 92&#x02013;95 and 97%, respectively, in endemic settings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. They are, however, very expensive compared to Rose Bengal test (RBT) and SAT. BrucellaCapt (Vircel) is also reported to detect the IgA response that characterizes chronic brucellosis.</p><p id="Par20">The gold standard for diagnosis of brucellosis is a positive culture. Manipulation of <italic>Brucella</italic> presents a risk if the manipulator is untrained or not working with the appropriate confinement (in a microbiological safety cabinet) and unnecessary manipulation (e.g. slide agglutination, antibiotic sensitivity testing) should be avoided. MALDI-TOF-MS is used in developed provincial CDCs and is becoming the method of choice for bacterial identification in some modern diagnostic laboratory. A new spectral database has been developed for the bioMerieux Vitek system which allows the identification of <italic>Brucella</italic> at the species level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p><p id="Par21">Detection of <italic>Brucella</italic> DNA in clinical samples by PCR is a powerful tool when culture is not conclusive. Many assays are based on detection of the <italic>Brucella</italic> specific <italic>IS</italic>711 sequence, which is found in multiple copies in the genomes of all <italic>Brucella.</italic> PCR was effectively employed to rapidly detect <italic>Brucella</italic> DNA in the blood of six suspected cases which all subsequently met confirmed case definitions, and multiplex assays can expedite the confirmation and speciation of <italic>Brucella</italic> isolated by culture and rapidly identify the species and biovar [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p><p id="Par22">The atypical strains present a major problem for the diagnostic laboratory. Phenotypically, many do not look like <italic>Brucella</italic> (rapid growth, motile, abnormal metabolic profiles) and many do not produce the persoamine based O antigen meaning that they will not be agglutinated by typing serum, and serological reactions to standard tests based on <italic>Brucella</italic> LPS will be negative.</p><p id="Par23">The identification of new diagnostic and prognostic biomarkers is a major challenge for future research. Since serum and plasma are accessed with relative ease, circulating biomarkers are promising targets. Fine analysis of cytokine levels may give clues. Studies increasingly indicate that dysregulated microRNAs (miRNAs) are associated with bacterial infection. Nevertheless, little is known about miRNAs that respond to <italic>Brucella</italic> infection and their potential clinical value. Although there are many studies on <italic>Brucella</italic> infection, few studies have been devoted to exploring the effects of brucellosis on serum miRNA expression, however miR-103b has been highlighted. Further exploration and validation are required to evaluate the potential target genes of miR-103b and their relationship with the occurrence and development of brucellosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Vaccination against brucellosis</title><p id="Par24">As a zoonotic infection, the best way to control human brucellosis is to control the disease in animals. Two vaccines, <italic>B. melitensis</italic> Rev1 for small ruminants and <italic>B. abortus</italic> S19 for bovine brucellosis have been used to control brucellosis throughout the world for many years. Although not perfect, they are the best available options and should be the basis of control with strict compliance to the International Epizootic Office (OIE) guidelines. However, should vaccines be developed to protect the animals or humans, even if doing so may have a negative economic effect on farmers? In cases where a vaccine has been successfully developed, how can we use it in the field without hampering serological diagnosis?</p><p id="Par25"><italic>B. abortus</italic> 104&#x02009;M has been used as a vaccine against brucellosis in China since 1965. This strain is poorly characterized, is not widely available and concerns exist about its safety. Much more work is required to develop a safe and effective vaccine for humans brucellosis. We can also ask whether such a vaccine is necessary; controlling animals disease and improved food safety (especially avoiding the consumptions of unpasteurized milk products) should be the first line of control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>French-Chinese collaborations</title><p id="Par26">A twinning project was established between the EU Reference Laboratory for Brucellosis (ANSES, Maisons Alfort, France) and the Chinese Animal Health and Epidemiology Centre (CAHEC, located in Qingdao, China) to strengthen the capacities of the CAHEC Brucellosis laboratory. This led to a series of training workshops organized in France by the ANSES laboratory.</p><p id="Par27">Surveillance of humans brucellosis is implemented by the State Key Laboratory for Infectious Disease Prevention and Control in China. There are close contacts with the brucellosis group from the French National Reference Centre in Nimes, with regular visits and discussion of joint projects. We are working on establishing a formal collaboration.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>One health strategies in China</title><p id="Par28">A cornerstone of zoonotic infectious disease epidemiology is the One Health concept. This disease will not be controlled or eradicated without meaningful collaboration between local and public partnerships. The National Brucellosis Control Program (2016&#x02013;2020) was issued by Ministry of Agriculture and National Health and Family Planning Commission. The OIE Reference Laboratory for Brucellosis (by Dr. Jia-Bo Ding) was established by China Institute of Veterinary Drug Control (CIVDC) in 2019. A series of training workshops will be held every year by China CDC and CIVDC.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Challenge of future research</title><p id="Par29">Immense challenges of future research are: (1) to develop and validate novel diagnostics to replace blood culture; (2) to develop efficacious animals vaccines that provide better protection to animal and professional populations (3) to develop genomic-based typing method in outbreak detection, source tracing, transmission mode discovery, and new epidemic clone identification.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par30">Human brucellosis is an easily neglected public health issues in China, which would profit from improved vaccines and simple, specific, and inexpensive diagnostic tests. The disease will be controlled with meaningful collaboration between local and public partnerships effectively applying a One Health framework. We recommended the following preparedness measures that should be taken by all stakeholders in China including (i) strengthening information dissemination and health education on brucellosis; (ii) improving veterinary and public health surveillance, such as preparing the fast detection tests for screening of suspected livestock and products, and setting standard operating procedures for risk assessment.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>MLST</term><def><p id="Par2">Multilocus sequence typing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MLVA</term><def><p id="Par3">Multiple-locus variable number tandem repeat analysis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NGS</term><def><p id="Par4">Next generation sequencing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WGS</term><def><p id="Par5">Whole-genome shotgun</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WHO</term><def><p id="Par6">World Health Organization</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LPS</term><def><p id="Par7">Lipopolysaccharide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CDC</term><def><p id="Par8">Center for Disease Control</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SAT</term><def><p id="Par9">Serum tube agglutination</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RBT</term><def><p id="Par10">Rose Bengal test</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OIE</term><def><p id="Par11">International Epizootic Office</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CAHEC</term><def><p id="Par12">Chinese Animal Health and Epidemiology Centre</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CIVDC</term><def><p id="Par13">China Institute of Veterinary Drug Control</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><p>Not applicable.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>H J and J-B D wrote a first draft of the editorial. D O revised the paper. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was funded by Major Infectious Diseases such as AIDS and Viral Hepatitis Prevention and Control technology major projects (Grant No. 2018ZX10712-001); and Major Infectious Diseases such as AIDS and Viral Hepatitis Prevention and Control technology major projects (Grant No. 2018ZX10201002).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par31">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par32">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par33">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deqiu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Donglou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiming</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology and control of brucellosis in China</article-title><source>Vet Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0378-1135(02)00252-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12414142</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of 1990 to 2001 surveillance effect of national major surveillance place for brucellosis</article-title><source>Chin J Control Endem Dise</source><year>2002</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>288</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Piao DR, Liu X, Di DD, Xiao P, Zhao ZZ, Xu LQ, et al. Genetic polymorphisms identify in species/biovars of <italic>Brucella</italic> isolated in China between 1953 and 2013 by MLST. BMC Microbiol. 2018;18(1):7.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Changing epidemiology of human brucellosis, China, 1955&#x02013;2014</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><year>2017</year><volume>23</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>184</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid2302.151710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28098531</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pappas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Akritidis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosilkovski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsianos</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Brucellosis</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>352</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>2325</fpage><lpage>2336</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra050570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15930423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characteristics of brucellosis related public health emergencies in China, 2006-2012</article-title><source>Dis Surveill.</source><year>2013</year><volume>28</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>723</fpage><lpage>725</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>QC</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiological investigation of outbreak of brucellosis caused by drinking of unpasteurized ewe&#x02019;s milk in Hezhou of Guangxi</article-title><source>Dis Surveill</source><year>2017</year><volume>32</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>634</fpage><lpage>637</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dadar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahali</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Whatmore</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human brucellosis caused by raw dairy products: a review on the occurrence, major risk factors and prevention</article-title><source>Int J Food Microbiol</source><year>2019</year><volume>292</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2018.12.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30572264</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdem</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Elaldi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gulsun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Karahocagil</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pekok</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Brucellosis in pregnancy: results of multicenter ID-IRI study</article-title><source>Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis</source><year>2019</year><volume>38</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1261</fpage><lpage>1268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10096-019-03540-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30989418</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>GZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>ZX</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A case report on mother-to-child transmission of <italic>Brucella</italic> in human, China</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2019</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>666</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-019-4302-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31351446</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Piao</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A case of brucellosis concomitant with HIV infection in China</article-title><source>Infect Dis Poverty</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>6</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40249-020-0624-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31948465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Department of Communicable Disease and Response</collab></person-group><source>WHO recommended surveillance standards</source><year>1999</year><edition>2</edition><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. 2012 Case definitions: nationally notifiable diseases and conditions. Atlanta: CDC; 2012. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wwwn.cdc.gov/nndss/document/2012_Case%20Definitions.pdf">http://wwwn.cdc.gov/nndss/document/2012_Case%20Definitions.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mizanbayeva</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smits</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhalilova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdoel</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozakov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ospanov</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The evaluation of a user-friendly lateral flow assay for the serodiagnosis of human brucellosis in Kazakhstan</article-title><source>Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis</source><year>2009</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2009.05.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19679230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mesureur</surname><given-names>Jennifer</given-names></name><name><surname>Arend</surname><given-names>Sandrine</given-names></name><name><surname>Celli&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>B&#x000e9;atrice</given-names></name><name><surname>Courault</surname><given-names>Priscillia</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotte-Pattat</surname><given-names>Pierre-Jean</given-names></name><name><surname>Totty</surname><given-names>Heather</given-names></name><name><surname>Deol</surname><given-names>Parampal</given-names></name><name><surname>Mick</surname><given-names>Virginie</given-names></name><name><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>Victoria</given-names></name><name><surname>Touchberry</surname><given-names>Joanne</given-names></name><name><surname>Burrowes</surname><given-names>Vanessa</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavigne</surname><given-names>Jean-Philippe</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Callaghan</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><name><surname>Monnin</surname><given-names>Val&#x000e9;rie</given-names></name><name><surname>Keriel</surname><given-names>Anne</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A MALDI-TOF MS database with broad genus coverage for species-level identification of Brucella</article-title><source>PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases</source><year>2018</year><volume>12</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e0006874</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0006874</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30335748</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winchell</surname><given-names>Jonas M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>Bernard J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiller</surname><given-names>Rebekah</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>Michael D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmaster</surname><given-names>Alex R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid Identification and Discrimination ofBrucellaIsolates by Use of Real-Time PCR and High-Resolution Melt Analysis</article-title><source>Journal of Clinical Microbiology</source><year>2010</year><volume>48</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>697</fpage><lpage>702</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.02021-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20053863</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive analysis of differentially expressed serum microRNAs in humans responding to <italic>Brucella</italic> infection</article-title><source>Ann Transl Med</source><year>2019</year><volume>7</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>301</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/atm.2019.05.74</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31475171</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>