<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The dynamics and connotations of words and images, can influence or even transform the consciousness of each individual to a certain extent and, consequently, affect social consciousness. Rarely is a word neutral. It carries our energy and our aim with it. Modern science (neurology, biology, anthropology, linguistics, etc.) can confirm this notion, as every single word is a process of thoughts that are the result of hormonal, biochemical and metabolic alterations, and electrical charges or discharges of our neurons (
 <xref rid="b7-mmr-22-04-3035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). We should not forget that the main goal of the targeter is to look indeterminable, incomprehensible, inaccessible, powerful, invincible, and invisible if possible (here we are not referring to SARS-CoV-2, but to the economic elite that define global social policies). When the root of the problem is traced within the DNA of the targeter, in our attempt to defend ourselves to survive the attack and to confront the enemy, we must come up with a plan for its total elimination. It is important to first record and then analyze the targeter's plan. We must study its purpose, what it seeks from its target, which in this case is us. Marx has already answered these questions as early as mid-19th century, with the phrase ‘
 <italic>The philosophers have only interpreted the world in various ways; the point, however, is to change it</italic>’ (
 <xref rid="b8-mmr-22-04-3035" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). For such a change it is necessary for the targeter to become the target and for the target to become the targeter, in the context of a scientific plan for social transformation that will move us, excite us and, as a shining star, guide us into the future. And in these imprinted thoughts we must search where they come from and where they may lead us to. Only then will we be able to understand whether they are good or bad. As Hölderlin wrote in ‘Patmos’: ‘
 <italic>But where there is danger, Salvation also grows’</italic>. It is a nice expression of the Heraclitean struggle of the opposites (
 <xref rid="b9-mmr-22-04-3035" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), which at the socio-political level may be translated as the struggle of the social classes.
</p>
