<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.49163.013</object-id>
 <label>Figure 4.</label>
 <caption>
  <title>CHIKV E2 K200R evades phagocytic cell-mediated clearance.</title>
  <p>(
   <bold>A</bold>) WT C57BL/6 mice were inoculated i.v. with CHIKV or CHIKV E2 K200R, and viral genomes in the inoculum and serum at the indicated times post-inoculation were evaluated by RT-qPCR. Mean ± SD. N = 6 per time point, two experiments. Two-way ANOVA with Bonferroni’s correction; ****p&lt;0.0001. (
   <bold>B</bold>) WT C57BL/6 mice were inoculated with human fibroblast-derived CHIKV or CHIKV E2 K200R, and viral genomes in the inoculum and in the serum at 45 min post-inoculation were quantified by RT-qPCR. Mean ± SD. N = 6, two experiments. Two-tailed, unpaired t-test; ****p&lt;0.0001. (
   <bold>C</bold>) WT C57BL/6 mice were treated i.v. with PBS liposomes or clodronate liposomes 42 hr prior to i.v. inoculation with CHIKV or CHIKV E2 K200R. Viral genomes in the inoculum and serum at 45 min post-inoculation were determined by RT-qPCR. Mean ± SD. N = 8, two experiments. Kruskal-Wallis; **p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001 (
   <bold>D</bold>) WT C57BL/6 mice were inoculated i.v. with the indicated viruses, and viral genomes in the inoculum and in the serum at 45 min post-inoculation were quantified by RT-qPCR (99659, SL15649), focus forming assay (37997), or plaque assay (ONNV SG650). Mean ± SD. N = 3, one experiment. Mann-Whitney test; p&gt;0.05. 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s1">Figure 4—figure supplement 1</xref> shows that mutation of E2 glycosylation sites does not influence CHIKV clearance from the circulation. 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4s2">Figure 4—figure supplement 2</xref> shows that the E2 K200R mutation does not alter the thermostability of CHIKV particles in serum (
   <bold>A</bold>), and that the E2 K200R mutation allows CHIKV particles to evade clearance from the circulation in multiple distinct mouse strains (
   <bold>B</bold>).
  </p>
  <p>
   <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="fig4sdata1">
    <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.49163.016</object-id>
    <label>Figure 4—source data 1.</label>
    <caption>
     <title>Raw data for 
      <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4A-D</xref>.
     </title>
    </caption>
    <media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-49163-fig4-data1.xlsx" orientation="portrait" id="d35e1063" position="anchor" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </supplementary-material>
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="elife-49163-fig4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 <p content-type="supplemental-figure">
  <fig id="fig4s1" specific-use="child-fig" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
   <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.49163.014</object-id>
   <label>Figure 4—figure supplement 1.</label>
   <caption>
    <title>Mutation of putative CHIKV glycosylation sites has no impact on viral clearance from the circulation.</title>
    <p>WT C57BL/6 mice were inoculated with WT CHIKV or the indicated mutants and viral genomes in the serum at 45 min post-inoculation were quantified by RT-qPCR. Mean ± SD. N = 8 with two experiments for WT CHIKV, E2 N263Q, and E2 N273Q; N = 4 with one experiment for E2 N263Q, N273Q. Kruskal-Wallis with Dunn’s multiple comparison test; p&gt;0.05 for all comparisons.</p>
   </caption>
   <graphic xlink:href="elife-49163-fig4-figsupp1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </fig>
 </p>
 <p content-type="supplemental-figure">
  <fig id="fig4s2" specific-use="child-fig" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
   <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.49163.015</object-id>
   <label>Figure 4—figure supplement 2.</label>
   <caption>
    <title>CHIKV E2 K200R does not impact virus stability and evades clearance in multiple mouse strains.</title>
    <p>(
     <bold>A</bold>) CHIKV or CHIKV E2 K200R particles were incubated in serum at 37°C or 4°C. At the indicated times, infectious virus in the serum was quantified by focus formation assay. Mean ± SD. N = 6, two experiments. Two-way ANOVA with Bonferroni’s correction. (
     <bold>B</bold>) WT 129S1/SvlmJ or BALB/cJ mice were were inoculated i.v. with CHIKV or CHIKV E2 K200R, and viral genomes in the inoculum or in the serum at 45 min post-inoculation were evaluated by RT-qPCR. Mean ± SD. N = 4, one experiment. Mann-Whitney test relative to PLL treated CHIKV inoculated group; *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01.
    </p>
   </caption>
   <graphic xlink:href="elife-49163-fig4-figsupp2" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </fig>
 </p>
</fig>
