<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.49163.021</object-id>
 <label>Figure 7.</label>
 <caption>
  <title>RRV clearance from the circulation is mediated by a distinct lysine residue, E2 K251.</title>
  <p>(
   <bold>A</bold>) WT C57BL/6 mice were treated i.v. with PLL or CLL 42 hr prior to i.v. inoculation with RRV strains T48 or DC5692. Viral genomes in the inoculum and in the serum at 45 min post-inoculation were quantified by RT-qPCR. Mean ± SD. N = 6, two experiments. Two-tailed unpaired t-test; **p&lt;0.01, ****p&lt;0.0001. (
   <bold>B</bold>) Schematic representation of the six amino acid differences between T48 and DC5649 within E2 shown, with position 251 underlined. WT C57BL/6 mice were inoculated i.v. with the indicated viruses and mutants. Viral genomes in inoculum and in the serum at 45 min post-inoculation were quantified as in (
   <bold>A</bold>). Mean ± SD. N = 6, two experiments. Kruskal-Wallis; **p&lt;0.01. (
   <bold>C</bold>) CHIKV trimeric spike (PDB 3J2W), with E2 K200 highlighted in green, and E2 K251 (RRV numbering) highlighted in yellow. The E1 glycoprotein is shown in gray, E2 domain A is shown in blue, E2 domain B is shown in orange, E2 domain C is shown in red, and the β-ribbon connector is shown in light blue. 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7s1">Figure 7—figure supplement 1</xref> shows evaluation of the clearance of RRV T48 and RRV DC5692 structural gene chimeras (
   <bold>A</bold>), demonstrates that the E2 K251R mutation does not alter the thermostability of RRV particles in serum (
   <bold>B</bold>), and that the clearance phenotypes of RRV T48 and RRV T48 E2 R251K viral particles are maintained when purified viral particles are used for mouse inoculation studies (
   <bold>C</bold>).
  </p>
  <p>
   <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="fig7sdata1">
    <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.49163.023</object-id>
    <label>Figure 7—source data 1.</label>
    <caption>
     <title>Raw data for 
      <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Figure 7A-C</xref>.
     </title>
    </caption>
    <media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-49163-fig7-data1.xlsx" orientation="portrait" id="d35e1351" position="anchor" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </supplementary-material>
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="elife-49163-fig7" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 <p content-type="supplemental-figure">
  <fig id="fig7s1" specific-use="child-fig" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
   <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.49163.022</object-id>
   <label>Figure 7—figure supplement 1.</label>
   <caption>
    <title>Chimeric analysis of T48 and DC5692, stability of T48 versus T48 E2 R251K, and serum clearance of purified viral particles.</title>
    <p>(
     <bold>A</bold>) WT C57BL/6 mice were inoculated i.v. with RRV strains T48, DC5692, or chimeras between T48 and DC5692 (DC), as shown in the schematic. Viral genomes in the inoculum and in the serum were quantified by RT-qPCR. Mean ± SD. N = 4, representative of two experiments. One-way ANOVA with Tukey’s correction; ***p&lt;0.001, ****p&lt;0.0001. (
     <bold>B</bold>) RRV T48 or T48 E2 R251K particles were incubated in serum at 37°C or 4°C. At the indicated times, infectious virus in the serum was quantified by plaque assay. Mean ± SD. N = 6, two experiments. Two-way ANOVA with Bonferroni’s correction. (
     <bold>C</bold>) WT C57BL/6 mice were inoculated i.v. with purified particles of RRV T48 or T48 E2 R251K derived in serum free media, and viral genomes in inoculum and in the serum at 45 min post-inoculation were quantified by RT-qPCR. Mean ± SD. N = 3, one experiment. Two-tailed, unpaired t-test; ***p&lt;0.001.
    </p>
   </caption>
   <graphic xlink:href="elife-49163-fig7-figsupp1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </fig>
 </p>
</fig>
