<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Considering the potential reversibility of COVID-19, it is essential to integrate recent recommendations in severe viral pneumonia therapy.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
  <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]
 </sup> An experiential strategy, which is summed from the guidelines on ARDS management, is suggested for critically ill COVID-19 patients rescued with ECMO. Implementation of ECMO should be suggested when the standard conventional respiratory care (lung-protective mechanical ventilation strategy, with tidal volume ≤6 mL/kg maintaining plateau pressure &lt;30 cmH
 <sub>2</sub>O and positive end-expiratory pressure ≥10 cmH
 <sub>2</sub>O; use of lung recruitment maneuver, prone positioning, neuromuscular blockade, and sedation) fails to correct respiratory failure.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]
 </sup> The indications for ECMO should be followed: (1) PaO
 <sub>2</sub>/FiO
 <sub>2</sub> &lt;100 mmHg, or alveolar-arterial gradient of the partial pressure of oxygen [P(A-a) O
 <sub>2</sub>] &gt;600 mmHg; (2) ventilator frequency &gt;35 breaths per minute, pH &lt;7.2 with the plateau pressure &gt;30 cmH
 <sub>2</sub>O; (3) Age &lt;65 years; (4) mechanical ventilation &lt;7 days. Alternatively, based on the standard care of the ECMO to Rescue Lung Injury in Severe ARDS trial,
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]
 </sup> ECMO should be considered if the patients meet one of the following criteria: (1) PaO
 <sub>2</sub>/FiO
 <sub>2</sub> &lt;50 mmHg, more than 3 h; (2) PaO
 <sub>2</sub>/FiO
 <sub>2</sub> &lt;80 mmHg, more than 6 h; (3) arterial blood pH &lt;7.25 and PaCO
 <sub>2</sub> &gt;60 mmHg, more than 6 h. Studies have confirmed that early implementation of ECMO (PaO
 <sub>2</sub>/FiO
 <sub>2</sub> between 100 and 150 mmHg) in ARDS can be advantageous. It is proven to minimize respiratory driven pressure, to inhibit pulmonary and systemic inflammation, and to reduce severe dysfunction of lung and extrapulmonary organs.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
  <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]
 </sup> Early “awake ECMO” treatment may be considered in the group of younger patients without extrapulmonary organ disorder or serious co-infection, who are expected to gain more benefits.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
  <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]
 </sup>
</p>
