<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par69">Progeny virus particles are considered the sole mechanism for the dissemination of flaviviruses. Nevertheless, cell-derived extracellular vesicles carrying 
 <italic>Flavivirus</italic> vRNA have recently been shown to be infectious [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111">111</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116">116</xref>], thus representing an alternate mode of virus dissemination. The pathway leading to the secretion of vRNA independently of virus particles is unknown, but parallels can be drawn with the export of cellular RNAs. In recent years, the literature has seen an explosion of studies on the extracellular RNA species that are found in supernatants from cultured cells and in extracellular compartments in vivo [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">117</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119">119</xref>]. RNA is found outside cells as cargo of extracellular vesicles (EVs) or in tight association with RBPs and/or lipids [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">117</xref>]. EVs are heterogeneous in size, and include apoptotic bodies, microvesicles and exosomes. Microvesicles (100–1000 nm) bud from the plasma membrane, and exosomes (40–100 nm) originate from the endocytic pathway [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120">120</xref>]. In the latter, vesicles progress from early to late endosomes, where cargo is sequestered into intraluminal vesicles (ILVs) (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). ILVs arise from the inward budding of the outer endosomal membrane, thus, forming a multivesicular body (MVB). MVBs either fuse with lysosomes for degradation or fuse with the plasma membrane in which case, the ILVs are released into the extracellular milieu as exosomes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121">121</xref>]. By transferring a wide range of molecules, such as proteins, RNAs and lipids, exosomes modulate intercellular communication during homeostatic and pathogenic conditions. For example, EVs from infected cells have been shown to harbour antiviral proteins such as APOBEC3G and STING [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">122</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR123">123</xref>], indicating how immune signals can be transferred to elicit responses in neighbouring cells. On the other hand, EVs are also hijacked by viruses to facilitate dissemination. 
</p>
