<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0095">Our results showed that the proposed diagnostic approach could reduce intravenous antibiotics treatment duration by 4.44 days without compromising patient outcomes. Historically, it has been advised to complete the course of intravenous antibiotics treatment despite the resolution of clinical symptoms. However, there is little evidence to support this practice.
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref> Overuse of antibiotics was associated with increased risk of 
 <italic>Clostridioides difficile</italic> infection, and a prolonged course of intravenous antibiotics may increase the risk of adverse drug events, organ dysfunction, or mortality.
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> It is noteworthy that the identification of respiratory virus alone may not be sufficient to reduce antibiotic use because of the concerns regarding mixed virus-bacteria coinfection, especially influenza with pneumococcus infection.
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>25</sup>
 </xref> Low serum level of PCT may help alleviate the concerns of mixed infection. In addition, communicating the results to the treating physicians is important.
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref> Although we did not have a formal antibiotic stewardship team, the study nurse communicated the results to the treating physicians and promoted antibiotics stewardship. Another finding is the underdiagnosis of influenza in older adult patients. Older adult patients were less likely to undergo a provider-ordered influenza test. They usually lack the typical presentation of influenza-like illness and may present with respiratory distress or confusion.
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>26</sup>
 </xref> A recent study showed that the diagnosis of influenza based on clinical grounds alone was associated with a suboptimal sensitivity of 36% and a specificity of 78%.
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>27</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
