<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>FIG 3 </label>
 <caption>
  <p>MK treatment does not alter influenza virus RNA synthesis. (A) Cultures of human HEK293T cells were transfected with plasmids expressing the polymerase subunits and the NP, as well as with a genomic plasmid expressing a deleted NS RNA segment (clone 23) (
   <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>) in negative polarity. As a control, similar experiments were performed without the PB1 subunit of the viral polymerase (CTRL). Extracts of these cultures were used for 
   <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription with β-globin mRNA as a cap donor and 20 µM MK or the corresponding amount of DMSO. The transcripts were analyzed by denaturing polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis. The mobility of a genome-size marker of 248 nt is indicated to the left. (B) Quantification of the results in panel A as percentages of the transcriptional activity of RNPs treated with DMSO. Average values and standard deviation of three independent experiments are presented. (C, D) Cultures of human A549 cells were infected with influenza virus at an MOI of 3 PFU/cell and then treated with 20 µM MK or the corresponding amount of DMSO. Total cell RNA was isolated at 6 hpi, and rRNA was removed. Viral RNA of each segment was determined by deep sequencing and classified according to the virus segment and polarity. The results were standardized by the total number of reads per sample. The use of total histone mRNA reads for standardization led to similar results. (C) Total accumulation of positive-polarity RNA of each viral segment. (D) Total accumulation of negative-polarity RNA of each viral segment. The data in panels C and D are presented as averages and standard deviations of three independent biological replicates. (E) Cultures of human A549 cells were infected with influenza virus at an MOI of 3 PFU/cell and then treated with 20 µM MK or the corresponding amount of DMSO in the presence or absence of cycloheximide (100 µg/ml). Total cell RNA was isolated at 6 hpi, and the accumulation of viral RNA was determined by RT-qPCR with probes specific for the NP segment. The accumulation of viral mRNA in cells treated with cycloheximide (CHX) and/or MK or not treated is presented as the average and standard deviation of three determinations.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="mbo0021627760003" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
