<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In order for progeny viruses to infect new cells, cleavage of the immature surface protein hemagglutinin (HA) into the biologically activated and infectious form is required (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Influenza viruses that contain a monobasic cleavage site can be cleaved by trypsin-like serine proteases such as human airway trypsin-like protease (HAT), transmembrane serine protease 2 (TMPRSS2), TMPRSS4, or matriptase present in the human respiratory tract (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). In the human CNS, expression of HAT in the cerebellum (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>) and matriptase mRNA in the frontal and temporal cortices, hippocampus, and cerebellum have been reported (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). Viruses that contain a multibasic cleavage site (MBCS), such as the HPAI H5N1 virus, can be cleaved by ubiquitously expressed subtilisin-like proteases such as furin and PC5/6 (
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). This MBCS is an important factor contributing to the ability to spread systemically, including in the CNS. Although extrarespiratory spread of HPAI H5N1 virus depends on the presence of the MBCS in ferrets, insertion of an MBCS into a seasonal H3N2 virus did not result in efficient systemic replication in ferrets, suggesting that more factors are necessary (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Other viruses that are associated with CNS invasion in mice or ferrets are 1918 H1N1 and A/WSN/33 viruses (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). These viruses do not possess an MBCS but use a different protease-mediated mechanism for HA cleavage, allowing trypsin-independent replication. Taken together, virus receptor specificity, receptor availability on host cells, protease distribution and availability, and HA cleavage mechanism all seem to play important roles in influenza virus infection and cell tropism as well as replication efficiency in the respiratory tract and beyond.
</p>
