<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite the fact that our respondents were asked to classify drugs into three categories, we decided to analyze the 4th, pooled category “drugs with renal recommendations,” assuming that both “reduce dose” and “avoid” categories indicate that the respondents are aware of some renal precautions, which is potentially less harmful than incorrect classification as “drug without renal recommendations.” The other reason for such analysis was discordance between sources as to recommendations for some drugs, eg, ibandronic acid. According to 
 <italic>The Renal Drug Handbook</italic> by Ashley and Dunleavy,
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> this drug should be administered with extended time between doses in subjects with eGFR &lt; 30 mL/min/1.73m
 <sup>2</sup>, which was classified as “dose reduction” for the purpose of this study. In contrast, this medication should be avoided in subjects with severe renal impairment according to the information on the Drugs.com web page.
 <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> The use of the pooled category instead of “avoid” category resulted in an increase in correct answers for ibandronic acid form ~40 to 70–80%. A similar pattern could be seen for other drugs with divergent recommendations: sotalol and metoclopramide. The problem of conflicting dosing information between different pharmacotherapy sources has been previously described.
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> To address this issue, the American Geriatric Society published consensus guidelines for 18 primarily renally cleared oral medications commonly taken by older adults; for a further 12 drugs the geriatric clinical pharmacist expert panel did not reach consensus.
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> A list of 20 drugs (including 12 medications not listed in the consensus guidelines) that should be avoided or requiring dose adjustment in subjects with a specific degree of renal impairment was also added in 2015 to the American Geriatrics Society Beers criteria for potentially inappropriate medications in older adults.
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Three more drugs were added to the American Geriatrics Society 2019 Updated AGS Beers Criteria.
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> However, drugs listed in the consensus guidelines and Beers criteria constitute only a small portion of all medications with renal precautions. The question also arises whether these documents are known to physicians who are not specialists in geriatrics.
</p>
