<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0015">Outbreaks of acute disease on farms and in animal shelters greatly facilitate virus-disease association studies if appropriate data and sample collection occurs. The affected animals should all exhibit pathogen-specific markers of infection, such as sero-conversion or the presence of a newly characterized virus. The pathogenicity of a new virus can also be tested in animals following direct inoculation with viral isolates (minimally passaged to prevent attenuation), the original biological samples (if shown to contain no other virus by metagenomics), or by synthesizing the genome and transfecting it 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> to generate infectious particles. Because of their protected status, such inoculations are not feasible in endangered species where more indirect means of testing disease causation, akin to the situation for novel human viruses, are required [
 <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. By identifying unusual symptoms or disease outbreaks, both academic and private veterinarians and scientists also contribute to the identification of previously unknown or emerging animal pathogens. Federal departments such as the USDA and CDC, state organizations concerned with fish and game or food and agriculture, and local government groups involved in animal care and control can also identify disease outbreaks in wild, farm or companion animals and collect samples for further studies. The Humane Society and the Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals, by closely monitoring and promoting animal health, may also detect and report early signs of emerging infections. International organizations such as the Food and Agriculture and World Health Organizations of the United Nations, World Organization for Animal Health (i.e. OIE), and ProMED can also assist in the recognition of emerging animal health problems, dissemination of information, and in coordinating international collaborations (
 <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). A growing realization of animals as the source of most emerging human and animal infections has led to the One Health Initiative to foster collaborations between physicians, veterinarians, and scientists to monitor the exchange of infectious agents between species [
 <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].
</p>
