<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The remarkable diversity of viral populations might indicate high host specificity of viruses in insects, which would support the idea that viruses are evolutionarily specialized to different ecological niches (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). However, the host barriers are not absolute. A significant risk for viral spillover is associated with trophic interactions, including both antagonism (e.g., herbivory, predation, and parasitism) and mutualism (e.g., pollination), in both directions during contact. The observations in our study demonstrate the possibility of interspecies virus transmission in cases in which predator-prey or host-parasitoid encounters occur, including but not limited to insect-insect interactions. For example, the ectoparasitic mite 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">Varroa destructor</named-content> has facilitated the global spread of deformed wing virus among populations of honeybees, as this method of transmission has allowed circumvention of ecological or evolutionary barriers to infect new hosts (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Increased direct or indirect contact might confer great opportunities for insect viruses to cross host boundaries. In this respect, the distribution and composition of viruses in insectivorous animals are extensively shaped by insect diet, as indicated by previously reported evidence from bats (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). It is commonly thought that hematophagous insects (e.g., mosquitoes, sandflies, and midges) carry a panel of viral pathogens which may be transmitted to humans or animal reservoirs through biting or feeding (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). The real risk may be greater than that represented by those examples. Numerous related virus species have been observed in a wide range of insects and can be traced back to the time of host specialization. In most cases, these wild insects do not appear to have direct contact with humans and it remains to be determined whether these viruses possess heterogeneous infectivity and pathogenicity for humans. Nevertheless, concerns about the potential risk of virus spillover are increasing in accordance with the rapid expansion of human activity and abrupt ecological change (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). Unlike animal viruses, most plant viruses are transmitted to their host plants by vectors such as insects, fungi, and nematodes (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). Many insects ingest viruses while feeding on the diseased plants (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>), and these viruses have developed the adaptive capacity to manipulate their insect vectors to facilitate their dispersion (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). The indispensable role of intermediate vectors in virus transmission and spread might explain the anomalous number of plant viruses observed in insects.
</p>
