<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<boxed-text id="BB1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
 <caption>
  <title>Executive summary</title>
 </caption>
 <sec id="S0017">
  <title>Coronavirus</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>In late 2019, novel severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) emerged in Wuhan/China, causing the COVID-19 disease and the WHO declared a pandemic.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>The seven α- and β-coronaviruses (CoVs) that were identified are 229E, NL63, OC43, HKU1, SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S0018">
  <title>Therapeutic approaches</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>Several conventional therapeutic approaches have been developed against COVID-19 including vaccines and antiviral agents.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S0019">
  <title>Vaccines</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>Several vaccine candidates for COVID-19 have entered the clinical phase, showing promising efficacy such as PiCoVacc from Sinovac Biotech, INO-4800 construct from Inovio Pharma, Ad5-nCoV from CanSino Biologics, mRNA-1273 from Moderna and LV-SMENP-DC &amp; COVID-19/aAPC from Shenzhen Geno-Immune Medical Institute.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S0020">
  <title>Antiviral agents</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>Repositioned drugs such as remdesivir, favipiravir, ribavirin and chloroquine have been tested clinically against COVID-19.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S0021">
  <title>Nanomedicine &amp; CoVs</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>Nanomedicine, the medical application of nanotechnology, has an important contribution in accelerating the development of promising clinically translatable therapeutics against COVID-19 in the field of vaccination, diagnosis and treatment.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S0022">
  <title>Nanoparticle-based vaccines against CoVs</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>Spike protein is the prime candidate for nanovaccines because it is the main attachment factor and immunodominant antigen in CoVs.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S0023">
  <title>Nanoparticle-based vaccines against CoVs</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>These are designed to improve vaccine efficacy and immunization strategies. These nanovaccines are mainly developed via self-assembly or functionalization of gold nanoparticles (NPs).</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S0024">
  <title>NP-based diagnosis for CoVs</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>Diagnosis could be achieved through extraction and/or detection of SARS-CoVs-2 by several types of NPs such as magnetic NPs and gold NPs.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S0025">
  <title>NP-based therapies for CoVs</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>These therapies target the different steps in CoV’s lifecycle and viral entry.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
</boxed-text>
