<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0040">MERS-CoV PCR-positive samples were subjected to next generation sequencing (NGS) using established methods [
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>]. Briefly, clinical samples were screened with RT-PCR, with amplification targeting both the upE and ORF1A for confirmation. NGS was performed on nucleic acid extracted from real-time PCR confirmed cases of MERS-CoV. 50 μL of nucleic acid was generated from 200 μL of tracheal aspirate or from a nasopharyngeal or throat swab with automated processing. PCR amplification of DNA amplicons covering the entire MERS-CoV genome were prepared. The PCR amplicons for each sample were pooled for Illumina library (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA) preparation with each sample processed to include a unique barcode sequence. Standard MiSeq 150 nt paired-end reads were generated. Sequence data were de-multiplexed into sample-specific readsets, processed to remove adapter and primer sequences at the ends of reads, and trimmed from their 3′ end until the median Phred quality score was &gt;35, discarding reads smaller than 125 nucleotides using QUASR [
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The processed readsets were 
 <italic>de novo</italic> assembled into large contiguous sequences (contigs) using SPAdes v.3.13.0 [
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Final quality control of genomes included checking intactness of open reading frames (ORFs) for full genomes, comparison of the obtained sequences and the encoded proteins with reference sequences retrieved from GenBank. All single nucleotide polymorphisms in the outbreak set were verified by counting all quality controlled short reads mapping across the position. A total of 15 samples yielded &gt;80% of the 30119 nt MERS-CoV genome and 18 samples yielded &gt;50% genomes which were examined in detail. The 18 assembled genomes were aligned using MAFFT v.7.42 [
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] and manually checked in Aliview. [
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], and the both ends were trimmed to the longest shared sequence (final length 30,123 nt). As previously described [
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], a Bayesian phylogenetic tree was inferred using MrBayes v.3.2.7a [
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] under the best fitted model of substitution estimated in IQTREE [
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], run in duplicate with 1 million generations with sampling performed every 1000 generations and with a removal of 25% burn-in. Three independent chains were run and checked for chain convergence.
</p>
