<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In three subjects, the symptoms of the common cold—one caused by influenza B virus and the others by respiratory syncytial virus A and B—developed during the 9-hour flight from Helsinki to Seoul. Two patients seemed to transmit the illness to another team member during the flight. Long-haul air travel is a well-known risk factor for the transmission of contagious diseases. One person with influenza can transmit the infection to 5–10 people during an intercontinental flight.
 <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Two cases of coronavirus OC43 infection were most probably travelling during the incubation period of the infection (3.5 days) and developed the illness within 2–3 days after arrival in the Olympic Village.
 <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27 34</xref> In addition, the first cases of rhinovirus and metapneumovirus infections were detected during the first week, suggesting that these infections also originated in Finland.
 <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> In addition to direct or indirect contact and droplets, respiratory viruses can spread via exhaled aerosols, even while talking.
 <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35 36</xref> Viruses may stay infectious on a surface for hours or days. The most commonly detected coronavirus 229E, stays infectious on common surfaces for at least 7 days.
 <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> Interestingly, it was recently shown that viruses can also spread through toilet flushing.
 <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> Ultimately, 7 clusters of different respiratory virus infections were recorded. Important factors in the transmission of the viruses were the housing with other athletes and the sport discipline (
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>). Competition venues may be a favourable environment for virus transmission. Rigorous hand washing, the use of hand sanitisers, enhanced disinfection and strict patient isolation were likely to prevent the spread of viruses within the team but were apparently not very effective (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">figure 2</xref>). This is due to the multifactorial transmission mechanisms of viral infections.
 <xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>
</p>
