<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>PPR is a disease of domestic livestock that is a threat to conservation of endangered wildlife small ruminant species. To date, there is no evidence that wildlife can maintain the disease in a way significant to the global epidemiological control of PPR. The possible areas for research at the livestock/wildlife interface have already been extensively reviewed [
 <xref rid="B12-viruses-12-00313" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. But is missing in this review, the research on wildlife and non-conventional species as well as the role of wildlife and wildlife/livestock interface in the epidemiology of PPR in different regions in order to address knowledge gaps. Epidemiology of the disease could focus on the potential role of wildlife and other animal species (including non-typical species in surveillance) to inform sheep and goat vaccination plans (PPRV transmission studies using virulent PPRV strains in sheep and goats and also non-typical species), There are now convincing reports demonstrating the ability of PPRV to cross the species barrier. Indeed, PPRV can infect animal species other than small ruminants, with dromedaries, wild goats, pigs and cattle reportedly being identified with PPRV [
 <xref rid="B12-viruses-12-00313" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-12-00313" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-viruses-12-00313" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-viruses-12-00313" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-12-00313" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. It is currently unclear whether these infections are relevant from an epidemiological and eradication perspective; however, it is essential to fully understand the role of wildlife in the spread and potential maintenance of PPRV in the environment in order to be able to initiate successful control strategies. Along these lines, further support is also needed to help local authorities understand and differentially diagnose PPR from a variety of diseases that cause similar respiratory problems and mortality in small ruminants.
</p>
