<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To monitor quasispecies in each infected plant, young apical leaves were harvested at 15, 30, and 45 dpi (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>) and lyophilized. DNA was extracted following the Edwards' procedure (Edwards et al., 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>) with some modifications. From each sample, 8 mg of dried tissue were ground in a 1.5 ml Eppendorf tube with liquid nitrogen, and 400 μl of extraction buffer [200 mM Tris-HCl, 200 mM NaCl, 25 mM EDTA, SDS 0.5% (w/v), pH 7.5, 0.1% β-mercaptoethanol] added. After vortexing at 37°C for 2 min extracts were centrifuged at 12,000 × 
 <italic>g</italic> at room temperature for 5 min. The supernatants were transferred to a new tube and mixed with 1 volume of phenol:chloroform (1:1). The aqueous phase was transferred to a new tube and mixed with 1 volume of isopropanol. After 2 min at room temperature, nucleic acids were recovered by centrifugation at 12,000 × 
 <italic>g</italic> at room temperature for 5 min. The pellet was washed with 70% ethanol, dried and resuspended in 200 μl of RTE buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 10 mM EDTA pH 8.0, 0.1% RNase A) by incubation at 65°C for 10 min. Viral DNA from total DNA extracts was amplified by rolling-circle amplification (RCA) with ϕ 29 DNA polymerase according to Inoue-Nagata et al. (Inoue-Nagata et al., 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>) using the TempliPhi DNA Amplification Kit (GE Healthcare). For all samples, 400 to 500 ng/μl of the amplification product measured by UV-spectrophotometry and gel electrophoresis were obtained. Full-lenght genomic consensus sequences were obtained by direct sequencing (Macrogen Inc., South Korea) of RCA products amplified from total DNA extractions. Primers used to sequence consensus sequences of TYLCSV, TYLCV, and TYLCMaV are indicated in Table 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Sanger sequencing was preferred over NGS due to the difficulty of the latter to discriminate between the error of the technology and the error rate of the viruses, which is paramount for quasispecies analysis.
</p>
