<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0120">Given the wide diversity and prevalence of contributing factors shown above, the public is exposed continually to myriad toxic stressors, with each individual being exposed to a distinct combination of toxic stressors over his/her lifetime (
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">Tsatsakis et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Hernández et al., 2020</xref>). As several studies have shown (
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Kostoff et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Laetz et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Hernandez et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Vardavas et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Docea et al., 2017</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Kalogeraki et al., 2017</xref>), the broader the combination of toxic stressors and the higher the concentrations of its constituents, the higher the likelihood of adverse combined effects. For infectious diseases, the effect of the combination of toxic stressors will determine the degradation/dysfunction of the immune system, and therefore the severity of the consequences of viral exposure. Different people will be exposed to distinct toxic stressors combinations, and will respond differently according to the composition of the toxic stressors combinations and a person's genetic makeup and overall level of health. There can be substantial synergies among the constituents of a given toxic stressors combination and, depending on the concentration and toxicity profile of the constituents, can result in enhanced adverse effects from the combination (
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Docea et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Kostoff et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Ginzburg et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Schulz et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr">Zmyslony et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Borman et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Tsatsakis et al., 2019a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Tsatsakis et al., 2019b</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Tsatsakis et al., 2019c</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Tsatsakis et al., 2019d</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr">Tsiaoussis et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Sergievich et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Margina et al., 2019</xref>). The key concept here is that the 
 <bold>
  <italic>virus-toxic stressors combination nexus</italic>
 </bold> is determining the ultimate health outcome, not necessarily any one of the constituents in isolation.
</p>
