<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>On 31 December 2019, the Word Health Organization reported for the first time on an epidemic of lower respiratory tract infection in Wuhan, in the Chinese province of Hubei. The causal agent was soon identified as Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2), a coronavirus (CoV), and the associated disease was named coronavirus disease 19 (COVID-19) (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). CoVs are positive-sense single-stranded RNA viruses resembling a crown under microscopy due to the presence of spike (S) glycoproteins on the viral envelope. There are four types of CoVs: αCoVs, βCoVs, δCoVs, and γCoVs. SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV, and SARS-CoV-2 are zoonotic (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), first infecting animals and then spreading to humans. βCoVs, which include SARS-CoV-2, are thought to originate in bats (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), among other species. These viruses can cause respiratory and enteric diseases in different animal species. In humans, HCoV-OC43 and HCoV-HKU1 (αCoVs), and HCoV-229E and HCoV-NL63 (βCoVs) can cause the common cold and self-limiting infection of the lower respiratory tract in immunocompetent individuals in seasonal periods (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Two previous epidemics have, however, been caused by CoVs; these were similar to the current pandemic, though with higher mortality rates, and were caused by the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) and middle east respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) and affected many countries (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Although they led to many research studies, expanding our knowledge of the viruses, the COVID-19 epidemic has had a far greater global impact. One as-yet unknown aspect of SARS-CoV-2 is its potential short- and long-term impact on the central nervous system. In this respect, although the rate of neurological symptoms associated with infection is not high (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), the possibility of subsequent effects of central nerve system (CNS) infection has been suggested by many authors (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>–
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). To address these questions, we need experimental models based on advances in biomedical research both 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>. We review these models in the present article.
</p>
