<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par199">HIV-1 encephalitis is characterized by (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">26.3a–j</xref>)
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par200">Multiple disseminated foci composed of microglia, macrophages, and multinucleated giant cells (MGCs). The foci are predominantly located in the cortex, deep gray matter, and the white matter.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par201">The multinucleated giant cells (MGC) are the hallmark for HIV-1 encephalitis.
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par202">They contain up to 20 round or elongated and basophilic nuclei which are usually arranged at the periphery of the cell.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par203">The cytoplasm is eosinophilic and appears densely stained in the center and vacuolated at the periphery.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par204">The cells are of monocyte/histiocyte lineage which includes microglia and macrophages.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par205">They are derived from HIV-1-mediated fusion of infected microglia and macrophages.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par206">The nucleic acids of HIV proteins have been demonstrated to be located in their cytoplasm.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par207">In their absence, the presence of HIV-antigen or HIV nucleic acids has to be demonstrated either by immunohistochemistry, i.e., gp41 and p24 (Fig. 
    <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">26.3j</xref>) or by in situ hybridization.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par208">HIVE usually occurs in the later stages of the AIDS infection.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par209">The electron microscopical analysis revealed retroviral particles either free in the cytoplasm or in cytoplasmic cisternae.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par210">Microglia/macrophages and MGC are capable of HIV synthesis and, thus, constitute the major reservoir and vehicle for the spread of the virus.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par211">Synonyms previously used: giant cell encephalitis, multifocal giant cell encephalitis, multinucleated cell encephalitis, subacute encephalitis</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
