<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0265">Cytotoxic lymphocytes mainly available as cytotoxic T lymphocytes (CTLs) and natural killer (NK) cells, these are essential for limiting the dangerous viral infections. Meijuan Zheng et al. reported that CD8+ T-cells and NK cells were significantly decreased, while NKG2A expression was dramatically increased in SARS-CoV-2 infected patients [
 <xref rid="bb0890" ref-type="bibr">178</xref>]. NK cells recognize the NKG2D, which is an activating receptor of NK cells involved in clearing the virus infected cells. Chimeric antigen receptors (CAR) exhibit an important role in modifying the NK cells and play an essential role in cell-based immunotherapy for treating cancer and viral diseases [
 <xref rid="bb0895" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>]. Actually, NK cells have shorter half-life and their activity was improved by IL-15 super agonist (sIL-15/IL-15Rɑ chimeric protein) upto 20 times more and ultimately increases the target cytotoxicity [
 <xref rid="bb0900" ref-type="bibr">180</xref>]. In general Granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF) neutralizes the CAR-T cell-mediated cytokine release syndrome (CRS) and neurotoxicity [
 <xref rid="bb0905" ref-type="bibr">181</xref>]. Chongqing Public Health Medical Center has constructed and prepared the universal off-the-shelf IL-15 super agonist- and GM-CSF neutralizing scFv-secreting NKG2D-ACE2 CAR-NK derived from cord blood. This developed vaccine system inhibited expression of the spike protein of SARS-CoV-2 and suppressed the NKG2DL on the surface of infected cells with ACE2. Additionally, IL-15 super agonist enhances the NK cells activity and CRS is prevented by GM-CSF neutralizing scFv. Further, ACE2 CAR-NK cells inhibited SARS-CoV-2 infection safely and effectively. These advanced targeted cell therapy strategies need to be evaluated under controlled clinical trials, which is already initiated currently (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04280224" id="ir0330" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04280224</ext-link> and 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04324996" id="ir0335" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04324996</ext-link>).Apart from the above mentioned pharmacological interventions, few more drugs are illustrated in 
 <xref rid="t0045" ref-type="table">Table 9</xref> about their anti-SARS-CoV and anti-MERS-CoV activity.
</p>
