<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Genomic data has become an important aspect of contemporary infectious disease surveillance ( 
 <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Gardy &amp; Loman, 2018</xref>). Yet for rabies and other neglected endemic diseases it is underused - largely limited to academic studies and retrospective analyses with more limited actionable outputs. Even well-funded research projects can take up to six months from sample collection to dissemination of results (e.g. 
 <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Brunker 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Boykin 
  <italic>et al</italic>., 2019
 </xref>), impeding the quick decision-making necessary for timely disease control. Using our MinION-based sequencing protocol, RABV samples can be sequenced in-country in a matter of days and at a cost much lower than third-party sequencing facilities ( 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3C</xref>), which typically requires the export of samples. We envision two broad applications of our protocols, for: 1) cost-effective batch sequencing of archived samples to characterize circulating RABV diversity, and 2) rapid 
 <italic>in situ</italic> genomic surveillance of new cases, particularly during the endgame when such information can target appropriate responses. Many countries have repositories of archived tissue samples from rabid animals, which could be sequenced in bulk and therefore at low cost. These samples are potentially very valuable to characterise historical RABV diversity in a locality from which to compare to contemporary sequences. This comparison can show whether lineages continue to circulate or have disappeared, perhaps as a result of rabies control efforts. The latter option of rapid 
 <italic>in-situ</italic> sequencing makes less use of cost-cutting measures such as multiplex sequencing, but the benefit of genomic surveillance to gain time-critical insights into persisting or re-emerging RABV far outweigh the expense of re-emergence. Further options to reduce costs when sample numbers are low include combining runs with other pathogens or using ONT’s low-cost, lower throughput Flongle flowcells (e.g. 
 <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Grädel 
  <italic>et al.,</italic> 2019
 </xref>).
</p>
