<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>NS1 functions as a virulence factor for influenza viruses 
 <italic>via</italic> interaction with different factors, exerting diverse functions to ensure efficient viral propagation. Among these, inhibiting both IFN production and counteracting the anti-viral effects of IFN-stimulated genes, namely, PKR and 2′5′-oligoadenylate synthetase (OAS)/RNase L, are well-described NS1-mediated actions that facilitate establishment at an early stage of infection (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Hale et al., 2008</xref>). Noticeably, suppression of cytokine expression (IFN and TNF-α) was compromised in NS1031 RG-AIV at an early stage of infection (6 hpi), which is consistent with its defective inhibition of PKR activation (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>), a factor potentially responsible for its poor infection outcomes (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2A</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Although NS1 sequence polymorphisms are present at many of the signatures involved in such intermolecular interactions, including PKR (highlighted in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>, box 2), and previous studies have identified residues R35, R46, I123/M124, and K126/N127 as critical for NS1–PKR interaction (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Min et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Schierhorn et al., 2017</xref>), these residues are completely conserved in NS1031 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>); thus, NS1 polymorphism cannot explain the low PKR association in NS1031. However, most research on key residues contributing to NS1 functionality has been conducted by a single amino acid change and loss-of-function studies, whereas reassortant viruses in our study possessed a high frequency of sequence polymorphisms spreading out over a large coding region of NS1 isolates, and, thus, it is likely that our local viruses possessed novel residues affecting PKR activation.
</p>
