<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>NS1 demonstrated a high frequency of variation at the C-terminus, not only in amino acid composition but also in length, among the four NS1 isolates analyzed in this study (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>); in particular, NS1680 carried a deletion of 218–230 aa. Residues 215–237 of NS1 interact with and impair the function of cellular poly(A)-binding protein II (PABP II), affecting maturation of pre-mRNAs, including IFN-β mRNA (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2007</xref>). We found that consistent with this knowledge, DF-1 cells infected with NS1680 had higher levels of IFN-β and TNF-α mRNA at 12 hpi. Moreover, four residues at the C-terminus of NS1, namely, PDZ-binding motifs (PBMs), have emerged as virulence determinants that modulate viral pathogenicity by mediating the association with cellular PDZ-domain-containing proteins that are involved in numerous cellular processes related to viral infection (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Javier and Rice, 2011</xref>). Three sets of PBM sequences exist, with RSE/KV predominating the NS1 proteins of influenza viruses with human origins, whereas EPEV predominates in AIVs (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Jackson et al., 2008</xref>), with the exception of ESEV, which predominates avian H5N1 virus isolates from human infections (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Bao et al., 2007</xref>). Diverse PBM sequences were found in our four NS1 isolates; EPEV characterized both NS0702 and NS683, ESEV characterized NS1031, and NS1680 lacked PBM altogether. ESEV PBM is responsible for the interaction of H5N1 NS1 with cellular PDZ proteins, namely, Dlg1 and Scribble, which ultimately leads to disruption of the host tight junction and to increasing permeability of infected monolayers (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Golebiewski et al., 2011</xref>); these pathologies are possible mechanisms of the severe disease associated with HPAIV H5N1. Taken together, it appears that substitution of the NS gene of AIV studied herein influences a spectrum of characteristics related to virulence and infectivity, and variations that occur at one particular known signature is unlikely to be fully responsible for the effect of an NS1 variant on countering PKR activation or modulating infection efficiency.
</p>
