<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As already mentioned in the chapters above, in principal food availability (as, e.g., beechnut mast) has an influence on population dynamics of bank voles. In contrast to other rodent species (e.g., 
 <italic>M. agrestis</italic> and 
 <italic>M. arvalis</italic>) bank voles may be more dependent on tree seeds such as beechnut. Data from Lower Saxony from 16 years on beech fructification and the abundance of bank voles showed that the fruits have a positive effect on the population in the next year. For negative trends the context between fruit and vole was true in 75% of the cases (Kühn et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">2011</xref>). As beech forest might be beneficial habitats for this species and populations may reach high densities some investigations were performed in Baden-Württemberg. There highest beech forest cover was found in the Swabian Alb (17.7%) and lowest cover in the eastern and middle regions and major cities of Baden-Wuerttemberg (1.6%). Data on annual mast production of beechnuts was obtained between 2000 and 2006. Cumulative incidence (2001–2007) of PUUV infections in Baden-Wuerttemberg is reported highest in the Swabian Alp region. Highest maximum incidence rates for human PUUV cases ranged from 2.28 per 100,000 population in 2007 to 1.16 per 100,000 population in 2006, which is considered a year with beech crop failure (Schwarz et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B147">2009</xref>). For the year 2010 a growth of the bank vole rodent population could be expected as at two study sites in Swabian Alb and around Münster there was an enhanced beechnut mast in 2009 (Jacob and Ulrich, personal communication). However, the 2010 PUUV outbreak in Germany again showed significant local differences. In conclusion, there exists no enough valid, longitudinal collected and critically summarized data on mast, rodent populations, and associated diseases in Germany as it was also discussed for Belgium and France.
</p>
