<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="f1" fig-type="figure" position="float">
 <label>Figure 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Mean values for 
   <italic>R</italic>
   <sub>0</sub> of the tick 
   <italic>I. scapularis</italic> obtained in tick model simulations using observed temperature data (ANUSPLIN: 1971-2010), and projected temperature data obtained from the RCM CRCM4.2.3 [according to Special Report on Emissions Scenarios (SRES) A2 emissions scenario] for (
   <italic>A</italic>) Southern Ontario, (
   <italic>B</italic>) Huron Ontario, (
   <italic>C</italic>) Upper Southern Ontario, (
   <italic>D</italic>) South-Western Quebec, (
   <italic>E</italic>) the Boreal region of central Ontario and Quebec, (
   <italic>F</italic>) Old Lyme (Connecticut), and (
   <italic>G</italic>) Fort McCoy (Wisconsin). The black arrows in each panel reference the first identification of Lyme disease in the United States (
   <xref rid="r94" ref-type="bibr">Wood and Lafferty 2013</xref>). The green arrows indicate the year of first field detection of 
   <italic>I. scapularis</italic> populations within the Canadian clusters. (
   <italic>A</italic>) In Southern Ontario, these dates are 1976 for Long Point (
   <xref rid="r92" ref-type="bibr">Watson and Anderson 1976</xref>), 1996 for Point Pelee (
   <xref rid="r38" ref-type="bibr">Lindsay et al. 1999a</xref>), 1999 for Rondeau Park (
   <xref rid="r53" ref-type="bibr">Morshed et al. 2003</xref>), and 2001 for Turkey Point (
   <xref rid="r83" ref-type="bibr">Scott et al. 2004</xref>). (
   <italic>D</italic>) The date is 2007 for a number of sites in South-Western Quebec (
   <xref rid="r69" ref-type="bibr">Ogden et al. 2008</xref>); the estimated numbers of Census Subdivisions (CSDs) with established 
   <italic>I. scapularis</italic> populations in South-Western Quebec, based on passive surveillance data (
   <xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr">Leighton et al. 2012</xref>), is shown as the green dashed line. The range of 
   <italic>R</italic>
   <sub>0</sub> values produced in simulations for 2020–2069 of CRCM4.2.3 and five other GCMs and RCMs is indicated by the error bar to the right of each panel except for the U.S. sites (
   <italic>F,G</italic>), for which only output from CRCM4.2.3 was available. Full details of all simulations are presented in Supplemental Material, Figure S6.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ehp.1307799.g001" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
