<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par63">In Barcelona, women reported all three of these barriers to harm reduction services. Multiple participants reported separation from their children and rejection from programmes for women who have experienced violence due to drug use and/or incarceration. Once their children had been removed from their care, several women reported difficulties in having them returned after release from prison. Social exclusion driven by the physical isolation of being in prison and discrimination against women who use drugs or women who have been incarcerated prevent them from meeting the administrative requirements necessary to take on care of their children. This was expressed by two female participants:
 <disp-quote>
  <p id="Par64">Do you think that I wouldn’t prefer a regular job? But I haven’t had a contract for over 20 years and I am a mum with 3 kids. Two of them are in a governmental juvenile facility because they consider that I don’t have enough money to provide for them. They think that my children are better in a centre that with their mother. I love them so much, and they love me too. They want to stay with me all the time, when they finish school they come for a visit, and we are together for the weekend.</p>
  <p id="Par65">When I was released from jail after 6 years for trafficking everything was different. My community was gone and I was alone. I tried to find a job, but who would give me a job, with my history of incarceration and no experience… I needed money to be able to recover my kids.</p>
 </disp-quote> Interactions with law enforcement officers, notably being targeted for searches, were also commonly reported. In one case, this referred specifically to interrupting a community organisation of women who use drugs:
 <disp-quote>
  <p id="Par66">We were leaving from the XADUD [Catalan Network of Women who Use Drugs], where we were organizing for the feminist demonstration and cops stopped and searched us. We try to explain, and I think that they knew that we did not have anything stolen, for sure they knew that we were not selling. Anyway, I think that they were just bored.</p>
 </disp-quote> While services such as NSPs and OAT are generally available in Spanish prisons, including those in Catalonia, women reported that incarceration still stood as a significant barrier to accessing such services. One former prison medical worker expressed concern that restrictions on access to harm reduction in prison were greater for women than for men:
 <disp-quote>
  <p id="Par67">Women are made invisible, with the excuse that there are fewer of them – only 4% of the prison population. So, their needs are ignored.</p>
 </disp-quote> With regard to the NSPs in prisons, participants reported that the existence of such a programme does not mean that people will use it. Barriers include concerns about poor quality, insufficient or inappropriate equipment given out by the NSPs:
 <disp-quote>
  <p id="Par68">The kit they give you as alcohol wipes and a syringe, but where are you supposed to cook the substance, in a spoon? They don’t give you a cooker, they don’t give you basic paraphernalia. The secondary complications of cooking the substance in something unsterile are serious.</p>
 </disp-quote> As has been documented in prison NSPs elsewhere (such as in Canada [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>]), a lack of anonymity can result in punitive responses from prison security staff:
 <disp-quote>
  <p id="Par69">Once you go and request a syringe they don’t leave you alone. They follow you, because they know you’re going to inject. They know you’re going to inject, so they watch you, they search for you.</p>
  <p id="Par70">They hassle you. They look for the substance you’re going to consume.[…] The NSP should be free from consequences like that, it should be anonymous and you shouldn’t have to be hassled once you’ve used it. Because it’s true that a lot of women stop going to it and just use whatever type of utensil or paraphernalia, which isn’t appropriate.</p>
 </disp-quote> In a finding not noted elsewhere in the literature, women reported that while OAT is widely available, it is commonly misused by prison authorities. Several women mentioned overmedication of methadone, as well as benzodiazepines:
 <disp-quote>
  <p id="Par71">When I went in, they kept giving me methadone and pills. They give them to you quite happily. There’s brutal overmedication.</p>
 </disp-quote>
</p>
