<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This scenario reflects the program costs of secondary distribution of HIVST as currently being rolled out by the Ugandan MOH. The MOH is providing HIVST to all pregnant women who attend public ANC services, regardless of their HIV status. Instead of individual counseling as performed in the Obumu intervention for PWLHIV in order to assess risk of social harm if a woman discloses her HIV status and provide strategies on how to approach male partners with HIVST kits, clinic staff conduct group counseling sessions, with group sizes ranging from 20 to 70 depending on the facility size. Through time and motion observations at the Obumu study clinic, we estimated an average of 30 women attended the daily HIVST group counseling sessions, which are led by nurses and peer support counselors, and last for approximately one hour. The sessions consist of HIVST training and demonstration, counseling on strategies for discussing HIV self-testing with male partners, and instructions on how to encourage men who test positive to seek confirmatory testing. At the end of the session, women are offered an HIVST kit and asked to write their contact information into a MOH record book for follow-up and MOH monitoring and evaluation. We assumed that 80% of women in these MOH status-neutral group counseling sessions agreed to take an HIVST kit. While male partners in the previous two scenarios were encouraged to link to the clinic for confirmatory testing regardless of their HIVST result, with HIV-negative men being offered PrEP, we assumed that only men who self-test HIV-positive are encouraged to come to the clinic in the MOH scenario, reflecting current HIVST delivery guidelines in Uganda. Based on communications with staff at the MOH, we assumed initial provider training on HIVST distribution was conducted by two trainers from the MOH, who led one-time training sessions at designated facilities. Each facility training lasted a total of 1.5 days (12 h over 3 days), and involved at least 2 nurses/midwives, 4 peer counselors, a data manager, and a laboratory technician. Supervision of training, and program monitoring and evaluation were conducted by an MOH representative. </p>
