<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The presence of putative low fitness variants in mutant spectra could be the result of compensatory mutations to maintain RNA secondary structure. Further, they may be maintained by complementation or by reduced purifying selection due to a release from the constraint of whitefly transmission in the conducted experiment. Our analysis of mutant spectra identified insertions, deletions, nonsense mutations and readthrough mutations. Such changes often have deleterious or lethal effects on proteins. Others may affect secondary structure or fall in regulatory elements needed to maintain structure for function like some of the mutations found in the IR adjacent to or within a regulatory element (see Table 
 <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref> and Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). Among mutations found in TYLCSV, TYLCV and TYLCMaV during infection time-courses in the four hosts (included in Table 
 <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref>) we highlight the following. The nonsense mutation Q81Stop (C395T) found in the TYLCV V2 protein in infected common bean lacks residues C84 and C86 that have been shown to be essential for PTGS suppression and interaction with the tomato SGS3 protein (Zrachya et al., 
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Glick et al., 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). The 
 <italic>Rep</italic> missense mutation C2466T in TYLCMaV-infected resistant tomato, results in an E52K (C2466T) amino acid change between the RCR-1 and RCR-2 DNA binding motifs involved in the specific binding of Rep to DNA (Jupin et al., 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>). The TYLCSV CP V135I and M136I (G711A and G716A, respectively) mutations are in the critical 129–152 region required for effective capsid assembly and transmissibility by 
 <italic>Bemisia tabaci</italic>, the virus vector (Noris et al., 
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>; Hallan and Gafni, 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Caciagli et al., 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), although in our experimental design the latter is not a limiting factor. The TYLCMaV CP R18C (C360T) amino acid change is adjacent to R19L, a change which has been shown to deeply impact both TYLCV capsid assembly, as well as CP protein interaction with the tomato nuclear receptor karyopherin α1 and the GroEL protein of 
 <italic>B. tabaci</italic> bacterial endosymbiont (Yaakov et al., 
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). CP mutations Q76E, Y78H, K80T, and R82C (C540G, T546C, A568C, and C585T, respectively) of TYLCV, and Q79H, R80L and D82V (G545T, G547T, and A553T) of TYLCMaV would affect the putative zinc finger motif, thus potentially impairing the ssDNA binding capacity of this protein.
</p>
