<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Super-spreading events have been documented for many infectious diseases 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003398-Stein1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003398-LloydSmith1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, including tuberculosis 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003398-Kline1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, measles 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003398-Paunio1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref> and SARS 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003398-Riley1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0003398-Shen1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. The underlying reasons for super-spreading are not fully understood, but include amount of pathogen excreted, length of the infectious period, social behavior and environmental factors. Understanding the mechanisms of super-spreaders in LF requires an understanding of all of these factors, but transmission of LASV is not well characterized. In the Jos outbreak, Carey et al. 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003398-Carey1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref> speculated that the severe pulmonary involvement of the index case and the location of her bed could cause airborne spread of virus to the rest of the ward. The long persistence of viruria, even during the recovery period, could facilitate transmission of LASV to other people or to the rodent reservoir host, especially in rural settlements in areas of West Africa where sanitary facilities are limited. Participatory modeling and ethnographic research 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003398-Leach1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref> would be an invaluable tool to assess the variety of practices and settings in which people come into contact with each other's urine and other body fluids, perceptions of risk, and approaches to hygiene. Apart the work of Stephenson 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref rid="pntd.0003398-Stephenson1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> and Peter 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref rid="pntd.0003398-Peters1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, we are not aware of specific experiments aimed to test routes of LASV transmission. Studies on environmental contamination are also required to explore if human-to-rodent transmission is important for the maintenance or spread of LASV infection 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003398-FichetCalvet1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>.
</p>
