<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Travel Med Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Travel Med Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Travel Medicine and Infectious Disease</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1477-8939</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1873-0442</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7416109</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S1477-8939(20)30340-9</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tmaid.2020.101844</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101844</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Dexamethasone: A boon for critically ill COVID-19 patients?</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>Shailesh Kumar</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="aff1">Division of Pathology, ICAR-Indian Veterinary Research Institute, Izatnagar, Bareilly, 243 122, Uttar Pradesh, India</aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Saikumar</surname><given-names>Gutulla</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="aff2">Division of Pathology, ICAR-Indian Veterinary Research Institute, Izatnagar, Bareilly, 243 122, Uttar Pradesh, India</aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Rana</surname><given-names>Jigyasa</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="aff3">Department of Veterinary Anatomy, Faculty of Veterinary and Animal Sciences, Rajeev Gandhi South Campus, Banaras Hindu University, Barkachha, Mirzapur, Uttar Pradesh, 231 001, India</aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Dhama</surname><given-names>Jaideep</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="aff4">Tara Hospital, Uttam Nagar, New Delhi, 11059, India</aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Yatoo</surname><given-names>Mohd Iqbal</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="aff5">Division of Veterinary Clinical Complex, Faculty of Veterinary Sciences and Animal Husbandry, Shuhama, Alusteng Srinagar, Sher-E-Kashmir University of Agricultural Sciences and Technology of Kashmir, Shalimar, Srinagar, 190006, Jammu and Kashmir, India</aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>Ruchi</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="aff6">Department of Veterinary Microbiology and Immunology, College of Veterinary Sciences, Uttar Pradesh Pandit Deen Dayal Upadhyaya Pashu Chikitsa Vigyan Vishwavidyalaya Evam Go Anusandhan Sansthan (DUVASU), Mathura, India &#x02013;281001, India</aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Morales</surname><given-names>Alfonso J.</given-names></name><email>arodriguezm@utp.edu.co</email><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff7">Public Health and Infection Research Group, Faculty of Health Sciences, Universidad Tecnologica de Pereira, Pereira, Colombia</aff><aff id="aff8">Latin American Network of Coronavirus Disease 2019-COVID-19 Research (LANCOVID-19), Pereira, Risaralda, Colombia</aff><aff id="aff9">Grupo de Investigaci&#x000f3;n Biomedicina, Faculty of Medicine, Fundaci&#x000f3;n Universitaria Aut&#x000f3;noma de Las Americas, Pereira, Risaralda, Colombia</aff><aff id="aff10">School of Medicine, Universidad Privada Franz Tamayo, Cochabamba, Bolivia</aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8"><name><surname>Dhama</surname><given-names>Kuldeep</given-names></name><email>kdhama@rediffmail.com</email><xref rid="cor2" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;&#x02217;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff11">Division of Pathology, ICAR-Indian Veterinary Research Institute, Izatnagar, Bareilly, 243 122, Uttar Pradesh, India</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. Public Health and Infection, Research Group, Faculty of Health Sciences, Universidad Tecnologica de Pereira, Pereira, Risaralda, Colombia. <email>arodriguezm@utp.edu.co</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2"><label>**</label>Corresponding author. Division of Pathology, ICAR-Indian Veterinary Research Institute, Izatnagar, Bareilly, 243 122, Uttar Pradesh, India <email>kdhama@rediffmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub" iso-8601-date="2020-10-01"><season>September-October</season><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>37</volume><fpage>101844</fpage><lpage>101844</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>27</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Elsevier Ltd</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p content-type="salutation">Dear Editor</p><p id="p0010">As observed at the beginning of other coronaviruses epidemics, such as SARS in 2002 and MERS in 2012 [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], the search of therapeutic interventions has been intense for the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). The absence of an effective vaccine, treatment regimen, and managemental guidelines for COVID-19 has been responsible for rapid spread and heavy death toll. The COVID-19 associated mortalities in severe forms were mainly attributed to respiratory failure, probably due to lethal pneumonia caused by rampant inflammation [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The SARS-CoV-2 infection is characterized by an increase in pro-inflammatory and decrease in anti-inflammatory cytokines resulting in a state of cytokine storm syndrome, which in turn leads to the development of acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), shock, multiple organ failure and subsequent death of the individual [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p id="p0015">Although the use of corticosteroids has been reported as a routine treatment of COVID-19 to curtail the inflammation associated with injury [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], their use is controversial, and validation through clinical trials is highly warranted. Concerning this, a total of 14 clinical trials were initiated till date to evaluate the safety and effectiveness of the dexamethasone (a corticosteroid) for the management of SARS-CoV-2 infection (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/results?cond=covid-19&#x00026;term=dexamethasone&#x00026;cntry=&#x00026;state=&#x00026;city=&#x00026;dist=" id="intref0010">https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/results?cond=covid-19&#x00026;term=dexamethasone&#x00026;cntry=&#x00026;state=&#x00026;city=&#x00026;dist=</ext-link>). Recently, dexamethasone was declared as the world's first treatment proven effective in reducing the risks of death among severely ill COVID-19 patients based on the positive results confirmed by the RECOVERY trial (NCT04381936) conducted by Oxford University. The world's largest clinical trial viz. RECOVERY trial, a randomized, controlled, and open-label trial has begun in March 2020 and aimed to investigate several potential COVID-19 treatments on hospitalized patients [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Moreover, dexamethasone has been proven to significantly reduce the mortality risk in COVID-19 patients on ventilation and oxygen by as much as 35% and 20%, respectively. After that, the dexamethasone has been authorized by the UK government for the treatment of critically ill COVID-19 patients. However, no clinical benefits were seen in patients with mild, moderate, and hospitalized COVID-19 patients, not on oxygen or ventilation [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p id="p0020">The dexamethasone (synthetic pregnane corticosteroid; a cortisol derivative) is a well-known lifesaving drug and commonly used to treat inflammatory and autoimmune conditions (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
). It is widely used for the treatment and management of rheumatic problems, skin diseases, asthma, many forms of allergies, chronic obstructive lung disease, brain edema, eye pain, as a result of eye surgery and bronchospasm. The mechanism of action of corticosteroids is diverse, with many effects on various body systems. The corticosteroids inhibit the action and expression of many molecules involved in pneumonia associated inflammatory response. Moreover, many molecular mechanisms are associated with corticosteroids and include transactivation by increasing the gene transcription of different anti-inflammatory cytokines [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>An overview of dexamethasone and its mode of action in COVID-19 patients.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p><p id="p0025">Additionally, the corticosteroids may induce <italic>trans</italic>-expression by decreasing gene transcription of various pro-inflammatory cytokines, chemokines, and adhesion molecules [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Moreover, experimental studies revealed a reduced inflammatory response after the administration of corticosteroid in severe community-acquired pneumonia [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In this context, the anti-inflammatory effect of the dexamethasone is suggested to probably counter the cytokine storm caused by SARS-CoV-2 infection safeguarding the lungs and subsequently lives, for which detailed investigations are needed.</p><p id="p0030">However, the use of corticosteroids may induce side effects, so the administration of immunoglobulins (IV-IG) and IFN-&#x003b2; simultaneously may help in the management of COVID-19 using corticosteroids. In this context, a clinical trial (IRCT20120225009124N4; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.irct.ir/" id="intref0015">https://www.irct.ir/</ext-link>) has already been launched to test the hypothesis of whether early administration of dexamethasone along with IV-IG and IFN-&#x003b2; can reduce the harmful effects of cytokine storm in critically ill COVID-19 patients or not. Moreover, dexamethasone is approved by the FDA as a broad-spectrum immunosuppressant and reported to be about 30 times more active than cortisone with an added advantage of longer duration of action. Furthermore, dexamethasone is suggested to limit the production of inflammatory cytokines and their damaging effect. However, inhibition of T cells functions and blockage of B cells from making immunoglobulins may potentially lead to an increase in plasma viral load, which is a primary concern and needs further investigation [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p id="p0035">The breakthrough discovery of dexamethasone as the first drug to save lives is very encouraging. It enlightens the hope to reduce the mortality in critically ill hospitalized patients. Though the drug is found to be effective in only patients on ventilators or oxygen, the overall impact on reducing the mortality will be huge because critically ill patients are the great contributors to the COVID-19 death toll. Furthermore, the comparatively low price and worldwide availability of the drug will contribute to the reduction worries caused by the pandemic. The drug will prove a boon for low and middle-income countries where an effective but expensive drug would be beyond the financial reach of the general population [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, finding effective drugs like dexamethasone will transform the global impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on lives and economies. However, the goal is not yet achieved, and an effective vaccine and treatment are still awaited to counter this pandemic.</p><sec id="sec1"><title>Funding source</title><p id="p0040">All sources of funding should also be acknowledged&#x000a0;and you should declare any involvement of study sponsors in the study design; collection, analysis and interpretation of data; the writing of the manuscript; the decision to submit the manuscript for publication. If the study sponsors had no such involvement, this should be stated.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="p0045">
<bold>Shailesh Kumar Patel:</bold> Conceptualization, Writing - review &#x00026; editing. <bold>Gutulla Saikumar:</bold> Writing - review &#x00026; editing. <bold>Jigyasa Rana:</bold> Writing - review &#x00026; editing. <bold>Jaideep Dhama:</bold> Writing - review &#x00026; editing. <bold>Mohd Iqbal Yatoo:</bold> Writing - review &#x00026; editing. <bold>Ruchi Tiwari:</bold> Writing - review &#x00026; editing. <bold>Alfonso J. Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Morales:</bold> Writing - review &#x00026; editing. <bold>Kuldeep Dhama:</bold> Writing - review &#x00026; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0050">We declare that we have no competing interests.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Momattin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Ali</surname><given-names>A.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Tawfiq</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A systematic review of therapeutic agents for the treatment of the Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV)</article-title><source>Trav Med Infect Dis</source><volume>30</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>18</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical features of patients infected with 2019 novel coronavirus in Wuhan, China</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>395</volume><issue>10223</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31986264</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahase</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Covid-19: demand for dexamethasone surges as RECOVERY trial publishes preprint</article-title><source>BMJ</source><volume>369</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">m2512</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.m2512</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ledford</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coronavirus breakthrough: dexamethasone is first drug shown to save lives</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/d41586-020-01824-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rhen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cidlowski</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-inflammatory action of glucocorticoids--new mechanisms for old drugs</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>353</volume><issue>16</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>1711</fpage><lpage>1723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra050541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16236742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sibila</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luna</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agust&#x000ed;</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baquero</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gando</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patr&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morato</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Absi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of glucocorticoids in ventilated piglets with severe pneumonia</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><volume>32</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>1037</fpage><lpage>1046</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.00009208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18508831</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>