<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par7">To date, natural outbreaks of EVD have only been recorded in central and west African countries. Before the outbreak of EVD in Guinea, Sierra Leone and Liberia from 2013 to 2015, outbreaks of the disease were limited to secluded and rural locations in central Africa [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. A cumulative 31,139 cases with 12,890 deaths have been recorded since the first recognition of EVD in 1976–2015, more than 90% of these cases were reported during the West Africa outbreak [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Single exported cases during outbreaks have been recorded in travellers with secondary transmission noted during four such events in South Africa, Nigeria, USA and Mali [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. The common perception is that children are spared during EVD outbreaks, and in fact this observation was made during several outbreak investigations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. This does however not mean that children are not affected. A retrospective study revealed that 20 of the 218 (9%) confirmed EVD cases during the 2000 Gulu, Uganda outbreak were in young children and adolescents [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Nearly 20% of the cases reported during the West Africa outbreak involved children below the age of 15 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. The putative index case of the West Africa outbreak was a 2 year old child that may have had exposure to bats whilst playing in the forest nearby his home [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. The risk of EVD in children may be related to cultural factors in handling and caring for ill persons within households. In communities where children are kept away from the sick the risk should be lower, but in many instances young children are co-admitted to hospital with their sick caregivers increasing the risk of them also being infected [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. During the Gulu-outbreak, it was noted that the under-five age group was more affected during this outbreak than other children. Here children were typically co-admitted to hospital with their symptomatic parents [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>].
</p>
