<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">The most effective licensed vaccines elicit long-term antigen-specific antibody responses by plasma cells in addition to the development of persisting T cell and B cell memory. In case of SARS-CoV infection both humoral and cellular immune responses are crucial for the clearance of infection (
 <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> ). Recombinant virus vectors work in a similar manner like an endogenous pathogen, by expressing axenic target protein in cytoplasm of the host cell. After, processing of such endogenous antigen, MHC class 1 molecules present them to CD8+ T-lymphocytes, which causes production of T-cytotoxic cells. This pathway, leads to establishment of cell-mediated immunity, which is crucial in getting rid of virus infected cells. Sub unit vaccine candidate particularly RBD of S protein of SARS-CoV contains major antigenic determinants that can induce neutralizing antibodies [
 <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The SARS-CoV S protein can also induce CD8+ T-cell responses. The RBD of S protein contains multiple conformation-dependent epitopes and is the main domain that induces neutralizing antibody and T-cell immune responses against SARS-CoV infection [
 <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] making it an important target for vaccine development. The approaches for developing RBD-based vaccines against SARS-CoV have provided useful information for designing safe and effective vaccines against SARS-CoV 2 since RBDs of SARS-CoV 2 also contain similar epitopes. Similarly Adenoviral vectors are able to induce potent antibody as well as T cell responses with variations in the immune response depending on the serotype employed [
 <xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Replication-deficient Ad5, one of the most widely used adenoviral vectors, is able to induce exceptionally potent CD8+ T cell as well as antibody responses [
 <xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Furthermore DNA vaccination is also able to elicit both humoral and cellular immune responses, through activation of CD8+ cytotoxic and CD4+ helper T cells, respectively, Upon entry in the cell, DNA vaccines are sensed by a variety of innate immune receptors i.e. STING/TBK1/IRF3 pathways and the AIM2 inflammasome and many other factors are involved in DNA vaccine mode of action [
 <xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] but the exact mechanism of action is yet to be evaluated. However, immunization with S protein encoding DNA vaccine elicited protective immunity against SARS-CoV infection in a mouse model by inducing T cell and neutralizing antibody responses [
 <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].
</p>
