<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The identification of the GIV.2 NoV strain lion/Pistoia-387/06/IT in the lion cub [
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>] also represents the first report describing the possible association of these newly discovered NoVs with clinical signs characterized by severe hemorrhagic enteritis. The lion tested negative for common feline and canine viral pathogens, but it was found co-infected with toxigenic clostridia. The detection of NoV in a lion raised questions on the role of the carnivores in the epidemiology of this virus. Accordingly, in order to acquire additional information, an enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) based on the recombinant VP1 capsid protein of the lion NoV strain expressed by baculovirus system was developed and employed to screen a collection of cat and dog sera [
 <xref rid="B50-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. IgG antibodies against GIV.2 NoVs were detected in 16.1% of cats and in 4.8% of dogs, providing the first serological evidence on the circulation of these NoVs in domestic carnivores. In the molecular investigation performed by Pinto et al. [
 <xref rid="B11-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], the RNA of GIV.2 NoVs was detected in 6/14 samples collected from kittens with enteritis housed in a shelter in New York State [
 <xref rid="B11-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Interestingly, upon sequence analysis of the ORF2 gene, the six NoVs were identical to each other, suggesting the spread of a unique strain within the shelter. Subsequent molecular studies reported detection rates of GIV.2 NoVs in cats ranging from 1.2% in Japan [
 <xref rid="B51-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] to 2.8% in Brazil [
 <xref rid="B52-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] and to 6.2% in Italy [
 <xref rid="B48-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], either alone or in mixed infections with other viral pathogens such as FPV, FeCoV, feline calicivirus, and feline kobuvirus [
 <xref rid="B48-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>].
</p>
