<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0535">Following an incubation period of 9–10 days (range 6–20 days) patients develop catarrhal symptoms including cough, and over 1–2 weeks develop coughing paroxysms that end in the characteristic “whoop” associated with this infection. Although the cause of the characteristic “whoop” associated with 
 <italic>B. pertussis</italic> infection remains unresolved, a significant body of knowledge has accumulated to explain how 
 <italic>B. pertussis</italic> induces immune suppression, evasion, and modulation, thereby leading to a poor clinical outcome. 
 <xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 49.6</xref>
 <xref rid="bib195" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>195</sup>
 </xref> gives an overview of several 
 <italic>B. pertussis</italic> virulence factors that have immunomodulatory properties, the cells that they target, and the mechanisms thought to be involved in the induction of immune dysregulation caused by this infection. It has been shown that 
 <italic>B. pertussis</italic>-derived filamentous hemagglutinin (FHA) is the major surface structure that mediates adherence of 
 <italic>B. pertussis</italic> to host cells, primarily to cilia of airway ciliated epithelium. However, multiple factors likely contribute to this binding process,
 <xref rid="bib196" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>196</sup>
 </xref> including secreted adenylate cyclase toxin (ACT), which enhances FHA adherence to lung epithelial cells.
 <xref rid="bib197" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>197</sup>
 </xref> FHA also has immunosuppressive and modulatory activities by its ability to induce FHA-specific Tregs that secrete IL-10 and suppress T
 <sub>h</sub>1-like responses to 
 <italic>B. pertussis.</italic>
 <xref rid="bib198" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>198</sup>
 </xref> Anti-FHA antibodies can also reduce phagocytosis of these bacteria by human neutrophils.
 <xref rid="bib199" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>199</sup>
 </xref> ACT, a secreted toxin, targets host phagocytic cells by binding complement receptor 3 (CR3; CD11b/CD18).
 <xref rid="bib200" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>200</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib201" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>201</sup>
 </xref> ACT-deficient mutants of 
 <italic>B. pertussis</italic> are more efficiently phagocytosed by human neutrophils,
 <xref rid="bib202" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>202</sup>
 </xref> and in mice, lower bacterial loads are found in the respiratory tract.
 <xref rid="bib203" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>203</sup>
 </xref> Secreted ACT upregulates major histocompatibility complex class II MHC and co-stimulatory molecule expression on dendritic cells (DCs). ACT also prevents maturity, and thereby decreases their pro-inflammatory cytokine production.
 <xref rid="bib204" ref-type="bibr">204</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib205" ref-type="bibr">205</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib206" ref-type="bibr">206</xref> Tracheal cytotoxin (TCT) is also expressed at relatively high levels by 
 <italic>B. pertussis</italic>, and is a disaccharide-tetrapeptide fragment of peptidoglycan. Purified TCT, in synergy with lipopolysaccharide (LPS), damages ciliated airway epithelial cells through production of IL-1a and nitric oxide,
 <xref rid="bib207" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>207</sup>
 </xref> causing deleterious effects on neutrophils.
 <xref rid="bib208" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>208</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
