<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Four common human CoVs with low pathogenicity are 229E (α-CoV), NL63 (α-CoV), OC43 (β-CoV) and HKU1 (β-CoV), these cause mild diseases. However, serious effects, which can be life threatening, are seen with SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV and the latest emerging CoV (SARS-CoV-2) [
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. In late 2002, a spillover of SARS-CoV from bats to human occurred in China, causing SARS, which disappeared by 2004 [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27–29</xref>]. After controlling the SARS-CoV epidemic, MERS-CoV emerged in late 2012 originating from camels in the Middle East region [
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30–32</xref>]. The seventh identified CoV (SARS-CoV-2) was discovered for the first time in December 2019 in Wuhan (China). It infects human, causing COVID-19 disease and is currently is responsible for the worldwide health emergency [
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The overall structure of SARS-CoV-2 is similar to that of other CoVs [
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], with the phylogenetic similarity (79.5%) with SARS-CoV leading to the name SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Additionally, genome sequencing revealed that SARS-CoV-2 is 96.2% identical to bat CoV RaTG13, confirming that bats are a natural host of the virus, however, it might have an intermediate host [
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34–36</xref>]. The clinical spectrum of COVID-19 varies from no symptoms to multiorgan failure such as respiratory failure. The common symptoms include fever, cough, fatigue, dyspnea, headache and loss of taste or smell [
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Gastrointestinal symptoms such as diarrhea can also be a presenting feature for COVID-19. This has been attributed to a connection between gut functionality and microbiome responses to SARS-CoV-2 infection [
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Alterations of fecal microbiota are considered to be associated with SARS-CoV-2 fecal levels and COVID-19 severity [
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. While SARS-CoV-2 has lower mortality rate than SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV, the number of COVID-19 cases worldwide is higher [
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].
</p>
