<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par59">Detection of ZIKV RNA can be achieved in several sample types derived from infected individuals including blood–derived samples (whole blood, plasma, serum), other body fluids (semen, urine, saliva, vaginal secretions), and cytological specimens [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>]. The period of time during which viral RNA is detectable varies depending on the sample type as well as individual variation, ranging from a short (transient viremia) to a prolonged time post-infection in the case of other body fluids such as urine, semen, and saliva. Even though detection of ZIKV RNA during the viremic period is usually possible within the first week after disease onset [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>], a recent study has estimated that ZIKV RNA loss occurs at a median of 14 days in serum (95th percentile up to 54 days), 8 days in urine (95th percentile up to 39 days), and 34 days in semen (95th percentile up to 81 dpi) in infected humans [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]. However, ZIKV has been detected for as long as 6 months in semen of some individuals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]. Viral titers are also variable depending on the clinical specimen tested, days post-infection, and other factors. Viremia titers can range from 2 to 10
 <sup>6</sup> PFU/ml (~9 × 10
 <sup>2</sup>–7.3 × 10
 <sup>5</sup> viral RNA copies/ml) of blood [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>] while urine titers seem to be frequently within the 10 to 10
 <sup>3</sup> PFU/ml range (~4.3 × 10
 <sup>2</sup>–2.5 × 10
 <sup>5</sup> viral RNA copies/ml) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]. Interestingly, seminal shedding occurs at very high viral loads (2.9 × 10
 <sup>8</sup>–1.2 × 10
 <sup>3</sup> viral RNA copies/ml) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>]. In this study, specimens were spiked over a range of viral concentrations according to the estimated viral titers observed in ZIKV naturally infected individuals. Since the RT-iiPCR, CDC E, and PAHO NS2B assays showed an equal 100% detection rate (10 PFU/ml) and strong agreement between each other (k = 0.83), it is expected that the RT-iiPCR would have a similar clinical performance as the reference RT-qPCR assays and be suitable for detecting clinical specimens with at least a viral titer of 10 PFU/ml, while lower viral titers as those observed during late viremia may offer challenges and, consequently, the use of other tests may be more suitable at that stage of infection (i.e. serological tests). Even though we have extensively evaluated this assay using spiked human specimens and mosquitoes, testing of clinical specimens derived from infected individuals and mosquitoes is required to further confirm the performance of this new PON assay under field conditions.
</p>
