<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0050">There is a global effort to find an effective treatment for COVID-19. Although the benefits of some available drugs have been proven, they are not yet a certain specific cure for the disease, and controversies remain [
 <xref rid="bb0250" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. According to previous experience with other coronavirus family members, convalescent plasma therapy has been tested on some critically ill patients, with promising results. In this regard, several studies have confirmed the positive effects of this treatment, especially in critically ill patients in the ICU and with ARDS to shorten hospitalization time and reduce the mortality rate. The COVID-19 specific IgG antibodies act as passive immune therapy, and after administration by the transfused plasma might neutralize viral particles and activate the complement system, which could consequently lead to viral elimination. Despite its efficacy, this method has some difficulties such as concerns about causing an infection, and non-infectious transfusion reactions. Transfusion-induced infection is rare in industrial countries (unlike poor countries) while the latter is a global worry known as transfusion-related acute lung injury (TRALI) and allergic reactions. As an important point, IgG collected in one country may be different from another country, because lifestyle, diet, genetics, and the environment could play an important role in the development of specific antibodies against the virus. Furthermore, differences between strains of coronavirus should be considered in geographically distinct areas; so, treatment of infected cases with polyclonal IgG, collected from the same area may increase the chance of an effective response [
 <xref rid="bb0250" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0255" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0260" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0265" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0270" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0275" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>]. As a result, specific monoclonal antibodies that recognize the virus particles to inhibit multiplication and cell entry may be more practical and reliable. Wang et al. reported some positive findings about creation of a monoclonal antibody against the S protein of the virus, that could inhibit cell attachment and entry [
 <xref rid="bb0280" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>].
</p>
