<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Australia remains at risk of ZIKV introduction due to its close proximity to the Western Pacific, the presence of competent strains of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> in Queensland [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> in the Torres Strait [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], and favourable climatic conditions for transmission [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Despite 51 reports of imported cases of ZIKV since 2014 (Queensland Government, Australia, accessed 8 October 2018), Australia has not yet reported autochthonous transmission. Previous studies have reported the vector competence of Australian 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> for African, Cambodian and Western Pacific strains [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> (Torres Strait islands) for Cambodian ZIKV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. These studies demonstrated that Australian mosquito strains can be infected and transmit ZIKV; however, large heterogeneity has been observed in the susceptibility of mosquitoes to infection, which may be associated with the origin of the virus strains. There have been no investigations of the vector competence of Australian strains to isolates of ZIKV from South America, despite the continent recording the largest epidemics with a high prevalence of the most severe ZIKV disease manifestations [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. To assess the public health risk imposed by ZIKV to Australia, we determined the vector competence of local populations of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> (Torres Strait Islands) for a strain of ZIKV isolated from a febrile patient from Paraiba state, at the centre of the 2015/2016 Brazil epidemic. In addition to maintaining infected mosquitoes under a standard constant temperature regime, we also used a fluctuating diurnal temperature range (DTR). Our study indicates that 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> has higher relative vector competence than 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic>, which may be mediated by a salivary gland barrier to virus transmission in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> for this ZIKV strain.
</p>
