<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat.1007716.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007716.g004</object-id>
 <label>Fig 4</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Critical residues for binding of cross-reactive antibody d462.</title>
  <p>The structural presentation of the critical residues of the epitope on DENV4 domain I. (A) Critical resides (green spheres) are mapped on both monomers of the mature E protein dimer structure (PDB, 1UZG). Domain I is red, domain II yellow, domain III blue and fusion loop cyan. The asymmetric monomer rotated 180 degrees is gray. (B) Sequence alignment of the epitope region on the E protein. Residues V160, V173 and D177 on DENV4 are not identical among different serotypes. However, they have similar chemical characteristics for DENV3 in position 173 (
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Valine" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Valine</ext-link> compare to 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alanine" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Alanine</ext-link>) and 177 (Aspartic 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glutamic_acid" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">acid</ext-link> compare to 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aspartic_acid" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Glutamic acid</ext-link>). The NCBI accession numbers of the sequences are ACJ04226 (DENV1), AGS49173 (DENV2), AJA37731 (DENV3) and ACW82884 (DENV4) respectively. (C) Antibody d462 epitope on an E protein raft (PDB, 4CBF). The black line shows the boundary of a single asymmetric unit. The residues that interact with d462 are shown as green spheres. Enlarged view (right) shows the epitope region on F
   <sub>0</sub>, G
   <sub>0</sub> β-strands, and the G
   <sub>0</sub>H
   <sub>0</sub> loop on E protein domain I. The epitope of d462 (V160, V173, D177) is overlapped with that of the reported chimpanzee antibody 5H2 (E172, K174, D177, E180, R293). (D) Structural comparison of the epitope region on DENV4 (PDB, 3UC0) and DENV3 (PDB, 1UZG), indicating the structural similarity of the key residues. DENV4 is shown in red ribbon and DENV3 is shown in gray ribbon. The residues on DENV4 are shown as green sticks, on DENV3 as gray sticks. Atoms are colored red for O, blue for N. The analysis was performed using “Structural Comparison: Match -&gt; Align” of UCSF chimera. Molecular graphic images were produced using the UCSF Chimera (
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rbvi.ucsf.edu/chimera" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.rbvi.ucsf.edu/chimera</ext-link>). (E) Percentage neutralization of the DENV4 reporter virus particles, and its critical amino acid residue substitution mutants. Antibody d462 was tested at the concentration of 3 μg/ml. The assays were performed in triplicates and data were analyzed using GraphPad Prism.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1007716.g004" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
