<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0040">Here, we generated a comprehensive human-SARS-CoV-2 interactome encompassing 12,852 nodes and 84,100 edges. By integrating expressed SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV genes, we created Calu-3-specific human-SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV 
 <underline>i</underline>nteractome (CSI) containing 4,176 nodes and 18,630 edges. Our network analysis indicates that the average degree, betweenness, and information centrality of SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV interacting proteins (SIPs) are enriched in CSI. Module-based functional pathway analyses discovered a number of disease-related clusters that are enriched in several signaling pathways and biological processes including eIF2 signaling/translation, striated muscle contraction, protein ubiquitination pathway, viral infection/mRNA transport, T cell receptor regulation of apoptosis, cell cycle, p38 MK2 pathway, and amino acid degradation pathways. Network topology analyses identified 33 high-value targets of SARS-CoV-2, which can form complexes with other highly influential nodes within CSI. These most important nodes are possibly involved in the viral entry, proliferation, and survival in the host tissue as well as required to induce a conducive environment for viral sustenance and pathogenesis. Moreover, we incorporated transcriptome data of COVID-19 patients derived from bronchoalveolar lavage fluid (BALF) cells and peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) with our CSI data. Subsequently, we performed dynamic gene regulation modeling on the CSI nodes to decipher the intricate relationships between important transcription factors (TFs) and their target genes upon SARS-CoV-2 infection. Of particular interest is the TF-regulatory relationships involved in host modifying processes such as protein translation, ubiquitination, interferon signaling, and the cytokine storm. In summary, our integrative network topology analyses led us to elucidate the underlying molecular mechanisms and pathways of SARS-CoV-2 pathogenesis.
</p>
