<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The ability of an AIV to transmit amongst humans may rely on the ability of the virus to replicate efficiently in swine cells. Swine are often the host for viral reassortment and generating novel viruses in the ecosystem (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-2515135518821625">Figure 2</xref>).
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr81-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>
 </sup> Cells found in the respiratory tract of swine species have both -2,3 and -2,6 sialic acid receptors, making them a ‘mixing pot’ for the generation of novel pathogenic viruses.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr82-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>
 </sup> Reassorted H3N2 swine viruses cause epidemics in the swine population, as seen in the 1998 outbreak that occurred in the USA in North Carolina, Texas, Minnestota, and Iowa pig farm outbreaks.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr83-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr84-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>
 </sup> Genetic analysis of the swine viral isolates revealed viral genes from human, swine, and AIVs.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr84-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>
 </sup> Swine viruses are able to spill over into the human population and cause severe disease in people.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr85-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>
 </sup> There have been a total of three documentated swine infections in the human population recorded in the USA.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr83-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>
 </sup> Although H3N2 and H1N1 viruses are known to replicate and reassort in swine, the ability of H5Nx viruses to infect these species is still under investigation. As of October 2018, there have been 50 submissions of H5N1 swine infection uploaded to the GISAID (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gisaid.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.gisaid.org</ext-link>) website between 1968 and 2017, with 36 of the HA sequences being unique. Few pigs are naturally infected with H5 viruses. Surveillance of pig farms in Vietnam in 2004 showed that only 0.25% of 3175 pig tested were positive for H5N1 viruses.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr86-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>
 </sup> These H5N1 viruses were found to replicate in naïve swine, but did not cause severe disease or weight loss, and did not transmit to naïve contact pigs.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr86-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>
 </sup> The potential for reassortment of AIVs and mammalian influenza viruses in pigs is still unknown, but swine are permissive hosts for viral replication of AIVs.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr87-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr88-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr89-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>
 </sup> Newly characterized clade 2.3.4.4 H5Nx viruses do not readily infect trachea cell extracts collected from pigs.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr89-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>
 </sup> There are multiple studies showing that HPAIVs and LPAIVs do not cause clinical symptoms in naïve swine.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr87-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr88-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr"/>
  <xref rid="bibr89-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr"/>
  <xref rid="bibr90-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr91-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>
 </sup> Microscopic pathological analysis does reveal some cellular infiltrates, along with minor macroscopic lesions, but replication in these hosts does not permit transmission to naïve pigs.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr87-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>
 </sup> In addition, co-housing poultry that were infected with HPAIVs were not able to transmit the virus to naïve pigs.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr92-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>
 </sup> In pigs infected with H5Nx influenza viruses the virus replicated in the lower respiratory tract, since nasal swabs were negative in reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) assays, but bronchoaveolar lavage fluid contained viral titers postinfection
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr87-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>
 </sup> demonstrating that AIVs replicate in the lower respiratory tract in pigs. This site of replication in the lungs is consistent with the location of the α-2,3 alpha receptors found in the lower respiratory tract of pigs and not present in the upper respiratory tract.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr82-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>
 </sup> A survelliance study performed in China monitored and tested 16 swine farms in southern China, and serum samples collected from the swine determined that no pigs were serologically positive for H5N1 virus.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr93-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>
 </sup> These studies showed that pigs are not easily susceptible to H5Nx infection, and that those that do become infected do not easily transmit to naïve companions. However, there is always the concern that due to the lack of H5N1 virus-induced clinical manifestations, H5Nx and seasonal H1N1/H3N2 influenza viruses could co-infect the same animal resulting in a reassortment event that leads to a human transmissible H5 influenza virus.
</p>
