<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0080">In addition to evaluate the neutralization activity, vaccine development needs to evaluate the antigenicity and immunogenicity for vaccine seed strain selection, especially for re-emerging viruses such as avian influenza virus H5 containing various subtypes. Although recent emerging SARS-CoV-2 has only one dominant strain with genetic variants, we suspected that the emerging virus might steadily evolve with “antigenic drift” like influenza virus under strong herd immunity in the near future due to the high transmission rate with millions of confirmed reported cases around the world. If the recent emerging SARS-CoV-2 continuously circulates among the community and becomes another ‘re-emerging virus’, SARS-CoV-2 will also face a strong positive selection pressure from herd immunity which drives the virus to exhibit diverse antigenic properties and causes antigenic property changes. Constant surveying of the antigenic evolution of SARS-CoV-2 virus and updating the vaccine antigen for inactivated vaccine, recombinant S protein antigen for subunit vaccine, or even delivered S gene for DNA/RNA vaccine are necessary in the process of vaccine development. In the following of surveying antigenic property of re-emerging virus, the immunogenicity of re-emerging S protein/gene will be next examined. The immunogenicity analysis of vaccine antigen provides valuable information for vaccine selection, indicating the true scenario of raised neutralizing antibody response against target virus. According to the immunogenicity results, we will assess the feasibility of utilizing selected antigens as immunogens to induce proper neutralizing antibody response. Here we used avian influenza virus H5 as an example to demonstrate the feasibility of our pseudovirus system applying in not only vaccine efficacy evaluation by using neutralization assay but also antigenicity and immunogenicity assessments by utilizing pseudovirus of re-emerging viruses. As we used various H5Nx concentrated pseudovirus as antigens to immunize mice, we revealed minor diversity of antigenic property and immunogenicity of each examined H5Nx pseudovirus by antigenic cartography. In previous studies, antigenic cartography was successfully applied using influenza, enterovirus A71, and dengue viruses to access the antigenic variation [
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>]. Combining with cross-neutralization results and antigenic cartography, we visualized the antigenic properties of influenza virus H5Nx subtypes. Results demonstrated that the avian influenza virus H5Nx localized in a short distance on the antigenic map, which shows the close antigenic property among examined H5Nx subtypes. Nonetheless, the cross-neutralization results revealed the different feasibility of H5Nx antigens to raise neutralizing antisera. We found that antisera raised from H5N8 TWX37 immunization showed the generally broad spectrum of neutralization against all examined subtypes pseudovirus, suggesting its good immunogenicity against avian influenza viruses H5N2, H5N6, and H5N8.
</p>
