<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Coinfection (by which we mean that individuals are simultaneously infected with different strains), hereafter defined as ‘concurrent infection’, was observed in influenza (e.g., [
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]). Concurrent infection can be produced by either the simultaneous transmission of two strains [
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] or two separate transmissions with the transmission of the second strain before recovery from the first strain. This is different to secondary infection after individuals have recovered from primary infection which is referred to as sequential infection (or re-infection). Within concurrent infections, strains may interact with each other in a way different from how they interact when infections are sequential. This can be argued from the following points: first, as Liu et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] noticed, within two days of symptom onset, no patients infected with influenza A virus had detectable hemagglutination inhibition (HI) antibodies against other strains of influenza; second, through better aerosolisation infection with one strain of influenza may increase the chance of being infected with another strain of influenza during the infectious period of the first infection [
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Though Brundage [
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>] focused on the interactions between influenza viruses and bacterial respiratory pathogens, the same argument might also apply to the interaction between influenza viruses through the better aerosolisation. These two points might imply the possibility of infectivity enhancement within concurrent infection. So far there is no direct report showing infectivity enhancement within concurrent infection in influenza, which is perhaps because of the short duration of influenza virus infectiousness (typically less than a week). Based on the observed data [
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] of concurrent infection and co-transmission events, Zhang and De Angelis [
 <xref rid="pone.0142170.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>] demonstrate an indirect evidence of infectivity enhancement during concurrent infection in flu. As a theoretical exploration, we will in this paper investigate how this possible interaction along with the well-known cross-immunity affects dynamic patterns of season flu.
</p>
