<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?OLF?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Medicine (Abingdon)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Medicine (Abingdon)</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Medicine (Abingdon, England : UK Ed.)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1357-3039</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1878-9390</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Published by Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7467026</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1357-3039(20)30205-X</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mpmed.2020.08.012</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>What is the role of a psychiatrist in the COVID-19 pandemic?</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>David S.</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="aff1"><bold>David S Baldwin MA DM FHEA FRCPsych</bold> is a Professor of Psychiatry in the Faculty of Medicine of the University of Southampton, UK, Honorary Professor of Psychiatry at the University of Cape Town, South Africa, and Visiting Professor at Shandong Mental Health Centre, Jinan, China. Competing interests: Professor Baldwin is a Medical Patron of Anxiety UK and Clinical Advisor to the National Clinical Audit of Anxiety and Depression</aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>2</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Published by Elsevier Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Covid-19</kwd><kwd>Pandemic</kwd><kwd>Mental health</kwd><kwd>Psychiatrist</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="p0010">Previous epidemics have been associated with high rates of psychiatric morbidity, and there are escalating reports of common mental health problems and more marked neuropsychiatric disorders associated with the COVID-19 pandemic. These may arise from direct effects of infection with enforced isolation and quarantine after viral exposure, and from additional stressors such as complicated bereavement, job losses, intra-familial tension and sudden impoverishment. How can a psychiatrist contribute in a viral pandemic?</p><p id="p0015">In previously mentally healthy individuals, the central effects of viral infection and its complications and treatments include the development of novel neuropsychiatric conditions (e.g. delirium, demyelination, encephalopathies, seizures, stroke).<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> Psychiatrists therefore have a role in assisting neurologists to determine whether atypical presentations within the context of COVID-19 infection are best understood as neurological or psychiatric in origin, and in advising on the management of acute confusional states.</p><p id="p0020">The potential adverse psychological impact of viral infection in patients with established psychiatric illnesses is uncertain: individuals with known mental health problems may be particularly vulnerable, but the effects of the pandemic on risk of relapse or need for increased use of mental health services in this group are not yet established.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> However, many of the experimental approaches to treating COVID-19 infection &#x02013; including azithromycin, hydroxychloroquine and remdesivir &#x02013; have a risk of interaction with concomitantly prescribed psychotropic medication.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Psychiatrists therefore need to be especially attentive to current patients, working to minimize relapse and prevent avoidable admissions to potentially hazardous hospital environments where physical distancing can be hard; and they should be aware of potential interactions with psychotropic medications if a patient develops severe COVID-19 infection. They also need to be assertive when protecting staff and environmental resources as these might be vulnerable to diversion to more obviously &#x02018;front-line&#x02019; physical health services.</p><p id="p0025">Prolonged enforced isolation and quarantine is known to have a range of adverse effects on psychological well-being: anxiety, irritability, poor concentration, fatigue and lowered mood are common. Healthcare workers may be particularly affected, perhaps because of concerns about being away from the workplace at a time of heightened demand (see Further reading). These untoward effects can be minimized by keeping isolation as brief as possible, ensuring individuals understand fully when quarantine is essential, ensuring adequate supplies to meet basic needs, and by reducing boredom and improving communication. Psychiatrists should work with other mental health professionals in helping populations to understand that many of the experiences are shared by others and are likely to resolve as entry back into wider society becomes possible.</p><p id="p0030">The pandemic places many healthcare professionals in previously unanticipated situations, needing to make swift difficult decisions on limited evidence under duress, having to choose between similarly affected patients when allocating limited resources, and trying to balance their commitment to providing clinical care with their own, and their family's, physical and mental needs. These pressing challenges can cause some to experience &#x02018;moral injury&#x02019; (psychological distress resulting from actions that violate individual moral or ethical codes) and can contribute to subsequent mental health problems (see Further reading). Consultation-liaison psychiatric services and occupational mental health services could therefore be important in attending to distressed colleagues and supporting systems designed to support a psychologically robust workforce.</p></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>Key references</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chesney</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychiatric and neuropsychiatric presentations associated with severe coronavirus infections: a systematic review and meta-analysis with comparison to the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Lancet Psychiatr</source><volume>7</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>611</fpage><lpage>627</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Varatharaj</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellul</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurological and neuropsychiatric complications of COVID-19 in 153 patients: a UK-wide surveillance study</article-title><source>Lancet Psychiatr</source><year>2020</year><comment>S2215-0366(20)30287-X</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>K.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petkova</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhui</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>T.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;global needs assessment in times of a global crisis: world psychiatry response to the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>BJPsych Open</source><volume>6</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>e48</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32250235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Connor</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>V.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multidisciplinary research priorities for the COVID-19 pandemic: a call for action for mental health science</article-title><source>Lancet Psychiatr</source><volume>7</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>560</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bishara</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalafatis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emerging and experimental treatments for COVID-19 and drug interactions with psychotropic agents</article-title><source>Ther Adv Psychopharmacol</source><volume>10</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ref-list id="fread0010"><title>Further reading</title><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The psychological impact of quarantine and how to reduce it: rapid review of the evidence</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>395</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>912</fpage><lpage>920</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32112714</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Docherty</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gnanapragasam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wessely</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Managing mental health challenges faced by healthcare workers during covid-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Br Med J</source><volume>368</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>m1211</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32217624</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>