<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Infect. Dis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Infectious Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2334</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7104526</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">4957</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-020-04957-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Google Health Trends performance reflecting dengue incidence for the Brazilian states</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Romero-Alvarez</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><address><email>daromero88@gmail.com</email><email>da.romero@ku.edu</email><email>dan_rom@lanl.gov</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Parikh</surname><given-names>Nidhi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Osthus</surname><given-names>Dave</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>Kaitlyn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Generous</surname><given-names>Nicholas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>del Valle</surname><given-names>Sara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Manore</surname><given-names>Carrie A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.266515.3</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2106 0692</institution-id><institution>Department of Ecology &#x00026; Evolutionary Biology and Biodiversity Institute, </institution><institution>University of Kansas, </institution></institution-wrap>Lawrence, Kansas USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.148313.c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0428 3079</institution-id><institution>Information Systems and Modeling (A-1), Los Alamos National Laboratory, </institution></institution-wrap>Los Alamos, NM USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.148313.c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0428 3079</institution-id><institution>Statistical Sciences (CCS-6), Los Alamos National Laboratory, </institution></institution-wrap>Los Alamos, NM USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.254549.b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8155</institution-id><institution>Applied Math and Statistics, Colorado School of Mines, </institution></institution-wrap>Golden, CO USA </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.148313.c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0428 3079</institution-id><institution>National Security &#x00026; Defense Program Office (GS-NSD), Los Alamos National Laboratory, </institution></institution-wrap>Los Alamos, NM USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><elocation-id>252</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Dengue fever is a mosquito-borne infection transmitted by <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and mainly found in tropical and subtropical regions worldwide. Since its re-introduction in 1986, Brazil has become a hotspot for dengue and has experienced yearly epidemics. As a notifiable infectious disease, Brazil uses a passive epidemiological surveillance system to collect and report cases; however, dengue burden is underestimated. Thus, Internet data streams may complement surveillance activities by providing real-time information in the face of reporting lags.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">We analyzed 19 terms related to dengue using Google Health Trends (GHT), a free-Internet data-source, and compared it with weekly dengue incidence between 2011 to 2016. We correlated GHT data with dengue incidence at the national and state-level for Brazil while using the adjusted R squared statistic as primary outcome measure (0/1). We used survey data on Internet access and variables from the official census of 2010 to identify where GHT could be useful in tracking dengue dynamics. Finally, we used a standardized volatility index on dengue incidence and developed models with different variables with the same objective.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">From the 19 terms explored with GHT, only seven were able to consistently track dengue. From the 27 states, only 12 reported an adjusted R squared higher than 0.8; these states were distributed mainly in the Northeast, Southeast, and South of Brazil. The usefulness of GHT was explained by the logarithm of the number of Internet users in the last 3 months, the total population per state, and the standardized volatility index.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">The potential contribution of GHT in complementing traditional established surveillance strategies should be analyzed in the context of geographical resolutions smaller than countries. For Brazil, GHT implementation should be analyzed in a case-by-case basis. State variables including total population, Internet usage in the last 3 months, and the standardized volatility index could serve as indicators determining when GHT could complement dengue state level surveillance in other countries.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Google health trends</kwd><kwd>Digital epidemiology</kwd><kwd>Brazil</kwd><kwd>Volatility</kwd><kwd>Epidemiology</kwd><kwd>Internet data streams</kwd><kwd>Internet penetration</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000057</institution-id><institution>National Institute of General Medical Sciences</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>R01GM130668</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100008902</institution-id><institution>Los Alamos National Laboratory</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>Laboratory Directed Research Development Program</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par41">Dengue fever is transmitted by the homonymous arthropod-borne virus (i.e., arbovirus) from the family <italic>Flaviviridae</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. There are four dengue virus (DENV) serotypes with a potential fifth serotype described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], all of them distributed in tropical and subtropical regions worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] with emerging cases in northern latitudes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The pathogen is mainly transmitted by <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> mosquitoes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Dengue disease symptoms range from asymptomatic, mild fever, rash, and joint pain (i.e., dengue with and without warning signs), to life threatening syndromes involving hemorrhagic fever and shock (i.e., severe dengue) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]; severe clinical presentations are related with immunological cross-reactivity between dengue serotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. As a viral infection, treatment is based mainly on support measures during the acute and critical phase of the infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Although there has been progress on the development of vaccines, more research is needed before they are used as an effective public health mechanism for control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p><p id="Par42">The burden of dengue fever is high; around half of the world population is estimated to be at risk of infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] and every year, ~&#x02009;100 million symptomatic cases are detected [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. This poses a significant burden to the health systems in at least 128 countries worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] as well as economic impacts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] that likely will expand to new regions in the future [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. In Brazil, dengue was re-introduced in 1986 in the state of Roraima [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] and quickly spread to the rest of the country [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. In 2018, the total number of cases reported in Brazil was 265,934 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] and so far 1,439,471 cases have been reported in 2019 through August [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>].</p><p id="Par43">As a notifiable infectious disease, any case of dengue detected in the Brazilian public health system must be reported to the corresponding health authorities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Case notification relies on a passive surveillance framework in which disease reporting builds on patients seeking medical attention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. However, cases are often missed by the official reporting system because of non-severe presentations, lack of accessibility to health care infrastructure, misdiagnosis, or even misreporting. Thus, reported case counts are assumed to be an underestimation of the true disease burden [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Moreover, availability of health data based on traditional public health surveillance is usually constrained by time, bureaucracy, and staffing, with a lag of 2 weeks for the best systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], partial notifications in high burden settings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], or even complete lack of reporting due to political instability as recently evidenced [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Timely disease reporting is critical for preparedness and executable real-time interventions to curb outbreaks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].</p><p id="Par44">As a consequence, the exploitation of Internet data as a source to characterize epidemiological patterns for communicable and non-communicable diseases has been promoted since the mid-90&#x02019;s under the concept of digital epidemiology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. These efforts have focused on leveraging freely available information from Twitter, Google, Wikipedia, among others, to follow traces of disease patterns in the population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Following the pioneering work of Eysenbach G. on using web-based search queries to track influenza [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] and other efforts that used Google-derived data for influenza in the United States [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] and dengue in different countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], Google developed Google Flu Trends (GFT) in 2009 and Google Dengue Trends (GDT) in 2011, as specific disease surveillance tools for digital epidemiology. However, a close examination of the predicting power of these algorithms, specifically GFT, showed signs of over and under prediction and low performance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] cautioning against the broader implementation and applicability of these tools. As a consequence, both GFT and GDT were shut down in 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Nevertheless, two portals remained open to harvest search queries from Google, Google Trends (GT, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://trends.google.com/trends/?geo=US">https://trends.google.com/trends/?geo=US</ext-link>), and Google Health Trends (GHT). GT was released in 2006 as a free and publicly available source, whereas GHT, although free, it requires access through an application private interface (API, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.google.org/flutrends/about/">https://www.google.org/flutrends/about/</ext-link>). Many researchers have continued using Google-derived data to assess epidemiological patterns and inform epidemiological models for different pathogens with encouraging or conflicting results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>].</p><p id="Par45">For Brazil, digital tools to quantify dengue reporting have been previously explored, in fact Chan et al. (2011) inspired the creation of GDT in the first place, showing a strong correlation with dengue cases in Brazil, among other countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Recently, Marques-Toledo et al. (2017) found that Twitter was useful in characterizing dengue incidence for different Brazilian cities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>], and the authors further compared their results against GT and Wikipedia query logs at the country level finding close agreement among several models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Moreover, Yang et al. (2017) recently used an autoregressive model with Google search queries as exogenous variables (ARGO) to predict dengue cases in Brazil and showed good model performance at the country level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Neither of these studies examined the ability of Google-derived data to characterize dengue incidence at the state level, and in fact, only few studies have examined Google-based algorithms at smaller political administrative levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. To address this gap, we explore the ability of GHT to characterize weekly dengue cases from 2011 to 2016 in Brazil. For this goal, we used 19 dengue-related search terms for all 27 Brazilian states and quantified how Internet penetration data, demographic variables, and a standardized volatility index could determine a-priori where GHT might be a reliable tool.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Dengue incidence data</title><p id="Par46">We obtained weekly dengue case counts for Brazil and all its 27 states from January 1st, 2011 to July 31st 2016. Data was given by the Brazilian Ministry of Health as a weekly aggregated data sheet with cases identified as counts without any identity information (e.g., names, gender, age, etc) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. This data encompasses the number of confirmed and suspected dengue cases reported by the official surveillance system, which follows specific guidelines of mandatory disease notification [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Incidence rates were calculated as the number of cases per week divided by the total population per state according to the official Brazilian population census of 2010 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]; for our analysis we used incidence instead of case counts to allow comparisons of dengue burden between Brazilian states [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Google health trends data</title><p>The private API of GHT provides Internet search query data starting in 2004. Queries are sampled from the overall Google dataset in the form of a relative proportion, dividing the number of searches for a specified term over a particular time interval (i.e., days, weeks, months, or years) by the total number of term searches in that time, and multiplied by a predefined constant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. Thus, it differs from GT which provides a ranked score from 0 to 100 based on the highest frequency of searches in a particular period of time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. We obtained weekly GHT data for the same timeframe of dengue cases using 19 disease and mosquito vector related terms in Portuguese and English, including: &#x0201c;aedes&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;<italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;aedes eg&#x000ed;pcio&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;aegypti&#x0201d;, dengue&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;dengue &#x000e9; v&#x000ed;rus&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;dengue fever&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;dengue hemorrhagic fever&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;dengue sintomas&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;dengue v&#x000ed;rus&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;DENV&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;DHF&#x0201d; (i.e., dengue hemorrhagic fever), &#x0201c;eg&#x000ed;pcio&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;mosquito&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;mosquito dengue&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;mosquitoes&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;novo v&#x000ed;rus da dengue&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;sintomas da dengue&#x0201d;, and &#x0201c;v&#x000ed;rus da dengue&#x0201d;. We downloaded the data on June 26th, 2017 and gathered information for the 27 Brazilian states and for the whole country.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par48">We fitted a linear regression model using GHT search terms as predictors of dengue incidence at the state level and recorded the adjusted R squared statistic as the primary outcome measure (0/1). Then, we fitted a multiple linear regression model using all the terms retrieving information by state (i.e., all terms model). Due to the potential overlap from conceptually related terms (e.g., &#x0201c;aedes&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;<italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>&#x0201d;), we also calculated Pearson&#x02019;s correlation among terms and developed multiple linear regression models with those with a correlation less than 0.7 (i.e., uncorrelated terms model). Finally, we fitted models using four terms: &#x0201c;dengue&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;dengue sintomas&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;aedes&#x0201d;, and &#x0201c;mosquito&#x0201d;, which although correlated, have the potential to capture the full spectrum of searches considering the information they provide related to the disease and the mosquito vector (i.e., four terms model). We addressed the statistical differences between models with full vs. reduced number of terms, and between full and individual terms per state using pair-wise analysis of variance (ANOVA).</p><p id="Par49">Given the heterogeneous Internet access throughout Brazil, we analyzed the role that accessibility could play in explaining our ability to track dengue incidence via GHT. Since 2005, Brazil has monitored the accessibility of their population to information and communication technologies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>] through the &#x0201c;Survey for Internet Access, Television and Mobile Phone Possession for Personal Use (Acesso &#x000e0; Internet e a Televis&#x000e3;o e Posse de Telefone M&#x000f3;vel Celular para Uso Pessoal, Portuguese)&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. The survey is part of the National Household Sample Survey (Pesquisa Nacional por Amostra de Domic&#x000ed;lios (PNAD), Portuguese) conducted by the Brazilian Institute for Geography and Statistics (Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estat&#x000ed;stica (IBGE), Portuguese [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]). We analyzed data from the 2015 survey, which included a sample of 356,904 individuals and 151,189 households distributed across the country and was subsequently extrapolated to a total of 177,657 million people and 68,037 million households [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. From all the available variables provided in this survey (~&#x02009;150), we used: (1) the total number of people above 10 years using Internet in the last 3 months, (2) the number of households that have used Internet in the last 3 months, (3) the number of people with mobile phones, and (4) the number of households with computers, as working predictors. In addition to these four variables, we used their logarithmic transformation considering their positive (i.e., right) skewed distribution, for a total of eight variables.</p><p id="Par50">We explored all the available demographic variables from the 2010 official census provided by the IBGE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. The census includes information at the municipality level for multiple socio-economic factors including education, sanitation, income, etc., with a total of 237 potential predictors. We aggregated the information to the state level and examined them together with their logarithmic transformations as explained above for a total of 474 variables. Because they represent information with different magnitudes in the form of total counts, percentages, and rates, we normalized all the variables before the analysis. We examined each variable individually with a pair-wise univariate linear regression using the R squared for GHT against dengue cases as a dependent variable; we selected those variables with an adjusted R squared higher than 0.6, and performed a Pearson&#x02019;s correlation among those selected to keep those with a score below 0.8. We then performed a multiple linear regression using the same dependent variable. We compared the ability of the selected variables to quantify GHT usefulness in Brazil using a principal component analysis (PCA) with the 474 predictors and selecting those components recovering more than 90% of the variance. The Pearson&#x02019;s correlation statistic was also implemented in order to assess the relatedness between Internet and demographic variables.</p><p id="Par51">Finally, to determine if variability in the signal of dengue incidence influences GHT accuracy, we computed a standardized volatility index for the dengue incidence data in each state. First, we normalized the dengue incidence time series, subtracting the mean and dividing it by its standard deviation. For this normalized time series, we averaged the absolute difference between each point in the data for each state&#x02014;incidence per week in this case&#x02014;to obtain a value representing the stability of dengue incidence (i.e., stable vs. unstable). All analyses were performed in R programming language [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>] using standard packages for statistical analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Results</title><p id="Par52">The Brazilian states with the overall highest yearly median number of dengue case counts from 2011 to 2016 are: S&#x000e3;o Paulo (829; min&#x02009;=&#x02009;52; max&#x02009;=&#x02009;61,944), Goi&#x000e1;s (693; min&#x02009;=&#x02009;29; max&#x02009;=&#x02009;9094), Minas Gerais (687; min&#x02009;=&#x02009;13; max&#x02009;=&#x02009;43,424), and Rio de Janeiro (635; min&#x02009;=&#x02009;12; max&#x02009;=&#x02009;18,602), followed by Cear&#x000e1; (526; min&#x02009;=&#x02009;5; max&#x02009;=&#x02009;6754), Bahia (507; min&#x02009;=&#x02009;12; max&#x02009;=&#x02009;6654), Esp&#x000ed;rito Santo (382; min&#x02009;=&#x02009;11; max&#x02009;=&#x02009;4279), and Pernambuco (326; min&#x02009;=&#x02009;19; max&#x02009;=&#x02009;5881; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: cases/incidences). States such as Rio Grande do Sul and Santa Catarina had a median of 4 and 3 cases, with a minimum of 0 cases and a maximum of 324 and 561 respectively, during the whole study period (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and Additional file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Conversely, when considering the weekly dengue incidence, there were two states with the overall highest yearly median values: Goi&#x000e1;s (1.154x10e-4; min&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.83x10e-6; max&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.515x10e-3) and Esp&#x000ed;rito Santo (1.087x10e-4; min&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.129x10e-6; max&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.217x10e-3), followed by Rio Grande do Norte (8.996&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10e-5; min&#x02009;=&#x02009;0; max&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.893x10e-3), Tocantins (8.638x10e-5; min&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.614x10e-6; max&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.539x10e-4), Alagoas (8.236x10e-5; min&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.602x10e-6; max&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.637x10e-4), Mato Grosso (7.034x10e-5; min&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.59x10e-7; max&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.762x10e-4), Acr&#x000e9; (6.271x10e-5; min&#x02009;=&#x02009;0; max&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.931x10e-3), and Cear&#x000e1; (6.223x10e-5; min&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.915x10e-7; max&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.991x10e-4; Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>); Santa Catarina and Rio Grande do Sul remained the states with the lowest median of weekly dengue incidence in the whole study period (4.801x10e-7 and 3.740x10e-7, respectively; Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>).
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Dengue weekly incidence and case counts at the state level in Brazil aggregated across 2011&#x02013;2016. States with low (yellow) and high (red) weekly incidence (top panel) and case counts (bottom panel) are depicted according to the median for the whole study period from 2011 to 2016. Boxplots (right panel) represent the variability of each state during the same time period. Maps were created with shape files from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.naturalearthdata.com/">https://www.naturalearthdata.com/</ext-link>. Labels are the official abbreviations of Brazilian states: AC: Acr&#x000e9;, AL: Alagoas, AP: Amap&#x000e1;, AM: Amazonas, BA: Bahia, CE: Cear&#x000e1;, DF (arrow): Distrito Federal, ES: Esp&#x000ed;rito Santo, GO: Goi&#x000e1;s, MA: Maranh&#x000e3;o, MT: Mato Grosso, MS: Mato Grosso do Sul, MG: Minas Gerais, PA: Par&#x000e1;, PB: Paraiba, PR: Paran&#x000e1;, PE: Pernambuco, PI: Piau&#x000ed;, RJ: Rio de Janeiro, RN: Rio Grande do Norte, RS: Rio Grande do Sul, RO: Rond&#x000f4;nia, RR: Roraima, SC: Santa Catarina, SP: S&#x000e3;o Paulo, SE: Sergipe, TO: Tocantins</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12879_2020_4957_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par53">From the 19 GHT terms, seven were useful in recovering information for all the Brazilian states, namely: &#x0201c;aedes&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;dengue&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;mosquito&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;aegypti&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;<italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;sintomas da dengue&#x0201d;, and &#x0201c;dengue sintomas&#x0201d;. From the remaining 12 terms, five never provided information and therefore were discarded in further analysis (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Six terms tracked dengue for some but not all the states; for example, the word &#x0201c;mosquitoes&#x0201d; were valuable for Distrito Federal, Minas Gerais, and Paran&#x000e1;, but unimportant for Acr&#x000e9;, Mato Grosso, or Santa Catarina. Two terms were informative in only one case: &#x0201c;dengue hemorrhagic fever&#x0201d; for S&#x000e3;o Paulo, and &#x0201c;DENV&#x0201d; for Brazil (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Availability of Google Health Trends to track dengue trends in Brazil and its states by term</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Terms</th><th>Number of terms</th><th>States</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Informative terms</td><td>&#x0201c;aedes&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;dengue&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;mosquito&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;aegypti&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;<italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;sintomas da dengue&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;dengue sintomas&#x0201d;</td><td char="." align="char">7</td><td>Brazil and all states</td></tr><tr><td>Uninformative terms</td><td>&#x0201c;aedes eg&#x000ed;pcio&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;eg&#x000ed;pcio&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;v&#x000ed;rus da dengue&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;novo v&#x000ed;rus da dengue&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;dengue &#x000e9; &#x02018;virus&#x0201d;</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td>Brazil and all states</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="6">Ambiguous terms</td><td>&#x0201c;dengue fever&#x0201d;</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td>Brazil and BA, CE, ES, GO, MG, PB, PR, RJ, RS, SP (10 states)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x0201c;dengue hemorrhagic fever&#x0201d;</td><td/><td>SP (1 state)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x0201c;DENV&#x0201d;</td><td/><td>Brazil</td></tr><tr><td>&#x0201c;DHF&#x0201d;</td><td/><td>Brazil and BA, GO, MT, MG, PR, PR, PE, RJ, RS, SP (10 states)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x0201c;dengue v&#x000ed;rus&#x0201d;</td><td/><td>Brazil and AM, BA, CE, DF, ES, GO, MA, MS, MG, PA, PB, PR, PE, RJ, RN, RS, RO, SC, SP (19 states)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x0201c;mosquitoes&#x0201d;</td><td/><td>Brazil and DF, MG, PR, RJ, RS, SP (6 states)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>From the 19 terms explored, only seven were able to consistently track dengue incidence from Google Health Trends in Brazil (i.e., national level) and its individual states. Abbreviations of Brazilian states: AC: Acr&#x000e9;, AL: Alagoas, AP: Amap&#x000e1;, AM: Amazonas, BA: Bahia, CE: Cear&#x000e1;, DF: Distrito Federal, ES: Esp&#x000ed;rito Santo, GO: Goi&#x000e1;s, MA: Maranh&#x000e3;o, MT: Mato Grosso, MS: Mato Grosso do Sul, MG: Minas Gerais, PA: Par&#x000e1;, PB: Paraiba, PR: Paran&#x000e1;, PE: Pernambuco, PI: Piau&#x000ed;, RJ: Rio de Janeiro, RN: Rio Grande do Norte, RS: Rio Grande do Sul, RO: Rond&#x000f4;nia, RR: Roraima, SC: Santa Catarina, SP: S&#x000e3;o Paulo, SE: Sergipe, TO: Tocantins</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par54">As expected, models developed with all the available terms per state fitted better to the weekly incidence dengue data than models developed with only four terms, uncorrelated terms, or with any of the individual terms when measuring the adjusted R squared statistic (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, and Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: adjusted R squared for individual terms). Individually, the most informative terms among those conceptually related with the disease included &#x0201c;dengue sintomas&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;dengue&#x0201d;, and &#x0201c;sintomas da dengue&#x0201d; (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Among the terms related with the vectors, &#x0201c;mosquito dengue&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;mosquito&#x0201d; were the most informative (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Correlated and uncorrelated terms for each state are shown in Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>. We used a pair-wise ANOVA between models developed with all terms vs. models developed with reduced combination of terms (i.e., four terms and uncorrelated terms), and the individual terms for each state. From 328 comparisons&#x02014;different number of terms were available for different states (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>)&#x02014;only in ten comparisons a reduced model was statistically comparable (i.e., not different, <italic>F</italic> statistic with a <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05) to the model with all the terms, namely: the models based on four and uncorrelated terms and the model with the word &#x0201c;dengue&#x0201d; for Amap&#x000e1;, models developed with four terms for Distrito Federal, Maranh&#x000e3;o, Par&#x000e1;, Rio Grande do Norte, Santa Catarina, and Sergipe, and models developed with uncorrelated terms for Roraima. Thus, for the subsequent analysis we used the adjusted R squared statistic from the models built using all the available terms in each state.
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Adjusted R squared according to Google Health Trends search terms. All available terms per state and combined terms (i.e., all, four, and uncorrelated terms) were assessed in their ability to track weekly dengue incidences during 2011&#x02013;2016. Combined terms showed the median highest adjusted R squared values (purple)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12879_2020_4957_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Adjusted R squared for multiple linear models using all, uncorrelated, and four available terms</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>State</th><th>Adjusted R squared &#x02013; All terms model (n)</th><th>Adjusted R squared &#x02013; Uncorrelated terms model (n)</th><th>Adjusted R squared &#x02013; Four terms model (<bold><italic>n</italic></bold>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;4)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Acr&#x000e9; (AC)</td><td>0.126 (7)</td><td>0.110 (6)</td><td>0.092</td></tr><tr><td>Alagoas (AL)</td><td>0.481 (8)</td><td>0.418 (3)</td><td>0.470</td></tr><tr><td>Amap&#x000e1; (AP)</td><td>0.096 (7)</td><td>0.099 (6)</td><td>0.103</td></tr><tr><td>Amazonas (AM)</td><td><bold>0.847 (9)</bold></td><td>0.590 (2)</td><td><bold>0.821</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Bahia (BA)</td><td>0.647 (11)</td><td>0.603 (3)</td><td>0.624</td></tr><tr><td>Cear&#x000e1; (CE)</td><td><bold>0.839 (10)</bold></td><td>0.746 (3)</td><td><bold>0.812</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Distrito Federal (DF)</td><td><bold>0.829 (10)</bold></td><td>0.433 (2)</td><td><bold>0.830</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Esp&#x000ed;rito Santo (ES)</td><td>0.725 (10)</td><td>0.537 (3)</td><td>0.688</td></tr><tr><td>Goi&#x000e1;s (GO)</td><td>0.785 (11)</td><td>0.660 (3)</td><td>0.768</td></tr><tr><td>Maranh&#x000e3;o (MA)</td><td><bold>0.859 (9)</bold></td><td>0.615 (2)</td><td><bold>0.856</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Mato Grosso (MT)</td><td>0.573 (9)</td><td>0.453 (3)</td><td>0.559</td></tr><tr><td>Mato Grosso do Sul (MS)</td><td>0.713 (9)</td><td>0.583 (3)</td><td>0.694</td></tr><tr><td>Minas Gerais (MG)</td><td><bold>0.923 (12)</bold></td><td>0.718 (4)</td><td><bold>0.919</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Par&#x000e1; (PA)</td><td>0.600 (9)</td><td>0.277 (2)</td><td>0.596</td></tr><tr><td>Paraiba (PB)</td><td><bold>0.837 (10)</bold></td><td>0.683 (3)</td><td><bold>0.832</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Paran&#x000e1; (PR)</td><td><bold>0.845 (12)</bold></td><td>0.741 (4)</td><td><bold>0.821</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Pernambuco (PE)</td><td><bold>0.819 (10)</bold></td><td>0.714 (2)</td><td><bold>0.808</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Piau&#x000ed; (PI)</td><td>0.553 (8)</td><td>0.377 (3)</td><td>0.542</td></tr><tr><td>Rio de Janeiro (RJ)</td><td>0.765 (12)</td><td>0.704 (5)</td><td>0.744</td></tr><tr><td>Rio Grande do Norte (RN)</td><td><bold>0.890 (9)</bold></td><td>0.706 (2)</td><td><bold>0.891</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Rio Grande do Sul (RS)</td><td><bold>0.804 (12)</bold></td><td>0.724 (4)</td><td>0.779</td></tr><tr><td>Rond&#x000f4;nia (RO)</td><td>0.568 (9)</td><td>0.415 (4)</td><td>0.544</td></tr><tr><td>Roraima (RR)</td><td>0.093 (7)</td><td>0.091 (6)</td><td>0.058</td></tr><tr><td>Santa Catarina (SC)</td><td><bold>0.826 (9)</bold></td><td>0.788 (2)</td><td><bold>0.825</bold></td></tr><tr><td>S&#x000e3;o Paulo (SP)</td><td><bold>0.930 (13)</bold></td><td><bold>0.861 (6)</bold></td><td><bold>0.919</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Sergipe (SE)</td><td>0.308 (8)</td><td>0.216 (3)</td><td>0.300</td></tr><tr><td>Tocantins (TO)</td><td>0.415 (8)</td><td>0.342 (4)</td><td>0.401</td></tr><tr><td>Brazil</td><td><bold>0.888 (14)</bold></td><td><bold>0.852 (7)</bold></td><td><bold>0.850</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Different numbers of terms (n) were available depending on the state (e.g., S&#x000e3;o Paulo vs. Acr&#x000e9;) and were correlated considering a state-by-state basis (e.g., Amap&#x000e1; vs. Maranhn&#x000e3;o; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: terms per state). Four terms model was developed with &#x0201c;dengue&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;dengue sintomas&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;aedes&#x0201d;, and &#x0201c;mosquito&#x0201d;. Bold represent adjusted R squared values above 0.8. Data for Brazil is shown in the last row</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par55">As demonstrated previously, GHT fit the aggregated country-level dengue incidence well (All terms adjusted R squared&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.888, Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and Additional&#x000a0;file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: all plots for Brazil). For Distrito Federal, GHT data was only available starting November 24th, 2013; thus, for this case we performed all the analysis starting that date (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>: all plots for the 27 states). When analyzing each state separately, GHT was useful in some states but uninformative in others (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The highest adjusted R squared was for Minas Gerais (0.923) and S&#x000e3;o Paulo (0.930), while the worst fit was for Amap&#x000e1; (0.096) and Roraima (0.093; Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Overall, by using all the terms combined, GHT was able to track weekly dengue incidences for 12 states with an adjusted R squared higher than 0.8, namely: Amazonas, Cear&#x000e1;, Distrito Federal, Maranh&#x000e3;o, Minas Gerais, Paraiba, Pernambuco, Paran&#x000e1;, Rio Grande do Norte, Rio Grande do Sul, Santa Catarina, and S&#x000e3;o Paulo (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Considering an adjusted R squared value of 0.7, we can include four more states in this list: Esp&#x000ed;rito Santo, Goi&#x000e1;s, Mato Grosso do Sul, and Rio de Janeiro, for a total of 16 states were GHT might be implemented for tracking dengue dynamics (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Google Health Trends and weekly dengue incidence in four Brazilian states, 2011&#x02013;2016. Models built with all the terms available per state were useful for tracking dengue incidence during the study period for some (top panel) but not all (bottom panel) Brazilian states. The states that are not well predicted have noisier signals and lack strong seasonal dengue case counts, which may account for poor correlation with Google Health Trends in these regions. Lower access to Internet may also be a factor (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12879_2020_4957_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par56">All the Internet data variables were highly correlated with each other (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>: correlation plot). The logarithm of the number of Internet users per state partially explains when GHT will be able to track dengue incidence (all terms adjusted R squared&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.621, Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). For instance, in the case of S&#x000e3;o Paulo and Minas Gerais, with the highest number of Internet users [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>], the adjusted R squared for GHT and dengue incidence was high (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, log scale); on the other hand, states such as Acr&#x000e9;, Amap&#x000e1;, or Roraima with low numbers of Internet users [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>] had a lower R squared value (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, log scale). States such as Rio Grande do Norte, Amazonas, Paraiba, and Distrito Federal, had high GHT fit and a low number of Internet users, and viceversa for Rio de Janeiro and Bahia (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Logarithm of Internet users and Google Health Trends adjusted R squared. Maps (right panels) depict the adjusted R squared statistic per state when assessing Google Health Trends with their corresponding dengue incidence (linear regression plot). Twelve of 27 states showed values above 0.8 (top, dark blue). The logarithm of Internet users shows that the majority of the Brazilian states with high numbers of Internet users were concentrated at the southeast of Brazil (bottom, dark blue), but the remaining states show limited Internet penetration (pale green). Some states showed low number of Internet users but high GHT data fit (e.g., Amazonas, Maranh&#x000e3;o, Paraiba, Distrito Federal). Maps were created with shape files from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.naturalearthdata.com/">https://www.naturalearthdata.com/</ext-link>. Abbreviations of Brazilian states: AC: Acr&#x000e9;, AL: Alagoas, AP: Amap&#x000e1;, AM: Amazonas, BA: Bahia, CE: Cear&#x000e1;, DF: Distrito Federal, ES: Esp&#x000ed;rito Santo, GO: Goi&#x000e1;s, MA: Maranh&#x000e3;o, MT: Mato Grosso, MS: Mato Grosso do Sul, MG: Minas Gerais, PA: Par&#x000e1;, PB: Paraiba, PR: Paran&#x000e1;, PE: Pernambuco, PI: Piau&#x000ed;, RJ: Rio de Janeiro, RN: Rio Grande do Norte, RS: Rio Grande do Sul, RO: Rond&#x000f4;nia, RR: Roraima, SC: Santa Catarina, SP: S&#x000e3;o Paulo, SE: Sergipe, TO: Tocantins</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12879_2020_4957_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par57">From the 474 census demographic predictors, only 49 had an adjusted R squared higher than 0.6, all of which corresponded to variables related to the logarithmic transformation of the state population (see Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">7</xref>: 49 demographic variables). The 49 variables were highly correlated with each other (minimum <italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.946); thus, a model including only the logarithm of the total population per state (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> top-left panel) was similar to the one using the logarithm of the total number of Internet users (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>&#x02014;adjusted R squared&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.6218&#x02014;vs. Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> top-left panel&#x02014;adjusted R squared&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.6143), a consequence of the high correlation between the predictors involved: population and number of Internet users (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.98). Within the PCA framework, the first six PCs recovered 91% of the variance and a model developed with these components yielded similar results as the ones obtained using either the logarithm of the number of Internet users or the logarithm of total population per state (Adjusted R squared&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.654; Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media">8</xref>: PCA results).
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Total population and volatility index as predictors of Google Health Trends adjusted R squared. From 474 predictors, variables related with population where the most informative anticipating GHT behavior (top-left). The volatility index was useful detecting GHT accuracy although imprecise in some states such as Acr&#x000e9; (top-right). Models considering the standardized volatility index and either the total population (bottom-left) or the number of Internet users (bottom-right) were the most informative anticipating GHT accuracy. Abbreviations of Brazilian states: AC: Acr&#x000e9;, AL: Alagoas, AP: Amap&#x000e1;, AM: Amazonas, BA: Bahia, CE: Cear&#x000e1;, DF: Distrito Federal, ES: Esp&#x000ed;rito Santo, GO: Goi&#x000e1;s, MA: Maranh&#x000e3;o, MT: Mato Grosso, MS: Mato Grosso do Sul, MG: Minas Gerais, PA: Par&#x000e1;, PB: Paraiba, PR: Paran&#x000e1;, PE: Pernambuco, PI: Piau&#x000ed;, RJ: Rio de Janeiro, RN: Rio Grande do Norte, RS: Rio Grande do Sul, RO: Rond&#x000f4;nia, RR: Roraima, SC: Santa Catarina, SP: S&#x000e3;o Paulo, SE: Sergipe, TO: Tocantins</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12879_2020_4957_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par58">States with the highest standardized volatility index, or high variability in reported dengue incidence, had less informative adjusted R squared when fitting GHT to incidence. States with smoother signals of dengue incidence, and therefore low volatility, had a better fit of GHT to incidence, resulting in adjusted R squared values above 0.8 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). However, even with a stable dengue incidence signal, GHT was not able to track dengue in Acr&#x000e9; (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> top-right panel). A model using the logarithm of the number of Internet users, the volatility index, and their interaction as predictors of GHT had the highest adjusted R squared among all the variables explored (= 0.694, Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> bottom-right panel). The same model with the logarithm of population instead of Internet users showed a similar adjusted R squared (= 0.688, Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> bottom-left panel). These models were comparable to those using the individual terms of the logarithm of total population, the number of Internet users, or the selected PCs (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media">8</xref>). Eliminating Acr&#x000e9;, the state with low volatility but low GHT accuracy (i.e., outlier), we saw an improvement in the models using the standardized volatility index plus its interactions with Internet users or total population (All terms vs. volatility index model, adjusted R squared&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.717; all terms vs. Internet users (log)&#x02009;+&#x02009;standardized volatility index, adjusted R squared&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.793; and all terms vs. population&#x02009;+&#x02009;standardized volatility index adjusted R squared&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.809).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par59">Digital surveillance systems have been shown to be useful for predicting country-wide dengue incidence in several countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. Here, we evaluate the usefulness of GHT in tracking dengue incidence both at the country and the state level in Brazil, by evaluating GHT correlation with weekly dengue incidence data over 6 years. We have shown that the performance of GHT varies across states (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, and additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>); however, it is highly correlated with dengue incidence (adjusted R squared &#x0003e;&#x02009;0.8) in 12 Brazilian states that are geographically dispersed. Moreover, we showed that proxies of Internet penetration such as the number of Internet users in the last 3 months only partially explain the usefulness of GHT (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). In fact, the logarithm of the total population, from among 474 potential demographic predictors, allowed us to build a model that quantified GHT usefulness with similar accuracy to that of Internet penetration data (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). The standardized volatility index in combination with the number of Internet users or the total population provided the highest accuracy when predicting GHT usefulness (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).</p><p id="Par60">Harvesting epidemiological information from Internet-data streams remains an active area of research for health purposes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Despite its caveats [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], it has the potential to improve and complement traditional disease surveillance methods. In particular, they may be useful in timely outbreak detection and in settings where health surveillance is underdeveloped [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. However, before implementation, tools such as GHT should be explored at spatial resolutions smaller than countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. Ours is one of the few studies addressing this gap showing that GHT usefulness will be heavily impacted by the political boundaries at which we wish to predict [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. In our case, GHT had an adjusted R squared score higher than 0.8 in 12 states, distributed among the five macro-regions of Brazil. The majority of states where GHT successfully track dengue incidence were located in the Southeast&#x02014;Minas Gerais and S&#x000e3;o Paulo&#x02014;, South&#x02014;Paran&#x000e1;, Santa Catarina, Rio Grande do Sul&#x02014;, and Northeast of the country&#x02014;Cear&#x000e1;, Maranh&#x000e3;o, Paraiba, Pernambuco, Rio Grande do Norte&#x02014;, with the latter concentrating states with higher incidences (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). In general, these three macro-regions are considered the most economically developed of Brazil [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. The Southeast and the South macro-regions have, in general, lower dengue incidence despite having the majority of cases (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), highlighting the importance of normalizing measures to allow disease burden comparisons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. We calculated incidence rates based on the total population of each state to compare dengue burden, showing that high number of dengue cases in the Southeast are explained by the presence of high-density populations. Among the Southeast, Rio de Janeiro state might benefit from integrating GHT surveillance into dengue modeling and prediction efforts, considering an adjusted R squared of 0.765 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). At the Northeast, Cear&#x000e1; and Rio Grande do Norte showed higher dengue incidence (= 6.223x10e-5 and 8.996x10e-5, respectively) with a high GHT fit to incidence data (adjusted R squared&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.839 and 0.890, respectively) followed by Paraiba and Pernambuco (adjusted R squared&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.837 and 0.819, respectively; Figs. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par61">The remaining states where GHT was able to track dengue incidence were found in the Central-West&#x02014;Distrito Federal&#x02014;, and the North&#x02014;Amazonas&#x02014;macro-regions, with one state each (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Both macro-regions represent the fourth and fifth economies of Brazil, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. GHT for the Amazonas state could complement traditional clinical surveillance approaches (adjusted R squared&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.847) considering its large area extent, moderate dengue incidence aggregated across all years (= 3.014x10e-5), and geographical location (Western portion of the North macro-region and far from the developed Brazilian Southeast; Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). The North macro-region also included the states of Acr&#x000e9;, Amap&#x000e1;, Roraima, and Tocantins where GHT showed a poor behavior due to the low number of Internet users (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Both the North and Central-West areas include states with high dengue incidence consisting of Acr&#x000e9;, Goi&#x000e1;s, Mato Grosso, and Tocantins (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>); among them, only Goi&#x000e1;s showed a high GHT fit (adjusted R squared&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.785); meanwhile the other states showed adjusted R squared values lower than 0.5 (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).</p><p id="Par62">Among the North and Northeast Brazilian macro-regions, Maranh&#x000e3;o, Par&#x000e1;, and Sergipe have the lower dengue incidence (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). For these states, only Maranh&#x000e3;o showed a good GHT fit (adjusted R squared&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.859). The state of Alagoas showed a moderate dengue incidence aggregated across all years (=8.236x10e-5; Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>) but poor GHT behavior (adjusted R squared&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.481) despite being surrounded by states with good GHT performance (e.g., adjusted R squared Pernambuco&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.819 and Bahia&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.647; Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). We expected Alagoas to have similar dynamics as the rest of its surrounding states due to similar environmental and epidemiological trends, all limited by the Atlantic Ocean with a comparable area extent (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). However, variability in local surveillance and mosquito control strategies might account for the differences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p><p id="Par63">We suggest that multiple search terms should be explored when using GHT. In our case, only 7 from the initial 19 terms, retrieved information consistently in all the Brazilian states within our study period (Tables <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>), from the other terms, information was recovered only in specific instances (e.g., &#x0201c;dengue virus&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;dengue fever&#x0201d; for Bahia but not for Acr&#x000e9;; Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Models developed with all terms were statistically different from models developed with any of the subset term schemes (i.e., uncorrelated terms, four terms, individual terms) with the exception of ten comparisons. From them, Distrito Federal, Maranh&#x000e3;o, Rio Grande do Norte, and Santa Catarina were states in which GHT adjusted R squared was higher than 0.8 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) and the four term model was not statistically different from the full term model (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05 in an ANOVA pair-wise comparison). Still, this was not the case for any of the other comparisons (i.e., 318), and more importantly, not for any of the terms individually. We recommend gathering GHT data using multiple terms in order to track dengue incidence dynamics at the state level in Brazil, potentially, this approach would be useful in other countries. While the approach for determining search terms vary, we posit that they should include both keywords (e.g., &#x0201c;dengue&#x0201d;) and conceptual words (e.g., &#x0201c;dengue sintomas&#x0201d;) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] and should be selected according to the official and common languages of the country studied, Portuguese and English in our case; for instance, in Singapore searches using English terms were superior than searches using the Malay or Tami local languages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p><p id="Par64">Intuitively, the ability to determine if Internet data is going to be useful should depend on access to information and communication technologies. In this study, we found that the number of Internet users acts as a moderate predictor for GHT performance (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Similarly, Internet penetration has been demonstrated as a dubious variable for data derived from Google search engines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>], and here, we showed that at least for states with both high and low Internet access (e.g., S&#x000e3;o Paulo, Minas Gerais vs. Acr&#x000e9;, Roraima, Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), this variable can be regarded as a good predictor. However, for states such as Amazonas, Distrito Federal, Paraiba, and Rio Grande do Norte, only relying on the number of Internet users would have been an equivocal signal of GHT usefulness; thus, our data support a case-by-case investigation of Internet data.</p><p id="Par65">Variables related to the total population per state were informative in determining GHT performance (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">7</xref>: demographic variables) and these predictors were highly correlated with the total number of Internet users (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.98). As Internet penetration increases worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>], the total population per studied political unit, might be a reliable predictor to inform whether or not dengue surveillance based on digital epidemiology tools can complement traditional surveillance. However, other demographic predictors could also serve as indicators of GHT performance. We explored this possibility using various variable selection methods including Pearson&#x02019;s correlation on the full 474 variables, a stepwise (i.e., forward and backward) multiple linear regression, and an elastic net regression with L1 normalization (i.e., Least Absolute Shrinkage and Selection Operator or Lasso) using leave-one-out cross validation fashion (Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM9" ref-type="media">9</xref>: variable selection). Although a combination of five demographic variables allowed us to develop an improved prediction than total population alone (adjusted R squared&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.670), how those variables may translate to other countries is not immediately clear (e.g., percentage of population that lives in urban households with garbage collecting services; Additional&#x000a0;files&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM9" ref-type="media">9</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM10" ref-type="media">10</xref>: other demographic variables). In addition, models developed using multivariate linear regressions with different variable combinations never outperformed the model developed using PCA (Additional&#x000a0;files&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media">8</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM9" ref-type="media">9</xref>), or those involving population and the standardized volatility index (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, bottom-left panel).</p><p id="Par66">The volatility index discussed here might also aid on addressing when to use GHT predictions for dengue (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). In the context of detailed Internet access data, a model considering volatility and Internet users might be a straightforward exploration (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). From a practical perspective, due to the potential lack of fine-resolution data on Internet accessibility in other countries, the total number of people plus the described standardized volatility index might be useful indicators of GHT performance. Finally, as has been discussed previously, we also explored if the total number of dengue cases would be a useful predictor to assess GHT performance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>], but this predictor was less useful than any of the others explored (i.e., GHT for all terms vs. logarithm of total number of dengue cases, adjusted R squared&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.274).</p><p id="Par67">There are some limitations and caveats to our study. For the Distrito Federal state, GHT data was available for half of the study period, thus, we tested the GHT against weekly dengue incidence only for the corresponding timeframe, which involved ~&#x02009;3&#x02009;years. The state of Distrito Federal corresponds to a small geographical region established as the capital of the country in 1960 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>); we hypothesize that the lack of data was an artifact of Google&#x02019; algorithm missing the corresponding state before November 2013. Although we do not have any specific evidence of this, it is possibly related to what has been called &#x0201c;blue team dynamics&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], that is, changes on the search engine can affect how and when GHT gathers data. In the same way, GHT retrieves information as a relative proportion of search volumes, as a consequence GHT data for the Brazilian states will not sum up to the same data at the country level and therefore GHT data for the whole country should be evaluated as an independent unit from its states [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. This explains issues such as those presented in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> where, for example, the term &#x0201c;DENV&#x0201d; was only available for the whole country and not for any particular state. Regardless, GHT&#x02019;s relative proportion volume represents search patterns in an improved way than the ranked scores from GT. In the majority of studies using the latter, a transformation is needed in order to continue with the analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], this step might add noise to prediction studies with GT.</p><p id="Par68">In the present work, we did not split our data on training-testing datasets, which is a limitation of our approach. However, instead of dealing with prediction ability (i.e., forecasting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]), we based our evaluation on how GHT reflects dengue incidence in the Brazilian states and where it could inform and complement traditional epidemiological surveillance. Further, we did not include environmental variables known to alter dengue dynamics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. To implement GHT as complementary surveillance tool, other sources of uncertainties should be considered, among them, dengue information-seeking behavior might be confounded by the surge of other arbovirus-diseases such as chikungunya or Zika [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>], or less well-known pathogens such as Mayaro, Oropouche, or West Nile viruses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>], all transmitted by different vectors from the order Diptera, which could trigger local web search behavior. This is especially true because of unspecific initial clinical presentations for those pathogens, media-induced panic or interest [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>], and because health campaigns are often aimed towards vector control due to the lack of specific treatments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Moreover, the GHT platform is unstable and could potentially be altered by any update or improvement on Google&#x02019;s search algorithm itself [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] hindering replicability of these kind of studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>].</p><p id="Par69">Although GHT and other digital tools might be also capturing information from non-infected individuals, searching for the disease terms with different goals or induced by panic related media, it is likely also capturing a portion of the population that is missing medical care for multiple reasons. As has been shown for dengue surveillance in Brazil, the number of patients that are hospitalized and recorded as true &#x0201c;dengue&#x0201d; cases are more than ~&#x02009;50% the number of patients that are actually registered in the official epidemiological surveillance system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], which is a broad phenomena described also for other countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]. Thus, an agreement between suspected dengue cases and GHT would indicate at least the presence of an outbreak.</p><p id="Par70">Despite critics of models based on Google-derived data, several studies are demonstrating the potential usefulness of this approach for epidemiological research and how it can complement other forecasting models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]. Nonetheless, further studies face another problem:&#x000a0;the availability of reliable health data, which is seldom shared in homogeneous user-friendly formats for representative timeframes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]. Only by assuring a constant supply of sound, consistent, and truly open access health reports, digital epidemiology could exploit the potential of big data considering the massive, but usually inaccessible, information from the public health domain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par71">Digital epidemiology approaches based on GHT or other tools should be explored beyond country level to consider its actual ability to inform local public health departments. In the case of dengue in Brazil, 12 out of 27 states showed an adjusted R squared higher than 0.8, which suggests the potential ability of GHT to complement classical epidemiological surveillance, even though some states had low incidence during the 6-year study period (i.e., 2011&#x02013;2016). Models developed with multiple terms were most informative than models using reduced sets or individual terms. Variables such as number of Internet users and total population per state are useful in determining where GHT could complement current surveillance strategies in several Brazilian states. Moreover, both variables benefit from the use of a standardized volatility index for selection of areas of GHT usefulness. The methods proposed here might be applied in other countries to test the ability of GHT to support dengue surveillance. Future studies might also explore the ability of GHT to track dengue using detailed measures of dengue transmission such as the force of infection, only confirmed cases, finer political boundaries (e.g., GHT data is available to particular cities in the world), or different temporal schemes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec9"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12879_2020_4957_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1.</bold> Total, median, minimum, and maximum numbers of dengue cases and incidence from the period 2011&#x02013;2016.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12879_2020_4957_MOESM2_ESM.docx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 2.</bold> Adjusted R squared between Google Health Trends and weekly incidence of dengue for Brazil and all the 27 states for individual search terms.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="12879_2020_4957_MOESM3_ESM.docx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 3.</bold> Available, correlated and uncorrelated terms, and adjusted R squared for multiple linear models with their corresponding correlation plots.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="12879_2020_4957_MOESM4_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 4.</bold> Plots of multiple and simple linear models between Google Health Trends data and weekly dengue incidence for Brazil.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="12879_2020_4957_MOESM5_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 5.</bold> Plots of multiple and simple linear models between Google Health Trends data and weekly dengue incidence for each of the 27 Brazilian states.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="12879_2020_4957_MOESM6_ESM.docx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 6.</bold> Correlation plot of the Internet access variables selected in the study.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM7"><media xlink:href="12879_2020_4957_MOESM7_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 7.</bold> Definition of 49 demographic variables showing an adjusted R squared higher than 0.6 on a pair-wise linear regression models.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM8"><media xlink:href="12879_2020_4957_MOESM8_ESM.docx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 8.</bold> Results of the principal component analysis of 474 predictors.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM9"><media xlink:href="12879_2020_4957_MOESM9_ESM.docx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 9.</bold> Variables selected by applying different variable selection routines and definitions of each of the selected predictors.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM10"><media xlink:href="12879_2020_4957_MOESM10_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 10.</bold> Description of variables selected according to different methods.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>API</term><def><p id="Par5">Application private interface</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DHF</term><def><p id="Par6">Dengue hemorrhagic fever</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DENV</term><def><p id="Par7">Dengue virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GDT</term><def><p id="Par8">Google Dengue Trends</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GFT</term><def><p id="Par9">Google Flu Trends</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GHT</term><def><p id="Par10">Google Health Trends</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GT</term><def><p id="Par11">Google Trends</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IBGE</term><def><p id="Par12">Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estat&#x000ed;stica (Brazilian Institute for Geography and Statistics, English)</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PNAD</term><def><p id="Par13">Pesquisa Nacional por Amostra de Domic&#x000ed;lios (National Household Sample Survey, English)</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><glossary><title>Brazilian states</title><def-list><def-item><term>AC</term><def><p id="Par14">Acr&#x000e9;</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AL</term><def><p id="Par15">Alagoas</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AP</term><def><p id="Par16">Amap&#x000e1;</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AM</term><def><p id="Par17">Amazonas</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BA</term><def><p id="Par18">Bahia</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CE</term><def><p id="Par19">Cear&#x000e1;</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DF</term><def><p id="Par20">Distrito Federal</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ES</term><def><p id="Par21">Esp&#x000ed;rito Santo</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GO</term><def><p id="Par22">Goi&#x000e1;s</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MA</term><def><p id="Par23">Maranh&#x000e3;o</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MT</term><def><p id="Par24">Mato Grosso</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MS</term><def><p id="Par25">Mato Grosso do Sul</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MG</term><def><p id="Par26">Minas Gerais</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PA</term><def><p id="Par27">Par&#x000e1;</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PB</term><def><p id="Par28">Paraiba</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PR</term><def><p id="Par29">Paran&#x000e1;</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PE</term><def><p id="Par30">Pernambuco</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PI</term><def><p id="Par31">Piau&#x000ed;</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RJ</term><def><p id="Par32">Rio de Janeiro</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RN</term><def><p id="Par33">Rio Grande do Norte</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RS</term><def><p id="Par34">Rio Grande do Sul</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RO</term><def><p id="Par35">Rond&#x000f4;nia</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RR</term><def><p id="Par36">Roraima</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SC</term><def><p id="Par37">Santa Catarina</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SP</term><def><p id="Par38">S&#x000e3;o Paulo</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SE</term><def><p id="Par39">Sergipe</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TO</term><def><p id="Par40">Tocantins</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1186/s12879-020-04957-0.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thanks the rest of Los Alamos National Laboratory team working actively on epidemiology including Geoffrey Fairchild, Jessica Conrad, Katherine Kempfert, and Amanda Ziemann.</p><p>Further, we extend our thanks to Marcelo Henrique de Araujo, who pointed us to the information and communication technology survey in Brazil.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>DRA and CM drafted the first version of the manuscript. DRA, NP, and KM collected data and performed analysis. DO developed statistical indices. DRA, NP, and CM designed and coordinated the study. NG, SV, and CM, conceived the study and supervised the project. All authors read, reviewed, and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This research was partially funded by the Laboratory Directed Research Development Program at Los Alamos National Laboratory (20190581ECR and 20200033DR), and by NIH/NIGMS under grant R01GM130668. Los Alamos National Laboratory is operated by Triad National Security, LLC under Contract No. 89233218CNA000001 with the U.S. Department of Energy. The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the sponsors. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>Datasets analyzed in the present study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par72">The Ministry of Public Health from Brazil handed out weekly case counts. No information associated with personal information of the cases was disclosed or used for the development of this study.</p></notes><notes><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par73">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par74">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gubler</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Izquierdo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Halstead</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dengue infection</article-title><source>Nat Rev Dis Prim</source><year>2016</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>16055</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27534439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mustafa</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasotgi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Discovery of fifth serotype of dengue virus (DENV-5): a new public health dilemma in dengue control</article-title><source>Med J Armed Forces India</source><year>2015</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25609867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Messina</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Golding</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraemer</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name><name><surname>Wint</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The current and future global distribution and population at risk of dengue</article-title><source>Nat Microbiol</source><year>2019</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1508</fpage><lpage>1515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31182801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Messina</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pigott</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brownstein</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoen</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A global compendium of human dengue virus occurrence</article-title><source>Sci Data</source><year>2014</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>140004</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25977762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tomasello</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlagenhauf</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chikungunya and dengue autochthonous cases in Europe, 2007&#x02013;2012</article-title><source>Travel Med Infect Dis</source><year>2013</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23962447</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Semenza</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Suk</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vector-borne diseases and climate change: a European perspective</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>2017</year><volume>365</volume><fpage>fnx244</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kraemer</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinka</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Duda</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mylne</surname><given-names>AQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shearer</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The global distribution of the arbovirus vectors <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and <italic>Ae. Albopictus</italic></article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e08347</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26126267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenawy</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rady</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Khaled</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Samy</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mapping the global potential distributions of two arboviral vectors <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> under changing climate</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>e0210122</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30596764</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Alwis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dengue viruses are enhanced by distinct populations of serotype cross-reactive antibodies in human immune sera</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e1004386</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25275316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Halstead</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Secondary infection as a risk factor for dengue hemorrhagic fever/dengue shock syndrome: an historical perspective and role of antibody-dependent enhancement of infection</article-title><source>Arch Virol</source><year>2013</year><volume>158</volume><fpage>1445</fpage><lpage>1459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23471635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization (WHO). Special Programme for Research and Training in Tropical Diseases (TDR). Dengue: guidelines for diagnosis, treatment, prevention, and control. Geneva: WHO; 2009. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/tdr/publications/training-guideline-publications/dengue-diagnosis-treatment/en/">https://www.who.int/tdr/publications/training-guideline-publications/dengue-diagnosis-treatment/en/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effective dengue vaccines: a pipe dream?</article-title><source>Viral Immunol</source><year>2019</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31074691</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salles</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;-Guimar&#x000e3;es</surname><given-names>TDE</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarenga</surname><given-names>ESLD</given-names></name><name><surname>Guimar&#x000e3;es-Ribeiro</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Meneses</surname><given-names>MDF</given-names></name><name><surname>Castro-Salles</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>History, epidemiology and diagnostics of dengue in the American and Brazilian contexts: a review</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors</source><year>2018</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>264</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29690895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhatt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gething</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Messina</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Farlow</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Moyes</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The global distribution and burden of dengue</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2013</year><volume>496</volume><fpage>504</fpage><lpage>507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23563266</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stanaway</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepard</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Undurraga</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Halasa</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Coffeng</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The global burden of dengue: an analysis from the global burden of disease study 2013</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>712</fpage><lpage>723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26874619</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shepard</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Coudeville</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Halasa</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zambrano</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dayan</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Economic impact of dengue illness in the Americas</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source><year>2011</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21292885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Luther</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Moo-Llanes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramsey</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Danis-Lozano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change influences on global distributions of dengue and chikungunya virus vectors</article-title><source>Philos Trans R Soc B</source><year>2015</year><volume>370</volume><fpage>20140135</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez-Barraquer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Cordeiro</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Braga</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>WV</given-names></name><name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>DAT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From re-emergence to hyperendemicity: the natural history of the dengue epidemic in Brazil</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e935</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21245922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gubler</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dengue, urbanization and globalization: the unholy trinity of the 21st century</article-title><source>Trop Med Health</source><year>2011</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>S3</fpage><lpage>S11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Minist&#x000e9;rio da Sa&#x000fa;de, Brasil. Secretaria de Vigil&#x000e2;ncia em Sa&#x000fa;de</collab></person-group><source>Boletim Epidemiol&#x000f3;gico 04. Semana Epidemiol&#x000f3;gica 52 de 2018</source><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Minist&#x000e9;rio da Sa&#x000fa;de, Brasil. Secretaria de Vigil&#x000e2;ncia em Sa&#x000fa;de</collab></person-group><source>Boletim Epidemiol&#x000f3;gico 22. Semana Epidemiol&#x000f3;gica 34 de 2019</source><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coelho</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerroni</surname><given-names>MDP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sensitivity of the dengue surveillance system in Brazil for detecting hospitalized cases</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0004705</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27192405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nsubuga</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Thacker</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Blount</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Broome</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><etal/><etal/></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Jamison</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Breman</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Measham</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><etal/><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chapter 53: Public health surveillance: a tool for targeting and monitoring interventions</article-title><source>Disease control priorities in developing countries</source><year>2006</year><edition>2</edition><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>World Bank and Oxford University Press</publisher-name><fpage>997</fpage><lpage>1015</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fairchild</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Generous</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hickmann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Osthus</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Priedhorsky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epidemic forecasting is messier than weather forecasting: the role of human behavior and internet data streams in epidemic forecast</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>214</volume><fpage>S404</fpage><lpage>S408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28830111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romero-Alvarez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Escobar</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surveillance fatigue (fatigatio vigilantiae) during epidemics</article-title><source>Rev Chil Infectol</source><year>2017</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>290</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grillet</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez-Villena</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Llewellyn</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Paniz-Mondolfi</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tami</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincenti-Gonzalez</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Venezuela&#x02019;s humanitarian crisis, resurgence of vector-borne diseases, and implications for spillover in the region</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2019</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>e149</fpage><lpage>e161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30799251</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kluberg</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekaru</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mclver</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Madoff</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawley</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Smolinski</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global capacity for emerging infectious disease detection, 1996&#x02013;2014</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>10</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salath&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Digital epidemiology: what is it, and where is it going?</article-title><source>Life Sci Soc Policy</source><year>2018</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29302758</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brownstein</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Freifeld</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandl</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surveillance sans Fronti&#x000e8;res: internet-based emerging infectious disease intelligence and the HealthMap project</article-title><source>PLoS Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e151</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18613747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hugh-Jones</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global awareness of disease outbreaks: the experience of ProMED-mail</article-title><source>Public Health Rep</source><year>2001</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>S27</fpage><lpage>S31</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pollett</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Althouse</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Forshey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutherford</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarman</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Internet-based biosurveillance methods for vector-borne diseases: are they novel public health tools or just novelties?</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2017</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e0005871</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29190281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hovet</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fung</surname><given-names>ICH</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>K-W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tse</surname><given-names>ZTH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using twitter for public health surveillance from monitoring and prediction to public response</article-title><source>Data</source><year>2018</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>6</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Priedhorsky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Osthus</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Daughton</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Generous</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fairchild</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Measuring global disease with Wikipedia: success, failure, and a research agenda</article-title><source>Proc 2017 ACM Conf Comput Support Coop Work Soc Comput</source><year>2017</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>1812</fpage><lpage>1834</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milinovich</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Clements</surname><given-names>ACA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Internet-based surveillance systems for monitoring emerging infectious diseases</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24290841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eysenbach</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infodemiology and infoveillance: framework for an emerging set of public health informatics methods to analyze search, communication and publication behavior on the internet</article-title><source>J Med Internet Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e11</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19329408</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ginsberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohebbi</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Brammer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Smolinski</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Brilliant</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detecting influenza epidemics using search engine query data</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2009</year><volume>457</volume><fpage>1012</fpage><lpage>1014</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19020500</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polgreen</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennock</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using internet searches for influenza surveillance</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2008</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1443</fpage><lpage>1448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18954267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahai</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Conrad</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brownstein</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using web search query data to monitor dengue epidemics: a new model for neglected tropical disease surveillance</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e1206</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21647308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Althouse</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>DAT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prediction of dengue incidence using search query surveillance</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e1258</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21829744</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lazer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Vespignani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The parable of Google Flu: traps in big data analysis</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2014</year><volume>343</volume><fpage>1203</fpage><lpage>1205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24626916</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Conrad</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fowlkes</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohebbi</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing Google flu trends performance in the United States during the 2009 influenza virus a (H1N1) pandemic</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e23610</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21886802</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shay</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuzil</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fowlkes</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Goss</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monitoring influenza activity in the United States: a comparison of traditional surveillance systems with Google flu trends</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e18687</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21556151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pollett</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Boscardin</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Azziz-Baumgartner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tinoco</surname><given-names>YO</given-names></name><name><surname>Soto</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluating Google flu trends in Latin America: important lessons for the next phase of digital disease detection</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27678084</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Google AI Blog. The next chapter for Flu Trends. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ai.googleblog.com/2015/08/the-next-chapter-for-flu-trends.html">https://ai.googleblog.com/2015/08/the-next-chapter-for-flu-trends.html</ext-link>. Accessed 28 October 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapit&#x000e1;ny-F&#x000f6;v&#x000e9;ny</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferenci</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sulyok</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kegele</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>V&#x000e1;lyi-Nagy</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Can Google trends data improve forecasting of Lyme disease incidence?</article-title><source>Zoonoses Public Health</source><year>2019</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30447056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mckee</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuckler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Google trends: opportunities and limitations in health and health policy research</article-title><source>Health Policy</source><year>2019</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>338</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30660346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dynamic forecasting of Zika epidemics using Google trends</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e0165085</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28060809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cervellin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Comelli</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lippi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is Google trends a reliable tool for digital epidemiology? Insights from different clinical settings</article-title><source>J Epidemiol Glob Health</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28756828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohart</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Milinovich</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Avril</surname><given-names>SMR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disease surveillance based on internet-based linear models: an Australian case study of previously unmodeled infection diseases</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>38522</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27994231</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvajal</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bautista</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Capistrano</surname><given-names>JDR</given-names></name><name><surname>Viacrusis</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>LFT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Using Google trends to examine the spatio-temporal incidence and behavioral patterns of dengue disease: a case study in metropolitan Manila, Philippines</article-title><source>Trop Med Infect Dis</source><year>2018</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>118</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osthus</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Daughton</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Priedhorsky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Even a good influenza forecasting model can benefit from internet-based nowcasts, but those benefits are limited</article-title><source>PLoS Comput Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>e1006599</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30707689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marques-Toledo</surname><given-names>CDA</given-names></name><name><surname>Degener</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinhal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Coelho</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Meira</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Code&#x000e7;o</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dengue prediction by the web: tweets are a useful tool for estimating and forecasting dengue at country and city level</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2017</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e0005729</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28719659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kou</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Brownstein</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooke</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Santillana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Advances in using internet searches to track dengue</article-title><source>PLoS Comput Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>e1005607</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28727821</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gluskin</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Santillana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brownstein</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of internet-based dengue query data: Google dengue trends</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e2713</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24587465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Minist&#x000e9;rio da Sa&#x000fa;de, Brasil. Informes Arboviroses. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://saude.gov.br/informes-de-arboviroses">http://saude.gov.br/informes-de-arboviroses</ext-link>. Accessed 28 Oct 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estat&#x000ed;stica. Censo Demogr&#x000e1;fico 2010. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ww2.ibge.gov.br/home/estatistica/populacao/censo2010/default.shtm">https://ww2.ibge.gov.br/home/estatistica/populacao/censo2010/default.shtm</ext-link>. Accessed 28 October 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vandenbroucke</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incidence rates in dynamic populations</article-title><source>Int J Epidemiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>1472</fpage><lpage>1479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23045207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stocking G, Matsa KE. Using Google trends data for research? Here are 6 questions to ask. Pew Research Center. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://medium.com/@pewresearch/using-google-trends-data-for-research-here-are-6-questions-to-ask-a7097f5fb526">https://medium.com/@pewresearch/using-google-trends-data-for-research-here-are-6-questions-to-ask-a7097f5fb526</ext-link>. Accessed 28 Oct 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishijima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanauskas</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarti</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution and determinants of digital divide in Brazil (2005&#x02013;2013)</article-title><source>Telecommun Policy</source><year>2017</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>24</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Araujo</surname><given-names>MHD</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinhard</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Categorization of Brazilian internet users and its impacts on the use of electronic government sevices</article-title><source>JISTEM</source><year>2016</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>254</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pesquisa Nacional Por Amostra de Domicilios 2015. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ilo.org/surveydata/index.php/catalog/1548">https://www.ilo.org/surveydata/index.php/catalog/1548</ext-link>. Accessed 26 June 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estat&#x000ed;stica. Acesso &#x000e0; Internet e a televis&#x000e3;o e posse de telefone m&#x000f3;vel celular para uso pessoal. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://sidra.ibge.gov.br/pesquisa/pnad/suplementos/acesso-a-internet-e-a-televisao-e-posse-de-telefone-movel-celular-para-uso-pessoal">https://sidra.ibge.gov.br/pesquisa/pnad/suplementos/acesso-a-internet-e-a-televisao-e-posse-de-telefone-movel-celular-para-uso-pessoal</ext-link>. Accessed 28 Oct 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>R Core Team</collab></person-group><source>The R Project for Statistical Computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing</source><year>2018</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Husnayain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazuardi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Husnayain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlation between Google trends on dengue fever and national surveillance report in Indonesia</article-title><source>Glob Health Action</source><year>2019</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1552652</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31154985</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nuti</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Wayda</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranasinghe</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dreyer</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The use of Google trends in health care research: a systematic review</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e109583</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25337815</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caldana</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>MTD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regional development and engineering education: an analysis of Brazil&#x02019;s micro-regional scenario</article-title><source>Prod</source><year>2017</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>e20162250</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">The World Bank. Individuals using the Internet (% of population) | Data. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/IT.NET.USER.ZS?end=2017&#x00026;start=1960&#x00026;view=chart">https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/IT.NET.USER.ZS?end=2017&#x00026;start=1960&#x00026;view=chart</ext-link>. Accessed 28 Oct 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paix&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zika, chikungunya and dengue: the causes and threats of new and re-emerging arboviral diseases</article-title><source>BMJ Glob Health</source><year>2018</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>e000530</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Arden</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mayaro virus: a forest virus primed for a trip to the city?</article-title><source>Microbes Infect</source><year>2016</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>724</fpage><lpage>734</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27989728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>EVPD</given-names></name><name><surname>Casseb</surname><given-names>LMN</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>SPD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>ACR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pantoja</surname><given-names>JADS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>First isolation of West Nile virus in Brazil</article-title><source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source><year>2019</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>e180332</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30672980</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romero-Alvarez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Escobar</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oropouche fever, an emergent disease from the Americas</article-title><source>Microbes Infect</source><year>2017</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29247710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Southwell</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jimenez-Magdaleno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Squiers</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zika virus-related news coverage and online behaviour, United States, Guatemala, and Brazil</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1320</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27100826</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wichmann</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Vong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Limkittikul</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbons</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Mammen</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dengue in Thailand and Cambodia: an assessment of the degree of underrecognized disease burden based on reported cases</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e996</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21468308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGough</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Brownstein</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Santillana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Forecasting Zika incidence in the 2016 Latin America outbreak combining traditional disease surveillance with search, social media, and news report data</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2017</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e0005295</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28085877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fairchild</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasseff</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalsa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Generous</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Daughton</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Velappan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epidemiological data challenges: planning for a more robust future through data standards</article-title><source>Front Public Health</source><year>2018</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>336</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30533407</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Panhuis</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Emerson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Grefenstette</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilder</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Herbst</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A systematic review of barriers to data sharing in public health</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1144</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25377061</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>