<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Post-infectious CNS symptoms:</italic> Human acute WNV infection induces a significant upregulation of various proinflammatory proteins and cytokines that may initiate and maintain inflammation. Although induction of neuroinflammation is necessary for defense against many viral infections, including other flaviviruses, it is also recognized as a potential contributor to neuropathogenesis [
 <xref rid="B159-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>,
 <xref rid="B160-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>,
 <xref rid="B161-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>]. Moreover, levels of some cytokines including IL-2, IL-6, IL-12, granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF), IFN-γ, IFN-γ induced protein 10 (IP-10), IL-17A and OPN [
 <xref rid="B30-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B78-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>], have been reported to be elevated for months to years following the recovery of acute illness, leading to a post-infectious proinflammatory state that may contribute to long-term neuroinflammation in WNV survivors [
 <xref rid="B30-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B78-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. Among a large cohort of participants with a history of WNV infection in Houston, TX, USA, approximately 40% of those who presented with clinical disease continued to experience WNV-related morbidity up to eight years post-infection [
 <xref rid="B162-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>]. Another observational study on the Houston cohort showed that the majority of patients (86%, 30/35) with encephalitis had abnormal neurological exam findings compared with uncomplicated fever (27%, 3/11) and meningitis (36%, 5/14) cases during 1–3 years following WNV infection. At the second assessment between 8–11 years post-infection, 57% (4/7) of West Nile fever, 33% (2/6) of West Nile meningitis, and 36% (5/14) of West Nile encephalitis had developed new neurological complications [
 <xref rid="B163-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">163</xref>]. Importantly, MRI (magnetic resonance imaging) evaluation of the Houston cohort demonstrated that participants with abnormal neurologic and neurocognitive exam findings showed significant cortical thinning as compared to age- and gender-matched controls, with affected regions primarily occurring in the frontal and limbic cortices. Regional atrophy occurred in the cerebellum, brain stem, thalamus, putamen, and globus pallidus [
 <xref rid="B164-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>]. These MRI findings provide valuable evidence regarding the neurologic outcomes following WNV CNS infection. Post-infectious CNS symptoms included post-exertion fatigue, dizziness, altered sensation, arthralgias, dysautonomia impaired memory, difficulty concentrating, depression, anxiety, sleep disruption, and recurrent headaches [
 <xref rid="B30-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Moreover, numerous WNV patients have developed autoinflammatory or autoimmune-related diseases, including myasthenia gravis (MG) [
 <xref rid="B165-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>,
 <xref rid="B166-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">166</xref>], suggesting that WNV infection may promote or amplify underlying autoimmunity. Interestingly, RAGE and S100B signaling has been reported to promote the development of experimental autoimmune MG [
 <xref rid="B167-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>] and to play a role in the pathophysiology of human MG [
 <xref rid="B168-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">168</xref>]. In addition, IL-17A is upregulated in human cases of MG, where it plays a vital role in the pathogenesis of MG with higher levels correlating with greater disease severity and thymic hyperplasia [
 <xref rid="B169-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">169</xref>]. IL-17-producing CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells also contribute to a loss of B-cell tolerance in experimental autoimmune MG [
 <xref rid="B170-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">170</xref>]. These results indicate that over-expression of IL-17 following WNV infection could contribute to the development of MG, although it can be beneficial in clearing WNV by promoting CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cell cytotoxicity [
 <xref rid="B118-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. Furthermore, WNV infection has also been suggested to induce other autoimmune diseases, including GBS and other immune-mediated neuropathies [
 <xref rid="B31-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B171-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">171</xref>], brachial plexopathies [
 <xref rid="B172-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">172</xref>], stiff-person syndrome [
 <xref rid="B173-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">173</xref>], and autoimmune encephalitis [
 <xref rid="B174-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">174</xref>]. However, more clinical data and experimental evidence are still needed to establish the cause-effective relationship of WNV infection with autoimmune diseases.
</p>
