<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The presence of infectious MAYV particles in the body, legs, and saliva samples was tested by FFU assay in Vero cells. Vero cells were grown to a confluent monolayer in 96-well plates at 37°C with 5% CO
 <sub>2</sub> in complete media (Dulbecco’s modified-essential media [DMEM], 100 units/mL penicillin/streptomycin, and 10% FBS). The next day, wells were washed with DMEM without FBS and incubated with a 30-μL of 10-fold serial dilutions (10
 <sup>−1</sup> to 10
 <sup>−4</sup>) of each homogenized tissue sample for 2 h at 37°C. Saliva samples were not diluted. After the incubation step, the 30-μL aliquot was removed from the cell monolayer and any unattached viral particles removed with a DMEM wash. A total of 100 μL of overlay medium (1% methyl cellulose in complete growth medium) was dispensed into each well, and plates incubated at 37°C with 5% CO
 <sub>2</sub>. Cells were fixed at 24 h (bodies and legs samples) or 48 h (saliva samples) post-infection with 4% paraformaldehyde (Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA). Fixed cells were blocked and permeabilized for 30 min with blocking solution containing detergent (3% bovine serum albumin and 0.05% Tween 20 in PBS) and washed with cold PBS. Viral antigens in infected cells were labeled using the monoclonal anti-chikungunya virus E2 envelope glycoprotein clone CHK-48 (which reacts with Alphaviruses) (BEI Resources, Manassas, VA, USA) diluted 1:500 in blocking solution. Subsequently, cells were washed 4 times with cold PBS to remove unbound primary antibodies. The primary antibody was labeled with the Alexa-488 goat anti-mouse IgG secondary antibody (Invitrogen, Life Science, Eugene OR, USA) at a dilution of 1:500, and green fluorescenct foci observed and enumerated with an Olympus BX41 microscope equipped with an UPlanFI 4× objective and a FITC filter. Fluorescent foci were counted by eye (the dilution with less than 100 foci was selected for each sample) and virus titers calculated and expressed as FFU/mL.
</p>
