<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the past, three major approaches were pursued to improve the speed of baculovirus killing action by genetic engineering technology: (1) introduction of a gene encoding an insect-specific toxin, hormone, or enzyme into the baculovirus genome; (2) deletion of baculovirus genes that affect infection; and (3) incorporation of a toxin, like Bt toxin, into the polyhedrin matrix [
 <xref rid="B2-ijms-20-00419" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-ijms-20-00419" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-ijms-20-00419" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. In this paper, we provide a new strategy: disturbing insect hormones by baculovirus-mediated RNAi. This strategy can be combined with previous improvements. For example, the baculovirus used in this study has already had the ecdysteroid UDP-glucosyltransferase (EGT) gene deleted, which may result in a reduction in food consumption and time to kill the host compared with wild-type HearNPV [
 <xref rid="B41-ijms-20-00419" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-ijms-20-00419" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Laboratory analysis in this work has demonstrated that the recombinant HearNPV expressing dsJHBP could further shorten the killing time of 
 <italic>H. armigera</italic> larvae with fewer occlusion bodies comparison to vHaBacΔegt. These characteristics make it possible for vHaBacΔegtdsJHBP to be further developed into a new bioinsecticide. However, we need to consider the production of baculoviruses for industrial application. The number of OB produced by each larva may be reduced, since larvae will die earlier after infection with vHaBacΔegtdsJHBP. Perhaps it would be more advantageous for industrialization to replace vHaBacΔegt with wildtype baculoviruses, which harbor the 
 <italic>egt</italic> that prevents molting and prolongs the larval stage of infected insects, and allows for production of more progeny virus. Besides, as the recombinant baculovirus have stronger insecticidal activity, its application amount will also decrease.
</p>
