<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Anti-viral treatment with interferon-alpha inhalation (50 μg two times daily), lopinavir and ritonavir (anti-retroviral drugs) (400 mg twice each day and 100 mg twice every day, respectively), and arbidol (200 mg two times every day) is recommended. Patients obtained treatment with a corticosteroid (40-80 mg/day) and gamma globulin (15-20 g/day) for three to five days while their resting respiratory rate became greater than 30 per minute, or oxygen saturation was under 93% without oxygen, or multiple pulmonary lobes showed more than 50% progression of sickness in 48 hours on imaging. Patients additionally may be treated with probiotics to relieve gastrointestinal illness. Quinolones and higher generation cephalosporins (oral and intravenous) can be administered if fever lasted for more than seven days or C-reactive protein levels were 30 mg/L or more (normal range: 0-8 mg/L). After the course of treatment, the patients infected with SARS-CoV-2 can be discharged from the hospital only after two negative results of the samples collected with 24-hour interval using an RT-PCR [
 <xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Other drugs like chloroquine (anti-malaria drug), hydroxychloroquine (used to treat rheumatoid arthritis, Lupus), azithromycin (anti-bacterial drug), and favipiravir are all either drugs recommended for other causes (repurposed) or drugs that are under clinical trials to treat serious infections caused by SARS-CoV-2. Protease inhibitors (lopinavir/ritonavir) in combination with ribavirin may be used for anti-viral therapy in the early phase, and nelfinavir was found to be a promising alternative. The role of interferon and systemic corticosteroid therapy in preventing immune-mediated lung injury requires further investigation. Besides, other anti-viral treatments, RNA interference, monoclonal antibody, synthetic peptides, and vaccines are being developed [
 <xref rid="REF42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Corticosteroids can be used to limit excessive lung damage due to an inflammatory response, and a high flow of oxygen supplementation and mechanical ventilation can be used in cases of respiratory failure [
 <xref rid="REF41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Tracheostomy may be performed in patients who require prolonged mechanical ventilation and longer intensive care unit (ICU) stay. Strict adherence to infection control guidelines is mandatory while performing tracheostomy in the ICU or operating rooms, as well as during subsequent changes of the tracheostomy tube. Care should be taken during the treatment procedures to reduce complications and the chances of transmission [
 <xref rid="REF30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The use of high-dose pulse methylprednisolone during the clinical course of a SARS outbreak was associated with clinical improvement, but randomized controlled trials are needed to ascertain its efficacy [
 <xref rid="REF49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>].
</p>
