<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<boxed-text id="pntd.0005135.box001" position="float" orientation="portrait">
 <sec id="sec015">
  <title>Key learning points</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>Deforestation is associated with elevated ZIKV risk. Less forest cover correlates with higher rates of confirmed ZIKV-linked microcephaly cases in Brazil.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>ZIKV transmission may be linked to poverty. Lower per capita GDP correlates strongly with higher rates of confirmed ZIKV-linked microcephaly cases in Brazil.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Inadequate or damaged infrastructure may increase the abundance of mosquito breeding sites and thereby promote ZIKV transmission. Following a major earthquake in Manabi, Ecuador, the incidence of ZIKV cases in the province increased dramatically.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>In Brazil, capuchin monkeys and common marmosets may be important reservoirs for ZIKV. Both primates are physically and phylogenetically close to humans and have high rates of seroconversion for ZIKV.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>As a model for ZIKV, the rubella outbreak in the United States suggests that (potentially illicit) abortion rates may increase in the Americas as a result of the ZIKV epidemic.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec016">
  <title>Top four papers</title>
  <list list-type="order">
   <list-item>
    <p>Hales DS, de Wet N, Maindonald J, Woodward A. Potential effect of population and climate change on global distribution of dengue fever: an empirical model. The Lancet [Internet]. 2002 Sep 14;360(9336).</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Hotez PJ. Neglected Tropical Diseases in the Anthropocene: The Cases of Zika, Ebola, and Other Infections. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2016 Apr 8;10(4):e0004648.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Stewart Ibarra AM, Ryan SJ, Beltrán E, Mejía R, Silva M, Muñoz Á. Dengue Vector Dynamics (Aedes aegypti) Influenced by Climate and Social Factors in Ecuador: Implications for Targeted Control. 2013 Nov;8(11).</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Musso D, Cao-Lormeau VM, Gubler DJ. Zika virus: following the path of dengue and chikungunya? The Lancet. 2015 Jul;386(9990):243–4.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
</boxed-text>
