<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0380">
 <list list-type="simple" id="lis0045">
  <list-item id="lsti0110">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="par0385">The entry of picornaviruses into cells requires the disruption of interactions among the four capsid proteins, so as to release the viral genome into the cytoplasm. A number of compounds have been identified that insert into “pockets” in the virion surface, stabilizing the capsid and preventing its disassembly (
    <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">De Palma et al., 2008</xref>). Such compounds have protected mice against lethal poliovirus infection, and pleconaril, which acts by this mechanism, has been extensively tested for antirhinovirus activity in humans (
    <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">De Palma et al., 2008</xref>, 
    <xref rid="bib0395" ref-type="bibr">McKinlay and Steinberg, 1986</xref>). The highly specific interaction of such compounds with the viral capsid suggests that they could be used to image sites of picornaviral infection.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0115">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="par0390">The 3C protease of human rhinovirus is inhibited by a number of compounds, including the small-molecule rupintrivir, which binds irreversibly to the enzyme's active site (
    <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">De Palma et al., 2008</xref>). Because the viral enzyme has no known human homologue, it should be a good target for virus-specific imaging.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0120">
   <label>•</label>
   <p id="par0395">The benzimidazole analogue enviroxime inhibits the replication of rhinoviruses and enteroviruses by blocking viral RNA replication, apparently by directly inhibiting the action of the 3A protein. The compound protected mice against lethal Coxsackie myocarditis and has shown activity in protecting humans against rhinoviruses (
    <xref rid="bib0495" ref-type="bibr">Victor et al., 1997</xref>, 
    <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">De Palma et al., 2008</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
