<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28">Psychological intervention is very necessary for patients, health care workers and the general public. We should pay attention to the high-risk groups prone to disease, and at the same time eliminate the stimulation factors that induce PTSD and depression as much as possible, and timely and early intervention is beneficial to reduce the incidence of PTSD [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. We should not be overly pessimistic the prognosis of patients with COVID-19, although part of the source of mental illness is poor prognosis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. For some drugs that cause long-term adverse physical conditions, such as hormones [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], they are abandoned or restricted in the treatment guidelines of COVID-19, and according to all materials known on PubMed, the newly add drugs have no clear long-term impact. According to statistics, effective antidepressants such as chronic antidepressants can greatly reduce the degree of depression and anxiety symptoms [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>], its chronic effect is related to the repair and possible construction of injured neural network; moreover, it can promote the growth of axons and dendrites [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], and may also play a role in the organ injury caused by chronic inflammation. However, we are concerned about the psychological status of medical workers in some countries, because some studies have shown that during the outbreak, medical workers experienced anxiety, depression and poor sleep. Such situation began to improve 2 weeks after the adoption of SARS prevention and control measures, and systematic SARS prevention plan improved the mental state of medical workers [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. At the same time, the country’s active and timely resource scheduling and integration is particularly important, and ecouraging the health care workers and improving the long-term potential for adverse mental health conditions is an important part of the country’s response to the epidemic [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].
</p>
