<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.39023.015</object-id>
 <label>Figure 5.</label>
 <caption>
  <title>ZIKV sfRNA antagonizes FMRP’s antiviral function.</title>
  <p>(
   <bold>A</bold>) HeLa cells were infected at MOI of 3 with WT ZIKV or ∆10 ZIKV. 24 hr post-infection, cell-associated RNA was harvested and levels of gRNA and sfRNA were analyzed by NB. (
   <bold>B</bold>) sfRNA/gRNA ratios for WT and ∆10 ZIKV were calculated by densitometry analysis of two independent experiments. (
   <bold>C–G</bold>) HeLa cells were transfected with control siRNA (siControl) and pooled FMR1 siRNAs for 48 hr. Cells were then infected with WT and ∆10 ZIKV at MOI of 0.2 and 24 hr later collected and analyzed for infection rate by flow cytometry (
   <bold>C and D</bold>). Representative scatter plots are shown in 
   <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5s1">Figure 5—figure supplement 1</xref>. In parallel, viral NS4B and NS2B proteins were analyzed by WB along with FMRP and Actin loading control (
   <bold>E</bold>). The quantitative expression levels of NS2B (
   <bold>F</bold>) and NS4B (
   <bold>G</bold>) are shown. Data represents the mean ±SEM of one representative experiment for C, four independent experiments for D and two independent experiments for F and G. (*p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.005, ***p&lt;0.001. a = 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01 compared to siControl cells infected with WT ZIKV). .
  </p>
  <p>
   <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="fig5sdata1">
    <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.39023.017</object-id>
    <label>Figure 5—source data 1.</label>
    <media mime-subtype="xlsx" mimetype="application" xlink:href="elife-39023-fig5-data1.xlsx" orientation="portrait" id="d35e1211" position="anchor" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </supplementary-material>
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="elife-39023-fig5" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 <p content-type="supplemental-figure">
  <fig id="fig5s1" specific-use="child-fig" orientation="portrait" position="anchor">
   <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.39023.016</object-id>
   <label>Figure 5—figure supplement 1.</label>
   <caption>
    <title>Scatter plots of WT and ∆10 ZIKV infected cells.</title>
    <p>Representative scatter plots obtained by flow cytometry and used to construct 
     <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5C</xref>, indicate the infection rate in cells transfected with control siRNA (siControl) or FMR1 siRNA (siFMR1) and infected with WT and ∆10 ZIKV. ZIKV +cells are identified by positive staining for ZIKV E protein (Alexa fluor 647 fluorescence). NI, non-infected cells.
    </p>
   </caption>
   <graphic xlink:href="elife-39023-fig5-figsupp1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </fig>
 </p>
</fig>
