<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0010">The typical profile of a patient attending a hepatology clinic has substantially changed in the last few years. As the number of HCV-infected patients decline, there has been a surge in the number of individuals diagnosed with non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD); it is now the leading cause of chronic liver disease worldwide, affecting approximately 25% of the global population,
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> and it will soon become the primary indication for liver transplantation, as an increasing number of younger individuals are affected by the so-called “adipose wave effect”.
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>2</sup>
 </xref> The development of NAFLD is closely linked with underlying insulin resistance, with a rise in NAFLD that parallels that of type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) and obesity. From a global health perspective, the increasing prevalence of these diseases
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> in the setting of unhealthy lifestyles, particularly unhealthy diet
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref> and sedentarism
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref> constitutes an evolving public health crisis, with increased healthcare-associated costs and resource utilization.
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref> As stated in the conclusion of a recent modelling study,
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref> “NAFLD represents a large and growing public health problem and efforts to understand this epidemic and to mitigate the disease burden are needed. Public health campaigns to increase awareness and diagnosis, and to promote diet and exercise can help manage the growth in future disease burden”. In this issue, Hallsworth 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref> examine the evidence behind dietary changes, weight loss, physical activity and exercise in improving hepatic steatosis and liver histology in patients with NAFLD. A comprehensive review with well-designed figures highlights the complex and multi-faceted driving forces behind unhealthy lifestyle habits that can, however, be successfully combated to induce significant health benefits. Indeed, when successful, lifestyle changes leading to weight loss have been shown to be highly effective in reducing fibrosis and the necro-inflammatory changes of non-alcoholic steatohepatitis (NASH). Unfortunately, only 10–20% of individuals are able to lose ≥10% of their body weight over a 1- to 2-year period, which is the threshold associated with the greatest benefit. Furthermore, sustained lifestyle changes and weight loss are difficult to maintain. The authors identify potential barriers to adopting lifestyle changes and strategies to overcome these. The impact of different diets, the role of gut microbiome manipulation, the reality behind the Mediterranean diet, the role of alcohol, coffee, tea or micronutrients and the effects of physical activity and exercise, including aerobic and resistance training, are thoroughly dissected. This review underscores the need to tailor optimal lifestyle programme recommendations to the individual patient based on clinical characteristics, comorbidities, current fitness and patient preference and the importance of incorporating behaviour change techniques to encourage patients to take a level of responsibility for their own health.
</p>
