<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another class of regulatory cells that modulates the immune response by producing anti-inflammatory cytokines such as interleukin-10 (IL-10), IL-35, and transforming growth factor β (TGF-β) is a subset of B cells called regulatory B cells (Bregs) (
 <xref rid="B166" ref-type="bibr">166</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B167" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>). Bregs cells inhibit the expansion of pro-inflammatory lymphocytes and other pathogenic T cells (
 <xref rid="B166" ref-type="bibr">166</xref>) by exerting the inhibitory effect on production of pro-inflammatory molecules, such as TNF-α, IFN-γ, and IL-17 from CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells (
 <xref rid="B167" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>). However, Bregs also regulate the immune response by modulating the induction of cell death and IgM production, as reported both in humans and mice models (
 <xref rid="B168" ref-type="bibr">168</xref>–
 <xref rid="B171" ref-type="bibr">171</xref>). CD9
 <sup>+</sup> Bregs stimulate differentiation of CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells into Tregs by producing high levels of TGF-β (
 <xref rid="B171" ref-type="bibr">171</xref>) which further alleviates the production of TNF-α and induces apoptosis in pro-inflammatory CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells. Production of IgM persuades elimination of apoptotic bodies, leading to reduction of pro-inflammatory mediators (
 <xref rid="B172" ref-type="bibr">172</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B173" ref-type="bibr">173</xref>). Bregs have been studied for their role in rheumatoid arthritis (RA) and its regulation seems to be one of the key players that enhance RA disease (
 <xref rid="B174" ref-type="bibr">174</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B175" ref-type="bibr">175</xref>). Considering that chikungunya-induced arthritis is an inflammatory response triggered by the virus that persists in joint tissues resulting in chronic rheumatoid disease (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), it is possible that Bregs might be involved in the regulation of chikungunya-induced RA via modulating inflammatory responses.
</p>
