<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mutations in the viral genome impact at viral propagation and adaptation of these lineages in different vectors. 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> mosquitoes are the main vectors in the urban cycle of CHIKV transmission. Studies showed that genomic differences amongst circulating CHIKV accounted for its transmission from each of these vectors. For instance, the presence of the A226V variant on the envelope (E1) gene of CHIKV was related to an increase in viral infectivity, dissemination, and transmission in 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>, resulting in the wide spread of the virus (
 <xref rid="B172" ref-type="bibr">Tsetsarkin et al., 2007</xref>). This mutation did not confer any advantage to transmission in 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>. Followed by the selection of A226V, adaptation substitutions L210Q and K252Q (E2 protein) that arose independently in the IOL strain in India are associated with a greater increase of CHIKV dissemination in 
 <italic>Ae. albobictus</italic> vector (
 <xref rid="B173" ref-type="bibr">Tsetsarkin and Weaver, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B170" ref-type="bibr">Tsetsarkin et al., 2014</xref>). Still, variants K211E, in the E1 gene, and V264A, in the envelope (E2) gene, lead to an increase in viral dissemination and transmission for 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> but not for 
 <italic>Ae. Albopictus</italic> (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Agarwal et al., 2016</xref>). Moreover, the T98A variant in E1 enhances the vector-adaptability effect of A226V, since epistatic interactions between E1-98T and E1-A226V are restrictive (
 <xref rid="B169" ref-type="bibr">Tsetsarkin et al., 2011</xref>). In another study, variant G60D in the E2 increased CHIKV infectivity in 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> in the presence of either alanine or valine at position 226 in E1 protein. This change also increases infectivity in 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti.</italic> The E2 variant, I211T, increases the CHIKV infectivity exclusively for 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> but only when associated with A226V change. I211T variant could be related to the maintenance of CHIKV in the enzootic Africa cycle since it was detected in most sequences from the ECSA clade obtained before 2005 (
 <xref rid="B171" ref-type="bibr">Tsetsarkin et al., 2009</xref>). Mutations occurring at the 3′-UTR could also contribute to vector adaptability, since a 177 nt duplication found in the Caribbean strain of CHIKV and confirmed in sequences from Mexico, Trinidad, and the Dominican Republic, conferred a growth advantage in insect cell cultures to viruses harboring this duplication over the Asian strain and other Caribbean strains lacking the duplication (
 <xref rid="B155" ref-type="bibr">Stapleford et al., 2016</xref>). The most relevant variants, as well as their impact on each vector and in virus infectivity, are summarized in 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.
</p>
