<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The dual signal amplification system with the hybridization chain reaction and enzyme-induced metallization with anodic stripping voltammetry measures miRNA in the femtomole range.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref>
 </sup> The polydiacetylene microtube waveguide with catalytic hairpin assembly as a signal amplification strategy shows femtomolar sensitivity for RNA detection.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref40">40</xref>
 </sup> The amperometric genosensor based on peptide nucleic acid (PNA) probes immobilized on carbon nanotube-screen printed electrodes determines trace levels of viral RNA.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">41</xref>
 </sup> The plasmonic nanoparticle-based optical biosensor array functionalized with capture DNA binds to complementary viral RNA, which can be reversed by chemical treatment (10 mM HCl).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">35</xref>
 </sup> FET with a two-dimensional channel made of a single graphene layer achieves label-free detection of RNA down to attomolar concentration.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42">42</xref>
 </sup> Single-molecule fluorescence resonance energy transfer remains a promising tool for multiplex viral RNA detection (∼200 pM) with interconvertible hairpin-based sensors.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">43</xref>
 </sup> Nanoporous anodic alumina supports oligonucleotides as gated ensembles to detect the presence of viral RNA.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref>
 </sup> The 3D nanostructure has a high surface-to-volume ratio and well-controlled shape factors for virus and nucleic acid capture.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref45">45</xref>
 </sup> Previously, a bead-stacked nanodevice has been developed for pathogen trapping
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46">46</xref>
 </sup> and micropillar polydimethylsiloxane, for rapid viral DNA sensing.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref47">47</xref>
 </sup> Protein nanopore detects viral RNA at the single-molecule level using specific DNA probes.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref48">48</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
