<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The genus 
 <italic>Ebolavirus</italic> comprises six species, of which four contain known human pathogens, namely Ebola (species 
 <italic>Zaire ebolavirus</italic>), Sudan (species 
 <italic>Sudan ebolavirus</italic>), Bundibugyo (species 
 <italic>Bundibugyo</italic>
 <italic>ebolavirus</italic>) and Taï Forest (species 
 <italic>Taï Forest</italic>
 <italic>ebolavirus</italic>) virus (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2A</xref>). All ebolaviruses share a non-segmented, linear negative-sense RNA genome of ca 18.9 kb. The genome comprises seven genes that are flanked by untranslated regions (UTR). To date, 70% of ebolavirus outbreaks have been caused by members of the species 
 <italic>Zaire ebolavirus, </italic>however, in each outbreak, new variants arose (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2B</xref>). EBOV-specific protocols are available and feasible given that the overall genomic identity is around 98% (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2C</xref>). Published PCR-based assays capable of amplifying members of different EBOV variants comprise 30–60 primer pairs, such as the protocol from Quick et al. [
 <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] or the Artic V3 protocol available only online (https://artic.network/ebov/), both designed for MinION-based downstream sequencing. Another protocol from Arias et al. [
 <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] contains up to 140 primer pairs amplifying small genomic fragments with downstream Ion Torrent-based sequencing. These protocols use single-round conventional PCR in a highly multiplexed approach to reduce the number of reactions [
 <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Beyond EBOV protocols, the development of a genus-wide protocol is challenging given that the average sequence identity across the genome of all known variants comprised in the different species forming the 
 <italic>Ebolavirus</italic> genus is only around 62% (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2C</xref>) [
 <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].
</p>
