<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Interestingly, DENV-2 samples belonged to two different genotypes. Ten samples belonged to the Asian I genotype, which has been commonly reported in several countries in Asia such as in Myanmar [
 <xref rid="pone.0221179.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], Vietnam [
 <xref rid="pone.0221179.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], Thailand [
 <xref rid="pone.0221179.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0221179.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], Laos PDR [
 <xref rid="pone.0221179.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] and Taiwan [
 <xref rid="pone.0221179.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. These 10 strains do not show a wide genetic diversity and cluster into a monophyletic lineage with DENV-2 strains isolated during a large outbreak in China in 2014 and 2015 (Province of Yunnan) and Myanmar 2015 [
 <xref rid="pone.0221179.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0221179.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Furthermore, 10 other DENV-2 strains were classified as Cosmopolitan genotype and formed a specific clade into a single lineage with strains from Malaysia, Singapore, Sri Lanka as well as strains recently isolated from the Central and Northern region of Thailand. These strains were also related to viruses isolated from 2009 to 2016 in the insular region of Southeast Asia and Australia, where the Cosmopolitan genotype was the predominant genotype (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221179.g003">Fig 3</xref>). As reported by Twiddy 
 <italic>et al</italic>, the Cosmopolitan genotype is spreading worldwide, including throughout Southeast Asia [
 <xref rid="pone.0221179.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Our analysis suggested that this genotype has also spread to Thailand, corroborating recent findings in the Central and Northern region of Thailand [
 <xref rid="pone.0221179.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The Cosmopolitan genotype strains of our study are genetically close to strains from the Central and Northern regions of Thailand collected in 2016 [
 <xref rid="pone.0221179.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Thus, our findings may suggest a route of introduction of DENV-2 into Thailand from the Malaysian peninsula or from other southern countries of Thailand, considering that our samples were collected in 2015 and 2016. Furthermore, these strains were genetically-related to the DENV-2 strains associated with outbreaks in Singapore and Malaysia in 2013 and 2014 [
 <xref rid="pone.0221179.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0221179.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0221179.g003">Fig 3</xref>). Further investigation is needed to assess whether several routes of introduction could be possible from countries to the north or south of Thailand. Both the genotype Asia I and Cosmopolitan genotype were reported to be regionally endemic [
 <xref rid="pone.0221179.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0221179.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], suggesting that there is a frequent crossover between countries in Southeast Asia–highlighting the importance of continuously monitoring DENV in Southern Thailand. While the Asian/American genotype was displaced by the Asian-I genotype in Vietnam and Cambodia [
 <xref rid="pone.0221179.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], our results suggest a shift towards the Cosmopolitan genotype in Thailand. However, to date, reports of the presence of the Cosmopolitan genotype are seldom [
 <xref rid="pone.0221179.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0221179.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], highlighting the importance of permanent surveillance in Thailand.
</p>
