<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Methods to perform sample processing and RNA extraction varied according to resources available on site. In research or diagnostic laboratories, samples were handled in containment level (CL) 2+ or CL3 conditions until sample inactivation. At field sites, samples were handled in a portable glove box (UY-33666-50, Cole Parmer). RNA extraction was performed using the Zymo Quick RNA Miniprep kit (R1054, Zymo Research) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. Sample preparation varied according to the state of the sample (fresh/frozen, homogenised/non-homogenised) and its preservation (RNAlater [Invitrogen], DNA/RNA Shield [Zymo Research], 50% glycerol-saline solution). Recommended methods for different sample types can be found in the manufacturer’s instructions but generally the following protocol was used. A small amount of brain tissue (50–100mg) was transferred from the original sample tube, using a wooden applicator stick or toothpick, to a 2ml reinforced homogeniser tube containing 1.4mm ceramic beads (Qiagen) and ~1ml of Zymo kit RNA lysis buffer. The sample was homogenised using a Terralyzer (Zymo Research) with 30 second pulses until fully homogenised and left to inactivate for 2 minutes. When a Terralyzer was unavailable, samples were manually homogenised using a toothpick. Lysed samples were processed according to manufacturer’s column-based RNA purification protocol with in-column DNase I treatment to remove genomic DNA. In brief, lysed samples were added to filter columns and subject to a series of centrifugation steps to selectively bind RNA and purify (ethanol washes) and finally eluted. Purified viral RNA was eluted in 50µl DNase/RNase-Free Water. Aliquots of four samples stored in RNA later were shipped on dry ice from Tanzania to the Animal &amp; Plant Health Agency (APHA, Weybridge UK) in 2017. These, and two samples used for validation (see below), were extracted according to a previously described Trizol-based method at APHA ( 
 <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Brunker 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015
 </xref>). Briefly, 50–100mg of brain tissue was homogenised in 1ml Trizol and 200µl chloroform added to enable phase separation. RNA separates into the upper aqueous phase, which is removed and RNA precipitated using isopropanol. This is followed by centrifugation to pellet RNA and ethanol washes to purify, with elution in DNase/RNase-Free Water.
</p>
