<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To date, the immediate interventions for SARS-CoV-2 transmission have centered on contact tracing, quarantine, and social distancing. Adaptation of these physical distancing measures to mitigate the pandemic has managed to flatten the curve in some countries (
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>). Cities worldwide have begun to reopen their economy; however, a second wave of COVID-19 cases and deaths is predicted to begin 2–4 weeks after reopening (
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>). Post-pandemic transmission dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 project recurrent outbreaks during the wintertime and resurgence of this disease may persist for another 3 years (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>). Mathematical modeling of various scenarios with one-time social distancing measures has simulated a resurgence of infection when social distancing measures were lifted (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>). Thus, additional methods that circumnavigate enforced social distancing and shutting down the economy are needed. Alternatively, the pathways to herd immunity will require either mass vaccination or natural immunization over time. However, the latter approach suggests that a large portion of the population would succumb to the disease (
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>). The R
 <sub>0</sub>, basic reproductive number, represents the transmissibility of infectious agents in a naive population and can vary depending on transmission dynamics (
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>). As such, the R
 <sub>0</sub> differs across populations. The R
 <sub>0</sub> of SARS-CoV-2 has been reported to range from 1.4 to 6.49 in recent studies from January 2020 – February 2020 (
 <xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>). With an R
 <sub>0</sub> of 6.49, the population would require 85% of individuals to have immunity to abate the spread of disease, 1 – 1/R
 <sub>0</sub>. It is uncertain how long it will take for different populations to acquire herd immunity due to factors of transmission dynamics, such as demography, cultural influences, contact rates, and population density (
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>). Therefore, targeting individuals who are considered low-risk could build community protection to protect those that are vulnerable and not immune.
</p>
