<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The unique ability of RV to replicate in iPSCs without cytopathogenic alterations enabled passaging of RV-infected iPSCs and their differentiation into embryonic germ layer cells [
 <xref rid="B106-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]. However, their aggregation into EBs was impaired, which appeared to be due to a reduced level of expression of genes involved in cell adhesion. RV infection does not possess the capacity to direct differentiation of iPSCs into a distinct developmental pathway as the transcriptomic profile of mock-infected iPSCs after induction of undirected differentiation was comparable to those infected with RV [
 <xref rid="B106-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]. Directed differentiation of RV-infected iPSCs into embryonic germ layer cells revealed dysregulated developmental pathways, such as Wnt in mesodermal cells. Specifically, compared to the uninfected control, a downregulation of eye field transcription factors such as Six homeobox 3 (SIX3) and retina and anterior neural fold homeobox (RAX) involved in eye development was found in RV-infected ectodermal cells [
 <xref rid="B106-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]. Moreover, endodermal differentiation especially, was affected as indicated through an increased expression of markers for definitive endoderm such as Eomesodermin (EOMES) and Cerberus (CER). Through cooperative crosstalk with the precardiac mesoderm, the endoderm is involved in specification of cells of the cardiac lineage [
 <xref rid="B112-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. These findings in ectodermal cells on dysregulation of genes involved in eye development and the upregulation of definitive endoderm markers, together with an altered Wnt activity in mesodermal cells, can be correlated to retinal and cardiac defects, respectively. These are two of the main CRS symptoms. These examples highlight the value of iPSC/ESC-based cell culture models for the study of congenital virus infections. During congenital infection, all three viruses, HCMV, ZIKV, and RV can cause eye defects. The analysis of their course of infection during ectodermal differentiation, and more specifically on retinal organoids, could identify common, but also different, strategies pursued by the three viruses. These strategies need to be identified and compared to get a complete picture of the mechanisms of congenital virus infections.
</p>
