<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The complement system is an important branch of innate immunity that plays an essential role in the clearance of pathogens. The complement system is triggered by three main pathways, the classical, the lectin, and the alternative pathways [
 <xref rid="B77-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. The first two pathways are activated with the help of pattern recognition molecules, whereas the alternative pathway is activated spontaneously. Interestingly, it is known that viruses are recognized by the three pathways. In the classical pathway, the C1 complex recognizes antigen-antibody complexes, which are formed on the pathogen surface. C1QBP (Complement C1q Binding Protein) can bind to the globular heads of C1q molecules, activating the classical pathway [
 <xref rid="B78-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. On the other hand, in the lectin pathway, the mannan-binding lectin (MBL)/ficolin/mannan-binding lectin serin protease (MAP) complex recognizes specific carbohydrates on the pathogen surface. Complexes activated after the classical and lectin pathways, cleave C4 and C2, resulting in the generation of C4bC2a (C3 convertase). In the alternative pathway, spontaneous hydrolysis of native C3 results in the formation of C3b-like C3 that binds factor B and after cleavage by factor D forms the initial C3 convertase [
 <xref rid="B77-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. The three pathways converge at the cleavage of C3 into C3a and C3b by C3 convertases (C4b, 2a and C3b, Bb). Then, the C3b molecules formed bind covalently to the C3-convertases forming the C5-convertases that cleave C5 into C5a and C5b. CD55 blocks C3 and C5 activation by preventing the formation of new C3 and C5 convertases [
 <xref rid="B79-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. C5b starts the formation of C5b-9 or the membrane attack complex (MAC). Next, C8 binds to the membrane attached trimer and begins binding and polymerization of C9 that is inserted into the membrane, inducing virolysis [
 <xref rid="B77-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>].
</p>
