<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0255">After the COVID-19 outbreak was stated pandemic by the WHO Director-General Dr. Tedros on the 11th of March, the world started noticing the alarming levels of the upswing in the COVID-19 cases. Hitherto, the patients suffering from COVID-19, are receiving symptomatic treatment due to the unavailability of a specific therapy. In severe cases, the treatment includes support to the functioning of the vital organs [
 <xref rid="bb0945" ref-type="bibr">189</xref>]. The understanding of the whole genome sequence of COVID-19 allows the refinement of current technologies in developing the potent and targeted therapeutics [
 <xref rid="bb0950" ref-type="bibr">190</xref>]. Though, several clinical trials are presently in progress in various parts of the world to meet the vital requirements in developing the effective therapeutics and vaccines, WHO recently launched a global mega-trial called ‘Solidarity’ which emphasizes on the four most assuring therapies: the antimalarial medications chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine, an antiviral compound remdesivir, a combination of two anti-HIV drugs, ritonavir, and lopinavir, and lastly the same combination along with an immune system messenger, interferon-beta that can aid in paralyzing the virus [
 <xref rid="bb0955" ref-type="bibr">191</xref>]. Chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine prevent the entry and transport of the virus by altering the pH of endosomes. Remdesivir a nucleotide analog, likely terminates the RNA synthesis leading to the induction of mutagenesis. Both ritonavir and lopinavir being protease inhibitors block the viral cellular entry where ritonavir inhibits Cyt-P450 and prolongs the half-life of lopinavir. Interferon-beta inhibits viral replication [
 <xref rid="bb0960" ref-type="bibr">192</xref>]. In quest of an effective therapeutic moiety, various research institutes and pharma companies are repurposing several antivirals, antibiotics, and their combinations. If the efficacy of these repurposed drugs reveals beneficial outcomes against COVID-19, it would be a case of good fortune rather than good preparedness. The current strategy for pandemic drugs is to develop or repurpose a drug right after the discovery of a novel outbreak. Several aspects of the pandemic seem to have shown good progress using this strategy. Within weeks, viral genome sequences were understood and published which helped in identifying the suitable drug candidates. Clinical trials of interferons, ACE inhibitors, remdesivir, hydroxychloroquine, and monoclonal antibodies are under progress [
 <xref rid="bb0965" ref-type="bibr">193</xref>] . Though the window of the usefulness of steroids for COVID-19 patients is narrower, they are still preferred because of their capability of preventing lung fibrosis and stopping cytokine storm [
 <xref rid="bb0970" ref-type="bibr">194</xref>]. Testing of the proposed drugs takes more time particularly when it is performed on humans as a part of clinical trials.
</p>
