<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Larocca et al. (2016)</xref> demonstrated that a prM-E DNA vaccine could provide complete protection in mice against challenge with ZIKV strains linked to major clinical complications. That study also noted that a prM-deleted mutant plasmid DNA vaccine could not offer the same protection, evidencing the important role of prM protein in enhancing ZIKV immunogenicity. The ZIKV prM-E DNA vaccine resulted in a higher titer of envelope antibody production as well as ZIKV-specific neutralizing antibodies but not prM-specific antibodies. This phenomenon has also been reported in another study using a ZIKV prM-E immunogen as a vaccine candidate (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Yi et al., 2017</xref>). This outcome may be due to the structural nature of ZIKV E protein as it is the main viral protein participating in binding and fusion to host receptors, enabling easy access to this epitope by host immunity. Although the antibody-recognizing epitope is located on the E protein, prM is suggested to enhance immunogenicity because prM interacts with domain II of E protein to avoid premature virion release (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Pierson and Diamond, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Kostyuchenko et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira et al., 2017</xref>). Other studies have also reported that ZIKV-neutralizing antibodies do not bind to fully mature virions but only to immature virions (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Dai et al., 2016</xref>), and the prM proteins of these latter may be processed during ingress by furin proteases available in endocytic vesicles (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Pierson and Diamond, 2012</xref>). Another DNA vaccine encoding full-length prM-E protein has also shown the ability to confer full protection against ZIKV challenge in humanized DRAG mice that have robust antibody responses and are useful for testing vaccination approaches (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Danner et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Yi et al., 2017</xref>).
</p>
