<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13">The estimation of the basic reproduction number (measuring the expected number of secondary infections generated by a single infected individual introduced into a completely susceptible population during his/her infection) is usually an utmost important question in the study of mathematical models of infectious diseases. The instantaneous reproduction number is considered when part of the population is immune. In mathematical models with periodic coefficients, the basic reproduction number can be obtained as the spectral radius of a linear integral operator on a space of periodic functions (for details, see
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>
 </sup>). In general, the actual value of the basic reproduction number cannot be calculated analytically, however, there exist methods to numerical approximate it (see Supplementary Information S.3 or e.g.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>
 </sup> for details). Besides determining the basic reproduction number of the periodic model, computing the formula for the basic reproduction number of the time-constant model obtained from the periodic model by setting the time-dependent parameters (mosquito birth rate and transmission rates between humans and mosquitoes) to constant also provides interesting results. The derivation of the formula for the basic reproduction number can be found in the Supplementary Information S.2. This formula gives us the basic reproduction number in any given time instant by substituting the parameter values into it, including the value of the time-dependent parameters at that given moment. This also allows us to calculate the instantaneous reproduction rate 
 <inline-formula id="IEq54">
  <alternatives>
   <tex-math id="M107">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${{\mathscr{R}}}_{{\rm{i}}{\rm{n}}{\rm{s}}{\rm{t}}}$$\end{document}</tex-math>
   <math id="M108">
    <msub>
     <mrow>
      <mrow>
       <mrow>
        <mi mathvariant="script">R</mi>
       </mrow>
      </mrow>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mrow>
       <mi mathvariant="normal">i</mi>
       <mi mathvariant="normal">n</mi>
       <mi mathvariant="normal">s</mi>
       <mi mathvariant="normal">t</mi>
      </mrow>
     </mrow>
    </msub>
   </math>
   <inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_53062_Article_IEq54.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </alternatives>
 </inline-formula> which estimates the average number of secondary cases per infectious case in a population made up of both susceptible and non-susceptible individuals and which can be obtained by multiplying the basic reproductive rate by the size of the susceptible fraction of the host population.
</p>
