<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The most likely cluster of overseas acquired cases occurred in Herston, Brisbane. As there is no 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquito in the Brisbane area, it cannot initiate any autochthonous transmission. However, an entomological household survey in Brisbane found that approximately 26% of all premises surveyed harboured 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>notoscriptus</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0220134.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. It is interesting to note that both 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>notoscriptus</italic> have similar ecologies to 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0220134.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], and a study has discussed the overlapping capacities of their habitats [
 <xref rid="pone.0220134.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] as well as the potential displacement of native species by the more aggressive 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0220134.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. In recent times, 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> has been established in Torres Strait Islands and caused the 2016 outbreak in that region [
 <xref rid="pone.0220134.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0220134.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], and also increased the chance of this mosquito becoming established in mainland Australia, especially Cairns which is 800 km away from Torres Strait Island [
 <xref rid="pone.0220134.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Further, several incursions of 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> also occurred in different ports such as Cairns, Brisbane and Townsville [
 <xref rid="pone.0220134.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Given the presence of imported dengue cases as well as several incursions of 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> in this region, future local transmission is likely. An economic cost analysis of severity of dengue posed by establishment of 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> in Brisbane found mosquito control program would be cost-effective rather than ignoring the possibility of establishment [
 <xref rid="pone.0220134.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] suggesting that household level surveillance could be a feasible approach.
</p>
