<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Consistent with prior research among MSM in LMIC [
 <xref rid="pone.0221558.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0221558.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0221558.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], PrEP attributes were commonly perceived barriers to PrEP use among participants in both the “perceived PrEP attribute barriers” and “high level of perceived barriers” classes. Although antiretroviral therapy (ART) is universally available in Mexico [
 <xref rid="pone.0221558.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], it is currently unknown how PrEP will be incorporated into Mexico’s healthcare system. Branded FTC/TDF can cost up to 850 US dollars per month in high-income countries [
 <xref rid="pone.0221558.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>], while generic FTC/TDF, which is used as ART in some LMIC [
 <xref rid="pone.0221558.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0221558.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>], is estimated to cost 6.5 US dollars per month (~123 Mexican pesos). In our study, 30% of participants who reported that they would be willing to pay for PrEP said they would only do so if it cost ≤150 Mexican pesos (~8.0 US dollars) per month. Thus, making generic FTC/TDF available as PrEP in Mexico may enhance its acceptability to many MSM in Tijuana, while its integration into Mexico’s public healthcare system may fully address concerns related to cost within this vulnerable population. Although PrEP use has been associated with several mild, short-term side-effects [
 <xref rid="pone.0221558.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], and non-progressive and reversible declines in renal function and bone density [
 <xref rid="pone.0221558.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>], it is generally considered safe and well tolerated [
 <xref rid="pone.0221558.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Given that almost half (45%) of our sample was in the “perceived PrEP attribute barriers” class, raising potential PrEP users’ awareness of cost coverage options that may enhance its affordability and increasing their knowledge of the nature and duration of potential side-effects may significantly improve PrEP uptake among MSM in Tijuana.
</p>
