<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>However, to achieve complete PrEP coverage among MSM in Tijuana, additional efforts may be needed to address the range of barriers to PrEP use endorsed by those in the “high level of perceived barriers” class within our sample. For example, a history of incarceration was associated with membership in this class. Persons with a history of incarceration often face elevated rates of unemployment, substance use, mental illness, and inadequate access to healthcare [
 <xref rid="pone.0221558.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0221558.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>], which may limit PrEP uptake among this population. A peer navigation intervention initiated pre-release, which addressed social-environmental factors and incorporated individualized problem-solving techniques, was shown to effectively support viral suppression maintenance among HIV-positive men and TW released from jail [
 <xref rid="pone.0221558.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Interventions which assess PrEP interest and eligibility during incarceration and provide peer navigation services post-release may support PrEP uptake and adherence and be particularly effective for MSM like those in the “high level of perceived barriers” class. However, lower levels of social support were also associated with being in this class. In Mexico, cultural norms of homophobia and 
 <italic>machismo</italic> often inhibit MSM from being able to “come out” and positively experience their sexual identity [
 <xref rid="pone.0221558.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. This can cause psychological distress among MSM, resulting in withdrawal from social support networks (e.g., family and friends) [
 <xref rid="pone.0221558.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0221558.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>], which can impact their ability to access culturally competent healthcare [
 <xref rid="pone.0221558.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0221558.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0221558.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. As such, community-level programs which reduce negative social attitudes towards MSM in combination with counseling interventions to help MSM identify supportive social network members may be critical to PrEP use and adherence among MSM in Tijuana.
</p>
