<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat.1008142.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1008142.g006</object-id>
 <label>Fig 6</label>
 <caption>
  <title>EV71 preferentially infects astrocytes of mice brain and induces IL-6 production 
   <italic>via</italic> TLR7.
  </title>
  <p>(
   <bold>A</bold> and 
   <bold>B</bold>) The neonatal (6-day-old) WT and TLR7
   <sup>-/-</sup> mice were sacrificed and the sections of mice cerebral cortex or hippocampus were subjected to immunofluorescence (IF) staining with DAPI (Blue) and neural cells markers (GFAP, astrocyte marker; NeuN, neuron marker; IBA-1, microglia marker) (Green) (A) or TLR7 (Red). GFAP and IBA-1 staining in cerebral cortex; NeuN staining in hippocampus. The presentative images were acquired using fluorescence microscopy (B). Bar = 20 μm. (
   <bold>C</bold>) Neonatal WT mice were intracranially injected with PBS or EV71. The cerebral cortex sections from mice after 3 days EV71 incubation were subjected to immunostaining with DAPI (Blue), neural cells markers (Green) and dsRNA (Red). The presentative images were acquired using fluorescence confocal microscopy. Bar = 20 μm. (
   <bold>D</bold> and 
   <bold>E</bold>) Neonatal WT and TLR7
   <sup>-/-</sup> mice were intracranially injected with PBS or EV71. After 3 days EV71 incubation, brain sections from mice were subjected to immunostaining with DAPI (Blue), GFAP (Green) and IL-6 (Red) (D). Bar = 20 μm. Cells were observed using fluorescence confocal microscopy and the IL-6 expression in GFAP-positive (GFAP
   <sup>+</sup>) cells was calculated (E). Graphs show mean ± SD. **, 
   <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.01. (
   <bold>F</bold> and 
   <bold>G</bold>) There-day-old WT mice were intracranially injected with 10 μl PBS or 10 μl PBS containing 50 μg R837 per mouse, and then sacrificed on day 1 post R837 administration. Immunostaining of the brain’s cortex sections from day 1 was probed with IL-6 (Red), GFAP (Green) and stained with DAPI (Blue) (F), or cl-Caspase-3 (Red), GFAP (Green) and DAPI (Blue) (G). The presentative images were acquired using fluorescence microscopy. Bar = 20 μm.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1008142.g006" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
