<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0040">Vit D deficiency is a global health problem common among all age groups [
 <xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Negligible UV-B radiations reach the earth surface during winters at latitudes &gt; 40°. This increases the risk of Vit D deficiency during wintertime [
 <xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Epidemiological evidence suggests that during first month of winter, influenza infection is most common worldwide when Vit D levels are at their minimum [
 <xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Sufficient Vit D levels have shown to safeguard against influenza and respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) infections [
 <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Also, serum 25-hydroxy Vit D levels tend to drop with age [
 <xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. This is important with regard to COVID-19 as case-fatality rates (CFRs) surge with age [
 <xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Bergman et al [
 <xref rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] conducted a meta analysis of randomized controlled trials (RCT) of Vit D for prevention of respiratory tract infection (RTI). They demonstrated that risk of developing RTIs is reduced by prophylactic administration of Vit D (odds ratio: 0.64; 95% CI: 0.49 to 0.84). Rhodes et al [
 <xref rid="bb0140" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] highlighted relationship between mortality from COVID-19 per million of population and countries based on their latitudes. It was observed that countries lying below 35° North latitude have low mortality rates. This could be attributed to the fact that people living in countries lying above 35° North do not encounter adequate sunlight during winter and suffer from Vit D deficiency. Likewise, Daneshkhah et al [
 <xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] showed that the age-specific case fatality rate (CFR) of COVID-19 was highest in Italy, Spain, and France where severe Vit D deficiency (mean 25OHD concentration &lt; 0.25 ng/L) is reported in comparison to other countries. In elderly population, overactivation of adaptive immune system results from a shortage of memory B cells and aberrant innate immune response, which leads to cytokine storm as observed in COVID-19 patients [
 <xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In another study, Lau et al [
 <xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] assessed 25OHD levels in twenty COVID-19 patients admitted in intesive care unit (ICU). 11 subjects had Vit D insufficiency (VID) and all patients below 75 years of age had VDI. Among these, 7 patients had &lt;20 ng/mL and three had &lt; 10 ng/mL of 25OHD levels. This study demonstrated that VDI intensifies COVID-19 severity. A retrospective multinomial logistic regression study by Alipio [
 <xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] on data of 212 COVID-19 patients in south-Asian countries, suggests that increase in serum 25OHD levels could improve clinical outcomes. Statistical analysis was carried out using Mann-Whitney U and χ
 <sup>2</sup> tests. As the severity of disease increased from mild to critical, serum 25OHD levels decreased from 31.2 ng/ml to 17.1 ng/ml and were statistically significant with clinical outcomes (p&lt;0.001). Out of 212 patients, 80 exhibited Vit D insufficiency (25 OHD&lt; 21-29 ng/ml) and 77 exhibited Vit D deficiency (25 OHD&lt; 20 ng/ml). The odds of having mild clinical outcome increases and critical outcome decreases (OR=0.051, p&lt;0.001), with increase in serum 25 OHD level.
</p>
