<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">Under observed conditions, the effective reproduction number 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>e</sub> decays over time as both efforts are made to control disease spread and the pool of susceptible reduces, which results in 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> being equal to 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>e</sub> only when time 
 <italic>t</italic> is zero. Therefore, to calculate effective contact rate 
 <italic>β</italic>, we allowed 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>e</sub> to decay per time step 
 <italic>t</italic> (Supplementary Equations 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">8</xref> and 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">9</xref>). However, countries that can invest more in health infrastructure (e.g., barrier nursing, surveillance) should see a more rapid reduction in 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>e</sub> over time compared to countries that do not have such infrastructure and also a concomitantly, a decrease in CFR. Therefore, we derived an empirical estimate of the relationship between wealth (measured using GDP-PPP per capita) and both the relative rate of decay of 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>e</italic>
 </sub> over time (Supplementary Equation 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">10</xref>) and CFR (Supplementary Equation 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">11</xref>). Using a spatially disaggregated poverty data layer
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>
 </sup> we weighted the per grid cell per time step 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>e</italic>
 </sub> reduction and CFR accordingly to the values in each grid cell. While we found the relationship between wealth and both 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>e</italic>
 </sub> and CFR reduction over time to be best described using curves with exponents of −0.08 and −0.02, respectively, this was inferred using relatively few data points (Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>). In our simulation runs, therefore, we allowed these exponents to vary similarly to the parameters above, to allow either more linear declines or deeper curves to best estimate the true impact of this relationship.
</p>
