<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Coronaviruses (CoVs) are positive-sense single-stranded RNA viruses (Group IV of the Baltimore classification). CoVs are part of the Coronaviridae family and fall into the Orthocoronavirinae subfamily, which includes four genera: Alphacoronavirus, Betacoronavirus, Gammacoronavirus, and Deltacoronavirus [
 <xref rid="B5-foods-09-01036" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-foods-09-01036" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Until 2019, six coronaviruses capable of infecting humans were known. Two of these, both from the Betacoronavirus group, caused major epidemics characterized by fatal respiratory disease: SARS-CoV, responsible for severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) in 2002 in the province of Guangdong in China; and MERS-CoV, responsible for Middle-East respiratory syndrome (MERS) in 2012 in the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia [
 <xref rid="B7-foods-09-01036" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Recently, a new CoV, called severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) [
 <xref rid="B8-foods-09-01036" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], was responsible for the outbreak of the COVID-19 pandemic on 31 December 2019 in China [
 <xref rid="B9-foods-09-01036" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The previous SARS and MERS outbreaks involved 29 and 27 countries, respectively, and, given that over 170 countries have been affected by the COVID-19 pandemic after only 3 months, the severity of the current infection is evident [
 <xref rid="B10-foods-09-01036" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-foods-09-01036" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-foods-09-01036" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The most common symptoms and signs of SARS-CoV-2 infection are respiratory symptoms, fever, dry cough, fatigue, and dyspnea [
 <xref rid="B13-foods-09-01036" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-foods-09-01036" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], whereas the clinical manifestations of infection range from asymptomatic to severe pneumonia. It is noteworthy that pneumonia, a lower respiratory tract infection, has occupied the first position in the communicable disease rank and the fourth position in the top ten causes of death globally [
 <xref rid="B15-foods-09-01036" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].
</p>
