<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to Myanmar strains, A(H1N1)pdm09 collected from various prefectures (Okinawa, Nagasaki, Gunma, Shizuoka, Kyoto, Nara, and Hokkaido prefectures) in Japan as part of the influenza investigation conducted by Niigata University during the 2017–2018 season was also sequenced by Sanger Method [
 <xref rid="pone.0229601.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. All the sequences used in this study were registered with the Global Initiative on Sharing All Influenza Data (GISAID) (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0229601.s001">S1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0229601.s002">S2</xref> Tables). Reference strains such as the influenza vaccine strains for the 2017–2018 Japanese vaccine, A/Singapore/GP1908/2015, and the 2017 southern hemisphere vaccine, A/Michigan/45/2015, as well as strains collected in India during May and August of 2017 (GISAID Isolate ID: EPI_ISL_281596, EPI_ISL_281597, EPI_ISL_281600, EPI_ISL_281601, EPI_ISL_281602, EPI_ISL_281603, EPI_ISL_281604, and EPI_ISL_282867) were downloaded from GISAID. India is specifically included in this analysis because A(H1N1)pdm09 outbreaks due to Clade 6B and 6B.1 viruses were repeatedly reported in India during 2015–2017, thus suggesting the possibility that the Myanmar strains may have originated in India [
 <xref rid="pone.0229601.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0229601.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Phylogenetic analysis was performed using the Hasegawa-Kishino-Yano model with discrete Gamma distribution (HKY+G) and the General Time Reversible model with discrete Gamma distribution incorporating Invariant sites (GTR + G + I) as the best-fit nucleotide substitution models for the HA and NA datasets, respectively, as implemented in the MEGA 6.0 software (Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis) [
 <xref rid="pone.0229601.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Best fitting trees for the HA and NA genes were constructed by the maximum likelihood method and bootstrap analysis of 1,000 replicates. Deduced amino acid sequences were analyzed, and amino acid changes were compared with A/California/07/2009 (H1N1pdm09) (GISAID Isolate ID: EPI_ISL_227813).
</p>
