<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">Approximately 90 % of people worldwide have been exposed to one or both HSV viruses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. HSV-1 is more common, with 65 % of persons in the USA being seropositive to HSV-1 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. It is almost universal in the developing world, usually acquired in childhood secondary to close contact with infected family members and causes oral cold sores [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. HSV-2 on the other hand is less ubiquitous and incidence varies from 15 to 80 %, depending on the population. Transmission is almost exclusively during sexual activity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].
 <list list-type="simple">
  <list-item>
   <label>2.</label>
   <p id="Par19">Which subgroups are at a particularly high risk for liver involvement with HSV?</p>
   <p id="Par20">The infection in the liver with HSV is uncommon. However, when it does occur, it frequently leads to acute liver failure with a high mortality. Severe HSV infections are typically associated with impaired cell-mediated immunity that may occur in a transplant recipient or in patients on high-dose steroids. Females in the third trimester of pregnancy are also particularly at risk for acute liver failure.</p>
   <p id="Par21">The diagnosis is often missed as skin lesions that provide clinical clues to the diagnosis are often lacking in patients with HSV-associated hepatitis. A high degree of suspicion, even in the absence of skin lesions, combined with early diagnostic modalities and early institution of appropriate therapy with parenteral acyclovir may dramatically improve survival [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].
   </p>
   <p id="Par22">Four mechanisms of HSV dissemination and resultant hepatitis have been hypothesized [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]: (a) a large HSV inoculant overwhelming the defense system; (b) an impairment in host macrophages, cytotoxic T lymphocytes, and delayed-type hypersensitivity reactions; (c) enhanced virulence; and (d) activation of a latent hepatovirulent strain.
   </p>
   <p id="Par23">HSV hepatitis is characterized by rapid development of fulminant hepatic necrosis with serum aminotransferase levels 100- to 1000-fold above normal and hyperbilirubinemia [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Positive serology often points at the diagnosis with polymerase chain reaction (PCR) confirming the diagnosis. In the era of widespread availability of PCR testing, a liver biopsy is now less commonly needed to secure the diagnosis. Common findings on liver biopsy include massive liver necrosis with almost complete absence of portal tracts and central veins. Presence of typical intranuclear viral inclusions is the hallmark finding on a liver biopsy, confirmed with immunohistochemical staining.
   </p>
   <p id="Par24">Given the time-sensitive nature of the disease, initiation of empiric therapy with acyclovir is indicated while awaiting diagnostic confirmation in a patient with acute liver failure.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
