<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As ZIKV incidence data become available, the annual transmission “high-season” and “low-season” should be characterized so pregnancy may be planned such that sensitive periods of gestation are aligned with the low-season window of opportunity. After the initial wave of the epidemic, ZIKV transmission models can be fitted and transmission parameters estimated using time series data from ZIKV surveillance. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.1002520.g002">Fig 2</xref> provides a potential ZIKV Susceptible-Infected-Recovered transmission model developed with a focus on the demography relevant to congenital ZIKV. To estimate seasonal transmission parameters, this model would require extensive time series data on reported ZIKV cases either weekly or monthly. To overcome data limitations, data from other ZIKV surveillance systems could be used in parallel to parameterize such a model. Surveillance data that could be used to study ZIKV transmission and pathology include reported cases, registries of miscarriage and CZS, ZIKV serology data, and mosquito surveillance data. Models with similar levels of complexity in transmission, pathology, and demography have been parameterized for poliovirus and measles [
 <xref rid="pbio.1002520.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.1002520.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]; see [
 <xref rid="pbio.1002520.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] for statistical inference methods. By combining transmission models with reported ZIKV cases, data on vector abundance, and other covariates that could influence transmission (e.g., temperature, humidity, and human movement), the underlying mechanistic drivers of ZIKV transmission seasonality could be revealed (knowledge gap 1). Assuming vector abundance is an important driver of ZIKV seasonal transmission, based on the 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> data from Puerto Rico, the high-transmission season in Puerto Rico would occur between October–December and the trough would be April–June (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.1002520.g001">Fig 1A</xref>). The impact of vector abundance on 
 <italic>flavivirus</italic> transmission is indicated by the 2013 DENV epidemic in Puerto Rico, which had a trough in April (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.1002520.g001">Fig 1C</xref>), as would be predicted based on vector seasonality. Importantly, the high and low transmission seasons are tied to local climate conditions and will therefore be region-specific.
</p>
