<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>With knowledge of regional transmission seasonality, initiating pregnancy during the seasonal window of opportunity for conception would minimize risk of maternal infection and subsequent damage to the fetus. Birth defects resulting from in utero infection with CMV, herpes simplex, and rubella virus are reported to be highest when maternal infection occurs within the first 20 weeks of gestation [
 <xref rid="pbio.1002520.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>–
 <xref rid="pbio.1002520.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Miscarriages of known ZIKV-positive fetuses have been reported at 11 and 13 weeks gestation [
 <xref rid="pbio.1002520.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Preliminary data suggest miscarriage and CZS are most likely when maternal infection occurs during the first or second trimester [
 <xref rid="pbio.1002520.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.1002520.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.1002520.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.1002520.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], but fetal abnormalities have been found in women infected with ZIKV during weeks 8–35 of gestation [
 <xref rid="pbio.1002520.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], indicating all three trimesters are vulnerable to some extent. The critical window of susceptibility for ZIKV-induced miscarriage and CZS needs to be identified and taken into account when determining the seasonal window of opportunity for conception. Identifying the period of susceptibility for the fetus and using planned seasonal conception to redistribute births—i.e., to take advantage of the transmission low season and ensure sensitive gestation occurs during the ZIKV low season—would reduce risk to the fetus by minimizing maternal exposure. Based on the size of the 2014 birth cohort in Puerto Rico, redistributing births even by a small amount, for example with as little as 3% fewer births experiencing a susceptible trimester during the high transmission season, would translate to reducing risk for approximately 1,000 births annually. In a large country like Brazil, which had a birth cohort of approximately 3 million in 2015 [
 <xref rid="pbio.1002520.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], planned seasonal conception for 3% of births could reduce risk in &gt;88,000 pregnancies. The absolute reduction in risk, however, is unknown, as it will depend on the incidence of ZIKV infection in the population and the subsequent risk of trans-placental transmission and fetal abnormalities.
</p>
