<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P21">Total RNA was extracted from 50 μl of mosquito tissue and body homogenates using the Mag-Bind Viral DNA/RNA 96 Kit (Omega Bio-tek Inc., Norcross, GA) on a Kingfisher Flex automated nucleic acid extraction device (ThermoFisher Scientific, Waltham, MA) following the manufacturer’s instructions. Samples were eluted in 50 μl ddH
 <sub>2</sub>O. ZIKV RNA was detected in mosquito tissues using a previously described RT-qPCR primer-probe set (ZIKV 1087/1163c/1108 FAM)
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>
 </sup>. DENV-2 RNA was detected using a previously described primer-probe set spanning the 3’-UTR
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>
 </sup> and CHIKV RNA was detected using the previously described 6856F/6981c/6919-FAM primer-probe set
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>
 </sup>. The same RT-qPCR protocol was used to detect all three viruses. In brief, 25 μl reactions containing 2.5 μl of total RNA were assayed with the TaqMan RNA-to-C
 <sub>t</sub> 1-Step Kit (ThermoFisher Scientific) on a CFX96 Touch Real-Time PCR Detection System (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA) using the following parameters: RT – 50°C for 30 min, 95°C for 10 min, PCR – 95°C for 15 s., 60°C for 1 min followed by a plate read (50 cycles). Data were analyzed using the Bio-Rad CFX Manager 3.1 software. The cut-off value used for ZIKV exposed samples to be considered positive by RT-qPCR was C
 <sub>t</sub> &lt;37. This cut-off value was empirically determined by comparing paired serial ten-fold dilutions either inoculated on Vero cells or assayed by RT-qPCR (
 <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S5</xref>). C
 <sub>t</sub> values &lt;35 cycles were considered positive for CHIKV and &lt;33 cycles for DENV-2. The use of RT-qPCR for scoring positives was validated by comparing RT-qPCR and cell culture isolation using salivary glands from ZIKV-exposed 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>. While the percent positive rate was higher by RT-qPCR, the difference in infection rates between single-feed and double-feed samples was maintained (
 <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S6</xref>).
</p>
