<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Based upon its superficial similarity in morphology and genome organization to the caliciviruses, HEV was originally classified in the 
 <italic>Caliciviridae</italic> family [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R135">135</xref>]. The predicted putative functional motifs of HEV non-structural proteins are also similar to those of 
 <italic>Rubella virus</italic> and alphaviruses of the 
 <italic>Togaviridae</italic> family as well as to the plant furoviruses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref>]. The HEV capping enzyme has properties very similar to those of viruses within the “alphavirus-like super group” [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R117">117</xref>]. A cap structure has been identified at the 5′ end of the HEV genome [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">60</xref>]. Although HEV shares several properties with these families, it has sufficient differences to be classified into a new 
 <italic>Hepeviridae</italic> family [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>]. HEV genomes vary significantly and consist of at least four major mammalian genotypes (1–4) and one avian HEV [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R101">101</xref>] (Fig. 1). Mammalian HEV and avian HEV share only approximately 50–60% nucleotide sequence identity, thus avian HEV may constitute a separate new genus distinct from the current genus 
 <italic>Hepevirus</italic>. Genotype 1 and genotype 2 mammalian strains are restricted in humans and mainly associated with large waterborne epidemics in endemic regions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78">78</xref>]; genotype 3 and 4 mammalian HEV strains are found both in human and other mammalian reservoirs (swine, wild boar, deer, mongooses) and are mainly responsible for sporadic cases of hepatitis E. Genotype 3 is found mainly in Europe, the USA and Japan, and genotype 4 has been identified mainly in Asia (China, Japan and India) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78">78</xref>] and occasionally in Europe (Germany and one possible case imported from Vietnam to Spain) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R144">144</xref>]. In addition to the prototype avian HEV strains from the USA, several genetically-distinct strains of avian HEV have been identified recently from chickens in Australia and Europe (Hungary and Spain), and there exist at least three genotypes of avian HEV worldwide [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R104">104</xref>] (Fig. 1). Very recently, a novel strain of HEV was isolated from farm rabbits in China. The rabbit HEV is most closely related to HEV genotype 3 with approximately 82% of nucleotide sequence homology, suggesting that rabbit HEV may be a variant of genotype 3 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R154">154</xref>] (Fig. 1). Currently there is little information regarding the host range and zoonotic potential of this rabbit HEV. Since the rabbit HEV is a variant of genotype 3, it is possible that the rabbit HEV may also have the ability to infect across species. More recently, a new hepatitis E-like virus was identified in the feces of wild rats in Germany. Partial sequence analyses showed that the rat HEV only shares approximately 59.9% and 49.9% sequence identities, respectively, with known human and avian HEV, suggesting that rat HEV may represent an additional new HEV genotype within the hepevirus genus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref>]. The complete genomic sequence of the rat HEV is needed for a definitive classification. It remains to be determined whether or not rat HEV can infect humans. 
</p>
