<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">ACE2-associated lung injury has been suggested in SARS-CoV infection (Imai 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2008</xref>; Kuba 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2005</xref>); SARS-CoV S protein can downregulate ACE2 (Glowacka 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2010</xref>; Wang 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2008</xref>), and induce the shedding of catalytically active ACE2 ectodomain (Haga 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2008</xref>; Jia 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2009</xref>; Lambert 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2005</xref>). Loss of pulmonary ACE2 function has been suggested to be associated with acute lung injury (Imai 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2005</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2008</xref>; Kuba 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2005</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2006</xref>); the reduction in ACE2 function can cause dysfunction of the renin-angiotensin system (RAS) and enhance inflammation and vascular permeability. In a murine ARD model, loss of ACE2 expression resulted in enhanced vascular permeability, increased lung edema, neutrophil accumulation, and diminished lung function (Imai 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2005</xref>). In addition, in human airway epithelia, ACE2 is constitutively shed by the action of disintegrin and metalloprotease 17 (ADAM17, also known as TNF-α cleavage enzyme, TACE) to release enzymatically active soluble ACE2 (sACE2) (Lambert 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2005</xref>). Both SARS-CoV infection and inflammatory cytokines such as IL-1β and TNF-α can enhance ACE2 shedding (Haga 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2008</xref>; Jia 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2009</xref>; Lambert 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2005</xref>). The biological function of sACE2 remains largely unknown. However, SARS-CoV S protein-induced ACE2 shedding has been found to be tightly coupled with TNF-α production in cell culture conditions (Haga 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2008</xref>). Intriguingly, the S protein from another coronavirus, HNL63-CoV, does not induce ACE2 shedding, although the virus also binds to ACE2 to mediate NHL63-CoV entry (Haga 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2008</xref>). HNL63-CoV infection only causes the common cold, suggesting a potential pathogenic role of sACE2 in SARS-CoV infection. These previous studies suggest that sACE2 may be directly involved in the inflammatory responses of SARS-CoV, and possibly SARS-CoV-2 as well.
</p>
