<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Following enhanced surveillance and improved understanding of transmission dynamics, there are several opportunities to treat or prevent neglected infections of poverty in the US using existing drugs or other control tools (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0000256-t003">Table 3</xref>). Through either population-based drug administration or case identification and treatment, the soil-transmitted helminths could be controlled by administration of albendazole and ivermectin 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Bethony1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, while expanded use of praziquantel would treat schistosomiasis among selected immigrant populations 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Posey1" ref-type="bibr">[90]</xref> and prevent transmission of 
 <italic>T. solium</italic> eggs and possibly reduce the incidence of cysticercosis 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Garcia1" ref-type="bibr">[153]</xref>. Metronidazole and tinidazole are available for the treatment of trichomoniasis and giardiasis 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Nailor1" ref-type="bibr">[154]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-5" ref-type="bibr">[155]</xref>, and nitazoxanide is available for cryptosporidiosis and giardiasis 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Yoder1" ref-type="bibr">[144]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-6" ref-type="bibr">[156]</xref>. Pyrimethamine plus sulfadiazine is used for the treatment of toxoplasmosis, and the optimal length of treatment and its impact on child development and neurological sequelae need to be determined 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-McLeod1" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>. Antibiotics are available for the treatment of leptospirosis and other bacterial zoonoses 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Griffith1" ref-type="bibr">[157]</xref>. An important role also exists for veterinary public health interventions to prevent zoonotic transmission to humans, possibly including the mass treatment of 
 <italic>Toxocara</italic>-infected dogs, 
 <italic>Toxoplasma</italic>-infected cats, and other measures 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Jones3" ref-type="bibr">[158]</xref>. The control of almost all of the neglected infections of poverty would also benefit from improvements in environmental sanitation, piped clean water, and improvements in housing in some of the poorest endemic areas. For Chagas disease, dengue, and leishmaniasis, consideration of expanded vector control approaches is warranted 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Gubler1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Yamagata1" ref-type="bibr">[159]</xref>.
</p>
