<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0023">As an important part of TCM, acupuncture and moxibustion therapy have made vital contributions in the history of anti-epidemic action in China. Modern clinical and experimental studies have shown that acupuncture and moxibustion therapy can regulate the human immune function, preventing inflammation and infection. In the current epidemic of COVID-19, acupuncture and moxibustion therapy were actively used for both prevention and treatment. According to Guidelines on Acupuncture and Moxibustion Intervention for COVID-19 (second edition) (
 <xref rid="bib0036" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2020</xref>), acupuncture and moxibustion intervention was divided into three phases: medical observation phase (suspected cases), clinical treatment phase (confirmed cases), and convalescence phase. In the medical observation phase, the main points were Fengmen (BLl2), Feishu (BLl3), Pishu (BL20), Hegu (LI4), Quchi (LI11), Chize (LU5), Yuji (LU10), Qihai (CV6), Zusanli (ST36), and Sanyinjiao (SP6). The purpose was to stimulate the vital qi and the functions of the lungs and spleen, enhancing the viscera's defense. During the clinical treatment phase, the main points chosen were as follows: Hegu (LI4), Taichong (LR3), Tiantu (CV22), Chize (LU5), Kongzui (LU6), Zusanli (ST36), Sanyinjiao (SP6), Dazhu (BLll), Fengmen (BLl2), Feishu (BLl3), Xinshu (BLl5), Geshu (BL17), Zhongfu (LU1), Danzhong (CVl7), Qihai (CV6), Guanyuan (CV4), and Zhongwan (CVl2), in order to stimulate the vital qi of the lungs and spleen, protect the viscera, and dispel pathogens. In the convalescence phase, the main points were Neiguan (PC6), Zusanli (ST36), Zhongwan (CVl2), Tianshu (ST25), and Qihai (CV6). The aim in this phase is to remove residual virus, restore vitality, and repair the functions of the lungs and spleen. Scholars have provided other ideas for prevention and treatment of COVID-19. Lin Shiyu (
 <xref rid="bib0036" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2020</xref>) selected Dazhui (DU14), Fengmen (BLl2), Shaoshang (LU11), Yuji (LU10), Lidui (ST45), and Neiting (ST44) can be used as part of a fire needle treatment plan to prevent COVID-19 and relieve patients’ symptoms. Liu Kaiping (
 <xref rid="bib0039" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2020</xref>) suggested that moxibustion not only effectively prevents and treats COVID-19, but also improves the quality of life of patients. After the comparative induction and analysis of relevant references, 
 <xref rid="bib0082" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al. (2020)</xref> pointed out that moxibustion on Dazhui (DU14) and Quchi (LI11) could be selected for fever; moxibustion on Dazhui (DU14), Feishu (BL13), and Dingchuan (EX-B1) could be selected for cough; moxibustion on Zusanli (ST36), Guanyuan (CV4), and Qihai (CV6) could be used for fatigue; and moxibustion on Zhongwan (CV12), Zusanli (ST36), and Tianshu (ST25) could be used for upper digestive system discomfort. Besides, 
 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al. (2020)</xref> suggested that Ren and Du meridian moxibustion can play an important role in the prevention of new COVID-19 infectionsand in preventing recurrence after recovery.
</p>
