<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The emergence of pandemic H1N1 (pH1N1) influenza in 2009 was the first influenza pandemic in the post-genomic era. Genetic analysis of the pandemic in its early stages was aided by pre-planned and intensive virus sequencing in some countries, and by the immediate and open sharing of the resulting data through online databases. Consequently, the molecular epidemiology of the virus could be tracked in ‘real time’ as the epidemic unfolded [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. This included phylogeographic analyses that studied the global dispersal of the virus during its establishment phase [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], which followed patterns of international air travel [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. The intensive sampling of virus sequences during the pandemic enabled the molecular epidemiology of IAV to be scrutinized at such a high resolution that the importation, extinction and persistence of individual transmission chains in specific locations could be observed (e.g. [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>–
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]). Comparisons among countries of the dynamics of transmission chains may provide useful insights. For example, only two of many pH1N1 lineages that were introduced to the UK at the start of the pandemic were detected there six months later [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>], while a pair of pH1N1 transmission chains appear to have persisted in west Africa for almost 2 years [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. The latter observation seems to be at odds with the extensive spatial mixing of IAV imposed by air travel, but west Africa is connected comparatively weakly within the global air transportation network [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>] and influenza persistence might be facilitated there by climatic variability that can generate temporal overlap among epidemics in neighbouring regions [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>], as has been previously suggested for IAV persistence in southeast Asia [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>].
</p>
