<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Intern Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Intern. Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Internal Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0918-2918</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1349-7235</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Japanese Society of Internal Medicine</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6995725</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31511487</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.3435-19</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Two Cases of Primary Human Parainfluenza Virus 1 Pneumonia in Which Bronchoalveolar Lavage Fluid Yielded Human Parainfluenza Virus 1</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ishiguro</surname><given-names>Takashi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Yasuhito</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>Kenji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ozawa</surname><given-names>Ryota</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>Yoshihiko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Takayanagi</surname><given-names>Noboru</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>Department of Respiratory Medicine, Saitama Cardiovascular and Respiratory Center, Japan</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>Department of Pathology, Saitama Cardiovascular and Respiratory Center, Japan</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p>Correspondence to Dr.&#x03000;Takashi Ishiguro, <email>ishiguro.takashi@pref.saitama.lg.jp</email></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>9</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>59</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2020 by The Japanese Society of Internal Medicine</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->The Internal Medicine is an Open Access journal distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License. To view the details of this license, please visit (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Two patients, a 76-year-old woman and 66-year-old woman, presented to our hospital with symptoms of lower respiratory tract infection. Both patients showed chest imaging findings of bilateral ground-glass opacities and consolidations. We initially suspected these patients of having influenza-associated pneumonia and cryptogenic organizing pneumonia, respectively, and performed bronchoalveolar lavage, but only human parainfluenza virus-1 infection was detected by multiplex polymerase chain reaction testing. These findings suggest that pneumonia due to human parainfluenza virus-1 should be included in the differential diagnosis of such cases. </p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>human parainfluenza virus</kwd><kwd>viral pneumonia</kwd><kwd>multiplex PCR</kwd><kwd>corticosteroid</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Human parainfluenza viruses (HPIVs) are single-stranded, enveloped RNA viruses belonging to the <italic>Paramyxoviridae</italic> family. Compared with findings in studies of HPIV infection in children, less is known about these infections in adults. In previous studies, 0.2 to 11.5% of hospitalized patients with pneumonia were found to have HPIV infection (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>); however, the characteristics of primary viral pneumonia due to HPIV are not well known. We recently experienced two cases of pneumonia in which HPIV-1 was isolated from bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) fluid and confirmed by a multiplex polymerase chain reaction (PCR) test (Fast Track Diagnostics Resp 21 Kit, Silema, Malta), which detects the following respiratory pathogens: influenza A and B viruses; coronaviruses NL63, 229E, OC43, and HKU1; human parainfluenza viruses 1, 2, 3, and 4; human metapneumovirus A/B; rhinovirus; respiratory syncytial virus A/B; adenovirus; enterovirus; human parechovirus; bocavirus; and <italic>Mycoplasma pneumoniae</italic>. We herein report these cases and review the clinical and radiological features.</p></sec><sec><title>Case Reports</title><sec><title>Case 1</title><p>A 76-year-old woman presented to our hospital with appetite loss and fever in March. On the first day of illness, she initially developed appetite loss, and on the second day, she developed a fever of 37.7&#x02103;. On the fourth day, she developed dyspnea, sore throat, and cough, and on the ffth day, she presented to a local physician who found abnormal shadows on chest X-ray and referred her to our hospital. She had no noteworthy past history. She was a never-smoker and was never exposed to dust. On admission, her vital signs included a body temperature of 37.8&#x02103;, respiratory rate of 20/min, systolic blood pressure of 119 mmHg, and heart rate of 90 beats per min. Chest auscultation showed bilateral coarse crackles. An arterial blood gas analysis under O<sub>2</sub> of 4 L/min by nasal canula showed a pH of 7.49, partial pressure of carbon dioxide in arterial blood (PaCO<sub>2</sub>) of 31.6 Torr, partial pressure of arterial oxygen (PaO<sub>2</sub>) of 70.9 Torr, and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> of 25.3 mmol/L. Laboratory data showed a white blood cell count of 8,100/mm<sup>3</sup> (neutrophils, 78.3%; lymphocytes, 10.7%; eosinophils, 2.4%; basophils, 0.4%; and monocytes, 8.2%), hemoglobin of 12.8 g/dL, platelets of 23.0&#x000d7;10<sup>4</sup>/mm<sup>3</sup>, aspartate aminotransferase (AST) of 56 IU/L, lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) of 253 IU/L, creatinine of 0.6 mg/dL, C-reactive protein (CRP) of 1.7 mg/dL, and procalcitonin of 0.090 ng/mL. Her Krebs von den Lungen-6 (KL-6) level was 1,096 U/mL. Autoantibodies were all negative, and anti-human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) antibody was also negative. Rapid nasopharyngeal or oropharyngeal diagnostic tests for influenza virus and <italic>Mycoplasma pneumoniae</italic> and urinary antigen tests for <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> and <italic>Legionella</italic> spp. were all negative. Chest X-ray showed bilateral ground-glass opacities (GGOs) and consolidations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="g001">Fig. 1a</xref>). Chest computed tomography showed GGOs and consolidations in both lung fields (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="g001">Fig. 1b and c</xref>). Pleural effusion or lymphadenopathy were not found. We performed bronchoscopy and the BAL procedure from the internal segment of the right middle lobe. BAL fluid (85 of 150 mL recovered) showed 3.5&#x000d7;10<sup>5</sup> cells/mL (neutrophils, 1.6%; lymphocytes, 62.0%; macrophages, 32.0%; and eosinophils, 4.4%) but did not show any microorganisms by Gram staining or yield significant pathogens including <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic> or <italic>Legionella</italic> spp. Cytology of the BAL fluid showed no significant findings. A transbronchial lung biopsy specimen showed alveolitis, fibrin exudation, and intraluminal organization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="g002">Fig. 2</xref>). Blood culture was negative. We suspected her of having influenza-associated pneumonia and started ampicillin/sulbactam and peramivir. Her chest shadows gradually improved, and her fever abated on hospital day (HD) 6. Oxygen by nasal canula was stopped on HD 10, and she was discharged on HD 16. Specific antibody titers against <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic>, <italic>C. pneumoniae</italic>, <italic>C. psittaci</italic>, <italic>Legionella</italic> spp., influenza virus, adenovirus, and respiratory syncytial virus in paired sera did not increase, but antibodies against HPIV were not measured. We analyzed the BAL fluid with multiplex PCR, which showed positive results only for HPIV-1. Two years after discharge, she has not relapsed.</p><fig id="g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Chest imaging of Case 1. Chest X-ray showed bilateral ground-glass opacities (GGOs) and consolidations (a). Chest computed tomography (CT) showed bilateral GGOs (b, c).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1349-7235-59-0101-g001"/></fig><fig id="g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Histological findings of Case 2. Transbronchial lung biopsy showed an infiltration of macrophages, neutrophils, and lymphocytes. Exudates of fibrins and mild alveolitis were also found, which indicate alveolitis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1349-7235-59-0101-g002"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Case 2</title><p>A 66-year-old woman presented to our hospital with cough, sputum, and sore throat of 3 weeks duration in May. She initially visited a local physician who detected abnormal shadows on her chest X-ray and then referred her to our hospital. She had not received any antibiotics before presenting to our hospital. She had a history of gastric carcinoma when she was 61 years old and had undergone gastrectomy. Her cancer had not recurred. She was an ex-smoker with Brinkman index of 880, but she had never been exposed to dust. On admission, her vital signs included a body temperature of 36.4&#x02103;, respiratory rate of 22/min, systolic blood pressure of 116 mmHg, and heart rate of 65 beats per min. Chest auscultation showed bilateral coarse crackles. An arterial blood gas analysis under ambient air showed a pH of 7.48, PaCO<sub>2</sub> of 34.9 Torr, PaO<sub>2</sub> of 99.3 Torr, and HCO<sub>3</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> of 25.2 mmol/L. Laboratory data showed a white blood cell count of 5,700/mm<sup>3</sup> (neutrophils, 59.9%; lymphocytes, 31.9%; eosinophils, 3.4%; basophils, 0.4%; and monocytes, 4.4%), hemoglobin of 12.2 g/dL, platelets of 24.6&#x000d7;10<sup>4</sup>/mm<sup>3</sup>, AST of 23 IU/L, LDH of 215 IU/L, creatinine of 0.53 mg/dL, CRP of 0.3 mg/dL, and KL-6 of 328 U/mL. Autoantibodies were negative, as was an anti-HIV antibody test. Rapid nasopharyngeal or oropharyngeal diagnostic tests for influenza virus and <italic>Mycoplasma pneumoniae</italic> and urinary antigen tests for <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic> and <italic>Legionella</italic> spp. were all negative. Chest X-ray showed bilateral consolidation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="g003">Fig. 3a</xref>), and chest computed tomography showed non-segmental and subpleural consolidation bilaterally in the lower lobes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="g003">Fig. 3b</xref>). No centrilobular pulmonary nodules, pleural effusion, or lymphadenopathy was detected. We performed bronchoscopy and BAL from the lateral segment of the right lower lobe. BAL fluid (70 of 150 mL recovered) showed 1.6&#x000d7;10<sup>5</sup> cells/mL (neutrophils, 3.3%; lymphocytes, 35.9%; macrophages, 54.5%; and eosinophils, 6.3%) but did not show any microorganisms by Gram staining or yield significant pathogens including <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic>. Cytology of the BAL fluid also showed no significant findings. We could not obtain adequate specimens for evaluation via transbronchial lung biopsy. We initially suspected her of having cryptogenic organizing pneumonia (COP) and administered prednisolone 20 mg daily. Her chest shadows gradually improved, and she was discharged on HD 9. We analyzed the BAL fluid with multiplex PCR, which showed positive results only for HPIV-1. Specific antibody titers against <italic>M. pneumoniae</italic>, <italic>C. pneumoniae</italic>, <italic>C. psittaci</italic>, <italic>Legionella</italic> spp., influenza virus, adenovirus, and respiratory syncytial virus in paired sera did not increase, but antibodies against HPIV were not measured. We then gradually tapered the prednisolone and stopped it two months after hospital discharge. At four years since her treatment, she has not developed a relapse.</p><fig id="g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Chest imaging of Case 2. Chest X-ray on admission showed nodules in the bilateral lung fields (a). Computed tomography showed diffuse bronchial wall thickening and bilateral ground-glass opacities (b).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1349-7235-59-0101-g003"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>We herein report two immunocompetent patients with primary HPIV-1 pneumonia. One patient required oxygen supplementation on admission, and both patients recovered without the administration of antiviral agents.</p><p>Most HPIV infections in adults cause mild upper respiratory tract symptoms, but the elderly or those with a compromised immune system are associated with progressive disease (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>-<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). HPIV is responsible for 1 to 15% of acute respiratory illnesses in adults. In other studies, 0.2 to 11.5% of hospitalized patients with pneumonia were found to have HPIV infection (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Furthermore, HPIV is present in 7.6% of severe pneumonias, which indicates that HPIV is a frequent pathogen of both non-severe and severe pneumonia (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). However, previous reports that investigated virus infections in patients with pneumonia used nasopharyngeal or oropharyngeal swabs to detect viruses, which raises the possibility of upper respiratory tract infection by HPIV. Furthermore, these studies include mixed viral and bacterial infections, and the clinical characteristics of the immunocompetent patients with primary HPIV pneumonia are not fully known. In our two cases, HPIV was detected in BAL fluid, which indicated the HPIV in our cases to be a pathogen of not the upper airways but the lower respiratory tract and of pneumonia. In addition, BAL fluid did not yield other significant pathogens, nor did specific antibody titers against other pathogens of pneumonia in paired sera increase, which support the diagnosis of primary HPIV infection in our patients.</p><p>Four subtypes of HPIV (HPIV-1, 2, 3, and 4) have been identified, and HPIV-3 is the most prevalent serotype of infections. Among adults hospitalized with pneumonia, HPIV-3 was found in 3.1% of patients (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). The causative virus in our patients was HPIV-1, a subtype found in 2.5% of adult pneumonias (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Although our patients recovered successfully, Tamaki et al. reported a fatal case of viremia due to HPIV-1 in a patient with adult T-cell leukemia-lymphoma treated with mogamulizumab (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), which indicates that HPIV-1 can also be a fatal pathogen in immunocompromised patients.</p><p>Diseases mainly suspected in our patients before identification of HPIV-1 via multiplex PCR testing were primary influenza virus pneumonia and COP, respectively. A previous study reported that viral pneumonia is frequently misdiagnosed as COP (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). In the differentiation of these diseases, sore throat is a more frequent symptom of viral pneumonia than of acute interstitial lung diseases including COP (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), and our patients both had sore throats. However, typical symptoms in adult patients with HPIV infection include fever, rhinorrhea, cough, and a sore throat, which do not clinically distinguish it from other respiratory viruses (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Cunha et al. reported that the clinical presentation of HPIV pneumonia closely mimics H1N1 pneumonia (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Chest CT findings in our patients included bronchial wall thickening, bilateral consolidations, and GGOs, which were compatible with typical CT findings of HPIV pneumonia, e.g., multifocal patchy consolidation with GGOs, and centrilobular nodules with bronchial wall thickening (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>); however, these findings seem nonspecific for HPIV pneumonia. Pokharel et al. reported multinucleated giant cells with organizing pneumonia as findings suggestive of HPIV infection (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), but the sensitivity and specificity of the pathologic findings were not known and these findings were not present in our patients. Thus, it is important to include viral infections in the differential diagnosis and investigate respiratory specimens with viral PCR tests. HPIV causes epidemics during the spring season or a small secondary period of increased activity in the fall, and thus seasonality and local epidemiology may be clues suggestive of HPIV pneumonia.</p><p>Currently, no treatments with proven efficacy are approved for the treatment of HPIV infections. Corticosteroids, generally dexamethasone and budesonide, are associated with fewer clinic visits and admissions for croup and the reduced use of nebulized epinephrine (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). We initially misdiagnosed our patient in Case 2 as having COP and administered corticosteroids. The efficacy of corticosteroid administration in immunocompetent adult patients with HPIV pneumonia is not known. Some data suggest favorable effects on varicella-zoster virus (in combination with acyclovir) and hantavirus (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) and in influenza-associated pneumonia in some clinical settings (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Among 13 previously reported patients with influenza-associated pneumonia, corticosteroids were administered without neuraminidase inhibitors in 6 and were effective (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Among the patients with viral pneumonia due to non-influenza viruses, corticosteroids were administered to 21, 1 of whom did not survive, but were effective in the other 20 patients (95.2%) (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). However, the mainstay of therapy in patients with HPIV infection is considered to be the reduction of immune suppression, which includes corticosteroids use (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Further studies are needed to clarify the significance of corticosteroids as a treatment option for primary HPIV pneumonia in immunocompetent patients. However, much of the available data for the use of antiviral agents in the treatment of HPIV comes from immunocompromised patients. The efficacy of antiviral drugs in immunocompetent adults with HPIV pneumonia has not been fully evaluated, and thus further studies are needed.</p><p>One limitation of this report is that the possibility of detecting viruses from the upper respiratory tracts when using the BAL technique cannot be denied. To avoid this concern and ensure that samples are obtained only from the lower respiratory tract, intubation or use of a protected specimen brush is required.</p><p>In conclusion, we experienced two immunocompetent patients with primary HPIV-1 pneumonia. Primary HPIV pneumonia can resemble influenza-associated pneumonia and COP, and HPIV pneumonia should be included in the differential diagnosis of such cases.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title/><p><bold>The authors state that they have no Conflict of Interest (COI).</bold></p></sec><sec><title>Financial Support</title><p>A part of this study was supported by a Research Fund from Saitama Cardiovascular and Respiratory Center under Grant No. 16ES.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ison</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Parainfluenza virus in the hospitalized adults</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
<volume>65</volume>: <fpage>1570</fpage>-<lpage>1576</lpage>, <year>2017</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28591775</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frans&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heigl</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wolontis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Forsgren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Svedmyr</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Infections with viruses in patients hospitalized with acute respiratory illness, Stockholm 1963-1967</article-title>. <source>Scand J Infect Dis</source>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>-<lpage>136</lpage>, <year>1969</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4329060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jewett</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tollefson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Epidemiology and clinical impact of parainfluenza virus infections in otherwise healthy infants and young children &#x0003c;5 years old</article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis</source>
<volume>175</volume>: <fpage>807</fpage>-<lpage>813</lpage>, <year>1997</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9086134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Respiratory syncytial virus and parainfluenza virus</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<volume>344</volume>: <fpage>1917</fpage>-<lpage>1928</lpage>, <year>2001</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11419430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ison</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Respiratory syncytial viral infections in transplant recipients</article-title>. <source>Antivir Ther</source>
<volume>12</volume> (<issue>4 pt B</issue>): <fpage>627</fpage>-<lpage>638</lpage>, <year>2007</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17944270</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Viral infections in patients with severe pneumonia requiring intensive care unit admission</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>
<volume>186</volume>: <fpage>325</fpage>-<lpage>332</lpage>, <year>2012</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22700859</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falsey</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Viral pneumonia in older adults</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
<volume>42</volume>: <fpage>518</fpage>-<lpage>524</lpage>, <year>2006</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16421796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ison</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Parainfluenza Viruses</article-title>. In: <source>Mandell, Douglas, and Bennett's Principles and Practice of Infectious Diseases</source>. <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>, <year>2014</year>: <fpage>1937</fpage>-<lpage>1941</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ison</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Respiratory syncytial viral infections in transplant recipients</article-title>. <source>Antivir Ther</source>
<volume>12</volume> (<issue>4 pt B</issue>): <fpage>627</fpage>-<lpage>638</lpage>, <year>2007</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17944270</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kinjo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Toyose</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Fatal pneumonia and viremia due to human parainfluenza virus type 1 in a patient with adult T-cell leukemia-lymphoma treated with mogamulizumab</article-title>. <source>J Infect Chemother</source>
<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>820</fpage>-<lpage>823</lpage>, <year>2015</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26231316</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishiguro</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Uozumi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Viral pneumonia requiring differentiation from acute and progressive diffuse interstitial lung diseases</article-title>. <source>Intern Med</source>
<volume>58</volume>: <fpage>3509</fpage>-<lpage>3519</lpage>, <year>2019</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31839671</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Corbett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mickail</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Human parainfluenza virus type 3 (HPIV3) viral community-acquired pneumonia (CAP) mimicking swine influenza (H1N1) during the swine flu pandemic</article-title>. <source>Heart Lung</source>
<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>76</fpage>-<lpage>80</lpage>, <year>2011</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20888645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Do</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Radiographic and CT features of viral pneumonia</article-title>. <source>Radiographics</source>
<volume>38</volume>: <fpage>719</fpage>-<lpage>739</lpage>, <year>2018</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29757717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pokharel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meirickel</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alatassi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Parainfluenza virus-3-induced cytopathic effects on lung tissue and bronchoalveolar lavage fluid in a bone marrow transplant recipient: a case report</article-title>. <source>Diagn Cytopathol</source>
<volume>42</volume>: <fpage>521</fpage>-<lpage>524</lpage>, <year>2014</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23554422</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Gorman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klassen</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Glucocorticoids for croup</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>
<fpage>CD001955</fpage>, <year>2011</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21249651</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yuen</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Medical treatment of viral pneumonia including SARS in immunocompetent adult</article-title>. <source>J Infect</source>
<volume>49</volume>: <fpage>262</fpage>-<lpage>273</lpage>, <year>2004</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15474623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salluh</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>P&#x000f3;voa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Castro-Faria-Neto</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bozza</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bozza</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The role of corticosteroids in severe community-acquired pneumonia: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Crit Care</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>R76</fpage>, <year>2008</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18547407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <collab>National Influenza A(H1N1)pdm09 Clinical Investigation Group of China</collab>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Effect of low-to-moderate-dose corticosteroids on mortality of hospitalized adolescents and adults with influenza A(H1N1)pdm09 viral pneumonia</article-title>. <source>Influenza Other Respir Viruses</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>345</fpage>-<lpage>354</lpage>, <year>2017</year>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28464462</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>