<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P29">Although genetic differentiation and isolation of 
 <italic>E. helvum</italic> in the STP cluster was expected to be reflected epidemiologically, perhaps with an absence of antibodies on these islands due to restricted population sizes, we found that seroprevalences to both viruses were comparable to those on the mainland. These data suggest that: population sizes on each island are sufficient to maintain LBV and henipaviruses and are above the critical community size (CCS) required for persistence (although this concept requires further theoretical exploration for animal populations where birth rates, and hence population sizes, are highly seasonal); sufficient movement may occur between the two islands to maintain a larger epidemiologically connected population; alternative hosts may be involved; or our original assumptions on transmission and persistence may need re-examination (see below). The use of satellite telemetry has been enlightening in other fruit bat species 
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>
 </sup> and would be required to definitively assess movement patterns of bats on these two islands. However, dispersal between São Tomé and Príncipe was suggested by our observation of a single asynchronous birth on Príncipe in the absence of other pregnant or lactating females, but which was contemporaneous with the presence of neonates on São Tomé. The asynchronous Príncipe birth is highly unusual for a species which employs delayed implantation to facilitate a highly synchronised birth pulse. If the two populations are connected via dispersal, the asynchrony in reproductive seasons between São Tomé and Príncipe could facilitate viral persistence by staggered introduction of susceptible individuals, via birth, into the population. Finally, LBV has been detected in bats of several species in Africa, with ranges overlapping that of 
 <italic>E. helvum</italic>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>
 </sup>, but the role that inter-species transmission plays in the maintenance of LBV in its host populations remains a gap in our knowledge. Of all these species, only 
 <italic>Rousettus aegyptiacus</italic>, the Egyptian fruit bat, is present on São Tomé and Príncipe. This is a cave-roosting species, and mixed colonies with 
 <italic>E. helvum</italic> are unlikely although these two species might mix at feeding sites. LBV has been isolated from 
 <italic>R. aegyptiacus</italic> on two occasions (reviewed in 
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>
 </sup>), and seroprevalence levels comparable to those reported in 
 <italic>E. helvum</italic> were detected in Kenya
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>
 </sup>. On São Tomé and Príncipe, 
 <italic>R. aegyptiacus</italic>, or indeed other species, may facilitate the persistence of LBV in 
 <italic>E. helvum</italic>.
</p>
