<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P30">While findings from the CB and STP populations could be consistent with a metapopulation model of persistence, as proposed for HeV in Australia
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>
 </sup> and NiV in Malaysia 
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>
 </sup>, our results from Annobón indicate that this appears unnecessary for the persistence of henipaviruses or LBV in 
 <italic>E. helvum</italic>. On Annobón, 
 <italic>E. helvum</italic> is the only bat species confirmed to be currently present and has a population size of only ~2,500
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>
 </sup>. Surprisingly, and in contrast to findings in other, less-isolated island systems
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>
 </sup>, the henipavirus seroprevalence in the Annobón 
 <italic>E. helvum</italic> population was within the range of that observed in both the CB and the STP populations. Conversely, the Annobón LBV seroprevalence was much lower than in other populations. While evidence of infection with lyssaviruses has been reported in other island bat species (e.g. 
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref>
 </sup>), the bat populations in those studies were either much larger, within flight distance of continental bat populations, and/or hosted multiple sympatric bat species. In Annobón, all LBV seropositive individuals were adult, and further longitudinal studies are required to determine whether LBV is persistently maintained on this island (i.e. the population size is greater than the CCS), or whether these findings represent a single epidemic wave subsequent to introduction of the virus from another population. Unfortunately, deriving a quantitative estimate for the CCS is problematic, particularly for virus-host systems where little information is available regarding host demographics, virus-transmission mechanisms and within-host immune responses
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref>
 </sup>. For both LBV and henipaviruses, important areas of future study include viral diversity and phylogeography, within-host persistence and immunity, incubation periods, and frequency- vs density-dependent transmission.
</p>
