<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Pentoxifylline is a xanthine indicated in some severe cases of alcoholic hepatitis. It also acts on the plasma membrane of red blood cells rendering it more malleable, thus improving blood perfusion. Pentoxifylline exerts several antioxidant and anti-inflammatory activities; it restores glutathione levels, it maintains mitochondrial viability, it inhibits TNF-α production, it preserves vascular endothelial functions. It also improves oxygenation rates and induces a stronger immune response [
 <xref rid="B132-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">132</xref>]. In patients with ALI/ARDS it diminishes the length of hospital stay, the length of ICU stays, the rate of multiple organ dysfunctions, the mechanical ventilation time and the mortality rate [
 <xref rid="B133-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>]. In a randomized controlled study that included 120 newborns with a mean gestational age of 30 weeks, administration of pentoxifylline (5 mg/kg/h iv for 6 h for 6 days) diminished levels of CRP and TNF-α, decreased duration of respiratory support and antibiotic treatment, diminished the need for vasopressors, resulted in a shorter hospitalization time and decreased incidence of metabolic acidosis, thrombocytopenia and disseminated intravascular coagulopathy [
 <xref rid="B134-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>]. However, no difference in short-term morbidity was observed between treated with pentoxifylline and untreated neonates with sepsis [
 <xref rid="B135-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>]. In a meta-analysis involving 6 studies, with the pentoxifylline administration of in septic infants, pentoxifylline was shown to be effective in decreasing length of hospital stay and reducing all-causes of mortality. There was also a significantly diminished mortality in preterm infants, neonates and infants with proven sepsis and in infants with gram-negative sepsis in a subgroup analysis that resulted in the conclusion that pentoxifylline may be a beneficial adjuvant treatment in sepsis [
 <xref rid="B136-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>] and could also be used in COVID-19.
</p>
