<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Substitution of alanine at DE Motif I of either MHV (M-ExoN) or SARS-CoV (S-ExoN) allows recovery of viable mutants with modest replication defects of less than 1 log in peak titer compared to wild type, indicating that functional ExoN activity is not required for CoV replication in culture. Sequencing revealed 12- to 20-fold increases in mutation frequency and up to 14-fold increase in mutation rate than comparably isolated and sequenced wildtype MHV or SARS-CoV (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">
  <bold>Fig. 3</bold>
 </xref>).
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref> Thus, both M-ExoN and S-ExoN have similar high-level mutator phenotypes, from 5 to 20 times greater than that seen with other RNA viruses with described fidelity defects, representing the highest-level mutator phenotype of any RNA virus. The mutator phenotype of M-ExoN was maintained over at least 17 passages, as was the stable replication defect. The mutations accumulated in a linear manner over passage consistent with a stable mutator phenotype. Interestingly, M-ExoN has an estimated mutation rate similar to other known wt RNA viruses, while wt MHV in fact had a mutation rate 15-fold less than other RNA viruses, suggesting that ExoN confers very high replication fidelity on CoV genome replication. This result was consistent with predictions that ExoN may be required for the stability of large RNA genomes.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">59</xref> To test whether these findings could be applied across divergent CoVs, the studies also were performed with S-ExoN in Vero cells with very limited replication cycles and complete genome sequencing (Sanger) of 10 wt and 10 S-ExoN plaque isolates from a single round of infection. The results showed a 21-fold increase in mutational frequency and 14-fold increase in mutation rate across the S-ExoN genomes compared with wt SARS-CoV. For both S-ExoN and M-ExoN, mutations were distributed across the genomes with no statistical bias for regions of the genome, for type of mutation (codon position, transversion, transition) or for synonymous, non-synonymous or non-coding mutations. The analysis was only performed on viable replication-competent populations or plaques, and therefore excluded lethal or profoundly deleterious individual or combination mutations. Thus, the results likely highly under-represent the numbers, types and locations of mutations that would be detected in analysis of total viral genomes from a round of replication that would include both non-viable or minor mutations and defective interfering genomes. When the mutation patterns in the genomes from each of the 10 plaque isolates of S-ExoN were compared, 100 mutations were identified, and both the individual mutations and the “mutation sets” for each genome were unique. Finally, the growth of multiple plaque isolates showed that all plaque isolates had growth patterns with defects compared to wt SARS-CoV but indistinguishable from the initial recovered S-ExoN population or from each other.
</p>
