<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P9">The midgut is encased in a proteoglycan extracellular matrix, termed the basal lamina, which provides protection and support to the epithelium. The pore size of the basal lamina is roughly 10 nm, yet the arboviruses tested in this study are 50–70 nm in size
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>
 </sup>. To determine if blood-feeding alters basal lamina integrity thereby accommodating transit of the larger virus particles, we performed scanning electron microscopy on 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> midguts pre- and post-bloodmeal. The basal lamina of unfed midguts appeared intact and ruffled, while the basal lamina of midguts 24 hpbm (hours post-bloodmeal) were distended and had clear signs of damage (
 <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2a</xref>). By 72 hpbm, the integrity of the basal lamina was reconstituted. Temporal quantification of basal lamina damage was performed using a collagen hybridizing peptide (CHP) binding assay. CHP specifically binds to damaged collagen IV, a major component of the basal lamina (
 <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2b</xref>). Consistent with the SEM data, the CHP binding assay revealed high degrees of binding within 15 mpbm (minutes pbm) and statistically significant elevated levels of binding up to 36 hpbm (
 <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2c</xref>). By 48 hpbm, CHP binding levels had returned to pre-bloodfed levels suggesting basal lamina repair. It has been proposed that bloodmeal-induced basal lamina damage is due to enzymatic degradation 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>
 </sup>. However, our temporal data suggests that basal lamina damage is more likely the result of mechanical distention because it occurs immediately after blood engorgement. To evaluate how bloodmeal-induced microperforations in the midgut basal lamina might affect virus transit, we performed a retrograde infection assay. ZIKV was intrathoracically inoculated into a cohort of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and half were provided a non-infectious bloodmeal 3 days post-inoculation. Nine days post-bloodmeal, mosquito midguts were removed, ZIKV antigen was detected by immunofluorescence, and ZIKV genome equivalents were quantified by RT-qPCR. ZIKV titers were significantly higher in those provided a bloodmeal (
 <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2d</xref>) and clear signs of midgut epithelial infection could be detected in those provided a bloodmeal, whereas ZIKV antigen could not be detected in the epithelium of non-bloodfed individuals (
 <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2e</xref>). Together these data provide a likely mechanism by which arboviruses are able to disseminate from the mosquito midgut and explain how virus already seeded in the midgut can easily escape upon acquisition of a second bloodmeal, while non-infectious bloodmeals provided prior to an infectious bloodmeal fail to enhance escape (
 <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Extended Data 1</xref>).
</p>
