<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0045">According to another article published by Economic Times India, Venous Thromboembolism (VTE) is becoming a leading cause of death along with heart disease, Brain stroke and cancer [
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. It is an under-diagnosed disease among many and most common preventable cause of death in India. VTE leads to long term complications like post-thrombotic syndrome (PTS) and chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension (CTEPH). PTS can cause swelling and pain in the affected leg and CTEPH can cause the right side of the heart to work harder than normal owing to abnormal high-blood pressure. In both the condition, early diagnosis is necessary. It can be achieved by measuring the levels of thrombin or thrombin content in blood serum. The available methodologies to measure thrombin levels require both time and technicians. Recently, Xue et al constructed a Microfluidic paper-based photo-electrochemical device (μPECD) to detect thrombin at point-of-care (POC) [
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. μPECD employs the complete separation of the detection signal and excitation source, thus, providing high sensitivity with a low background signal. The high sensitivity in μPECD can be achieved by the production of large photocurrent signals; which was achieved by incorporating Titanium Dioxide in the paper substrate, due to its good biocompatibility, photoelectric activity, and chemical stability. Again to gain more sensitivity, aptamers were used, instead of antibodies, due to their stability and reusability. To check its real-world feasibility, four human serum samples were tested with the μPECD and ELISA. The results had no significant differences, thus demonstrating the excellent potential practical application of μPECD. However, a year before, Lim et al developed a μPAD for simultaneous detection of multiple cardiac biomarkers, viz. glycogen phosphorylase isoenzyme BB (GPBB) for early diagnosis; and troponin I or T (cTnI or cTnT), creatine kinase-MB (CK−MB) for late diagnosis of Acute Myocardial Infarction (AMI) which is an indicator of Acute Coronary Syndrome (ACS) [
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Early detection of AMI upon onset of heart attack-like situations is crucial for patient survival. It is generally done by observing elevation of ST-segment in Electro-Cardiogram (ECG), which accounts for 23–40% of misdiagnosed myocardial infarction cases. The developed μPAD could give accurate, reliable and quantitative results.
</p>
