<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Enhancement of disease severity may occur if multiple arboviruses synergize and augment each other’s replication in vivo. Chikungunya, dengue, and Zika viruses infect some of the same cells, cause similar disease symptoms, and interfere with immune responses via similar mechanisms [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>–
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. For instance, signal transducer and activator of transcription 1 (STAT1) and STAT2 are two transcription factors involved in interferon signaling, an important antiviral response. Thus, if chikungunya virus interferes with STAT1 nuclear transport and dengue virus blocks STAT2 phosphorylation [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], inhibiting both STAT1 and STAT2 during chikungunya/dengue coinfection may enhance replication of both viruses. As other examples, virus inhibition of 5′-3′ exoribonuclease 1 (XRN1), a cellular exonuclease that degrades viral RNA, may promote replication of a flavivirus (e.g., dengue and Zika virus) coinfecting the same cell [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], and increased endothelial permeability during dengue virus infection may alter tissue tropism of coinfecting viruses [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Even if coinfecting viruses do not enhance each other’s replication, coinfection may still result in increased disease severity due to exacerbated immune responses. There are some reports of severe disease after coinfection, but these are currently based only on individual case reports [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>–
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] or small-scale cohort studies [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>–
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]—there are no controlled animal experiments or larger cohort studies providing evidence for enhanced disease severity. Acevedo and colleagues [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], for instance, reported three patients with Guillain-Barre syndrome who were all coinfected with multiple arboviruses, including Zika virus. While these findings are concerning, none of the studies are powered to detect even fairly substantial changes in clinical presentation.
</p>
