<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>All previous scenarios imply that there is a consequential interaction between multiple arboviruses infecting the same person. It is possible, however, that coinfecting viruses can replicate within the host as if no other virus was present and that there is no significant impact on virus replication or clinical presentation—i.e., the “neutral” hypothesis. We compiled data from reports of human coinfections over the last 50 years and the clinical presentation associated with them (
 <bold>
  <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pbio.3000130.s001">S1 Table</xref>
 </bold>) [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>–
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>–
 <xref rid="pbio.3000130.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. While severe disease manifestations occurred rarely, the majority of cases were comparable to single infections with a febrile illness, arthralgia, myalgia, and rash, most of which cleared within a week or two. Some of the more severe disease manifestations also occur in patients with single infections, such as hemorrhagic fever, encephalitis, or persistent joint pain. To directly compare single and coinfections, we compiled data from those publications that provided sufficient clinical information for both (
 <bold>
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.3000130.g003">Fig 3A</xref>
 </bold>). While these data include only a relatively small number of coinfections, disease severity was comparable between single and coinfections, with the majority of cases presenting with a dengue-like febrile illness. This could imply that coinfections either 1) have no virological or clinical impact or 2) that one virus outcompeted the other, resulting in symptoms consistent with single infection.
</p>
