<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Nucleic acids and viral hepatitis-associated proteins have been identified in EVs from the sera of patients with chronic viral infections [
 <xref rid="B35-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Long non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs) can affect the regulation of gene expression and have an impact on many different cellular processes. Xu et al. demonstrated significantly higher levels of exosomal HNRNPH1 in HBV-associated HCC patients with vascular invasion and lymph node metastasis than those in non-HCC patients [
 <xref rid="B36-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. A positive correlation among lncRNA-HULC, lncRNA-HEIH, and hepatitis B X-interacting protein (HBXIP) indicated that hepatitis B X protein (HBx) may alter lncRNA expression, which in turn may promote HCC development [
 <xref rid="B37-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. lncRNA-HULC modulates microRNA-539 (miR-539), which downregulates APOBEC3B, thereby promoting HBV replication [
 <xref rid="B38-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Both serum and exosomal lncRNA-HEIH expression levels increase in HCV-related HCC patients, whereas serum lncRNA-HEIH expression levels are significantly lower than exosomal lncRNA-HEIH expression levels in CHC patients [
 <xref rid="B39-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. These data suggest that lncRNA is a potential liquid biotarget for HBV-related HCC. MHC class I chain-related A (MICA) is another HCV-associated liquid biopsy target. High levels of soluble MICA (sMICA) have been identified in the sera of HCV-induced HCC patients bearing the G allele as opposed to the A allele as a result of the single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) rs2596538 [
 <xref rid="B40-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. There was an increase in the risk of liver fibrosis in the CHC patients with the G allele, whereas the levels of sMICA were elevated in the HCV-associated HCC patients following viral eradication [
 <xref rid="B41-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. A genome-wide association study (GWAS) demonstrated that elevated serum levels of MICA and soluble MICA (sMICA)—encoded by the G allele resulting from SNP rs2596542—increased the risk of HBV-associated HCC [
 <xref rid="B43-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].
</p>
