<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>RRV is maintained in nature within an enzootic cycle between vertebrate hosts, mainly macropod marsupials, and mosquito vectors [
 <xref rid="B309-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">309</xref>,
 <xref rid="B311-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">311</xref>]. Despite the key role of marsupials, the ecology of RRV is actually quite complex, since there is a large number of other potential vertebrate hosts [
 <xref rid="B309-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">309</xref>,
 <xref rid="B314-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">314</xref>], such as non-macropod marsupials, bats, and horses [
 <xref rid="B318-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">318</xref>]. Additionally, evidence suggests that human–mosquito–human transmission may occur as well, as outbreaks have occurred in regions where suitable nonhuman vertebrate hosts are absent [
 <xref rid="B309-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">309</xref>,
 <xref rid="B319-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">319</xref>,
 <xref rid="B320-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">320</xref>]. The RRV was first isolated in 1959, Australia, from a pool of female 
 <italic>Ae. vigilax</italic> mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="B321-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">321</xref>]. Notably, 
 <italic>Ae. vigilax</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae. camptorhynchus</italic> are the most important vectors in coastal regions, while the principal vectors in the inland are 
 <italic>Cx. annulirostris</italic> and 
 <italic>Coquillettidia linealis</italic> [
 <xref rid="B318-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">318</xref>,
 <xref rid="B322-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">322</xref>]. The virus has also been isolated from several other 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> species and other genera as well, with some species proven to be able to transmit RRV by vector competence studies [
 <xref rid="B317-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">317</xref>,
 <xref rid="B318-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">318</xref>]. Furthermore, it seems that other species may play a role of transmission in specific regions, given the diverse range of vector habitats in these locations [
 <xref rid="B318-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">318</xref>,
 <xref rid="B323-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">323</xref>]. Therefore, there is a singular complexity in the ecological transmission of RRV.
</p>
