<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Building upon earlier work on H5 viruses that caused outbreaks in Korea in 2013–2014, two isolates from the 2016–2017 winter season were evaluated for their zoonotic potential [
 <xref rid="B103-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. Specifically, A/environment/Korea/W541/2016 (H5N6) and A/common teal/Korea/W555/2017 (H5N8) were studied as representative H5N6 and H5N8 strains. In NHBE cells, the A/environment/Korea/W541/2016 (H5N6) virus grew to significantly higher titers compared to a 2009 pandemic H1N1 strain, while the A/common teal/Korea/W555/2017 (H5N8) virus had reduced titers at 24 h but achieved comparable titers at 48 and 72 h post-infection. In human lung explants, A/environment/Korea/W541/2016 (H5N6) grew to similar titers as the H1N1 virus, while A/common teal/Korea/W555/2017 (H5N8) displayed reduced growth. In ferrets, animals infected with the A/environment/Korea/W541/2016 (H5N6) virus displayed moderate clinical signs and had nasal wash titers of 10
 <sup>5.3</sup> and 10
 <sup>4.8</sup> EID50/mL on days 3 and 5, respectively. In contrast, A/common teal/Korea/W555/2017 (H5N8) infected animals had minimal clinical illness and had reduced nasal wash titers between 10
 <sup>2</sup> and 10
 <sup>3.8</sup> EID/mL on day 3 and no viral shedding on day 5. In a separate experiment, infected ferrets were paired with a single direct contact and a single respiratory contact animal. Neither virus transmitted to respiratory contacts, and none of the direct contact animals became infected with A/common teal/Korea/W555/2017 (H5N8); however, three of three direct contact animals shed the A/environment/Korea/W541/2016 (H5N6) virus. Given the propensity for limited transmission, receptor-binding studies were performed and revealed that both viruses had a strong α2,3-SA acid preference, although low-level binding to α2,6-SAs was also observed [
 <xref rid="B103-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]. In response to case reports of human infections with H5N6 viruses in China, an additional Korean isolate A/mandarin duck/Korea/K16-187-3/2016 (H5N6) was also evaluated in the ferrets. In virus-infected animals, low titers were recovered in the nasal washes (i.e., 10
 <sup>1.7–2.3</sup> EID
 <sub>50</sub>/mL) and the animals did not display overt clinical signs. In transmission studies, neither direct contact or respiratory contact animals shed virus or seroconverted, indicating the virus failed to transmit [
 <xref rid="B104-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. Together, these studies demonstrate that the GsGd clade 2.3.4.4 viruses isolated in Korea, North America, and Europe have limited ability to replicate and transmit in mammals.
</p>
