<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0110">The pathogenicity of SeACoV in pigs remains controversial. Initially, it was believed that SeACoV causes enteric disease with a mortality rate over 35 % in piglets less than 10 days old (
 <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2018b</xref>). Its clinical symptoms were similar to PEDV and TGEV, including severe diarrhea, vomiting, and dehydration (
 <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">Pan et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2018b</xref>). Although the viruses isolated from different groups were able to infect piglets by the oral route, they each caused mild or severe diarrhea symptom (
 <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">Pan et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2018b</xref>). In a challenge experiment on 4-day-old piglets using a cell culture strain GDS04-P12, clinical signs developed gradually and the virus was shed in the feces throughout the experimental period (
 <xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2019</xref>). All piglets (n = 10) challenged with the virus died from 5 to 12 days post-infection (dpi). Examination of the affected pigs revealed that the small intestine had accumulated a large amount of yellow liquid in the colon and the cecum, the intestine was inflated, and the intestinal wall was thin and transparent. SeACoV antigen was detected in the cytoplasm of the villous enterocytes of the challenged piglets by immunohistochemical analysis. Histopathology revealed that the intestinal villi of the duodenum, jejunum, and other places had varying degrees of atrophy, and the intestinal epithelium also showed necrosis (
 <xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2019</xref>). These results indicated that GDS04-P12 is highly pathogenic to the newborn piglets. A pathogenesis study using the cell culture strain CN/GDWT/2017 from the group that designated the virus “SADS-CoV” also showed high mortality (3/6) in the inoculated 3-day-old piglets (
 <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2018b</xref>). However, immunohistochemical analysis displayed only a few jejunal epithelial cells that were stained with viral antigen in challenged piglets, which may not be in line with the 50 % mortality (
 <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2018b</xref>). We have conducted a couple of experimental infection of neonatal piglets with a moderate or high dose of purified SeACoV (isolate CH/GD-01/2017), and they resulted only in mild-moderate diarrheal signs or subclinical infection compared to the first outbreaks in pig herds [(
 <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">Pan et al., 2017</xref>) and unpublished data], implying a lower pathogenicity of SeACoV.
</p>
