<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is known that SARS patients develop strong neutralizing antibody responses against the virus [
 <xref rid="B30-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Indeed, a meta-analysis demonstrated significant reduction in mortality and viral load, thus effectiveness of convalescent plasma (CP) immunotherapy for the treatment of SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV [
 <xref rid="B31-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In principle, this may represent a tool to increase protection against CoVs by binding S-proteins immunogenic parts thus neutralizing their function. In the course of the present COVID-19 pandemic, recent attempts suggest that, indeed, early administration of CP from recovered patients at high titers of neutralizing antibodies can likely reduce the viral load and disease mortality. CP transfusion may affect COVID-19 pathogenesis through direct neutralization of the virus, controlling a cytokine storm, Th1/Th17, and complement cascade activation and immunomodulating the hypercoagulable state [
 <xref rid="B32-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In the study by Duan et al. (2020) [
 <xref rid="B34-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], one dose of 200 mL of CP with neutralizing antibody titers above 1:640 was administered to 10 patients. In addition, patients received maximal supportive care and anti-viral agents. In this initial trial, the primary endpoint was to verify safety of CP infusion; the second endpoint was improvement of clinical symptoms and laboratory parameters within 3 days after treatment. No severe side effects were reported. No specific virus was detected in CP before transfusion; indeed, plasma was subjected to methylene blue photochemistry to inactivate residual viral particles. Patients did not develop transfusion-related lung damage. Further, there was no antibody-dependent infection enhancement that may occur when subneutralizing concentrations of antibodies are transfused through suppression of innate mechanism of defense with the consequence of intracellular growth of the virus [
 <xref rid="B35-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Small group studies were also reported from Chinese clinical Centers [
 <xref rid="B36-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. An investigation on 25 patients recruited at the University of Texas (Houston, TX, USA) confirmed CP safety; however, it underlined the difficulty of analyzing data due to confounding variables of other treatment regimens, such as antivirals and anti-inflammatories administration [
 <xref rid="B39-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Nevertheless, from the initial studies of CP transfusion, optimal dosing, timing and clinical benefits of this approach will require further evaluation in larger well-controlled trials. Investigations have been undertaken to explore the use of neutralizing human monoclonal antibodies against CoV2 generated from B cells of convalescent patients (NCT04354766). One ongoing clinical trial is recruiting patients in Shanghai (China), but, to our knowledge, no relevant results were announced yet (NCT04292340) for anti-SARS-CoV2 CP [
 <xref rid="B37-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In another trial, carried out in China by recruiting patients with severe or life-threatening COVID-19 syndrome from 7 medical centers, CP therapy added to standard treatment did not significantly improve timing to clinical amelioration within 28 days compared to standard treatment. Interpretation of results may have been affected by early termination of the trials originally recruiting 103 participants [
 <xref rid="B40-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. A trial was recently started at the Columbia University Irving Medical Center in New York (NCT04359810, New York, NY, USA) to assess CP efficacy on a cohort of 129 enrolled patients [
 <xref rid="B41-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. An interventional proof of concept single-arm trial to produce hyperimmune plasma from convalescent donors to be administered to critical COVID-19 patients was started in Italy in March 2020 (NCT04321421), with the limited recruitment of 43 patients [
 <xref rid="B42-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. On a general ground, the use of human products, such as human immunoglobulin administration, is, however, associated with increased risk of same day thrombotic events [
 <xref rid="B32-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Certainly, the use of CP with high neutralizing antibody titers should follow precise ethical and controlled measures of selection, especially in absence of knowledge of the basic biology of COVID-19, including its variability and mutation capacity [
 <xref rid="B43-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].
</p>
