<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This is a well-developed and effective but potentially underused approach in vector control. It consists of treating the surfaces upon which common mosquitoes rest inside houses with a long-lasting insecticide. The most affected species among the endophilic species will be 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>, which rests mainly indoors, feeds on humans, and is thus more likely to be reached by IRS than by space sprays [
 <xref rid="B69-pathogens-09-00310" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. IRS has some limitations and imperfections, such as the need for specialised training, which is time consuming in terms of obtaining public acceptance within a region. It does not prevent people from being bitten but above all, it must be adapted to several factors specific to a region, such as insecticide resistance, which is expensive and takes several years [
 <xref rid="B70-pathogens-09-00310" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. IRS has had a considerable impact on the mortality of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>, and used alone [
 <xref rid="B71-pathogens-09-00310" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>] or in combination with larval control [
 <xref rid="B72-pathogens-09-00310" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>] contributed to the elimination of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> in Guyana and the Cayman Islands, respectively [
 <xref rid="B70-pathogens-09-00310" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. In 2006, the WHO reaffirmed the importance of IRS for malaria transmission control, which was supported by the President’s Malaria Initiative (PMI) in 2012 [
 <xref rid="B73-pathogens-09-00310" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Malaria eradication campaigns using IRS in the Mediterranean region seem to have led to the elimination of malaria [
 <xref rid="B74-pathogens-09-00310" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. New formulations could last between five and eight months [
 <xref rid="B70-pathogens-09-00310" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. The potential evolution of insecticide resistance in the vector to pyrethroids can be controlled using alternative formulations, such as bendiocarb [
 <xref rid="B75-pathogens-09-00310" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] and other new IRS formulations [
 <xref rid="B67-pathogens-09-00310" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-pathogens-09-00310" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="B76-pathogens-09-00310" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>,
 <xref rid="B77-pathogens-09-00310" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Good insecticide management is based on an alternation of formulations to combat the evolution of resistance, which may maintain efficacy over time, especially for location-specific interventions [
 <xref rid="B70-pathogens-09-00310" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>].
</p>
