<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our monthly visits from 1988 to 2018 were homogeneous; therefore, it was possible to compare the relative monthly prevalence of clinical myxomatosis. In relation to epidemics between November and March, when temperatures were low, Fenner and Ratcliffe [
 <xref rid="B14-animals-09-00780" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] described the favorable effect of cold weather, as MYXV is thermolabile; “the disease is less severe and lethal at higher temperatures”. However, “”ambient temperature has no direct effect on the course of RHD in infected rabbits” [
 <xref rid="B44-animals-09-00780" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. In winter, MYXV causing atypical myxomatosis is airborne, whether insects are present or not; however, evidently, they contribute to the spread of the disease in summer and autumn. We advised producers to heat their doe barns to prevent cold weather from weakening their immune system, in accordance with Moberg [
 <xref rid="B57-animals-09-00780" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Our results suggest that myxomatosis occurrence in domestic rabbits is similar to that observed in wild rabbits by Ross et al., [
 <xref rid="B58-animals-09-00780" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] during 1971–1978. Arthur and Louzis [
 <xref rid="B59-animals-09-00780" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] studied classic myxomatosis during 1953–1965, and the atypical form since 1979; in the first case, there were more epidemics in August–October, whereas in the second, they also occurred in winter. In Spain, according to Villafuerte et al [
 <xref rid="B60-animals-09-00780" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] from 2003 to 2009 there was a higher occurrence of myxomatosis in wild rabbits during summer and autumn. Some years, there were outbreaks during winter [
 <xref rid="B61-animals-09-00780" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>], depending on the rainfall and the availability of food, the reproductive activity and the presence of susceptible young rabbits [
 <xref rid="B62-animals-09-00780" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>].
</p>
