<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Experimental results suggest that most of the pathogenic and commensal bacteria in the nasopharynx may directly or indirectly interfere with influenza infection during host colonization or infection (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="ppat.1006770.t001">Table 1</xref>). The best-studied influenza–bacteria interaction is with 
 <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Influenza is thought to increase bacterial adherence and facilitate the progression from carriage to severe disease [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], although evidence from population studies is not so clear-cut [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Influenza was also shown to impair methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) clearance in coinfected mice, thereby increasing their susceptibility to MRSA infection [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Similarly, in mice, increased severity of 
 <italic>H</italic>. 
 <italic>influenzae</italic> induced by influenza was suggested, based on experiments of sequential infection with sublethal influenza then 
 <italic>H</italic>. 
 <italic>influenzae</italic> doses [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Notably, ecological studies revealed a positive association between influenza and 
 <italic>Neisseria meningitidis</italic> incidence [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] and in vitro studies suggested that direct interaction between influenza A neuraminidase and the 
 <italic>N</italic>. 
 <italic>meningitidis</italic> capsule enhanced bacterial adhesion to cultured epithelial cells [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Lastly, in patients with pulmonary tuberculosis, there is evidence of increased risk of severe outcomes on influenza infection [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. This finding was supported by experiments in mice [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] that demonstrated that 
 <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> and influenza coinfected mice mounted weaker immune responses specific to 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>bovis</italic> Bacillus Calmette–Guerin (BCG) in the lungs compared with mice infected with BCG alone.
</p>
