<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<boxed-text>
 <label>Boxed Example 3 Improving Influenza Vaccination Coverage in Health Care Workers (Source: Kimura et al., 2005)</label>
 <p>
  <bold>Problem:</bold> In 2003, influenza vaccination coverage was only 40% among health care workers (HCW). HCW can transmit influenza to patients. CMS (
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7_7">2007</xref>) is mandating infection prevention and control programs that include both patient and employee populations.
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>Methods:</bold> A controlled study in 70 southern California nursing homes during the 2002–2003 influenza season. Nursing homes were selected by convenience sample and were assigned to one of four groups: (1) group A (
  <italic>n</italic> = 25), which conducted no interventions; (2) group B (
  <italic>n</italic> = 15), which conducted an educational campaign; (3) group C (
  <italic>n</italic> = 15), which held [influenza] Vaccine Days; and (4) group D (
  <italic>n</italic> = 15), which conducted both an educational campaign and held Vaccine Days.
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>Data and Results:</bold> The control group (group A) had 27% vaccination coverage. Vaccine Days when implemented in combination with the educational campaign (group D) had 53% coverage; adjusted odds ratio [AOR] = 3.54; 95% confidence interval [CI] = 2.17–5.72) and when implemented alone (group C) (45%; AOR = 2.28; CI = 1.30–3.98). The educational campaign alone (group B) had a vaccination coverage of 34% (AOR = 1.31; CI = 0.76–2.25).
 </p>
 <p>
  <bold>Managerial Epidemiologic Interpretation:</bold> The control group in an intervention study is the referent. The higher AOR for the educational campaign alone was not significantly different from the control group because the 95% CI contained 1.0. The Vaccine Days intervention alone was effective in increasing the prevalence of vaccination coverage because the CI lower limit (1.30) was greater than 1.0. Vaccine days offered in combination with an educational campaign yielded a significantly higher coverage than the control group (AOR = 3.54) and was the most effective strategy. Considering the national prevalence of health care worker (HCW) influenza vaccination coverage rate is 40% in 2003, a multi-component intervention will be necessary to increase the rate in HCWs.
 </p>
</boxed-text>
