<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Both contact and airborne transmission contribute to the spread of an influenza virus in humans [
 <xref rid="B39-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. In animal models, contact transmission is considered a less stringent indicator of human-to-human transmission [
 <xref rid="B41-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]; however, all pandemic influenza viruses transmit via contact in ferrets and guinea pigs [
 <xref rid="B30-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], and this mode of transmission in animal models most likely represents a degree of mammalian adaptation. To evaluate direct contact or airborne transmission, a donor ferret is typically inoculated with a relatively high dose of virus (i.e., 10
 <sup>6</sup> infectious units) and contact animals are introduced 24 h later. To study contact transmission, a naïve animal is co-housed in the same cage with the infected donor, while for airborne transmission, the donor and contact animals are placed in a modified cage that allows the animals to share the same air space but prevents direct physical contact. To assess transmission to contact animals, nasal wash samples or swabs are collected and these samples are titrated on Madin–Darby Canine Kidney Epithelial (MDCK) cells. As a secondary method to assess transmission, serological samples from contact animals are also evaluated for seroconversion. Most transmission studies are performed using a limited number of animals (i.e., three or four pairs), thus the assessment of transmission is considered a qualitative measurement [
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-viruses-10-00461" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].
</p>
