<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Due to differences in recombination patterns and synteny, we used different methods for phylogenetic analyses of the full dataset and of the ST-192 isolates only. For the full dataset, where we expected high levels of recombination, large differences in gene content and relatively low synteny, we used an alignment of concatenated alleles from the PubMLST 
 <italic>
  <named-content content-type="species">
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1601/nm.1926" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">N. meningitidis</ext-link>
  </named-content>
 </italic> core genome multilocus sequence typing (MLST) v1.0 scheme. Missing alleles were filled with gap characters. Out of the 1605 loci included in this scheme, only 42 (2.6 %) were present in &lt;95 % of isolates. For the subset of ST-192 genomes, where we expected a more clonal relation, we used the program parsnp v1.2 [
 <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] to construct a whole-genome alignment from 
 <italic>de novo</italic> assembled contigs, and the circularized genome of strain AR00441 was used as a reference. In this latter case, we filled all non-core regions with ambiguous (‘N’) sequence. Gubbins version 2.3.4 [
 <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] with default parameters was used to identify and exclude recombination tracts from the whole-genome alignments prior to phylogenetic analyses. As outgroups in this analysis, we used 
 <italic>
  <named-content content-type="species">
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.1601/nm.1924" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">N. lactamica</ext-link>
  </named-content>
 </italic> (AR01252_T8 – BIGS ID no. 44922) for the full dataset and OL24904 (BIGS ID no. 56376) for the ST-192 subset. Within ST-192, we gathered the length of each recombination block from the Gubbins output GFF file. Phylogenetic trees were recreated using the program iq-tree version 1.6.7 [
 <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] with 1000 bootstraps of the ultrafast bootstrap algorithm [
 <xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The evolutionary model used was the generalized time-reversible model with four gamma categories, as favoured by the program bModelTest [
 <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Phandango [
 <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] was used for visualization of inferred recombination hotspots. In this analysis, we additionally included the ribosomal MLST (rMLST) score as metadata.
</p>
