<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In 2010, Neumann et al. reported the first successful prevention of HCV reinfection and SVR 24 (sustained virological response in 24 weeks after treatment) after liver transplantation by the post-transplant administration of intravenous Legalon
 <sup>®</sup> SIL monotherapy for 14 days in a genotype 3a patient who was non-responsive to Peg-IFN+RBV therapy [
 <xref rid="B46-molecules-24-01552" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The next year, Beinhardt et al. reported another IFN non-responder with mixed genotype 1a/4 infection achieving SVR 20 after liver transplantation by the administration of intravenous Legalon
 <sup>®</sup> SIL monotherapy starting from 15 days pre-transplant to 25 days post-transplant [
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-24-01552" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Both groups suggested in their studies that relatively low viral load before transplantation could be a good prognostic factor [
 <xref rid="B46-molecules-24-01552" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-molecules-24-01552" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Concordant with the viral load observation, Eurich et al. further reported a case series of four Peg-IFN+RBV non-responders who started intravenous Legalon
 <sup>®</sup> SIL treatment months after liver transplant [
 <xref rid="B48-molecules-24-01552" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. The patient who had the lowest viral load eliminated the virus during the first week of the 14-day Legalon
 <sup>®</sup> SIL monotherapy, while the patient who had the second lowest viral load eliminated the virus under Peg-IFN+RBV therapy 2 months later. Both patients achieved SVR 24. As for the other two patients with higher initial viral load, 2.3 and 2.9 logs of viral load drop, respectively, were observed during the first 10 days of Legalon
 <sup>®</sup> SIL administration, despite the rebounding viremia in the follow-up Peg-IFN+RBV therapy. On the other hand, Aghemo et al. presented a genotype 2a patient who started intravenous Legalon
 <sup>®</sup> SIL monotherapy 24 h pre-transplant but failed to eliminate graft reinfection [
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-24-01552" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The authors proposed that this may be a result of genotype difference, but did not discuss about the relatively high viral load (more than 10
 <sup>6</sup> IU/mL) before treatment of this patient [
 <xref rid="B49-molecules-24-01552" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. In contrast, Knapstein et al. reported a genotype 3 Peg-IFN+RBV non-responder who also had pre-treatment viral load of more than 10
 <sup>6</sup> IU/mL but successfully treated with Peg-IFN+RBV and intravenous Legalon
 <sup>®</sup> SIL combination therapy at the post-transplant stage and achieved SVR 24 [
 <xref rid="B50-molecules-24-01552" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].
</p>
