<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Analyses using only laboratory confirmed cases underestimates the true burden of infection in the population where the majority are likely to be sub-clinical [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008110.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008110.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] and will be additionally confounded by both the vagaries of doctors’ demands for analyses to be performed and unequal access to health care facilities depending on the subdivision. This is especially evident in the Tuamotu-Gambier subdivision, from where there were few analyses performed and low confirmed dengue rates, but which was subsequently shown to have the same sero-prevalence rates as the other subdivisions [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008110.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. An additional confounding factor in this study was that increasingly sensitive diagnostic techniques were used over time, thus making comparisons among epidemics untenable. However, insofar as this work analysed the data, for the most part, within time-period and across islands, temporal variation in diagnostic sensitivity should not alter our conclusions significantly. One feature not considered in this present study was the association of dengue incidence with climate. In French Polynesia, climate is suitable for dengue transmission year round with little variation in ambient temperature and the epidemics observed did not coincide with any major El Niño-Southern Oscillation events. However, the different nature of the islands, high islands as compared to atolls, could generate variability in local climate, especially rainfall and hence suitability for dengue transmission. Such island specific variation could differentially impact the different mosquito species that occur in the larger islands (
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>) compared to the smaller outer islands (
 <italic>Aedes polynesiensis</italic>)[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008110.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008110.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Both are capable of transmitting virus but have different ecologies and thus may be differentially affected by variation in climatic factors. With suitable environmental data at an island level, if available, further analysis would be of interest.
</p>
