<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="Tab1">
 <label>Table 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>The cardiovascular risks of potential anti-COVID-19 drugs</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th>Drugs</th>
    <th>Pharmacologic mechanism</th>
    <th>Evidences of anti-COVID-19</th>
    <th>FDA approved Indications</th>
    <th>Clinical trials for COVID-19
     <sup>#</sup>
    </th>
    <th>CV drug interactions</th>
    <th>Cardiovascular risks</th>
    <th>Other organ toxicity</th>
    <th>Ref.</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="9">Anti-viral drugs</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>  Remdesivir</td>
    <td>A nucleotide prodrug, transforming to adenosine analogue, causing RNA pre-mature termination and inhibiting viral replication</td>
    <td>• Reducing viral copy numbers in SARS-CoV-2 and binding to the active site on RNA polymerase of SARS-CoV-2</td>
    <td>RSV, Junin virus, Nipah virus, Hendra virus, and research on Ebola virus</td>
    <td>
     <p>NCT04302766</p>
     <p>NCT04280705</p>
     <p>• NCT04292730; NCT04292899*</p>
    </td>
    <td>A substrate of CYP2C8, CYP2D6, CYP3A4, and transporters OATP1B1 and P-gp but due to rapid distribution, metabolism and clearance, drug interaction is minimal.</td>
    <td>CV toxicity has yet to be reported</td>
    <td>Liver toxicity (rare)</td>
    <td>14, 15, 17, 73</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>  Atazanavir</td>
    <td>An analog of the peptide chain substrate binding to the active site HIV protease and preventing the pro-form of viral proteins cleaving into the working form.</td>
    <td>Binding to SARS-CoV-2 3C-like proteinase (3CLpro); Atazanavir inhibits SARS-CoV-2 replication and pro-inflammatory cytokine in vitro experiments</td>
    <td>HIV</td>
    <td>Not yet lunched</td>
    <td>An inhibitor of CYP3A4, UGT1A1, CYP2C8, and OATP1B1</td>
    <td>Dose-dependent PR and QTc prolongations</td>
    <td>Liver toxicity</td>
    <td>21–24</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>  Ritonavir/lopinavir</td>
    <td>A nucleoside analogue 
     <italic>and</italic> protease inhibitor of HIV; SARS, MERS?
    </td>
    <td>Binding to SARS-CoV-23C-like proteinase (3CLpro); Though no significant benefits in clinical improvement and mortality in a randomized clinical trial (ChiCTR2000029308)</td>
    <td>HPV; HIV</td>
    <td>
     <p>NCT04252885</p>
     <p>NCT04275388</p>
     <p>NCT04276688</p>
     <p>NCT04286503</p>
     <p>NCT02845843</p>
     <p>NCT04307693</p>
     <p>NCT04261907</p>
     <p>NCT04295551</p>
     <p>NCT00578825</p>
    </td>
    <td>Inhibitors of CYP3A and drug transporters such as P-gp, BCRP, and OATP1B1</td>
    <td>PR/QTc prolongation; rare reports of 2nd or 3rd degree AVB; lopinavir/ritonavir; decreased serum concentrations of clopidogrel and prasugrel but increase statins, ticagrelor, rivaroxaban, and apixaban</td>
    <td>Liver toxicity, pancreatitis, GI upset, neurotoxicity</td>
    <td>22, 26, 28, 29, 33, 42, 73</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>  Favipiravir</td>
    <td>A selective inhibition of viral RNA-dependent RNA polymerase</td>
    <td>Suppressing viral RNA-dependent RNA polymerase of SARS-CoV-2; in vitro?</td>
    <td>Influenza viruses, West Nile virus, yellow fever virus, foot-and-mouth disease virus</td>
    <td>
     <p>NCT04303299 (THDMS-COVID-19); NCT04310228;</p>
     <p>ChiCTR2000029600 (plus IFN-α)</p>
    </td>
    <td>Only a weak inhibitor of CYPs 1A2, 2C9, 2C19, 2D6, 2E1, and 3A4</td>
    <td>Minimal clinically significant drug interactions</td>
    <td>Not reported</td>
    <td>34–38</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>  Ribavirin</td>
    <td>A nucleoside inhibitor, stopping viral RNA synthesis and mRNA capping</td>
    <td>Binding to the active site on RNA polymerase on SARS-CoV-2; in vitro?</td>
    <td>HCV, RSV and some viral hemorrhagic fevers</td>
    <td>NCT04276688</td>
    <td>No report of cytochrome P450 enzyme mediated metabolism of ribavirin.</td>
    <td>Ribavirin has no characterized direct CV toxicity; ribavirin has variable effects on warfarin dosing</td>
    <td>Liver toxicity, hematologic disorder</td>
    <td>40, 43, 44</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>  Ivermectin</td>
    <td>An influx of Cl− ions through the cell membrane of invertebrates by activation of specific ivermectin-sensitive ion channels.</td>
    <td>Inhibiting the nuclear transport activity of SARS-CoV-2; currently on in vitro study</td>
    <td>Head lice, scabies, strongyloidiasis, trichuriasis, ascariasis, and lymphatic filariasis</td>
    <td>Not yet lunched</td>
    <td>An inducer of several cytochrome P450 isoenzymes, including CYP1A, 2B, and 3A</td>
    <td>Tachycardia, orthostatic hypotension, PR interval prolongation</td>
    <td>Dermatitis, GI upset</td>
    <td>4, 45–51</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="9">Immune-modulating drugs</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>  Chloroquine/hydroxychloroquine (HCQ)</td>
    <td>Sequestering protons in lysosomes to increase the intracellular pH; interfering with the glycosylation of its cellular receptor, ACE2; reduce the viral copy number of SARS-CoV-2.</td>
    <td>Reducing viral copy numbers in SARS-CoV-2; Under debates between China and France?</td>
    <td>Anti-malaria. Treatment of rheumatoid arthritis, lupus, and porphyria cutanea tarda</td>
    <td>
     <p>NCT04286503</p>
     <p>NCT04303507</p>
     <p>NCT04307693</p>
     <p>NCT04261517</p>
     <p>NCT04303299</p>
     <p>NCT04334512</p>
     <p>More than 50 ongoing trials combined with Zithromax, vitamin, zinc</p>
    </td>
    <td>Metabolism by CYPs 2C8, 3A4 and 2D6 (increased concentration beta-blockers)</td>
    <td>
     <p>Intermediate-to-delayed cardiotoxicity</p>
     <p>1. Direct: restrictive or dilated cardiomyopathy</p>
     <p>2. Altered conduction: AV block, bundle branch block, torsade de pointes, ventricular tachycardia/fibrillation</p>
    </td>
    <td>Neutropenia, seizure, blurred vision, GI upset</td>
    <td>10, 12, 13, 37, 53, 55–59</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>  Tocilizumab</td>
    <td>Anti-IL-6 receptor monoclonal antibody</td>
    <td>Anti-cytokine storm? In vitro?</td>
    <td>Rheumatoid arthritis, juvenile idiopathic arthritis.</td>
    <td>
     <p>NCT04306705 (TACOS);</p>
     <p>NCT04320615 (COVACTA)</p>
    </td>
    <td>Reversal of IL-6 inducing suppression of CYP3A4, CYP2C19, CYP2C9, and CYP1A2, resulting in higher drug exposure of substrate drugs</td>
    <td>Hypertension, increased serum cholesterol; no known effect on QTc interval</td>
    <td>Allergic reaction, susceptible to infection</td>
    <td>62–68</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>  Interferon-β1</td>
    <td>A cytokine produced by innate immune cells, including macrophages, dendritic cells, and non-immune cells</td>
    <td>Recognizing viral components by pattern recognition receptors (PRR) (Liu, 2005)</td>
    <td>Multiple sclerosis</td>
    <td>NCT04293887</td>
    <td>Reduce the activity of hepatic cytochrome P450-dependent enzymes</td>
    <td>
     <p>No clinically significant effects on QTc prolongation have been observed.</p>
     <p>PVC and AVB case report</p>
    </td>
    <td>Flu-like symptoms</td>
    <td>69–72, 74, 86</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>  Fingolimod</td>
    <td>An oral immune-modulating agent with high potent of functional antagonist on the lipid sphingosine-1-phosphate (S1P) receptors in the lymph node T cells</td>
    <td>As an effective immunology modulator, fingolimod with potentials of anti-SARS-CoV-2</td>
    <td>Multiple sclerosis, refractory</td>
    <td>NCT04280588</td>
    <td>Metabolism by CYP4F2. Us in caution when combined with class Ia and III anti-arrhythmic agents and beta-blockers</td>
    <td>
     <p>Pros: Arthero-protection, anti-hypertrophy</p>
     <p>Cons: Bradycardia, AVB, hypertension</p>
    </td>
    <td>Liver toxicity, headache, GI upset, flu-like symptoms</td>
    <td>80–84</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <p>The FDA-approved CV drugs involved with COVID-19</p>
  <p>
   <italic>CV</italic> cardiovascular, 
   <italic>GI</italic> gastrointestinal, 
   <italic>SARS-CoV-2</italic> severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2, 
   <italic>RNA</italic> ribonucleic acid, 
   <italic>RSV</italic> respiratory syncytial virus, 
   <italic>HIV</italic> human immunodeficiency virus, 
   <italic>HPV</italic> human papillomavirus, 
   <italic>AVB</italic> atrioventricular 
   <italic>block</italic>
  </p>
  <p>
   <sup>#</sup>Clinical trials summarized here till April 13, 2020
  </p>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
