<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">SARS-CoV-2 is a novel β-coronavirus that belongs to the subfamily Orthocoronavirinae in the family of Coronaviridae, in the order of Nidovirales. The SARS-CoV-2 is an enveloped positive-sense single-stranded RNA (+ssRNA) virus with 4 major proteins in its structure, including the spike (S) protein (which mediates attachment to the host receptor and subsequent fusion of the virus and cell membrane), the membrane (M) protein, the envelope (E) protein, and the nucleocapsid (N) protein (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) and Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) are other β-coronavirus widespread epidemics in 2002 and 2012, respectively (
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Based on recent pieces of evidence, SARS-CoV-2 has approximately 79–82% similarity to human SARS-CoV genome at the nucleotide sequences. It has been supposed that the SARS-CoV-2 virus, similar to SARS CoV, uses the angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) as the receptor for entering host cells (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). ACE2 receptors are expressed in the membrane of various cells in the human body, including type II alveolar epithelial cells of the lung (
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Accordingly, it is expected that the bilateral diffuse alveolar injury with cytodiagnosis of myxoid fibroma exudate is the first pathological finding of COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Furthermore, kidney, intestine, heart, and blood vessels are the other organs expressing ACE2 receptor, and this may describe why some patients with COVID-19 (∼46%) experience renal, gastrointestinal, and cardiovascular problems (
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). The spike glycoprotein (S) mediates virus entry via binding to the host cell's ACE2 receptor and membrane fusion (
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). It is supposed that the interaction of the viral particle with specific proteins on the host cell surface and entering of the virus to human cells are the main triggers, which initiate infection and inflammatory cascade through various mechanisms with consequent release of pro-inflammatory cytokines (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). To the best of our knowledge the main clinical features of patients with COVID-19 consist of a) high concentration of inflammatory parameters such as C-reactive protein (CRP) and pro-inflammatory cytokines such as interleukin-1 (IL-1), IL-6, tumor necrosis factor-α (TNFα), etc.; b) Infiltration of immune cells to the lung lesion mostly monocytes and macrophages; c) Destruction of the immune system owing to atrophy of spleen and lymph nodes; d) Reduction of lymphocytes (lymphopenia) in lymphoid organs; and ultimately; e) Vasculitis, hypercoagulability, and multiple organs damage (
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>).
</p>
