<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par70">Vaccines and antiviral drugs are the prophylactic and therapeutic measures against a viral disease CoV-2. On March 17, 2020, Pfizer Inc. and BioNTech announced to co-develop and distribute a potential mRNA-based coronavirus vaccine which is likely to enter clinical testing by the end of April 2020 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pfizer.com/news/press-release/press-release-detail/pfizer_and_biontech_to_co_develop_potential_covid_19_vaccine" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.pfizer.com/news/press-release/press-release-detail/pfizer_and_biontech_to_co_develop_potential_covid_19_vaccine</ext-link>). However, in pandemic scenarios of new infectious diseases such as COVID-19, vaccine supplies will be limited or nonexistent at the early phase in lieu of the novelty of the disease and the unpredictability of the pandemic occurrence. Thus, vaccines cannot be stockpiled, and production can only start once the novel virus has been recognized. With the current state-of the-art, the first doses of vaccine are not likely to become available in the early months of the pandemic. However, the pandemic action plans have accounted for forward planning to increase the likelihood that the vaccine will progressively become available as the pandemic unfolds. Importantly, national or regional priorities need to be fixed in the action plan for the rational use of the building/limited supply of the novel vaccine. Also, production and use of vaccines during the inter-pandemic period will influence their availability during a pandemic. Thus, improving the infrastructure and logistics for vaccine production, administration, cold-chain, and professional training with the novel vaccines are important to avert/cruise through future outbreak events. The WHO advisory on prioritizing the population groups are as enlisted in descending order. However, the priorities need tailoring in each country/region according to local needs and epidemiological circumstances.
</p>
