<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par76">Antivirals are a crucial adjunct to vaccination as a potential strategy for managing COVID-19. Several drugs such as chloroquine, arbidol, remdesivir, and favipiravir are currently undergoing clinical studies to establish their efficacy and safety against COVID-19. It is important to establish a regular supply chain of antivirals and a high surge capacity in the face of CoV-2 pandemic and future outbreaks. Antivirals have a significant impact in reducing morbidity and mortality in light of unlikelihood of availability of vaccine against in early phases of pandemic. It is important to evaluate the non-interference of the antiviral interventions with the eventual vaccination, as well as the epidemiology of the group of individuals most seriously affected. It is also advisable to make available the information about the performance characteristics, side effects, and costs of antiviral therapy to public. Also the commonly used neuraminidase inhibitors in influenza pandemics are ineffective in the case of CoV-2 mediated infection and outbreaks (Pang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2020</xref>; Dong et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2020a</xref>, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/csr/resources/publications/influenza/11_29_01_A.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.who.int/csr/resources/publications/influenza/11_29_01_A.pdf</ext-link>). The incorporation of antiviral therapy can be categorized as a prophylactic and for treatment use. As with vaccines, prioritizing of groups for antiviral therapy is advised as follows:
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par77">Essential service providers, including healthcare workers (prophylaxis or treatment). Especially, healthcare providers are in a position to be in direct contact with infectious individuals and are thus entitled to priority antiviral therapy. Other community services such as those responsible for vaccine manufacture and delivery and personnel responsible for enforcing law and order and public safety.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par78">Groups at high risk of death and severe complications requiring hospitalization. The goal of prophylaxis or treatment here is to rein the mortality and morbidity. Thus, high-risk persons living in the community outbreaks, seriously ill hospitalized patients, patients for whom a potential CoV-2 vaccination is contraindicated are prioritized.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par79">Persons without known risk factors for complications from COVID-19. Here the approach is generally therapeutic and aims to rein the morbidity and rationalize the use of healthcare resources such as antibiotics. Though, the logistics of this strategy are extensive and expensive (requires large quantities of antivirals and access to healthcare service providers), it is most likely to limit the economic and social destabilization associated with a pandemic (Monto 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2006</xref>; Henry 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2019</xref>, 
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/csr/resources/publications/influenza/11_29_01_A.pdf" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.who.int/csr/resources/publications/influenza/11_29_01_A.pdf</ext-link>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
