<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0115">As a neuraminidase inhibitor, oseltamivir has effectively combated the pandemic influenza A and B, so it is a first-line commonly used antiviral drug, especially in primary hospitals. At the same time, oseltamivir, as an over-the-counter drug, is also a popular antiviral drug. As healthcare workers fighting against COVID-19, we have found that many patients experiencing discomfort or considered to be infected with a virus take oseltamivir. From SARS-CoV in 2003 to MERS- CoV in 2012, and now the current SARS-CoV-2 epidemic, there is not plenty of evidence showing that oseltamivir is effective against coronavirus. Still, there is also no sufficient evidence to refute its ineffectiveness. We cannot predict whether there will be a pandemic of respiratory coronavirus in the future, so we hope to initiate such research and preliminarily explore whether oseltamivir is effective for COVID-19, which can better guide healthcare workers in the selection of appropriate antiviral drugs in the face of coronavirus epidemics. Although there was no expression of neuraminidase in SARS-CoV-2, Zhang et al, who discovered through homology modeling that the S1 protein of SARS-CoV had a similar active center as neuraminidase and considered that neuraminidase inhibitors were likely to inhibit SARS-CoV through targeting S1 protein activity, which provided us inspiration for research the structural similarity between SARS-CoV-2 and neuraminidase 
 <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Considering the homology of the S protein of SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV, we conducted a structural alignment of the crystal structure of S protein with influenza A neuraminidase. We found that the active center of neuraminidase was not similar to the RBD domain on the S1 subunit and the HR1 domain on the S2 subunit, which were the active sites of S protein. We were not surprised by these findings because the sequence conservation of S1 in both SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV was only 71%, and there were structural variations 
 <xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. We, therefore, focused our attention on the NC protein, 3CLPro, PLpro, and Pol/RdRp, which have been widely studied in SARS-CoV, are highly conserved with SARS-CoV-2, and are the main proteins targeted by drugs. We used structural alignment to discover that, except for 3CLpro, the active centers of the other three proteins did not match that of neuraminidase. We observed that in the reported regimen in Thailand, the dosage of oseltamivir was 300 mg/day, and our patients’ treatment dose was still based on the conventional dose of 150 mg/day for flu (news link: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://xw.qq.com/cmsid/20200221A0HN1400%3ff%3dnewdc" id="ir030" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://xw.qq.com/cmsid/20200221A0HN1400?f=newdc</ext-link>), so we next studied the relationship between dose of oseltamivir and therapeutic effect. However, the data suggested that oseltamivir failed to fight against SARS-CoV-2 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>, which was consistent with the result of our retrospective case analysis. Xi Wang et al and Choy et al also found that oseltamivir was ineffective in inhibiting SARS-CoV-2 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>
 <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0170" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>.
</p>
