<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">For infection into human cells, the receptor-binding domain of spike protein (S) present on the envelope of the virus binds to ACE2 protein present on human cells, initiating the entry process. This binding induces large conformational change in S protein that leads to exposure of its proteolytic site. The proteolytic site is then cleaved by a protease, causing the fusion of the viral envelope to the host cell membrane, completing the entry of the virus into a human cell. Further, it is shown that the S protein of SARS-CoV-2 has a higher binding affinity with ACE2 as compared to SARS (Wrapp 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2020</xref>). Based on these results, it could be concluded that SARS-CoV-2 is a variant of SARS; however, the SARS-CoV-2 genome has additional features like the presence of a polybasic (RRAR) cleavage site at the junction of S1 and S2 subunits of the spike protein. The presence of a polybasic cleavage site helps in effective cleavage by furin and proteases and determines viral infectivity and host range (Andersen 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2020</xref>). Interestingly, in case of the avian influenza virus, the gain of this polybasic site in HA that performs a similar function of host receptor binding like Spike protein, can transform the virus from low virulent to high virulent forms. Along with this, the acquisition of cleavage site is positively selected for fast replication and transmission rates (Alexander and Brown 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2009</xref>). To better understand the transmission rates, the growth rate r
 <sub>0</sub> that defines the natural transmission of a pathogen needs to be calculated for SARS, MERS, and SARS-CoV-2. It is interesting to observe that although they belong to the same family, SARS-CoV-2 has twice the transmission rate when compared to SARS. Along with this, the multiplication cycles range is 5–10 days for SARS and MERS and 2–3 days for SARS-CoV-2 (Liang 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2020</xref>). Probably this the reason why SARS and MERS were far more contained, whereas COVID-19 is highly widespread. The mortality rate of SARS-CoV-2 during the early outbreak in Wuhan, China, was calculated as 1.4% (Wu 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2020</xref>). However, in late February, WHO estimated this rate to increase to 5.8%. On the other hand, South Korea registered a death rate of 1% or less, while the death rate in Italy seems to be, for now, several folds higher (Rosenbaum 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR01">2020</xref>). The infection has advanced to more than 210 countries and territories with an average mortality rate of 3.4% according to recent reports (Rajgor 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2020</xref>). Therefore, therapeutic and vaccine initiatives in this direction are inevitable. Efforts have been made in drug therapy as well as vaccine development to combat COVID-19.
</p>
