<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Rev Soc Bras Med Trop</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Rev. Soc. Bras. Med. Trop</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">rsbmt</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Revista da Sociedade Brasileira de Medicina Tropical</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0037-8682</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1678-9849</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Medicina Tropical - SBMT</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0037-8682-0270-2020</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">00913</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Letter</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>COVID-19: challenges for a new epoch</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>Cleyton Martins</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7732-8336</contrib-id><name><surname>Arbilla</surname><given-names>Graciela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label> Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro, Instituto de Qu&#x000ed;mica, Rio
de Janeiro, RJ, Brasil. </aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label> Universidade Veiga de Almeida, Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brasil.</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> Prof. Graciela Arbilla. <bold>e-mail:</bold><email>gracielaiq@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con" id="fn2"><p>
<bold>Authors&#x02019; contribution:</bold> All authors contributed towards the
conceptualization, drafting, critical review, and finalization of the
manuscript.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn3"><p>
<bold>Conflict of Interest:</bold> The authors declare no potential
conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or
publication of this manuscript.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>01</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>53</volume><elocation-id>e20200270</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>09</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution License</license-p></license></permissions><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>Dear Editor:</p><p>The term &#x0201c;pan-epidemic Anthropocene&#x0201d; was proposed by Lucey et al. to refer to multifocal
large infectious disease epidemics related to anthropogenic forces that have impacted
and transformed the Earth System<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref>. Smallpox was restricted to the Old World for thousands of years but became the
first &#x0201c;pan-epidemic Anthropocene&#x0201d; when Europeans brought it to the Americas in the 16th
century. </p><p>The arrival of Europeans in America was considered as the first globalization event where
the two civilizations met on unequal terms after 12,000 years of separation. Smallpox
emerged in January 1519 and spread rapidly to the mainland of Central America. Native
Americans had no immunity to the infections brought in by the Europeans. Smallpox,
influenza, measles, typhus, pneumonia, scarlet fever, malaria, and yellow fever emerged
subsequently and affected millions. Approximately 90% of the estimated 50-80 million
Native American population died of these diseases, which suggests approximately 10% of
mankind died during 1493-1650. This event initiated the globalization and homogenization
of the world&#x02019;s species and diseases<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>.</p><p>In the 20th century, epidemics and pandemics continued to kill millions of people. The
first pandemic of the 21st century was reported as influenza A (H1N1) in 2009-2010 that
resulted in 100,000-400,000 deaths in the first year; however, for the first time, a
vaccine was developed, produced, and distributed worldwide during the first year<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref>. </p><p>Globalization, the exchange of species, materials, energy, and culture, as well as
urbanization and the increase in the world&#x02019;s population and the global flow of people,
had a clear, and probably irreversible, impact on the environment and the equilibrium of
the Earth System that led to the proposal of a new geological Epoch, called
Anthropocene<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref>. The term &#x0201c;Anthropocene&#x0201d; was proposed by Crutzen and Stoermer in 2000, to
emphasize the central role of mankind in geology and ecology<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref>. The increasing impact of human actions on the environment was substantial,
global, and long-lasting<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref>. There is an increasing consensus on the formal recognition of Anthropocene as a
geological Epoch, functionally and stratigraphically distinct from the Holocene<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref>. New anthropogenic materials such as plastics, concrete, aluminum, and synthetic
fibers; modification of sedimentary process; wastes from nuclear weapons testing;
increase in atmospheric methane and CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations; changes in carbon,
nitrogen, and phosphorus cycles; climate and biotic changes are clear Earth System
trends that confirm the transformations to be driven by human residents. Globalization,
urbanization, transportation, increase in economic activities, and the flux of people,
live species, and manufactured products are clear socioeconomic trends that characterize
this new epoch, commonly referred to as &#x0201c;Human Epoch.&#x0201d; </p><p>All these factors, in addition to political destabilization and civil and international
wars, led to poverty, increase in maternal and child death, and spread of diseases.
Hotez<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref> reported that these changes have promoted the emergence of catastrophic
neglected tropical diseases (NTDs), first being dengue fever in the 1980s in the
American continent, chikungunya and Zika virus infections in Latin-American and
Caribbean regions, and malaria in the Amazonian region of South America. NTDs along with
other infections such as leishmaniasis, schistosomiasis, and Middle East Respiratory
Syndrome (MERS) coronavirus infection, measles, and polio spread in the Middle East and
North Africa. During 2014-2015, the Western African Ebola virus epidemic decimated
numerous families and caused a socioeconomic disruption in Guinea, Liberia, and Sierra
Leone.</p><p>The outbreak of COVID-19 provides strong evidence that urbanization and globalization
have changed the way people live in communities, and advances in transport and
communications have led to a rapid spread of diseases, through both domestic and
international transportation modes such as buses, trains, boats, and flights. Increased
density of people in residences, public transportation, work environments, shopping
centers, and cultural, political, sport, and religious events have increased the
possibilities of virus transmission in the metros. Social inequalities lead to higher
risks, particularly in middle- and low-income countries that generally have weaker
health systems and a limited capacity to handle a rapid surge in cases. Poverty
contributes to disseminating epidemics and pandemics, while simultaneously helping to
perpetuate poverty through their longstanding negative effects.</p><p>As no specific drugs or vaccines are available, the mitigation of the exponential spread
of COVID-19 relies on community mitigation strategies<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref>. There is a crescent consensus that social isolation to prevent the virus spread
is the correct strategy from not only the human rights point of view but also the
economic point of view. It seems clear that the collapse of the health care systems and
millions of deaths would decimate countries financially, and as a society, thus saving
human lives must be the governments&#x02019; first priority. </p><p>Although the pandemic is a global phenomenon and the consequence of urbanization,
transport, and interchange of people, live species, and manufactured products, its
impact is greatly shaped by decisions taken by the individual governments. Many
governments responded swiftly while others, after an initial slow response, acknowledged
their error and adopted the World Health Organization&#x02019;s (WHO) recommendations.
Unfortunately for all, some are still ignoring WHO&#x02019;s recommendations on avoiding mass
gatherings. Recently, Croda et al.<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref> reported on the progression of COVID-19 cases in Brazil and previous experiences
with other health emergencies that constituted an important legacy in dealing with
epidemics and demonstrated Brazil&#x02019;s scientific capacity. They also discussed the
initially implemented measures to reduce the virus spread and mortality. Despite the
exceptional efforts by the state governors and city mayors, the response of the
country&#x02019;s President contributes to the growing uncertainty among the population about
the health risks and economic impacts of the pandemic<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>10</sup>
</xref>. In uncertain times, positive leadership navigates through a crisis; leaders are
required to make the right decisions based on science and to craft a good narrative to
clarify the problems and unite the population to manage the situation. Global problems
require global solutions and everybody&#x02019;s efforts. </p><p>In addition to all the negative impacts, the pandemic has opened new opportunities,
displayed examples of solidarity in the local communities, and allowed sharing of
resources, information, and expertise from countries further ahead in the pandemic or
with better results and knowledge in controlling the spread. The scientific communities
worldwide have joined hands and many universities have organized groups of researchers
and students to help in the pandemic relief efforts in every possible manner. </p><p>The pandemic is a strong reminder that to be prepared for the future, a fundamental
change in our mindset, commitments, and values is necessary. It is necessary to create a
change in our current way of living and a concentrated effort to establish conditions
for humanity to manage itself in the Anthropocene, the &#x0201c;Age of Humans.&#x0201d; British
economist Kate Raworth, from Oxford University, has rightly mentioned that humanity&#x02019;s
21st-century challenge is to meet the needs of all within the means of the Planet<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref>. Her model, known as &#x0201c;Doughnut Economics&#x0201d;, has recently been adopted to guide
Amsterdam out of the economic impact left by the coronavirus pandemic<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">
<sup>12</sup>
</xref>. Environmental repair, renewable energy, more investments in science, public
health, and education are needed to reduce inequalities, climate changes, and the human
impact on Earth&#x02019;s equilibrium, else, humanity will never be prepared enough to confront
the devastating challenges of a pandemic. Humans have the opportunity of saving their
own lives and the life of all species in the Earth System through advanced technology
and science.</p><p>Preparedness is crucial to reduce the health, economic, and social impacts of a future
epidemic, it is also the only way to avoid the spread of other diseases. Pandemics are
not aleatory events but are the consequence of human interactions with the environment
and could be avoided or reduced through science and investments in health, education and
transportation and improved through better conditions of living. </p><p>This is an opportunity for the global community to take advantage of the spirit of
cooperation, embrace diversity and arrive at a necessary common global agreement to
manage the future of Earth collectively.</p></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="supported-by" id="fn1"><p>
<bold>Financial Support:</bold>
<bold>GA and CMS</bold> received partial financial support from the Brazilian
National Council for Scientific and Technological Development (CNPq) and the
National Foundation for the Development of Private Higher Education (FUNADESP),
respectively. </p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES </title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lucey</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sholts</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Donaldson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On health education for future physicians in the pan-epidemic
&#x0201c;Age of Humans&#x0201d;</article-title><source>Int J Infect Dis</source><year>2017</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28838849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Maslin</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><source>The human planet. How we created the Anthropocene</source><edition>1st ed</edition><publisher-loc>New Haven and London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name><year>2018</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>WHO. World Health Organization</collab></person-group><source>Past Pandemics</source><year>2020</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date" iso-8601-date="2020-04-30">2020
April 30</date-in-citation><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.euro.who.int/en/health-topics/communicable-diseases/influenza/pandemic-influenza/past-pandemics">http://www.euro.who.int/en/health-topics/communicable-diseases/influenza/pandemic-influenza/past-pandemics</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Arbilla</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anthropocene: the challenges of a new world</article-title><source>Revista Virtual de Qu&#x000ed;mica</source><year>2018</year><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1619</fpage><lpage>1647</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crutzen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoermer</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The &#x0201c;Anthropocene&#x0201d;</article-title><source>IGBP Newsletter</source><year>2000</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>18</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Zalasiewicz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Summerhayes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnosky</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Poirier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Anthropocene Is Functionally and Stratigraphically Distinct
From the Holocene</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2016</year><volume>351</volume><issue>6269</issue><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>147</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hotez</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neglected tropical diseases in the Anthropocene: The cases of
zica, ebola, and other infections</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>30004648</fpage><lpage>30004648</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Villela</surname><given-names>DAM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The value of mitigating epidemic peaks of COVID-19 for more
effective public health responses</article-title><source>Rev Soc Bras Med Trop</source><year>2020</year><volume>53</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Croda</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveria</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Frutuoso</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandetta</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Baia-da-Silva</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 in Brazil: advantages of a socialized unified health
system and preparation to contain cases</article-title><source>Rev Soc Bras Med Trop</source><year>2020</year><volume>53</volume><elocation-id>e20200167 </elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32320998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Editorial</collab></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 in Brazil: &#x0201c;So what?&#x0201d;</article-title><source>The Lancet</source><year>2020</year><volume>395</volume><fpage>1461</fpage><lpage>1461</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raworth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><source>Doughnut Economics: Seven Ways to Think Like a 21<sup>st</sup>-Century
Economist</source><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cornerstone</publisher-name><year>2017</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>The Guardian</collab></person-group><source>Amsterdam to embrace &#x0201c;doughnut&#x0201d; model to mend post-coronavirus
economy</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date" iso-8601-date="2020-05-08">2020 May
8</date-in-citation><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/apr/08/amsterdam-doughnut-model-mend-post-coronavirus-economy">https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/apr/08/amsterdam-doughnut-model-mend-post-coronavirus-economy</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>