<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Generally, the efficacy of alcohols in eradicating microorganisms is optimum between 60% and 90% by solution in water (v/v).
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>30</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>33</sup>
 </xref> In one of the studies, it was reported that 80% ethyl alcohol was effective at eradicating hepatitis B virus under 2 min and 70% isopropyl alcohol of that within 10 min.
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>34</sup>
 </xref> However, the virucidal activity of alcohol depends greatly on its concentration of the actives and the type of test viruses. Ethyl alcohol is effective against enveloped viruses and a few non‐enveloped viruses. Studies have shown that ethyl alcohol inactivates enveloped virus such as herpes and influenza to select non‐enveloped viruses such as adenovirus, rhinovirus, and rotavirus.
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>30</sup>
 </xref> Isopropyl alcohol, however, was reported to be effective against enveloped viruses but ineffective against similar non‐enveloped viruses.
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>30</sup>
 </xref> The differential virucidal action could potentially be a result of the lipophilic nature of isopropyl alcohol as compared to ethanol.
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>31</sup>
 </xref> The efficacy of alcohols to inactivate viruses is heavily dependent on the surface properties of the microorganism. Isopropyl alcohol, by nature lipophilic, interacts favorably with enveloped viruses and disrupts their activity effectively. The envelope layer of viruses mainly comprises lipid bilayers, which causes the membrane to be sensitive to the chemical and physical conditions.
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>35</sup>
 </xref> Non‐enveloped viruses are generally known to be more resilient to disinfectants compared to enveloped viruses, and this includes alcohols. Studies have been shown that both alcohols are potent virucidal agents against enveloped viruses such as Hepatitis B virus
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>34</sup>
 </xref>, Herpes virus
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>36</sup>
 </xref>,SARS‐CoV,
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>37</sup>
 </xref> and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>38</sup>
 </xref>, but not non‐enveloped viruses such as Hepatitis A virus
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>34</sup>
 </xref> and polio virus.
 <xref rid="viw216-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>39</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
