<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Coronavirus is the most prominent example of a virus that has crossed the species barrier twice from wild animals to humans during SARS and MERS outbreaks (
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>). The possibility of crossing the species barrier for the third time has also been suspected in the case of SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19). Bats are recognized as a possible natural reservoir host of both SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV infection. In contrast, the possible intermediary host is the palm civet for SARS-CoV and the dromedary camel for MERS-CoV infection (
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>). Bats are considered the ancestral hosts for both SARS and MERS (
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>). Bats are also considered the reservoir host of human coronaviruses like HCoV-229E and HCoV-NL63 (
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>). In the case of COVID-19, there are two possibilities for primary transmission: it can be transmitted either through intermediate hosts, similar to that of SARS and MERS, or directly from bats (
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>). The emergence paradigm put forward in the SARS outbreak suggests that SARS-CoV originated from bats (reservoir host) and later jumped to civets (intermediate host) and incorporated changes within the receptor-binding domain (RBD) to improve binding to civet ACE2. This civet-adapted virus, during their subsequent exposure to humans at live markets, promoted further adaptations that resulted in the epidemic strain (
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>). Transmission can also occur directly from the reservoir host to humans without RBD adaptations. The bat coronavirus that is currently in circulation maintains specific “poised” spike proteins that facilitate human infection without the requirement of any mutations or adaptations (
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>). Altogether, different species of bats carry a massive number of coronaviruses around the world (
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>).
</p>
