<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It seems surprising that most of the found targets of existing drugs are not related to infectious diseases but, rather, are associated with inflammation, cancer, or immune disorders. However, since we analyzed virus–host interactions, we could expect that SARS-CoV-2 and HIV-1 interaction with the host would be associated with processes like inflammation and those that affect the host immune system. The association between cancer development and inflammation has been discussed in several studies [
 <xref rid="B72-molecules-25-02944" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-molecules-25-02944" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-molecules-25-02944" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,
 <xref rid="B75-molecules-25-02944" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Moreover, the role of the targets associated with autoimmune diseases in the development of cancer has been described [
 <xref rid="B74-molecules-25-02944" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Based on the analysis of the targets strongly related to the found conditions according to the Clarivate Analytics Integrity database [
 <xref rid="B39-molecules-25-02944" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]—provided in the 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-molecules-25-02944">Supplementary Materials (Table S2)</xref>—we identified three main groups of proteins. The first group contains interleukins (IL), interferon (IFN), interferon regulatory factor (IRF), IL6, IL8, IL12a, IL12b, IL18, IRF3. For these proteins, their role in inflammation and the immune response during infection is well studied [
 <xref rid="B76-molecules-25-02944" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. The second group contains a few proteins, such as the Toll-like receptors (TLR) TLR3 and TLR7, whose role in the immune response is described above. The third group contains some transcription factors and kinases which play a role in various molecular processes that are related to the inflammation response. They also can be important for the development of cancer. Regarding pathological conditions, in general, the results found using Integrity are very similar to those found using UniProt and KEGG. Still, an interpretation of the results collected from Integrity can help to better understand the effectiveness of approved drugs for the treatment of SARS-Co-V2 when specific antiviral medicines are not known.
</p>
