<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Serial dilutions of heat-inactivated serum samples were pre-incubated with either Zika virus or dengue virus serotype 2 (5,000–10,000 viral RNA copy numbers) for 1 h at 37°C. Fcγ receptor-bearing K562 cells (ATCC) were added and incubated for 3 (Zika virus) or 4 (dengue virus) days. Then the cell culture supernatant was harvested and used for virus detection by qPCR. Viral RNA was isolated with the RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen) and cDNA was generated with the iScript cDNA Synthesis Kit (BioRad), according to manufacturers’ instructions. cDNA was mixed with TaqMan Universal PCR Master Mix (Applied Biosystems/Thermo Fisher Scientific), 25 pmol of primers and 10 pmol of probe (Eurofin Genomics). Primers and probes used in this study targeted the NS5 gene: Zika virus: forward primer: ACAAGGGGAATTTGGAAAGGC; reverse primer: GAATCCAAGGGCTTCGAACTC; probe: FAM-AGCCGCGCCATCTGGTATATGTGG-TAMRA. Dengue virus 2: forward primer: CAGATGGAGGGAGAAGGAGTC; reverse primer: CGCCCTACTCTTGCTAACCA; probe: FAM-ACAGTCACAGAAGAAATCGCCGTGCA-TAMRA. The samples were amplified under the conditions described in [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008034.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]: 3 min at 50°C followed by 10 min at 95°C, and 45 cycles of 95°C (15 s), 55°C (30 s), and 72°C (30 s) using Quantstudio 3 (Thermo Fisher Scientific). A plasmid encoding part of the NS5 gene of Zika virus or dengue virus 2 (synthesized by GeneArt/Thermo Fisher Scientific) was included to generate a standard curve with 10-fold dilutions for quantification, as described previously [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008034.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008034.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. The first point of the linear standard curve was 10
 <sup>8</sup> RNA copies/reaction, the last point 100 RNA copies/reaction (limit of detection, because this amount resulted consistently in detectable PCR amplification above background levels). Fold enhancement of infection was calculated as the ratio between viral RNA copies in the presence of a positive serum and viral RNA copies in the presence of a flavivirus-negative control serum.
</p>
