<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Classical swine fever (CSF), which was first recognised in 1810, is a contagious disease of pigs characterised by fever and haemorrhage with an acute or chronic process (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2020-0020_ref_001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2020-0020_ref_010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), and it leads to economic losses around the world (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2020-0020_ref_006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). The pathogenic agent, CSFV, is a member of the genus 
 <italic>Pestivirus</italic> of the family 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic> (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2020-0020_ref_008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) and is hosted naturally only by domestic pigs and wild boars. The positive-sense, single-stranded RNA genome of CSFV is 12.3 kb in length, and it is composed of one long open reading frame followed by two non-translated regions, one on each side (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2020-0020_ref_012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2020-0020_ref_015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Field strains of this virus have been found to belong to various genotypes. Thanks to the application of live attenuated vaccines in experimental immunisations and/or accurate epidemiological surveillance (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2020-0020_ref_014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), CSF has been controlled or completely eradicated from domestic pigs in some countries and regions, such as Australia, New Zealand, North America, and Western Europe (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2020-0020_ref_005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2020-0020_ref_011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). However, it still has a large effect on swine production in Asia, South America, Eastern Europe, and parts of the former Soviet Union (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2020-0020_ref_005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Experimental prophylactic vaccination with live attenuated vaccines (such as C-strain vaccine) and a non-vaccination eradication policy have proved to be effective ways to limit CSF epidemics (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2020-0020_ref_009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). CSFV antigens have played an important role as vaccine components in the prevention and control of CSF (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2020-0020_ref_017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) and it is important to produce CSFV in substantial quantities for research not only on vaccines but also on diagnosis of and treatment methods for CSFV infection. CSFV has been cultured 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> in cell lines including porcine kidney cells (PK15, CPK, and SK6) and porcine, bovine, and sheep testicular cells (
 <xref rid="j_jvetres-2020-0020_ref_018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Among these lines, PK15 and ST cells are widely used for the
</p>
