<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0095">Since the beginning of infectious disease modelling, sweeping, gross assumptions have had to be made in order to make progress. One of the most fundamental is the “closed population”, which only exist in very special circumstances such as boarding schools and isolated populations (
 <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">Keeling and Grenfell, 1997</xref>). But people (and non-human hosts) move. An important problem at the time of writing is the emergence and spread of the novel coronavirus (Covid-19), initially in Wuhan, China (
 <xref rid="bib0195" ref-type="bibr">Riou and Althaus, 2020</xref>). As well as the need to rapidly understand the natural history of infection of this new virus, it is essential to understand how population movement will impact spread. An important part of the data revolution is the increasing ease with which we can collect geostatistical information; it is increasingly common to use flight data to estimate patterns of emergence and associate an individual with a precise and temporally changing spatial location, utilising GPS devices and smartphones (
 <xref rid="bib0225" ref-type="bibr">Wesolowski et al., 2015</xref>). The analysis of infectious disease spread in geographical space and time is an area requiring more attention. The paper by Milton et al. (see Box 6, (
 <xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr">Milton et al., 2019</xref>)) is different from the others in the issue in that the dynamics are not at the centre of attention, but this approach represents one of our bets for the future. Infectious disease dynamics drive spatio-temporal statistical patterns on an aggregate level, providing an alternative angle for inference when strong assumptions on the transmission process cannot be justified. First considered for measles by 
 <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">Grenfell et al. (2001)</xref>, methodology for analysing these patterns has been a major growth area and is likely to continue.
</p>
