<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>On the other side of the interaction, virus reproductive success is determined by its ability to be transmitted to susceptible hosts. Recently developed mathematical models predict that on-going climate change will result in higher prevalence of infectious diseases [
 <xref rid="B26-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. These works proposed that variations in temperature and humidity will promote parasite plant-to-plant transmission (horizontal transmission) through effects on population dynamics of vectors that increase population sizes or biting rates [
 <xref rid="B28-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. This seems to be the case of plant viruses, many of which are transmitted by vectors. Indeed, lower humidity and higher temperature positively affect plant virus transmission by increasing vector reproductive success and flying activity, and by enhancing host competence [
 <xref rid="B32-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Notably, mathematical models attribute to light intensity a minor role in virus horizontal transmission. However, transmission by vectors is far from being the only mode of plant virus dispersal. More than 25% of known plant viruses can be transmitted from-parent-to-offspring through seeds (vertical transmission) [
 <xref rid="B35-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The fitness of vertically transmitted parasites is highly dependent on host reproductive potential, as hosts need to reproduce for the parasite to infect new individuals [
 <xref rid="B37-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Hence, reduced virulence would favor plant virus seed transmission. Recently, the efficiency of seed transmission has been also associated with higher virus multiplication in reproductive organs [
 <xref rid="B40-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Thus, environmental conditions that favor reduced virus virulence without controlling its level of within-plant multiplication (by definition, tolerance) may enhance vertical transmission. In this context, light may become a major determinant of virus transmission if increased light intensity results in higher tolerance as proposed by theoretical models [
 <xref rid="B22-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-plants-08-00304" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. However, to date this hypothesis has not been experimentally tested.
</p>
