<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This cross-sectional study was done at Baylor Clinic in Mbabane, Eswatini from October 2017 to June 2018. Baylor Clinic is a well established HIV and Tuberculosis Center of Excellence providing care and treatment to children and adolescents with HIV as well as their families at no charge in partnership with the Eswatini Ministry of Health. The study population of 300 adolescents and young adults captured 40% (300 of 767) of the total population of adolescents and young adults enrolled in care. As part of comprehensive HIV care, all adolescents and young adults at the clinic are actively screened for risk of STIs and for STI symptoms. For male urethritis or vaginal discharge syndromes, patients are treated with ceftriaxone, azithromycin, and metronidazole per national guidelines. Additional doses of azithromycin, and extended metronidazole in women, are recommended for scrotal swelling and lower abdominal pain syndromes, respectively. Erythromycin or doxycycline is substituted when azithromycin is unavailable. Integrated cervical cancer screening is offered to sexually active women via a screen and treat approach, and sexual and reproductive health counseling and screening is routinely offered to all patients beginning in adolescence. Condoms (male and female) as well as hormonal contraceptive options are available. Human immunodeficiency virus-positive patients, 15 to 24 years of age, were enrolled consecutively (4 per day). Participants completed a paper-based sexual health history survey (SHHS), discussed SHHS results and STI symptoms with a healthcare worker, and provided urine and/or swab specimens. If positive for an STI, participants were called to come back to the clinic for treatment. Symptomatic patients received syndromic management as per National Guidelines, inclusive of treatment for CT, NG, or TV if identified by testing. Asymptomatic patients received treatment specific to the pathogen identified by Xpert testing. All patients with an STI syndrome or a positive STI test were advised to inform sexual partners to go to the nearest clinic for treatment, following national STI treatment guidelines. Three months to 12 months posttreatment, patients were tested again to confirm the successful treatment without reinfection or treatment failure.</p>
