<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Propagation of K103N within the network is noteworthy, and of high relevance not only to Mexico but also to many other resource-limited countries that still use efavirenz-based first-line ART regimens without availability of baseline HIV genotyping and weak viral load monitoring systems. The lack of fitness costs associated with this mutation
 <xref rid="dkz502-B52" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>52</sup>
 </xref> in addition to the low-genetic barrier of efavirenz and its wide use as part of first-line ART regimens have resulted in worryingly high K103N prevalence in several countries.
 <xref rid="dkz502-B3" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> These observations, together with our current study, support the hypothesis of an endemic self-sustained reservoir of specific DRMs that persists in ART-naive populations mostly through onward transmission.
 <xref rid="dkz502-B52" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>52</sup>
 </xref> This lesson needs to be taken into account in countries migrating to INSTI-based regimens, especially if low-genetic barrier drugs are to be used, considering the predicted impact of different DRMs on viral fitness and drug resistance in the context of possible interactions between DRMs in RT and integrase.
 <xref rid="dkz502-B53" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>53</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="dkz502-B54" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>54</sup>
 </xref> In our study, local transmission of HIVDR variants was notable for the Gustavo A. Madero municipality, which showed the highest frequency of persons sharing DRMs, but was not included among the strongly supported transition events in the phylogeographic diffusion model, suggesting an important role of locally sustained transmission. However, strongly supported transition events across municipalities, including Benito Juárez–Nezahualcóyotl, Cuauhtémoc–Benito Juárez, Cuauhtémoc–Iztapalapa and Iztapalapa–Nezahualcóyotl, could partly explain HIVDR spread, mostly in the northern area of Mexico City, which was identified as the geographic epicentre of Mexico City’s epidemic.
</p>
