<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although bats have been strongly suspected, evidence that human outbreaks have resulted from contact with bats is, so far, indirect. As the only set of species that have shown replication and high circulating titres of Ebolavirus without accompanying illness [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], bats appear to be capable of functioning as reservoirs. Moreover, detection of virus in lung tissues and faeces suggests that bats could transmit virus to other susceptible species via multiple routes [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. On the other side, recent experimental inoculations of Egyptian fruit bats (
 <italic>Rousettus aegyptiacus</italic>) with Ebolavirus strains [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] resulted in low levels of detectable viral RNA suggesting that fruit bats could, instead, be dead end hosts incapable of transmitting. Circumstantially, bat consumption associated with an annual bat migration has been tied to the index case of an Ebolavirus disease outbreak (May 2007) in the Democratic Republic of Congo [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. As further circumstantial evidence, an insectivorous bat (
 <italic>Mops condylurus</italic>) tested positive for Ebolavirus-specific antibodies [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], survived experimental infection while showing high viremia [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] and, although evidence is anecdotal rather than serological, 
 <italic>M. condylurus</italic> may have been the source of infection to the human index case in the 2014 West African Ebola epidemic [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. However, with little market as bushmeat [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], direct human contact with insectivorous bats may be more limited than with fruit bats or rodents. And, despite the importance of fruit bats in bushmeat markets across Africa [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], no fruit bat hunter has yet been identified as the index case in any Ebolavirus disease outbreak [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], nor has any rodent species been directly tied to Ebolavirus spillover despite widespread exploitation of rodents for food [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Thus, although thousands of individuals have been tested, live virus has never been isolated from wild bats or rodents [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180337C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].
</p>
