<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par25">In densely sampled outbreaks, such as the context of this study (foot-and-mouth disease detected in a previously free country), coalescent times and transmission times can differ markedly, leading to important differences between the transmission network and the phylogenetic tree nested within it
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup>. Following
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup>, we simulated phylogenetic trees nested within the given transmission networks with VirusTreeSimulator (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/PangeaHIV/VirusTreeSimulator" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/PangeaHIV/VirusTreeSimulator</ext-link>; last accessed 3 December, 2018) then SeqGen version 1.3.3
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup> for Monte Carlo simulation of molecular sequence evolution along the simulated phylogenetic trees. Based on empirical observations of model fit and parameters from the 2001 outbreak of FMD in the UK
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup> and the 2010 outbreak of FMD in Japan
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>, we assumed the HKY model
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>
 </sup> with a rate of nucleotide substitutions of 2.168 × 10
 <sup>−5</sup> changes per site per day, with a ratio of 7.61 transitions to transversions, empirically estimated nucleotide frequencies (of 
 <italic>π</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>A</italic>
 </sub> = 0.253, 
 <italic>π</italic>
 <sub>C</sub> = 0.282, 
 <italic>π</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>G</italic>
 </sub> = 0.257, 
 <italic>π</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>T</italic>
 </sub> = 0.208), mutations assumed to occur independently along the sequence owing to little selective pressure, and no recombination, insertions or deletions within the short time-frames of the epidemics under consideration. Within-farm diversity was modelled with a within- and between-host neutral coalescent model assuming a constant effective population size of 100 and that the bottleneck at transmission was complete. This model is described in detail elsewhere
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>. Only a single sample was considered per IP, given that sequencing of virus from different animals from the same farm in the UK 2001 outbreak indicated very limited within-farm sequence variability
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
