<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Lopinavir–ritonavir is a combination therapy used to treat HIV. Ritonavir is an inhibitor of cytochrome P450 and is used to increase the plasma half-life of lopinavir.
 <xref rid="b54-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> Lopinavir is a protease inhibitor that has been demonstrated to have antiviral effects against SARS, MERS-CoV, and SARS-CoV-2
 <italic> in vitro</italic>.
 <xref rid="b54-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="b55-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">55</xref> Several trials have been investigating the efficacy of lopinavir–ritonavir compared with other drugs as a treatment for COVID-19.
 <xref rid="b39-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="b56-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>–
 <xref rid="b58-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">58</xref> Nevertheless, the results so far indicate that lopinavir–ritonavir treatment has little benefit as a standalone therapy against SARS-CoV-2 infection. In a clinical trial involving 199 patients with laboratory-confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection, lopinavir–ritonavir treatment was not associated with any clinical improvements compared with standard care.
 <xref rid="b54-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> Furthermore, lopinavir–ritonavir treatment caused gastrointestinal adverse events, and nearly 14% of the recipients could not complete the full 14-day course of treatment.
 <xref rid="b54-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> Other adverse effects included gastrointestinal intolerance, hepatotoxicity, pancreatitis, and QT prolongation. The use of ritonavir can cause severe drug–drug interactions in medications metabolised through the cytochrome system. The tolerance of the side effects might limit the dosage needed, as the concentration necessary to inhibit viral replication is relatively high.
 <xref rid="b54-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> Other clinical trials have been testing lopinavir–ritonavir combined with different drugs and different combinations such as ritonavir and interferon 1b.
 <xref rid="b39-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="b56-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> Early use of lopinavir–ritonavir as an additional treatment to ritonavir–methylprednisolone for SARS-CoV was associated with a reduction in the overall death rate and intubation rate when compared with a matched cohort.
 <xref rid="b59-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">59</xref> A clinical phase II trial has been investigating the use of lopinavir–ritonavir combined with interferon β-1b as a treatment for MERS since 2016, but the trial is ongoing and results have yet to be published.
 <xref rid="b60-dic-2020-4-15" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>
</p>
