<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0050">Concerning triggering events and maintaining factors, the media might play a central role in epidemics/pandemics (e.g., excessive COVID-19-related Internet use as safety-seeking behavior; 
 <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">Garfin, Silver, &amp; Holman, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">Hansen, 2009</xref>). The use of media can both itself represent a safety-seeking behavior (e.g., researching whether symptoms are a sign of a virus infection) and, due to possible disturbing information, can trigger or reinforce further safety-seeking behavior (e.g., further/excessive Internet use, visits to the doctor) (
 <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">Brown et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">Garfin et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr">Jungmann, Brand, Kolb, &amp; Witthöft, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">Starcevic &amp; Berle, 2013</xref>). Cyberchondria, repeated and/or excessive health-related Internet search associated with emotional stress (especially anxiety), is a common safety-seeking behavior that can increase and/or maintain worries and anxiety (
 <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">Brown et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr">Starcevic &amp; Berle, 2013</xref>). During virus outbreaks, media reports are increasingly consumed, which often use emotional language and address emotional content that catches people's attention (
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">Bao, Sun, Meng, Shi, &amp; Lu, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">Garfin et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">Hansen, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">Klemm, Das, &amp; Hartmann, 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0345" ref-type="bibr">Tausczik, Faasse, Pennebaker, &amp; Petrie, 2012</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr">Hansen (2009)</xref>, for example, conducted a detailed narrative analysis of media reports in Norway during the SARS pandemic of 2003 and concluded that the media stir up anxiety among the population, e.g., by reporting selectively negative individual cases or inappropriate comparisons (e.g., Black Death in 14th century in Europe) and by using emotional and dramatic language. Studies during previous pandemics and the current COVID-19 pandemic found that media consumption is positively associated with anxiety (
 <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0245" ref-type="bibr">Moghanibashi-Mansourieh, 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0260" ref-type="bibr">Purohit et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0300" ref-type="bibr">Roy et al., 2020</xref>). However, the results are inconsistent with regard to the exact relationship between knowledge about the virus and health anxiety (
 <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">Blakey &amp; Abramowitz, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr">Goulia et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">Lei et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2020</xref>). While 
 <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">Blakey and Abramowitz (2017)</xref> and 
 <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">Lei et al. (2020)</xref> found that a higher level of knowledge about the virus is associated with increased anxiety, 
 <xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr">Goulia et al. (2010)</xref> found that perceived knowledge is associated with less worry. In the study by 
 <xref rid="bib0365" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. (2020)</xref>, there was no significant correlation between knowledge about the virus and anxiety, but the desire for additional information was associated with less anxiety. However, little research exists on possible factors contributing to the links between media consumption and knowledge about the virus and anxiety (
 <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">Garfin et al., 2020</xref>). Probably, the relationships depend on the type, content, source, intention and/or extent of media consumption (e.g., accurate vs. ambiguous, Internet research as safety-seeking behavior, concrete information on preventive measures; 
 <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">Gao et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">Garfin et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0260" ref-type="bibr">Purohit et al., 2018</xref>).
</p>
