<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0055">In addition to the above-mentioned factors for the development and maintenance of health anxiety, the role of coping processes and emotional regulation in health anxiety has been increasingly investigated in recent years (
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Bailer, Witthöft, Erkic, &amp; Mier, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">Görgen, Hiller, &amp; Witthöft, 2014</xref>). The study of emotional and coping processes can contribute to the extension of existing models of health anxiety and to the development of possible preventive and interventional approaches. Previous studies have shown positive correlations between dysfunctional emotion regulation strategies such as rumination and catastrophization and health anxiety (
 <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">Görgen et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0215" ref-type="bibr">Marcus, Hughes, &amp; Arnau, 2008</xref>). 
 <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">Fergus and Valentiner (2010)</xref> found that a higher level of cognitive reappraisal can predict lower disease convictions. In the context of the research on epidemics/pandemics, the term "coping" is used more frequently, whereby there is a considerable overlap between the definition of coping ("… changing cognitive and behavioral efforts to manage specific external/internal demands …", 
 <xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr">Lazarus &amp; Folkman, 1984</xref>, p. 141) and emotion regulation ("… processes by which individuals influence which emotions they have, when they have them, and how they experience and express these emotions …", 
 <xref rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr">Gross, 1998</xref>, p. 275) as well as regarding individual strategies (e.g., acceptance, distraction). For example, 
 <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">Garnefski, Kraaij, and Spinhoven (2001)</xref> also conceptualize “coping as an aspect of emotion regulation” (p. 1312). In dealing with an epidemic, avoidant coping strategies (i.e., denying and disengagement) were associated with psychological complaints, while active coping strategies (e.g., planning, positive interpretation, and acceptance) were associated with subjective well-being (
 <xref rid="bib0210" ref-type="bibr">Main et al., 2011</xref>). In the study by 
 <xref rid="bib0335" ref-type="bibr">Taha, Matheson, Cronin, and Anisman (2014)</xref>, strategies such as self-blame, rumination, and passive resignation were grouped as emotion-focused coping strategies, which were positively associated with anxiety in relation to the H1N1 pandemic in 2009.
</p>
