<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One step that can potentially be fast-tracked is authorisation. The European Medicines Agency (EMA) has regulatory mechanisms in place to speed up development and approval. The PRIME scheme was launched to provide early and enhanced scientific and regulatory support to medicines that have the potential to address unmet medical needs. Developers of medicines and vaccines benefitting from PRIME will be eligible for accelerated assessment, reducing the time frame for the EMA to review applications for market authorisation. The EMA can also grant a conditional marketing authorisation for vaccines where the benefits of immediate availability outweigh the risks of less comprehensive data than normally required. Developers working on vaccines that could be used for the prevention of COVID-19 are encouraged to contact the EMA and discuss their research as soon as possible.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr12-1470320320926902" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
 </sup> Once a safe and effective vaccine has been developed, there are further hurdles, including large-scale manufacturing. Many organisations researching a vaccine do not have the required manufacturing capacity. Vaccine development is high risk, with many candidates failing to reach clinical application. Further, manufacturing facilities tend to be tailored to specific vaccines. Scaling up these facilities when the future deployment of a vaccine is still in the uncertain early stages is not commercially viable. However, CEPI can shoulder some of this risk by providing funding not only to research facilities developing vaccine candidates but also to manufacturing facilities in parallel. At the same time as clinical trials are taking place in Oxford, production of the vaccine is being scaled up ready for larger trials and possible future deployment.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr5-1470320320926902" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
 </sup> With early-stage scale-up, researchers can ensure that sufficient doses will be available as soon as possible if the trials prove that the vaccine is safe and effective.
</p>
