<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza viruses are highly contagious pathogens that are associated with a year-round global record reaching nearly a million morbidities and half-a-million mortalities. Four types of influenza viruses (i.e., A, B, C, and D) have been identified. Influenza viruses C (isolated in pigs and humans) and D (isolated from cattle) are less common; typically, influenza virus C is associated with less severe illness [
 <xref rid="B1-vaccines-07-00053" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-vaccines-07-00053" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. On the other hand, influenza viruses A (infecting avian and mammals including human) and B (almost exclusively infecting humans and seals) account for the annual global burden of influenza [
 <xref rid="B3-vaccines-07-00053" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-vaccines-07-00053" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The persistence of influenza viruses A and B has been attributed to their ability to evolve rapidly. Antigenic variabilities are also common with influenza viruses A and B, and these are partly as a result of a phenomenon called the antigenic drift, referring to amino acid changes that allows viral escape from neutralizing antibodies [
 <xref rid="B5-vaccines-07-00053" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-vaccines-07-00053" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Such immune-escape mutants often tend to have a higher host-cell avidity (compared to the wild-type virus) in exposed or vaccinated host and vice-versa, in naïve host [
 <xref rid="B7-vaccines-07-00053" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Studies by Fergusson et al. revealed that antigenic drifts in seasonal influenza viruses (H3, H1, and B) were estimated at fixation rates of 0.0037, 0.0018, and 0.0013 nucleotide substitutions per site per year (±0.001) respectively [
 <xref rid="B8-vaccines-07-00053" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. This supports the idea that antigenic drifts occur more frequently in influenza A viruses than influenza B viruses. In addition, high mutation rates cause a tremendous impact in efficacy of the seasonal influenza vaccines which comprise forecasted strains [
 <xref rid="B9-vaccines-07-00053" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. For instance, gain or loss of N-linked glycosylation sites in the hemagglutinin (HA) can also participate in the antigenic drift: Skehel et al. showed that a single D63N substitution in HA1 created a novel N-glycosylation site that allowed an antigenic variant of an H3N2 to escape neutralization by a monoclonal antibody [
 <xref rid="B10-vaccines-07-00053" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In the same study, the authors further observed that the 1968 influenza epidemic strain (A/VIC/3/75) that had N63 (known glycosylation site), was also recognized (when un-glycosylated) by antibodies raised against viruses of two earlier epidemics. As illustrated, altering glycosylation patterns is one of the means used by viruses that results in potential cause of vaccine failure. 
</p>
