<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0060">Although no case of recent emerging diseases threat has been reported in Saudi Arabia, rapid and coordinated leadership for resource mobilization and financing of (Hajj and Umrah) pilgrims and populations’ maintenance of disease preventive capacities are behind these successes. Population -based surveillance and response implementation is needed against emerging viral diseases outbreaks. The coherent and sustainable emerging outbreak preparedness and response system development and establishment is core to increase awareness, re-enforcement of individual pilgrim and host community preventative and precautionary measures. Increasing advocacy on emerging viral disease R&amp;D roadmap taskforce development and implementation of outbreaks countermeasures (diagnostics, therapeutics and vaccines) that are most needed by affected and prone countries through national and international multidisciplinary and intersectorial stakeholders’ partnership is crucial to promote early diagnosis, timely treatment, and vaccination programs implementation. Strengthening routine diagnostic and surveillance port of entry and hospitals and community-health centers including private clinics and treatment standards best practice adherence in upholding infection emergence and spread prevention and control. The absence of accessible and available safe drug and vaccine, sensitive and point of care accurate diagnostic tools and timely safe drugs Nipah and Zika or Ebola remain a major challenge for scale mass administration and immunization programs in most endemic areas and worldwide. Implementing integrated “One Health” and AntiMicrobial Resistance (AMR) stewardship platforms and data sharing to coordinate multi-sectoral emerging pandemic threat collaboration and coordination at national level is a must opportunity to leverage their efforts, by institutionalizing key structures and capacity, and not a choice. It is still unclear and challenging to quantify and ascertain the spread and impact improvements in emerging epidemics and epidemics training, and to ensure the likelihood and sustainable development. and disbursement to prevent further spread, fast-track an understanding contextual risk factors, and contain the deadly remote rural and urban outbreak transmission dynamics and losses can be averted, prevent and contain through proven effective and innovative approaches, and sustainable strategies. In addition, community alertness and empowerment is needed to reduce and minimize contact with infected bats, pigs and raw food products which may have been contaminated sources and host reservoirs diversity. Likewise, comprehensive fruits bats/population migration, phylogenetic mapping of the global Ebola, Zika and NiV/HeV strains genetic variability and evolutionary data and enhanced capacity for data sharing and sequence data analysis for forecasting and modeling to support collaborative clinical research, including methods and standards.</p>
