<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this study, we evaluated viruses with known strain variation, and expected these differences to affect the host genes linked to virus replication as was discovered for PV studies [
 <xref rid="pone.0188333.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Another example of antigenically distinct viruses are DENV which has been classified into four individual serotypes (DENV 1–4) [
 <xref rid="pone.0188333.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0188333.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. DENV like many other viruses has evolved multiple mechanisms to evade the innate immune response and increase virus replication. It is clear that universal vaccination can have major impacts on diseases such as PV, MUV, and RUBV [
 <xref rid="pone.0188333.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0188333.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. One the other hand, vaccine-preventable diseases such as IAV continue to cause significant disease because of use of our inadequate use of vaccines [
 <xref rid="pone.0188333.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Advances in vaccine technology are now providing the opportunity to target new diseases and create enhanced vaccine cell lines. Making a cell line that allows for reduced costs is a rate-limiting feature that will drive prioritization and going forward. For example, RV is a common cause of severe gastroenteritis in children. RV causes a large disease burden ($US 2 billion in 2007) [
 <xref rid="pone.0188333.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], where morbidity and mortality occurs in malnourished infants in low and middle income countries. Vaccines typically confer 85–100% protection against severe disease, while in low income regions protection is around 46–77%, thus the RV vaccination program must rely upon sustained vaccine efficacy level against evolving strains. Cost effectiveness depends largely on the RV mortality rate and the price of the vaccine in relation to the per capita gross domestic product. An enhanced vaccine cell line like Vero cells could save millions of dollars and improve the quality life worldwide.
</p>
