<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Coumestrol is an isoflavonoid-like compound having the ability to inhibit the replication of HSV-1 (both acyclovir sensitive and resistant strains) and also some strains of HSV-2 [
 <xref rid="B172-pharmaceutics-12-00171" ref-type="bibr">172</xref>]. Argenta et al. [
 <xref rid="B173-pharmaceutics-12-00171" ref-type="bibr">173</xref>] have designed a formulation in an effort to obtain a topical product for coumestrol delivery at the level of mucosa. In this approach, the bioactive compound was entrapped by fluid or rigid phospholipid nanoemulsions (dioleylphosphocholine, DOPC and distearoylphosphocholine, DSPC, respectively) dispersed in a hydroxyethylcellulose gel. The effectiveness of the proposed antiviral agents was tested regarding permeation and retention ability on intact and damaged porcine esophageal mucosae and for antiherpes activity on cell culture assays using Vero and GMK AH1 cell lines. The greatest performance of both coumestrol-loaded nanoemulsions NE-COU/DOPC and the same product thickened with hydroxyethylcellulose, HNE-COU/DOPC, as compared to those based on DSPC, relies largely on the physico-chemical properties of the nanoemulsion. The positively charged nanoemulsion showing highest values of ζ-potential may interact with negatively charged surface of mucosa membrane, with beneficial consequences relating to transmucosal delivery of coumestrol [
 <xref rid="B174-pharmaceutics-12-00171" ref-type="bibr">174</xref>]. The length of phospholipids alkyl chain, the number of unsaturations, the lipophilic/hydrophilic balance of the active principle also contributed to the global effect, so that the fluid-state of hydrocarbon chain induced by DOPC explained the interaction between the oil-water interface and mucosa, increasing coumestrol permeation and retention. The low IC
 <sub>50</sub> values proved an enhanced antiviral activity against HSV-1 and HSV-2 after coumestrol formulation using nanoemulsions based on DOPC, which could be considered for advanced studies in order to be introduced in therapy.
</p>
