<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par40">RNA interference (RNAi) is the central antiviral mechanism in insects, particularly in controlling virus infection through degradation of RNA, also known as RNA silencing. The key event in the RNAi pathway is the production of small RNAs from long viral double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. There are three major types of small RNAs: (i) small interfering RNAs (siRNAs), (ii) microRNAs (miRNAs), and (iii) PIWI-interacting RNAs (piRNAs), with siRNAs being the main antiviral responses in mosquito. Mosquito-borne viruses are primarily RNA viruses, with their genomes comprised of single-stranded RNA that is either positive-sense (+) or negative-sense (−) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. During genome replication, these viruses generate dsRNA as replication intermediates [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. The siRNA pathway is responsible for the major antiviral response [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. The viral dsRNA binds to a Dicer-2-R2D2 complex, which consists of a RNase III enzyme, called Dicer-2 (Dcr-2), and an associated protein, called R2D2 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The dsRNA is cleaved by the RNase III domain of Dcr-2 to produce siRNAs of 21–23 nucleotides (nt) in length [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. The siRNAs then activate the RNAi machinery by binding to another multiprotein known as the RNA-induced silencing complex (RISC), in which one of the RNA strands is degraded. The remaining single-stranded RNA (ssRNA) then serves as a guide-strand to detect and degrade cognate viral RNA by host endonuclease, Argonaute-2 (Ago2) in a sequence specific manner [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. One study has demonstrated that silencing of the RNAi pathway during DENV2 infection in 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> enhanced virus replication, indicating their role in controlling viral replication [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Transgenic 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> mosquitoes with RNAi pathway impairment in the midgut were observed to have enhanced SINV replication in the midgut and increased virus dissemination rates [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. In DENV-infected 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>, virus-specific siRNAs (20–23 nt), piRNAs (24–30 nt) and unusually small RNAs (13–19 nt) were detected [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. The siRNA pathway is also an elicited antiviral response in 
 <italic>An. gambiae</italic> against ONNV infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. 
</p>
