<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>First, the current surveillance system operated by the KCDC provides a limited understanding of the characteristics of serious influenza and its disease burden. The hospitalization and mortality surveillance system is being operated, but the data collected are very limited and cannot be used to fully understand the clinical course. It is also difficult to identify the characteristics of viruses associated with severe influenza because specimens are not collected. If it is not possible to collect enough data on severe influenza, it would be difficult to fully assess the burden of influenza. In the US, when assessing the burden of influenza illness, the spectrum of influenza from mild to dead is estimated based on hospitalized patients. Another limitation is the difficulty in assessing the effectiveness of influenza vaccines. Although information regarding influenza vaccination history has been collected, the reliability of the information is insufficient. In order to ensure a reliable vaccination history, it is necessary to approach history taking via various methods such as reviewing past medical records, reviewing vaccine registration data, and in-depth interview. However, it is difficult to obtain such reliable data in the current surveillance system. In addition, evaluating vaccine effectiveness among outpatients would yield unrepresentative results, so data should be collected from both outpatients and inpatients. An example is the surveillance system for influenza vaccine effectiveness in the US. The assessment of the burden of influenza and the evaluation of the vaccine effectiveness is very important not only in the determination of policy direction and assessment of the impact, but also in the risk-communication with people on the influenza. The surveillance system should have a clear objective, and a single system cannot fulfill every purpose. To meet the unmet need of influenza surveillance in Korea, therefore, it does not simply suffice to adjust the data collected from the existing influenza surveillance system.</p>
