<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29">With the increase in mutations, a change in antigenicity can also occur in addition to viral virulence. The capsid proteins have long been a target in producing antibodies against EV-A71 for immune system recognition. VP1 capsid region has been found to possess many antigenic determinants and is considered to play an important role in characterizing antigenicity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>]. Neutralizing antibodies (NAbs) against EV-A71 have been suggested as one of the most important factors in limiting the severity of EV-A71 infections [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>]. Yu 
 <italic>et. al.</italic> (2000) had demonstrated that adult mice were resistant to multiple EV-A71 challenges, thus producing neutralizing antibodies post-infection that play a role in limiting severity of EV-A71 infection. These neutralizing antibodies showed a protective role against EV-A71 by administering hyperimmune serum (1:128) 1-day post-infection in a mouse model. The anti EV-A71 NAbs was found to be able to effectively protect neonatal mice when passively immunized and when delivered and fed by an immunized dam [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>]. Cross-neutralization activity of EV-A71 were also observed among various genotypes using guinea pig and rabbit antisera [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>]. Mizuta 
 <italic>et. al.</italic> observed that guinea pig antisera against genotypes B2 and C1 had higher neutralization titers against genotypes B2, B4, and B5 but lower titers against genotypes A, C1, C2, and C4. Similarly, van der Sanden 
 <italic>et. al.</italic> had similar results with rabbit antisera against genotypes B2 with higher neutralizing titers against genotypes B1 and B2 but lower titers against genotypes C1, C2, and A. However, rabbit sera against genotype C1 showed higher neutralization activity with EV-A71 genotypes A, B, and C [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>]. Huang 
 <italic>et</italic>. 
 <italic>al</italic>. had previously investigated the cross reactivity and antigenic property of human antiserum from EV-A71 infected patients from 1998 to 2008 against human pathogenic EV-A71. Using sero-microneutralization data, an antigenic map was constructed which showed the antigenic diversity of the different genotypes. Based on this map, they had found that genotype B1 and B4 viruses were clustered closely together, genotype C2 and C4 formed a separate cluster from genotype B that was more spread out. Genotype B5, however, had formed its own cluster within the map (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. These data suggest the difference in antigenic properties and the antigenic diversity among the various genotypes of EV-A71. Recently, Huang 
 <italic>et. al.</italic> (2015) had confirmed that the amino acid residues VP1–98, − 145, and − 164 worked in a cooperative manner as antigenic determinants for B4 and B5 strains (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). By creating reverse-genetics EV-A71 viruses containing mutations at VP1–98 K, VP1–145Q, and VP1-164E, they had found that these mutants significantly decreased neutralizing titers by 4-fold against the antisera of 3 of the 6 healthy individuals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. However, it was also noted that none of the single mutation alone was responsible for the antigenic changes, but rather all 3 mutations cooperatively influence the viral antigenic phenotype. With a combination of genotypic shifts, antigenic changes, as well as recombination events, EV-A71 may possess many traits that allow for the virus to continuously persist and escape herd immunity. These factors would thus aid in the event of another outbreak.
</p>
