<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Through conversations with the vector control teams, the most common breeding sites in apartments were flowerpots. While these were commonly positive for 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> pupae, they do not produce large numbers of pupae and therefore resultant adult vectors [
 <xref rid="B70-ijerph-16-01759" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="B72-ijerph-16-01759" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Houses, on the other hand, are much more likely to have gardens or yards with or without patios that contain used or discarded water-holding containers, as well as very large domestic water storage containers (drums and tanks) that are the principal 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> breeding sites, holding 72% to 78% and 65% to 96% of the pupae populations in the wet and dry seasons, respectively, in three study neighbourhoods in Barranquilla [
 <xref rid="B70-ijerph-16-01759" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Previous studies have found that residents living in apartments were at a reduced risk for DENV infections [
 <xref rid="B33-ijerph-16-01759" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-ijerph-16-01759" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-ijerph-16-01759" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], probably due to reduced availability of suitable sites for 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> breeding [
 <xref rid="B41-ijerph-16-01759" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-ijerph-16-01759" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Our data supported these findings since the southwestern area of the city, where the neighbourhoods contained much higher percentages of houses (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01759-f002">Figure 2</xref>A), was an important hotspot during the CHIKV outbreak (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-01759-f003">Figure 3</xref>). Much lower combined 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> spp. premise indexes, an indicator of premises with active breeding sites, were reported in apartments rather than compound houses in Singapore [
 <xref rid="B41-ijerph-16-01759" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Surprisingly, however, 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> was shown to have adapted to breeding in the ‘ecosystems’ present on each floor of high-rise apartment buildings in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia [
 <xref rid="B75-ijerph-16-01759" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>].
</p>
