<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig6">
 <label>Fig. 6</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Role of CCR5 and BDNF in mediating HIV-1 Tat and morphine-induced interactive cytotoxicity in striatal medium spiny neurons (MSNs). A proportion of glial fibrillary acidic protein (GFAP)-immunolabeled striatal astrocytes display punctate patterns of μ-opioid receptor (MOR) (
   <bold>a</bold>) and CCR5 (
   <bold>b</bold>) (43.8 ± 2.4%) immunofluorescence—with some faint immunoreactivity extending into the cell processes; scale bars = 10 μm (
   <bold>a-b</bold>). HIV-1 Tat and morphine are no longer toxic to MSNs when CCR5 is deleted from glia (
   <bold>c-f</bold>). In C57BL/J wild-type mixed glia-MSN co-cultures, Tat is neurotoxic (*
   <italic>p</italic> = 0.001 vs. controls), and co-exposure to morphine enhanced Tat-induced toxicity over a 72-h period (**
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001 vs. controls, 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs. Tat) and antagonized by naloxone (
   <bold>c</bold>). Naloxone or morphine by themselves had no effect on neuronal survival (
   <bold>c</bold>). In co-cultures with CCR5-deficit glia and wild-type neurons, exposure to Tat by itself is significantly toxic (*
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001 vs. controls); however, the enhanced toxicity seen with combined morphine exposure was eliminated (
   <bold>d</bold>). Unexpectedly, morphine co-treatment entirely abolished the toxic effects of Tat, restoring MSN survival to control levels. Pre-treatment with naloxone re-established Tat toxicity, suggesting that the paradoxical protective effects of morphine are mediated by MOR (or perhaps another opioid receptor type) (
   <bold>d</bold>) (see Kim et al. 
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR237">2018</xref>). The neurotoxic patterns seen in CCR5-deficient MSNs and wild-type glial co-cultures are similar to wild-type co-cultures (
   <bold>e</bold>). Co-cultures in which MSNs and glia are both deficient in CCR5 are similar to those in which CCR5 is only deficient in glia (
   <bold>f</bold>). CCR5 deletion alters the expression and processing of BDNF precursor (pro-BDNF) to mature (mBDNF) by mixed-glial cultures (
   <bold>g</bold>). BDNF is expressed by both astroglia and microglia; mBDNF is neuroprotective, while pro-BDNF can promote programmed cell death. mBDNF and pro-BDNF levels were analyzed in conditioned media from wild-type or CCR5-deficient mixed glia treated with Tat ± morphine after 6 h or 24 h to assess pro-BDNF and mBDNF levels. The proportion of pro-BDNF/mBDNF levels was significantly higher in wild-type compared to CCR5-null glia at 24 h (
   <italic>lower row;</italic>
   <bold>g</bold>), suggesting reduced neuronal support. Although morphine significantly decreased pro-BDNF in CCR5-deficient glia at both 6 h and 24 h compared to control levels (
   <italic>not shown</italic>), the pro-BDNF/mBDNF ratios were unaltered (
   <italic>upper and lower rows;</italic>
   <bold>g</bold>). By contrast, combined Tat and morphine significantly decreased the pro-BDNF/mBDNF ratio at 6 h, suggesting transient protection with CCR5 deficiency that was not fully sustained at 24 h (
   <italic>p</italic> = 0.17) (*
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, wild-type vs. CCR5-null) (
   <bold>g</bold>). Exogenous mBDNF is neuroprotective against combined Tat and morphine treatment (
   <bold>h</bold>). Wild-type, mixed glial-MSN co-cultures were treated with mBDNF and Tat, or combined Tat and morphine (represented by dotted survival curves). Tat alone was neurotoxic (*
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05), and Tat was significantly worsened by co-exposing MSNs to morphine (**
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001). The addition of mBDNF (50 ng/ml; 72 h) fully protected MSNs against combined Tat and morphine toxicity, but only tended to protect (albeit not significantly) MSNs treated with Tat alone (
   <sup>#</sup>)(
   <bold>h</bold>). Overall, the results in 
   <bold>c-h</bold> suggest (1) an important role for glial CCR5 in mediating HIV-1 and opiate neurotoxic interactions, (2) that CCR5 deficiency influences signaling through MOR, and (3) that CCR5 (and perhaps MOR) act via a BDNF intermediary to promote or obstruct neuronal survival (Kim et al. 
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR237">2018</xref>). (
   <bold>a-b</bold>) Modified and reprinted with permission from Podhaizer et al. (
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR402">2012</xref>). (
   <bold>c-h</bold>) Modified and reprinted from Kim et al. (
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR237">2018</xref>), which is an open access article distributed under the terms of the 
   <italic>Creative Commons CC BY license</italic>
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="11481_2020_9941_Fig6_HTML" id="MO7" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
