<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Objective</title>
  <p>Since December 2019, an outbreak of corona virus disease 2019 (COVID-19) occurred in Wuhan, and rapidly spread to almost all parts of China. This was followed by prevention programs recommending Chinese medicine (CM) for the prevention. In order to provide evidence for CM recommendations, we reviewed ancient classics and human studies.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>Historical records on prevention and treatment of infections in CM classics, clinical evidence of CM on the prevention of severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) and H1N1 influenza, and CM prevention programs issued by health authorities in China since the COVID-19 outbreak were retrieved from different databases and websites till 12 February, 2020. Research evidence included data from clinical trials, cohort or other population studies using CM for preventing contagious respiratory virus diseases.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>The use of CM to prevent epidemics of infectious diseases was traced back to ancient Chinese practice cited in Huangdi’s Internal Classic (Huang Di Nei Jing) where preventive effects were recorded. There were 3 studies using CM for prevention of SARS and 4 studies for H1N1 influenza. None of the participants who took CM contracted SARS in the 3 studies. The infection rate of H1N1 influenza in the CM group was significantly lower than the non-CM group (relative risk 0.36, 95% confidence interval 0.24–0.52; n=4). For prevention of COVID-19, 23 provinces in China issued CM programs. The main principles of CM use were to tonify qi to protect from external pathogens, disperse wind and discharge heat, and resolve dampness. The most frequently used herbs included 
   <italic>Radix astragali</italic> (Huangqi), 
   <italic>Radix glycyrrhizae</italic> (Gancao), 
   <italic>Radix saposhnikoviae</italic> (Fangfeng), 
   <italic>Rhizoma Atractylodis Macrocephalae</italic> (Baizhu), 
   <italic>Lonicerae Japonicae Flos</italic> (Jinyinhua), and 
   <italic>Fructus forsythia</italic> (Lianqiao).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>Based on historical records and human evidence of SARS and H1N1 influenza prevention, Chinese herbal formula could be an alternative approach for prevention of COVID-19 in high-risk population. Prospective, rigorous population studies are warranted to confirm the potential preventive effect of CM.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Electronic Supplementary Material</title>
  <p>Supplementary material is available in the online version of this article at 10.1007/s11655-020-3192-6.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
