<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">The docking protocol was done against the SARS-CoV-2 ACE2 receptor (PDB code = 6M0J), the SARS-CoV-2 3CL protease (PDB code = 1Q2W) and its four active sites. The active sites were isolated and used as dummy atoms. The parameters and charges were assigned with the MMFF94x force field. After alpha-site spheres were generated using the site finder module of MOE, the structural model of the compounds were docked on the surface of the interior of the receptor using the DOCK module of MOE (Abdel-Rhman et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2019</xref>). The Dock scoring in MOE software was done through the London dG scoring function and has been upgraded by two unrelated refinement methods. Auto rotatable bonds were allowed, and the best five binding poses were directed for analysis to achieve the best score. We used the database browsers to compare the docking poses to the ligand in the co-crystallized structure and to obtain RMSD of the docking pose. To rank the binding affinity of the synthesized compounds to the protein molecule, the binding free energy and hydrogen bonds between the compounds and amino acid in the receptor were calculated (Abdellattif et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2018</xref>; Ketan et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2020</xref>). Evaluation of the hydrogen bonds was done by measuring the hydrogen bond length, which does not exceed 3.5 A°. Also, the RMSD of the drug position compared to the docking pose was used in the ranking. RMSD, as well as the mode of interaction of the native ligand within the structure of the receptor, was used as a standard docked model (Abdel-Rhman et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2019</xref>; Abdellattif et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2018</xref>; Althagafi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2019</xref>; Mashat et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2019</xref>; Ketan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2020</xref>).
</p>
