<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For contrast with the stochastic model above, a simple regression forecast was conducted based solely on outbreaks of size 10 or greater. Time series for all 18 such prior outbreaks were obtained, including seven prior ones from DRC, dating back to 1976 (
 <bold>
  <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0213190.s001">S1 Table</xref>; 
  <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0213190.s003">S2 Fig</xref>
 </bold>).[
 <xref rid="pone.0213190.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0213190.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0213190.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0213190.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0213190.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] One (5.6%) of the 18 prior outbreaks in our sample (the 2013–2016 West Africa outbreak) achieved a large size (over 28,000 cases). No exclusions were made; no attempt to model specific features of the April-July 2018 outbreak was conducted. The regression model predicted the outbreak size based on values of the outbreak size at a specific earlier time. The beginning of each outbreak was not reliably characterized; therefore, all time-series were aligned on the day they reached 10 cases. In the April-July 2018 outbreak, we observed cases over the period from April 4 to May 27 (day 0 to day 53). May 27 corresponded to day 34 since reaching 10 reported cases. For the prior 18 outbreaks, linear interpolation was used to obtain the number of cases on day 34 (after reaching 10 cases). To reduce the influence of outliers and high leverage points, and to improve linearity, we calculated the pseudologarithm transform f(x) = arcsinh(x/2), asymptotically logarithmic but well-behaved at 0. We used non-parametric Theil-Sen regression (R-package 
 <italic>mblm</italic>) followed by calculation of the resulting prediction interval for a new observation.[
 <xref rid="pone.0213190.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0213190.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] Finally, we reported the median and 95% central coverage intervals for the prediction distribution conditional on the value being no smaller than the observed value on day 34. Sensitivity analysis was conducted using ordinary least squares regression. These analyses were conducted using R 3.4.2 (R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria).
</p>
