<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11">Hepatitis E virus is a positive-stranded RNA virus with a genome of ~7.2 kb belonging to the family 
 <italic>Hepeviridae</italic>. Four major genotypes are discerned and novel lineages of hepatitis E viruses have been identified in rabbits, rats, wild boar, ferrets and possibly foxes more recently [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>]. Different genotypes of hepatitis E virus determine differences in epidemiology; genotype 1 is usually seen in developing countries and causes community-level outbreaks while genotype 3 is usually seen in developed countries and rarely causes outbreaks. Hepatitis E virus is transmitted via the faecal-oral route primarily via faecal contamination of water supplies, shellfish and contaminated animal meat, and possibly through zoonosis from pigs. Human-to-human transmission of the virus is rare. Outbreaks and sporadic cases occur worldwide; the virus is most prevalent in East and South Asia and endemic in Asia, Africa and Mexico [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>]. An estimated 20 million hepatitis E infections occur worldwide yearly, which are usually self-limited and resolve within 4–6 weeks. Over three million cases of acute fulminant hepatitis E however occur resulting in over 50,000 deaths [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>]. Infection with hepatitis E virus is frequent in children in developing countries, but the disease is mostly asymptomatic or causes a very mild illness without jaundice. It causes acute sporadic and epidemic viral hepatitis most commonly in young adults aged 15–40 years with symptoms including jaundice, anorexia, hepatomegaly, abdominal pain and tenderness, nausea, vomiting, and fever that last for up to 2 weeks. A unique disease profile has been observed in pregnant women, where infections with HEV often result in fulminant liver failure, stillbirth and death in 25 % of cases. Treatment and vaccines are unavailable, but currently in development [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>].
</p>
