<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although the multivalent interaction of GRFT with high-mannose oligosaccharides is believed to account for most of its picomolar antiviral potency, the looser correlation between gp120-binding ability and HIV inhibitory potency for the binding site mutants of GRFT suggests the possibility of another unknown antiviral mechanism of GRFT that is not based on simple gp120 binding [
 <xref rid="B21-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. According to an isothermal titration calorimetry binding study, GRFT bound to glucose and 
 <italic>N</italic>-acetyl glucosamine in a similar fashion to that of mannose, demonstrating its flexible specificity in binding carbohydrates [
 <xref rid="B23-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. This binding flexibility might have an implication for its broad antiviral spectrum. To study the potential role of the GRFT dimer in the suppression of HIV-1 infectivity, either two or four amino acids were inserted at the dimerization interface of GRFT. This resulted in a monomeric form of GRFT (mGRFT) with greatly reduced antiviral activity against HIV-1. These results further emphasize the importance of multivalent interactions between dimeric GRFT and oligosaccharides present on HIV envelope glycoproteins for the successful cross-linking and aggregation of viral particles [
 <xref rid="B20-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Interestingly, an obligate dimer of GRFT with a peptide linker between the two subunits altered the structure of gp120 by exposing the CD4 binding site. However, GRFT-linker-GRFT with mutated carbohydrate-binding sites largely lost this ability [
 <xref rid="B37-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. On the other hand, the glycan-specific DC-SIGN receptor binds the virus and mediates its transfer to CD4+ cells [
 <xref rid="B38-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. In this regard, GRFT’s ability to partially block gp120 from binding to human DC-SIGN [
 <xref rid="B34-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] and its potent inhibition of DC-SIGN-dependent transfer of HIV-1 [
 <xref rid="B38-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] could synergize with its antiviral action by blocking viral entry. To maximize the antiviral synergy caused by GRFT multimerization, tandem repeats of mGRFT (mGRFT tandemers) were engineered. They displayed picomolar-level antiviral activity in whole-cell anti-HIV assays [
 <xref rid="B37-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. However, since mGRFT tandemers could not aggregate HIV virions, Moulaei et al. suggested the intra-virion crosslinking of HIV envelope glycoproteins may be more integral to their antiviral activity [
 <xref rid="B36-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Inter-virion aggregation or clustering of HIV-1 gp120 on the viral membrane was found to be related to neutralization potency [
 <xref rid="B35-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. 
</p>
