<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0190">Since ancient times, Indian herbs have been used as a treatment and preventive strategy for several diseases, including respiratory viral infections. The benefit of using these herbs in viral respiratory infections is to build immune stimulating and inflammation modulating effects of manage the immune system. Holistic approach of AYUSH systems of medicine gives focus on prevention through lifestyle modification, dietary management, prophylactic interventions for improving the immunity and simple remedies based on presentation of the symptoms (
 <xref rid="bb0550" ref-type="bibr">AYUSH, 2020</xref>). Indian preventive and prophylactic medicinal plants recommended by AYUSH for COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Also, other studies on coronavirus using medicinal plants are rather minimal in India, a study has shown anti-mouse coronaviral activity (a surrogate of SARS-CoV) by the plants 
 <italic>Indigofera tinctoria</italic> (
 <italic>AO</italic>), 
 <italic>Vitex trifolia</italic>, 
 <italic>Gymnema sylvestre</italic>, 
 <italic>Abutilon indicum</italic>, 
 <italic>Leucas aspera</italic>, 
 <italic>Cassia alata</italic>, 
 <italic>Sphaeranthus indicus</italic>, 
 <italic>Clitoriaternatea</italic>, 
 <italic>Clerodendruminerme Gaertn</italic>, 
 <italic>Pergulariadaemi</italic> and 
 <italic>Evolvulus alsinoides</italic> in Tamil Nadu (
 <xref rid="bb0770" ref-type="bibr">Vimalanathan et al., 2009</xref>). Among them 
 <italic>Vitex trifolia and Sphaeranthus indicus</italic> have been found to reduce inflammatory cytokines using the NF-kB pathway, a pathway that has been implicated in respiratory distress in SARS-CoV (
 <xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">Alam et al., 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0720" ref-type="bibr">Srivastava et al., 2015</xref>). 
 <italic>Clitoria ternatea</italic> has been identified as a metalloproteinase inhibitor, ADAM17, a metalloproteinase that is involved in ACE shredding can be targeted using this plant, as ACE-2 shredding has been associated with an increased formation of viruses (
 <xref rid="bb0505" ref-type="bibr">Maity et al., 2012</xref>). The plants 
 <italic>Glycyrrhiza glabra</italic> (
 <xref rid="bb0580" ref-type="bibr">Nourazarian, 2015</xref>) and 
 <italic>Allium sativum</italic> (
 <xref rid="bb0385" ref-type="bibr">Keyaerts et al., 2007</xref>) have been known to target the viral replication of SARS-CoV, arising as promising candidates against SARS-CoV-2. 
 <italic>Clerodendrum inerme Gaertn</italic>, another herb has been found to have the potential to inactivate the viral ribosome, this can be further investigated for its utility as a drug targeting SARS-CoV-2 protein translation (
 <xref rid="bb0585" ref-type="bibr">Olivieri et al., 1996</xref>). Similarly, 
 <italic>Strobilanthes Cusia</italic> (
 <xref rid="bb0765" ref-type="bibr">Tsai et al., 2020</xref>) blocked the viral RNA genome synthesis and induced papain like protease activity targeting the HCoV. In Asia, Himalayan forests are abundantly flourished with rich medicinal plant species and a study has documented the presence of ethnomedicinal plants against bronchitis (
 <xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">Amber et al., 2017</xref>). The study screened the antiviral plant properties against bronchitis, which showed that 
 <italic>Hyoscyamus niger</italic>, 
 <italic>Justicia adhatoda</italic> and 
 <italic>Verbascum thapsus</italic> reduced infections caused by influenza viruses. The molecular mechanism by which these plants target influenza virus can be studied to understand if they attack any molecules overlapping between SARS-CoV-2 and the Influenza viruses. 
 <italic>Hyoscyamus niger</italic> was found to be a bronchodilator and also had inhibitory effects on Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> channel (
 <xref rid="bb0245" ref-type="bibr">Gilani et al., 2008</xref>). This could be used to target the orf3a Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>channels that trigger various downstream pathways upon viral infection. Most importantly, various medicinal plants have shown inhibitory effects against ACE, and these include 
 <italic>Coriandrum sativum</italic> (
 <xref rid="bb0330" ref-type="bibr">Hussain et al., 2018</xref>), 
 <italic>Boerhaavia diffusa</italic>, 
 <italic>Cynara scolymus</italic>, 
 <italic>Coscinium fenestratum</italic>, 
 <italic>Punicagranatum Cassia occidentalis</italic> and 
 <italic>Embeliaribes</italic>. Among them, 
 <italic>Punicagranatum</italic> showed a competitive mode of action while the rest were non-specific inhibitors (
 <xref rid="bb0395" ref-type="bibr">Khan and Kumar, 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0625" ref-type="bibr">Prathapan et al., 2013</xref>). These plants need to be studied further to examine their actual effects on the entry of SARS-CoV-2 into the host cell. One of the tropical species in the Acanthaceae family, 
 <italic>Andrographis paniculata</italic> (kalmegh) present in South Asia has a strong treating capacity of viral respiratory infections in Ayurvedic and other medicinal systems (
 <xref rid="bb0880" ref-type="bibr">Yarnell, 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">Arora et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr">Coon and Ernst, 2004</xref>). It was noted that 
 <italic>Andrographis paniculata</italic> suppressed increased NOD-like receptor protein 3 (NLRP3), caspase-1, and interleukin-1β molecules which are extensively involved in the pathogenesis of SARS-COV and likely SARS-CoV-2 as well (
 <xref rid="bb0470" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2020a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0475" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2020b</xref>). 
 <italic>Salacia oblonga</italic> (
 <xref rid="bb0295" ref-type="bibr">He et al., 2011</xref>) another plant from Tamil Nadu has also displayed suppressive effects on angiotensin II, AT1 signal, which was related to lung damage. Many plants have also shown inhibitory actions towards HIV proteases, these plants can be promising drugs for COVID-19. They include, 
 <italic>Acacia nilotica</italic> (
 <xref rid="bb0680" ref-type="bibr">Shanti, 2016</xref>), 
 <italic>Eugenia jambolana</italic> (
 <xref rid="bb0590" ref-type="bibr">Otake et al., 1995</xref>), 
 <italic>Euphorbia granulate</italic> (
 <xref rid="bb0680" ref-type="bibr">Shanti, 2016</xref>). Some plants like 
 <italic>Ocimum sanctum</italic> (
 <xref rid="bb0650" ref-type="bibr">Rege and Chowdhary, 2014</xref>), 
 <italic>Ocimumkilim and scharicum</italic> (
 <xref rid="bb0755" ref-type="bibr">Thayil Seema and Thyagarajan, 2016</xref>), 
 <italic>Solanum nigrum</italic> (
 <xref rid="bb0895" ref-type="bibr">Yu, 2004</xref>), 
 <italic>Vitex negundo</italic> (
 <xref rid="bb0570" ref-type="bibr">NAIR, 2012</xref>) have been known to target the reverse transcriptase activity of HIV and can be studied for activity against SARS-CoV-2 as well. Further, 
 <italic>Sambucus ebulus</italic> (
 <xref rid="bb0235" ref-type="bibr">Ganjhu et al., 2015</xref>) has been known to inhibit the activity of enveloped viruses and can also be used to target this virus. These medicinal plants can be used to ameliorate the symptoms of COVID-19. Though many medicinal plants have been identified, a lot of research has to be carried out for the development of drug specific to SARS-CoV-2. Therefore, it is important to explore the effect of these prescribed traditional medicines on SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="t0025" ref-type="table">Table.5</xref>). Various Indian medicinal plants that have been widely used for respiratory diseases have been included (
 <xref rid="ec0005" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 1</xref>).
</p>
