<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat-1003059-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003059.g007</object-id>
 <label>Figure 7</label>
 <caption>
  <title>NS1 inhibits the Riplet-dependent RIG-I ubiquitination and IFN induction in murine cells.</title>
  <p>(
   <bold>A</bold>) Mouse Hepa 1.6 cells were transfected with vector or Flag-tagged mRiplet with or without NS1-PR8. WCLs were subjected to IP with RIG-I antibody, followed by IB with anti-Ub or anti-RIG-I antibody. Expression of mRiplet, NS1, and ubiquitin (Ub) was determined in the WCLs by IB with anti-Flag, anti-NS1 or anti-Ub antibody. (
   <bold>B</bold>) Mouse Hepa1.6 cells were transfected with IFN-β luciferase reporter plasmid together with empty vector or mRIG-I together with or without mRiplet and NS1-PR8. At 24 h posttransfection, cells were lysed and subjected to luciferase assay. Data shown is representative of 3 independent experiments and depicted is the mean ± SD (n = 3). (
   <bold>C</bold>) Influenza NS1 protein specifically inhibits the Riplet-dependent ubiquitination of mouse RIG-I. Hepa1.6 cells were transiently transfected with non-silencing control siRNA (si.C), or with a siRNA specific for mouse Riplet (si.Riplet) together with empty vector or NS1-PR8. At 24 h posttransfection, cells were infected with SeV (50 HA units/ml) for 22 h. WCLs were used for IP with anti-RIG-I antibody, followed by IB with anti-Ub or anti-RIG-I antibody. (
   <bold>D–F</bold>) Knockdown of endogenous Riplet in mouse embryonic fibroblasts enhances influenza A virus replication. WT or 
   <italic>TRIM25 −/−</italic> MEFs were transfected with non-silencing control siRNA (si.C), or with a siRNA specific for mouse Riplet (si.Riplet). At 30 h posttransfection, cells were infected with recombinant A/PR/8/34 WT virus (MOI 0.1). Knockdown of endogenous Riplet was confirmed by RT-PCR (
   <bold>D</bold>). Supernatants were assayed for progeny virus yields 24 h postinfection in standard plaque titrations (
   <bold>E</bold>). Virus yields are depicted in Pfu/ml. The results of three independent experiments are shown. Furthermore, viral NS1 protein expression was determined in the WCLs of infected cells (
   <bold>F</bold>).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1003059.g007" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
