<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Targeted pathogen monitoring in arthropods is an important part of surveillance programs for the circulation of vector-borne agents and likely to predict probable disease emergence in susceptible human or animal populations [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007334.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The recent detection of invasive 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitoes in Turkey, in parallel with the territorial expansion identified in several countries, have raised concerns about the reestablishment of these species as well as emergence of associated viruses [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007334.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0007334.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. This study was carried out to investigate the presence of the invasive 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> species around the sites of previous detection and fill the current information gap on the circulation of viruses potentially spread by these mosquitoes. Specimen collection encompassed mosquito active seasons for two consecutive years, utilizing human landing catches, considered as a the most highly sensitive and effective approach for sampling anthropophilic 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> species [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007334.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. We detected 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> and 
 <italic>Cx</italic>. 
 <italic>pipiens</italic> s.l. in all provinces targeted for surveillance and throughout the screening period (
 <bold>
  <xref rid="pntd.0007334.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
 </bold>). However, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> was lacking in the Trabzon province, despite being identified regularly in the remaining provinces. 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> was detected in high frequencies in all sampling sites, and comprised 89.6% of the study cohort overall. These findings indicate that these invasive 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> are firmly established in the coastal Black Sea region of northeastern Turkey, at least in certain locations. It has been previously suggested that further spread of these species to the ports around the Black Sea via ships and ferries is probable, as well as dispersion via ground transportation into major cities of Turkey [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007334.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Therefore, continuous and integrated surveillance of invasive mosquitoes are imperative to monitor the spread of these species further into Asia Minor and to implement effective control strategies as become necessary.
</p>
