<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Many states plan to enlist commercial pharmacies in the dispensing of SNS antiviral drugs during future influenza pandemics ( 
 <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>20</italic>
 </xref>
 <italic>–</italic>
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>22</italic>
 </xref>
 <italic>,</italic>
 <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>34</italic>
 </xref> ). We have developed and demonstrated a simple, extensible, facility-location model for designing pharmacy-based antiviral drug distribution networks that effectively reach target populations. This model has been parameterized for the state of Texas and incorporated into a Web-based decision-support tool ( 
 <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>28</italic>
 </xref> ) for the Texas DSHS ( 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figures 5</xref> , 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> ). The user can opt to target the underinsured or total population statewide or within any specified counties and to exclude or include particular pharmacies and pharmacy chains. On the basis of user input, the tool solves a family of optimization models, spanning the full range of possible network sizes, and presents the structure and performance of the optimized networks by using interactive graphs and maps. The tool is designed for use by Texas DSHS staff, who have Web-based access to it. Although this implementation is specific for Texas, the general model structure is readily adaptable to other jurisdictions. Adaptation requires specification of geographic units (e.g., ZIP code areas or counties), distances between each pair of units, estimated target population sizes within each unit, and number of pharmacies from each eligible chain located within the unit. The model can be easily extended to other states by using data available through the US Census Bureau and state pharmacy associations ( 
 <xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>29</italic>
 </xref> , 
 <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>35</italic>
 </xref> ).
</p>
