<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several other X‐linked genes (such as those for the ILs, FOXP3, XIST, and TLR7/8) and Y‐linked genes (SRY and SOX9) may also explain sex differences (Ghosh &amp; Klein, 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). These and other immune regulatory genes encoded by the X and Y chromosomes may explain lower viral loads and reduced inflammation in women compared to men (Conti &amp; Younes, 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>; Márquez, Trowbridge, Kuchel, Banchereau, &amp; Ucar, 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>; Table 
 <xref rid="bph15207-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>). In particular, the two X chromosomes seem to regulate the immune system even if one of them is inactive. The X chromosome regulates the immune system also modulating other proteins, including 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/LigandDisplayForward?ligandId=5077" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">CD40L</ext-link>, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/ObjectDisplayForward?objectId=70" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">CXCR3</ext-link>, and 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/ObjectDisplayForward?objectId=1758" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">TLR8</ext-link>. These can be up‐regulated in women and can determine the response to viral infections as well as to vaccinations. A differentially expressed genes (DEGs) network was constructed to identify a specific gene signature characterizing SARS‐CoV‐2 infection (Fagone et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Intriguingly, 10 DEGs were modulated by sex hormones. Six DEGs were 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/ObjectDisplayForward?objectId=628" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">androgen receptor‐</ext-link>regulated, with genes for 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/LigandDisplayForward?ligandId=808" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">CCL20</ext-link> and 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/LigandDisplayForward?ligandId=819" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">CXCL1</ext-link> being up‐regulated, whereas those for THBD, HEY2, BBOX1 and 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/ObjectDisplayForward?objectId=1552" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">MYLK</ext-link> were down‐regulated. Four DEGs were regulated by 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/ObjectDisplayForward?objectId=620%26familyId=96%26familyType=NHR" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">oestrogen receptor‐α</ext-link>, with C3 and 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/LigandDisplayForward?ligandId=989" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">EDN1</ext-link> genes being up‐regulated and 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/ObjectDisplayForward?objectId=2144" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">PDK4</ext-link> and VTCN1 down‐regulated. Moreover, sex differences in the immune response, determined by genes and hormones (Ghosh &amp; Klein, 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Klein &amp; Flanagan, 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>), may play an important role in modulating the severity of COVID‐19. Also, the number of CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells differs between sexes, being higher in women with a better immune response (Conti &amp; Younes, 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Finally, the number of sex‐independent, non‐genetic factors that can change susceptibility and mortality is enormous, and many other factors are likely to be considered, including gender and cultural habits in different countries. For example, an outbreak in the Republic of Korea exhibited a high incidence of cases in women due to social and religious events occurring at the time (Report on the Epidemiological Features of Coronavirus Disease 2019 [COVID‐19] Outbreak in the Republic of Korea from January 19 to March 2, 2020). Smoking can be another gender‐related habit and independent risk factor for COVID‐19 exacerbation. Nevertheless, the role of smoking on ACE/ACE2 ratio and function is not clear. In different studies, both an increase in ACE2 expression (Cai, 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>) and a decrease in enzyme activity have been described (Yuan et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0086" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). We can speculate that higher levels of ACE2 (more virus receptors) may allow for more virus entry, while ACE2 down‐regulation (less protection conferred by ACE2 anti‐inflammatory function) may explain, at least in part, COVID‐19 severity in smokers.
</p>
