<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Antibodies play a critical role in the clearance of CHIKV infections by both neutralizing virus infection and enhancing the clearance of virally infected cells [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Potent neutralizing antibodies, composed of multiple subclasses, are directed against the E2 protein [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Early induction of anti-CHIKV anti-E2 human IgG3 subclass antibodies successfully clear CHIKV infections and lead to faster recovery. In adult mice, the most effective vaccine candidates were CHIK VLPs with no adjuvant or VLP plus QuilA, both administered by IM injections. Both of these vaccine formulations elicited antibodies directed against both the E1 and E2 proteins. A combination of robust IgG1, IgG2c, and IgG3 anti-E1 responses were detected [
 <bold>
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0007316.g002">Fig 2F–2H</xref>
 </bold>]. In contrast, IgG3 antibodies were the predominant anti-E2 response elicited by these vaccines, with lower titers of pro-inflammatory IgG2c elicited by VLP alone or IgG1 by VLP vaccines formulated with QuilA [
 <bold>
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0007316.g002">Fig 2J–2L</xref>
 </bold>]. Mouse IgG3, which is not a homolog of human IgG3, is induced independently of T-cell help and appears shortly after vaccination [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. This anti-CHIKV IgG3 response may enhance clearance of CHIKV infected cells in adult mice, since CD4 knockout mice are still able to control and clear CHIK virus as effectively as wild-type mice [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In contrast, B cell deficient mice (μMT) remain persistently infected [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Mouse IgG3 binds FcγRI, but is thought to function primarily through activation of complement [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. These anti-E1 and anti-E2 responses were absent in aged mice vaccinated with CHIK VLPs or VLP plus QuilA. The sera from aged mice vaccinated did react with whole VLP preparations by ELISA, with similar levels of anti-VLP IgG1 as the adult mice. Perhaps the presence of these antibodies that did not bind specifically to soluble E1 or E2, contributed to CHIKV disease enhancement in these animals. A phenomenon coined antibody-dependendent enhancement has been described for dengue and other viruses whereby non-neutralizing antibodies facilitate entry of antibody-bound virions via FcγR [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Antibody-dependent enhancement has also been observed 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> with another alphavirus, Ross River Virus [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. A more recent study shows that convalescent sera from CHIKV-infected subjects mediates enhanced binding, but not enhanced replication of CHIKV in primary human monocytes and B cells 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> via FcγRs [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. In contrast, increased chikungunya viral replication is observed in Raw 264.7 mouse macrophages in the presence of mouse anti-CHIKV IgG 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>. Mice infected with CHIKV and then treated with subneutralizing levels of anti-CHIKV IgG also develop higher levels of viremia and disease as measured by foot swelling [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].
</p>
