<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In contrast to our observations in CHIKV-infected aged mice, a study by Uhrlaub 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] found that CHIKV infections resulted in more severe infections in aged mice. There are a few key differences between our studies. The ages of the adult and aged mice were similar, but we used female mice, while Uhrlaub 
 <italic>et al</italic>. used male mice. They also used a different CHIKV strain: SL15649. This strain resulted in a different disease progression in adult male mice than what we observed in adult female mice: foot-swelling was biphasic with two peaks on days 3 and then on day 8 with SL15649 infection, while we observed one main peak on day 7 with LR2006-OPY1. While the progression of CHIKV-associated foot swelling we observed is comparable to what has been previously published by Gardner et al [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] and Metz et al [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] using CHIKV LR2006 OPY1 strain, biphasic foot-swelling has also been in observed with this same strain at 10
 <sup>6</sup> CCID
 <sub>50</sub> in female mice [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] and at 10
 <sup>3</sup> focus-forming units in female and male mice [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Thus, the use of different strains cannot be solely responsible for the difference in results. While not previously anticipated in our study, the stark difference in results may have to do with gender in aged mice. A longitudinal, retrospective study on prognostic factors of inhospital deaths in elderly patients by L. Godaert 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007316.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] found that the male sex was an independent predictor of inhospital deaths due to CHIKV infection. Thus, perhaps in aged mice, the male sex may also predispose them to more severe disease. In addition study by Uhrlaub 
 <italic>et al</italic>. also showed that CD4+ T cells and neutralizing antibody responses elicited by CHIKV infections were significantly decreased in aged, male mice compared to the adult, male mice. Thus overall, even in the male mice, the VLP vaccine formulations would likely also elicit poor protective responses as compared to those in adult mice.
</p>
