<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="sec1">In the last 15 years, humans have witnessed 5 pandemic diseases, severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS), Swine flu, Ebola, Middle East respiratory syndrome (MERS), and coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), where both MERS and COVID-19 are actively present within our community, with the latter having more severe complications and infection rates in recent times. COVID-19 is an infectious disease caused by the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV2) virus, which was actively revealed in Wuhan, China in December 2019 and later sequenced in January 2020.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>
 </sup> In just a period of 2 months (March 2020), the disease had spread to 90% of the countries on our planet. In parallel, there remains a great interest in the biosensors and nanoscale visualization/characterization tools such as the electron microscopy (EM), atomic force microscopy (AFM), and X-ray diffraction (XRD) for the early detection and revealing prognostic features of a given pathogen.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref>
 </sup> Recent advances have also extended the use of these advanced sensing techniques into the development of high-throughput devices capable of screening a large number of candidate compounds for quick drug discovery and vaccine development during pandemics.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref>
 </sup> Most of the latest sensors currently available in both academia and industry are based on the electrical or optical transduction methods.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>
 </sup> These include single-molecule sensors,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref9">9</xref>
 </sup> wearable devices,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>
 </sup> ingestible capsules,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>
 </sup> disposable screen-printed electrodes,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref>
 </sup> and hand-held portable instruments
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>
 </sup> which could actively detect the infectious disease-causing pathogen at an early stage of the infection. Nevertheless, despite their vast availability and well-known advantages in academia, the full potential of the biosensing and characterization tools is yet to be harnessed in on-site applications, such as during the outbreak of an infectious disease. Certainly, there are scientific challenges and opportunities for bio/chemical sensors before they can live up to the expectation of accurate, precise, and early diagnosis of emerging diseases. It is in this context that we present an analysis of the state of art instruments and technologies, in particular concerning COVID-19, for the detection and analysis of pandemic strains. In general, we can segregate the detection of viruses into three main categories: (1) direct detection of the virus, (2) viral RNA/DNA detection, and (3) antibody detection.
</p>
