<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">The reliance on phylodynamic methods for estimating a pathogen’s population-level characteristics (e.g., effective population size) and their relationships with epidemiological data suffers from a high cost – increasing the number of inference models, and thus parameters associated with these models, requires an even greater increase in the information content, or phylogenetic resolution, of the sequence alignment and associated phenotypic data. Low coverage [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] and the presence of organism- or sequencing-mediated recombination [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], can skew estimates of the evolutionary rate and even impact the underlying tree topology, particularly when dealing with priors in the Bayesian statistical framework commonly used for phylodynamic inference. Programs such as SplitsTree [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] can take as input a nucleotide alignment and output a network in which the dual origins of recombinant sequences are displayed in a phylogenetic-like context. However, network-reconstructing programs have difficulty distinguishing actual recombination events from phylogenetic uncertainty, and branch lengths do not usually reflect true evolutionary distances [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Despite much work ongoing in this area, there are currently no broadly applicable methods that are able to reconstruct phylogenetic network graphs that explicitly depict recombination and allow for phylodynamic inference. Although the Bayesian framework has shown to be fairly robust with the inclusion of recombinant sequences in large population studies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], the inclusion threshold has not been thoroughly investigated and is likely dependent on a number of factors, such as sample size and sequence length. Recombinant sequences are thus usually removed prior to analysis; however, the ability to incorporate recombinant sequences is imperative given our knowledge of the role of recombination in virus adaptation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], for example. More details on methods that can potentially account for recombination, applicable to a variety of pathogens, are discussed by Martin, Lemey, &amp; Posada [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].
</p>
