<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">With the expansion of phylodynamic methods to global epidemics, theoretical studies have found that inferences of infection dynamics within the coalescent framework are limited by the assumption of a freely mixing population [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. This assumption is often violated with the inclusion of several isolated geographical areas with single or few pathogen introductions. Without considering this factor, population structure within a phylogeny can severely bias inferences of the evolutionary history and associated epidemiological parameters [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. To overcome this limitation, software packages such as BEAST (Bayesian Evolutionary Analysis Sampling Trees) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>] have recently developed algorithms that allow for the integration of coalescent, mathematical, and spatial diffusion models [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. More importantly, BEAST readily implements a comparative phylogenetic approach, which incorporates parameterization of phenotypic trait evolution to identify predictors of population dynamics and spatial spread, all of which are estimated/assessed simultaneously during reconstruction of the evolutionary history [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. Statistical evaluation of the risk factors for pathogen population growth and spread can be performed concurrently with the assessment of phylogenetic resolution within the data [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>], discussed above as a challenge to complex phylodynamic analyses. For example, in the absence of strong phylogenetic resolution, Bayesian statistics are more sensitive to long-branch attraction bias [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>], wherein rapidly evolving lineages appear to be closely related, regardless of their true evolutionary relationships. This phenomenon, therefore, influences inferences of spatiotemporal spread of the studied pathogen, as well as estimation of the relationship of pathogen population behavior with potential risk factors, such as climate change, host and/or vector distribution, accessibility and so on. The influence of low-resolution molecular data on the reliability of phylodynamic inferences highlights the importance of the implementation of the method described by Vrancken et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>], or even a priori estimation of the phylogenetic and temporal resolution (sufficient time between sampling) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>].
</p>
