<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24">Unlike other phylogenetic frameworks, Bayesian inference enables utilization of prior knowledge in the form of prior distributions (in combination with information provided by the data); however, abuse of prior knowledge is possible and can lead to incorrect conclusions. Even within the Bayesian school of thought, scientists do not always agree with regard to the specification of prior distributions under certain conditions. The incorporation of prior information is, however, intuitively appealing, as it allows one to rationalize the probability of an estimate based on previous knowledge of the typical behavior of the parameter among populations of the organism under study. But what can we do if we have no knowledge regarding a particular organism or population? This has become a more pertinent issue recently with the increasing rate of discovery, facilitated by NGS, of organisms for which we have limited prior knowledge, such as novel viruses and bacteria, [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. One of the advantages of the Bayesian phylodynamic approach is the ability to test multiple hypotheses regarding the evolution or epidemiological models used to describe infectious disease behavior, but because of the intricate relationship of these models, reliable inferences require testing of all combinations of the individual proposed models. Although often neglected due to computational complexity, improved estimates of marginal likelihoods used for statistical model comparison have been demonstrated with less computational effort [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. Additionally, if we know that we know nothing about the parameter in question, then, in fact, we know something. Referred to as the “objective Bayesian” approach, this ideal allows researchers to alter a normally “subjective” prior to create one that is minimally informative. This term is used because the impact of this type of prior on parameter estimation can be controlled to a minimum, allowing the data to dominate the analytical process and conclusions drawn [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. Although similarly appealing, this approach can be particularly problematic with small datasets [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>] or biased datasets, such as the exclusion of potential intermediate sampling locations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. The expanding volume of sequence data and increasing efforts to combine epidemiological and laboratory data in open access locations can help to improve evolutionary estimates. Additionally, the growing availability of data and collaboration can accelerate our understanding of the emergence and spread of infectious diseases through coordinated efforts by multi-disciplinary researchers across various institutions and public health organizations. More detail on the benefits of open access databases and data sharing in the context of phylogenetic epidemiology is reviewed in [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>] and [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>].
</p>
