<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Herpesviruses, a large and diverse family of enveloped viruses with double-stranded DNA genomes, can bring about lifelong, latent infections (
 <xref rid="B118" ref-type="bibr">Pellet and Roizman, 2013</xref>). These viruses are classified as three subfamilies, alpha-, beta-, and gamma-, on the basis of their genome sequences and biological properties (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">Davison et al., 2009</xref>). In alpha-herpesviruses, herpes simplex virus types 1 and 2 (HSV-1 and HSV-2) and varicella-zoster virus (VZV) are human pathogens, which routinely infect humans (
 <xref rid="B124" ref-type="bibr">Roizman et al., 2013</xref>). HSV, among the most widespread pathogenic agents in the human population, causes varieties of diseases, ranging from oral and genital ulcers to devastating encephalitis. Following the initial infection at a peripheral site, it will establish a lifetime latency in sensory neurons, which can be reactivated by some internal or external stimuli, including fever, immunosuppression, trauma, etc. (
 <xref rid="B124" ref-type="bibr">Roizman et al., 2013</xref>). So far, three categories of drugs have got approval for the treatment of HSV infection, including (1) the nucleoside analogs such as acyclovir (ACV), (2) the acyclic nucleotide analog cidofovir and (3) the pyrophosphate analog foscarnet (
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">Kimberlin and Whitley, 2007</xref>). Till now, ACV remains the prototypic antiviral agent and the reference for treating HSV infection. However, viral resistance to ACV has become a critical clinical problem, especially concerning immunocompromised patients undergoing long-term therapy (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Englund et al., 1990</xref>). Although the other two drugs also have been proven to be effective for treating HSV infection, they are reserved for confirmed cases of ACV resistance due to their nephrotoxicity (
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Galdiero et al., 2013</xref>). In addition, these drugs all exert antiviral effects by targeting viral DNA polymerase in target cells, therefore no antiviral drugs targeting HSV entry are available currently, let alone inactivating virions (
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Galdiero et al., 2013</xref>).
</p>
