<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The emergence of pandemics affects people's health, the economy and many other sectors of society. The emergence of viruses (COVID‐19, Zika, H1N1, H5N1, SARS, etc.), bacteria (
 <italic>Vibrio cholerae, Escherichia coli, Salmonella thyphimurium</italic>, etc.) and different types of parasites (species of 
 <italic>Plasmodium</italic>, 
 <italic>Trypanosoma</italic>, etc.) frequently strike our societies (Daszak 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="mbt213635-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). The identification of infected individuals in one part of the country can also result in overly stringent measures affecting other distant communities due to their geographical location, even when no case of infection has ever been found in the later and the infection risk is low (Gatto 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="mbt213635-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). These measures may include the restriction of visitors, blocking and subjection to quarantine of local inhabitants, interruption of flights and other transport of people and goods, preventive treatments such as the use of face masks, gloves or protective glasses (Feng 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="mbt213635-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Curative programmes (including vaccines and drugs prescription) are also included to reduce the effect of the disease, and even the construction or adaptation of hospital facilities to respond to the demands of those affected. Frequently, health and local authorities avoid performing clinical analyses such as the use of scarce detection kits, involving qPCR, or seroprevalence surveys using tests for the detection of antibodies, that determine the extent of the contagion to prevent side effects. In many cases, the results of these analyses demonstrate the lack of rigor from authorities regarding the spread of the disease in their jurisdiction, especially by those infected people who do not suffer serious effects, but who are transmitters of the disease (London and Kimmelman, 
 <xref rid="mbt213635-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). The clear determination of which communities are affected and which are free from pathogens is of great importance to establish the best containment measures without unnecessarily affecting communities free of the infectious agent. Such measures reduce damage caused by the fear of the population, and the reduction of negative economic impact, which responds with an unnecessary alarm even in unaffected areas. Therefore, specific and independent protocols are required to ensure exhaustive monitoring of the pathogen’s spread. We propose an analysis of local communities instead of, or in addition to, the scrutiny of individuals. Patients affected by a large number of infectious pathogens including SARS‐CoV‐2 release them through their faeces (Wu 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="mbt213635-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). These faeces are finally treated in wastewater treatment plants (WWTPs; Randazzo 
 <italic>et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="mbt213635-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). The number of pathogens found in these WWTPs is proportional to the number of affected people and their degree of affection. Given that the network of households that discharge their wastewaters into each of the WWTPs is perfectly defined, the determination of pathogens found in each WWTP allows us to establish a clear map of the geographical extension of the disease and to estimate the number of individuals affected in each zone in real time.
</p>
