<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Today, we have enough culture‐independent techniques for the extraction and massive sequencing of nucleic acids (e.g. Illumina or Ion Torrent) and through specific amplification of pathogen genes by qPCR, to monitor the unusual presence of pathogens at any population’s WWTPs. We therefore suggest the creation of Units for Vigilance of Emerging Diseases (UVEDs) based on the continuous analysis of pathogens in WWTPs in potentially affected areas and especially during epidemics and pandemics. The results potentially found by these UVEDs would allow collecting adequate information for the development of new therapeutic and preventive tools. For example, mass sequencing allows us to identify if certain microorganisms present in the wastewater carry antibiotic resistance genes or if a subpopulation may have changed the epitope recognized by a vaccine. This may allow to know the probability of the efficacy of a treatment in advance. We could avoid unnecessary expenses, unnecessary exposure to therapeutics such as antibiotics, preventing thus the occurrence of resistance and reduction in the efficacy of certain drugs. However, in order to provide a reliable service, some issues need to be addressed, such as developing an accurate nucleic acid (DNA and RNA) extraction protocol and a topological analysis of the sanitation network. For the nucleic acid extraction protocol, most of the available extraction kits are for human samples (including stools) and environmental samples such as soils, but not designed to extract RNA from wastewater samples. Wastewater are of heterogeneous nature and can be mixed with different concentrations of sanitation products such as bleach that could affect the stability of the nucleic acids and the efficiency of the extractive technique. Therefore, buffering the wastewater sample is of paramount importance prior to the nucleic acid extraction. In addition, the extraction method should equally work for bacteria and for the different viral pathogens that can be grouped into seven different categories accordingly to the type of nucleic acid they contain by the Baltimore Classification (including double‐stranded DNA, single‐stranded DNA, double‐stranded RNA, and positive‐ and negative‐single‐stranded RNA). For the topological analysis of the sanitation network, appreciation of the different discharge of wastewaters needs to be taken into consideration, since there are times when the volume of wastewater is higher and an appropriate model needs to be established to consider such variations and to be able to provide an approximate number of affected people in relation to the detected viral particles.</p>
