<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Sequences were aligned and compared to VEEV sequences available in the GenBank database (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd-0001875-t001">Table 1</xref>). Amino acid sequence alignments were performed using the ClustalW in SeaView version 4.2.12 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001875-Gouy1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, and the nucleotide sequences were aligned manually based on codon homology. A set of 55 sequences, which included reference strains for other VEEV subtypes, was trimmed to a minimum common length of 1,677 nt. Phylogenetic analyses were performed using the neighbor joining (NJ) and maximum parsimony algorithms implemented in the PAUP* version 4.0 software package 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001875-Swofford1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001875-Wilgenbusch1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> as well as the maximum likelihood (ML) algorithm implemented in PhyML 3.0 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://atgc.lirmm.fr/phyml" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://atgc.lirmm.fr/phyml</ext-link>) 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001875-Guindon1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. For NJ analysis, the HKY85 distance formula was used, and bootstrap analyses were performed with 1,000 replicates to place confidence values on the nodes within trees 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001875-Felsenstein1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. For ML analysis, the general time-reversible (GTR) model of nucleotide substitution was used for the data set, and the starting tree in the analysis was found using BIONJ (an improved version of the NJ algorithm) 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001875-Gascuel1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, which was followed by successive rounds of tree bisection reconstruction branch-swapping, identifying the ML substitutions model at each stage until the tree of highest likelihood was found. Bootstrapping was subsequently performed to assess the robustness of tree topologies using 1,000 replicate BIONJ trees under a ML substitution model.
</p>
