<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The reported mortality varies based on race, sex, age, and comorbid conditions (Baud et al.; Porcheddu et al., 
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Currently the true mortality still is not well-established, as the mortality may occur up to 30 days post infection. Based on current literature, most severe SARS-CoV-2 cases progressed within 14–21 days after disease onset. Various laboratory abnormalities have been observed even preceding the significant respiratory dysfunction (Lu et al., 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Mortality related to SARS-CoV-2 in China as reported by the WHO is about 3.4% (Guo et al., 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; Sohrabi et al., 
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). The most severe cases have been predominantly reported in elderly or subjects with preexisting conditions, predominantly cardiovascular diseases such as hypertension and congestive heart failure (Zhou et al., 
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Interestingly, these risk factors are similar to the reported risk factors (diabetes, hypertension, obesity) associated with MERS-CoV related mortality, although MERS-CoV respiratory disease occurred in younger individuals (Assiri et al., 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; World Health Organization, 
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). These clinical and epidemiological observations may provide some direction on the mechanism of disease. Recent reports indicate that a significant portion of SARS-CoV-2 related hospitalization in the USA are below the age of 50 years. Given the fact of a higher prevalence of metabolic diseases, including obesity, hypertension, cardiovascular diseases and diabetes in the US population (Moore et al., 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), this infection may cause higher mortality. The virus gains entrance into its host cell via the ACE2 receptor. How the known epidemiological and clinical manifestation of SARS-CoV-2 infection may be explained by perturbations of physiological functions of the ACE2 receptor due to receptor virus interaction will be discussed in this manuscript.
</p>
