<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12">Limited capacity for specialized laboratory diagnosis exists in most countries where EVD has been previously reported. This remains one of the biggest challenges in effective outbreak responses for the future [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. Laboratory investigations are typically carried out by national reference centres and involve specialized testing to detect the virus, or the body’s response to the infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. Specific laboratory confirmation is by reverse transcription (RT)-PCR which detects the viral RNA in a patient’s sample. Antigen detection using enzyme immunosorbent assays (ELISA) are also commonly used. Live virus may also be isolated in cell culture, but typically serves as a complimentary assay and due to the time required for results, not always useful for diagnosis or a timely outbreak response. Detection of specific IgM responses or rise in specific IgG titre is also indicative of recent infection. The latter is tested using indirect immunofluorescence assays or ELISA. Some laboratories may offer additional testing such as electron microscopy and immunohistochemistry on tissue samples, but this may be viewed as complimentary testing in most cases. It is recommended that blood and tissues of suspected EVD cases be handled in biosafety level 4 facilities; although RT-PCR testing during the West Africa EVD outbreak was done under field conditions working under modified biosafety level 3 conditions. The West Africa outbreak has highlighted the need for rapid and sensitive tests for EVD. Tests that can be conducted at facility level or at the bedside will be helpful in directing clinical decisions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. Although testing at reference laboratories may be laborious and more time consuming than facility-level testing, it is still recommended that all investigations be confirmed by experienced reference laboratories. Several rapid EVD assays are being developed in response to the West Africa outbreak, but are not yet widely available [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>].
</p>
