<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For the majority of the aforementioned teratogenic viruses, an essential determinant of the clinical symptoms of the newborn is the gestational age at which infection occurs, e.g., [
 <xref rid="B35-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Hereafter, we will outline the similarities and differences of the congenital infections caused by HCMV and ZIKV as opposed to RV. Like RV, both viruses can be transmitted to the embryo in the first trimester of pregnancy and cause an analogous congenital syndrome. In contrast to ZIKV and RV, HCMV can not only be vertically transmitted during primary infection, but also after reactivation during pregnancy [
 <xref rid="B39-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. However, the transmission rate during non-primary or recurrent infection is as low as about 1% [
 <xref rid="B39-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. With up to 34% the transmission rate during primary HCMV infection, which is considerably lower than the maximum rate of nearly 90% observed for RV during maternal rubella infection during the first 11 weeks of pregnancy [
 <xref rid="B11-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. While congenital rubella is largely restricted to primary infection during the first trimester of pregnancy, the transmission rate of HCMV during the third trimester of pregnancy occurs at a higher rate than during the first trimester, albeit with less severe symptoms [
 <xref rid="B41-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. ZIKV emerged in 2013/2014 in French Polynesia and in 2015 in Brazil [
 <xref rid="B42-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. The first evidence of perinatal transmission of ZIKV was noted for two infants born in French Polynesia [
 <xref rid="B44-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. This report by Besnard on these first two cases was eventually followed by solid proof that ZIKV infection during pregnancy is linked to congenital malformations in the newborn [
 <xref rid="B45-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The study by Rasmussen illustratively describes which criteria are necessary to turn an observed coincidence into the identification of ZIKV as a cause of birth defects in humans [
 <xref rid="B45-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Boppana et al. contrast congenital ZIKV to non-ZIKV infections and provide a meaningful comparison of the structural damage caused by HCMV and ZIKV in the brain and spinal cord, as revealed by imaging studies outlined in their review [
 <xref rid="B40-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. CNS defects are a less common manifestation of CRS, whereas congenital HCMV and ZIKV infections have a devastating influence on CNS development. This suggests a common pathology of both viruses in relation to the developmental stage of the CNS at the time point of maternal infection [
 <xref rid="B40-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].
</p>
