<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>So far, an efficient vaccine is only available for RV, which was implemented in an effective vaccination program and led to a dramatic decrease in the incidence of CRS. However, there are still developing countries in Africa and Asia lacking routine rubella vaccination [
 <xref rid="B33-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Thus, future research efforts on RV are more likely to focus on the elucidation of virus-associated teratogenic mechanisms. As detailed above, the types of symptoms caused are similar for some teratogenic viruses (e.g., neurologic and morphologic symptoms), while some of the most prominent manifestations show variations. Insights into the associated mechanisms including the elucidation of molecular pathways will be highly valuable as benchmark data, not only for the comparative analysis of known teratogens, but also of emerging or even re-emerging viruses with teratogenic potential. This could contribute to the identification of essential cellular markers and antiviral pathways for the conduct of the discovery of curative treatment options. Pluripotent stem cells, especially iPSCs, provide potent tools for the conduction of high-throughput screening (HTS) assays in therapy development, assessment of vaccine safety, and toxicity screenings. Even drugs may represent a toxin when they induce side effects. In the context of ZIKV infection, caspase-3 activity is elevated, representing a promising target for HTS [
 <xref rid="B47-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. HTS of compound collections in human neural progenitors, astrocytes, and organoids revealed small molecules, such as the pan-caspase inhibitor Emricasan, as neuroprotective and antiviral agents [
 <xref rid="B48-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Today, computational design, in vitro cell culture applications, in vivo animal models, and clinical trials are part of the pipeline. Structural-bioinformatics-based methodologies and frameworks are suitable for the design of ZIKV monoclonal antibodies against five envelope proteins and to estimate their performance in vitro or in vivo [
 <xref rid="B49-cells-09-00542" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. These candidate compounds need to be transferred to appropriate HTS assays and require appropriate cell culture models. The application of iPSCs may represent a promising advance to improve safety prediction, especially when patients are pregnant women.
</p>
