<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6">In Africa prior to 2016, YFV outbreaks occurred predominantly in West and East Africa, with low or no endemicity in Central Africa (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>). In 2013, highly endemic regions in Africa were estimated to have a YF burden of 130,000 cases per year, which accounted for greater than 90% of the global burden [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. It had also been observed that ambient or environmental temperatures and rainfall patterns could sustain mosquito vectors and promote the spread of YFV to regions of low endemicity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. In December 2016, YF cases were detected in Luanda, the capital city of Angola, which was previously categorized as a low-risk region for YF. The epidemic rapidly spread from Luanda to other urban populations in Angola and crossed into the neighboring country, Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Modeling studies predict that YFV transmission was continued for longer than usual due to the rain patterns affected by the 2016 EL Niño phenomenon [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Emergency vaccines were deployed to affected regions, but by mid-2016 the entire global stockpile of YF vaccine doses was exhausted, and fractional dosing of the YF vaccine was implemented as an emergency measure [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. By November 2016, WHO had confirmed 962 cases and 393 deaths related to this YFV outbreak. Since Angola and DRC were previously classified as low-risk for YFV transmission, these countries had not qualified for the previous vaccination campaigns within the YFI [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Low herd immunity, due to low YF vaccination coverage facilitated the large 2016 outbreak in Angola and DRC. As a response, the WHO revised its YFI program and implemented the new “EYE” strategy, with the goal of eliminating all global YF epidemics by 2026 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>••]. Since 2016, there have been outbreaks of 100 or more cases reported to WHO from Mali and Chad (2018) and Nigeria (2019). As a step towards eliminating future YF outbreaks, mass vaccination campaigns are currently being carried out in YF endemic regions where previously vaccine coverage had been poor [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>••].
</p>
