<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Moreover, the increased time-dependent pattern of the 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>y</italic>
 </sub> appears to have coincided with an increase in the proportions of GII and GII.4 genotypes (especially in 2006 when the GII.4 2006b strain was identified [
 <xref rid="pone.0173996.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0173996.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]), implying that the viral genogroup or genotype is responsible for characterizing the increased transmissibility. The positive association between transmissibility and GII is consistent with the findings of a published systematic review [
 <xref rid="pone.0173996.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. While GII.4 was not linked to transmissibility in the same report [
 <xref rid="pone.0173996.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], another study showed that GII.4 is likely to be involved in human-to-human transmissions [
 <xref rid="pone.0173996.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0173996.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0173996.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. GII.4 is known to bind to histo-blood group antigens more than other genotypes, and the diversity of its P2 domain implies that this genotype may experience more rapid molecular evolution than other genotypes [
 <xref rid="pone.0173996.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0173996.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0173996.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Two studies have indicated that while transmission of GII.4 2006b has decreased [
 <xref rid="pone.0173996.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0173996.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], it has been replaced by later genotypes such as GII.4 New Orleans 2009 and Sydney 2012, and new GII.4 variants may likely replace the earlier GII.4 genotype because substantial herd immunity to earlier genotypes probably exists [
 <xref rid="pone.0173996.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0173996.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The present study has contributed to improved understanding of the evolutionary dynamics of NVI by demonstrating that the time-dependent infection dynamics can be partly explored by estimating the 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>y</sub> and examining the epidemiological and virological data concurrently. Continued monitoring of the major routes of transmission for NVIs is of the utmost importance, while better understanding of the mechanisms underlying norovirus evolution is eagerly awaited.
</p>
