<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We model a single season of Influenza A virus (IAV) H3N2 and apply this model to 102 HA-1 sequences collected between 2004 and 2005 in New York state [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006546.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006546.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. We build on a simple susceptible-infected-recovered (SIR) model which accounts for importations of lineages from the global reservoir of IAV, which we will see is a requirement for good model fit to these data (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006546.g001">Fig 1</xref>). This model has two demes: The first deme corresponds to IAV lineages circulating in New York, and the second deme corresponds to the global IAV reservoir. The global reservoir will be modeled as a constant-size coalescent process. Within New York state, new infections are generated at the rate 
 <italic>βI</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>)
 <italic>S</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>)/
 <italic>N</italic> where 
 <italic>β</italic> is the per-capita transmission rate per day, 
 <italic>I</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>) is the number of infected and infectious hosts, 
 <italic>S</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>) is the number of hosts susceptible to infection, and 
 <italic>N</italic> = 
 <italic>S</italic> + 
 <italic>I</italic> + 
 <italic>R</italic> is the population size. 
 <italic>R</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>) denotes the number of hosts that have been infected and are now immune to this particular seasonal variant. With the above definitions, we define the matrix-valued function of time: 
 <disp-formula id="pcbi.1006546.e003">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1006546.e003.jpg" id="pcbi.1006546.e003g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M3">
    <mtable displaystyle="true">
     <mtr>
      <mtd columnalign="right">
       <mrow>
        <mi>F</mi>
        <mo>(</mo>
        <mi>t</mi>
        <mo>)</mo>
       </mrow>
      </mtd>
      <mtd>
       <mrow>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mo> [</mo>
        <mtable>
         <mtr>
          <mtd columnalign="left">
           <mrow>
            <mi>β</mi>
            <mi>I</mi>
            <mo>(</mo>
            <mi>t</mi>
            <mo>)</mo>
            <mi>S</mi>
            <mo>(</mo>
            <mi>t</mi>
            <mo>)</mo>
            <mo>/</mo>
            <mi>N</mi>
            <mo>(</mo>
            <mi>t</mi>
            <mo>)</mo>
           </mrow>
          </mtd>
          <mtd>
           <mn>0</mn>
          </mtd>
         </mtr>
         <mtr>
          <mtd>
           <mn>0</mn>
          </mtd>
          <mtd>
           <mrow>
            <mi>γ</mi>
            <msub>
             <mi>N</mi>
             <mi>r</mi>
            </msub>
           </mrow>
          </mtd>
         </mtr>
        </mtable>
        <mo>]</mo>
        <mo>.</mo>
       </mrow>
      </mtd>
     </mtr>
    </mtable>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
  <label>(2)</label>
 </disp-formula> Note that births within the reservoir do not vary through time and depend on the effective population size in that deme 
 <italic>N</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>r</italic>
 </sub>.
</p>
