<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0010">
 <label>Table 14.1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Milestones in cell cultures and microfluidics.</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td>1878</td>
    <td>Claude Bernard</td>
    <td>Established that a physiological state of the cell similar to the live cell can be maintained even after the death of the organism.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1907</td>
    <td>Harrison</td>
    <td>Cell entrapment and frog embryo nerve fiber growth in vitro.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1912</td>
    <td>Alexis Carriel</td>
    <td>Initiated tissue culture of chick embryo heart cells using embryo extracts as cultural media passaged for a reported period of 34 years.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1913</td>
    <td>Steinhardt, Israeli, and Lambert</td>
    <td>Grew vaccinia virus in fragments of guinea pig corneal tissue.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1916</td>
    <td>Rous and Jone</td>
    <td>Used trypsin to suspend attached cells in culture.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1927</td>
    <td>Carrel and Rivera</td>
    <td>First viral vaccine against chicken pox.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1948</td>
    <td>Sanford, Earle, and Likely</td>
    <td>Single-cell culture using microscale glass capillaries</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1949</td>
    <td>Enders, Weller, and Robbins</td>
    <td>Polio virus grown on human embryonic cells in culture.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1952</td>
    <td>Gey</td>
    <td>Establishment of continuous cell line from a human cervical carcinoma (HeLa cells).</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1955</td>
    <td>Eagle</td>
    <td>Established nutrient requirements of cells in culture and defined culture media for growth.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1956</td>
    <td>Little Field</td>
    <td>HAT (hypoxanthin, aminopterin, thymidine) medium introduced for cell selection.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1961</td>
    <td>Hayflick and Moorhead</td>
    <td>Studied human fibroblasts (WI-38) and showed finite lifespan in culture.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1965</td>
    <td>Ham</td>
    <td>First serum-free HAMS’s media.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1975</td>
    <td>Kohler and Milstein</td>
    <td>First hybridoma secreting a monoclonal antibody.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1977</td>
    <td>Genetech</td>
    <td>First recombinant human protein: somatistatin.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1979</td>
    <td>Terry, Jerman, and Angell</td>
    <td>Gas chromatography system using silicon-etched microchannels</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1985</td>
    <td>Collen</td>
    <td>Recombinant tissue plasminogen activator (tPA) in mammalian cells. Human growth hormone produced from recombinant bacteria was accepted for therapeutic use.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1986</td>
    <td>FDA approval</td>
    <td>First monoclonal antibody was approved by the FDA for use in humans (Orthoclone OKT3).</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1986</td>
    <td>Genetech</td>
    <td>First recombinant protein commercialized (interferon alpha-2a).</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1989</td>
    <td>Amgen</td>
    <td>Erythropoietin (EPO) recombinant protein produced in CHO cells available commercially.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1992</td>
    <td>Manz, Harrison, Verpoorte, Fettinger, Paulus, Ludi, and Widmer</td>
    <td>Micro-machined glass chip electrophoresis for separating molecules</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1992</td>
    <td>FDA approval</td>
    <td>First genetically engineered recombinant blood-clotting factor used in the treatment of hemophilia A.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1996</td>
    <td>Wilmut</td>
    <td>Production of transgenic sheep (Dolly) through nuclear transfer technique.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1997</td>
    <td>Hadd, Raymond, Halliwell, Jacobson, and Ramsey</td>
    <td>Microchip device for enzyme assay</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>1998</td>
    <td>Duffy, McDonald, Schueller, and Whitesides</td>
    <td>Creation of microfluidic systems using PDMS (polydimethylsiloxane)</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>2000</td>
    <td>Panaro, Yuen, Sakazume, Fortina, Kricka, Wilding</td>
    <td>Lab-on-chip system (bioanalyzer)</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>2002</td>
    <td>Cloneaid</td>
    <td>Claimed to produce cloned human baby named EVE.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>2003</td>
    <td>Zheng</td>
    <td>Protein crystallization chip</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>2004</td>
    <td>FDA approval</td>
    <td>First antiangiogenic monoclonal antibody that inhibits the growth of blood vessels or angiogenesis (for cancer therapy).</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>2005</td>
    <td>Sanford, Earle, and Likely</td>
    <td>Single-cell culture in open microfluidic systems</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>2005</td>
    <td>Birch</td>
    <td>Reported antibody titers at an industrial scale of 5 g/L and more.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>2009</td>
    <td>Nathalie Cartier-Lacave</td>
    <td>Combined gene therapy with blood stem cell therapy, which may be a useful tool for treating fatal brain disease.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>2011</td>
    <td>Melanie Welham, David Tosh</td>
    <td>1 M molecule treatment causes stem cells to turn into precursors of liver cells.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>2012</td>
    <td>Willison and Klug</td>
    <td>Single-cell and single-molecule proteomics utilizing nanospace technology</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>2012</td>
    <td>Maria Blasco</td>
    <td>First gene therapy successful against aging-associated decline in mice.</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
