<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0018">Remdesivir is a nucleoside analogue with antiviral activity developed by Gilead Sciences. Its anti-RNA virus activity has been confirmed, such as against Ebola virus, Marburg virus, Nipa virus and Hendra virus 
 <xref rid="bib0061" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0062" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0063" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>. Furthermore, remdesivir has exhibited preventive and therapeutic effects against MERS-CoV and SARS-CoV in vitro 
 <xref rid="bib0064" ref-type="bibr">[64</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">65]</xref>. Remdesivir has been observed to have the ability to reduce MERS-CoV replication, improve pulmonary function and reduce pulmonary lesions in Calu-3 cells and mouse models 
 <xref rid="bib0054" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>. It has been reported that in the Vero E6 cell model, remdesivir inhibits the infection of SARS-CoV-2 virus, with an EC
 <sub>50</sub> (half-maximal effective concentration) of 0.77 μM and a selectivity index of &gt;129.87 
 <xref rid="bib0066" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref>. Since SARS-CoV-2 and MERS-CoV possess a similar coronavirus structure 
 <xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">[2</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">8]</xref>, remdesivir has great potential against SARS-CoV-2. As reported previously, the first case of new coronavirus pneumonia treated in the USA received only supportive treatment for nausea, vomiting and other symptoms at the initial stage of admission, whilst the patient's symptoms improved significantly after receiving an i.v. injection of remdesivir for 1 day 
 <xref rid="bib0051" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>. However, remdesivir has not been approved in any country and its safety and effectiveness must be confirmed. Thus, two randomised controlled, double-blind phase III trials have been initiated in February 2020 (ClinicalTrials.gov ID 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04252664" id="interref0001" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04252664</ext-link> and 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="ClinicalTrials.gov" xlink:href="NCT04257656" id="interref0002" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">NCT04257656</ext-link>).
</p>
