<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Some of the most significant outbreaks, epidemics, and global pandemics, with high morbidities and mortality are from viral respiratory infections caused by influenza virus or CoV species; for which treatment is compromised by secondary bacterial infections (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2020</xref>). While a viral infection alone can be detrimental to a patient, the pathogen that exasperates disease progression is most commonly of bacterial origin (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2020</xref>). During the 2009 H1N1 influenza pandemic, between 29 and 55% of fatal cases were caused by secondary bacterial infections (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Center for Disease Control and Prevention, 2012</xref>). During the ongoing COVID-19 pandemic, around 15% of hospital cases have been associated with secondary bacterial pathogens, and 50% of patients died (
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2020</xref>). Clinical cases of COVID-19 have developed high rates of up to 50% of secondary bacterial infections leading to secondary bacterial pneumonia. Half of COVID-19 fatalities experienced some form of secondary infection (pulmonary or other) that may have contributed to their death. During severe COVID-19 disease with pneumonia, the air sacs of the lungs fill with pus and fluids, nutritious substrates for pathogens including 
 <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> and 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>. Tissues are breached by the cytolytic activity of the virus and bacteria invade deeper into the tissue, continuing to secrete toxins that further destroying surrounding cells. The frequency (30–40%) of complications due to bacterial involvement was significantly higher in fatal COVID-19 patients than for COVID-19 survivors (
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2020</xref>). In fatal COVID-19 cases, death is most frequently a result of respiratory failure from severe pneumonia, caused either by SARS-CoV-2 itself or as a result of a secondary bacterial infection (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">Tetro, 2020</xref>).
</p>
