<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat.1006788.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1006788.g006</object-id>
 <label>Fig 6</label>
 <caption>
  <title>RNA-Seq of feet of mice housed at 30°C or 22°C.</title>
  <p>(A) Mice housed at 30°C or 22°C were injected s.c. into feet with poly(I:C)/jetPEI. After 12 hours feet were harvested, mRNA was extracted and subjected to RNA-Seq analysis. Differentially expressed genes (q&lt;0.01, CPM&gt;1 in at least 3 samples) were analyzed by the IPA upstream regulator (USR) function (direct only). Selected USRs associated with the type I IFN response are shown ranked by Z score. Transcription factor activities associated with enhanced type I IFN responses are colored red. Transcription factor activities associated with reduced type I IFN responses are colored green. P values are provided above/below the bars. (B) As for (a) with mice housed at 30°C or 22°C for 2 days, but with feet harvested without any treatment. (C) The raw RNA-Seq sequencing data was independently analyzed by ISMARA (full results shown in 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1006788.s011">S1 Table</xref>). The transcription factor binding site (left) and site activity (right) are shown (with associated Z values) for XBP1, ATF3 and HSF1. ISMARA quantifies significance as a Z-value, with a site with a higher Z value ranked as more significant than one with a lower Z value. The activity score is an arbitrary score provided by the program and if error bars overlap significance is deemed not to have been reached [
   <xref rid="ppat.1006788.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. The significant Expression/Activity correlations (positive for XBP1 and HSF1, and negative for ATF3) are shown in 
   <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1006788.s007">S7B Fig</xref>.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1006788.g006" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
