<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par42">Although the therapeutic use of peptide drugs (Vlieghe et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR197">2010</xref>) and biologics including recombinant enzymes, hormones, and antibodies is steadily increasing and meanwhile well established, a treatment with synthetic, small-molecule drugs offers significant advantages. They can be produced at low costs in large quantities and offer the possibility for oral administration with a negligible risk of allergic reactions. In initial studies a weak antiviral effect after treatment with ECA (
 <bold>5</bold>, ε-aminocaproic acid, Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">11.4</xref>) was observed in mice infected by IAV including the plasmin-dependent WSN strain (Zhirnov et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR207">1982a</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR208">b</xref>). Due to its small size, ECA (
 <bold>5</bold>) cannot bind efficiently to the active site of trypsin-like proteases and reduces mainly the activation of plasminogen by blocking the lysine binding site on the kringle domains of plasminogen (Al-Horani and Desai 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2014</xref>). A pronounced protective effect was also observed, when IAV-infected mice were treated with a cocktail of 4-(2-aminoethyl)benzenesulfonylfluoride (
 <bold>6</bold>, AEBSF or Pefabloc
 <sup>®</sup>SC) and 
 <italic>p</italic>-aminobenzamidine (
 <bold>7</bold>, 
 <italic>p</italic>-AB) prior to infection. Both compounds are relatively unspecific protease inhibitors and can only occupy the S1 pocket of trypsin-like serine proteases. AEBSF 
 <bold>6</bold> leads to a covalent sulfonylation of the active-site Ser195 side chain (second-order inactivation constant 
 <italic>k</italic>
 <sub>2</sub>/
 <italic>K</italic>
 <sub>i</sub> for trypsin 30 M
 <sup>−1</sup> s
 <sup>−1</sup>), while 
 <italic>p</italic>-AB acts as a reversible competitive inhibitor with 
 <italic>K</italic>
 <sub>i</sub> values in the two- and three-digit micromolar range depending on the specific target (Stürzebecher et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR185">2001</xref>). Although AEBSF 
 <bold>6</bold> is more stable in buffer than the related phenylmethane sulfonylfluoride (PMSF), it is also susceptible to hydrolysis in aqueous media (Powers et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR149">2002</xref>) and not suitable for further development. Derivatives of the classical active-site titrant 
 <italic>p</italic>-nitrophenyl-
 <italic>p</italic>-guanidinobenzoate (Chase and Shaw 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">1967</xref>) including compounds like camostat 
 <bold>8</bold> (FOY-305) and nafamostat 
 <bold>9</bold> (FUT-175) (Fujii and Hitomi 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">1981</xref>) inhibit numerous trypsin-like serine proteases by covalent acylation of their active-site Ser195, providing relatively stable acyl-enzyme complexes. These compounds are active against numerous monobasic IAV and IBV strains (Hosoya et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">1993</xref>; Lee et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">1996</xref>; Someya et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR177">1990</xref>) but suffer from instability of their ester bond in aqueous media and the circulation (t
 <sub>½</sub> &lt;1 min after intravenous application of camostat in man (Midgley et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133">1994</xref>)). A very short half-life is also reported for nafamostat, although this could be an advantage for certain applications. Notably, nafamostat has been widely used as anticoagulant for hemodialysis patients with a tendency to bleed (Han et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">2011</xref>). 
</p>
