<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0050">Lives can be saved, expansion of the ailment might be curbed and huge data could be generated from AI models with the quick and precise diagnosis of COVID-19. Scientists working on AI applications show that it can give extra time to radiologists and do a diagnosis quicker and less expensive than with coronavirus regular tests. For this purpose, the doctors can use X-rays as well as CT scans, Computed Tomography [
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. 
 <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> explains different artificial intelligence applications in CT diagnosis of COVID-19. Coronavirus tests are short in supply and costly, however, all emergency clinics have X-Rays (or CT) machines. With the assistance of Deep Learning, radiologists can diagnose COVID-19 using X-ray pictures. COVID-Net an artificial intelligence application is created to analyze COVID-19 symptoms in chest x-rays utilizing information of different lung conditions and COVID-19 from patients [
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In a diagnostic study, an AI platform was established using inception migration neural network for extracting COVID-19 symptoms using CT images, achieving 89.5% accuracy [
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. An initial detection model was created to recognize COVID-19 pneumonia from Influenza-A viral pneumonia and sound cases with pulmonary CT pictures utilizing deep learning systems. The patient’s infected parts were proportioned by using a 3-D deep learning model. This study showed 86.7% accuracy of the model [
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Jin et al. developed a deep learning model that can precisely identify corona virus symptoms from the community acquired pneumonia (CAP) and other lung diseases. A 3D deep learning framework using chest CT was constructed using a neural network (COV-Net) [
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. For Coronavirus diagnosis; a deep learning model was proposed which straightforwardly accepts CT scans information as input and implements lung division, diagnose COVID-19 and finds abnormal slices. Furthermore, the study trusts that the diagnosis outcomes of AI framework can be quantitatively clarified in the initial picture to mitigate the disadvantage of deep neural systems as a black box [
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. An automated tool was created to quantifying the symptoms of this virus in the lungs of the patient and to observe the growth of the infection or reaction to cure, using a deep learning method. The capability of AI in diagnostics isn’t yet practiced, though Chinese hospitals have installed ’’AI-assisted" radiology technology. Reverse. Transcription Polymerase Chain Reaction (RT-PCR) tests are the key methodology used for diagnosing coronavirus, yet they have restrictions as far as specimen assortment, time required for the study, and execution [
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Specific abnormality in images and designs in CT scans showing COVID-19 symptoms has been discovered [
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].
</p>
