<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par50"> Transmission of WNVvia dialysis has been suggested [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR192">192</xref>], and transmission via blood transfusion and organ transplantation has been well documented [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR193">193</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR197">197</xref>]. In immunocompromised hosts, central nervous system involvement is common, although CSF pleocytosis may be minimal [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR198">198</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR200">200</xref>]. Community-acquired infection has been reported following solid organ transplantation, occurring 2 months to 10 years posttransplant [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR185">185</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR199">199</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR202">202</xref>]. A study of WNV infection during an outbreak in Toronto noted that liver, kidney, and heart transplant recipients had 40 times the risk of symptomatic infection as normal hosts [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR203">203</xref>]. In all cases, the recipients had participated in outdoor activities without the use of insect repellant or other personal protective measures. Fever often preceded neurologic symptoms. A delayed serologic response was noted in the transplanted cohort in which infection carried a mortality rate of 25%, versus 9% in the general population. In a Colorado outbreak in 2003, 11 transplant recipients (4 kidney, 2 liver, 2 kidney/pancreas, 1 lung, and 2 HSCT) developed infection requiring hospitalization [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR204">204</xref>]. Ten (91%) developed meningoencephalitis, one developed acute flaccid paralysis without encephalitis, and three patients had meningoencephalitis and paralysis. Two patients died (18% mortality), and three suffered significant neurologic sequelae. It appears that transplant recipients are more likely to develop meningoencephalitis in the setting of acute West Nile virus infection than immunocompetent hosts, perhaps with a higher mortality rate. Prolonged infection can also occur [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR205">205</xref>].
</p>
