<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Living in Hong Kong, the emergence COVID‐19 immediately drew parallels with the 2003 severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) outbreak, which brought devastation to the region. The profound impact that SARS had upon the people of Hong Kong can still be clearly seen seventeen years later; people habitually wearing protective facemasks, communally touched surfaces in public places being regularly disinfected, antibacterial hand gel dispensers located throughout all shopping centres, and public toilets that are amongst the cleanest in the world. The intent to prevent another SARS‐like infection in Hong Kong is clear for all to see; however, that all changed at the end of last year with the emergence of novel coronavirus in Mainland China, Quickly, cases were confirmed in Hong Kong and the fear of another pandemic lead rapidly to a pandemic of fear. People were panic buying, prices were rising, and supermarket shelves were very quickly stripped of essential food items and basic cleansing products. It was impossible to turn on the television without being told about the importance wearing surgical masks, how to wear surgical masks, the surgical masks celebrities were wearing and the danger of wearing “fake” surgical masks. Interestingly, limited attention was being given to the effectiveness of wearing a surgical facemask in the face of viral infection. Surgical masks were, and still are, in very short supply and retail prices have increased sharply. One enduring television image of recent weeks has been the sight of older people standing in line overnight in cold weather to get a small package of surgical masks hoping to protect themselves from the virus. Perhaps, all of these activities 
 <italic>mask</italic> the truly important public health message that good personal hygiene and effective handwashing is the most effective way to curb the spread of the virus. As clinical nurses, we all know that engaging in these actions will outweigh the benefits of wearing any surgical mask.
</p>
