<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite countermeasures against influenza that prevent (vaccines) or treat (antivirals) viral infections, this respiratory human pathogen infects 5–15% of the world population during seasonal epidemics. Notably, data from the World Health Organization (WHO) estimate that seasonal influenza virus infections are responsible of about 3–5 million cases of severe disease and about 250,000–650,000 deaths worldwide yearly [
 <xref rid="B36-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] (
 <uri xlink:href="http://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/influenza-(seasonal)" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/influenza-(seasonal)</uri>). Current available options to counter influenza infections include both vaccines and antivirals. Vaccines are the most cost-effective approach, due to the induction of sterilizing immunity, and they are the primary prophylactic means to prevent influenza viral infections [
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The first vaccine option is the chemically inactivated influenza vaccine (IIV), which requires a large quantity of virus to induce NAbs sufficient for protection against subsequent infections. However, IIV are suboptimal because the limited, if any, cellular-mediated immune responses they are able to induce. Moreover, immunocompromised and elderly individuals typically show reduced responses compared to young or healthy population [
 <xref rid="B39-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Importantly, IIV has a limited protection when the seasonal vaccine formulation does not match the predicted circulating strains. Most recently, an influenza vaccine made of purified recombinant HA antigens (
 <uri xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/flu/protect/vaccine/qa_flublok-vaccine.htm" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.cdc.gov/flu/protect/vaccine/qa_flublok-vaccine.htm</uri>) has been licensed with similar immunogenic characteristics to IIV. The remaining prophylactic option is the live attenuated influenza vaccine (LAIV), which is associated with broader responses and protection by the induction of both innate and humoral B- and T-cell adaptive immune responses. In addition, its administration mimics the usual route of influenza virus infection that has been shown to provide more efficient cross-reactive cellular-mediated protection against heterologous influenza viruses, important in cases where the vaccine and circulating strains do not match [
 <xref rid="B41-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. However, current LAIV remain restricted for use in healthy children and non-pregnant adults.
</p>
