<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Comparing our results to what has been reported in mammalian systems reveals that at least for DENV-2 and ZIKV the general patterns are consistent. The increase in titers upon TOR-inhibition with torin-1 suggests that both DENV-2 and ZIKV benefit from downstream pathways regulated by TOR, one of which is autophagy. We observed increased flavivirus titers in Aag2 cells upon torin-1 treatment suggesting that flaviviruses benefit from an autophagic state and this is consistent with what has been found in mammalian cells [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007754.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007754.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. However, increased titers were also observed upon suppression of autophagy by spautin-1 suggesting an antiviral role. While these outcomes seem contradictory, they are consistent with the current model for DENV-autophagy interactions. In mammalian cells, DENV and DENV replication complexes are targeted for degradation by autophagy while simultaneously benefitting from more efficient mature virion processing and increased energy availability as a result of virus-induced lipophagy [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007754.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007754.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0007754.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. While the flavivirus data was consistent with what has been observed in mammalian systems, the CHIKV data was not. Numerous studies have found that autophagy functions in an antiviral manner during infection with members of the family 
 <italic>Togaviridae</italic>, specifically alphaviruses [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007754.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007754.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007754.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007754.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. While inhibition of autophagy did result in increased CHIKV titers as would be expected, induction also increased titers. This discrepancy may reflect a difference in the role of autophagy during CHIKV infection of mosquito and mammalian cells.
</p>
