<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">It is estimated that 65 % of fatalities in Old World camels (OWC, i.e., 
 <italic>Camelus dromedarius</italic> and 
 <italic>C. bactrianus</italic>) and 50 % in New World camelids/South American camelids (NWC/SAC, i.e., the domestic alpaca (
 <italic>Vicugna pacos</italic>) and llama (
 <italic>Lama glama</italic>)) are caused by infectious diseases (Wernery and Kaaden 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">2002</xref>). In the past, camels were used mainly for transportation beside their role as the main source of milk and meat for pastoralists. Dromedary camel in sub-Saharan Africa was traditionally known to be reared in the arid and semiarid lands. Due to aridity and desertification, they obliged to move to the higher rainfall areas side by side with other domestic livestock and wildlife. This change resulted in exposure of camels to diseases that were uncommon in their natural habitat such as dermatophilosis, tick paralysis, trypanosomosis, and brucellosis. The situation in Niger, Chad, and Sudan is an example where diseases like contagious ecthyma, trypanosomosis, and tick paralysis have become very serious with increased mortality rates due to the migration of camels south of their well-known camel belt. Drought in the Sahel and the Horn of Africa has also brought pastoralists closer to urban centers, and sales of camel milk became their main source of cash income. Due to an increased demand of urban populations of many countries, particularly in North Africa and the Middle East for camel milk, many dairy farms are established in intensive and semi-intensive systems. This development may be responsible for making camels more susceptible to certain disease. Brucellosis, enterotoxemia, and Johne’s disease are examples of these diseases. A similar situation could be envisaged for an increased incidence of enterotoxemia in camels when raised in an intensive husbandry system as in the UAE (Wernery and Kaaden 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">2002</xref>) or Syria (Khalafalla AI 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">2015</xref>, personnel communication). Changes in animal husbandry related to increasing camel contacts with other animal species, such as equids, may cause disease emergence. Examples of newly emerged diseases of camels resulting from sharing premises with equines are glanders (Wernery et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">2011</xref>), melioidosis (Wernery et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">1997</xref>), and 
 <italic>Rhodococcus equi</italic> infection (Kinne et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2011</xref>). Another factor that may contribute to the emergence of camel diseases is the migration into new habitat that never was reached before by camels (Faye and Vias 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">2010</xref>).
</p>
