<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite the importance of geography for infectious disease epidemiology, the effects of global mobility upon the genetic diversity and molecular evolution of pathogens are under-appreciated and only beginning to be understood; indeed, a recent monograph on the spatial epidemiology of infectious disease makes no reference to pathogen genetic variation [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Patterns of host mobility may be particularly important for RNA viruses, the infections on which we focus here. Because many viruses do not survive for long outside the environment of their host, close proximity of hosts (or of hosts and vectors) is often necessary for transmission. Further, because rates of RNA virus mutation and evolution are high, their genomes can accrue genetic differences while being spatially disseminated during an individual outbreak. The evolutionary and spatial dynamics of these pathogens are therefore linked and reciprocally influence each other [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. This fundamental principle has several important consequences. First, genetic differences among viruses sampled from diverse locations will contain information about the spatial processes that gave rise to the virus's geographical distribution. The abundance of viral gene sequences and advances in analytical methods have increased our ability to infer these processes and track viral spread [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Second, rapidly evolving viruses are capable of adapting swiftly to the novel environments they encounter as they spread geographically [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], with the potential to alter, for example, vector specificity or sensitivity to drugs or immune responses. Third, spatial sampling provides a common frame of reference whereby virus evolution and migration can be integrated with epidemiological data, or with environmental measurements such as humidity or land use. Integration of geographical data with genetic analysis promises to provide a fuller understanding of the origins, dispersal and dynamics of evolving pathogens [
 <xref rid="RSPB20142878C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].
</p>
