<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<boxed-text id="BB1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
 <caption>
  <title>Executive summary</title>
 </caption>
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p>The COVID-19 that originated in Wuhan, China in December 2019, is caused by SARS-CoV-2 infection. COVID-19 is now a global pandemic, and almost all countries in the world have recognized its seriousness and implemented various measures to curb its spread.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>The numbers of confirmed asymptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infections continue to increase, indicating that a large number of unidentified asymptomatic individuals with contagious infections may remain undetected in communities. In general, these patients do not know to self-isolate or seek treatment, and thus, are unlikely to be detected by healthcare workers. However, their potential to spread the virus cannot be underestimated, and emerging evidence indicates that they are an important source of transmission.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>SARS-CoV-2 has been detected in nasopharyngeal swabs, sputum samples, blood samples and stool samples from asymptomatic patients, and asymptomatic patients with SARS-CoV-2 infection can carry high viral loads.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>The incubation period of asymptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infections is complex and exists in the process of crowd and family-clustered outbreaks. In addition, asymptomatic patients are even the source of infection in contagious outbreaks among families.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Asymptomatic infections can occur in patients of any age and either gender, and they may not exhibit any abnormalities on laboratory or computed tomography examinations.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>The identification and isolation of asymptomatic patients are essential to controlling virus outbreaks. To avoid missing any infected patients, anyone who has had close contact with a confirmed or suspected case of infection should be closely monitored and screened. Therefore, centralized isolation for medical observation and related tests for COVID-19 need to be applied to the greatest extent possible, even among contacts who have no symptoms. Healthcare workers should pay close attention to screening consultations and collect detailed information, including the presence of even very mild symptoms.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Coronaviruses were once considered an insignificant, benign family of viral pathogens, but have now caused three major outbreaks of serious illness in the last two decades. Thus, we must all stay alert to such emerging infectious viral diseases, and this will be a long-term challenge.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</boxed-text>
