<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The precise and complete etiology of several long-term neurological pathologies still represent a conundrum. Multiple sclerosis (MS) represents one such neurological disease for which an infectious agent or agents may play a triggering role, with viruses the most likely culprit in genetically predisposed individuals [
 <xref rid="B301-viruses-12-00014" ref-type="bibr">301</xref>]. It has been suggested that several neurotropic viruses could be involved in MS pathogenesis but that they may do so through similar direct and/or indirect mechanisms [
 <xref rid="B302-viruses-12-00014" ref-type="bibr">302</xref>,
 <xref rid="B303-viruses-12-00014" ref-type="bibr">303</xref>,
 <xref rid="B304-viruses-12-00014" ref-type="bibr">304</xref>,
 <xref rid="B305-viruses-12-00014" ref-type="bibr">305</xref>,
 <xref rid="B306-viruses-12-00014" ref-type="bibr">306</xref>]. However, although research has not yet led to a direct link to any specific virus, association of coronaviruses with MS has been suggested [
 <xref rid="B307-viruses-12-00014" ref-type="bibr">307</xref>]. Even though HCoV-OC43 and -229E were detected in some control brains and in some brains coming from patients with different neurological diseases, there was a significantly higher prevalence of HCoV-OC43 in brains of MS patients [
 <xref rid="B245-viruses-12-00014" ref-type="bibr">245</xref>]. Moreover, autoreactive T cells were able to recognize both viral and myelin antigens in MS patients but not in controls during infection by HCoV-OC43 and HCoV-229E [
 <xref rid="B308-viruses-12-00014" ref-type="bibr">308</xref>,
 <xref rid="B309-viruses-12-00014" ref-type="bibr">309</xref>]. Thus, the immune response may participate in the induction or exacerbation of long-term neuropathologies such as MS in genetically or otherwise susceptible individuals. Furthermore, it was shown that in recombination activation gene (RAG) knock-out mice, HCoV-OC43-induced encephalitis could be partially mediated by the T-cell response to infection [
 <xref rid="B263-viruses-12-00014" ref-type="bibr">263</xref>]. This underlines the possibility that, like its murine counterpart MHV, long term infection of the CNS by HCoV [
 <xref rid="B245-viruses-12-00014" ref-type="bibr">245</xref>] may participate in the induction of demyelinating MS-like lesions.
</p>
