<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Many statistical aberrancy detection methods have been described for epidemic surveillance [
 <xref rid="pone.0191324.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0191324.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0191324.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], including time series modeling [
 <xref rid="pone.0191324.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0191324.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0191324.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Some of these methods have been applied to the same data sets and formally compared [
 <xref rid="pone.0191324.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0191324.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0191324.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Of the two studies that addressed the value of historical data, a generalized linear model (GLM) that took advantage of 3 years of past data often outperformed EARS [
 <xref rid="pone.0191324.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], whereas a seasonally adjusted cumulative sum (CUSUM) method did not [
 <xref rid="pone.0191324.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Even though a number of explanations could help reconcile these results, we note that as the size of an epidemic signal increases relative to the background noise, outbreak recognition becomes easier and the performance of alternative detection methods becomes more and more difficult to distinguish [
 <xref rid="pone.0191324.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0191324.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. This rationale could explain why the GLM approach implemented by Jackson et al. did not add value under all conditions, but performed well with slow-escalating outbreaks qualitatively similar to the one used in our study [
 <xref rid="pone.0191324.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. In our particular real-world case, we found SARIMA to be more sensitive than EARS at discovering signals related to the pH1N1 pandemic wave that hit Baltimore in the summer of 2009. However, there was no associated timeliness advantage to SARIMA, as the initial peak of ARI cases was large enough to be picked by both statistical approaches. Given the variability in real-world outbreak signals, a negative finding for one specific outbreak does not reduce the impetus to design ever more sensitive and specific surveillance systems.
</p>
