<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phytoviruses transmitted persistently often tend to alter the phenotypic and physiological traits of their host plants thus making them more suitable to their arthropod vectors, particularly hemipterans [
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Visual, volatile, and gustatory cues from plants infected by such viruses make them more apparent to their vectors and also affect vector fitness [
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Even though a few studies have documented virus-induced direct effects on vectors [
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], the majority of studies seem to attest that virus-induced effects on vectors are mediated via hosts. Studies that documented host-mediated virus-induced effects on vector preference and/or fitness were, more often than not, conducted using expressive hosts or hosts that display flamboyant symptoms upon virus infection [
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. It is unclear if such observed effects on vector preference and/or fitness would also be noticeable in not-so expressive hosts, including host genotypes that exhibit resistance to the pathogen. Further, most experiments that documented persistent virus induced-effects on vectors were conducted in a single time frame post host inoculation. It is also not clear if such induced effects are sustained over time. This study aims to address the two questions using a 
 <italic>Begomovirus</italic>-whitefly-tomato model pathosystem.
</p>
