<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A number of studies have examined the effects of 
 <italic>Begomovirus</italic> infection on whiteflies. In several cases plants were deemed to be more attractive to whiteflies, and the vira1infection in plants improved the performance of whiteflies [
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. However, in some cases, neutral and negative effects of TYLCV infection on the preference and fitness of whiteflies were also documented [
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. On the whole, effects on vector fitness seem to vary with several factors such as the whitefly biotype, the species of 
 <italic>Begomovirus</italic>
 <sub>,</sub> and the plant host chosen to evaluate such interactions [
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. For instance, 
 <italic>Begomovirus</italic> infection differentially affected the performance and preference of the whiteflies depending on the biotype of whiteflies [
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. 
 <italic>Tomato yellow leaf curl china virus</italic> (TYLCCNV) infection in tobacco plants was correlated with negative fitness effects on the indigenous whitefly biotype ZHJ1 when compared with the b-biotype in China [
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Another 
 <italic>Begomovirus</italic>, 
 <italic>Tomato curly shoot virus</italic> (TbCSV), infection in tomato was also correlated with increased fitness effects on the invasive b-biotype whiteflies than the indigenous biotype ZHJ1 [
 <xref rid="pone.0142114.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Most of these whitefly-TYLCV studies were conducted at a single time point, often at the time of substantial symptom expression on plants. Whitefly preference to virus-infected plants before and after substantial symptom expression is rather unknown. This study attempts to elucidate the temporal effects of TYLCV infection in susceptible and resistant genotypes on virus accumulation, virus acquisition by whiteflies, whitefly preference, as well as the effects of TYLCV infection on whitefly development.
</p>
