<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A second advantage of co-production in this context is that the spatial grain of models for zoonotic diseases was tailored to the scale at which forests are used, and to the size and distance between settlements, that govern how forest communities access health services and report cases of KFD. Thus co-production helped to bridge the traditional gap between the scale of model outputs and the scale of intervention and ecosystem use [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008179.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and enabled finer scale relationships to be established between the environment and human disease cases (household-level). Many predictive models in the scientific literature that map geographical patterns in infectious diseases draw data from online databases such as ProMed and HealthMap which can often record only the locations of hospital or Primary health centres where cases are reported [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008179.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. By working with disease managers to collate and interpret case data, it becomes clear that visits to health centres can occur far away from the settlements or forest habitat in which infection is acquired (e.g. for KFD may range from 5–10 km for small-holders but some 10s of km for tourists, students travelling between home and college, pilgrims and migrant labourers). If hospital or health centre data are used indiscriminately to parameterise disease-environment relationships, the resulting associations and predictive maps could be spurious and unsuitable for spatial targeting of interventions. Though these data drawbacks have long been noted for tick-borne diseases[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008179.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>], probably due to the time required to collate fine scale data and engage with local disease managers, predictive maps are still being developed based solely on health centre locations and advocated as disease management tools, including for KFD [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008179.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. We concur with Boden and McKendrick [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008179.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], who argued that all models supplied to health policy makers should adhere strictly to the principles of independence, transparency (autonomy), beneficence and justice. It is incumbent on disease modellers to appraise and be transparent about the suitability of available case data for relating and predicting infection processes from environmental conditions. The iterative, reflexive engagement with stakeholders’ needs and knowledge, through a co-production process, can facilitate this transparency.
</p>
