<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza virus M2 protein is an integral membrane protein expressed on the viral surface in low quantities, while being abundantly present on the surface of infected cells [
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. This expression pattern plays an important role in viral replication. The M2 protein consists of an N-terminal extracellular region (M2e), transmembrane region, and C-terminal cytoplasmic tail region. The M2e is composed of 24 amino acids and is highly conserved among different influenza A subtypes [
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Thus, this region may be a good candidate epitope for the preparation of a universal vaccine. However, in its natural state, viral M2e has low immunogenicity and abundance. To improve immunogenicity, previous studies have used multimeric forms of M2e created by fusing M2e to highly immunogenic carriers or by applying them in conjunction with adjuvants. The main types of vaccines include peptide vaccines, recombinant protein vaccines, and virus-like particles [
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9–13</xref>]. Currently, several M2e universal vaccines have entered clinical trials. However, some problems surfaced during clinical trials, which prevented the commercialization of these vaccines [
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Some of the more prominent problems include unsatisfactory immune efficacy and certain side effects. These problems may be due to the vaccine containing multiple ingredients [
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Moreover, this type of vaccine has a relatively high cost of production and a complex manufacturing technique, which further limits its development. Therefore, further research on M2e vaccine is necessary. Among the various types of vaccines, DNA vaccines are particularly attractive because of their simplicity, ease of production, and lack of anti-vector immune responses. Though the development of novel cross-protective influenza vaccines based on M2e DNA is a promising strategy, few of the enhanced immunogenic vaccine strategies have been successful. Thus, further research is necessary.
</p>
