<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Despite the mutation at HA-Q226L, H7N9 retains stronger specificity for avian type SA receptors [
 <xref rid="B41-microorganisms-08-00778" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Sustained transmission in humans is postulated to require additional amino acid substitutions with specificity for α-2,6 linked SA residues [
 <xref rid="B31-microorganisms-08-00778" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. All human pandemic IAV strains have specificity for α-2,6 linked SA receptors [
 <xref rid="B42-microorganisms-08-00778" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-microorganisms-08-00778" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], which is consistent with the switch from avian to human SA receptors that are accompanied by mutations within the HA receptor-binding pocket. In a systematic mutational analysis, de Vries et al. [
 <xref rid="B31-microorganisms-08-00778" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] investigated the effect additional mutations would have towards establishing complete human-type receptor binding specificity [
 <xref rid="B31-microorganisms-08-00778" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The authors used site-directed mutagenesis of the wild type influenza A virus (A/Shanghai/2/2013), where HA-Q226L was already present. Two substitutions, each containing three amino acid mutations (V186G/K-K193T-G228S or V186N-N224K-G228S), successfully demonstrated an acute loss of binding to α-2,3 SA receptors whilst increasing avidity for α-2,6 SA receptors and subsequent effective binding to human trachea epithelial cells, as shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="microorganisms-08-00778-f005">Figure 5</xref>. This approach successfully demonstrated how a combination of amino acid mutations in H7 HA could result in increased specificity of the H7N9 virus to the α-2,6 linked SA receptors on epithelial cells. The authors concluded that such a mutation would raise the potential for human-to-human viral transmission via airborne droplets, which could lead to a pandemic outbreak [
 <xref rid="B31-microorganisms-08-00778" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].
</p>
