<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The genome of DENV is a single-stranded, positive-sense RNA, and its single open reading frame encodes a polyprotein consisting of three structural proteins, which are as follows: the capsid, membrane-associated, and envelope (E) proteins. In addition, seven nonstructural proteins, NS1, NS2A, NS2B, NS3, NS4A, NS4B, and NS5, are also present in its structure.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
 </sup> Four distinct DENV serotypes (DENV1, DENV2, DENV3, and DENV4) have been identified, and the extensive diversity within DENV1 enables it to recognize different genotypes, such as genotype I (Southeast Asia and East Africa), genotype II (Thailand), genotype III (Malaysia), genotype IV (South Pacific), and genotype V (America/Africa).
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
 </sup> Dengue genotypes are phylogenetically distinct clusters of viruses, often associated with specific geographical regions, that are linked to epidemics of varying intensities and disease severity.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
  <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
 </sup> Phylogeny is a science that makes use of a set of relationships among groups of genes or organisms and reflects their evolutionary history. The maximum likelihood method is used to describe and analyze biological sequences.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
 </sup> Alignment of the nucleic acid sequences of the DENV followed by its phylogenetic analysis and subsequent generation of phylogenetic trees revealed information regarding its genetic evolution and epidemiology of the disease worldwide.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–
  <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
 </sup> The E protein of the DENV is responsible for its tropism and virulence.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
 </sup> The gene encoding the E protein has demonstrated its usefulness for decades for the phylogenetic reconstruction of the DENV. Thus, complete analysis of the coding region can help assign the correct DENV genotype and infer the relationships within genotypes and lineages accurately.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
 </sup> Therefore, the E protein provides adequate resolution to characterize genetic relationship and evolution of the DENV.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="b19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
