<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0030">Previous pandemics due to different viruses have showed their effects on fetal developments which led to significant enhancement in number of infants with mental illnesses like schizophrenia, autism spectrum disorder and attention deficit disorder 
 <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. As per report of “The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC),” prenatal COVID-19 infections can also develop its impact on fetal brain development by the effects of the maternal inflammatory response on the fetus and placenta 
 <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. The 
 <xref rid="s0070" ref-type="sec">supporting data</xref> regarding this impact of COVID-19 is expected to be available in near future. Current reported data from CDC based on Infant Behaviour Questionnaire Revised (IBQ-R) regulation 
 <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref> suggest that no symptoms of viral infections are found after 3 months of birth on the children of COVID-19 infected mothers having high digestive choline level (≥7.5 μM) during the first 16 weeks of pregnancy. Some specific diets and food supplements are the source of choline for human body. Medical reports suggested that higher choline level in expecting mothers may protect fetal brain development from COVID-19, which definitely may support infant behavioral development though the mothers got COVID-19 infection in their gestation stage when the brain is being formed 
 <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. These findings have motivated us to work on a specific nutrient food supplement: 
 <italic>Choline</italic> (C
 <sub>5</sub>H
 <sub>14</sub>NO) which is supposed to be used to protect the fetal brain development specifically during pregnancy 
 <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. Our in silico studies by virtual screening, molecular docking and molecular dynamics on choline as ligand and 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> main spike protease of CoV2 as receptor have been able to establish that prenatal COVID-19 infections can be nullified by choline contained food supplements as they help to shield the fetal brain in mother’s womb from the possible detrimental impact from COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> a, b).
</p>
