<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par89">Considering the high morbidity and mortality among the avian population arising from infections with the H5N1 bird flu virus around the turn of the century and the serious concern over possible mutagenesis of the strain to a human-to-human-infecting one, we undertook detailed comparisons of the H5N1 strains’ neuraminidase sequences over a 10-year span to determine what changes were taking place (Nandy et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">2007</xref>). Assuming that mutational changes in the sequences will be quantified by estimates of the graph radii, 
 <italic>g</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>R</italic>
 </sub>, in a 2D graphical representation model (Nandy 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">1994</xref>), we assembled a database of 173 neuraminidase sequences for the years 1996–2005 and computed the average 
 <italic>g</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>R</italic>
 </sub> values separately over periods when the flu was highly pathogenic to humans (1996–1997 and 2003–2005) and when less pathogenic (1998–2002). We found from computations of the 
 <italic>g</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>R</italic>
 </sub> that, e.g. an H5N1 neuraminidase A/Chicken/Hong Kong/220/97(H5N1) had a very close similarity to another NA sequence from the same year, A/HongKong/156/97(H5N1), a result that matched with a conventional phylogenetic study by Suarez et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">1998</xref>), whereas comparison with A/chicken/China/1/02-(H5N1)NA 5 years later showed that the two sequences were dissimilar almost seven times as much as the dissimilarity between the previous two sequences as estimated through Δ
 <italic>g</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>R</italic>
 </sub>. This provides a descriptor-based insight into how rapidly the virus mutates over the years. A more detailed analysis with the 
 <italic>g</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>R</italic>
 </sub> of the individual segments showed that the 
 <italic>g</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>R</italic>
 </sub> expanded in the years of high pathogenicity to humans, more so for the period 2003–2005, whereas the period of low pathogenicity showed reduced values of 
 <italic>g</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>R</italic>
 </sub>. This indicates a relative increase in the A, T component of the neuraminidase gene sequences in the pathogenic years, which could be a contributor to the high pathogenicity observed (Nandy et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">2007</xref>).
</p>
