<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="RSTB20180335F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 2.</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Data used to estimate ecological and human population components of spillover (
   <italic>a–k</italic>) and estimates of overall spillover risk (
   <italic>l</italic>–
   <italic>o</italic>). Number of primate reservoir species (
   <italic>a</italic>), vector species probability of occurrence (
   <italic>b</italic>), reservoir–vector contact probability (
   <italic>c</italic>), human–vector contact probability (
   <italic>d</italic>), human susceptibility approximated by 1 minus estimated vaccine coverage (
   <italic>i</italic>), and human distribution (
   <italic>j</italic>) vary spatially. Vector seasonal abundance is modelled as a function of rainfall using mosquito capture data (
   <italic>e</italic>). Vector dispersal depends on distance and is estimated from mark–recapture studies (
   <italic>f</italic>). Vector survival has been measured at different temperatures in laboratory (open circles) and field (closed circles) settings and was used to estimate temperature-dependent vector lifespan (
   <italic>g</italic>). Transmission studies at different temperatures inform modelled probability of vector infectiousness as a function of days since infecting bite and temperature (
   <italic>h</italic>). Phenomenologically modelled reservoir disease prevalence (light blue line, 
   <italic>k</italic>) is approximated from human case data (blue dots, 
   <italic>k</italic>). All mechanistic model components (
   <italic>a–k</italic>) are derived from empirical data in previously published studies. Components 
   <italic>a–h</italic> are used to predict environmental risk of disease spillover (
   <italic>l</italic>), components 
   <italic>a</italic>–
   <italic>i</italic> are used for immunological risk (
   <italic>m</italic>), components 
   <italic>a</italic>–
   <italic>j</italic> are used for population-scaled risk (
   <italic>n</italic>) and components 
   <italic>a</italic>–
   <italic>h</italic> and 
   <italic>k</italic> are used for periodic risk (
   <italic>o</italic>). The four disease risk metrics presented here for illustrative purposes were estimated for January 2001 (
   <italic>l–o</italic>). (Online version in colour.)
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="rstb20180335-g2" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
