<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The shaping of these peptides through the antigen processing machinery (APM) begins in the cytoplasm by the proteasome that cuts intracellular proteins into heterogeneous fragments. Peptides are subsequently transported by the transporter associated with antigen processing (TAP) within the endoplasmic reticulum (ER), where they are trimmed at the N-terminus, in order to generate suitable length peptides to be bound by MHC class I molecules and presented on cells’ surface. In humans, the main aminopeptidases responsible for N-terminal peptide trimming are ERAP1 and ERAP2 (collectively ERAPs), two IFNγ- and TNFα-inducible enzymes that are expressed in various human tissues and belong to the M1 family of zinc aminopeptidases [
 <xref rid="B2-cells-09-00720" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. These two proteins act in concert and play a critical role in shaping conformationally stable peptides to ensure their loading onto MHC class I molecules. The trimming of precursors, indeed, stabilizes MHC class I peptides conformation/structure and presentation [
 <xref rid="B4-cells-09-00720" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. ERAPs activities are coordinated, yet not redundant, indeed, they act together handling substrates and trimming peptides, while maintaining marked differences in enzymatic specificity. ERAP1 preferentially cleaves peptides with large hydrophobic C-terminal amino acids and shows a strong tendency to cut 9–16 amino acids peptides into pieces of 8–9 amino acids, namely the optimal length for binding to MHC I molecules [
 <xref rid="B4-cells-09-00720" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-cells-09-00720" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-cells-09-00720" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-cells-09-00720" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-cells-09-00720" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Noteworthy, peptides with proline in position 2 or which are shorter than 8 amino acids are less susceptible to ERAP1 activity [
 <xref rid="B6-cells-09-00720" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].
</p>
