<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Models of influenza virus transmission have proved very useful in expanding knowledge of influenza biology, evolution, and epidemiology. For example, models of evolutionary change and immunity aim to predict the dominant strain of influenza in the coming season [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Spatially explicit models have convincingly linked commuting movements to the spread of influenza in the United States [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Models have also been crucial to public health, contributing to the optimization of control strategies, including the use of vaccines and antivirals [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. As the modelling field has developed, there has been an effort to improve realism by incorporating heterogeneity in human contact patterns, age-related susceptibility, cross immunity after previous infections [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], and the potential effect of environmental variables on transmission [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Notably, the vast majority of modelling work has neglected the microbial environment: most mathematical and computational models of influenza are focused on single or sequential influenza infections and have broadly simplified pathogen ecology. For example, despite secondary bacterial infections being recognized as an important cause of mortality, models have not been exploited to estimate the indirect effect of seasonal influenza vaccination on the incidence of severe bacterial infections in the elderly. Furthermore, modelling used to plan vaccine interventions during the 2009 pandemic in the United Kingdom considered influenza transmission alone [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006770.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].
</p>
