<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In late 2019, a cluster of pneumonia cases in Wuhan City, Hubei Province, China were identified as with a novel betacoronavirus, first called the 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCov) and often referred to as the Wuhan coronavirus. When the genomics of the 2019-nCov was sequenced, it shared 79.5% of the genetic sequence of the SARS-CoV that caused the 2002–2003 pandemic [
 <xref rid="B4-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] and the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses renamed the 2019-nCov as SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B5-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Patients began to present in November and December with various degrees of respiratory distress of unknown etiology and treated at the time as possible influenza infections. As it became apparent that most cases had a shared history of exposure to the Huanan Seafood Wholesale Market (the so-called “wet market”), the Wuhan local health authority issued an epidemiologic alert on 30 December 2019 and the wet market was closed. About a week later, on 9 January 2020, Chinese researchers shared the full genetic sequence of the novel coronavirus, now called SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B6-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Since the novel coronavirus was recognized, the disease it caused was termed coronavirus disease 2019 (CoVID-19), and several reports on the clinical presentation, epidemiology, and treatment strategies have been published [
 <xref rid="B7-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In addition, several websites have been setup to track the epidemic and the case detection rate, which are being updated as often as hourly [
 <xref rid="B11-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. On 30 January 2020, the World Health Organization (WHO) declared the COVID-19 outbreak to be a global public health emergency, sixth after H1N1 (2009), polio (2014), Ebola in West Africa (2014), Zika (2016) and Ebola in the Democratic Republic of Congo (2019), and on 11 March 2020, the WHO characterized COVID-19 as a pandemic [
 <xref rid="B15-pathogens-09-00231" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The timeline of events is summarized in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pathogens-09-00231-f001">Figure 1</xref>.
</p>
