<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Oxidative stress due to dysregulated reactive oxygen species (ROS) production and altered metabolism has been directly implicated in the pathogenesis of influenza virus infections.
 <xref rid="resp13524-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="resp13524-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">5</xref> The consensus is that excessive ROS response triggers redox‐sensitive pathways that contribute to the respiratory burst, causing inflammation and tissue injury. Therefore, targeting the primary source of ROS production in inflammatory cells, that is the NOX2‐containing NADPH oxidase to attenuate ROS generation, may be an effective means for reducing the ROS‐induced viral burden and tissue damage. To support this notion, the specific deletion of the NOX2 gene was associated with improved lung function and a reduced amount of lung tissue damage.
 <xref rid="resp13524-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="resp13524-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="resp13524-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">8</xref> Our recent findings revealed that the primary subcellular site of ROS generation to influenza virus infection is the endosome.
 <xref rid="resp13524-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref> We previously showed that influenza A virus (IAV) triggers ROS production within the endosome by: (i) internalizing into early endosome antigen‐1 (EEA1)‐positive endosomes by a clathrin‐coated pit‐dependent endocytic process; (ii) activation of endosomally located toll‐like receptor 7 (TLR7) by its single‐stranded RNA content; (iii) activation of protein kinase C that is downstream of TLR7 activation resulting in phosphorylation of the NOX2 oxidase, organizer protein p47phox; and finally (iv) the assembly of the NOX2 oxidase complex at the endosomal membrane releasing superoxide within the endosome lumen.
 <xref rid="resp13524-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref> Strikingly, we demonstrated that several seasonal and pandemic IAV strains each evoke elevated ROS production in endosomes and we therefore hypothesized that targeting endosomal compartments to limit ROS production could reduce the viral burden associated with influenza infections. We developed an innovative molecular targeting system to deliver a specific NOX2 oxidase inhibitor (cholestanol‐conjugated gp91ds‐TAT; Cgp91ds‐TAT) to dampen the ROS response and limit viral pathogenesis.
 <xref rid="resp13524-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="resp13524-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref> This innovative endosome‐specific targeting system provided proof‐of‐principle for limiting ROS production to restrict viral pathogenesis, using a mild influenza viral strain, that is Hong Kong H3N2 X‐31 strain.
 <xref rid="resp13524-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref> To advance the concept that Cgp91ds‐TAT blocks the pathology to IAV infection irrespective of pathogenicity, the present study aimed to examine the effect of endosomal NOX2 inhibition against the highly virulent PR8 strain of IAV. In striking contrast to the mild Hkx‐31 strain, PR8 causes a more profound lung inflammation that is characterized by a high degree of peribronchial inflammation and parenchymal inflammation or alveolitis. Here, we show that Cgp91ds‐TAT treatment 1 day prior to PR8 infection significantly reduced airway and lung inflammation, and in particular alveolitis, neutrophil infiltration and oxidative stress. This confirmed that endosomal ROS promotes a deleterious inflammatory immune response in the lung, following influenza virus infection, and that this may be exploited as a novel therapeutic target via local delivery of endosomal NOX2 oxidase inhibitors.
</p>
