<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The use of molecular methodologies based on viral gene sequencing and phylogenetic analysis is the best approach to identify and confirm potential suspected viral transmission events, by assessing genetic viral similarities within the individuals allegedly involved. A number of studies have shown that a phylogenetic tree analysis of individual HCV RNA isolates provides clear documentation of HCV transmissions occurring within healthcare settings. In 2006, molecular phylogenetic analysis was used to prove the innocence of foreign medical staff accused of transmitting HIV strains to children being treated in a hospital in Benghazi, in Libya [
 <xref rid="B30-cells-08-00666" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In that study, in fact, researchers showed that both HCV and HIV-1 strains were already circulating in the hospital, before the arrival of the foreign medical staff in March 1998, suggesting that the hospital had a long-standing nosocomial infection control problem [
 <xref rid="B30-cells-08-00666" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Several other nosocomial HCV transmission scenarios have been observed, with HCV infection transmission between haemodialysis patients [
 <xref rid="B51-cells-08-00666" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-cells-08-00666" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-cells-08-00666" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-cells-08-00666" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-cells-08-00666" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-cells-08-00666" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>], or among hematologic patients, generally through inappropriate use of medical devices (e.g., the inappropriate reuse of saline flush syringes) [
 <xref rid="B57-cells-08-00666" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] and in patients with β-thalassemia [
 <xref rid="B58-cells-08-00666" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-cells-08-00666" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. However, the number of reported transmissions during the acute phase is limited, mainly because acute HCV infections are not always detected, due to the asymptomatic nature of the infection. Recently, an outbreak of HCV transmission in a Dutch haemodialysis unit was documented through the use of NS5A gene sequencing [
 <xref rid="B10-cells-08-00666" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. We have also recently identified separate episodes of HCV transmission in two healthcare settings by performing a phylogenetic analysis on NS3, NS5A and NS5B genes using Sanger sequencing: one case regarding patients with acute HCV infection diagnosis affected by onco-hematologic disease [
 <xref rid="B36-cells-08-00666" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and the second case in patients with acute HCV infection diagnosis with β-thalassemia [
 <xref rid="B31-cells-08-00666" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In this present study, through NS5A NGS analysis we aimed to investigate the intra-host viral quasispecies composition in 15 patients, all of whom were putatively involved in transmission clusters. The Bayesian analysis on NS5A gene confirmed the five transmission clusters considered epidemiologically monophyletic clades, by a posterior probability ≥90. Among the 15 patients analyzed, 14 patients were involved in transmission clusters, composed of between two and four patients per cluster. Among the five onco-hematologic patients, all of whom showing acute HCV infection in the same hospital during the same period, the NGS analysis confirmed a transmission cluster involving only four patients, with one patient outside the cluster, for whom no evidence of minority HCV variants in common with the other four patients was found. The other transmission clusters concerned β-thalassemia patients with acute and/or chronic HCV state of infection. Notably, three transmission clusters involved both acute and chronic HCV infected patients and one cluster involved three HCV chronic patients, all of whom were being treated in the same clinical center, during the same period. NGS analysis confirmed that all individuals were infected with HCV GT1b subtype, without cases of minority variants of other genotypes and/or HCV subtypes, excluding cases of coinfection. Overall, the Bayesian phylogenetic tree performed on NGS NS5A sequences confirmed the previous results, suggesting that the viruses present in the identified clusters have such a high degree of similarity that they can be assumed to have a common origin.
</p>
