<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recent advances in microfabrication, such as 3D printing and stereolithography, can allow for more sophisticated MNs designs.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref125">125</xref>
 </sup> Liquid-based vaccine formulations are still the most widely used.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref125">125</xref>
 </sup> However, liquid-based vaccine formulations are incompatible with most solid-based MNs forms. Inspired by the capability of snake-fangs to efficiently inject venom, Bae 
 <italic>et al</italic>. used an exposure lithography-based strategy to produce MNs patches with snake-fang architectures for efficient liquid formulations delivery.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref125">125</xref>
 </sup> The design was compatible with most existing vaccine formulations, and the patch can be applied with the pressure of the thumb and achieve an efficient transdermal delivery.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref125">125</xref>
 </sup> Nevertheless, solid-based vaccines, including MNs-based ones, also attracted significant attention because of the decreased cost of vaccine manufacturing, transport, and storage when compared to the liquid-based formulations.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref149">149</xref>
 </sup> One of the key challenges faced by these MNs patches is the loss of vaccine activity during the drying or heating process of MNs patch fabrication,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref150">150</xref>
 </sup> where molecular structures of vaccines may be disrupted.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref151">151</xref>
 </sup> Different strategies can be adopted, such as the use of lyoprotective polymers as MNs matrices, which include silk fibroin,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref122">122</xref>
 </sup> gelatin, dextran, and PVP,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref152">152</xref>
 </sup> or adding sugar molecules as stabilizing excipients, including trehalose and sucrose.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref147">147</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref152">152</xref>
 </sup> In the vaccine discovery phase, the introduction of certain mutations can improve the thermal stability of vaccines as well,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref148">148</xref>
 </sup> which can be further applied to specific MNs formulations. Additionally, a hyperstabilized vaccine formulation, such as the interbilayer-cross-linked multilamellar vesicles, helped protect vaccines during the drying process of MNs fabrication and have outperformed other traditional delivery strategies in inducing a potent antigen-specific immune response.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref123">123</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
