<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A thought-provoking keynote presentation was delivered by invited international speaker, 
 <bold>Benjamin tenOever</bold> (Icahn School of Medicine, Mount Sinai, New York, NY, USA) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00621-f008">Figure 8</xref>), who examined the implications of the evolution of RNA-mediated antiviral defenses from lower order prokaryotes, to simple eukaryotes through to higher mammals. During evolution, RNA-guided CRISPR defenses highly effective against DNA viruses, and accounting for 99% of prokaryote viruses, were replaced by RNA interference mechanisms. These mechanisms use short dsRNAs to guide the targeting of RNAse III enzymes to quell the RNA viruses that dominantly infect multicellular eukaryotes, and ultimately in mammals was replaced by interferon-mediated responses to viral DNA or structured RNA. While the ancient RNAi mechanisms were adopted into the miRNA pathway that offers fine control of gene expression, the presentation questioned why human viral defense came to depend largely on an interferon-mediated response to a wide variety of pathogen molecular patterns. Furthermore, did this evolution eliminate the utility of the ancestral RNA-mediated antiviral pathways? In a series of playful experiments that code tandem miRNA targets into mammalian (−)ssRNA 
 <italic>paramyxoviruses</italic> and 
 <italic>orthomyxoviruses</italic>, Ben tenOever showed that the RNA interference pathways used Dicer and Ago2, functioning only for miRNA biogenesis, were able to effect full control of virus replication. For (+)ssRNA viruses, where the target exists in incoming viral genomes, viral replication was slowed, but not eliminated, by the miRNA pathway acting for RNAi. Replication delay resulted from the short lag used precisely to excise the target miRNA sequences from the viral genome, probably due to homologous recombination. Targeting RNAi to nucleoprotein-coding RNA of (−)ssRNA viruses additionally leads to an induction of interferon response, whereas targeting to other regions, such as RNA-dependent polymerase, did not. These experiments of curiosity demonstrate that fully functional RNA defense pathways exist in vertebrates that may be limited by the lack of sufficiently active RNA-dependent RNA polymerases needed to produce the quantity of RNA effectors, especially for larger animals, or a mutually exclusive incompatibility between RNAi and interferon pathways. These findings have implications for new antiviral strategies in humans.
</p>
