<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig3">
 <label>Figure 3</label>
 <caption>
  <p>The effects of AIDS mortality and HIV transmission routes on the serodiscordant proportion (SDP). In the top row, the thick black lines show estimated historical SDP as fitted to the 2007 Demographic Health Survey in Zambia (chosen as a representative example); the black points indicate the SDP observed in the survey; gray lines show simulated SDP under various counterfactual scenarios: without AIDS mortality, with scaled pre-couple or extra-couple contact coefficients, with scaled transmission rates, or with increasing amounts of heterogeneity (
   <inline-formula id="IEq13">
    <alternatives>
     <tex-math id="M25">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\sigma $$\end{document}</tex-math>
     <math id="M26">
      <mrow>
       <mi>σ</mi>
      </mrow>
     </math>
     <inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24249_Article_IEq13.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </alternatives>
   </inline-formula> indicates standard deviation of lognormally distributed risk deviate) or between-partner assortativity (
   <inline-formula id="IEq14">
    <alternatives>
     <tex-math id="M27">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\rho $$\end{document}</tex-math>
     <math id="M28">
      <mrow>
       <mi>ρ</mi>
      </mrow>
     </math>
     <inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24249_Article_IEq14.gif" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </alternatives>
   </inline-formula> indicates inter-partner correlation in risk deviate) in infection risk. The lower row shows for each country the sensitivity of the simulated SDP (Y axis) in 2008 to variation in these same factors (on X axis). Colors indicate each country analyzed. Vertical gray bars highlight simulations parameterized as fit to the individual-level data on couple serostatus and relationship history. The serodiscordant proportion is extremely sensitive to the transmission rate, heterogeneity or assortativity in infection risk; slightly affected by AIDS mortality; and relatively insensitive to pre-couple and extra-couple contact coefficients. All simulated SDPs represent simulations of 100,000 couples.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_24249_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e2005" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
