<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several T cell-based vaccine candidates are in different stages of clinical development, the major underlying strategy of which is to deliver multiple T cell epitopes derived from different viral antigens including internal as well as surface antigens (Sridhar, 
 <xref rid="B213" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Delivery platforms include replicating or non-replicating viral vectors derived from vaccinia or adenovirus, recombinant VLPs, recombinant protein or peptide vaccines, and DNA vaccines (Sridhar, 
 <xref rid="B213" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Clemens et al., 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Modified vaccinia Ankara (MVA) vector encoding NP and M1 was shown to induce robust T cell responses and provide cross-protection against multiple subtypes in animals and humans (Antrobus et al., 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Powell et al., 
 <xref rid="B195" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Hessel et al., 
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Folegatti et al., 
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). The baculovirus VLPs carrying influenza HA/NA and M1 offered cross-protection where T cells played a significant role in protection in mice (Hemann et al., 
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Keshavarz et al., 
 <xref rid="B118" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Synthetic peptides or fusion proteins harboring multiple conserved T cell epitopes have also been evaluated for immunogenicity and protective efficacy in animal models (Adar et al., 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Rosendahl Huber et al., 
 <xref rid="B203" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). While the vaccine approaches described above deliver exogenous antigens and induce CD4+ T cells as well as CD8+ T cells by cross-presentation, DNA vaccines are designed to predominantly activate cytotoxic CD8+ T cells to recognize endogenously expressed antigens presented on MHC class I molecules. In fact, the first report on DNA vaccines was targeted to influenza virus (Cohen, 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>; Ulmer et al., 
 <xref rid="B232" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>), but initial success in a mouse model did not well-translate into higher animal models due to poor performance (Porter and Raviprakash, 
 <xref rid="B194" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). To date, much progress has been made to improve the efficacy of DNA vaccine against influenza virus, encompassing rational design of antigens and expression vectors and the development of novel adjuvants and delivery methods (Lee et al., 
 <xref rid="B148" ref-type="bibr">2018a</xref>). Candidate universal DNA vaccines encoding NP, matrix proteins, or PB1 were shown to decrease viral load and cross-protect against heterologous challenges in diverse animal models including mice, pigs, ferrets, and macaques (Ulmer et al., 
 <xref rid="B232" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>; Tompkins et al., 
 <xref rid="B228" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Price et al., 
 <xref rid="B197" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Bragstad et al., 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="B242" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Koday et al., 
 <xref rid="B128" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Further studies are required for to refine DNA vaccine approaches as a stand-alone UIV. Recent studies have indicated that DNA vaccines may serve an attractive component of prime-boost strategy, considering it as a very effective means to priming immune system when preexisting immunity is low (Ledgerwood et al., 
 <xref rid="B144" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; DeZure et al., 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Despite the potential for broad protection, the safety issues need to be monitored closely, especially because of the documented rise in pathological consequences associated with CTL responses (Peiris et al., 
 <xref rid="B187" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Duan and Thomas, 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).
</p>
