<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Viruses co-opt host cells for their replication. Viruses must employ aspects of the host cellular machinery to translate viral mRNA, and to avoid host defenses in order to replicate. Additionally, viral strategies to replicate include the use of non-coding RNAs, the manipulation of translation factors, as well as modification of host cell microRNAs that regulate genes [
 <xref rid="pone.0188333.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0188333.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Using small interfering RNA technology (siRNA) it is possible to knock-down (KD) host genes affecting virus replication allowing one to determine pro- and anti-viral genes [
 <xref rid="pone.0188333.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. A general approach in creating a universal vaccine cell line is to ablate host cell defenses, and/or create or improved cell tropism. Thus, the host-resistance genes to poliovirus (PV), influenza A virus (IAV) and rotavirus (RV) in Vero cells were identified using siRNAs [
 <xref rid="pone.0188333.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0188333.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0188333.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0188333.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The results show that one can increase virus replication without altering antigenicity [
 <xref rid="pone.0188333.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0188333.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0188333.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Once the host genes needed for virus replication are validated, it is possible with clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeat (CRISPR)-Cas9 reagents to knock-out (KO) host genes with goal of gene editing cells to improve viral antigen and/or increase viral replication with the long-term goal of creating enhanced vaccine cells lines [
 <xref rid="pone.0188333.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0188333.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].
</p>
