<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0100">Due to the diversity of viral particle sizes (from 25 nm to over 300 nm) and structures, viruses have evolved several strategies to export their DNA or RNA genome into the nucleoplasm. With regard to the NPC, these pathways can be divided into NPC-dependent and NPC-independent mechanisms. Due to size limitations, only a few, very small viral capsid particles, such as hepatitis B virus (HBV; 32–36 nm diameter), can pass through the NPC (
 <xref rid="bb0340" ref-type="bibr">Cohen et al., 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb1425" ref-type="bibr">Rabe et al., 2003</xref>) in an importin-dependent manner. HBV then disassembles at the nuclear side of the NPC (the nuclear basket), releasing its genome into the nucleoplasm (
 <xref rid="bb0485" ref-type="bibr">Fay and Panté, 2015</xref>). The capsid shells or ribonucleoprotein complexes (RNPs) of some larger viruses, such as influenza A virus and HIV-1, disassemble within the cytoplasm. The viral genome, released from the shell and complexed with NLS-containing components, is then translocated through the NPC (
 <xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">Ambrose and Aiken, 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0210" ref-type="bibr">Campbell and Hope, 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0340" ref-type="bibr">Cohen et al., 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0485" ref-type="bibr">Fay and Panté, 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0785" ref-type="bibr">Hutchinson and Fodor, 2013</xref>). Another mechanism, used by herpes simplex virus (HSV) and adenoviruses, involves cellular (importins, Nup) or viral protein-mediated attachment (docking) of the capsid shell at the cytoplasmic side of the NPC. This facilitates the passage of genomic DNA into the NPC either by ejection from an almost intact particle (through the capsid portal in HSV-1) or upon complete disassembly of the capsid shell (in adenoviruses) (
 <xref rid="bb0945" ref-type="bibr">Kremer and Nemerow, 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb1295" ref-type="bibr">Ojala et al., 2000</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb1350" ref-type="bibr">Pasdeloup et al., 2009</xref>). NPC-independent mechanisms are used by some retroviruses (e.g. MLV) that enter the nucleus during the mitotic phase of the cell division cycle when the nuclear envelope is dissolved (
 <xref rid="bb1165" ref-type="bibr">Matreyek and Engelman, 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb1485" ref-type="bibr">Roe et al., 1993</xref>). Another mechanism, described for parvoviruses, involves partial disruption of the nuclear envelope (
 <xref rid="bb0335" ref-type="bibr">Cohen and Pante, 2005</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0485" ref-type="bibr">Fay and Panté, 2015</xref>).
</p>
