<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0185">Traditional Indian medicine use plants, minerals and animal products for curing human diseases. Traditional knowledge regarding the plant sources and their usage are essential to use them accurately and for the right condition (
 <xref rid="bb0735" ref-type="bibr">Tabuti et al., 2003</xref>) About 25,000 plant based formulations have been used in folk remedies in Indian medicine (
 <xref rid="bb0630" ref-type="bibr">Pundarikakshudu and Kanaki, 2019</xref>). Recently, the total number of Indian medicinal plants was estimated to be around 3000, yet, traditional practitioners use around 8000 different species for their practice (
 <xref rid="bb0630" ref-type="bibr">Pundarikakshudu and Kanaki, 2019</xref>). Traditional medicines are generally ignored in research and development of modern drugs since their translational potentials are often underestimated. Although these medicines are ambiguous, there are wide contexts for their usage in non-Western medical technology (
 <xref rid="bb0900" ref-type="bibr">Yuan et al., 2016</xref>). A single herb may contain many phytochemical constituents that function alone or in combination with other compounds to produce the desired pharmacological effect (
 <xref rid="bb0605" ref-type="bibr">Parasuraman et al., 2014</xref>). Due to their use in traditional medicine, many plant molecules have been studied and subsequently modulated into drugs for various diseases (
 <xref rid="bb0480" ref-type="bibr">Li-Weber, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr">Fabricant and Farnsworth, 2001</xref>). The search for new compounds with antiviral activity has often been unsatisfactory due to viral resistance along with viral latency and recurrent infection in immune-compromised patients (
 <xref rid="bb0730" ref-type="bibr">Sumithira et al., 2012</xref>). Among antiviral therapeutic methods, the majority of them are non-specific for viruses (
 <xref rid="bb0350" ref-type="bibr">Jiang et al., 2015</xref>). The advancements in developing antiviral agents are the major focus in medical research. The antiviral effects of medicinal plants have played a tremendous role at different stages of viral growth (
 <xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">Akram et al., 2018</xref>). Plant derived pharmacological formulations marked a major contribution for viral infections (
 <xref rid="bb0170" ref-type="bibr">Cragg et al., 1997</xref>). Based on the availability of suitable, efficient and rapid bioassay systems, the antiviral compounds have been used for rapid screening from plant extracts and fractions (
 <xref rid="bb0675" ref-type="bibr">Scior et al., 2012</xref>). Instead of synthetic antiviral drugs, medicinal plants deliver basic raw materials for important antiviral drugs (
 <xref rid="bb0560" ref-type="bibr">Moghadamtousi et al., 2015</xref>). Synthetic drugs have been replaced by medicinal plants, as life-saving drugs (
 <xref rid="bb0275" ref-type="bibr">Gurib-Fakim, 2006</xref>) in various viral diseases. Unfortunately, the usage of these medication have been passed down to generations by word of mouth and most of them have been lost over time, due to the lack of proper documentation. Research on these herbs and medicinal plants may help to promote their usage in clinical settings to prevent or treat various illnesses. Since many Indian medicinal plants exhibit antiviral, anti-inflammatory and antioxidant properties, it may be favorable to consider them for the treatment of COVID-19. It is clear that standard clinical trials should be carried out to scientifically prove its efficacy.
</p>
