<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Only four of these twelve strains generated successful epidemics in humans: HIV-1 groups M and O, and HIV-2 groups A and B. The pandemic group M strain clusters most closely with SIVcpz endemic in wild chimpanzees from the southeast corner of Cameroon 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Keele1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. There is compelling evidence, both from serology and AIDS cases, that HIV-1 infections were initially restricted to the Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC) 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hooper1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Rmy1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. The geographical origin of the simian ancestor of HIV-1 group O is still unknown, but its human epicenter was Cameroon, a country to which it remains largely restricted 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-QuionesMateu1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. Both HIV-2 groups A and B cluster more closely with SIVsmm from sooty mangabeys living in the forests of southwestern Côte d'Ivoire 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Santiago1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Both groups spread abundantly in this country, and have spread only recently to Guinea, Sierra Leone, and Liberia, while group A was able to spread to Guinea-Bissau early in its epidemic history 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hooper1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-DeCock1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. This suggests that Côte d'Ivoire was the main early epicenter of these HIV-2 groups. Of the four main groups, HIV-1 group O is the most confined; it currently infects only tens of thousands of people, mainly in Cameroon and Nigeria 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-QuionesMateu1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Peeters1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Ayouba1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. HIV-1 group N is much rarer and restricted to Cameroon 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Yamaguchi2" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref> and the remaining HIV groups have been found in just one patient 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hahn1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Marx1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Yamaguchi1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Plantier1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, including the recently identified HIV-1 group P strain 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Plantier1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. See 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0009936.s001">Figure S1</xref> for an illustration of HIV biogeography.
</p>
