<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is conceivable that host or circumstantial factors currently increasing the transmissibility of HIV were also involved in its origin and initial spread. This notion is implicit in the theories that proposed unsterile injections as the driving factor 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Marx1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Gisselquist1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Ppin1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. Standard per-reuse transmissibility of unsterile intravenous injections is considerably higher than standard per-act sexual transmissibility (0.6–1.6% vs. 0.05–0.1%) 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Gisselquist2" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hayes1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. However, the involvement of genital ulcer disease (GUD) dramatically raises the latter. GUD-assisted per-act transmissibilities for HIV-1 were estimated at: 1) man to woman with GUD: 7.4% (95% CI 3.8–15.7%) 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hayes1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>; 2) woman with GUD to man: 16% (95% CI 6–32%) in a cohort in which two thirds of the men were circumcised; the measured per-act transmissibility was 4% for the circumcised men, and 43% for the uncircumcised 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Hayes1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Cameron1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. Although the per-exposure risk for men with GUD has not been measured, evidence from observational studies also suggest a very high HIV transmission risk 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Fleming1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Freeman1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. The effect of GUD infections is also very strong at the population level: more than half of new HIV infections in Africa might be attributed to GUD facilitated transmission 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-White1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. However, to our knowledge no study has investigated the role of GUD prevalence in the origin, initial spread and adaptation of HIV. Another host factor linked with HIV transmissibility is circumcision. For heterosexual men, per-act risk of HIV-1 acquisition is about 6–11 times higher if they are uncircumcised 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Cameron1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Baeten1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, although more moderate odds ratios have been estimated over longer periods. For uncircumcised men exposed to GUD-suffering sex workers, the measured per-act risk was 43% 
 <xref rid="pone.0009936-Cameron1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. Second to transfusions, this is the highest HIV transmissibility ever measured.
</p>
