<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>BRD has negative effects on the animals' life and the producers' economy. It is a major cause of morbidity, mortality and economic loss in both the beef and dairy cattle industries (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Fatalities, treatment costs, and handling of sick animals contribute to the economic losses in the acute stage of an outbreak. Considerably higher number of animals are usually found to have lung-lesions at slaughter, compared to the number of clinical BRD cases in a herd. This indicates that observed clinical cases represent only part of the problem (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). The long-term consequences are also less recognized, but reduced feed conversion, growth rate and performance might contribute considerably to the total economic losses. A long-term reduction in weight gain (7 months) was seen following a BRD outbreak among bulls in Norway (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Calves with BRD have also been found to produce less milk when they reach first lactation (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). National studies from the UK have estimated costs associated with BRD amounting to £80 million annually for the cattle industry (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). The only scientific publication where the national-level economic effect of BRD has been estimated is from France, where an epidemiology- and productivity model was used to link BRD incidence with productivity in the different cattle industry sectors (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). The authors found that eradication of BRD in beef calves would increase the whole beef sector's productivity by 4.7–5.5%, but that the benefits from eradication would differ between enterprises. For example, young bull and veal feedlot enterprises were estimated to increase in productivity by 8.7–12.8% while the breeding farms would gain less (5.1–6.0%) (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>).
</p>
