<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although we obtained no conclusive evidence that regions at the Mexico-U.S. border were enzootic for VEEV, the potential for outbreaks in this region and the ability of the virus to spread into the U.S. remains a concern, as indicated by the involvement of at least 5 Texas counties, primarily Cameron and Hidalgo, during the 1969–1971 epidemic/epizootic 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001875-Walton1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001875-Sudia1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001875-Sudia2" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. Additionally, it is also known that several epizootic VEEV vectors inhabit the coastal regions of the States of Tamaulipas and Texas, specifically 
 <italic>Ae. taeniorhynchus</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae. sollicitans</italic>. These mosquitoes also can transmit enzootic strains of VEEV 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001875-Brault1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Moreover, the movement of hundreds-of-thousands of people per year across the Mexico-U.S. border is a concern because infected individuals have the potential to become viremic and transmit the virus to biting mosquitoes 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001875-Weaver1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001875-Bowen1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. In this regard, the states that were surveyed in our study (States of Tamaulipas, Veracruz, and Tabasco) were relevant because they are vital transit points for many people and animals moving within Mexico 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001875-US1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. According to some reports, approximately 400,000 people annually from at least 50 different nationalities begin their journey from the Mexico/Guatemala border, including the Tenosique-Balancan region of the State of Tabasco, with the ultimate goal of reaching major cities in the U.S. 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001875-Camara1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. This journey would take these individuals from the States of Chiapas and Tabasco, Mexico, through the State of Veracruz, and then, to one of the Mexico-U.S. border towns in the State of Tamaulipas 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001875-US1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001875-Camarota1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. If immigrants cross the border into the U.S. in areas that are also “hot spots” of endemic or epizootic VEEV activity, they could become the source of VEEV transmission 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001875-Bowen1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0001875-Bowen2" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0001875-Weaver2" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>.
</p>
