<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although the original Task Force and those who have updated their work acknowledged certain key obstacles, in reality, even when the commitment is strong, funding is seldom entirely sufficient for the tasks at hand, motivation of all key stakeholders is difficult to sustain, and political and social insecurities remain an unpredictable threat. The intensive effort to eradicate polio has been a test case. In 1988 WHO formally initiated its campaign to eradicate poliomyelitis. Under the overall leadership of WHO, it and numerous public and private organizations (e.g., CDC, Rotary International, UNICEF, and the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation) have persevered in this mission for more than 20 years [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR172">170</xref>]. It is noteworthy that even before the inception of this more coordinated effort, in 1979 Rotary International began its remarkable commitment to polio eradication, and for three decades, through its worldwide chapters, it performed tireless vaccine campaign work that has recently captured the attention of major news organizations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR173">171</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR174">172</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR178">176</xref>]. By 2006 polio remained endemic in only four countries, whereupon gains continued but began to be punctuated by periodic setbacks. Then new blows began to be struck in late 2012 as a result of lethal attacks on health-care workers conducting polio immunization campaigns in Pakistan and Nigeria and even on their police escorts [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR175">173</xref>], as well as introductions into countries where war had degraded the public health infrastructure. Continual political and social unrest has fueled the spread of lies about motives of the health workers and the consequences of immunization [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR176">174</xref>]. All of this turmoil has seriously threatened the eradication program.
</p>
