<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our top predictors of viral emergence require a comprehensive sampling of the viral and host population. Although exact measurements of these quantities are practically infeasible, our results suggest that targeting molecular surveillance towards precise and accurate estimation of viral growth rates, both for newly emerging clusters and the resident circulating viruses, may enhance influenza prediction. One approach is to target the two key components of growth rate separately––mutational load and effective susceptibility. Changes in the mutational load can be estimated from sequence data, comparing the number of differences that occur in non-epitope portions of the genome over time [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Our parameterization of 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>c</sub> follows the empirical method of [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], with fitness costs based on nonsynonymous amino acid differences between a given strain and its most recent common ancestor. Estimating the effective susceptibility is more challenging, as it depends on the interaction between an individual’s exposure history [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>–
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] and new amino acid substitutions in epitope coding regions [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Nonetheless, several studies introduce innovative methods for estimating susceptibility from the historic distribution of influenza subtypes, seasonal influenza prevalence, and HI-titers. For example, Neher 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] predict antigenic properties of novel clades by mapping both serological and sequence data to a phylogenetic tree structure of HA sequences. Łuksza &amp; Lässig estimate effective susceptibility by first estimating the historic frequency of clades in six-month intervals and then estimating cross-immunity between those clades and the focal cluster based on amino acid differences in epitope regions [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007683.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. However, both methods only consider clusters that have already surpassed 10% relative frequency, at which point strains are thought to be geographically well-mixed and less prone to geographic sampling bias.
</p>
