<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0080">Molecular features of the viral coronavirus family, which includes SARS–CoV, MERS-CoV, and the recently identified novel Coronavirus (SARS–CoV-2), have been well-elucidated. A review of the coronavirus structure and function help to inform us on the pathophysiology of coronavirus infectivity. Coronaviruses are large, single-stranded, enveloped RNA viruses approximately 32 kilobase (
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). The viral RNA genome is housed inside a nucleocapsid, which itself is contained within a viral envelope (
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). This envelope comprises three distinct proteins: a “membrane protein” and “envelope protein,” which are both directly responsible for viral assembly, as well as a “spike protein,” which mediates viral entry into host cells (
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). When viewed with electron microscopy, these spike proteins are surface-exposed markers that produce a recognizable “crown-like” appearance to the virus. The spike proteins serve a critical step in initiating human infection, as well as determining host tissue specificity and inducing host immune response (
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). The coronavirus spike protein is composed of two unique subunits that facilitate viral-host binding (
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). The S1 domain of the spike protein functions in viral binding and attachment to the host cell membrane. Numerous receptors on the human cell membrane that are involved in S1 subunit binding have been identified to date, including angiotensin-converting enzyme-2 (ACE2), CD26, Ezrin, and cyclophilins (
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). The S2 domain of the spike protein is responsible for fusion of the viral and host cell membranes, allowing the SARS–CoV-2 viral genome to enter the host cell. This process involves a complex interaction between viral and host machinery, which culminates in rapid viral replication within target cells. International research efforts are currently underway aimed at using the S1 domain of the spike protein as a target for therapeutic anti-viral therapy, as well as vaccine development.
</p>
