<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> C6/36 cloned cell lines infected separately with reference strains of DENV1-4 [
 <xref rid="pone.0231408.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] were kindly provided by the Genetech, Sri Lanka. RNA was extracted from field collected specimens following methods described by Boom 
 <italic>et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0231408.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] with some modifications. Briefly, an aliquot of 140 μl of specimen samples were transferred to 1.5 ml micro-centrifuge tube containing 10 μl of acid treated Silica Coarse (SC) and 1 ml of lysis buffer. Then, the solution was vortexed for 15 seconds followed by incubation for 5 minutes at room temperature. After that, the tube was vortexed again for 15 seconds and incubated for 5 minutes at room temperature. Then, the tube was centrifuged at 12,000 rpm for 10 seconds at room temperature and the supernatant was discarded. Next, an aliquot of 1 ml of washing buffer was transferred into the micro-centrifuge tube and the solution was mixed well by vortexing for 15 seconds. Then, the tube was centrifuged at 12,000 rpm for 10 seconds at room temperature and the supernatant was discarded. The washing step was repeated again. An aliquot of 500 μl of double DW was added and the tube was inverted until the silica pellet was dissolved. After centrifuging at 12,000 rpm for 10 seconds, the supernatant was discarded. Next, the tube was centrifuged again at 12,000 rpm for 10 seconds again and the remaining water was removed carefully. Then, an aliquot of 20 μl of PCR water was added and the SC pellet was dissolved well by tapping prior to incubation at 56°C for 10 minutes. After the incubation period, the tube was centrifuged at 12,000 rpm for 10 seconds and an aliquot of 14 μl of the supernatant was transferred into a 1.5 ml new micro-centrifuge tube. An aliquot of 4U of RNase inhibitor (RNaseOut
 <sup>TM</sup>, Invitrogen, USA) was added before storing the isolated RNA at -20°C (R600a, HISENSE, China).
</p>
