<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our analysis assumes that any ZIKV outbreaks in Texas originate with infected travelers returning from active ZIKV regions. To estimate the ZIKV importation rate for specific counties, we (1) estimated the Texas statewide importation rate (expected number of imported cases per day) for August 2016, (2) estimated the probability 
 <italic>(import risk)</italic> that the next Texas import will arrive in each county, and (3) took the product of the state importation rate and each county importation probability.
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p>During the first quarter of 2016, 27 ZIKV travel-associated cases were reported in Texas [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], yielding a baseline first quarter estimate of 0.3 imported cases/day throughout Texas. In 2014 and 2015, arbovirus introductions into Texas increased threefold over this same time period, perhaps driven by seasonal increases in arbovirus activity in endemic regions and the approximately 40% increase from quarter 1 to quarter 3 in international travelers to the US [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Taking this as a 
    <italic>baseline</italic> (lower bound) scenario, we projected a corresponding increase in ZIKV importations to 0.9 cases/day (statewide) for the third quarter.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>To build a predictive model for import risk, we fit a probabilistic model (maximum entropy) [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>] of importation risk to 183 DENV, 38 CHIKV, and 31 ZIKV Texas county-level reported importations from 2002 to 2016 and 10 informative socioeconomic, environmental, and travel variables (Additional file 
    <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: section 1.1). Given the geographic and biological overlap between ZIKV, DENV and Chikungunya (CHIKV), we used historical DENV and CHIKV importation data to supplement ZIKV importations in the importation risk model, while recognizing that future ZIKV importations may be fueled by large epidemic waves in neighboring regions and summer travel, and thus far exceed recent DENV and CHIKV importations [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Currently, DENV, CHIKV, and ZIKV importation patterns differ most noticeably along the Texas-Mexico border. Endemic DENV transmission and sporadic CHIKV outbreaks in Mexico historically have spilled over into neighboring Texas counties. In contrast, ZIKV is not yet as widespread in Mexico as it is in Central and South America, with less than 10 reported ZIKV importations along the border to date (October 2016). We included DENV and CHIKV importation data in the model fitting so as to consider potential future importation pressure from Mexico, as ZIKV continues its increasing trend since March 2016 [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. To find informative predictors for ZIKV importation risk, we analyzed 72 socio-economic, environmental, and travel variables, and removed near duplicate variables and those that contributed least to model performance, based on out-of-sample cross validation of training and testing sets of data [
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], reducing the original set of 72 variables to 10 (Additional file 
    <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Tables S3-S4). We validated our importation model by comparing the predicted distribution of cases across the state given a total number of imported cases (September 2016) as a linear predictor of the empirical distribution of cases across counties.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
