<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The HA stalk region, in contrast to the HA head region, is less immunogenic. The antigenic subdominance of HA stalk region may be due to the steric shielding of HA head domain, making it less accessible to the humoral immunity [
 <xref rid="B85-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Therefore, antibodies against the stalk region are not readily stimulated and detected in natural infection of humans. Nevertheless, low levels of stalk-specific B cells are detected in influenza patients [
 <xref rid="B86-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. Furthermore, anti-stalk antibodies with broad neutralizing activity have been isolated and characterized [
 <xref rid="B87-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>,
 <xref rid="B88-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="B89-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>,
 <xref rid="B90-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>,
 <xref rid="B91-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>,
 <xref rid="B92-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. Since the stalk domain is more conserved than the head domain, these antibodies exhibit broad-spectrum binding and are capable of conferring heterosubtypic protection by interfering with the membrane fusion. HA stalk antibodies were shown to neutralize subtypes in the same group or cross both group 1 and group 2 [
 <xref rid="B93-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>,
 <xref rid="B94-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. Ekiert et al. reported that HA stalk-binding human antibody, CR6261, neutralizes multiple influenza subtypes from group 1 [
 <xref rid="B95-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. Corti et al. found that one antibody generated from single human plasma targeting fusion sub-domain of the HA stalk could bind and neutralize influenza A viruses from both group 1 and group 2 [
 <xref rid="B94-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. Dreyfus et al. reported an HA stalk-binding antibody, CR9114, broad binding to influenza A and B HAs and the antibody was able to confer protection against not only influenza A virus infection, but also influenza B virus infection in mice [
 <xref rid="B89-viruses-12-00276" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]. It should be noted that some antibodies targeting the stalk region are not highly potent when compared to those against the head region. This deficiency should be addressed in future studies.
</p>
