<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Zoonoses refer to infectious diseases that are transmissible between animals and humans. Such transmission occurs either directly or indirectly through vectors between humans and animals to transport pathogens from one organism to another. Types of pathogens include viruses, bacteria, mold, parasites, and protozoa. Their modes of transmission are direct contact with or inhalation of pathogens, consumption of food or water containing pathogens, and vector bites [
 <xref rid="B25-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Chikungunya is a zoonosis spread by vector mosquitoes (
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic>) that bite natural hosts. The chikungunya virus is maintained in nature in both urban and sylvatic cycles involving mosquito vectors and human or vertebrate animal hosts [
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. A study indicated that the unprecedented destruction of natural barriers between nonhuman primates and humans has increased health risks for a large population, including people living in urban areas [
 <xref rid="B28-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Additionally, the chikungunya virus is an RNA virus with a high mutation rate of up to one million times higher than that of their hosts, and these high rates are associated with enhanced virulence and evolvability, which are beneficial traits for viruses [
 <xref rid="B29-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Population growth as well as improper and excessive land development in Taiwan have damaged natural spaces and disturbed ecosystems, thereby increasing human exposure to wild animals and vector insects. Therefore, residents of cities (or the countryside) in Taiwan typically live in the same geographical areas as macaques living in mountains. It was unknown whether any study has described chikungunya infection in primates in Taiwan. Such a geographical area of modern urban living space is also a hot zone of viral spread by arthropod vectors. In particular, international studies have reported that the chikungunya [
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] and dengue viruses [
 <xref rid="B30-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], which are spread by vectors, are often transmitted between humans and monkeys. Such cross-species infection poses a severe threat to human health. According to a Taiwan CDC report [
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], the 20 chikungunya cluster cases in Taiwan overlapped considerably with imported cases from Myanmar in terms of the patients’ neighborhoods of residence and regularly visited places. Patients with imported cases from Myanmar lived only hundreds of meters away from those with domestic cases, and patients with both imported and domestic cases has visited mountain trails in their neighborhoods (risk areas) during the incubation period. Among water-holding containers along the mountain trails tested by a health and environmental protection specialist, 24.6% tested positive for 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic>, and they had a level-6 container index, indicating an extremely high risk of vector mosquito transmission. Laboratory results indicated that the DNA sequence of the virus in an imported case from Myanmar had high affinity to that of the domestic cases. Therefore, this study inferred that the genotype of the virus strain that infected the chikungunya cluster cases in 2019 originated in Myanmar. A study also indicated that two genotypes of chikungunya virus strains were imported to Taiwan between 2006 and 2014, namely ECSA and Asian [
 <xref rid="B32-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The ECSA genotype was the most commonly imported genotype of the chikungunya virus before 2010; strains with this genotype originated mainly in Bangladesh, Malaysia, India, and Thailand. The Asian genotype was most common after 2011; strains with this genotype were mainly from Indonesia, the Philippines, and Singapore. This serves as a reminder for Taiwan’s vulnerable public-health system that, in addition to understanding pathogens, Taiwan must adopt comprehensive disease control measures, enhance environmental protection, and prevent the breeding of vector mosquitoes to effectively prevent the spread of chikungunya and protect the public from this health crisis.
</p>
