<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Because the government regards the epidemic as a war, this study referred to the Taiwan CDC’s promotion of epidemic prevention [
 <xref rid="B33-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] and revealed numerous breeding sites in mountainous areas. However, epidemic control in those areas is difficult. Compared with the dengue virus, the chikungunya virus requires less time to replicate in the body; thus, it has a higher transmission speed than the dengue virus does. Vector mosquitoes of chikungunya are not selective regarding bite targets, implying that, after the chikungunya virus enters a community that contains breeding sites for vector mosquitoes, chikungunya spread is possible. Therefore, people should ensure that breeding sites for vector mosquitoes are located away from living spaces. This study proposed the following recommendations to prevent chikungunya: (1) measures should be enacted to prevent mosquito bites among people in areas with chikungunya spread. These people may reside in buildings with installed window screens or air conditioning. During outdoor activities, they should apply mosquito repellents that are certified by the competent authority to contain N,N-diethyl-meta-toluamide or picaridin [
 <xref rid="B34-ijerph-17-03615" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. If they plan to remain outdoors for an extended period, they should wear long-sleeved tops and pants on which mosquito repellent should be applied to enhance protection. (2) Preventive measures can be enacted at home and during outdoor activities. All vases and water-holding containers, particularly their inner surfaces, should be washed weekly. To prevent vector mosquitoes from breeding in stagnant water, all indoor vases and containers not in use should be stored upside down. All waste tires and outdoor water-holding containers should be removed immediately. Additionally, epidemic-control specialists and public-health experts may conduct epidemic-control interventions as well as promote and communicate relevant information to medical practitioners and the public through media in a timely manner to improve people’s understanding and awareness of chikungunya. Such collaboration among health and epidemic-control agencies, clinical doctors at medical institutions, and the public may facilitate effective control of the spread.
</p>
