<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0200">Discovery efforts have been focused on targeting SARS-CoV-1 structural proteins. In one study, bioinformatic analysis was used to identify 10 peptides from the S protein sequence. Two peptides (P8: PSSKRFQPFQQFGRDVSDFT and P9: CANLLL
 <underline>QYGSFCTQLNRALSGIA</underline>) blocked the interaction of viral S protein with the host ACE2 receptor and showed promising viral neutralization in syncytia formation models at nearly 50 % [
 <xref rid="bib0665" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>]. In a separate study, a set of 20-residue peptides derived from S protein fragments were investigated. Four peptides (P2: PTTFMLKYDENGTITDAVDC, P6: YQDVNCTDVSTAIHADQLTP, P8: 
 <underline>QYGSFCTQLNRALSGIA</underline>AEQ and P10: IQKEIDRLNEVAKNLNESLI) showed significant antiviral effects in cytopathic effect (CPE)-based assays, a reduction in viral titer in TCID50 assays, as well as a reduction in intracellular viral RNA levels as determined by quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR). The antiviral effects of P8 were further confirmed by electron microscopy, which showed the absence of virus in the P8-treated cells and the presence of SARS-CoV-1 particles in the untreated cells [
 <xref rid="bib1160" ref-type="bibr">232</xref>]. It should be noted that the sequence corresponding to 737–753 (
 <underline>QYGSFCTQLNRALSGIA)</underline> of the S protein was shared in both studies mentioned above, warranting further work to optimize this peptide. In another study, S protein derived peptide S
 <sub>471−503</sub> (ALNCYWPLNDYGFYTTTGIGYQPYRWVLSFEL) was identified and shown to block the interaction between receptor binding domain (RBD) and ACE2 in a competition ELISA and inhibit plaque formation of SARS-CoV in Vero E6 cells [
 <xref rid="bib0475" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. Additional viral structural proteins have been studied as potential targets. N protein from the nucleocapsid forms a complex with the viral RNA [
 <xref rid="bib0640" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. A 15-mer peptide phage display library was panned against purified N protein. As a result, six phage clones that bound to the N protein in ELISA were identified. The selected peptides had high homology with the peptide SNA5 (GGGWFCPIVRGRVSC) that appeared at the highest frequency among the selected peptides.
</p>
