<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In adult Swiss mice, the CbaAr-4005 strain of SLEV resulted in 100% (10/10) illness and death compared with sympatric nonepidemic SLEV strains isolated previously in Córdoba and Santa Fe Province, Argentina (
 <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>26</italic>
 </xref>). Inoculation of only 1 plaque-forming unit in 10-day-old mice or 2 plaque-forming units in 21-day-old mice caused a 50% death rate with the strain CbaAr-4005 (lethal dose 50 [LD
 <sub>50</sub>] in 10-day-old mice = 0.02), proving it to be the most lethal strain compared in the study (78V-6507
 <sub>LD50</sub> = 1.75; CorAn-9275
 <sub>LD50</sub> = 3.90). That evidence supports the hypothesis that a more virulent SLEV strain was introduced into Córdoba City in early 2005 from Santa Fe (Argentina) or São Paulo (Brazil) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Serologic studies of wild birds sampled before and during the 2005 outbreak indicated that 99% (434/437) of the avian population lacked a SLEV-neutralizing antibody and were therefore susceptible to infection with SLEV, potentially serving as amplification hosts (
 <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>27</italic>
 </xref>). The absence of natural immunity in the wild avian population may have promoted the 2005 SLE outbreak in Córdoba City. A host competence study in avian species showed that the eared dove (
 <italic>Zenaida auriculata</italic>) and picui ground-dove (
 <italic>Columbina picui</italic>) produce high levels of viremia compared with other avian species tested (
 <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>28</italic>
 </xref>). Moreover, that study confirmed the role as amplifying host of these 2 doves species during the 2005 SLEV outbreak in Córdoba. Additional studies indicate that the population of eared doves has been increasing in the central region of Argentina during the past 10 years because of agricultural geographic expansion (
 <xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>29</italic>
 </xref>).
</p>
