<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Using the validated model, we were interested in where the temperature was suitable for 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and/or 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> transmission for some or all of the year to predict the potential geographic range of outbreaks in the Americas. We visualized the minimum, median, and maximum extent of transmission based on probability of occurrence thresholds from the 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> models for both mosquitoes. We calculated the number of consecutive months in which the posterior probability of 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> &gt; 0 exceeds a threshold of 0.025, 0.5, or 0.975 for both mosquito species, representing the maximum, median, and minimum likely ranges, respectively. The minimum range is shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005568.g004">Fig 4</xref> and all three ranges are overlaid in Fig D in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0005568.s001">S1 Text</xref>. This analysis indicates the predicted seasonality of temperature suitability for transmission geographically, but does not indicate its magnitude. To generate the maps, we cropped monthly mean temperature rasters from 1950–2000 for all twelve months (Worldclim; 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldclim.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.worldclim.org/</ext-link>) to the Americas (
 <italic>R</italic>, 
 <italic>raster</italic> package, 
 <italic>crop</italic> function) and assigned cells values of one or zero depending on whether the probability that 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> &gt; 0 exceeded the threshold at the temperatures in those cells. We then synthesized the monthly grids into a single raster that reflected the maximum number of consecutive months where cell values equaled one. The resulting rasters were plotted in ArcGIS 10.3, overlaying the three cutoffs (Fig D in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0005568.s001">S1 Text</xref>). We employed this process for both mosquito species.
</p>
