<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We demonstrate the potential for substantial heterogeneity in the intensity of block-level dengue transmission. Based on the relatively low average daily rates of transmission that can be inferred from prior studies on fine scale dengue transmission[
 <xref rid="pone.0144451.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0144451.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], there was little expectation of finding high levels of PCR positivity within city blocks, particularly in highly endemic areas of cities that have experienced prior of epidemics of DEN2. Indeed, in 8 of the 10 study patches PCR positivity in children was below 30%. Thus our findings of 9/16 PCR positive children in Barranquilla and 22/23 in Armenia confirm the theoretical prediction of high variability in the daily force of dengue infection [
 <xref rid="pone.0144451.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0144451.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Given the short time window in which PCR positivity can be maintained, these data suggest an intensity of fine-scale dengue transmission far exceeding previous estimates from rural and urban areas. Particularly extraordinary is the simultaneous infection with DEN2 virus of 22 children residing in a 2-block patch in La Fachada, the highest DF-reporting neighborhood in Armenia (2001–2011). Armenia, in turn, was the Colombian city with the highest number of reported DF cases between 2001 and 2006, and almost certainly experienced epidemics of DEN2 during this period, based on INS records. The PCR22 patch had a number of distinguishing factors that might make it prone to dengue transmission, including the highest under five population, lowest residence time and highest Breteau Index (
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> habitats per house). This finding begged the question of how susceptibility to DEN2 was maintained despite such intense historical dengue transmission in the surrounding areas.
</p>
