<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The currently predominant viral infections are the result of evolutionary processes between hosts and parasites which have taken place over very long time periods. Frequently, viral species related to human pathogens are found in various animal species. It is thought that these have adapted to humans during their evolution to become human pathogens, which remain permanently in the population after a certain period of time. If they are highly pathogenic for humans, then they will eliminate themselves from the population by destroying their hosts immediately. Therefore, the ideal situation is a balance between survival of the host and a more or less optimal viral replication with minimal damage. Examples for the optimal adaptation to a host are some arenaviruses (10.1007/978-3-642-20718-1_16), among them lymphocytic choriomeningitis virus and the causative agent of Lassa fever. Both viruses are highly adapted to their hosts, namely wild mice. These viruses are transmitted vertically during pregnancy to offspring, in which they induce an immune tolerance. These animals are healthy virus carriers, and excrete large amounts of viruses for life. However, if they infect humans, this frequently leads to severe diseases. Occasionally, new viral infections emerge in humans. This is particularly the case when contact occurs with rare and reclusive species which transmit the adapted pathogens to humans. An example in this context is the SARS epidemic of 2003. It is assumed that bats are the animal species that serves as the natural host of this very dangerous virus for humans (10.1007/978-3-642-20718-1_14). Other examples are human Nipah and Hendra infections, which are also transmitted by bats. Poliomyelitis was also a relatively well adapted human virus infection under living conditions with low hygiene standards. Here, the pathogen was usually transmitted during the first 6 months of life. Protective maternal IgG antibodies are still available in the infants at this time. Sequelae from the disease and occasionally paralysis are found only in infections occurring at an older age (10.1007/978-3-642-20718-1_14).</p>
