<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">Irrespective of whether they become infected, MOR-expressing, HIV or HIV protein-exposed astrocytes release greater amounts of inflammatory cytokines and dysfunction sufficient to harm bystander neurons upon treatment with opiates (El-Hage et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130">2005</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134">2008b</xref>; Zou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR560">2011</xref>; El-Hage et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR138">2014</xref>). MOR-expressing subsets of glia, especially microglia and astroglia, are prominent in driving the interactive opioid and HIV neuropathogenesis (Hauser et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR207">2007</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR209">2012</xref>; Hauser and Knapp 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR201">2014</xref>; Liu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR293">2016a</xref>; Chilunda et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">2019</xref>; Murphy et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR351">2019</xref>). When MOR is deleted from glia (astrocytes and microglia), morphine no longer increases the death of Tat-exposed striatal medium spiny neurons (MSNs) (Zou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR560">2011</xref>). Conversely, if MOR is deleted from MSNs, morphine exacerbates the neurotoxic effects of Tat in MSNs (Zou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR560">2011</xref>). The proinflammatory effects of Tat alone or in combination with morphine on glia are mediated through a Beclin-1-dependent autophagy pathway (Rodriguez et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR433">2017</xref>; Lapierre et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR269">2018</xref>). Drugs with selective glial anti-inflammatory activity (i.e., ibudilast or AV411) attenuated the deleterious effects of HIV and opiate exposure, including HIV-1 replication, cytokine release, and neurotoxicity in vitro (El-Hage et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR138">2014</xref>). Thus, the observed neuronal death is largely mediated by MOR-expressing glia (Zou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR560">2011</xref>), including astroglia (El-Hage et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130">2005</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134">2008b</xref>) and microglia (Turchan-Cholewo et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR514">2008</xref>; Bokhari et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2009</xref>; Turchan-Cholewo et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR515">2009</xref>; Gupta et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR195">2010</xref>).
</p>
