<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The therapy which is currently available in the world, can be divided into supportive, immunosuppressive, antiretroviral and possible new therapies (
 <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Supportive therapy consists of oxygen administration as well as hemodynamic support. Early intubation and invasive mechanical ventilation are crucial in patients with severe, progressive symptoms and where there is a great need for oxygenation. As heart damage has occurred, as it’s mentioned earlier, it is necessary to include therapy given for cardiac decompensation as well as antiarrhythmics. Due to thromboembolic complications, anticoagulant therapy must be included. Antiviral therapy is also included (
 <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>-
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). From the range of the drugs, Anakinra (Kineret) can be used, which blocks the activity of the specific cytokine interleukin 1 (IL-1). In addition, Tocilizumab (Actemra) is increasingly being used. Tocilizumab blocks the activity of another cytokine, interleukin 6 (IL-6), which is thought to be a key of biological mediator responsible for the cytokine storm. During a cytokine storm, an increase in IL-6 can have severe consequences for the cardiovascular system. Tachycardia, atrial fibrillation, hypotension, and left ventricular dysfunction may occur with concomitant increase in GNP. In a recently published retrospective multicenter analysis in 150 patients from Wuhan, IL-6 was a clinical predictor of mortality in COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). In China, Tocilizumab is approved for use in severe complications with COVID-19 and where IL-6 levels are elevated (
 <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). In Italy, too, Tocilizumab has been used successfully in critically ill patients where complications of COVID-19 have developed. Similar studies with tocilizumab are underway in France, Belgium and Denmark. Other therapeutic options include chloroquine, hydroxychloroquine, lopinavir/ritonavir (Kaletra), ribavirin, favipiravir, intravenous immunoglobulin, and Janus kinase (JAK) inhibition. Inhibition of JAK can affect inflammation and virus entry into cells (
 <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). The already mentioned therapy with corticosteroids and antibiotics is still possible.
</p>
