<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Reporting rates may vary significantly over time and location. For instance, temporal fluctuations in the number of available hospital beds may cause corresponding fluctuations in case ascertainment rates [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006161.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Increased case ascertainment through increased access to care may itself lower transmission rates, because hospitalized cases are less likely to transmit [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006161.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The number of non-hospitalized cases, and the proportion of non-hospitalized cases relative to the total case burden, are also important indicators of the impact of interventions [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006161.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], as fewer community based cases reflects better access to hospital care, or a downturn in transmission rates, or both. Estimates of reporting rates for non-hospitalized cases may not be a priority at the beginning of an outbreak. During an outbreak, such infrastructure is difficult to establish at an appropriate scale, beyond informal reports, until resources are allocated according to case data from patient hospitalizations. As a result, the non-hospitalized cases that occur in the initial weeks of an outbreak, in a new area, are often not extensively captured. Thus, transmission and reporting may be intertwined, making it difficult to tell whether a change in incidence is driven by contagion or surveillance thereof, although the relative contributions of the two processes can have important implications for public health responses. Estimates of disease transmission dynamics during the 2014–2016 Ebola epidemic drove recommendations for a variety of containment strategies—including contact tracing, quarantine, and safe burial—based on estimates of the reproductive number of the disease in different contexts [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006161.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. However, it is unclear how robust these analyses are to temporal and spatial fluctuations in ascertainment bias in case time series, especially in situations where many cases are unreported.
</p>
