<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="editorial"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?OLF?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Intensive Crit Care Nurs</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Intensive Crit Care Nurs</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Intensive &#x00026; Critical Care Nursing</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0964-3397</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1532-4036</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7132475</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S0964-3397(20)30065-3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.iccn.2020.102862</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">102862</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>End-of-life decisions and care in the midst of a global coronavirus (COVID-19) pandemic</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au005"><name><surname>Pattison</surname><given-names>Natalie</given-names></name><email>natalie.pattison@nhs.net</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af005">Florence Nightingale Foundation Clinical Professor of Nursing: University of Hertfordshire, East &#x00026; North Herts NHS Trust, United Kingdom</aff><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>2</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><elocation-id>102862</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Elsevier Ltd</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p id="p0005">The unprecedented and unfolding global situation with Coronavirus (the virus SaRS Cov-2, leading to the disease named COVID-19) (<xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2020</xref>) has forced health care providers across the world to consider end-of-life issues in a very rapidly changing scenario. During this pandemic, end-of-life decisions, in the face of finite critical care support such as staff, beds and equipment are necessary now more than ever. The reported global mortality is only an estimate, given not all countries, including the UK, are testing all those who are symptomatic. The spread and course of the disease has led to critical care services being overrun in many places across the world, and those who present to critical care with COVID-19 are the most severe cases and much more likely to die in critical care, up to 1 in 2 in the UK at present, compared with a usual mortality in critical care of 16% (<xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">ICNARC, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Intensive Care National Audit and Research Centre (ICNARC), 2019</xref>).</p><p id="p0010">Doctors are being encouraged to have end-of-life conversations with people with chronic illness, ethics committees are hastily convened and in some parts of the world, health care providers have to face the prospects of no more critical care beds available. Some of these stretched services are unable to offer supportive critical care to all those in need.</p><p id="p0015">Pandemic planning must encompass the wider issues of deciding who to treat and who should not be treated. Established ethical principles are challenged in pandemics. Terms such as reverse triage, where patients most likely to survive are prioritised and surge capacity, the ability to increase demand rapidly, are utilised (<xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">Pollaris and Sabbe, 2016</xref>). Canada led much of this work when H5N1 emerged (<xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Christian et al., 2006</xref>), and again later when H1N1 was declared a pandemic in 2009. It is much harder to argue for individual autonomy, where individuals have a right to determine what happens to them in a resource-limited setting, as options are diminished. It is even harder for principles of autonomy to override the concept of utilitarianism, the greatest good for the greatest number, often cited in pandemics as an ethical framework (<xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">Conway Morris, 2015</xref>).</p><p id="p0020">The COVID 19: Rapid Guidance for Critical Care (<xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">National Institute of Clinical Health and Excellence (NICE), 2020</xref>) published in response to the pandemic, places the focus on how and when to use frailty on admission to help patients, clinicians and families make rapid and timely admission decisions. Increased frailty is highly important and known to correspond to worsening patient outcome and increased mortality in critical care (<xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">Flaatten et al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">Muscedere et al., 2017 Aug</xref>). This NICE admission guidance also encompasses end-of-life care decision-making and advanced care planning for those at greatest risk (<xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">NICE, 2020</xref>). Consequences of admission have to be considered, and data already shows us that Coronavirus disproportionately affects those who are frail and, or with chronic health conditions (<xref rid="b0170" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2020</xref>). It is also highly likely that, despite this guidance, there will be limited critical care resources, as seen across the world in the face of this pandemic. Not everyone will be able to access the level of care they might need. The greater emphasis over the past decade on making timely and appropriate treatment escalation decisions that align with a person&#x02019;s wishes has, to some extent, paved the way for these conversations necessary in the current climate. Clinicians have to become confident in these conversations and about the implications of critical care for individuals. The long-term sequelae associated with ICU admission (post-intensive care syndrome [PICS]) includes physical weakness and/or psychosocial and cognitive morbidity, particularly when ventilated for a length of time (<xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">Desai et al., 2011</xref>, <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">Kress and Hall, 2014</xref>). These PICS-related consequences can result in significant and persistent burden (<xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">Bagshaw et al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">Iwashyna et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">Wade et al., 2015</xref>), and a much lower quality of life, even years later (<xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">Cuthbertson et al., 2010</xref>). However, in a pandemic scenario, it is rarely feasible to have meaningful conversations about a person&#x02019;s opinions and wishes about ICU admission because people are admitted acutely unwell. For patients with coronavirus in the UK there is rapid escalation to intubation, and sadly therefore little time for those discussions. By necessity, many family conversations are also taking place via telephone, with little opportunity for reading important non-verbal cues (<xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">Hall et al., 1995</xref>), thereby diminishing the quality of that end-of-life communication.</p><sec id="s0005"><title>End-of-life care</title><p id="p0025">So, how do health professionals prepare for providing large scale end-of-life care in critical care in a pandemic? There has been a renewed focus on the disaster literature, following other infectious disease outbreak situations, and the H1N1 outbreak in 2009 in particular (<xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">Kain and Fowler, 2019</xref>), but end-of-life care planning within this rarely features. Coronavirus (COVID-19) has presented a new scenario given the large numbers dying worldwide from in critical care units, or makeshift units. Following the H1N1 outbreak and a surge in critical care demand, <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">Downar et al. (2010)</xref> described the need for a palliative pandemic plan, with a view to providing palliative care outside the critical care unit. <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">Downar et al. (2010, p 293)</xref> outlines four key aspects; <italic>Stuff</italic> (stockpiling equipment and palliative medication such as opioids, anti-psychotics for delirium/nausea, antimuscarinic agents for secretions and syringe drivers, sub-cutaneous butterflies for medication administration); <italic>Staff</italic> (identifying staff with expertise, education, preparing protocols and guidelines for practice, ensuring grief/bereavement counsellors), <italic>Space</italic> (maximising existing palliative care beds/hospice facilities and identifying non-clinical areas appropriate for large numbers of people to die) and <italic>Systems</italic> (ensure advance care plans and care plans in place, triage for specialist palliative care, liaison across provider networks to access knowledge and facilitate direct access for clinicians needing consultation support).</p><p id="p0030">The <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">Association of Palliative Medicine (2020)</xref> have issued guidance this week to support palliative care clinicians providing palliative care in secondary care. Focusing on ward-based patient care, the guidance defers to critical care expertise around ventilatory withdrawal. These principles are already described in the <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">Faculty of Intensive Care Medicine (FICM) (2019)</xref> end of life care in critical care guidance. However, in a pandemic situation, teams do not have the luxury of providing the best end-of-life care possible as advocated in the literature and guidance (<xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">Faculty of Intensive Care Medicine, 2019</xref>, <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">Pattison and Campbell, 2016</xref>, <xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">Pattison et al., 2013</xref>). Adjustments have to be made, and expectations altered.</p><p id="p0035">End-of-life care in these scenarios is pressured by rapid bed turnover, far exceeding usual bed pressures. COVID ventilation practices focus on limiting lung damage and minimising staff risk, and withdrawal of ventilation at end of life also has to minimise any risk to staff of aerosol exposure. Extubation, practiced at end of life in many countries but less commonly in the UK, is an aerosol generating procedure and may have to be reconsidered above turning off ventilators. Nurses and teams have to provide care in extreme situations, and may even be providing care in critical care which is outside their area of usual practice. Offering clear, accurate and consistent communication to patient and families at end of life in critical care in this situation is challenging, with senior critical care nurses bearing much of the brunt of managing these scenarios. Having access to equipment to provide supportive end of life care, such as syringe drivers outlined above, is also increasingly difficult as demand for supplies increases day on day while we approach the height of the pandemic. Creative care planning can help mitigate some of these challenges, and staggering end of life care and withdrawal across units to ensure nurses can be fully present with patients as they are dying. Initiatives such as critical care gardens (<xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">Alexander and Tantam, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib171" ref-type="bibr">BBC</xref>) are being expedited to ensure patients have humanising experiences in the midst of an unfolding disaster, and that end-of-life care provided is as good as it possibly can be. Ensuring a critical care nursing presence, an interpersonal process characterised by sensitivity, intimacy, vulnerability alongside empathy and holistic care, is key to this (<xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">Finfgeld-Connett, 2008</xref>). Critical care nurses are swiftly finding alternative ways to communicate with families, such as videoconferencing, as most families will not be present, given pandemic visiting restrictions in place across critical care units worldwide. Bad news may have to be broken this way. In these challenging times, person-centred critical care nursing and high quality, empathic communication at end of life becomes most important.</p></sec><sec id="s0010"><title>Bereavement support</title><p id="p0040">We know that 27,000 families are bereaved each year annually in the UK (<xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">ICNARC, 2019</xref>) and it is expected the rate will be raised in 2020 following Coronavirus. At the time of writing, 2926 patients had died in the UK, and 34192 (8.5% of all reported cases, although likely to be much lower as many more suspected cases remain untested) (<xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">Johns Hopkins Coronavirus Resource Centre, 2020</xref>) globally from Coronavirus, what is unparalleled is having to provide end-of-life care to so many unexpectedly. Families bereaved in critical care experience worse outcomes, with a greater prevalence of PTSD (44%) and prolonged grief disorder (complicated grief) (52%) at six months than seen in the general population, which is around 5&#x02013;10% (<xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">Fujisawa et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">Kentish-Barnes et al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">Lundorff et al., 2017</xref>). Indeed, under these unusual pandemic circumstances we may well expect even higher figures of complicated grief.</p><p id="p0045">Unexpected death is a marked feature of coronavirus-related death, and this feature of bereavement can lead to maladaptive coping and difficulty adjusting. These bereavement experiences are compounded by the fact that most families will not have been permitted to say their goodbyes in person. Nurses and doctors in critical care are having to inform families of bereavement by phone, or share last moments via teleconferencing and videoconferencing facilities, placing an enormous emotional and psychological burden on teams and individuals, as well as families. Usual meaning-making practices, so important for bereavement adjustment (<xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">Park, 2010</xref>, <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Milman et al., 2019</xref>), such as fingerprinting, hair locks and patient diaries are harder, if not impossible altogether, to carry out. There is also a social legacy in disaster-related deaths, like in this pandemic. Collective grief, as seen in situations of high-profile deaths and disaster situations (<xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">K&#x000fc;bler-Ross and Kessler, 2005</xref>), is a recognised phenomenon, with shared mourning through bonding with strangers who have undergone a similar bereavement. This is really important for us to consider in terms of how we shape and provide bereavement support around COVID-related deaths. As <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">K&#x000fc;bler-Ross and Kessler (2005)</xref> suggest, trauma in such circumstances invites us to learn about our strength, endurance and eventually reach hope.</p><p id="p0050">Nurses&#x02019; and other professional grief may also be compounded by being unable to care for families and patients as they might wish. Burnout, moral distress and moral injury has been identified as a significant issue in critical care professionals (<xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">Colville et al., 2019</xref>, <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">Vincent et al., 2019 Nov</xref>) and caring for each other, in order to be able to care for our patients and families is paramount. The weeks and months ahead are likely to prove even more challenging and when this pandemic abates, and normal critical care services resume, there must be time built into staffing rotas to regroup, come together as teams, recognise our own grief and have the opportunity to reflect on what has been achieved under extraordinary circumstances.</p></sec><sec id="s0015"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="p0055">NP was a contributing author to FICM (2019) guidance and contributed to the NICE guidance (NG 159) and FICM/NICE and NHSI/E shared guidance.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bi005"><title>References</title><ref id="b0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0005">Alexander, G., Tantam, K. (2020). Ask and it shall be given. Supporting the NHS. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gracealexanderflowers.co.uk/words/2020/3/21/ask-and-it-shall-be-given-supporting-the-nhs%3ffbclid%3dIwAR3IheagNn2EqcR08DYZnzN3U9bqz9UknC4QUZ9PnFI-ELbqbRhE3E1w4pY" id="ir005">https://www.gracealexanderflowers.co.uk/words/2020/3/21/ask-and-it-shall-be-given-supporting-the-nhs?fbclid=IwAR3IheagNn2EqcR08DYZnzN3U9bqz9UknC4QUZ9PnFI-ELbqbRhE3E1w4pY</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0010">Association of Palliative Medicine. (2020). COVID-19 and Palliative, End of Life and Bereavement Care in Secondary Care Role of the specialty and guidance to aid care. (Published 22.3.20) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://apmonline.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/03/COVID-19-and-Palliative-End-of-Life-and-Bereavement-Care-22-March-2020.pdf" id="ir010">https://apmonline.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/03/COVID-19-and-Palliative-End-of-Life-and-Bereavement-Care-22-March-2020.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0015"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bagshaw</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stelfox</surname><given-names>H.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term association between frailty and health-related quality of life among survivors of critical illness: a prospective multicenter cohort study</article-title><source>Crit. Care Med.</source><volume>43</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>973</fpage><lpage>982</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25668751</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0020"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christian</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawryluck</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wax</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of a triage protocol for critical care during an influenza pandemic</article-title><source>CMAJ</source><volume>175</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>1377</fpage><lpage>1381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17116904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0025"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colville</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabinthiran</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A survey of moral distress in staff working in intensive care in the UK</article-title><source>J. Intensive Care Soc.</source><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>196</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31447911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0030"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conway Morris</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Triage during pandemic influenza: seeking absolution in numbers?</article-title><source>BJA: Br. J. Anaesth.</source><volume>114</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>865</fpage><lpage>867</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25991740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0035"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cuthbertson</surname><given-names>B.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roughton</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkinson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maclennan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vale</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality of life in the five years after intensive care: a cohort study</article-title><source>Crit. Care</source><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>R6</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20089197</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0040"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>S.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Needham</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term complications of critical care</article-title><source>Crit. Care Med.</source><volume>39</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20959786</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0045"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Downar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seccareccia</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><collab>Associated Medical Services Inc. Educational Fellows in Care at the End of Life</collab></person-group><article-title>Palliating a pandemic: all patients must be cared for</article-title><source>J. Pain Sympt. Manage.</source><volume>39</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>295</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0050"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faculty of Intensive Care Medicine</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Care at the end of life: a guide to best practice, discussions and decision-making in and around critical care</chapter-title><year>2019</year><publisher-name>FICM</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><comment>(www.ficm.ac.uk/eolc)</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0055"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finfgeld-Connett</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Qualitative convergence of three nursing concepts: art of nursing, presence and caring</article-title><source>J. Adv. Nurs.</source><volume>63</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>527</fpage><lpage>534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18373611</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0060"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flaatten</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Lange</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morandi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of frailty on ICU and 30-day mortality and the level of care in very elderly patients (&#x02265;80 years)</article-title><source>Intensive Care Med.</source><volume>43</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>1820</fpage><lpage>1828</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28936626</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0065"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyashita</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and determinants of complicated grief in general population</article-title><source>J. Affect. Disord.</source><volume>127</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>352</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20580096</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0070"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrigan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Non-verbal behavior in clinician-patient interaction</article-title><source>Appl. Prev. Psychol.</source><volume>4</volume><year>1995</year><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>35</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0075"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0075">ICNARC (2020). Report on 775 patients critically ill with COVID-19 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.icnarc.org/About/Latest-News/2020/03/22/Report-On-775-Patients-Critically-Ill-With-Covid-19" id="ir015">https://www.icnarc.org/About/Latest-News/2020/03/22/Report-On-775-Patients-Critically-Ill-With-Covid-19</ext-link> (published March 27, 2020). Accessed 27.3.20.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0080"><element-citation publication-type="other" id="h0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Intensive Care National Audit and Research Centre (ICNARC)</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Key statistics from the case mix programme-adult, general critical care units</article-title><comment>Retrieved from https://www.icnarc.org/Our-Audit/Audits/Cmp/Reports/Summary-Statistics. Accessed</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://21.3.20" id="ir020">21.3.20</ext-link><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0085"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwashyna</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ely</surname><given-names>E.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Langa</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term cognitive impairment and functional disability among survivors of severe sepsis</article-title><source>JAMA J. Am. Med. Assoc.</source><year>2010</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0090"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0090">Johns Hopkins Coronavirus Resource Centre, 2020. Coronavirus COVID-19 Global Cases by the Center for Systems Science and Engineering (CSSE) at Johns Hopkins. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://coronavirus.jhu.edu/map.html" id="ir025">https://coronavirus.jhu.edu/map.html</ext-link>. Data accessed 23.3.20.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b0095"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kain</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preparing intensive care for the next pandemic influenza</article-title><source>Crit. Care</source><volume>23</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>337</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31665057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0100"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kentish-Barnes</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaize</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seegers</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complicated grief after death of a relative in the intensive care unit</article-title><source>Eur. Respir. J.</source><volume>45</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1341</fpage><lpage>1352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25614168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0105"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>(2014) ICU-acquired weakness and recovery from critical illness</article-title><source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source><volume>370</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>1626</fpage><lpage>1635</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24758618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0110"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000fc;bler-Ross</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>On Grief and Grieving: Finding the Meaning of Grief Through the Five Stages of Loss</chapter-title><year>2005</year><publisher-name>Scribner</publisher-name><publisher-loc>NY</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0115"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lundorff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmgren</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zachariae</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of prolonged grief disorder in adult bereavement: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>J. Affect. Disord.</source><volume>212</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>138</fpage><lpage>149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28167398</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0120"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neimeyer</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prolonged grief and the disruption of meaning: Establishing a mediation model</article-title><source>J. Couns. Psychol.</source><volume>66</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>714</fpage><lpage>725</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31647284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0125"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muscedere</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Varambally</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of frailty on intensive care unit outcomes: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Intensive Care Med.</source><volume>43</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2017 Aug</year><fpage>1105</fpage><lpage>1122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28676896</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0130"><element-citation publication-type="other" id="h0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>National Institute of Clinical Health and Excellence (NICE)</surname></name></person-group><article-title>COVID 19: Rapid Guidance for Critical Care</article-title><comment>Accessed 22.3.20</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng159" id="ir030">https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng159</ext-link><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0135"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Making sense of the meaning literature: an integrative review of meaning making and its effects on adjustment to stressful life events</article-title><source>Psychol. Bull.</source><volume>136</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>301</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20192563</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0140"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pattison</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>End-of-life care in critical care: moving forward to enhance patient and family experiences</article-title><source>Intensive Crit. Care Nurs.</source><volume>33</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26949159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0145"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pattison</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turnock</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>'Viewing in slow motion': patients', families', nurses' and doctors' perspectives on end-of-life care in critical care</article-title><source>J. Clin. Nurs.</source><volume>22</volume><issue>9&#x02013;10</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>1442</fpage><lpage>1454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23506296</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0150"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pollaris</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabbe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reverse triage: more than just another method</article-title><source>Eur. J. Emerg. Med.</source><volume>23</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26479736</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0155"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brindley</surname><given-names>P.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Highfield</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Burnout Syndrome in UK Intensive Care Unit staff: data from all three Burnout Syndrome domains and across professional groups, genders and ages</article-title><source>J. Intensive Care Soc.</source><volume>20</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>369</lpage><comment>Epub 2019 Jul 11</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31695742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0160"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0160"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wade</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brewin</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>D.C.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>(2015) Intrusive memories of hallucinations and delusions in traumatized intensive care patients: an interview study</article-title><source>Br. J. Health Psychol.</source><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>631</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24944013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0165"><element-citation publication-type="other" id="h0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>World Health Organisation</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Naming the coronavirus disease (COVID-19) and the virus that causes it</article-title><comment>Accessed 22.3.20</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/technical-guidance/naming-the-coronavirus-disease-(covid-2019)-and-the-virus-that-causes-it" id="ir035">https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/technical-guidance/naming-the-coronavirus-disease-(covid-2019)-and-the-virus-that-causes-it</ext-link><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="b0170"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0170"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gou</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of comorbidities in the novel Wuhan coronavirus (COVID-19) infection: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Int. J. Infect. Dis.</source><year>2020</year><comment>Mar 12. pii: S1201-9712(20)30136-3. [Epub ahead of print]</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib171"><mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="ce.other-ref_s4v_m2v_glb">Coronavirus: Chelsea Flower Show plants donated to Derriford Hospital 2020.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>