<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">Noticeable findings from our study include: (1) Boceprevir (
 <bold>28</bold>), an FDA-approved HCV drug, inhibits the enzymatic activity of M
 <sup>pro</sup> with IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 4.13 µM, and has an EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 1.90 µM against the SARS-CoV-2 virus in the cellular viral CPE assay. The therapeutic potential of boceprevir (
 <bold>28</bold>) should be further evaluated in relevant animal models and human clinical trials. Since boceprevir (
 <bold>28</bold>) is an FDA-approved drug, the dose, toxicity, formulation and pharmacokinetic properties are already known, which will greatly speed up the design of follow-up studies; (2) GC-376 (
 <bold>64</bold>), an investigational veterinary drug, showed promising antiviral activity against the SARS-CoV-2 virus (EC
 <sub>50</sub> = 3.37 µM). It has the highest enzymatic inhibition against the M
 <sup>pro</sup> with an IC
 <sub>50</sub> value of 0.03 µM. This compound has promising in vivo efficacy in treating cats infected with FIP, and has favorable in vivo pharmacokinetic properties. Therefore, GC-376 (
 <bold>64</bold>) is ready to be tested in relevant animal models of SARS-CoV-2 when available. Importantly, the X-ray crystal structure of SARS-CoV-2 M
 <sup>pro</sup> in complex with GC-376 (
 <bold>64</bold>) provides a molecular explanation of the high binding affinity of aldehyde-containing compounds as they can adopt two configurations R and S. The conformational flexibility at the TSEDMLN loop explains the broad substrate scope at the P2 position of M
 <sup>pro</sup> inhibitors; (3) Three calpain/cathepsin inhibitors, MG-132 (
 <bold>43</bold>), calpain inhibitors II (
 <bold>61</bold>) and XII (
 <bold>62</bold>), are potent inhibitors of M
 <sup>pro</sup> with single-digit to submicromolar efficacy in the enzymatic assay. Calpain inhibitors II (
 <bold>61</bold>) and XII (
 <bold>62</bold>) also inhibit SARS-CoV-2 in the CPE assay with EC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 2.07 and 0.49 µM, respectively. This result suggests that calpain/cathepsin inhibitors are rich sources of drug candidates for SARS-CoV-2. Indeed, previous studies have shown that calpain II and cathepsin L are required for the proteolytic processing of the coronavirus S protein, a step that is essential for the viral fusion and genome release during the early stage of viral replication.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup> Calpain and cathepsin inhibitors such as MDL28170 (calpain inhibitor III),
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup> MG-132,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup> calpain inhibitor VI
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup> have been shown to inhibit SARS-CoV replication in cell culture. Other than the increased potency of targeting both M
 <sup>pro</sup> and calpain/cathepsin, an additional benefit of such dual inhibitors might be their high genetic barrier to drug resistance. A significant number of calpain/cathepsin inhibitors have been developed over the years for various diseases including cancer, neurodegeneration disease, kidney diseases, and ischemia/reperfusion injury.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>
 </sup> Given our promising results of calpain inhibitors II (
 <bold>61</bold>) and XII (
 <bold>62</bold>) in inhibiting the SARS-CoV-2 M
 <sup>pro</sup> and their potent antiviral activity in cell culture, it might be worthwhile to repurpose them as antivirals for SARS-CoV-2.
</p>
