<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">A set of mammalian proteins, more than 150, are anchored to the outer leaflets of cell membranes via a GPI-lipid anchor, which is a standard means of membrane protein anchoring in protozoan parasites. GPI-anchored proteins are enriched in lipid rafts and they can signal via cell membrane tyrosine kinases.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>
 </sup>. In humans, GPI-anchored proteins include two complement-regulatory proteins: CD55 (decay accelerating factor; DAF) inhibiting the C3 convertases
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup> and CD59 (protectin) that inhibits the membrane attack complex formation by binding to the terminal C5b-8 and C5b-9 complexes.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>
 </sup> Alterations in ganglioside profiles may cause changes in the properties of these protective proteins. A deficiency in the anchoring mechanism causes a hematological disorder, paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria (PNH), where affected blood cells become the target for complement attack. A critical feature of the disease is also an increased tendency for thromboses. Most commonly, the disease is caused by an acquired mutation in the X-chromosomal 
 <italic>PIG-A</italic> gene, whose product is involved in the GPI-anchor synthesis.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup> When cells are attacked by the complement membrane attack complex, they release vesicles enriched in GPI-anchored proteins. Overall, the GPI-lipid anchored proteins together with the attached gangliosides are only relatively loosely bound to cell membranes and can easily become detached. For example, high density lipoproteins in human plasma can transfer GPI-anchored CD59 between cells.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup> It is likely that the same applies for gangliosides, as well. Also, 
 <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic>, a long living companion in the human gastric ventricular mucosa, may acquire the human CD59 molecules to its surface to help the bacteria to survive attacks by the human complement system.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>
 </sup> Analogously, lipopolysaccharides (LPS) of Gram-negative bacteria may become transferred to the surfaces of human cells. Transfer of cell membrane glycolipids, including gangliosides and LPS, between human and microbial cells could—via an adjuvant type effect—be involved in the generation of antibody responses against these structures.
</p>
