<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The 
 <italic>Ae. geniculatus</italic> species is known under different names according to classifications. We use the species denomination from Knight and Stone’s catalog [
 <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. This species was later reclassified at the genus level by Reinert and colleagues [
 <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], but we considered the revised species name 
 <italic>Aedes (Dahliana) geniculatus</italic> from the stable classification of the tribe Aedini [
 <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. The following species denomination can be reported in the literature to describe the same specimens: 
 <italic>A. geniculatus</italic>, 
 <italic>Ochlerotatus geniculatus</italic> or 
 <italic>Dahliana geniculata</italic> [
 <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. 
 <italic>Aedes geniculatus</italic> specimens that were assessed for their vector competence for CHIKV in this study were genetically closed to 2 specimens collected in Germany in 2013 [
 <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] (
 <xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). This cluster of sequence was genetically separated from other described 
 <italic>Ae. geniculatus</italic> species and from the 
 <italic>Ae. echinus</italic> specimen, as represented by a Spanish sequence collected in 2011 [
 <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Another specimen collected in Austria (KM280584) and submitted in GenBank as 
 <italic>Ae. geniculatus</italic> (
 <xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>) appears to be genetically divergent from all other specimens. Three mosquito species from the subgenus “Finlaya” (Theobald, 1903) can be considered as the closest relative species of 
 <italic>Ae. geniculatus</italic>, namely 
 <italic>Ae. echinus</italic>, and 
 <italic>Aedes gilcolladoi</italic> [
 <xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Our morphological determination of the 
 <italic>Ae. geniculatus</italic> species was done as follow. At the adult stage, the female of 
 <italic>Ae. geniculatus</italic> is morphologically indistinguishable from 
 <italic>Ae. gilcolladoi</italic> specimens. While being morphologically very close to 
 <italic>Ae. echinus</italic> mosquitoes, 
 <italic>Ae. geniculatus</italic> adults females specimens can be distinguished from the former species by the absence of a pale scaly spot on the metameron [
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In addition, it is possible to distinguish 
 <italic>Ae. geniculatus</italic> from both other species at the larval stage by the ramification of most of the silks present on the abdominal segments IV to VII. Indeed, 
 <italic>Ae. echinus</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae. gilcolladoi</italic> have rigid silks generally with 7 or more branches while 
 <italic>Ae. geniculatus</italic> specimens have rigid silks with less than 6 branches [
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. These determination criteria were verified for adults and larvae from the mosquito population used in our study. As discussed by Krüger and colleagues, it is possible that the specimen identified as 
 <italic>Ae. echninus</italic> in Spain (COI GenBank accession number MK070853) belongs to the 
 <italic>Ae. gilcolladoi</italic> species. We can also make the assumption that the Austrian specimen identified as 
 <italic>Ae. geniculatus</italic> (COI GenBank accession number KM280584) belongs to the 
 <italic>Ae. echinus</italic> species and that our Albanian specimens are representatives of a cryptic sibling species of 
 <italic>Ae. geniculatus</italic>. Because no or few public reference DNA sequences are available for these species, it has yet to be determined if these different genetic clusters belong to distinct species or represent a different sub-species inside a complex. The vector competence dynamic values that are reported in this work might not be representative of other relative species, or sub-species from a hypothetical 
 <italic>Ae. geniculatus</italic> complex.
</p>
