<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par43">Understanding why some children develop severe bronchiolitis while most children experience an upper respiratory tract infection upon RSV infection remains essential and needs to be answered to improve the care of RSV-infected children in the future. Where several previous studies focused on the microbial content involved in bronchiolitis, most notably by Hasegawa and coworkers, our study exclusively focused on RSV-implicated bronchiolitis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. RSV disease severity is a multifactorial problem, in which the viral load and the inflammatory response are important drivers of disease, although this is mainly true in previously healthy children whose airways are normal [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. An important question this study tried to answer is whether nasopharyngeal microbiome composition relates to local viral load and exerts an influence on mucosal immune responses. Viral load and mucosal immune responses are thought to directly impact disease severity, and therefore, it is difficult to disentangle these direct and indirect effects of the microbiome on disease outcome. The alpha diversity of the microbiota from patients with an acute RSV infection showed a decrease in species richness but not in diversity compared to healthy infants. This means that the number of different species reduces while there is no difference in the distribution of the numbers of each species. A reduced alpha diversity of the upper respiratory tract has also been shown in a longitudinal cohort study of symptomatic rhinovirus infections in infants (&lt; 1 year) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] and after administration of an intranasal live-attenuated influenza vaccine in adults [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Both studies were performed prospectively and show that lower alpha diversity is caused by viral infection and is not a prerequisite for viral infection. In another observational study, comparing the microbiome during RSV and rhinovirus infections, it was shown that there might be an association with different nasopharyngeal microbiome profiles, although this has not been confirmed by others yet [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. This suggests that the type of alteration of the microbiome might be specific for RSV infection but also could be a more general effect of immune system perturbation. Yet, it is uncertain whether the observed microbiome changes in our study are the cause or effect of RSV infection.
</p>
