<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0015">It is an undisputed fact that coronaviruses can infect the CNS. CoV RNA has been detected in the CNS of patients with numerous neurological diseases.
 <xref rid="bib0475" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0480" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> CNS infection has caused symptoms of encephalitis in children.
 <xref rid="bib0485" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref> Cases of meningitis, Guillain-Barré syndrome, and other neuroimmune disorders have also been reported in the context of CoV infection.
 <xref rid="bib0490" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0495" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0500" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0505" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0510" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0515" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0520" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> HCoV-OC43 is considered the coronavirus with the greatest neuroinvasive potential, as it has been shown to invade, replicate, and remain in the mouse CNS, causing direct damage to neurons.
 <xref rid="bib0525" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0530" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> The virus has also been found to exploit axonal transport.
 <xref rid="bib0535" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref> HCoV-OC43 can induce cell degeneration and death.
 <xref rid="bib0540" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0545" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0550" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> In humans, HCoV-OC43 has been detected in brain tissue from patients with a wide range of neurological diseases, including Alzheimer disease, Parkinson's disease, and multiple sclerosis, as well as in the brains of healthy individuals. Likewise, HCoV-229E has been associated with febrile seizures.
 <xref rid="bib0555" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref> The literature also includes a report of an immunocompromised child who died due to HCoV-OC43–associated encephalitis.
 <xref rid="bib0560" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> Both HCoV-OC43 and HCoV-229E can infect innate immune cells.
 <xref rid="bib0565" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0570" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
</p>
