<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Silencing resistance breakdown can occur by mutation and selection (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">de Haan et al., 1992</xref>) or by mixed infection with other viruses (
 <xref rid="B234" ref-type="bibr">Syller, 2012</xref>). Transgenic plants with multiple constructs from different viral genomes (from the same species and/or different species) can be used to minimize the risk of resistance breakdown (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Bucher et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Duan et al., 2012</xref>). Another strategy is using a transgene mimicking the secondary structure of endogenous miRNA precursors (involved in plant gene expression and development) to express artificial miRNAS (amiRNAs) targeting viral sequences (
 <xref rid="B173" ref-type="bibr">Niu et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B200" ref-type="bibr">Qu et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B140" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2017</xref>). The main advantage is that the short sequence of amiRNAs makes it easier to find conserved sequences that are more difficult to overcome (they are usually under strong negative selective pressure) and can be used for broad range targets (genera and families). However, the amiRNA resistance can be also overcome by mutation and selection (
 <xref rid="B229" ref-type="bibr">Simón-Mateo and García, 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B137" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B131" ref-type="bibr">Lafforgue et al., 2011</xref>) or interaction with co-infecting viruses (
 <xref rid="B178" ref-type="bibr">Pacheco et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B152" ref-type="bibr">Martínez et al., 2013</xref>). A strategy to obtain more durable resistances is to express multiple amiRNAs to target different regions within a single viral genome (
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">Fahim et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B130" ref-type="bibr">Kung et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B132" ref-type="bibr">Lafforgue et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B123" ref-type="bibr">Kis et al., 2016</xref>). Synthetic trans-acting small interfering RNAs (syn-tasiRNAs) is another class of artificial small RNAs engineered in plants, which are especially suited to target multiple sites within a viral genome or different unrelated viruses (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Carbonell et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Carbonell and Daròs, 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Carbonell et al., 2019</xref>). The durability of these resistances can be evaluated by experimental evolution based on successive passages of the virus in the resistant plants. Resistance-breakdown can be detected by qPCR as an increase in virus accumulation (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Carrasco et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B188" ref-type="bibr">Peña et al., 2014</xref>). The mutations fixed after the passages can be detected by PCR followed by cloning and Sanger sequencing or HTS. Identification of the mutations leading to resistance breakdown is possible if infectious clones exist, so that each mutation can be tested for the increase of virus accumulation. An alternative to transgenic plants is the exogeneous application of 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>-produced dsRNAs from viral sequences onto plants (
 <xref rid="B238" ref-type="bibr">Tenllado and Díaz-Ruiz, 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B118" ref-type="bibr">Kaldis et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B172" ref-type="bibr">Niehl et al., 2018</xref>). The efficacy of this technique of immunization can be improved by high-pressure spraying plants (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Dalakouras et al., 2016</xref>), using cell-penetrating peptides (
 <xref rid="B174" ref-type="bibr">Numata et al., 2014</xref>) or clay nanoparticles stabilizing dsRNAs (
 <xref rid="B155" ref-type="bibr">Mitter et al., 2017</xref>).
</p>
