<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another immunization method is cross-protection based on inoculating mild or attenuated viral strains to protect plants against severe strains of the same virus. Cross-protection has been applied to several viruses and crops, such as PepMV in tomato and CTV in citrus crops (
 <xref rid="B189" ref-type="bibr">Pechinger et al., 2019</xref>). The mechanism of cross-protection is poorly understood and several models have been proposed: prevention of virus entry into cells; competition for host factors for replication, interference with disassembly, translation or replication; and induction of RNA silencing leading to sequence-specific degradation of the superinfecting virus (
 <xref rid="B272" ref-type="bibr">Ziebell and Carr, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">Folimonova, 2013</xref>). It has been suggested that cross-protection in some viruses might be an active virus-controlled function involving virus-coded proteins (
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">Folimonova, 2013</xref>). A recent model proposed that cross-protection is a mechanism that prevents the virus progeny to replicate in the cells to minimize mutation rate and collaterally targets highly homologous superinfecting viruses that are indistinguishable from progeny viruses (
 <xref rid="B269" ref-type="bibr">Zhang X. et al., 2018</xref>). To apply cross-protection it is necessary to evaluate the genetic and biological variability of the local virus population and search for mild isolates genetically close to the severe ones (
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">Hanssen et al., 2010</xref>). Mild or attenuated strains can also be generated by thermal treatment, random mutagenesis by using chemicals as nitrous acids and selection or directed mutagenesis in viral RNA silencing suppressors (
 <xref rid="B272" ref-type="bibr">Ziebell and Carr, 2010</xref>). Cross-protection assays can be evaluated by real-time qPCR with probes specific for each virus variant (
 <xref rid="B215" ref-type="bibr">Ruiz-Ruiz et al., 2009b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">Hanssen et al., 2010</xref>) and SSCP analysis (
 <xref rid="B219" ref-type="bibr">Sambade et al., 2002</xref>). However, the protection exerted by the mild isolate can be overcome and even a more severe disease can emerge by transmission to a different host species, interaction with other viruses in mixed infections, or recombination between divergent strains or viruses (
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">Fulton, 1986</xref>). Therefore cross-protection should be used only for devastating diseases when other protection measures fail, and the process should be monitored closely.
</p>
