<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>That the participants in the intervention arm were more likely to seroconvert to DENV infection was surprising, especially given the high use of the ITCs [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008097.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008097.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] and the promising entomological data reported in previous trials. Three factors, however, could have contributed to this unexpected result. First, despite being fabricated from a material that was expected to retain high insecticide levels over the course of several years, the ITCs quickly lost insecticidal efficacy, leading to the need for mass re-treatment only 1-year after they had been originally deployed. The 9-month serosurvey occurred before the ITCs were re-treated, which means that many were operating sub-optimally and could have potentially had reduced protective effectiveness. Second, a contributing factor may have been a false sense of security amongst the participants in the intervention arm; 
 <italic>i</italic>.
 <italic>e</italic>., perhaps the presence of the highly visible ITCs created a belief in their protective power among the treated households, who subsequently did not employ any additional measures typically used to avoid exposure to mosquito bites. This possibility was suggested as an explanation for a similar outcome associated with the use of insecticide aerosols and mosquito coils in a meta-analysis of dengue interventions [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008097.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Indeed, comments by participants about the expected benefit of the ITCs were noted during focus group discussions held 6-months after the ITCs were deployed. Participants that had received ITCs commented that when the curtains were first hung, the household reduced their use of mosquito repellents and stopped fumigating because they felt that it was no longer necessary due to the presence of the ITCs [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008097.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Third, higher seroconversion rates in treatment than control clusters (
 <xref rid="pntd.0008097.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) could reflect higher transmission risk for people in treatment areas; 
 <italic>i</italic>.
 <italic>e</italic>., treatment and control clusters were not balanced for transmission risk.
</p>
