<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Like most plant viruses, PPV is transmitted by winged non-colonising aphids in a non-persistent manner [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006085.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. To match the characteristics of this widespread transmission process, in our model transmission events are independent (conditional on infection sources) and transmission distances directly depend on host locations and on the distance travelled by an aphid within a single infectious flight. Although estimating this aphid dispersal kernel is crucial to plant virus epidemiology, it has long remained elusive. Traditional ecological methods such as capture-mark-recapture provide little information regarding aphid dispersal at the landscape scale [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006085.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. This has been a major obstacle to the parametrisation of models simulating the dispersal of these vectors and the pathogens they spread, as exemplified by the scarcity of landscape-scale models on cereal aphids [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006085.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] and by the informed guesses of flight-distance parameters in such models [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006085.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Here we estimated, for the first time, the dispersal of aphid vectors at the landscape scale. This estimation indicates that 50% of the infectious aphids leaving a tree land within about 90 meters, while about 10% of flights terminate beyond 1 km. Although dispersal estimation from simulated epidemics suggests that these distances may be overestimated, the large number of flights estimated to terminate within some tens of meters of the source tree is consistent with previous studies of within-patch clustering of trees infected by PPV-M [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006085.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006085.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006085.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] or PPV-D [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006085.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006085.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Indeed, one of these studies [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1006085.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] shows that 50% of the new PPV cases occur within 35-70 m of the nearest previous case; in addition, 10% of the new PPV cases were found beyond 200-460 m from the nearest previous case. Although the proportion of new PPV cases captured within a given radius is not equivalent to a dispersal kernel (e.g. because the trees are not always infected by the nearest previously detected neighbour), the figures are of the same order of magnitude. In particular, both studies highlight the long range of the dispersal kernel. Our estimation of the dispersal kernel at the landscape scale has important consequences. For example, current French regulations enforce at least one visual inspection per year within 2.5 km of a detected sharka case (followed by the removal of all trees with sharka symptoms). Our results suggest that less than 3% of flights should thus go beyond this radius (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1006085.g006">Fig 6</xref>). In a patchy French landscape, most of these aphids would land outside a peach orchard and thus lead to no infection. Such procedures are thus likely to efficiently detect most of the aphid-mediated secondary infections; actually, given the cost of surveillance and the speed of disease spread, this radius may even be oversized. Future work based on this study could aim at the definition of new management strategies against PPV. More generally, our results provide a unique reference point on the epidemiology, simulation and control of the principal group of plant viruses (i.e. those caused by non-persistant aphid-borne viruses), which have a major epidemiological and economic impact. Finally, by focusing on incidence data the presented estimation approach is adaptable to many epidemiological situations, including other vector-borne and airborne fungal diseases.
</p>
