<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>CD8
 <sup>+</sup> cytotoxic T lymphocytes (CTLs) recognize short, HIV-derived peptide epitopes presented by human leukocyte antigen (HLA) class I molecules on the surface of infected cells, thereby modulating early viremia control (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) and the establishment of the viral set point (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). HLA-restricted CTLs also exert strong evolutionary pressure on HIV 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>, promoting viral adaptation through the selection of escape mutations (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) that interfere with epitope processing (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), prevent binding of the viral peptide to HLA (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), or affect HLA-peptide recognition by the T-cell receptor (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Early observations that CTL escape in HIV tended to occur along predictable mutational pathways in persons responding to a given HLA-restricted viral epitope (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) led to the development of statistical approaches to systematically identify HLA-associated polymorphisms (HAPs), also known as HLA-associated “footprints,” on HIV, using large population-based data sets of viral sequences linked to HLA types (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). These analyses, which identify amino acids that are statistically overrepresented (or underrepresented) among persons expressing a given HLA allele while correcting for host and viral genetic confounders (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), confirmed the broadly reproducible nature of CTL escape in HIV (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">–</xref>
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). These studies also revealed that certain HLA-associated footprints can be host population specific due to substantial immunogenetic variation across human populations. For example, even though HIV subtype B predominates in Japan, Canada, the United States, and Australia, two-thirds of HAPs in Japan are not observed in the latter epidemics (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) due to the unique HLA distribution of the Japanese population.
</p>
