<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This review demonstrated that in the field of FMD epidemiology, several studies have been performed with the aim to show that a given risk factor contributes to the occurrence and/or transmission of the disease. However, it is likely that some identified risk factors are not causative and merely reflect increased risk via association with other risk factors. To this regard, logistic regression is a commonly used analytical technique for FMD risk factors analysis [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. One of the advantages of such an approach is that specific risk factors can be identified and their impact quantified, managed or controlled [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. On the other hand, this review showed the importance of using spatiotemporal models like the space-time scan statistic permutation model [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Indeed, assessing the spatiotemporal clustering of FMD prevalence or incidence appears to be a useful method for identifying geographical regions and periods of time in which the disease is more likely to occur. Hence, in the identified significant clusters, further FMD investigation should be implemented to identify predictors for outbreaks and epidemics to improve the effectiveness of preventive plans in reducing the occurrence of disease outbreaks [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. In addition, better appreciation of spatiotemporal aspects of an epidemic means better practical decision making (e.g. pre-emptive culling radius, surveillance period, and resources required and appropriate effort to trace the spread of infection from infected premises) [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. In our point of view, this is greatly needed, specifically in the context of endemic countries in SSA with a broad common pastoral space but mostly with limited financial and logistical resources.
</p>
