<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The selected papers highlighted several factors that contribute significantly to the occurrence of FMD outbreaks. Even though these studies were carried out in different geographical areas, the predominant risk factor of FMD remains the uncontrolled animal movements (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>]). Other risk factors, such as mixing animals around water points, on pastures and in livestock markets were also elucidated. Nevertheless, it should be noted that the magnitude of these risk factors, most likely related to the farming system, do not have a similar impact on the prevalence or incidence of the disease as well as on the control measures to be implemented. For example, during the UK FMD epizootic in 2001, in addition to the policy of slaughtering animals on infected farms, further control measures were initiated, including a ban on all animal movements, the closure of markets, and the restricted public use of footpaths across agricultural land [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. In contrast, in endemic countries with a huge epidemiological complexity and considering the livestock production system such as the transhumance or nomadic system, the application of the prevention and control options mentioned above would be unrealistic. Indeed, the context is so far different from that which prevails in several SSA countries where the animal husbandry system includes a seasonal cyclical movement, and where large herds must migrate over long distances in search of grass and water, within the country of origin or by crossing over the border to neighbouring countries (transboundary transhumance). This favours the contact between infected and healthy animals and between potentially infected wildlife and domestic animals and as a result induces a significant risk of disease spread, FMD included [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. However, there are specific risk factors for certain regions such as the presence of wildlife which plays an important role in the maintenance of FMDV of SAT serotypes in Africa [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref095" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. Some other studies identified risk factors including international livestock trade [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>] and transboundary movements of animals, and stressed the absolute necessity for an integrated control at country, regional or continental level [
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0208296.ref098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. This could be based, for example, on coordinated vaccination programs against FMDV serotypes circulating within a region.
</p>
