<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0140">In the E protein, there are about 8% differences in amino acids (about 40 residues) between Mie/41/2002 and GV JEVs. Previous studies on the identification of the sites involved in the attenuation of GIII JEV strains suggested that amino acid changes at positions 107, 138, 176, 177, 244, 264, 279, 315, 366, and 439 of E may be involved (
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2005</xref>) (
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Gromowski et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Liang et al., 2009</xref>) (
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2017</xref>) (
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2018</xref>) (
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al., 2018</xref>). Nine out of 10 amino acid residues at these positions are identical among the three strains used in this study. Amino acid residue at position 366 is different in Mie/41/2002 (serine) and GV JEVs (alanine); however, the residue in GV JEVs is the same as that in the attenuated strain SA-14-14-2 (
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Gromowski et al., 2015</xref>). There are more than 20 amino acid residues unique to GV JEVs in the E region, including E123. The E123 amino acid is serine or asparagine in GI, GII, GIII, and GIV JEV, but histidine in GV JEV (
 <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). In this study, we show that a serine-to-histidine substitution at E123 (E
 <sup>S123H</sup>) increased the virulence of Mie/41/2002. The E protein forms head-to-tail homodimers and consists of three domains: domain I, II, and III. E123 is located in domain II, which is important for homodimerization of the E protein, and amino acid mutations in domain II may influence the virulence by affecting low pH conformational transitions (
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Rey et al., 1995</xref>) (
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Kolaskar and Kulkarni-Kale, 1999</xref>) (
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Nybakken et al., 2006</xref>). It has been suggested that protonation of histidine residues in the E protein at acidic pH affects the structural transition and membrane fusion in the lifecycle of flavivirus (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Fritz et al., 2008</xref>) (
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Nelson et al., 2009</xref>). In contrast to serine, which belongs to the polar, uncharged side chain group, histidine is classified in the positively-charged side chain group, which also includes arginine. We previously showed that a serine-to-arginine substitution at E123 (E
 <sup>S123R</sup>) increases the virulence of JEV (
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Tajima et al., 2010</xref>), suggesting that a substitution of serine at E123 to a positively-charged amino acid may contribute to increased virulence of JEV in mice. Crystal structure analysis of the JEV E protein shows that E123 in the domain II is located on the surface of the JEV virion (
 <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>) (
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Luca et al., 2012</xref>). It is possible that the domain II interacts with cellular factors and amino acid residue of E123 influences the affinity of factors for the domain II. Our report also indicated that the E
 <sup>S123R</sup> mutation increases the proliferative capacity in mouse neuroblastoma N18 cells (
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Tajima et al., 2010</xref>). However, the proliferation ability of the Muar strain in N18 cells is lower than that of Mie/41/2002, whereas the growth kinetics of the 5NCME
 <sup>Muar</sup> mutant were similar to those of Mie/41/2002. These results suggest that the proliferative potential of JEV in N18 cells is not necessarily reflective of its virulence in mice.
</p>
