<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>2-(3,4-dihydroxyphenyl)-3,5,7-trihydroxy-4H-chromen-4-no, also called, quercetin (QRC) is a plant derivative belonging to the group of polyphenols called flavonoids. It is an aglycone. The main natural sources of QRC include onion, apple and black tea. It has antiviral, cardioprotective, antioxidant, anti-inflammatory and anti-carcinogenic effects [
 <xref rid="B126-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>]. In the small intestine QRC is absorbed and is immediately metabolized by enzymes in epithelial cells and subsequently by the liver. The catechol group of the QRC is methylated at position 3′–4′ by catechol-O-methyl transferase resulting in the formation of isorhamnetin (3’OCH3–QRC) or tamarixetine (4′OCH3–QRC). These metabolites together with the QRC can be conjugated in their hydroxyl groups with glucuronic acid or sulfate by the UCP-glucuronosyltransferase or sulfotransferase, respectively [
 <xref rid="B127-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>]. The half-life of plasma QRC in humans is between 17 and 18 h. Regarding the distribution of QRC (in a dose of 50 and another of 500 mg/kg for 11 weeks) its highest levels are found in the lungs and the lowest levels in the brain and white adipose tissue in rats, whereas concentrations of the metabolite aglycone isorhamnetin were higher in the liver [
 <xref rid="B128-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. QRC is safe for most people. However, in doses of up to 1 g daily, it may induce side effects such as headache and paresthesias in the hands and legs, which are reversible. Safety is only affected with the use of high doses, due to the risk of renal toxicity [
 <xref rid="B129-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>]. Safety is only affected with the use of high doses, due to the risk of renal toxicity. On the other hand, its interaction with antibiotics such as quinolones, with anti-neoplasics and immune-suppressants such as cyclosporine, in which their side effects increase, is known. There is also interaction with the use of diclofenac, celecoxib, fluvastatin, glipizide, ibuprofen, irbesartan, losartan phenytoin and others with cytochrome p450 2C9 substrate (CYP2C9) and with p450 2C (CYP2C8) such as paclitaxel, rosiglitazone, amiodarone and verapamil. However, QRC is currently a promise as a flavonoid with multifaceted therapeutic application that can be used in this pandemic from the initial asymptomatic stage, since it can be obtained through the diet, with foods that include grapes, strawberries, blackberries, the of fennel, lettuce and beans [
 <xref rid="B130-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>]. The QRC, present in H. cordata, inhibits several viruses including herpes simplex, mengovirus, pseudorarabias, parainfluenza type 3, Sindbis virus and respiratory syncytia [
 <xref rid="B131-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>]. QRC is able to inhibit the H
 <sup>+</sup>-ATPase of the lysosomal membrane and, therefore, prevent the removal of the virus [
 <xref rid="B127-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>]. Furthermore, QRC inhibits the ATPase of proteins related to resistance to many drugs elevating the bioavailability drugs against cancer and viruses in vivo [
 <xref rid="B127-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>]. Therefore, QRC may be considered is potentially effective as an antiviral [
 <xref rid="B131-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">131</xref>].
</p>
