<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0125">The human Angiotensin-converting enzyme 1 (ACE1) gene on chromosome 17 has an insertion (I) or deletion (D) of a 287 base pair (bp) Alu repeat sequence in intron 16 
 <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. Therefore, in the I/D polymorphism, there are three different genotypes, II, ID and DD. ACE1 is a metalloproteinase, which is a type I transmembrane glycoprotein. This protein plays an important regulatory function in the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (RAAS) and can convert angiotensin I (AngI) vasoconstrictor, which is inactive, to angiotensin II (AngII). AngII is the core product of the RAAS system, and causes various biological reactions through the angiotensin receptors (AT1 and AT2) while ACE2 (Angiotensin invertase 2) is a homologue of ACE and is well known as a receptor for SARS-COV-2. However, the original role of ACE2 is to digest AngII into Ang1-7 polypeptides, and protect the heart, vasodilate, resist growth, and resist proliferation. Also, the activity of bradykinin can be enhanced by ACE2. Very recently, we showed a strong negative correlation that the numbers of SARS-CoV-2 infected cases and deaths due to viral infection decreased with increasing ACE1 II genotype frequency 
 <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. The serum ACE1 level was significantly higher in those with the DD genotype compared with those with either the ID or the II genotype 
 <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, and viral infection may lead to suppression of ACE2 function and causes ACE1/ACE2 imbalance responsible for RAS over-activation and pulmonary shut-down 
 <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. This can further reduce the effects of ACE2, which counteracts the pathophysiological effects of Ang II produced by ACE1, and may worsen the pathology. In patients with the D allele, especially those with the DD genotype, higher risk of morbidity and mortality from sepsis, acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) and certain heart, lung and kidney conditions probably due to inflammation, vasculopathy and coagulopathy induced by AngII 
 <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref> is reported. Thus, the ACE1/ACE2 imbalance predicts that COVID-19 patients with the D allele of ACE1, especially the DD genotype, have a higher severity and prevalence of COVID-19.
</p>
