<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Native influenza HA protein is polymerized as trimer 
 <xref rid="pone.0053568-Stevens1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. It seems that recombinant HA fragments themselves cannot easily form functional, conformational trimeric or oligomeric structures, while the formation of these functional molecules of HA may be introduced through the addition of extraneous sequences 
 <xref rid="pone.0053568-Weldon1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0053568-Loureiro1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. A trimeric HA could be formed by fusing HA with a trimeric GCN4pII heptad repeat sequence derived from wild-type dimeric GCN4 repeat found in 
 <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>
 <xref rid="pone.0053568-Weldon1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. The Fd sequence, the C-terminal domain of T4 fibritin, is often applied as an artificial trimerization domain, and is thus required to form fibritin trimer structure 
 <xref rid="pone.0053568-Meier1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. Recombinant proteins conjugated with this motif have been shown to form stable trimers with improved antiviral activity 
 <xref rid="pone.0053568-Chen2" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. Fc is utilized as another motif to promote oligomeric conformation of expressed proteins for the purpose of increasing immunogenicity of recombinant proteins 
 <xref rid="pone.0053568-Loureiro1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. Therefore, we further constructed three additional recombinant proteins based on the identified neutralizing region fused with Fd and Fc by fusing the HA fragment with Fd-His, Fc or His, respectively, and the conformation of these proteins was subsequently evaluated. As expected, HA-13–263 protein with Fd and Fc (HA-13–263-Fdc) was able to form an oligomeric structure with the highest molecular weight, while those fused with Fc (HA-13–263-Fc) or Fd-His (HA-13–263-Fd-His) formed different polymeric conformations, including dimer or trimer, with relatively lower molecular weight. However, the protein without fusion with Fd or Fc (HA-13–263-His) did not form polymeric conformational structure, but remaining the monomeric form (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053568-g004">Fig. 4</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053568-g005">5</xref>). Thus, our results further emphasize the importance of adding foreign motif in promoting oligomerization of HA.
</p>
