<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="discussion"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?OLF?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pulmonology</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pulmonology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Pulmonology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2531-0429</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2531-0437</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Sociedade Portuguesa de Pneumologia. Published by Elsevier Espa&#x000f1;a, S.L.U.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7236731</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2531-0437(20)30104-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pulmoe.2020.05.003</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>COVID-19 and asthma: To have or not to have T2 inflammation makes a difference?</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0005"><name><surname>Morais-Almeida</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><email>mmoraisalmeida@netcabo.pt</email><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor0005" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0010"><name><surname>Bousquet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0005"><label>a</label>Allergy Centre, CUF Descobertas, Lisbon and Portuguese Association of Asthmatics (APA), Portugal</aff><aff id="aff0010"><label>b</label>Hospital Charit&#x000e9;, Universit&#x000e4;tsmedizin Berlin, Humboldt-Universit&#x000e4;t zu Berlin, and Berlin Institute of Health, Comprehensive Allergy Center, Department of Dermatology and Allergy, Berlin, Germany</aff><aff id="aff0015"><label>c</label>MACVIA-France, Montpellier, France</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor0005"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author. <email>mmoraisalmeida@netcabo.pt</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Sociedade Portuguesa de Pneumologia. Published by Elsevier Espa&#x000f1;a, S.L.U.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sociedade Portuguesa de Pneumologia</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><kwd-group id="kwd0005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Allergy</kwd><kwd>Asthma</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>Risk factors</kwd><kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd><kwd>T2 inflammation</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="par0005">During this pandemic, there has been some data discrepancy about whether patients with asthma have a lower risk of becoming infected or seriously ill from coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19)<xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> but there is no information about the real impact of SARS-CoronaVirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) on asthma control. Recent reports from the United States of America suggest that asthma is more common in children and adults with mild to severe COVID-19 than was previously reported in Asia and in Europe, but the prevalence is no higher than that described in the same population.<xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
</p><p id="par0010">SARS-CoV-2 binds mainly to angiotensin converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) receptors in host cells which are abundant in the lungs, heart, blood vessels and intestine and, after more than a decade of research, there are still no specific treatments or effective vaccines for coronavirus.<xref rid="bib0115" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>
</p><p id="par0015">COVID-19 mainly presents with respiratory symptoms, from mild to severe and a significant percentage of patients develop acute respiratory disease syndrome (ARDS); these severe symptoms are associated with a true cytokine storm, in particular IL-6, and death can occur.<xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>
</p><p id="par0020">Old age and underlying morbidities, such as cardiovascular diseases (in particular hypertension), metabolic disorders (obesity and diabetes), and respiratory system diseases were identified as significant risk factors for COVID-19 morbidity and mortality.<xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>
</p><p id="par0025">Even though respiratory viruses are one of the most common triggers for asthma exacerbations, not all of these viruses affect patients equally. In asthma exacerbations the human rhinovirus was identified as the main individual contributor and coronavirus does not seem to frequently induce asthma exacerbations.<xref rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> In a literature review concerning virus detection during asthma exacerbations, Zheng et al. confirmed that exacerbations were mainly associated with rhinovirus infection.<xref rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref>
</p><p id="par0030">In previous SARS outbreaks, patients with asthma, in particular children, appeared to be less susceptible to the coronavirus: the rate of asthma exacerbations described is low and prognosis good.<xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> In contrast, during influenza epidemics, asthma is involved in more severe cases, some needing mechanical ventilation, including patients of paediatric age.<xref rid="bib0145" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> The exact reasons for this remain unknown, but it has been confirmed during the current coronavirus pandemic with children having a better prognosis, although as likely as adults are to get infected with SARS-CoV-2.<xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Different ACE2 expression or maturation, innate immunity memory and a constitutional high lymphocyte count in children may be part of the explanation.<xref rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>
</p><p id="par0035">From the recent COVID-19 literature, no information can be extrapolated about asthma phenotypes, specifically about whether asthma was allergic or not. In a recent study that included paediatric and adult patients with asthma from three different cohorts, it was found that ACE2 expression was lowest in those with high levels of allergic sensitization, but non-atopic asthma was not associated with this reduced expression.<xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> Given that ACE2 serves as the receptor for SARS-CoV-2, these data suggest that this expression may be a potential contributor, among several other factors, to reduced COVID-19 severity in patients with T2 inflammation,<xref rid="bib0155" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> namely in patients with allergic asthma but also with other allergic diseases, such allergic rhinitis, which are more prevalent in all age groups.</p><p id="par0040">Additionally, considering that the virus cell entry also depends on S protein priming by host cell proteases, including transmembrane protease serine 2 (TMPRSS2), there is some early evidence coming from the Severe Asthma Research Programme-3 (SARP), that inhaled corticosteroid therapy is also associated with reduction in ACE2 and TMPRSS2 gene expression from sputum.<xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> Although gene expression for ACE2 and TMPRSS2 did not differ in healthy people and in asthmatics, the author's report that males, African Americans, and patients with diabetes mellitus have increased expression of ACE2 and TMPRSS2 in their sputum cells that can be associated with a poor prognosis when infected with the SARS-CoV-2.<xref rid="bib0160" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref>
</p><p id="par0045">Dong et al.,<xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> described eleven selected cases of patients with COVID-19, children and adults, demonstrating the profile complexity and different clinical presentations, from asymptomatic cases to patients with mild to severe symptoms. Patients with common allergic diseases, such as rhinitis or atopic dermatitis, did not develop distinct symptoms and severe clinical courses, suggesting a role of type 2 immune regulation in COVID-19 pathogenesis.</p><p id="par0050">During this outbreak it is more likely for a person with asthma to have an exacerbation caused by other triggers, including allergens or other virus exposures. New data are emerging daily, rapidly updating our understanding of this novel coronavirus, but it is crucial that patients with asthma and other allergic diseases maintain their controller medication, from inhaled steroids to biologics,<xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="bib0180" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> including allergen immunotherapy.<xref rid="bib0185" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> Self-dose adjustments or stopping medication may lead to higher risk of asthma exacerbations, increased OCS use and higher probability of recourse to emergency room and hospitalization which themselves represent risk factors for coronavirus exposure and spread.</p><p id="par0055">Asthma may worsen the disease course of COVID-19, should infection occur, namely if rescue OCS are prescribed,<xref rid="bib0190" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> as was suggested in previous coronavirus outbreaks when systemic steroids were associated with a higher viral load.<xref rid="bib0195" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="bib0200" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Clinicians must be aware and recognize the differences between hypoxic respiratory failure and bronchospasm on physical examination to carefully judge the need for a course of OCS.<xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref>
</p><sec id="sec0005"><title>Compliance with ethics</title><p id="par0060">This study involves a comment on the literature and did not involve any studies with human or animal subjects performed by the authors.</p></sec><sec id="sec0010"><title>Authorship</title><p id="par0065">The named authors met the International Committee of Medical Journal Editors (ICMJE) criteria for authorship of this manuscript, take responsibility for the integrity of the work as a whole, and have given final approval for the version to be published.</p></sec><sec id="sec0015"><title>Funding</title><p id="par0070">No funding was received in the publication of this letter.</p></sec><sec id="sec0020"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p id="par0075">The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bibl0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bib0105"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halpin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faner</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sibila</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Badia</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agusti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Do chronic respiratory diseases or their treatment affect the risk of SARS-CoV-2 infection?</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><volume>3</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>2020</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2213-2600(20)30167-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0110"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitaker</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Halloran</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holstein</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hospitalization rates and characteristics of patients hospitalized with laboratory-confirmed coronavirus disease 2019 &#x02013; COVID-NET, 14 States, March 1&#x02013;30, 2020</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><volume>69</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>458</fpage><lpage>464</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32298251</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0115"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Z.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new coronavirus associated with human respiratory disease in China</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>579</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32015508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0120"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lupia</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scabini</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mornese Pinna</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Perri</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Rosa</surname><given-names>F.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corcione</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) outbreak: a new challenge</article-title><source>J Glob Antimicrob Resist</source><volume>21</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32156648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0125"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gou</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of comorbidities and its effects in coronavirus disease 2019 patients: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Int J Infect Dis</source><volume>94</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32173574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0130"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Satia</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cusack</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Byrne</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Killian</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and contribution of respiratory viruses in the community to rates of emergency department visits and hospitalizations with respiratory tract infections, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and asthma</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><volume>15</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>e0228544</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32027687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0135"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>W.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L.-F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regional, age and respiratory-secretion-specific prevalence of respiratory viruses associated with asthma exacerbation: a literature review</article-title><source>Arch Virol</source><volume>163</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>845</fpage><lpage>853</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29327237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0140"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Bever</surname><given-names>H.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chng</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>D.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Childhood severe acute respiratory syndrome, coronavirus infections and asthma</article-title><source>Pediatr Allergy Immunol</source><volume>15</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>206</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15209951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0145"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tokuhira</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shime</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawasaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakurai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurosaka</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanically ventilated children with 2009 pandemic influenza A/H1N1: results from the national pediatric intensive care registry in Japan</article-title><source>Pediatr Crit Care Med</source><volume>13</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>294</fpage><lpage>298</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0150"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cristiani</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancino</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matera</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nenna</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierangeli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scagnolari</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Will children reveal their secret? The coronavirus dilemma</article-title><source>Eur Respir J</source><volume>55</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/13993003.00749-2020</pub-id><comment>pii: 2000749</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0155"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Busse</surname><given-names>W.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bacharier</surname><given-names>L.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kattan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Connor</surname><given-names>G.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of respiratory allergy, asthma and expression of the SARS-CoV-2 receptor, ACE2</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.200.04.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0160"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0160"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sajuthi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deford</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Christenson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rios</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SARS-COV-2 related genes in sputum cells in asthma: relationship to demographic features and corticosteroids</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.202003-0821OC</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0165"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>X.X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y.Q.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eleven faces of coronavirus disease 2019</article-title><source>Allergy</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/all.14289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0170"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0170"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morais-Almeida</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguiar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ansotegui</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebisawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arruda</surname><given-names>L.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>COVID-19, asthma and biologic therapies: what we need to know</article-title><source>World Allergy Organ J</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.waojou.2020.100126</pub-id><comment>May 16:100126</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0175"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0175"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Global Initiative for Asthma</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>2020 GINA Report. Global Strategy for Asthma Management and Prevention</chapter-title><year>2020</year><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ginasthma.org/" id="intr0005">www.ginasthma.org</ext-link> [accessed 28.04.20]</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0180"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0180"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bousquet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akdis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jutel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachert</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klimek</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agache</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intranasal corticosteroids in allergic rhinitis in COVID-19 infected patients: an ARIA-EAACI statement</article-title><source>Allergy</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/all.14302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0185"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0185"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klimek</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jutel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akdis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bousquet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akdis</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachert</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Handling of allergen immunotherapy in the COVID-19 pandemic: an ARIA-EAACI statement</article-title><source>Allergy</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/all.14336</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0190"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0190"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhatraju</surname><given-names>P.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghassemieh</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jerome</surname><given-names>K.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nalla</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Covid-19 in critically ill patients in the Seattle Region &#x02013; case series</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2004500</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0195"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0195"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen Chan</surname><given-names>K.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>E.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of early corticosteroid treatment on plasma SARS-associated Coronavirus RNA concentrations in adult patients</article-title><source>J Clin Virol</source><volume>31</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>304</fpage><lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15494274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0200"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0200"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arabi</surname><given-names>Y.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandourah</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Hameed</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sindi</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Almekhlafi</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Corticosteroid therapy for critically ill patients with Middle East Respiratory Syndrome</article-title><source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source><volume>197</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>767</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29161116</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>