<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The most advanced dengue vaccine is a chimera of structural genes of the four DENVs with the yellow fever vaccine non-structural genome. This vaccine was tested for vaccine efficacy and safety in placebo-controlled clinical trials enrolling 35,000 children (2 to 16 years old) in 10 dengue-endemic countries 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>
 </sup>. Efficacy results were mixed. Through year 3 after the first dose, vaccine protection against hospitalization of children at least 9 years old was 65.5% but among children 8 years old or younger was 44.6% 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>
 </sup>. In the 2- to 5-year-old age group, vaccinated children were hospitalized five times more frequently than those in the placebo group. Among the 11% of children whose serostatus (when vaccinated) was known, protection in seronegative children 8 years old or younger was 14.4% but in those 9 years old or older was 52.5%. These data led the manufacturer and expert committees to recommend that vaccine be restricted to children 9 years old or older 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>, 
  <xref rid="ref-103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>
 </sup>. A new serological test made it possible to distinguish those who were seronegative from those who were dengue-immune at the time of vaccination 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>
 </sup>. When this test was applied to sera from a 10% randomized cohort of phase 3 children, dengue seronegativity rather than age controlled risk to severe hospitalized dengue disease (platelet count of less than 100,000 mm 
 <sup>3 </sup>evidence of vascular permeability) over the period 5 to 6 years after first dose in children given vaccine 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>
 </sup>. With this evidence of declining efficacy, the World Health Organization (WHO) Scientific Advisory Group of Experts, the Global Advisory Committee on Vaccine Safety, and the WHO Dengue Vaccine Working Group in 2016 recommended that vaccine be given to individuals with known past dengue infection or to populations with 80% DENV seroprevalence 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
