<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The MP-12 vaccine was developed by the U.S. Army Medical Research Institute of Infectious Diseases (USAMRIID) for both human and veterinary use via 12 serial passages of the virulent ZH548 and ZH501 strains, isolated from Egyptian patients in MRC-5 cells in the presence of chemical mutagens (5-fluorouracil). MP-12 is temperature sensitive and carries redundant mutations in all three genomic segments of RVFV [
 <xref rid="B77-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Furthermore, reassortants between the wild-type strain and MP-12 showed that these segments contribute to the attenuation of MP-12 virulence in mice [
 <xref rid="B78-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. The reassortant strains contain one attenuated and two virulent segments that considered to be attenuated, therefore, the reassortment between wild-type virus and vaccine strain might produce an attenuated virus that protects against RVF [
 <xref rid="B78-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. The MP-12 vaccine was evaluated in pregnant ewes at 70–100 days of gestation. Interestingly, MP-12 did not induce abortions, fetal abnormalities or virus shedding in milk when administered after 3 months of gestation. Only some lamb losses (about 4%) were aborted when the MP-12 vaccine was administered at the early stage of pregnancy [
 <xref rid="B79-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. This induces neutralizing antibodies from 1:80 to 1:320 titers, and the newborn lambs acquire more than 1:80 neutralizing antibodies after they are fed colostrums via the passive transfer of maternal antibodies. The MP-12 vaccine was also evaluated for human use in Rhesus Macaques and produced protective antibody titers (≥1:40) against challenge test with RVFV ZH501 strain [
 <xref rid="B80-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Generally, MP-12 has the ability to produce antibody titers sufficient to protect the animals against RVFV infection and there is a potential beneficial effect of immunizing pregnant animals to obtain protection in newborns. The MP-12 vaccine contains virulent 
 <italic>NSs</italic> gene and can cause abortions and fetal abnormalities, but the vaccine is well tolerated, safe, and immunogenic when administered at an adequate dose. The MP-12 vaccine gave promising results when evaluated in more than 100 human volunteers [
 <xref rid="B71-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,
 <xref rid="B81-viruses-11-00139" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>].
</p>
