<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi</italic> is a tick-borne zoonosis widely distributed in North America and Europe. All three pathogenic species, 
 <italic>B. burgdorferi</italic>, 
 <italic>B. afzelii</italic> and 
 <italic>B. garinii</italic> occur in Europe, and the latter two have been identified in Asia. 
 <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi</italic> circulates between 
 <italic>Ixodes</italic> ticks and vertebrate hosts in an enzootic cycle. Ticks can transmit borrelia to humans, but humans are dead-end hosts, unlikely to continue the life cycle of the spirochete[
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Lyme disease (LD) has a broad spectrum of clinical manifestations. Primary infection presents as erythema migrans (EM). Late stages occur weeks to years following infection and include arthritis, peripheral neuropathy, and skin ﬁndings such as acrodermatitis chronica atrophicans[
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Neuroborreliosis is one of the manifestations of LD involving the central nervous system (CNS)[
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The role of immunosuppression in the development and progression of LD is not well understood. An analysis of SOT recipients on immunosuppressive treatment who presented with solitary EM did not reveal any signiﬁcant differences in the clinical course of infection as compared with the general population[
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The first case of LD in a transplanted patient was described in 1993 in a kidney transplant recipient in whom the disease progressed into the disseminated stage with severe neurological signs[
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. A study from Slovenia presented a case series of six SOT recipients with EM. All six patients had solitary skin lesions with clinical characteristics comparable to those of the skin lesions in immunocompetent patients. No clinical signs or symptoms suggesting borrelia dissemination were present or were reported either during the initial course of the illness or during the one-year follow-up period after antibiotic treatment and persistence of borrelia organisms in the skin after treatment was not established[
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. A case report of Lyme carditis after liver transplant that progressed to disseminated illness with a concomitant heart block and deterioration of mental status has also been described[
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].
</p>
