<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Due to the risk of blood-borne pathogen transmission, it is pivotal to implement cleaning and disinfection between BGM uses [
 <xref rid="pone.0180617.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The present cases of blood-borne infection are mainly associated with HBV, hepatitis C virus (HCV), and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) [
 <xref rid="pone.0180617.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0180617.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. HBV has larger pool of infectivity, high infection and environmental stability, even invisible amounts of blood or dried blood are sufficient to spread infection (in 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0180617.t004">Table 4</xref>) [
 <xref rid="pone.0180617.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0180617.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0180617.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. As a result, several incidents of outbreaks of HBV have been reported [
 <xref rid="pone.0180617.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0180617.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The disinfectant wipes (EPA registered No. 67619–12) we chose covers broad spectrum of disinfecting ability, including HBV, HIV and HCV listed in 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0180617.t004">Table 4</xref>. Our step-by-step demonstration of disinfection procedure can possibly prevent other relevant blood-borne pathogen transmission among persons improperly handling or sharing BGMs. 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0180617.t004">Table 4</xref> shows the blood-borne modern epidemics and their EPA-registered disinfectants. The detail information of EPA-registered disinfectant products are available from the website: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://iaspub.epa.gov/apex/pesticides/f?p=PPLS:1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://iaspub.epa.gov/apex/pesticides/f?p=PPLS:1</ext-link>. In addition, Ebola disease, one of current modern epidemics, also spreads through the direct contact with blood and body fluids of infected people. It had been proved that Ebola virus can be viable in dried blood for up to 5 days [
 <xref rid="pone.0180617.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The possible transmission of Ebola virus associated with the visible or invisible dried blood should be taken into account. Although there are less EPA-registered disinfectants against Ebola virus, an economical 10% solution of household bleach, has proved no adverse effects on BGMs’ accuracy and exterior surface [
 <xref rid="pone.0180617.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], may be an alternative. 10% bleach with our step-by-step demonstration of disinfection procedure may have beneficial effects to prevent the occurrence of transmission of Ebola virus. However, the contact time of effective disinfection on the BGM need to be further investigated.
</p>
