<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pntd.0003163.s004">
 <label>Table S3</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Vector competence data, vertebrate competence data, and mosquito feeding patterns were combined to estimate the Rift Valley fever virus amplification fraction displayed by the vectors and vertebrates in the United States. In the 
   <italic>F
    <sub>vi</sub>
   </italic> equation (
   <italic>F
    <sub>vi</sub>
   </italic> = 
   <italic>B
    <sub>i</sub>
   </italic>
   <sup>2</sup> * C
   <italic>
    <sub>i</sub>
   </italic> * C
   <italic>
    <sub>v</sub>
   </italic>), the number of infectious mosquitoes resulting from feeding on a vertebrate host, Fvi, is equal to vertebrate host competence (C
   <italic>
    <sub>i</sub>
   </italic>: located in row 5), multiplied by the vector competence (C
   <italic>
    <sub>v</sub>
   </italic>: located in column C), multiplied by the fraction of the total blood meals from host i squared (B
   <italic>
    <sub>i</sub>
   </italic>
   <sup>2</sup>: indicated in each cell as a number divided by total blood meals in column B). All 
   <italic>F
    <sub>vi</sub>
   </italic> values reflecting a vector-vertebrate pair were summed for each mosquito species (Column AC) and summed for each vertebrate species (Row 49). To present these values as a % risk (Column AD) the values of the vector amplification fraction were weighted over the total amplification demonstrated by all vectors, then multiplied by 100. To express the vertebrate contribution to RVFV amplification as a % risk (Row 50), the amplification values at the taxonomic resolution of Family and Order were weighted over the total amplification estimated by all mammals (Cell: Y49), then multiplied by 100. Because some blood meal data was only specific to the Mammalian class, 6.3% of the estimated amplification fraction is undetermined at the resolution of Order. Therefore, all order % risk estimates are minimum estimates.
  </p>
  <p>(XLS)</p>
 </caption>
 <media xlink:href="pntd.0003163.s004.xls" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <caption>
   <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
  </caption>
 </media>
</supplementary-material>
