<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We searched the literature to identify common risk factors of infectious disease outbreaks using three online databases: PubMed/Medline, Scopus and CINAHL using keywords ‘outbreak* OR epidemic* OR pandemic* OR emerging disease* OR re-emerged disease*’. We identified numerous initial factors associated with the severity of the disease outbreaks,
 <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24–27</xref> which we categorised as either disease-related parameters or country-related parameters. Additional disease-related parameters were selected based on a modified Disease Attribute Intelligence System risk assessment tool by the Institute of Environmental Science and Research Limited,
 <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> while additional country-related parameters were identified based on the risk analysis framework tool by Ajisegiri 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> The financial capability and the level of investment of a country plays a significant role in the early response to outbreaks.
 <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Sociopolitical factors also contribute to the length and outcome of outbreaks. For example, war and conflict provide ideal conditions for outbreaks of infection diseases. In conflict areas, health professionals flee, infrastructure is destroyed and the supply of medical equipment is halted.
 <xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> In some instances, hampering of immunisation efforts has also contributed to the spread of vaccine-preventable diseases,
 <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> making a country more vulnerable to outbreaks. The majority of severe disease outbreaks also originate from densely populated regions.
 <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Overcrowding coupled with lower living standards can lead to the efficient transmission of diseases and positively correlate with the risk of an outbreak.
 <xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> The existing health system within the country also plays a crucial role in the risk of outbreaks. An epidemic can spread wider and faster in a country with a weak health system.
 <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>
</p>
