<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">(i) Ferret transmission experiments: Donor ferrets were inoculated intratracheally with 10
 <sup>5</sup> TCID
 <sub>50</sub> of virus diluted in a 3 ml volume of phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) and subsequently intranasally with 10
 <sup>5</sup> TCID
 <sub>50</sub> of virus diluted in a 40 μl volume of PBS (20 μl instilled in each nostril). Half of the donor ferrets were inoculated with untagged viruses intranasally and tagged viruses intratracheally and the other half with the opposite placement of virus in order to correct for potential small differences in transmissibility (see Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref> for a summary). Throat and nose swabs were collected from donor ferrets every day until 7 days post inoculation (dpi) (donor ferret 1–4) or until the day transmission was observed or the latest at 5 dpi (donor ferrets 5–16). Recipient ferrets were placed four hours after inoculation (hpi) of donor ferrets in an opposite cage separated by two steel grids, 10 cm apart, to avoid contact transmission. Throat and nose swabs were collected from recipient ferrets 12 h respectively until 9 days post exposure (dpe). Swabs were stored at −80 °C in transport medium (Hanks’ balanced salt solution containing 0.5% lactalbumin (Sigma-Aldrich), 10% glycerol (Sigma-Aldrich), 200 U ml
 <sup>−1</sup> PEN, 200 mg ml
 <sup>−1</sup> STR, 100 U ml
 <sup>−1</sup> polymyxin B sulfate (Sigma-Aldrich), and 250 mg ml
 <sup>−1</sup> gentamicin (Gibco)) for end-point titration in MDCK and next-generation sequencing as decribed below. Shedding from recipient ferrets 5–16 was monitored every day by performing real-time RT-qPCR detecting the matrix gene on nose and throat swabs right after collection as described below. The rest of the swabs were stored in transport media at −80 °C for endpoint titration in MDCK cells and next-generation sequencing. The corresponding donor ferrets were euthanized by heart puncture under anesthesia when transmission to the recipient ferret was observed (two consecutive positive swabs with a threshold value in RT-qPCR (CT value) &lt; 35) or at 5 dpi the latest. Samples from the respiratory tract (nasal turbinates, upper part of the trachea, lower part of the trachea, left lung lobes and right lung lobes) were collected, homogenized in transport medium using a FastPrep system (MP Biomedicals) with 2 one-quarter-inch ceramic sphere balls, centrifuged at 1500 × 
 <italic>g</italic> for 10 min, aliquoted, and stored at −80 °C for endpoint titration in MDCK cells and next-generation sequencing. Additionally, throat and nose swabs were collected from donor ferrets 5–16 every day until euthanasia and stored in transport media at −80 °C for endpoint titration in MDCK cells and next-generation sequencing. Clonality of the virus inoculum was confirmed by next-generation sequencing. Virus inocula were back titrated to ensure that the right doses were used to inoculate donor ferrets.
</p>
