<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The impact of CVD on COVID-19 outcomes has been investigated in the article ‘
 <bold>Clinical characteristics and outcomes of Caucasian patients with COVID-19 and a history of cardiac disease in Northern Italy</bold>’ by Marco Metra and colleagues from the Università degli Studi di Brescia in Italy, one of the centres with the highest case load and mortality.
 <xref rid="ehaa435-B19" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref> They analysed 53 consecutive patients with confirmed COVID-19 and a history of CVD admitted between 4 and 25 March 2020, when the epidemic reached its peak. Their mean age was 68 years and 81% were males. The main cause of admission was either COVID-19 pneumonia with a history of CVD in 47% or an acute cardiac condition with concomitant COVID-19 in 52%. Of note, 16 presented with acute heart failure, 6 with acute coronary syndrome (ACS), and 4 with pulmonary embolism (
 <italic>Figure 
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ehaa435-F2">2</xref>
 </italic>). During hospitalization, 32% died, 11% developed thrombo-embolic events, 21% developed acute respiratory distress syndrome or ARDS, and 11% suffered septic shock. Non-survivors tended to be older, with a higher burden of cardiac comorbidities, impaired renal function, lower blood cells count, and higher D-dimer. Both high-sensitivity troponin and NT-proBNP were elevated at admission in both groups, with a trend towards higher levels among non-survivors. Patients who died were also more likely to have a lower PO
 <sub>2</sub>/FiO
 <sub>2</sub> ratio and need for high-flow oxygen support, compared with those who lived. Thus, Caucasian patients with CVD and superimposed COVID-19 have an extremely poor prognosis, findings that are put into context in an 
 <bold>Editorial</bold> by Pierpaolo Pellicori from the Hull and East Yorkshire Medical Research and Teaching Centre in Kingston upon Hull, UK.
 <xref rid="ehaa435-B20" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
