<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0035">Coronaviruses are single-stranded, zoonotic RNA viruses that cause symptoms ranging from common cold to more extreme respiratory, enteric, hepatic, and neurological symptoms [
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Besides, SARS-CoV-2 there are six other coronaviruses reported in humans. These are HCoV-OC43, HCoV-229E, SARS-CoV, HCoV-HKU1, MERS-CoV and HCoVNL63 [
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Over the last two decades Coronavirus has caused two major pandemics: SARS [
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] and MERS [
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. In order to find out the source of the COVID-19 outbreak CDC researchers of China collected 585 environmental samples from Huanan Seafood Market in Wuhan, Hubei Province. They found 33 samples were SARS-CoV-2 suggested that it came from wild animals sold on the market [
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Researchers also used the 'lung fluid, blood, and throat swab samples from 15 patients for laboratory research. Such laboratory studies revealed that virus-specific nucleic acid sequences in the sample vary from those of known human coronavirus species. The laboratory findings also showed SARS CoV-2 is identical to some of the beta (β) coronaviruses genera found in bats which is located in the SARS/SARS-like CoV groups [
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. For the conduction of next-generation sequencing from cultured isolates and bronchoalveolar lavage fluid nine inpatients were enrolled by researchers in Wuhan with viral pneumonia and without any common respiratory pathogens. The results indicated SARS-CoV-2 was more distinct from MERS-CoV (with approximately 50% sequence identity) and SARS-CoV (with approximately 79% sequence identity) than from two bat-derived SARS-like coronaviruses bat-SL-CoVZXC21 (with 87.2% sequence identity) and bat-SL-CoVZC45 (with 87.9% sequence identity) [
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The studies also showed that COVID-19 S-protein strongly interacted with human ACE2 molecules in spite of dissimilarity of its sequence with that of SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].
</p>
