<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As patients with COVID-19 frequently have isolated pulmonary findings, the initial hemostatic dysregulation may be localized to the lungs as a consequence of the bidirectional relationship between the innate immune system and thrombosis. Activated platelets through degranulation and coordinated interactions with monocytes, dendritic cells, and neutrophils, as well as activated T cells, NETs, tissue factor-bearing microparticles, and coagulation proteases may facilitate this crosstalk.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr54-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr76-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr77-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>
 </sup> In this model, immune cells, inflammatory cytokines, and pathogen-associated molecular patterns induce thrombi consisting of fibrin, monocytes, neutrophils, and platelets.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr57-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr58-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr78-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>
 </sup> These immunothrombi initially serve a protective purpose, promoting pathogen recognition and creating a sterile barrier against further pathogen invasion, but can become maladaptive and injurious to tissue and organ perfusion.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr57-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr79-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr80-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>
 </sup> During this process, there is abundant intra- and extra-vascular fibrin deposition and impaired fibrinolysis, which has been well described in ARDS.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr81-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr82-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>
 </sup> In postmortem studies, both macro- and microvascular thrombi are common in patients in ARDS (observed in up to 95% of patients).
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr82-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr83-1358863X20932640" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>
 </sup> In COVID-19, the alveolar immunothrombotic response may be an attempt to limit dissemination of SARS-CoV-2 outside the alveoli.
</p>
