<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0021">Third, not all cases were ascertained during the course of the epidemic. We let 
 <italic>q</italic> be the proportion of diagnosed Ebola patients among the total number of infected individuals. Diagnosed cases correspond to the incidence data of confirmed and probable cases (
 <xref rid="bib0034" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2016b</xref>). The total number of infected individuals is calculated by (1 + 
 <italic>λ</italic>) diagnosed cases if the number of undiagnosed cases per a diagnosed case is 
 <italic>λ</italic>. Then, the total number of ascertained cases was calculated by the sum of diagnosed cases and undiagnosed cases. We examined how influential the imperfect diagnosis would be on the declaration of the end of an epidemic by varying 100 × 
 <italic>q</italic> by setting 50% as the default and varying it from 10% to 90% as part of the sensitivity analysis (
 <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Houlihan et al., 2017</xref>). To examine the impact of under-ascertainment on the end of an epidemic, we recalculated the total number of cases using 
 <italic>q</italic> and the observed epidemic curve, estimating the undiagnosed cases as (1−
 <italic>q</italic>)/
 <italic>q</italic> times the observed epidemic curve. Although the simple use of (1−
 <italic>q</italic>)/
 <italic>q</italic> could potentially inflate the actual number of cases, and whereas the issue could be overcome by using a latent variable model that separates the observation process from unobservable transmission process, we did not employ the latent modeling, because its explicit incorporation requires us to implement additional formulation that influences the derivation of 
 <xref rid="eqn0005" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (5)</xref>. In addition, the 
 <xref rid="eqn0005" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (5)</xref> requires the reproduction number 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>f</sub> as an input, but 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>t</sub> varies with time. We examined the impact of using different 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>f</sub> estimates on the probability of declaring the end of an outbreak. As the baseline setting, 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>f</sub> was calculated by taking its average for the most recent 24 weeks.
</p>
