<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>HLA genotyping of 11 ethnic populations has been reported previously [
 <xref rid="B21-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], and the allelic frequencies are summarized in 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-cells-08-00711">Supplementary Table S2</xref>. The frequencies of 
 <italic>HLA-C1/C2</italic> allotype, 
 <italic>HLA-Bw4</italic> (
 <italic>Bw4-80I</italic> and 
 <italic>Bw4-80T</italic>)/
 <italic>Bw6</italic> allotype, and 
 <italic>HLA-A11, -A3</italic> were calculated using direct counting. The 
 <italic>HLA-C1</italic> and 
 <italic>HLA-C2</italic>, 
 <italic>HLA-A11</italic> and 
 <italic>HLA-A3</italic>, and 
 <italic>HLA-Bw4/Bw6</italic> groups were used to analyze KIR–HLA combinations. The observed frequencies of KIR–HLA matched pairs were calculated using direct counting. The significance of the correlations of KIR and HLA frequencies among populations were estimated using the correlation coefficient (r) and the 
 <italic>t</italic>-test was used to establish whether the correlation coefficient was significant using SPSS 16.0 [
 <xref rid="B26-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The chord distance of Nei (Da distances among the populations were calculated based on 11 KIR gene (
 <italic>2DL1</italic>, 
 <italic>2DL2</italic>, 
 <italic>2DL3</italic>, 
 <italic>3DL1</italic>, 
 <italic>2DS1</italic>, 
 <italic>2DS2</italic>, 
 <italic>2DS3</italic>, 
 <italic>2DS4</italic>, 
 <italic>2DS5</italic>, 
 <italic>3DS1</italic>, and 
 <italic>2DL5</italic>) frequencies; 
 <italic>HLA-A</italic>, 
 <italic>HLA-B</italic>, and 
 <italic>HLA-C</italic> allele frequencies; or HLA–KIR combinations. A neighbor-joining (NJ) tree was constructed using Mega 7.0 software based on the DA distance [
 <xref rid="B27-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Principal component analysis (PCA) was also performed based either on KIR genes, HLA alleles, or KIR–HLA combination frequencies using SPSS 16.0 software [
 <xref rid="B26-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Significant differences in KIR and KIR–HLA pair frequencies between two populations were determined using a contingency test. The difference between the northern and southern groups were detected using a 
 <italic>t</italic>-test with SPSS 16.0 software [
 <xref rid="B26-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. A value of 
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered to be statistically significant. The observed 11 KIR gene (
 <italic>2DL1</italic>, 
 <italic>2DL2</italic>, 
 <italic>2DL3</italic>, 
 <italic>3DL1</italic>, 
 <italic>2DS1</italic>, 
 <italic>2DS2</italic>, 
 <italic>2DS3</italic>, 
 <italic>2DS4</italic>, 
 <italic>2DS5</italic>, 
 <italic>3DS1</italic>, and 
 <italic>2DL5</italic>) frequencies of 47 other populations were from previous studies and the DA distance among 58 populations were calculated (
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-cells-08-00711">Supplementary Tables S5 and S6</xref>). The phylogenetic tree was constructed based on the DA distance using the minimum evolution method from Mega 7.0 software [
 <xref rid="B28-cells-08-00711" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].
</p>
