<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Trehalose (α,α-trehalose), a naturally occurring sugar, is a non-reducing disaccharide with two glucose molecules that functions as an energy source in many organisms. Trehalose is present in various organisms, such as plants, algae, fungi, yeast, bacteria, insects, and other invertebrates. In 2000, the U.S. FDA gave trehalose a generally recognized as safe (GRAS) status (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Because of its protectant effects against freezing and dehydration, trehalose has become an attractive ingredient in food, health, and pharmaceutical products (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). The optimized production process of trehalose makes it accessible and affordable. Although humans cannot synthesize trehalose, the small intestine can hydrolyze trehalose into two D-glucose molecules by the specific enzyme trehalase. Since the hydrolyzing activity of trehalase is ordinarily low, it causes only a mild increase in blood glucose and insulin levels (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). In contrast, sucrose, a disaccharide composed of glucose and fructose, immediately increases both blood glucose and insulin levels after oral intake (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). On the other hand, unhydrolyzed trehalose can be rapidly absorbed in the bloodstream after oral administration to mice, rats, and macaques, which peaked at ~15 min to 1 h post-dose and continued to be detectable in macaques up to 12 h post-dose (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). The pharmacokinetic data on non-human primates provide a promising incentive for human response to trehalose. In human subjects, the daily intake of 10 g/day trehalose for 12 weeks improved glucose tolerance, decreased the progression to insulin resistance, and decreased systolic blood pressure. Therefore, trehalose can induce systemic benefits that are not associated with an increase in glucose levels and insulin resistance (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Altogether, these studies support the feasibility and safety of trehalose treatment for the prevention of SARS-CoV-2 infection and transmission.
</p>
