<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0145">A previous study of SARS-CoV patients without pre-existing diabetes (
 <italic>n</italic> = 39) has reported that 20 of the 39 SARS-CoV patients developed diabetes during hospitalization because immunostaining of ACE-2 in the pancreatic tissue suggested that SARS-CoV might have damaged pancreatic islets and caused acute Type I diabetes mellitus like condition [
 <xref rid="bb0370" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0380" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. Whereas in the case of SARS-COV-2, evidence is still lacking to confirm that pancreatic destruction in COVID-19 patients. The development of a viral infection in diabetic patients renders them harder to treat due to oscillating blood glucose levels and the presence of other secondary diabetic complications. Therefore, it can be hypothesized that the treatment of COVID-19 cum diabetic patients with ACE-2 stimulatory drugs might increase the risk of acquiring more severe and fatal COVID-19. Another component that should be considered is the existence of ACE-2 polymorphisms in Asian populations, which is further linked to diabetes mellitus and hypertension, genetically predisposes towards increased risk of SARS-COV-2 infection [
 <xref rid="bb0490" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. In a nutshell, intake of ACE inhibitors may lead to the upregulation of ACE-2 receptors in diabetic patients, binding of spike (S) glycoprotein to the ACE-2 is a vital step for virus entry into human cells. Additionally, some other notions have been proposed that the immune system is exceedingly compromised in diabetic subjects, which render them harder to combat the virus and likely result in a more extended recovery period. Secondly, the virus can flourish for a longer time in an atmosphere of high blood glucose ([
 <xref rid="bb0385" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>], 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://diabetesvoice.org/en/news/covid-19-and-diabetes/" id="ir0485" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://diabetesvoice.org/en/news/covid-19-and-diabetes/</ext-link>).
</p>
