<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We used data from the 2012 South African National HIV Prevalence, Incidence and Behavior Survey (SABSSM IV) [
 <xref rid="pone.0212445.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. That survey sampled residents from 15 randomly selected households within each of 1,000 census enumeration areas (EAs) which were selected randomly with probability proportional to size from the 86,000 EAs of South Africa. A total of 42,950 individuals were contacted, 38,431(89.5%) consenting persons were interviewed and 28,997(67.5%) blood specimens were tested for HIV. We computed conventional Horvitz-Thompson design-based domain estimates [
 <xref rid="pone.0212445.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] of district-level HIV prevalence (proportion of HIV-positives) among persons of all ages and associated standard errors from those data, henceforth called direct estimates. District-level auxiliary predictors were: HIV prevalence among women making the first visit of their pregnancy to public ANC clinics participating in the 2012 National Antenatal Sentinel HIV &amp; Herpes Simplex Type 2 Prevalence Survey in South Africa (ANCSS) [
 <xref rid="pone.0212445.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]; population density (km
 <sup>-2</sup>); the percentages of housing units which were “formal” dwellings [
 <xref rid="pone.0212445.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]; dependency ratio (ratio of the numbers of residents aged 15-64 years to those younger than 15 years and older than 64 years) [
 <xref rid="pone.0212445.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]; socio-economic quintile (1-5) [
 <xref rid="pone.0212445.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]; and maternal mortality rate (maternal deaths within six weeks of parturition per 10,000 pregnancies) [
 <xref rid="pone.0212445.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. For the ANCSS, HIV testing was performed from 34,260 women between the ages of 15-49 during their first visits to the 1,497 ANC sites which had been selected randomly with probability proportional to size for inclusion in the 2012 round of surveillance. The auxiliary predictors were chosen based on both a priori assumptions about potential correlations with HIV prevalence and their availability. We do not assume that the set of auxiliary predictors selected for this demonstration provide the best possible predictions of HIV prevalence in the general population. SAE requires only that some among them contain information about HIV prevalence in the general population.
</p>
