<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The continuous importation of viraemic ruminants or camels, mainly from Sudan, was considered the main source of introduction of RVF into Egypt [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006143.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Furthermore, those importations may also result in the introduction of other exotic diseases such as the Middle East Respiratory Syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006143.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. RVF is considered to be endemic in sub-Saharan African countries (including Sudan), with major outbreaks associated with periods of heavy rainfall and flooding [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006143.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Socio-economic changes, with human population growth and the associated increased demand for meat, or changes in the meat market prices could result in greater controlled and uncontrolled transboundary movements of livestock. A consequence of all those changes would be an increase of the risk of introduction of RVFV into areas of the Mediterranean basin and the Middle East [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006143.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. While surveillance and diagnostic methods for RVFV are available, RVFV control is hindered by the difficulties of vector control, and the fact that vaccines are only available for ruminants, with either inactivated vaccines (with a limited efficacy) or live attenuated vaccines (with a residual pathogenic effect) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006143.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006143.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Therefore, the best strategy to protect countries at risk of RVFV introduction is the implementation of regional monitoring and control programmes in endemic countries, as well as the establishment of early warning systems in the countries at risk. The Egyptian authorities implement both measures to prevent the introduction of RVFV (vaccination of imported animals, quarantines and testing of a proportion of imported animals) and measures to prevent the spread (vaccination of the Egyptian susceptible population). If those measures were effective, there would be no risk of RVFV introduction and spread, however, their efficacy has not been evaluated, and some deficiencies have been identified in the past [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006143.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Given the limitation of resources, risk-based methods (i.e. focusing on those areas and/or practices that pose the highest risk) may be considered as a cost-effective alternative for the surveillance of RVF in Egypt. Many of those risk-based methods are data-driven, which rely on comprehensive information about disease-associated events. In a data-scarce context, knowledge-driven methods, which rely on the previous information on the factors associated with disease occurrence, offer an alternative approach to identify areas at risk [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006143.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].
</p>
