<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pan Afr Med J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Pan Afr Med J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PAMJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Pan African Medical Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1937-8688</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The African Field Epidemiology Network</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7266475</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PAMJ-SUPP-35-2-12</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11604/pamj.2020.35.2.22877</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Letter to the Editors</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>COVID-19 infection and oxidative stress: an under-explored approach for prevention and treatment?</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ntyonga-Pono</surname><given-names>Marie-Pierrette</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">&#x00026;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label>d&#x000b4;Endocrinologie, M&#x000e9;tabolisme, Facult&#x000e9; de M&#x000e9;decine de Libreville, Libreville, Gabon</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x00026;</label><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> Marie-Pierrette Ntyonga-Pono, d&#x000b4;Endocrinologie, M&#x000e9;tabolisme, Facult&#x000e9; de M&#x000e9;decine de Libreville, Libreville, Gabon</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>35</volume><issue>Suppl 2</issue><elocation-id>12</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Marie-Pierrette Ntyonga-Pono et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/"><license-p>The Pan African Medical Journal - ISSN 1937-8688. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><kwd-group><kwd>Oxidative stress</kwd><kwd>Covid-19</kwd><kwd>antioxidants</kwd><kwd>glutathione</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>To the editors of Pan African Medical Journal</title><p>Oxidative stress is the result of an imbalance in the body between the oxidizing system, consisting mainly of free radicals, reactive oxygen species (ROS) and reactive nitrogen species (RNS) [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], and antioxidant systems that neutralize these free radicals capable of multiple deleterious effects. This oxidative stress is involved in aging [<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] and is found in certain chronic pathologies such as diabetes mellitus, cancers, hypertension, coronary heart disease, etc. [<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] and certain infections, particularly by the RNA viruses [<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], a family to which belong corona viruses [<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The objective of this work is to explain the role of oxidative stress in RNA virus infections and probably also in Covid 19 infection, in order to propose measures for prevention and treatment of this deadly infection which has already caused more than 118000 deaths worldwide [<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. This is an analysis of literature about oxidative stress, ways to counteract it, known links with certain RNA viruses and possible links with the new Corona virus.</p><p><bold>Oxidative stress and reactive oxygen and nitrogen species (RONS)</bold>: reactive Oxygen and Nitrogen Species (RONS) are molecules characterized by the presence of unpaired valence electrons, which cause them to react with various biological molecules [<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Main ROS are hydroxyl radical (OH&#x000ba;), superoxide anion (O<sub>2</sub>&#x000ba;-), singlet oxygen (&#x000b9;O<sub>2</sub>), oxygen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) and ozone (O<sub>3</sub>), a powerful oxidant formed by endothermic reaction from O<sub>2</sub> [<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. For RNS it is nitric oxide (NO) peroxynitrite (ONOO<sup>-</sup>), the nitrosyl cation (NO<sup>+</sup>), the nitrosyl anion (NO-), nitrous acid (NH<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) .... [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] These free radicals are natural byproducts of various cellular processes and the functioning of structures such as mitochondria and the endoplasmic reticulum [<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Under physiological conditions these reactive species play an important role in cell signalling, regulation of cytokines, growth factors, as immunomodulators, etc [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] and are involved in the natural aging of the human organism [<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. But when the balance is broken between oxidizing agents and antioxidant systems, which characterizes oxidative stress, these free radicals will have deleterious effects on all biomolecules [<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The most reactive, hydroxyl radical can oxidize various molecules in its proximity, including DNA, phospholipids, and proteins. The superoxide can generate other free radicals and come into contact with nitric oxide (NO) to give the peroxynitrite radical (ONOO<sup>-</sup>), a powerful oxidant with NO depletion. Hydrogen peroxide is converted to hydroxyl and can cross cell membranes. Ozone is a powerful oxidant of lipid chains, it can generate other free radicals, and interact with a large number of organic and inorganic compounds [<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Damage caused by these free radicals will affect cell membranes through the phenomenon of lipid peroxidation, oxidation and denaturation of proteins, DNA damage which can induce inflammatory immune responses, mutations and tumorigenesis risk, apoptosis [<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. So oxidative stress is involved in the occurrence of certain pathologies such as cancers, autoimmune diseases, cataract, Alzheimer&#x02019;s and neurodegenerative diseases, diabetes mellitus, cardiovascular diseases, chronic kidney disease etc [<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p><bold>What are the situations promoting oxidative stress?</bold> about our subject, it is known that oxidative stress is triggered by a wide variety of viral infections [<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] including HIV 1, viral hepatitis B,C,D viruses, herpes viruses, respiratory viruses, most of the RNA viruses [<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] probably also corona viruses belonging to this family. Let us remind that corona viruses are encapsulated RNA viruses with different types: the classic coronaviruses, responsible for moderate respiratory infections in general, the SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV involved in epidemics of more severe respiratory infections [<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] and the new coronavirus (SARS-CoV2) discovered in January 2020 responsible for infectious disease called COVID-19 which is currently experiencing a worldwide outbreak [<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Generally, viral infections lead to an increase in production of free radicals and a depletion of antioxidants [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. The mode of action varies according to the viruses as demonstrated by the analysis of the oxidative stress induced by different viruses of the flaviviridae family [<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] but we find these two phenomena increasing the oxidative stress in these RNA viruses infections and for Ivanov [<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] one of the sources of production of these ROS could be the mitochondrial dysfunction caused by the penetration of the virus into the cell. A &#x0201c;cytokine storm&#x0201d; with release of Il-2, Il-6, Il-7, TNF &#x003b1; etc. as been described in COVID-19 [<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. These authors described a cytokine shock with hyperinflammation accompanied by cytopenia, hyperferritinemia, [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] which is known to generate by the Fenton reaction (Fe&#x000b2;+ + H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>&#x02192; Fe&#x000b3;+ + HO&#x0203e; + HO&#x0203e;) the production of ROS [<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In addition, cytokines and endotoxins will stimulate one of the isoforms of nitric oxide synthetase (NOs), the inducible isoform iNOs, which will stimulate the production of nitric oxide NO which will react with the superoxide ion to give the powerful oxidizing peroxynitrite radical (ONOO&#x0203e;) [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Other factors can promote the endogenous production of free radicals, such as intense physical activity, high blood pressure, tissue ischemia, the action of certain metals (lead, arsenic, cesium, mercury) counteracting the co-factors of antioxidant enzymes, notably superoxide dismutase, NADPH oxidase, myeloperoxidase which will lead to the production of the superoxide radical. Physical agents (ionizing radiation, UV), solvents, various pollutants, an anesthetic agent halotane and even paracetamol have also been incriminated in this genesis of free radicals [<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Several techniques can be used to evaluate the state of oxidative stress such as electron paramagnetic resonance, direct evaluation of oxidative stress markers such as oxidized glutathione, malonyl aldehyde, quantification of total antioxidant status etc [<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p><bold>How are these free radicals neutralized?</bold> there are multiple mechanisms to neutralize these free radicals: glutathione a natural antioxydant which has also an effect on viral replication [<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], certain vitamins such as vitamin E and C, carotenoids and polyphenol with scavenging effect, [<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] the glutathione peroxidase| glutathione reductase system allowing reduced glutathione (GSH) to bind to free radicals giving oxidized glutathione which will be regenerated into GSH through this system, super oxide dismutase (SOD) neutralizing superoxide anion (O<sub>2</sub>o&#x0203e;), catalase eliminating H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, the peroxyredoxin system that neutralizes the peroxidation of lipids, protecting them from oxidative damage. Some trace elements such as Zinc and Selenium have an anti-oxidant effect as co-factors of anti-oxidant enzymes [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p><bold>What about covid-19 and oxidative stress?</bold> SARS-CoV2, probably like other RNA viruses [<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] can trigger an oxidative stress. This hypothesis can easily be checked by the dosage of oxidative stress markers [<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] in the blood of sick people of COVID-19. A cytokin storm with hyper inflammation had been found in these patients [<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] but researchers should also chek for a possible oxidative storm with all he deleterious effects of RONS, notably lipid peroxydation and proteins oxidation of membranes which can contribute to the transformation, hyalinization of pulmonary alveolar membranes [<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] with letal respiratory distress. As elders and people suffering of diabetes, hypertension and cardiovascular diseases have already a state of oxidative stress [<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], viral infection will increasae this stress, giving us one possible explanation of the severity of COVID-19 in these categories of patients [<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><p><bold>Suggestions for prevention and treatment of covid-19 infection:</bold> in frail people, we propose to reduce their level of oxidative stress by providing them with substances that increase their antioxidant system [<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] such as Glutathione, some trace elements like Zinc and Selenium, vitamin E and C, carotenoids and polyphenols [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Glutathione has analogues and precursors such as N acetyl cysteine. Indeed, cysteine is one of the three constituent amino acids of the major natural antioxidant Glutathione which also has an immunomodulating effect and destructive action on viruses such as herpes, influenza etc. by blocking viral replication [<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. There are also many antioxidants food, and even food additives such as butylated hydroxyanisole, quercetin and curcumin [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] could also be tested. In sick people, in addition to the various used treatments, we suggest to add antioxidants mentionned above and especially, injectable N acetyl cysteine [<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] which has shown its effectiveness in hemorrhagic dengue fever [<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] another RNA virus infection [<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Various antioxidant which have been experimentally used successfully as melatonin, minocycline [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], can also be tested.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec2"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In the fight against Covid-19 infection, all the possible treatments deserve to be taken into account. Relying on the complex pathophysiology of this viral infection, we suggest tu use also antioxydants agents in the treatment.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></body><back><sec><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>Marie-Pierrette Ntyonga-Pono did the review of literature and wrote the article. The author have read and agreed to the final manuscript.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Camini</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Caetano</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>De Brito Magalh&#x000e3;es</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Implications of Oxidative Stress on Viral Pathogenesis</article-title><source>Arch Virol</source><year>2017</year><volume>162</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>907</fpage><lpage>917</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28039563</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liguori</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Curcio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Aran</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Della-Morte</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oxidative stress, aging, and diseases</article-title><source>Clinical Interventions in Aging</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29731617</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yaribeygi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sathyapalan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkin</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahebkar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular Mechanisms Linking Oxidative Stress and Diabetes Mellitus</article-title><source>Oxid Med Cell Longev</source><year>2020</year><volume>2020</volume><fpage>8609213</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32215179</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Rong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flaviviridae Viruses and Oxidative Stress: Implications for Viral Pathogenesis</article-title><source>Oxid Med Cell Longev</source><year>2019</year><volume>2019</volume><fpage>1409582</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31531178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>FMPMC-PS</collab></person-group><source>Chapitre 8 - Les virus respiratoires - 2<sup>&#x000e8;me</sup> partie. Les virus des oreillons, de la rougeole, de la rub&#x000e9;ole</source><comment>Accessed on April 3rd 2020.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Public Health France</collab></person-group><source>Infection with the new Coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2), COVID-19, France and World</source><comment>Accessed on April 14th 2020.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Valuev-Elliston</surname><given-names>VT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanova</surname><given-names>ON</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotchetkov</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Starodubova</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartoschsch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oxidative Stress during HIV Infection: Mechanisms and Consequences</article-title><source>Oxid Med Cell Longev</source><year>2016</year><volume>2016</volume><fpage>8910396</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27829986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bensakhria</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Oxidative stress, In General Toxicology-Oxidative Stress</source><year>2018</year><comment>Accessed on March, 25th 2020.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McAuley</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tattersall</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Manson</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COVID-19: consider cytokine storm syndromes and immunosuppression</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2020</year><month>3</month><day>28</day><volume>395</volume><issue>10229</issue><fpage>1033</fpage><lpage>1034</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32192578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fraternale</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Paoletti</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Casabianca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nencioni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Garaci</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal>Palamara AT et al.</etal></person-group><article-title>GSH and analogs in antiviral therapy</article-title><source>Molecular Aspects of Medicine</source><year>2009</year><volume>30</volume><issue>1-2</issue><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18926849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pathological findings of COVID-19 associated with acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title><source>The Lancet Respiratory Medicine</source><year>2020</year><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>420</fpage><lpage>422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32085846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical course and risk factors for mortality of adult inpatients with COVID-19 in Wuhan, China: a retrospective cohort study</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2020</year><month>3</month><day>28</day><volume>395</volume><issue>10229</issue><fpage>1054</fpage><lpage>1062</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32171076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manoj</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranasinghe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ragunathan</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Utilisation r&#x000e9;ussie de la N-ac&#x000e9;tyl cyst&#x000e9;ine et du facteur VII recombinant activ&#x000e9; en cas d&#x02019;insuffisance h&#x000e9;patique fulgurante et d&#x02019;h&#x000e9;morragie massive secondaire &#x000e0; la fi&#x000e8;vre h&#x000e9;morragique de la dengue</article-title><source>J Emerg Trauma Shock</source><year>2014</year><volume>47</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>315</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>