<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Nestling house finches, sparrows and other nestling passerines amplify the virus during the spring [
 <xref rid="B140-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>,
 <xref rid="B151-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">151</xref>,
 <xref rid="B152-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>,
 <xref rid="B153-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>]. The means by which the virus enters this amplification cycle remains unclear; studies in Texas and Colorado indicate that nestling passerines become infected before 
 <italic>Cx. tarsalis,</italic> thus implicating some unknown sylvatic vector [
 <xref rid="B152-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>,
 <xref rid="B153-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>], though, initial amplification in nestling passerines as a means of emergence is not found in all regions [
 <xref rid="B140-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>]. Furthermore, in the northern latitudes WEEV has been found actively circulating in snowshoe hares and ground squirrels before 
 <italic>Cx. tarsalis</italic> terminates diapause indicating a sylvatic transmission cycle precedes the springtime amplification, possibly vectored by mosquito belonging to the 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> genus or 
 <italic>Cs. inornata</italic> species [
 <xref rid="B154-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">154</xref>,
 <xref rid="B155-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>,
 <xref rid="B156-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>,
 <xref rid="B157-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>,
 <xref rid="B158-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>]. Adult passerines play a greater role in transmission during the summer. Additionally, domestic Galliformes (chickens) and Columbiformes (doves) may contribute to virus maintenance and amplification, though their ability to amplify the virus is dependent on their age, which makes them poor hosts [
 <xref rid="B140-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>,
 <xref rid="B153-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>]. Human and equine incidental infections are identified during the summer after transmission exceeds some undefined minimum threshold. Other ornithophilic mosquitoes may also participate in transmission, though their significance to virus maintenance is limited due to them being poor vectors [
 <xref rid="B139-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>]. As the year persists, the feeding pattern of 
 <italic>Cx. tarsalis</italic> becomes increasingly catholic. As the season progresses, virus transmission can spill over into an 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> spp.-mammal cycle. WEEV infections begin to subside in the colder fall months with concurrent lower detection rates in 
 <italic>Cx. tarsalis</italic> as they begin to die off for the year [
 <xref rid="B139-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">139</xref>,
 <xref rid="B158-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>,
 <xref rid="B159-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>,
 <xref rid="B160-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>]. Usually few infections occur after October [
 <xref rid="B140-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>,
 <xref rid="B143-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">143</xref>]. The mechanism by which WEEV overwinters remains cryptic. Significant work has been undertaken to determine potential overwintering mechanisms; however, no firm conclusions could be made [
 <xref rid="B149-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>,
 <xref rid="B161-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>,
 <xref rid="B162-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>,
 <xref rid="B163-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">163</xref>,
 <xref rid="B164-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>,
 <xref rid="B165-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>,
 <xref rid="B166-microorganisms-08-01167" ref-type="bibr">166</xref>].
</p>
