<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Currently, influenza is regarded predominantly as a respiratory illness, but before the last century a far broader conceptualisation existed. As early as a 1732 epidemic, clinicians made note of the nervous sequelae of infection, with manifestations including neurasthenia, melancholy, hysteria, mental prostration, and insanity (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). According to the historian of medicine Mark Honigsbaum: “in the mid-1890s British medical journals were full of tales of Victorian professionals driven to the brink of madness and beyond by the nervous sequelae of influenza… for some 30 years, from the first epidemics of Russian influenza in the 1890s through to the ‘Spanish’ influenza of 1918–19, the ‘psychoses of influenza' were a widely recognised psychiatric phenomenon” (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). In 1919, Karl Menninger published a now-classic paper reporting the characteristics of 100 patients with mental disturbances associated with influenza infection admitted in a 3-month period to the Boston Psychopathic Hospital. Of 80 on whom full data were available, 16 were diagnosed with delirium, 25 with “dementia praecox,” 23 with “other psychoses,” and 16 were unclassified (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Interestingly, two-thirds of the “dementia praecox” patients were reported to have fully recovered at 5-year follow up (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). A further historically important strand of evidence came from von Economo's (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) research on encephalitis lethargica (EL), a still poorly understood inflammatory CNS condition featuring psychotic and catatonic symptoms, which was broadly contemporaneous with and potentially aetiologically related to the 1918-1919 Spanish influenza pandemic. 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">
  <bold>Table 1</bold>
 </xref> provides an overview of historical influenza pandemics that have been linked to the occurrence of psychosis.
</p>
