<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="chapter-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><?noissn?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">978-3-319-30012-2</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-30012-2</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Electrophysiology </journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Electrophysiology </journal-title><journal-subtitle>Basics, Modern Approaches and Applications</journal-subtitle></journal-title-group><isbn publication-format="print">978-3-319-30011-5</isbn><isbn publication-format="electronic">978-3-319-30012-2</isbn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7123767</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-30012-2_8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Examples of Applications of Electrophysiology</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Rettinger</surname><given-names>J&#x000fc;rgen</given-names></name><address><email>rettinger@multichannelsystems.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>Silvia</given-names></name><address><email>silvia_schwarz@online.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>Wolfgang</given-names></name><address><email>schwarz@biophysik.org</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Multi Channel Systems GmbH, Aspenhaustra&#x000df;e 21, 72770 Reutlingen, Baden-W&#x000fc;rttemberg Germany </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8547.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000101252443</institution-id><institution>Shanghai Research Center for Acupuncture and Meridians, Shanghai Key Laboratory for Acupuncture Mechanism and Acupoint Function, </institution><institution>Fudan University, </institution></institution-wrap>Guoshoujing Rd. 199, 201203 Shanghai-Pudong, China </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7839.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000419369721</institution-id><institution>Institut f&#x000fc;r Biophysik, </institution><institution>Goethe-Universit&#x000e4;t Frankfurt, </institution></institution-wrap>60438 Frankfurt am Main, Hessen Germany </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>06</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Springer International Publishing Switzerland 2016</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This article is made available via the PMC Open Access Subset for unrestricted research re-use and secondary analysis in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for the duration of the World Health Organization (WHO) declaration of COVID-19 as a global pandemic.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p>All the techniques that we have discussed, flux measurements, steady-state and transient current measurements, as well as single-channel recordings and the corresponding analysis can be applied to the analysis of structure-function relationships. Such structure-function information can be obtained if we characterize and compare the function of wild-type and chemically or genetically modified transporters by using these techniques. The latter also includes naturally occurring mutations that are the source of various diseases; this is an important feature for the understanding and curing of such diseases.</p><p>For many of the transporters the amino acid sequence and the possible orientation of the protein in the membrane, or even the three-dimensional structures have been determined. In this chapter on Examples of Applications of Electrophysiology, we will illustrate the strategy of an electrophysiologist in investigating structure, function and regulation of membrane transport using as an example the Na<sup>+</sup>,K<sup>+</sup>-ATPase, the neurotransmitter transporter GAT (Na<sup>+</sup>-dependent GABA transporter), and the nucleotide receptors that form channels in the presence of extracellular ATP.</p><p>For an understanding of drug action as well as the development of new drugs for the treatment of diseases, electrophysiology is a powerful method to elucidate drug receptor interaction. As an example, this will be illustrated for viral ion channels that are essential for virus reproduction.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Antiviral Drug</kwd><kwd>Gaba Transporter</kwd><kwd>Nucleotide Receptor</kwd><kwd>Neurotransmitter Transporter</kwd><kwd>Large Extracellular Loop</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer International Publishing Switzerland 2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>All the techniques that we have discussed, flux measurements, steady-state and transient current measurements, as well as single-channel recordings and the corresponding analysis can be applied to the analysis of structure-function relationships. Such structure-function information can be obtained if we characterize and compare the function of wild-type and chemically or genetically modified transporters by using these techniques. The latter also includes naturally occurring mutations that are the source of various diseases; this is an important feature for the understanding and curing of such diseases.</p><p>For many of the transporters the amino acid sequence and the possible orientation of the protein in the membrane, or even the three-dimensional structures have been determined. In the following, we will illustrate the strategy of an electrophysiologist in investigating structure, function and regulation of membrane transport using as an example the Na<sup>+</sup>,K<sup>+</sup>-ATPase (Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">8.1</xref>), the neurotransmitter
transporter GAT (Na<sup>+</sup>-dependent GABA transporter; Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">8.4</xref>; Sect.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Sec1" ref-type="sec">8.1</xref>), and the nucleotide receptors (Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">8.6</xref>) that form channels in the presence of extracellular ATP (Sect.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Sec3" ref-type="sec">8.2</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.1</label><caption><p>Amino acid sequence of the Na<sup>+</sup>,K<sup>+</sup> ATPase. (Based on Vasilets and Schwarz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">1993</xref>)
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e358"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.2</label><caption><p>&#x0201c;Dentist&#x02019;s&#x0201d; presentation of the Na<sup>+</sup>,K<sup>+</sup>-ATPase</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e374"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.3a,b</label><caption><p>PTX -induced current in wild-type (<bold>a</bold>) and truncated mutants (<bold>b</bold>) without N-terminal peptide, (<bold>c</bold>) with the peptide added to the internal solution (based on Wu et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2003</xref>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e400"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.4</label><caption><p>Amino acid sequence of mouse GAT1
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e420"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.5</label><caption><p>Effect of mutation of glycosylation sites (based on Liu et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">1998</xref>). The code letter for amino acids represent positions 176, 181 and 184</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e438"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.6</label><caption><p>Amino acid sequence of human P2X<sub>1</sub>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e461"/></fig>
</p><p>For an understanding of drug action as well as the development of new drugs for the treatment of diseases, electrophysiology is a powerful method to elucidate drug receptor interaction. As an example, this will be illustrated for viral ion channels (Sect.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Sec16" ref-type="sec">8.3</xref>) that are essential for virus reproduction.</p><sec id="Sec1"><title>Structure-Function Relationships of Carrier Proteins</title><sec id="Sec2"><title>The Na<sup>+</sup>,K<sup>+</sup>-ATPase</title><p>The Na<sup>+</sup>,K<sup>+</sup>-ATPase (for a review, see [Vasilets and Schwarz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">1993</xref>]) is a heterodimer composed of an &#x003b1; subunit of about 100&#x02009;kDa and a smaller glycosylated &#x003b2; subunit of about 60&#x02009;kDa (see Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">8.1</xref>). At least four isoforms of the <italic>&#x003b1;</italic> subunit have been identified, and three isoforms of the <italic>&#x000df;</italic> subunit that all show tissue-specific distribution. The <italic>&#x003b1;</italic> subunits host all functionally significant sites including ATP-binding and phosphorylation sites, the sites for interaction with the transported cations and for specific inhibitors like cardiotonic steroids, and the binding site for palytoxin (see Sect.&#x0202f;10.1007/978-3-319-30012-2_7) .</p><p>Measurements of the electrogenic current generated by the Na<sup>+</sup>,K<sup>+</sup> pump confirm that mutation of Q<sub>118</sub> and N<sub>129</sub> to the charged residues R and D<italic>,</italic> respectively, causes insensitivity of the ATPase to the cardiac glycoside Ouabain. The <italic>&#x000df;</italic>&#x000a0;subunit is necessary for proper folding of the <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>&#x000a0;subunit and for assembly and proper insertion of the entire protein into the cell membrane. The combination of an <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>&#x000a0;subunit with different <italic>&#x000df;</italic>&#x000a0;subunits results in a different function and, therefore, a regulatory role of the <italic>&#x000df;</italic>&#x000a0;subunit has been discussed. In addition, a &#x003b3;&#x000a0;subunit has been identified, which also seems to have a regulatory function. One option to monitor modulation of the ion transport is the measurement of a pump-mediated current under voltage clamp.</p><p>In the <italic>&#x003b1;</italic> subunit of the Na<sup>+</sup>,K<sup>+</sup>-ATPase
several negatively charged amino acids can be localized in intramembraneous domains (Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">8.1</xref>) that may be involved in interaction with the transported cations. Mutation of some of these amino acids to Ala indeed alters the apparent dielectric length of the access channel that is represented by the effective valencies&#x000a0;<italic>z</italic>
(see, e.&#x02009;g. glutamate 334 and 960 in Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">8.2</xref>).</p><p>The N-terminus is the area, which shows the highest degree of diversity among the different isoforms of the <italic>&#x003b1;</italic> subunits, and may, therefore, account for isoform-specific function in different tissue. In fact, mutations (like truncation as illustrated in Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">8.2</xref>) or chemical modifications (by, e.&#x02009;g. regulatory phosphorylation, see Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">8.1</xref>) within the N-terminus leads to altered transport function including external cation interaction and external binding of the specific inhibitor Ouabain. It is interesting to mention that the highly flexible, cytoplasmic N-terminus interferes with the external interactions. This finding is an example illustrating the allosteric interaction within the complex protein structure.</p><p>We have described above (Sect.&#x0202f;10.1007/978-3-319-30012-2_7) that palytoxin transfers the Na<sup>+</sup>,K<sup>+</sup> pump into a channel. During long-lasting voltage-clamp pulses the palytoxin-induced current inactivates at very positive potentials (Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">8.3a</xref>).</p><p>Inactivation at positive potentials of Na<sup>+</sup> and K<sup>+</sup> channels has been ascribed to a positively charged ball at the N-terminus blocking the internal channel mouth (bal at a chain), which leads to an inward-rectifying steady-state IV relationship (cf., e.&#x02009;g. also Sect.&#x0202f;10.1007/978-3-319-30012-2_5). A similar interpretation has been suggested for the PTX -modified Na<sup>+</sup>,K<sup>+</sup> pump. Indeed, the truncated mutant does not show inactivation anymore (Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">8.3b</xref>), while application of the truncated N-terminal peptide restores inactivation (Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">8.3c</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>The Na-Dependent GABA Transporter (GAT1)</title><p>The activity of neurotransmitter transporters plays an important role in termination of synaptic transmission. Therefore, a detailed knowledge of structure-function relationships is essential for understanding the physiology, pathophysiology and pharmacology of brain function. We have already mentioned the importance of regulatory phosphorylation of the Na<sup>+</sup>,K<sup>+</sup> pump by protein kinases, and this is also the case for neurotransmitter transporters. The strategy for identification of such sites is the same as described for the Na<sup>+</sup>,K<sup>+</sup> pump. Possible candidates for phosphorylation
of GAT1 (see Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">8.4</xref>) have been mutated; the mutants are then functionally characterized and compared with the wild-type transporter. Again, transporter-mediated current can serve as a measure for transport activity.</p><p>More recently, also glycosylation
has been proposed to be involved in regulation of the transport function. Mutations in the glycosylation sites (see N<sub>176</sub>, N<sub>181</sub>, N<sub>184</sub> in Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">8.4</xref>) indeed lead to altered transport. The example illustrated in Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">8.5</xref> shows that mutation of two of the three asparagines (N) to aspartic acid (D) leads to reduced sensitivity for extracellular Na<sup>+</sup>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Structure-Function Relationships of Ion Channels</title><p>Ion
channels are classified due to their diverse modes of function or molecular structure. This can be ion selectivity, modes of gating, number of subunits comprising the functional channel, number of transmembrane domains or sequence homologies. Classically, ion channels are divided into major families having important properties in common like gating mechanisms and ion selectivity. Some of the families will be briefly presented in the next paragraphs.</p><sec id="Sec5"><title>Families of Various Ion Channels</title><sec id="Sec6"><title>The Voltage-Gated Ion Channel (VIC) Superfamily</title><p>Although
some members of this family are in addition controlled by ligand binding, their activity is generally controlled by the transmembrane electrical field. Functionally characterized members are selectively permeable for K<sup>+</sup>, Na<sup>+</sup>, or Ca<sup>2+</sup> ions. Members of the VIC family play a role in the generation of action potentials and modulation of excitability of cells.</p><p>The K<sup>+</sup> channels usually consist of homotetrameric structures with each subunit possessing six transmembrane domains (see also Fig.&#x0202f;10.1007/978-3-319-30012-2_6). At least ten types of K<sup>+</sup> channels are known , each responding in different ways to different stimuli: voltage-sensitive (Ka, Kv, Kvr, Kvs and Ksr), Ca<sup>2+</sup>-sensitive (BKCa, IKCa and SKCa) and receptor-coupled channels (KM and KACh). There are also tetrameric channels in which each subunit possesses two transmembrane (TM) domains that are homologous to TM-domains&#x000a0;5 and 6 of the six TM-domain types (inward rectifier Kir).</p><p>The &#x003b1; subunits of the Ca<sup>2+</sup> and Na<sup>+</sup> channels are about four times as large as the K<sup>+</sup>-channel subunits and possess four sequence repeats, with each repeat being homologous to the single subunit in the homotetrameric K<sup>+</sup> channels (compare Fig.&#x0202f;10.1007/978-3-319-30012-2_6 and 10.1007/978-3-319-30012-2_6). There are five types of Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels (L, N, P, Q and T), and at least six types of Na<sup>+</sup> channels (I, II, III, &#x000b5;1, H1 and PN3).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>The Ligand-Gated Ion Channel (LIC) Family</title><p>Members
of the LIC family of ionotropic neurotransmitter
receptors are activated by acetylcholine, serotonin, glycine, glutamate or &#x003b3;-aminobutyric acid (GABA). All of these receptor channels are homo- or heteromers of three, four or five subunits. The best characterized ones are the nicotinic acetylcholine receptors, which are pentameric channels of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>
<sub><italic>2</italic></sub>
<italic>&#x003b2;&#x003b3;&#x003b4;</italic> subunit composition. Channels of the LIC family are selective for cations or anions (e.&#x02009;g. the acetylcholine receptors are cation-selective, while glycine receptors are anion-selective).</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>The Chloride Channel (ClC) Family</title><p>The
large ClC family consists of dozens of sequenced proteins derived from bacteria, plants and animals. These proteins exhibit 10&#x02013;12 putative transmembrane <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-helical domains and appear to be present in the membrane as homodimers. While one member of the family, <italic>Torpedo</italic>
ClC-O, has been reported to have two channels, one per subunit, others are believed to have just one. All functionally characterized members of the ClC family are permeable for Cl<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, some of them are voltage-dependent. These channels are involved in a variety of physiological functions (cell volume regulation, membrane potential stabilization, signal transduction, transepithelial transport, etc.). Different homologues exhibit different anion selectivities, i.&#x02009;e. ClC4 and ClC5 share an NO<sub>3</sub>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;Cl<sup>&#x02212;</sup>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;Br<sup>&#x02212;</sup>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;I<sup>&#x02212;</sup> conductance sequence, while ClC3 has an I<sup>&#x02212;</sup>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;Cl<sup>&#x02212;</sup> selectivity. ClC4 and ClC5 channels exhibit outward rectifying currents with currents only at voltages more positive than +20&#x02009;mV.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>The Gap Junction-Forming (Connexin) Family</title><p>Gap
junctions consist of clusters of closely packed pairs of transmembrane channels in adjacent cells, the connexons, through which small molecules diffuse between neighbouring cells. The connexons consist of homo- or heterohexameric arrays of connexins, and the connexon in one plasma membrane docks end-to-end with a connexon in the membrane of a closely opposed cell. Over 15 connexin subunit isoforms are known. They vary in size between about 25 and 60&#x02009;kDa. They have four putative transmembrane <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-helical domains. A dodecameric channel is formed by two hexamers, and therefore, consists of 48 transmembrane domains in total.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>The Epithelial Na<sup>+</sup> Channel (ENaC) Family</title><p>The
ENaC family consists of more than 20 sequenced proteins exclusively from animals. There exist voltage-insensitive ENaC homologues in the brain. Some of these proteins are involved in touch sensitivity; other members of the ENaC family, the acid-sensing Na<sup>+</sup> channels
(H<sup>+</sup>-gated), ASIC1-3, mediate pain sensation in response to tissue acidosis. The (FMRF-amide)-activated Na<sup>+</sup> channel
is the first peptide neurotransmitter-gated ionotropic receptor that was sequenced. All members of this family exhibit a topology with intracellular N- and C-termini, two transmembrane spanning segments, and a large extracellular loop. Three homologous ENaC subunits, <italic>&#x003b1;, &#x003b2;</italic> and <italic>&#x003b3;</italic>, have been shown to assemble to form the highly Na<sup>+</sup>-selective channel with the stoichiometry <italic>&#x003b1;&#x003b2;&#x003b3;</italic> in a heterotrimeric architecture.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Mechanosensitive Ion Channels</title><p>Another interesting group of ion channel
s are those that are gated by mechanical stress, allowing transduction of mechanical forces into electrical signals (see, e.&#x02009;g. Delmas and Coste <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2013</xref>; Ranade et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2015</xref>). In particular, the patch-clamp technique of applying mechanical or osmotic stress to a cell and recording electrical responses reveals a continuously growing number of mechanosensitive or stretch-activated (SAC) ion channels (Nilius and Honor&#x000e9; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2012</xref>). A class of mechanosensitive channels that was conserved throughout evolution is formed by the Piezo channels (Bagriantsev et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2014</xref>). Another large class of ion channels sensitive to physical stimuli is formed by the transient receptor potential (TRP) channels (Christensen and Corey <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2007</xref>).</p><p>Mechanosensitive channels are involved in all kinds of mechanosensation, including, e.&#x02009;g. touch sensation, hearing or regulation of the tone of smooth muscle fibres. The transfer from an open to a closed configuration can be governed by mechanical forces on the membrane protein via the lipid bilayer or via tethered cytoskeletal or extracellular structures.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>ATP-Gated Cation Channel (ACC) Family</title><p>In
the following, we will present the strategy how electrophysiology can be utilized to learn about structure-function relationships of ion channels. As an example, we will use ATP-gated ion channels and focus on members of the P2X receptor family.</p><sec id="Sec13"><title>Structure and Classification of P2X Receptors</title><p>The relatively new class of ATP-gated ion channels, which belongs to the group of ligand-gated ion channels, will be described in more detail since, we will use members of this group as our last example for application of electrophysiological techniques in analysis of structure-function relationships.</p><p>Because the common feature of these channels is the sensitivity to extracellular ATP, they are termed nucleotide receptors. Another commonly used name is P2X receptors, and formerly they were known under the name purinoceptors . Although it was already proposed in 1972 that ATP plays a functional role as a neurotransmitter, it took until 1994 for the first two isoforms P2X<sub>1</sub> and P2X<sub>2</sub> to be cloned from rat vas deferens and PC12 cells, respectively.</p><p>From hydropathy analysis, a now commonly accepted secondary structure with intracellular N- and C-termini, a large extracellular loop and two transmembrane domains were derived (see Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">8.6</xref>), which resemble the architecture of the ENaC family. As is also known from other ion channel proteins, the functional channel unit is composed of more than one subunit. A quaternary structure of three subunits forming the functional receptor has been published (Nicke et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1000">1998</xref>); a stoichiometry that is different from what is known for other ligand-gated ion channels that are usually composed from tetramers or pentamers.</p><p>Nowadays, seven isoforms (Table&#x0202f;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">8.1</xref>) and various splice variants are known, which have more or less different pharmacological and functional properties (Burnstock <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">1999</xref>). Since all of the seven isoforms are ionotropic ion channels (meaning that receptor and channel function are localized on the same protein multimer), electrophysiology is the method of choice to characterize their functional properties.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;8.1</label><caption><p>Comparison of the known P2X subtypes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>P2X<sub>1</sub>
</th><th>P2X<sub>2</sub>
</th><th>P2X<sub>3</sub>
</th><th>P2X<sub>4</sub>
</th><th>P2X<sub>5</sub>
</th><th>P2X<sub>6</sub>
</th><th>P2X<sub>7</sub>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-methylene-ATP</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02212;</td><td>+</td><td>&#x02212;</td><td>&#x02212;</td><td>&#x02212;</td><td>&#x02212;</td></tr><tr><td>Desensitization</td><td><p>Fast &#x00026;</p><p>complete</p></td><td><p>Slow &#x00026;</p><p>incompl.</p></td><td><p>Fast &#x00026;</p><p>complete</p></td><td><p>Middle &#x00026;</p><p>incompl.</p></td><td><p>Slow &#x00026;</p><p>incompl.</p></td><td><p>Slow &#x00026;</p><p>incompl.</p></td><td><p>Slow &#x00026;</p><p>incompl.</p></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p>Before we introduce some of the electrophysiological data obtained for the P2X<sub>1</sub> and P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor, we give a short overview of the most evident differences between the subtypes. Although extracellular ATP is able to activate each of the ATP receptors, the ATP derivative <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-<italic>&#x000df;</italic>-methylene-ATP is an agonist only for P2X<sub>1</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub>. More or less pronounced desensitization is obtained for all P2X receptors subtypes, which means that the agonist induces an opening of the ion channels, but then channels close even in the presence of the agonist.</p><p>Fast inactivation within about a second has been found for P2X<sub>1</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub>, and slightly slower for the P2X<sub>4</sub> receptors, whereas the other subtypes desensitize only slowly and incompletely. A special feature of the P2X<sub>7</sub> receptor is the formation of a large pore with a diameter of 3&#x02013;5&#x02009;nm after prolonged application of the agonist. Similar behaviour, where at least the ion selectivity changes after prolonged activation, is also discussed for the other subtypes.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Experimental Results</title><p>In the following paragraphs we will present some results on the functional properties of the P2X<sub>1</sub>, and P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor. Although analysis of single-channel activity can provide the most valuable insight into ion-channel characteristics, it is sometimes difficult to detect single channel events depending on single-channel conductance, gating behaviour and channel density. In the case of the P2X receptors, mainly macroscopic currents have been analyzed either due to fast desensitization (P2X<sub>1</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub>) or due to fast gating (flickering) of the P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors (Ding and Sachs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">1999</xref>). Figure&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">8.7</xref> shows a current trace of the P2X<sub>1</sub> receptor in an outside-out oocyte-membrane patch. It is only at the end of the trace that current fluctuations caused by the opening and closing of the channels can be resolved.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.7</label><caption><p>Current trace of the P2X<sub>1</sub> receptor in an outside-out oocyte-membrane patch at a holding potential of &#x02212;60&#x02009;mV with superimposition of several single-channel events</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e1325"/></fig>
</p><p>The data shown in the following were recorded by the two-electrode voltage-clamp (TEVC) technique (Sect.&#x0202f;10.1007/978-3-319-30012-2_3 (<italic>The Two-Microelectrode Voltage Clamp</italic>)) with <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes (Sect.&#x0202f;10.1007/978-3-319-30012-2_7). Therefore, the currents represent simultaneous activity of a huge number of ion channels (millions) leading to currents in the &#x000b5;A-range. <italic>Xenopus</italic>
oocytes do not possess endogenous nucleotide receptors and are, therefore, an ideal tool for studying these channels after injection of the appropriate cRNAs.</p><p>Since P2X<sub>1</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors show fast activation and desensitization (within 1&#x02009;s), a fast and well-defined solution exchange is a prerequisite for correctly time-resolved measurements. Due to the large size of the oocyte (with a diameter of 1.2&#x02009;mm) a fast solution exchange is not easy to achieve, but is possible with a special design: a solution exchange system where the oocyte is placed in a small oocyte chamber of about 10&#x02009;&#x000b5;l volume in combination with fast perfusion (200&#x02009;&#x000b5;l/s). This design allows an exchange time (5&#x02013;95&#x02009;%) in the range of 100&#x02013;200&#x02009;ms. This can be determined, for example, by activating expressed nicotinic acetylcholine receptors with 30&#x02009;&#x000b5;M acetylcholine (ACh) or by monitoring the current change induced by a concentration change from Na<sup>+</sup>-rich to Na<sup>+</sup>-deficient solution (Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8.8</xref>). The reproducibility of the solution change is obvious in Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8.8</xref>(a) where seven consecutive responses to application of ACh at 1&#x02009;min intervals are shown.<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.8a,b</label><caption><p>Time course of solution exchange with nAChR-mediated currents (<bold>a</bold>) and with endogenous Na<sup>+</sup> conductance of the oocytes (<bold>b</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig8_HTML" id="d29e1403"/></fig>
</p><p>Although the exchange time of 100&#x02013;200&#x02009;ms is fast with respect to the large size of the oocyte, one should keep in mind that the currents that are elicited by a solution exchange (for example, ATP application to P2X receptors) are greatly influenced by the concentration change that occurs during the first 200&#x02009;ms. A significantly faster solution change in intact oocytes will be difficult to achieve, and if this becomes necessary, one has to use the cell-free patch-clamp method (Sects.&#x0202f;10.1007/978-3-319-30012-2_3 and 10.1007/978-3-319-30012-2_3), which allows for exchange times even in the sub-millisecond range.</p><sec id="Sec15"><title>The P2X<sub>1</sub> Receptor</title><p>As already mentioned, the P2X<sub>1</sub> receptor is a fast desensitizing receptor that opens an intrinsic ion channel that is non-selectively permeable for small cations when challenged with extracellular ATP. Figure&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">8.9</xref> shows the current in response to 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;M ATP for the first application of ATP (peak in Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">8.9a</xref>) and for consecutive ATP applications at 5-minute intervals and a holding potential of &#x02212;60&#x02009;mV.<fig id="Fig9"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.9</label><caption><p>P2X<sub>1</sub> receptor
currents activated with 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;M ATP at 5&#x02009;min intervals at a holding potential of &#x02212;60&#x02009;mV</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig9_HTML" id="d29e1455"/></fig>
</p><p>The receptor desensitizes in the presence of ATP completely within about 1&#x02009;s. After a period of 5&#x02009;min in ATP-free solution, typically only about 25&#x02009;% of the initial receptor current can be restored. This means that desensitization is fast but the recovery from the desensitized state is slow. As a matter of fact, tens of minutes are necessary to restore the full initial current response. The response of the P2X<sub>1</sub> receptors is dependent on the extracellular ATP concentration with an EC<sub>50</sub> value (the concentration that is needed for half-maximum response) of about 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;M.</p><p>Figure&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">8.10</xref> shows a typical experiment for determination of the EC<sub>50</sub> value by activating the receptors with different ATP concentrations in the range 0.03&#x02013;30&#x02009;&#x000b5;M. Figure&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">8.10b</xref> shows the dose-response curve of the receptor for ATP.<fig id="Fig10"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.10a,b</label><caption><p>P2X<sub>1</sub> receptor
currents activated with different ATP concentrations (<bold>a</bold>) and the ATP dose-response curve (<bold>b</bold>); EC<sub>50</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.6&#x02009;&#x000b5;M. Receptors were expressed in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes after RNA-injection</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig10_HTML" id="d29e1510"/></fig>
</p><p>Since the P2X<sub>1</sub> receptor shows fast activation after application of extracellular ATP, it is interesting to compare the signals that can be measured with the TEVC and the patch-clamp method. Figure&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">8.11a</xref> shows the current trace from an intact oocyte Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">8.11b</xref> that from an excised outside-out patch. In both cases the channels are activated by 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;M ATP.<fig id="Fig11"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.11a,b</label><caption><p>Comparison of P2X<sub>1</sub>-generated current activated by 1&#x02009;&#x000b5;M ATP in TEVC (<bold>a</bold>) and an outside out macro-patch (<bold>b</bold>) at a holding potential of &#x02212;60&#x02009;mV</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig11_HTML" id="d29e1540"/></fig>
</p><p>This comparison demonstrates that onset as well as offset of the current are significantly different for both methods. This difference can be explained by the difference in speed of solution exchange that was complete within 2&#x02009;ms by using the patch-clamp method, and hence two orders of magnitude faster than for the TEVC. Nevertheless, the TEVC method is commonly used, also for the analysis of fast receptor currents, but one should be careful with the quantitative interpretation of the data.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>The P2X<sub>2</sub> Receptor</title><p>As an example for a nearly non-desensitizing P2X receptor we introduce the P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor, which, like all members of the P2X family, opens an intrinsic ion channel after extracellular application of an appropriate agonist. Analogous to the P2X<sub>1</sub> receptor, Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">8.12a</xref> shows P2X<sub>2</sub> currents activated by different ATP concentrations and Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">8.12b</xref> the corresponding dose-response curve with an EC<sub>50</sub> value of about 30&#x02009;&#x000b5;M.<fig id="Fig12"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.12a,b</label><caption><p>P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor
currents activated with different ATP concentrations (<bold>a</bold>) and the ATP dose-response curve (<bold>b</bold>); EC<sub>50</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;29&#x02009;&#x000b5;M, <italic>HP</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;60&#x02009;mV</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig12_HTML" id="d29e1615"/></fig>
</p><p>After the presentation of these pharmacological data we will concentrate in the following on the use of electrophysiology in combination with biochemical methods. This combination can give answers to questions concerning the functional consequences of structural changes in the channel protein.</p><p>Analysis of the amino-acid sequence of the P2X<sub>1</sub> receptor revealed the presence of five consensus sequences for putative glycosylation localized on the extracellular loop of the protein (N1&#x02013;N5, see Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">8.6</xref>). Biochemical analysis of the receptor protein (expressed in oocytes) demonstrated that four out of these five sites are used for glycosylation. A question that cannot be answered with biochemical methods is whether functional properties of the expressed receptors (ATP dependence, kinetic parameters, etc.) are changed. Therefore, different constructs at which one or several glycosylation sites were removed by mutation of single amino acids were characterized electrophysiologically in respect to their ATP dependency and the magnitude of the ATP-activated current.</p><p>The electrophysiological analysis showed that removal of the third N-glycosylation site alters the apparent affinity of the receptor for ATP by a factor of about 3. None of the other N-glycosylation sites seem to have any influence on the ATP sensitivity. Figure&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig13" ref-type="fig">8.13</xref> gives a graphical representation of these results.<fig id="Fig13"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.13a&#x02013;d</label><caption><p>P2X<sub>1</sub> receptor currents of wild-type (<bold>a</bold>), N3-mutated subunits activated by different ATP-concentrations (<bold>b</bold>), ATP dose-response curves for wild-type and mutant &#x02206;N3, respectively (<bold>c</bold>). The bar graph shows the amount of current measured at 0.3&#x02009;&#x000b5;M relative to the maximal current at 30&#x02009;&#x000b5;M; it demonstrates that all mutants lacking the N-glycan at position N3 exhibit lower affinity for ATP (<bold>d</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig13_HTML" id="d29e1659"/></fig>
</p><p>Taken together, results from the combination of molecular biology, biochemistry, and electrophysiology demonstrate that an increased number of missing glycosylation sites lead to a decrease in the surface appearance of the receptors (reflected by decreasing currents and the decreasing intensity of bands on the SDS-gel). A functional difference was only found for the constructs that were deficient of the third glycosylation site. These constructs showed the effect of decreased ATP sensitivity with an EC<sub>50</sub> value of 2&#x02009;&#x000b5;M compared to the wild-type receptor with an EC<sub>50</sub> value of 0.6&#x02009;&#x000b5;M.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Viral Ion Channels</title><p>In
this section, we will present the strategy how electrophysiology can be combined with virology and pharmacology to develop new drugs against viral infection. As example, we will use the viral ion channels as a target for antiviral drugs. An interesting source for the development of new medicines are drug components of traditional Chinese herbs. The finding of artemisinin extracted from <italic>Artemisia annua</italic> as an effective antimalarial drug by the Chinese scientist Youyou Tu (see Tu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2011</xref>) was honoured by the Nobel Prize in 2015. As a pharmacological tool, our focus will also be on drugs extracted from Chinese herbs.</p><p>The genomes of various viruses encode for proteins that may form ion-selective channels in the infected cell. These ion channels play important roles in the viral life cycle, and therefore, may represent a target for new antiviral drugs.</p><p>Table&#x0202f;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">8.2</xref> lists examples of such channels (see, also Wang et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2011</xref>; Kr&#x000fc;ger and Fischer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2009</xref>; Fischer and Sansom <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2002</xref>). The pores are formed by multi-homomers.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;8.2</label><caption><p>Examples of viruses and their viral ion channels formed by multi-homomers, each subunit consists of 1&#x02013;3 transmembrane segments (TMS)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Virus family</th><th>Virus</th><th>Ion channel</th><th>Characteristics</th><th>Functional units</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
<bold>Coronaviridae</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>SARS-CoV</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>3a</bold>
</td><td><p>
<bold>&#x02248;&#x02009;20&#x02009;pS</bold>
</p><p>
<bold>monovalent cation</bold>
</p></td><td><p>
<bold>Tetramer </bold>
</p><p>
<bold>(3&#x000a0;TMS)</bold>
</p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">
<bold>Orthomyxoviridae</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>Influenza A (swine flu)</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>M2</bold>
</td><td><p>
<bold>&#x0003c;&#x02009;fS</bold>
</p><p>
<bold>proton</bold>
</p></td><td><p>
<bold>Tetramer </bold>
</p><p>
<bold>(1&#x000a0;TMS)</bold>
</p></td></tr><tr><td>Influenza B</td><td>BM2</td><td><p>&#x0003c;&#x02009;fS</p><p>proton</p></td><td><p>Tetramer </p><p>(1&#x000a0;TMS)</p></td></tr><tr><td>Picornaviridae</td><td>Poliovirus</td><td>2B</td><td>Non-selective</td><td><p>Tetramer</p><p>(2&#x000a0;TMS)</p></td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>Retroviridae</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>HIV-1</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>Vpu</bold>
</td><td><p>
<bold>&#x02248;&#x02009;20&#x02009;pS</bold>
</p><p>
<bold>monovalent cation</bold>
</p></td><td><p>
<bold>Pentamer </bold>
</p><p>
<bold>(1&#x000a0;TMS)</bold>
</p></td></tr><tr><td>Flaviviridae</td><td>HCV (hepatitis C)</td><td>p7</td><td><p>20&#x02013;100&#x02009;pS</p><p>monovalent cation</p></td><td><p>Hexamer </p><p>(2&#x000a0;TMS)</p></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p>The viral life cycle involves a sequence of steps that actually may all form a target for antiviral drugs. As an example, Figure&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig14" ref-type="fig">8.14</xref> illustrates various steps in the life cycle of coronavirus.<fig id="Fig14"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.14</label><caption><p>Viral lifecycle of SARS CoV. Binding of viral spike protein with angiotensine-converting-enzyme-2 receptor of the host cell is followed by virus uptake, uncoating, and transcription and translation of the viral genome. After assembly of new viruses, 3a channel activity stimulates exocytotic release of the viruses from the host cell</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig14_HTML" id="d29e1929"/></fig>
</p><p>The virus attaches to the host cell, followed by incorporation of the virus, uncoating of the viral genome and replication processes with transcription and translation; finally, new viral particles are assembled, and the viruses are released from the host cell to infect new cells. In the case of coronavirus, the release is dependent on the activity of an ion channel, which is encoded by the viral genome and inserted into the membrane of the host cell. For SARS coronavirus (SARS CoV) the membrane protein is called 3a protein. Inhibition of any of these steps could represent a potential target for antiviral drugs.</p><p>In the following, we will illustrate how inhibition of ion-channel function can interfere with the viral life cycle. In Table&#x0202f;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">8.2</xref> the respective viral ion channels dealt with in this section are printed in bold.</p><sec id="Sec18"><title>The 3a Protein of the Coronavirus</title><p>For
the 3a protein of the SARS coronavirus (cf. Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig14" ref-type="fig">8.14</xref>) it was demonstrated (Lu et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2006</xref>) that tetramers form the ion channel that is incorporated into the membrane of the infected cell (see Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig15" ref-type="fig">8.15</xref>).<fig id="Fig15"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.15</label><caption><p>Fluorescence-labelled 3a protein becomes visible in infected Vero E6 cells. (Based on Lu et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2006</xref>) (<bold>a</bold>). Orientation of 3a monomer in the cell membrane (<bold>b</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig15_HTML" id="d29e1980"/></fig>
</p><p>Patch-clamp analysis (Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig16" ref-type="fig">8.16</xref>) revealed a single-channel conductance of about 20&#x02013;30&#x02009;pS. The channel is selectively permeable for monovalent cations with highest selectivity for K<sup>+</sup>. As a result of 3a channel activity the membrane potential will depolarize, which results in Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel activation. The increase in intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> activity then facilitates the exocytotic release of viruses from the host cell (Lu et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2006</xref>).<fig id="Fig16"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.16a&#x02013;c</label><caption><p>Single-channel recordings from 3a protein expressed in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes (<bold>a</bold>), histograms of the current amplitudes (<bold>b</bold>), and voltage dependence of the single-channel current (<bold>c</bold>) (based on Schwarz et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2012</xref>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig16_HTML" id="d29e2023"/></fig>
</p><p>Voltage clamping is an easy method to detect and analyze function of the viral ion channels. Again using the model system <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocyte as an expression system (cf. Sect.&#x0202f;10.1007/978-3-319-30012-2_7), drugs can be screened with respect to their interaction with the 3a protein. As a general rule, a method has to be elaborated that allows extracting the current component of interest from the total membrane current. Injection of cRNA for the 3a protein results in elevation of the membrane current that can be blocked by 10&#x02009;mM Ba<sup>2+</sup> in the extracellular medium (Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig17" ref-type="fig">8.17</xref>).<fig id="Fig17"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.17</label><caption><p>Open triangles represent current-voltage dependency in oocytes not expressing 3a protein, open and filled squares those in 3a-expressing cells in the absence and presence of 10&#x02009;mM Ba<sup>2+</sup>, respectively. (Based on data from Lu et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2006</xref>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig17_HTML" id="d29e2055"/></fig>
</p><sec id="Sec19"><title>Inhibition of 3a-Mediated Current by the Anthraquinone Emodin</title><p>During the SARS epidemic in 2003, herbal extracts were used in Asia to treat the disease supplementarily to treatment with western medicine. Among those were also extracts from <italic>Rhei radix</italic> (rhubarb), and an effective component seemed to be the phytodrug emodin (1,3,8-trihydroxy-6-methylanthracene-9,10-dione), which blocks the Ba<sup>2+</sup>-sensitive current mediated by 3a protein, but not the endogenous component (Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig18" ref-type="fig">8.18</xref>).<fig id="Fig18"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.18</label><caption><p>Voltage dependency of Ba<sup>2+</sup>-sensitive current in oocytes expressing 3a protein in the absence (<italic>open circles</italic>) and presence (<italic>filled circles</italic>) of 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;M emodin, which completely inhibits 3a-mediated current but leaves endogenous component unaffected. (Based on Schwarz et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2011</xref>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig18_HTML" id="d29e2091"/></fig>
</p><p>Emodin not only blocks 3a-mediated current, but with the same IC<sub>50</sub> value of about 20&#x02009;&#x000b5;M the number of viral RNA copies in the medium of infected cells (Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig19" ref-type="fig">8.19a</xref>). The number of RNA copies correlates with the titre (Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig19" ref-type="fig">8.19b</xref>) indicating that the RNA originates from intact viruses. This proves that emodin can act as an antiviral drug and may form the basis for the development of new drugs against coronavirus infection.<fig id="Fig19"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.19a,b</label><caption><p>Emodin-dependent inhibition of 3a-mediated current and of extracellular viral cRNA (<bold>a</bold>), and of titre concentration (<bold>b</bold>). (Based on Schwarz et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2011</xref>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig19_HTML" id="d29e2121"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Inhibition of 3a-Mediated Current by the Kaempferol Glycoside Juglanin</title><p>Other effective phytodrugs are the flavonoids, especially kaempferol glycosides. The kaempferol glycoside juglanin effectively blocks 3a-mediated current (Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig20" ref-type="fig">8.20a</xref>), and it even more effective than emodin by an order of magnitude (IC<sub>50</sub>&#x02009;&#x02009;&#x02248;&#x02009;2&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) (Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig20" ref-type="fig">8.20b</xref>).<fig id="Fig20"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.20a,b</label><caption><p>a&#x000a0;Current-voltage dependencies of 3a-mediated current in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes in the presence of different amounts of the kaempferol glycoside juglanin (inset in <bold>b</bold>). <bold>b&#x000a0;</bold>Dependence of 3a-mediated current (at &#x02212;60&#x02009;mV) on juglanin concentration. (Based on Schwarz et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2014</xref>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig20_HTML" id="d29e2157"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>The Viral Protein Unit (Vpu) of HIV-1</title><p>The
viral protein unit Vpu of HIV-1 is also a membrane protein but with only one transmembrane segment (Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig21" ref-type="fig">8.21a</xref>), and a channel permeable for monovalent cations is formed by a pentamer.<fig id="Fig21"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.21a&#x02013;c</label><caption><p>a&#x000a0;Orientation of Vpu monomer in the membrane (<italic>bottom</italic>) and formation of ion channel by pentamer (<italic>top</italic>). b&#x000a0;Inhibition of Vpu-mediated current by 100&#x02009;&#x000b5;M of the flavonoid genistein (<bold>c</bold>). (Based on Sauter et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2014</xref>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig21_HTML" id="d29e2197"/></fig>
</p><p>The activation of the channel is necessary for virus release (Schubert et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">1996</xref>), and the search for Vpu channel blockers as antiviral drugs has been suggested. Vpu-mediated current can also be monitored as a Ba<sup>2+</sup>-sensitive current (Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig21" ref-type="fig">8.21b</xref>) and can partially be blocked by the flavonoid genistein.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>The M2 (Matrix Protein 2) Protein of the Influenza A Virus</title><p>The
genome of the influenza A virus (swine flu virus) encodes for an ion channel. As for the Vpu, this M2 protein has only a single transmembrane segment, but the channel is formed by a tetrameric structure (Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig22" ref-type="fig">8.22a</xref>) that exhibits low conductance for protons. With decreasing pH, the M2-mediated current increases dramatically (Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig22" ref-type="fig">8.22b</xref>). The activity of the channel also plays an essential role in virus production (see de Clercq 2006).<fig id="Fig22"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.22a,b</label><caption><p>
<bold>a</bold>&#x000a0;Illustration of structure of the M2 protein of the influenza A virus. <italic>Lower part</italic>: two monomers interacting with their N and C termini. <italic>Upper part</italic>: formation of the tetrameric channel. <bold>b&#x000a0;</bold>pH dependency of current mediated by M2 protein expressed in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig22_HTML" id="d29e2254"/></fig>
</p><p>In contrast to the 3a protein, M2 is an integral membrane protein of the viron and is involved in the uncoating of the viruses by permitting passage of protons across the membrane of the viron. In previous times, one of the most effective inhibitors of M2 function was amantidine, and in the past, a potent medicine for treatment of influence A infection. Meanwhile, all influenza A viruses have become amantadine-resistant, and worldwide laboratories are searching intensively for substitutes.</p><sec id="Sec23"><title>Inhibition of M2-Mediated Current by Kaempferol Triglycosides</title><p>Kaempferol glycosides may also form the basis for new drugs against influenza A. A triglycoside has been found that effectively inhibits pH-sensitive current when M2 is expressed in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes (Fig.&#x0202f;<xref rid="Fig23" ref-type="fig">8.23</xref>).<fig id="Fig23"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;8.23a,b</label><caption><p>Inhibition of M2-mediated current (<bold>a</bold>) by 20&#x02009;&#x000b5;M kaempferol triglycoside (<bold>b</bold>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="394785_1_En_8_Fig23_HTML" id="d29e2283"/></fig>
</p><p>In conclusion, the activity of various viral ion channels seems to be essential for virus reproduction in the infected cells. Hence, inhibition of channel activity by drugs will counteract that process, allowing the infected body to build up or strengthen its own immune system. Viral ion channels are, therefore, potential candidates for developing new antiviral drugs, and voltage clamping is an easy method to screen drugs, and detect and analyze inhibition of the ion channels. Screening of a large number of natural drugs revealed that kaempferol derivatives and anthraquinones may be interesting candidates.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Exercises</title><p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>What are the major tasks of the sodium pump?</p></list-item><list-item><p>What are the functional meanings of the <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-, <italic>&#x000df;</italic>-, and &#x003b3;<italic>-</italic>subunits of the sodium pump?</p></list-item><list-item><p>What is the physiological function of P2X receptors?</p></list-item><list-item><p>What role does a neurotransmitter transporter play in physiological and pathophysiological functions?</p></list-item><list-item><p>Which ion-channel families do you know?</p></list-item><list-item><p>Describe the role of viral ion channels in virus reproduction.</p></list-item><list-item><p>How can electrophysiology serve as a tool in development of antiviral drug? Name examples.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bagriantsev</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Gracheva</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Piezo proteins: Regulators of mechanosensation and other cellular processes</article-title><source>J.Biol.Chem.</source><year>2014</year><volume>289</volume><fpage>31673</fpage><lpage>31681</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.R114.612697</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25305018?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25305018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burnstock</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current status of purinergic signalling in the nervous system</article-title><source>Prog. Brain Res.</source><year>1999</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0079-6123(08)63541-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10550983?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10550983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Corey</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TRP channels in mechanosensation: direct or indirect activation</article-title><source>Nature Rev.Neurosc.</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>510</fpage><lpage>521</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn2149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Clercq</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiviral agents active against influenza A viruses</article-title><source>Nature Rev.Drug Discov.</source><year>2006</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1015</fpage><lpage>1025</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrd2175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17139286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delmas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Coste</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechano-gated ion channels in sensory systems</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2013</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>278</fpage><lpage>284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2013.09.026</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24120130?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24120130</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sachs</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single channel properties of P2X2 purinoceptors</article-title><source>J. Gen. Physiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>695</fpage><lpage>720</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1085/jgp.113.5.695</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10228183?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10228183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eckstein-Ludwig</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of uptake, steady-state currents, and transient charge movements generated by the neuronal GABA transporter by various anticonvulsant drugs</article-title><source>Br. J. Pharmacol.</source><year>1999</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bjp.0702794</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10498839?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10498839</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sansom</surname><given-names>MSP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Viral ion channels: structure and function</article-title><source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source><year>2002</year><volume>1561</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-4157(01)00009-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11988179?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11988179</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kr&#x000fc;ger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assembly of viral membrane proteins</article-title><source>J. Chem.Theory Comput</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2009</issue><fpage>2503</fpage><lpage>2513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ct900185n</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26616628?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26616628</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckstein-Ludwig</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of mutation of glycosylation sites on the Na+ dependence of steady-state and transient current generated by the neuronal GABA transporter</article-title><source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source><year>1998</year><volume>1415</volume><fpage>246</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0005-2736(98)00200-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9858742?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9858742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>CKL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Deubel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Severe acute respiratory syndrome-associated coronavirus 3a protein forms an ion channel and modulates virus release</article-title><source>PNAS</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>12540</fpage><lpage>12545</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0605402103</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16894145?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16894145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR1000"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicke</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>P2X1 and P2X3 receptors form stable trimers: a novel structural motif of ligand-gated ion channels</article-title><source>The EMBO Journal</source><year>1998</year><volume>17</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>3016</fpage><lpage>3028</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9606184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nilius</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Honor&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sensing pressure with ion channels</article-title><source>Trends Neurosci.</source><year>2012</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tins.2012.04.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22622029?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22622029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranade</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Syeda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Patapoutian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanically activated ion channels</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2015</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>1162</fpage><lpage>1179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2015.08.032</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26402601?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26402601</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rettinger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aschrafi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmalzing</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Roles of individual N-glycans for ATP potency and expression of the rat P2X1 receptor</article-title><source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>33542</fpage><lpage>33547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M002918200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10942758?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10942758</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sauter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genistein as Antiviral Drug against HIV Ion Channel</article-title><source>Planta Med.</source><year>2014</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>682</fpage><lpage>687</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0034-1368583</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24963618?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24963618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrer-Montiel</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Oblatt-Montal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Henklein</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Strebel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Montal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of an ion channel activity of the Vpu transmembrane domain and its involvement in the regulation of virus release from HIV-1-infected cells</article-title><source>FEBS Letters</source><year>1996</year><volume>398</volume><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(96)01146-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8946945?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8946945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emodin inhibits current through SARS-associated coronavirus 3a protein</article-title><source>Antivir. Res.</source><year>2011</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.antiviral.2011.02.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21356245?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21356245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Efferth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coronaviral ion channels as target for Chinese herbal medicine</article-title><source>Forum Immunopathol. Dis. Therap.</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1615/ForumImmunDisTher.2012004378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Karioti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilia</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Efferth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kaempferol derivatives as antiviral drugs against 3a channel protein of coronavirus</article-title><source>Planta Med.</source><year>2014</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0033-1360277</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24458263?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24458263</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The discovery of artemisinin (qinghaosu) and gifts from Chinese medicine</article-title><source>Nature Medicine</source><year>2011</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1217</fpage><lpage>1220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm.2471</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21989013?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21989013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Viral proteins function as ion channels</article-title><source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source><year>2011</year><volume>1808</volume><fpage>510</fpage><lpage>515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamem.2010.05.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20478263?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20478263</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasilets</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawamura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The N-terminus of the Na<sup>+</sup>,K<sup>+</sup>-ATPase &#x003b1;-subunit acts like an inactivation &#x0201c;ball&#x0201d;</article-title><source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source><year>2003</year><volume>1609</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0005-2736(02)00653-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12507758?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12507758</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vasilets</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure-function relationships of cation binding in the Na<sup>+</sup>/K<sup>+</sup>-ATPase</article-title><source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source><year>1993</year><volume>1154</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0304-4157(93)90012-D</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8218338?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8218338</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>