<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The literature has reported clinical manifestations of VEE to be similar in humans infected with VEEV varieties IAB, IC, ID, and IE, regardless of exposure route [
 <xref rid="B51-viruses-11-00807" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-viruses-11-00807" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-viruses-11-00807" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-viruses-11-00807" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-viruses-11-00807" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-viruses-11-00807" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,
 <xref rid="B60-viruses-11-00807" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. A recently published retrospective review of detailed medical records of laboratory- and vaccine-acquired VEEV IAB (TrD strain) infections during the U.S. Biowarfare (BW) program noted both aerosol and percutaneous routes of VEEV exposure to result in a self-limited, acute febrile illness that presented initially with an abrupt onset of fever, chills, severe headache, malaise, fatigue, weakness, back pain, myalgia (often in the lower back, thigh, or calf muscles), sore throat, anorexia, and nausea [
 <xref rid="B52-viruses-11-00807" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Incubation periods by both routes were similar (generally 1 to 4 days; range 2 h to 8 days), with most signs and symptoms occurring on the initial day of illness. Common physical examination findings included fever, pharyngeal erythema, conjunctival injection, and lymphadenopathy. Unlike mice and NHPs, in which aerosol-acquired infection resulted in an increased severity of central nervous system (CNS) disease compared to percutaneous-acquired infection [
 <xref rid="B48-viruses-11-00807" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-viruses-11-00807" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-viruses-11-00807" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-viruses-11-00807" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-viruses-11-00807" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-viruses-11-00807" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-viruses-11-00807" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="B66-viruses-11-00807" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], CNS signs and symptoms in humans were infrequent regardless of the exposure route, and severe encephalitis (e.g., seizures, paralysis, or coma) was not observed in this adult population (age 21–41 years). The only significant difference noted in aerosol-acquired infection was an association of increased upper respiratory tract-related symptoms and signs that included sore throat (with or without erythema), cervical lymphadenopathy, and neck pain. There were no deaths, and symptoms generally resolved within a week, with asthenia persisting in some cases for an additional 1 or 2 weeks. Fever, viremia, and lymphopenia were common markers of disease in humans by both exposure routes. Fever was observed in nearly all cases, viremia was common on days 1–4 of illness (range day 0–7 of illness), and lymphopenia (defined as &lt;1500 cells/mm
 <sup>3</sup>) was common early in infection (onset generally by day 1–3 of illness). The observed increase in upper respiratory tract-related findings associated with aerosol-acquired VEE in humans is supported by the mouse model in which aerosol and intranasal (IN) challenge were associated with nasal mucosa necrosis, necrotizing rhinitis, and increased viral burden in the upper respiratory tract, and by the IN challenge NHP model that detected VEEV in the cervical lymph nodes within 18 h post-challenge.
</p>
