<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?OLF?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Lancet Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Lancet Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Lancet. Infectious Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1473-3099</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1474-4457</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7295469</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S1473-3099(20)30465-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30465-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>COVID-19 in Africa: between hope and reality</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au10"><name><surname>Ntoumi</surname><given-names>Francine</given-names></name><email>fntoumi@fcrm-congo.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au20"><name><surname>Velavan</surname><given-names>Thirumalaisamy P</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Fondation Congolaise pour la Recherche M&#x000e9;dicale, Brazzaville, Republic of the Congo</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Marien Ngouabi University, Brazzaville, Republic of the Congo</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Institute for Tropical Medicine, University of T&#x000fc;bingen, T&#x000fc;bingen, Germany</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Vietnamese&#x02013;German Center for Medical Research, Hanoi, Vietnam</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Faculty of Medicine, Duy Tan University, Da Nang, Vietnam</aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Elsevier Ltd</copyright-holder><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p id="para10">When WHO declared the COVID-19 pandemic to be a Public Health Emergency of International Concern on Jan 30, 2020, countries around the world began to prepare. Preparation, however, is becoming increasingly difficult in many African countries, especially in central African countries, such as Republic of the Congo and others, where the effects of the Ebola virus disease epidemic on the economy and health structures are still being felt. The first case of COVID-19 in Africa was reported on Feb 14, and within a few weeks the virus had spread to 54 African countries. Only a few African Union member states have been successful in implementing detection, prevention, and control measures. Republic of the Congo reported its first case on March 14, and by May 9 a total of 274 confirmed cases and ten deaths had been reported. Very few countries in Africa have sufficient and appropriate diagnostic capacities, and obvious challenges exist to handle an outbreak of this extent.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref>
</p><p id="para20">Densely populated communities in urban areas are particularly vulnerable to COVID-19 outbreaks, and the most vulnerable region in Republic of the Congo is undoubtedly Brazzaville. Our institution, the Congolese Foundation for Medical Research,<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> supports the National Public Health Laboratory with COVID-19 diagnoses and thus with extended monitoring measures. We feel that operational research at the local level in Brazzaville through testing people living in densely populated communities and health workers is a moral responsibility. As of May 9, three asymptomatic health-care workers had tested positive for severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2. With the number of cases observed in our laboratory growing (up to 24 cases per day), fear and anxiety among our Congolese scientists also grows.</p><p id="para30">A question that Republic of the Congo and other member states in the region must ask themselves is why are we seeing only a gradual increase in the detection of cases? Are we missing infections? A probable answer is that people with symptoms do not present to health-care facilities because of their concerns about fragile health systems, social stigma, and quarantine in suboptimal facilities. Other questions still to be resolved are related to the dynamics of viral transmission across geographical regions, between humans, across different ecosystems, and within different genetic backgrounds, and to whether any protective herd immunity exists.</p><p id="para40">Given the fragile health systems in most sub-Saharan African countries, new and re-emerging infectious disease outbreaks can paralyse health systems and existing structures. Yet the COVID-19 pandemic poses a challenge not only for sub-Saharan African countries<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> but also for those with well functioning health systems.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> The responsibility now for African scientists is to join forces and fight at local and regional levels<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> to ensure the slow down and eventual halt of the spread of COVID-19. This can be well achieved by supporting existing regional and local health structures in sub-Saharan Africa.</p></body><back><ref-list id="bibl10"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Velavan</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The COVID-19 epidemic</article-title><source>Trop Med Int Health</source><volume>25</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>278</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32052514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ntoumi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ant who learned to be an elephant</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>333</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>1824</fpage><lpage>1825</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ihekweazu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ntoumi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is Africa prepared for tackling the COVID-19 (SARS-CoV-2) epidemic. Lessons from past outbreaks, ongoing pan-African public health efforts, and implications for the future</article-title><source>Int J Infect Dis</source><volume>93</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32119980</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ippolito</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ntoumi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeurer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zumla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toning down the 2019-nCoV media hype and restoring hope</article-title><source>Lancet Respir Med</source><volume>8</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>230</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32146924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dexter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiyaga</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitigating the effect of the COVID-19 pandemic on sickle cell disease services in African countries</article-title><source>Lancet Haematol</source><volume>7</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>e430</fpage><lpage>e432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32334676</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack><p>We declare no competing interests. Both authors contributed equally and are members of the Pan-African Network for Rapid Research, Response and Preparedness for Infectious Diseases Epidemics, which is funded through the European and Developing Countries Clinical Trials Partnership (grant number RIA2016E-1609).</p></ack></back></article>