<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This systematic review and meta-analysis examined the prevalence of HIV, HCV, HBV and their co-infections among PWID and FSWs worldwide, and the results were shown by different WHO regions. The prevalence of HIV in PWID and FSWs was 15% and 5%, respectively. That means one of seven PWID and one of 20 FSWs get infected with HIV, with the highest prevalence in PWID being in Africa (24%), South-East Asia (22%) and Europe (12%), and in FSWs being in Africa (19%) and South-East Asia (18%). The number of people living with HIV worldwide in 2017 was estimated to be 36.8 million [
 <xref rid="B145-pathogens-09-00432" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>]. HIV is most likely transmitted through unprotected sex and syringes and needles used for injections. A total of 69.5% of HIV infection in the general population occurs through needle sharing and 10% through unprotected sex [
 <xref rid="B146-pathogens-09-00432" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>,
 <xref rid="B147-pathogens-09-00432" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>,
 <xref rid="B148-pathogens-09-00432" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>]. In a meta-analysis study in 2017, the prevalence of HIV among PWID worldwide was reported to be 17.8%, and the largest population under study was from sub-Saharan Africa. A total of 95% of new HIV cases were among the key populations in the Middle East and North Africa (MENA) [
 <xref rid="B13-pathogens-09-00432" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In a 2019 study, the prevalence of HIV in PWID was 21% in Africa; in another study, HIV incidence in PWID in the MENA region was significant, with 75% of new cases occurring in PWID and their sexual partners [
 <xref rid="B149-pathogens-09-00432" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>,
 <xref rid="B150-pathogens-09-00432" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>]. The meta-analysis by Leung et al., in 2019, also estimated the highest prevalence of HIV in Africa and Asia, which is consistent with the results of our study [
 <xref rid="B151-pathogens-09-00432" ref-type="bibr">151</xref>]. The prevalence of HIV in Brazilian FSWs was 5%, and in part-time sex workers in Burkina Faso it was 6.5% [
 <xref rid="B31-pathogens-09-00432" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B152-pathogens-09-00432" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>].
</p>
