<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Preliminary inoculation studies included in this report were performed with California HOSPs and HOFIs prior to the generation of the SLEV.IC and WNV-prME/SLEV.IC infectious clone derived viruses (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0006302.t001">Table 1</xref>) in 2007. In the California HOFI study, a WNV seropositive HOFI was inadvertently inoculated with SLEV-prME/WNV.IC as the HOFI was EIA and plaque negative at the time of capture, but had seroconverted prior to the time of inoculation. Blood samples were collected from this HOFI as well. All subsequent avian experimental infection studies were performed in Colorado during and after 2010 and utilized the rescued SLEV and WNV parental and chimeric infectious clone viruses described previously [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006302.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Flavivirus seronegative HOSPs, HOFIs and AMCRs were needle- inoculated subcutaneously in the cervical region with 1,000–1,500 PFU/ 0.1mL of virus diluted in phosphate buffered saline (PBS) (Tables 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0006302.t001">1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0006302.t002">2</xref>). To ensure phenotypic concordance of the SLEV.IC with its parental virus, SLEV/IMP115, CO HOSPs were also inoculated with the field isolated SLEV/IMP115 virus. Birds were monitored daily for clinical signs of disease such as lethargy, fluffed feathers, decreased activity and emaciation [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006302.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006302.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. A 0.1mL aliquot of blood was drawn daily from HOSPs and HOFIs from the jugular vein from 1 to 7 dpi, diluted in 0.4mL of BA-1 media supplemented with 20% FBS, allowed to coagulate and centrifuged to pellet clotted cells. Serum sampling from AMCRs was performed in an identical manner with the exception that 0.2mL of blood was added to 0.8mL BA-1 media. Samples were stored at -80°C until titrated for infectious units by plaque assay on Vero cells [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006302.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The limit of virus detection was 1.7 log
 <sub>10</sub> PFU/mL of sera based on a 0.2 mL plaque assay inocula per well of the initial 1:10 diluted sera samples. Daily mean titers were calculated and plotted as a line graph against days post inoculation. Mean peak titers for each group were calculated by averaging the peak titer of each individual bird regardless of the day post-inoculation and were presented as scatter plots.
</p>
