<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While there are no drugs specifically approved for treatment of COVID-19, there are multiple ongoing clinical trials and a number of drugs that show promise. SARS-CoV-2 is an RNA virus, like human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) and Ebola, and molecules developed for other RNA viruses may be useful targets (fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). In particular, remdesivir is a nucleotide analog developed for use with Ebola infection. The drug inhibits the RNA-dependent RNA polymerase used by coronavirions to replicate their genome.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>
 </sup> Based on 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> evidence of effectiveness, the manufacturer initiated two phase 3 clinical trials of the use of remdesivir in COVID-19 (trial Nos. NCT04292730 and NCT04292899). Similar trials in severe and moderate cases of COVID-19 are underway in China (trial Nos. NCT04252664 and NCT04257656). Remdesivir is also the initial treatment arm in an adaptive clinical trial sponsored by the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (trial No. NCT04280705). This adaptive trial will be actively modified to add novel drugs of interest and to replace the control arm with the current best supported regimen. Interestingly, the antimalaria drug chloroquine has also been shown to inhibit SARS-CoV-2 at micromolar concentrations. This agent, which blocks virus infection both at entry and postentry stages, has been used in therapeutic and prophylactic regimens for more than 70 yr, so its safety profile, including prominent neurologic and gastrointestinal side effects, is well known.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>
 </sup> Among its possible mechanisms of action are altering the pH of endosomes and directly modifying angiotensin converting enzyme-2.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>
 </sup> Compared with a historical control cohort, SARS-CoV-1 patients treated with combination lopinavir/ritonavir had significantly lower risk of ARDS or death.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>
 </sup> The combination of lopinavir/ritonavir has been used in COVID-19 cases as well, based on these SARS data and 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> effectiveness.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>,
  <xref rid="R91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>
 </sup> However, clinical effectiveness remains unproven, and providers should be cognizant of the known side effect profile for this medication and monitor for hepatotoxicity, hyperglycemia, and arrythmias.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>
 </sup> An ongoing clinical trial is comparing patients randomized to lopinavir/ritonavir and the viral fusion inhibitor arbidol (trial No. NCT04252885). As the optimal regimen remains to be determined, affected patients should consider enrolling in clinical trials whenever available.
</p>
