<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="abs0005">
 <p>This concise manuscript aims to make suggestions for a small step forward in both preventative and therapeutic measures against the Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID 19) pandemic. This targeted strategy consists of using fully recovered COVID 19 Heroes, that is, brave volunteers, as the source of antibodies in plasma collected by plasmapheresis or affinity column- derived antibodies, both are sterilised and pathogen inactivated for substitution therapy for use in those populations in need of antibody. This include for use in critically ill COVID 19 patients and as a preventative measure, in those at potential risk of infection as no vaccine is yet available. This would be a small step forward, while we are waiting to produce an effective, validated vaccine and witnessing increasing demands for testing and self-isolation which are the two most effective current strategies. In line with this concept, some methodological aspects of the use of the UVC sterilization of FFP/ cryoprecipitate-depleted FFP or immunoglobulins containing neutralizing antibodies for clinical use against COVID-19 are highlighted. The plasmapheresis procedure is, of course, particularly targeted to male donors, who consist of about 75 % of the COVID-19 population and who are able to undergo multiple double, or even triple plasmapheresis procedures. Moreover, as some of these donors have already been in an induced-hypercoagulable state and prone to thrombosis and DVT, this strategy will be partially aimed at improving their health with the use of citrate based anticoagulants and removal of high molecular weight viscous components which contribute to the untoward clinical effects of DVT. Repeated targeted plasmapheresis or plasma exchange of selected COVID-19 positive individuals would undoubtedly lower their state of hypercoagulability and normalize their hypercoagulability. The recipients of such a derived FFP-product would benefit from the two to 3 doses of viral inactivated antibodies, which could neutralize the viral antigens even at very low concentration if present in the early stage. So, this practice would be a double-edged sword with benefits for both donors and recipients.</p>
</abstract>
