<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0006">What do we know about the new 2019-nCoV coronavirus syndrome 
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>? At the end of December 2019, the Chinese authorities reported a new respiratory flu-like syndrome originating in Wuhan, a city in Central China with around 11 million inhabitants. Complications in the initial 41 patients reported from Wuhan up to 2nd January 2020 included acute respiratory distress syndrome, acute cardiac injury and secondary infection 
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. A third of these patients were admitted to an Intensive Care Unit (ICU); these patients had higher levels of inflammatory cytokines than those not admitted to ICU 
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Following a serious delay by Chinese authorities in reporting and action in the first two weeks of the month, by the 28th January there had been over 4500 cases reported of Wuhan 2019-nCoV disease and 100 deaths 
 <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. By then, cases of 2019-nCoV infection had been reported in a further 15 countries, including elsewhere in Southeast Asia, Australia, Europe and North America Cases of person-to-person transmission have been reported, including in Germany, in a UK citizen visiting Singapore, possible materno-foetal transmission, and in 61 of 3700 passengers in a cruise ship quarantined off Yokohama, Japan. The initial doubling interval appears around 5 days, with on 7th February the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control (ECDC) reporting an increase to 31,503 laboratory-confirmed cases (31,217 in China) and 638 deaths, all but one in China. Up to the time of this editorial there have now been reports of 286 cases in 25 further countries and territories 
 <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Mortality is reportedly highest in frail patients, however there have already been reports of 2019-nCoV attributed deaths in health professionals in China 
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, including Dr Li Wenliang, the 34 year old Chinese ophthalmologist who was the first to alert his medical colleagues to the outbreak of this new coronavirus syndrome 
 <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>.
</p>
