<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial"><?OLF?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?covid-19-tdm?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Radiol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Radiol Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>La Radiologia Medica</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0033-8362</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1826-6983</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Milan</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Milan</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7104420</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1178</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11547-020-01178-y</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Facing the COVID-19 emergency: we can and we do</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Giovagnoni</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name><address><email>a.giovagnoni@staff.univpm.it</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1">Department of Radiology - Division of Special and Pediatric Radiology, University Hospital, Via Conca 71, 60126 Ancona, AN Italy </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Italian Society of Medical Radiology 2020</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This article is made available via the PMC Open Access Subset for unrestricted research re-use and secondary analysis in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for the duration of the World Health Organization (WHO) declaration of COVID-19 as a global pandemic.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par1">As Editor-in-Chief of this journal and being personally involved as Chief of Radiology Department in a university Italian hospital within one of the major hotbeds of COVID-19, I feel compelled to write an editorial about the Italian COVID-19 outbreak.</p><p id="Par2">As already highlighted by many published scientific papers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], diagnostic imaging has a pivotal role in the diagnosis and management of the patients affected by COVID-19.</p><p id="Par3">Although the main Worldwide Guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] define the molecular tests on nasopharyngeal and oropharyngeal swabs as the reference standard for the diagnosis, chest CT remains the main method for evaluating the disease pulmonary extension and for follow-up.</p><p id="Par4">Moreover, several papers, mostly on Chinese case series, have identified and defined the main patterns at chest CT of pulmonary involvement in COVID-19; thus, the Chinese authors themselves and the <italic>American College of Radiology</italic> (ACR) highly recommend to familiarize with the CT appearance of COVID-19 infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p><p id="Par5">For this purpose, the President of the Italian Society of Medical and Interventional Radiology (SIRMi) established a dedicated page on the SIRMi Web site with an Italian collection of COVID-19 imaging; in this way, the Italian radiologists, and not only, can freely access and become familiar with CT and radiographic images of anonymized COVID-19 cases collected form several Italian centers.</p><p id="Par6">Nevertheless, alongside the assistance to the patients affected by COVID-19, which mainly lies on a prompt and accurate diagnosis, I care to highlight another aspect: the huge effort that has been required to all the health professional of the radiology departments.</p><p id="Par7">So far, radiologists, radiographers, nurses, healthcare workers and administrative staff are daily fighting the COVID-19 emergency on the frontline.</p><p id="Par8">The <italic>World Health Organization</italic> (WHO) developed a document [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] defining rights, roles and responsibilities of all the healthworkers for the COVID-19 emergency setting.</p><p id="Par9">I would like to emphasize that WHO highlights not only the infective risk, but also the dramatic raise of the working hours for the healthworkers and therefore the growth of the psychological stress, of the fatigue and of risk of burnout for the whole health-working category.</p><p id="Par10">It is highly desirable that this document will be received in the radiological field.</p><p id="Par11">In these hard times, together with the medical and radiological skills that each of us must put into practice, we should not forget that behind healthworkers involved in all the Italian radiological departments, there are women and men from whom a huge personal effort is requested, an effort which is tremendous and unique even compared to wars, natural disasters and epidemics we dealt with during the last century.</p><p id="Par12">The whole staff of La Radiologia Medica, the President and the whole Board of Direction of SIRMi are strongly supporting and thanks all the women and men working in the Italian radiology departments.</p><p id="Par13">All together we can overcome this challenge!</p></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="ethics"><title>Compliance with ethical standards</title><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p></notes><notes><title>Ethical standards</title><p>This article does not contain any studies with human participants or animals performed by any of the authors.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19): role of chest CT in diagnosis and management</article-title><source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source><year>2020</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Chinese Society of Radiology</collab></person-group><article-title>Radiological diagnosis of new coronavirus infected pneumonitis: expert recommendation from the Chinese Society of Radiology (First edition)</article-title><source>Chin J Radiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>54</volume><issue>00</issue><fpage>E001</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Halsey</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>TML</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Performance of radiologists in differentiating COVID-19 from viral pneumonia on chest CT</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>200823</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.acr.org/Advocacy-and-Economics/ACR-Position-Statements/Recommendations-for-Chest-Radiography-and-CT-for-Suspected-COVID19-Infection">https://www.acr.org/Advocacy-and-Economics/ACR-Position-Statements/Recommendations-for-Chest-Radiography-and-CT-for-Suspected-COVID19-Infection</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/docs/default-source/coronaviruse/who-rights-roles-respon-hw-covid-19.pdf?sfvrsn=bcabd401_0">https://www.who.int/docs/default-source/coronaviruse/who-rights-roles-respon-hw-covid-19.pdf?sfvrsn=bcabd401_0</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>