<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0010">As of April 2020, some 93% of the global population (about 7.2 billion people) live in countries with some form of movement restrictions in place [
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. A new coronavirus disease, officially named COVID-19 by the World Health Organisation (WHO), has caused a global pandemic with profound impacts on many aspects of human life [
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. On 11 February 2020, the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses announced severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) as the name of the new virus [
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Unlike all previous pandemics in modern history, COVID-19 is truly a global crisis. Never before have we seen the health care systems of some of the world’s most industrialised nations on the verge of collapse [
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Unprecedented measures (social distancing, school and workplace closure, and restricted intra- and international movement) have been enforced by governments around the world to stop the spread of COVID-19. As the world adapts to unprecedented behavioural and societal changes in response to the threat posed by COVID-19, societal operations, including many essential municipal services must also adapt and change. These essential services such as waste collection and wastewater treatment are routine and indispensable. They play a key role in mitigating infectious disease transmission but are rarely mentioned in public health crises response communications [
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>]. Under current projections waste and wastewater industries are expected to bear significant financial impacts from COVID-19. For example, water utilities in the USA are expected to suffer over $27 billion in financial loss due to revenue reduction and expense increase as a direct consequence of COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].
</p>
