<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Lipid molecules are suitable for vaccine formulations because of their high safety profile and tunable physiochemical features.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref55">55</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref59">59</xref>
 </sup> These advantages also make them the leading platform in developing vaccines quickly. Currently, there are two mRNA vaccine forerunners in development for COVID-19 that are based on lipid formulations (Moderna and BioNTech).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref>
 </sup> Lipids are a class of amphiphiles that contain hydrophilic head groups and hydrophobic tails. Interactions between those molecules can drive the formation of spherical vesicles to encapsulate vaccine formulations either with one (unilamellar) or more (multilamellar) lipids bilayers.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref55">55</xref>
 </sup> Lipid molecules have also been explored to achieve distinct biological functions.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref59">59</xref>
 </sup> For instance, cationic lipids are commonly used for efficient cellular uptake and increase the loading of negatively charged mRNA and DNA.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref56">56</xref>
 </sup> DOTMA, DOTAP, and DOPE are common examples.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref56">56</xref>
 </sup> However, cationic lipids are commonly associated with high toxicity and neutralization by anionic serum proteins, which reduce the delivery efficacy.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref83">83</xref>
 </sup> Therefore, ionizable lipids that can change their charge state at different pH conditions can be utilized to maintain efficacy, to reduce toxicity, and to facilitate the endosomal release of cargos.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref84">84</xref>
 </sup> Some common strategies to improve the efficacy of LNPs include enhancing cellular uptake and promoting endosomal escape by incorporating cholesterol, polyethylene glycol (PEG) lipids, or helper lipids DOPE.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref56">56</xref>
 </sup> Hydrophobic cholesterol can fill the gaps between lipid tails to stabilize the vesicle. PEG lipids can shield the vesicles and protect them from clearance when systemically delivered.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref56">56</xref>
 </sup> Helper lipids have unsaturated bonds to form an unstable hexagonal lamellar phase that enhances the endosomal escape.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref85">85</xref>
 </sup> In addition, good biocompatibility of lipids makes it possible for expedited FDA approvals.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref86">86</xref>
 </sup> Therefore, LNPs can be optimized in vaccine formulations to stabilize and enhance uptake of cargo, to improve immunostimulatory functions for antigens, and for targeted delivery. Oberli 
 <italic>et al</italic>. utilized an ionizable lipid, a phospholipid, cholesterol, and a PEG anchored lipid as LNP formulations for mRNA vaccine delivery, which resulted in stable nanoformulations, efficient antigen presentation, and elicitation of a strong T cell response.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref54">54</xref>
 </sup> However, the 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> potency of LNP-based vaccines could be limited by their suboptimal physiological stability, which can cause the fast release of antigens before initiating any immune response. Moon 
 <italic>et al</italic>. developed a hyperstabilized lipid-based vaccine formulation by covalently cross-linking two lipid molecule layers between their head groups using a mild chemical condition that is compatible with loaded antigens.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref55">55</xref>
 </sup> The resulting vesicles are stabilized multilamellar structures that could trap high levels of protein antigens. Combined with PEGylation as a well-established stabilization strategy, the hyperstabilized NPs can sustain the release of antigens up to 30 days in the presence of serum, which significantly enhanced the humoral immune response.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref87">87</xref>
 </sup> By adding the lipid-like monophosphoryl lipid A (MPLA) as adjuvants, the vaccine formulation can further enhance T cell-mediated humoral responses.
</p>
