<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30">The onset of GBS can be explained by the molecular mimicry that occurs between gangliosides and the campylobacter’s lipo-oligosaccharides (LOS).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup> Although GM1 in particular is indicated as the target for AGAs in GBS, there are many other homologs between the campylobacter LOS and human gangliosides.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>
 </sup> As stated by Shahrizaila and Yuki the association between GBS and 
 <italic>C. jejuni</italic> is the is the first human autoimmune disorder that fulfills the criteria to conclude that GBS is caused by molecular mimicry.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>
 </sup> The criteria include (1) the establishment of an epidemiological association between infectious agent and the immune-mediated disease. In general, epidemiological studies have shown 30–35% positivity for 
 <italic>C. jejuni</italic> in GBS patients as compared to 4.4% in controls.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>
 </sup> The second (2) criterium is to identify antibodies or T cells directed against the target antigen. As previously stated, AGAs were identified in patients with GBS and recognized as the key pathological element in the pathogenesis. Depending on the ganglioside targeted a different manifestation of GBS may occur. Interestingly, also activated T cells and macrophages have been identified around the nerves of GBS patients.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>
 </sup> Apparently, patients develop T cell responses against the exogenous LOS and endogenous glycolipids (gangliosides). Further studies should address the nature of the responding T cells. Possible candidates include innate lymphoid cells, gamma-delta T cells or NK cells. As the third criterium (3) microbial mimics to the target antigens have been identified. They include the low molecular weight LOS of 
 <italic>C. jejuni</italic>. It has been observed that only certain specific 
 <italic>C. jejuni</italic> serotypes are associated with GBS, in particular O:19 and O:41.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>
 </sup> These serotypes correspond to the development of AGAs especially against GM1 but also to other gangliosides, like GD1a and GD3. As the final criterium (4) it has been shown that GBS can be induced in a rabbit model by an injection with either the GM1 ganglioside or the homologous LOS of 
 <italic>C. jejuni</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>
 </sup> The antibodies were found to disrupt lipid rafts, nodal structures and ion channel clusters in the peripheral motor nerves.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>
 </sup> Interestingly, in the animal model the neuronal damage could be inhibited with the synthetic serine protease inhibitor nafamostat mesilate that also acts as a complement inhibitor.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
