<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par33">There has been a considerable amount of research in the past 20 years in the field of HEV vaccination. One of the structural proteins, orf2, responsible for capsid formation, represents antigenic sites against which immune response can develop. Different strains of HEV share neutralizing epitopes on orf2 capsid proteins, thus providing cross-reactivity and potential antigens for vaccine development [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]. The first HEV vaccine to be tested in randomized, double-blind, controlled, phase II trial among 2000 Nepalese men showed 95.5% protection during a median follow up of 804 days [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>]. The vaccine contained a 56-kilo Dalton truncated (amino acid 112–607) 
 <italic>orf2</italic> protein administered in three doses at 0–1–6 months [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>]. The vaccine did not undergo further development. Another vaccine called HEV 239 (Hecolin®), tested in a double-blind, controlled, randomized phase III trial among 112,604 healthy men and women, is available commercially in China since 2012 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]. The vaccine contains 26 k Dalton recombinant, truncated (amino acid 368–606) 
 <italic>orf2</italic> protein, administered 30 μg intramuscularly at 0–1–6 months, and showed a protection rate of 95.5% after a year and cross-protection for HEV 1 and 4 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>]. Long-term follow up of the recruited subjects has shown the vaccine to be protective even after 4 years and safe in women [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>]. However, the vaccine is not available in other countries. The 30th Global Advisory Committee on Vaccine Safety, WHO has recommended a phase IV trial of the vaccine and further data on its safety in special population groups including children and elderly [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]. Experts recommend selective vaccination against HEV in certain high-risk groups such as immunosuppressed population, persons with chronic liver disease, pregnant women in disease-endemic areas, travelers from low-endemicity areas to high-endemicity areas and general population in hyperendemic areas [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>••].
</p>
