<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Seasonal variation has been reported in the incidence of sudden cardiac arrest (SCA) and sudden death/SCD,[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] typically with a winter peak and a summer nadir. Exposure to cold weather is considered the main factor influencing this seasonality.[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] However, these previous epidemiological studies are limited by differences in the definition of SCD (none had VF recording available) used and the fact that they often included SCD cases occurring in the setting of different cardiac pathologies (i.e., etiological heterogeneity in substrate for VF). Nevertheless, these seasonal patterns indicate the presence of seasonal external factors, such as viral infections, that could trigger VF. While several studies indicate consistent association between viral infections and MI,[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] there is weaker evidence of an association between viral exposure and cardiac arrhythmias and SCA[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. A genome-wide association study in the Dutch AGNES (Arrhythmia Genetics in the NEtherlandS) population showed that the most significant association with VF during first ST-elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI) is localized at chromosome 21q21 (SNP: rs2824292, odds ratio = 1.78, 95% CI 1.47–2.13, P = 3.3x10
 <sup>-10</sup>).[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] Interestingly, the closest gene to this locus is the 
 <italic>CXADR</italic> gene, which encodes the coxsackie (a member of enterovirus (EV)) and adenovirus receptor (CAR-receptor).[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] Furthermore, electrophysiological studies and molecular analyses on CAR in mice showed that CAR is a novel modifier of ventricular conduction and arrhythmia vulnerability in the setting of myocardial ischemia.[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] Moreover, we and others previously showed that SCD victims and individuals resuscitated from SCA experienced generalized fatigue and influenza-like symptoms in the days to weeks before SCD/SCA,[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] supporting the role of viral exposure in susceptibility to VF during an acute MI. Several studies have shown that influenza vaccine protects against acute MI and heart failure.[
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0226936.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] In addition, because EV and influenza epidemics can be accurately and reliably forecast, such forecasts could advise individuals with chest pain and flu-like symptoms to seek medical care in an early phase during outbreaks.
</p>
