<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig5" position="float">
 <label>Figure 5</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Inhibition exerted by LG on FMDV infection. 
   <bold>(A)</bold> Protein expression. BHK21 cell monolayers were preincubated or not with 10 μM LG and infected with FMDV C-S8 isolate at a M.O.I of 2 pfu/cell. Non-adsorbed virus was washed away and the cultures maintained in the presence or absence of LG for 4 h. Cell extracts obtained at different h.p.i. were subjected to western blot analysis to detect FMDV structural (VP1) and non-structural (3C) proteins. FMDV-induced proteins are indicated by arrows. Molecular weight markers are shown (MW) in the left lane. Graphs show relative quantification of bands corresponding to VP1 and 3C proteins versus α-tubulin expression control. 
   <bold>(B)</bold> RNA quantification. BHK21 cells were preincubated or not with 10 μM LG and infected with FMDV C-S8 isolate at a M.O.I of 2 pfu/cell. Non-adsorbed virus was washed away and the cultures maintained in the presence or absence of LG for 8 h. Total viral RNA (intracellular and extracellular) was extracted at different times p.i. and amplified by RT-qPCR. Data are expressed as VRC (number of viral RNA copies)/ml of total or extracellular virus. Detection limit was 10
   <sup>4</sup> VRC/ml. 
   <bold>(C)</bold> Effect of time of addition of LG on its inhibitory activity. Vero cells were infected with FMDV C-S8 isolate at a M.O.I. of 0.1 pfu/cell (low M.O.I.) or 1 or 5 pfu/cell (high M.O.I.), and 10 μM LG was added at different times before or after infection, maintaining the presence of LG up to 24 h.p.i. when total virus was titrated on BHK21 cell monolayers. Time 0 h.p.i. represents the end of virus adsorption (-2 to 0 h.p.i.). Statistically significant differences between control and LG-treated cells are indicated by asterisks (Student’s 
   <italic>t-</italic>test, *
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05, ***
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001, ****
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.0001).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="fmicb-10-01853-g005" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
