<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For preparedness purposes and to be ready to respond to any unexpected public health event, all countries should have the capacities to implement entry and exit screening at designated ports, airports, and ground crossings. Exit screening measures could be prioritized compared to entry measures, based on past temporary recommendations issued during PHEIC. Evidence from this review suggests that entry screening measures alone are not effective in detecting imported cases at borders, but may allow opportunities for raising awareness and educating the traveling public. The current review further suggests that there are difficulties in assessing the impact of border screening measures. Statistical data demonstrate very low detection rates of cases in both entry and exit screening. The decision about the implementation of screening measures should be examined on a case-by-case basis, after considering the disease and outbreak characteristics, the country situation, and the available resources, which can be compared to the cost and effectiveness of other alternative measures. Screening measures have important concomitant effects when implemented in combination with health education and informative strategies for travelers, the decision-making process should take those effects into consideration. Specificities at each type of point of entry (port, airport, ground crossing) should be considered for the implementation of screening measures, since different approaches are needed for each type of point of entry. The implementation of entry and exit screening measures require planning, allocation of resources, and careful design and application of protocols. Decision-makers should be aware and consider the limitations of screening methods, including false declarations by passengers about exposure and disease signs and symptoms, use of antipyretic drugs to conceal fever by travelers, inability to detect incubating or asymptomatic travelers, language barriers, and false positive and false negative results expected from temperature measuring devices. Based on review results, an algorithm about decision-making for entry/exit screening was developed. Guidance and advice on decision-making related to entry and exit screening measures from international organizations would be helpful to countries when developing their preparedness plans, as well as when deciding about response measures to public health events. Training of staff are among the key issues for implementing a robust screening program at points of entry. </p>
