<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Commercial antibody-capture ELISA-based test kit (Anti-ZIKV IgA, IgG or IgM ELISA) is available, developed by Euroimmun AG (Germany), for serodiagnosis of acute and past ZIKV infections. The assay uses ZIKV-specific NS1 recombinant antigen. The overall sensitivity and specificity of the assay are 100% and 94%, respectively, compared to RT-PCR. Creative Diagnostics (USA) also developed sandwich ELISA-based commercial kit (HIV 1 and 2 Ag/Ab ELISA kit) for qualitative determination of antigens or antibodies to HIV-1 and HIV-2 in human serum or plasma samples. The assay uses recombinant HIV antigens (HIV-1 glycoprotein (gp)41, gp120, and HIV-2 gp36) and anti-HIV viral gag protein p24 antibodies. The LoD of the assay for the detection of HIV p24 antigen is about 1pg/ml. Moreover, Bio-Rad (France) developed NS1 Ag capture ELISA-based commercial kit (Platelia Dengue NS1 Ag) for the qualitative or semiquantitative detection of dengue virus NS1 antigen in human serum or plasma samples. The assay employs anti-NS1 monoclonal antibody (Mab) as capture antibody and anti-NS1 Mab-HRP conjugate as detection antibody. The sensitivity rates of the assay related to virus serotype are 88.9%, 87.1%, 100%, and 93.3% for DENV1, DENV2, DENV3, and DENV4, respectively, compared to RT-PCR, and specificity of the assay is 100% for all serotypes. Recently, Euroimmun AG (Germany) has developed antibody-capture ELISA-based kit (Anti-SARS-Cov-2 ELISA IgG) for qualitative detection of IgG to SARS-CoV-2 in human serum or plasma samples. The assay uses recombinant S1 protein of SARS-CoV-2 as capture antigen. The assay has received EUA from US FDA for use in authorized laboratories. The estimated sensitivity and specificity of the assay are 90% and 100%, respectively, compared to nucleic acid amplification test. Epitope Diagnostics, Inc. (USA) has also developed two types of ELISA kits (COVID-19 IgG ELISA and COVID-19 IgM ELISA Kits) for the detection of anti-SARS-CoV-2 IgG and IgM in human serum samples, respectively. COVID-19 IgG ELISA kit uses SARS-CoV-2 recombinant antigen and HRP labeled anti-human IgG antibody. COVID-19 IgM ELISA employs anti-human IgM antibody and HRP labeled SARS-CoV-2 recombinant antigen. The assays have a LoD of 5IU/ml. The kits are approved by FDA for clinical and research use.</p>
