<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Analysis of selection pressure may suggest whether a mutation is supported or hindered by natural selection, the direction of virus evolution, and possible amino acid sites involved [
 <xref rid="pone.0220249.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0220249.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. On an overall scale, the evolution of H7 and N9, both in terms of time distribution and host species, is under negative selection pressure, which is consistent with previous research results on other subtypes IAVs [
 <xref rid="pone.0220249.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0220249.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Examination of single amino acid sites in AIVs before 2013 or in novel H7N9 AIVs or in avian-derived or human-derived H7N9 AIVs has revealed multiple sites on H7 and N9 that are under positive selection pressure. Only very few positive selection sites formed a 
 <italic>de facto</italic> substitution. This indicates that in the evolutionary process of the novel H7N9 AIVs, purifying selection still played the leading role. Since the emergence of the H7N9 epidemic in China in 2013, more positive selection sites have appeared in overall epidemics and/or human-derived H7N9 AIVs, e.g., 143(135), 148(140), 231(222), 235(226), 276(267)/56(48), 65(57), 67(59), 130(122), 285(276), and 321(312), which are located within the HA1 subunit. These findings are consistent with several recent findings. For example, Xiang et al. and Fang et al. also reported that sites within HA or NA are undergoing positive selection [
 <xref rid="pone.0220249.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0220249.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. This suggests that H7N9 may rapidly vary under the positive selection pressure. It is necessary to strengthen the surveillance of novel H7N9 AIVs, especially those isolated from human, to determine whether a new virus has emerged through selection pressure and to prevent future epidemics from occurring.
</p>
