<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>NLRP3 is an intracellular sensor belonging to the group of NOD-like receptors (NLRs) and is an intracellular sensor of PAMPs and endogenous danger signals. When stimulated by cellular stress or intracellular infection, it activates the NLRP3 inflammasome, a multimeric complex that initiates inflammatory cell death. NLRP3 is primarily expressed by macrophages, monocytes, neutrophils, and DCs [
 <xref rid="B80-viruses-12-00504" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Specifically, the activation of NLRP3 results in the recruitment of apoptosis-associated speck-like protein containing a carboxy-terminal CARD (ASC), the adaptor protein that connects NLRs and capase-1, and assembles a multimeric cytoplasmic complex called the inflammasome. The inflammasome mediates production of the proinflammatory cytokines IL-1β and IL-18. Several influenza virus proteins are associated with the activation of the NLRP3 inflammasome. For example, M2 protein, the proton channel of the influenza virus, activates the formation of the NLRP3 inflammasome [
 <xref rid="B71-viruses-12-00504" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Localization of M2 in the Golgi apparatus is essential for inflammasome activation. Interestingly, influenza virus NS1 proteins inhibit the secretion of IL-1β through interactions with NLRP3 [
 <xref rid="B53-viruses-12-00504" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B81-viruses-12-00504" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. The RNA-binding domain and TRIM25-binding domain of NS1 are associated with NS1-induced NLRP3 suppression. Further, the accumulation of PB1-F2 in the phagosome activates the NLRP3 inflammasome in macrophages [
 <xref rid="B61-viruses-12-00504" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. PB1-F2 peptides trigger IL-1β production, but knockdown of NLRP3 prevent the PB1-F2-induced secretion of IL-1β. These findings suggest that PB1-F2 facilitates activation of the NLRP3 inflammasome. However, another study found that mitochondrially targeted PB1-F2 impairs innate immune responses by suppressing RIG-I signaling and NLRP3 inflammasome activation [
 <xref rid="B82-viruses-12-00504" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. PB1-F2 translocates to the mitochondria in a manner dependent on Tom40 channels and causes defects in mitochondrial dynamics, resulting in the inhibition of RIG-I and NLRP3-mediated innate immune responses. Further studies are required to elucidate the interactions between PB1-F2 and activation of the inflammasome.
</p>
