<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Reports have shown poor outcomes and alarmingly high mortality rates among PLHIV coinfected with M/XDR-TB.
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>–
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> HIV is also responsible for all forms of M/XDR-TB epidemics or outbreaks.
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>–
 <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> TB in PLHIV is mostly smear-negative, and delayed diagnosis due to lack of rapid diagnostic tests and appropriate treatment has led to high mortality in PLHIV. Epidemics of DR-TB and HIV have not only affected different regions of the world but also converged in a deadly syndemic, particularly in sub-Saharan African and Eastern European regions, over the last decade, leading to poor treatment outcomes and high mortality.
 <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>–
 <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> The epidemic of HIV infection in the European region is concentrated within high-risk groups, whereas that in the sub-Saharan African region has affected the general population.
 <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> Outbreaks of MDR-TB among HIV-infected patients between 1985 and 1993 have been observed, even in developed countries, such as the US.
 <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>–
 <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> A Bayesian modeling study reported that HIV epidemics facilitate TB outbreaks only by enhancing increased susceptibility to infections, but that HIV coinfection was not a direct driver for evolution and transmission of DR strains.
 <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref> Development of acquired drug resistance is of concern, due to poor compliance with treatment, deficiencies or gaps in existing knowledge regarding management of diseases, and lack of uniform standards of care or guidelines, causing faulty practices. Other factors responsible for acquired drug resistance are suboptimal anti-TB treatment due to poor maintenance of quality of drugs; prescription of fixed-dose combinations unadjusted for appropriate body weight; intermittent or standardized TB regimens; undetected resistance to H and second-line anti-TB drugs, particularly FQs and SLIDs, at baseline in retreatment cases and high-risk groups; pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic variability; and poor drug penetration to target lesions, rendering drugs ineffective.
 <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>–
 <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> All these factors remain common in people living with or without HIV infection. Primary or transmitted resistance is also responsible for epidemics or outbreaks, as detected by molecular fingerprinting.
 <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> HIV-infected cases progress rapidly to disease, and in settings where M/XDR-TB is prevalent, this may lead to increased numbers of DR-TB patients, either in the general population or local populations, such as hospitals, prisons, and intravenous drug abusers, or an outbreak. PLHIV may also be more likely to be exposed to M/XDR-TB patients, due to either increased hospitalization in settings with poor infection control or association with colleagues with M/XDR-TB, particularly in prison settings. Temporal trends and transmission patterns were analyzed in a study from the US with restriction fragment–length polymorphism among TB patients and clustering of MDR-TB cases observed among HIV patients.
 <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Spread of drug resistance was caused by direct transmission from HIV-seronegative patients. The largest global outbreak of M/XDR-TB occurred in Tugela Ferry of the KwaZulu-Natal region in South Africa in an HIV-positive population, characterized by a high mortality rate of 99%. The main driver responsible for this deadly convergence was not only the evolution of drug-resistance mutations but also transmitted resistance among the surrounding population, unveiled by genotypic tests, including next-generation sequencing.
 <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>–
 <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> Studies from other cities, such as Tomsk, Russia and Shanghai, China, also reported similar findings.
 <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref> A study from Mumbai, India reported an alarmingly high burden of MDR-TB, MDR-TB with additional resistance to FQs or SLIDs, and XDR-TB, with prevalence rates of 38%, 21%, and 6%, respectively, among HIV-infected patients attending public ART centers, likely representing ongoing transmission in the community and health facilities.
 <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> Prevalence rates of mono-DR-TB and poly-DR-TB were 21% and 12%, respectively. Further, the prevalence rate of MDR-TB was 11.4% among new TB cases and 36.4% among retreatment TB cases. Despite existing weakness in the collection of data, the association between HIV and M/XDR-TB is a matter of concern, particularly given the implications for the clinical management of these patients.
</p>
