<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The competitive ELISA procedure described here (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="vaccines-08-00043-f001">Figure 1</xref>) utilized the ELISA Starter Accessory Kit (Bethyl Laboratories, Montgomery, TX, USA). ELISA plates were coated with purified recombinant HA (aa 18–529) (eEnzyme, Gaithersburg, MD, USA); serum samples were incubated with purified recombinant HA (aa 18–529) and head (aa 18–345) proteins from the A/California/7/2009 H1N1 influenza virus (eEnzyme, Gaithersburg, MD, USA). A solution of 5% non-fat dried milk (NFDM; Euroclonelone, Pero, Italy) in 0.05% Tris buffered saline-Tween 20 (TBS-T) (Thermo Scientific, Rodano, Italy) was used for plate blocking. ELISA 96-well plates were coated with the HA protein at a concentration of 1 µg/mL and incubated overnight at 4 °C. For each serum sample tested, three incubation conditions were prepared: 1) the HA recombinant protein in serial dilutions; 2) the head recombinant protein in serial dilutions; and 3) the TBS-T buffer without a protein, which was used for treatment control. Series of two-fold dilutions of HA and head proteins in TBS-T were prepared in rows of dedicated 96-well dilution plates. The starting concentration of the protein was 75 µg/mL in the first well, each well containing a volume of 20 µL of the solution. For each sample tested, one control row of wells containing 20 µL of the buffer (without HA or head proteins) was prepared. Serum samples that were designated for treatment were pre-diluted in TBS-T (1:250) and subsequently added to the prepared incubation rows in a 1:1 ratio; the protein concentration in each incubation well was halved in order to obtain a final serum dilution of 1:500. Reaction plates were incubated for 2 hours at 37 °C. Next, 60 µl of the TBS-T buffer were added to each well containing 40 µL of the serum solution. At the end of this step, each well contained 100 µL of serum that were diluted to 1:1250. Coated plates were washed three times with 300 µL/well of an ELISA washing solution. Plates were blocked and incubated at 37 °C for 2 hours. Blocked plates were washed 3 times with 300 µL/well of washing solution. Subsequently, 95 µL of prepared serum samples from incubation plates were transferred into the corresponding wells of the ELISA plate by means of a multichannel pipette. Experimental plates were covered and incubated at 37 °C for 1 hour. Next, the plates were washed as previously stated, and 100 µL/well of goat, anti-human IgG-Fc HRP-conjugated antibody (Bethyl Laboratories, Montgomery, TX, USA) was added. Plates were incubated at 37 °C for 1 hour. Following incubation, the plates were washed, and 100 µL/well of 3,3′,5,5′-tetramethylbenzidine (TMB) substrate (Bethyl Laboratories, Montgomery, TX, USA) was added and incubated in the dark at room temperature for 30 minutes. The reaction was stopped by adding 100 µL of an ELISA stop solution (Bethyl Laboratories, Montgomery, TX, USA), and then it was read within 20 minutes at 450 nm. Optical density (OD) values were used to draw a graph that confirmed the saturation of the samples with the protein (values reaching the lower plateau of the plot should have been seen in the samples that were treated with the highest concentration of the recombinant protein). Next, a blank OD was subtracted from all raw data results. The results from each serum sample in the three conditions (HA, head and no protein) were selected for stalk OD calculation. For these calculations, only 4 wells (at the lower plateau OD level) were used (e.g., the first four wells with the highest head (HA1) and HA protein concentrations). Results were calculated as follows:
 <disp-formula>
  <math id="mm1">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mi mathvariant="bold">OD</mi>
     <mo>.</mo>
     <mi mathvariant="bold">HA</mi>
     <mn mathvariant="bold">2</mn>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mover accent="true">
      <mrow>
       <mi mathvariant="bold">OD</mi>
      </mrow>
      <mo stretchy="true">¯</mo>
     </mover>
     <mi mathvariant="bold">HA</mi>
     <mn mathvariant="bold">1</mn>
     <mo>−</mo>
     <mover accent="true">
      <mrow>
       <mi mathvariant="bold">OD</mi>
      </mrow>
      <mo stretchy="true">¯</mo>
     </mover>
     <mi mathvariant="bold">HA</mi>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula>
 <disp-formula>
  <math id="mm2">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mi mathvariant="bold">OD</mi>
     <mo>.</mo>
     <mi mathvariant="bold">HA</mi>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mover accent="true">
      <mrow>
       <mi mathvariant="bold">OD</mi>
      </mrow>
      <mo stretchy="true">¯</mo>
     </mover>
     <mi mathvariant="bold">NT</mi>
     <mo>−</mo>
     <mover accent="true">
      <mrow>
       <mi mathvariant="bold">OD</mi>
      </mrow>
      <mo stretchy="true">¯</mo>
     </mover>
     <mi mathvariant="bold">HA</mi>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula>
 <disp-formula>
  <math id="mm3">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mi mathvariant="bold">OD</mi>
     <mo>.</mo>
     <mi mathvariant="bold">HA</mi>
     <mn mathvariant="bold">1</mn>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mfenced>
      <mrow>
       <mover accent="true">
        <mrow>
         <mi mathvariant="bold">OD</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mo stretchy="true">¯</mo>
       </mover>
       <mi mathvariant="bold">NT</mi>
       <mo>−</mo>
       <mover accent="true">
        <mrow>
         <mi mathvariant="bold">OD</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mo stretchy="true">¯</mo>
       </mover>
       <mi mathvariant="bold">HA</mi>
      </mrow>
     </mfenced>
     <mo>−</mo>
     <mfenced>
      <mrow>
       <mover accent="true">
        <mrow>
         <mi mathvariant="bold">OD</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mo stretchy="true">¯</mo>
       </mover>
       <mi mathvariant="bold">HA</mi>
       <mn mathvariant="bold">1</mn>
       <mo>−</mo>
       <mover accent="true">
        <mrow>
         <mi mathvariant="bold">OD</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mo stretchy="true">¯</mo>
       </mover>
       <mi mathvariant="bold">HA</mi>
      </mrow>
     </mfenced>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula> Where 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm4">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mover accent="true">
      <mrow>
       <mi>OD</mi>
      </mrow>
      <mo stretchy="true">¯</mo>
     </mover>
     <mi>HA</mi>
     <mn>1</mn>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> is the average OD of samples incubated with the head (HA1) protein, 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm5">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mover accent="true">
      <mrow>
       <mi>OD</mi>
      </mrow>
      <mo stretchy="true">¯</mo>
     </mover>
     <mi>HA</mi>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> is the average OD of samples incubated with the HA protein, and 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm6">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mover accent="true">
      <mrow>
       <mi>OD</mi>
      </mrow>
      <mo stretchy="true">¯</mo>
     </mover>
     <mi>NT</mi>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> is the average OD of samples incubated with the buffer (non-treated samples).
</p>
