<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As found in studies in other countries in the Northern Hemisphere, we found the number of norovirus outbreaks was highest during October–March (
 <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>17</italic>
 </xref>,
 <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>18</italic>
 </xref>). Person-to-person transmission was the dominant route (95.1%), even higher than has been reported in other countries (
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>11</italic>
 </xref>,
 <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>19</italic>
 </xref>). Almost all (93.7%) outbreaks in our study occurred in childcare centers and schools (primary schools, middle schools, and universities). These outbreak settings have likewise been identified in other Asia countries, such as Japan and South Korea (
 <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>18</italic>
 </xref>,
 <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>20</italic>
 </xref>), as the most common settings for norovirus outbreaks. In contrast, in the United States and Europe, healthcare facilities (primarily nursing homes and hospitals) are the most commonly reported setting for norovirus outbreaks (
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>11</italic>
 </xref>,
 <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>21</italic>
 </xref>,
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>22</italic>
 </xref>). The high proportion of norovirus outbreaks in childcare centers and schools seems unique to China and might be associated with the high population density in these settings (
 <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>23</italic>
 </xref>) and the enhanced monitoring and reporting of any outbreaks in schools in China. In 2006, the national government started to require school officials to check and screen children attending kindergarten, primary school, and middle schools each morning for fever, vomiting, or diarrhea (
 <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>24</italic>
 </xref>). This program has helped facilitate the detection and reporting of infectious diseases, including norovirus, at kindergartens and schools. However, we received few norovirus outbreak reports from other settings involving more adults and elderly persons (such as companies, restaurants, and nursing homes). This difference in the collection of norovirus outbreaks between school and other settings may cause potential bias of the strain patterns of norovirus.
</p>
