<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The basic SIR formulation embodies the dynamics of immunizing infections. Because viruses reproduce rapidly in the host, we ignore within-host kinetics in the simplest SIR models (but see Sect. 
 <xref rid="Sec23" ref-type="sec">8</xref>); depending on model details, this leads to a compartmentalization of the host population between (as yet uninfected) susceptible individuals, infected, recovered, and other classes. An initial taxonomic split here is between the SIR model (which crudely assumes that all infected individuals can pass on infection) and the SEIR (susceptible, exposed, infected, recovered) model, which adds an “exposed” (infected but not yet infectious) class [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. SIR and SEIR models have qualitatively very similar dynamics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]; however, we describe the latter with its more realistic depiction of viral incubation. The basic SEIR model, illustrated in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">5.1b</xref>, reflects the following set of biological assumptions; we use measles as the classic acute exemplar here [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. After a few months of maternally derived passive immunity, infants enter the virus-naïve “susceptible” (S) class; susceptibles can then become infected by close contact with infectious individuals (generally via respiratory aerosol for measles). Infection moves individuals into the “exposed” (E) class, where they incubate but do not transmit the infection for around a week; this leads to the infectious (I) class, where virus is shed, again for approximately a week, after which individuals enter the recovered state (R). In the basic SEIR model, recovered individuals are assumed to be immune for life, both to clinical disease and to retransmitting the infection. However, subclinical infection (and hence boosting of immunity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]) is in principle possible. The lifelong sterilizing immunity induced by such an infection also makes this an excellent potential vaccine candidate [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. For the SEIR model, vaccination is at its simplest assumed to be delivered to a proportion 
 <italic>p</italic> of infants at the end of the maternal immunity period (i.e., near the effective “birth” of susceptibles). For individuals who seroconvert, immunity is then often assumed to be lifelong, moving susceptibles into the recovered class (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">5.1c</xref>). There is also a considerable literature exploring more operationally realistic age distributions and immunogenic characteristics of vaccines in specific cases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].
</p>
