<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">A novel coronavirus, designated 2019-nCoV, by the World Health Organization, is identified as the cause for an outbreak of viral pneumonia first detected in Wuhan city of China and it continues to spread throughout the world (Perlman, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2020</xref>; Zhu et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2020</xref>). These viruses have a characteristic “crown” structures observed by electron microscopy and are classified under the family 
 <italic>Coronaviridae</italic> within the order 
 <italic>Nidovirales</italic>. The coronavirus genome is composed of a positive-sense, single-stranded RNA of about 30Kb, which is the largest non-segmented genome among known RNA viruses. It can cause respiratory, digestive, and nervous system diseases in humans and animals (Hilgenfeld and Peiris, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2013</xref>). Initially, few cases of viral pneumonia were reported in Wuhan, the capital of Hubei province, in December 2019, and most of the patients affected had visited a common local seafood and animal market, which suggested animal-to-person transmission (Huang et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2020</xref>; Wang et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2020</xref>). However, it was later reported that a growing number of patients did not have exposure to animal markets, indicating that a person-to-person spread is occurring (Chan et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2020</xref>). This outbreak brought back memories of the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) outbreak in China in 2003, and the Middle East Respiratory Syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) in Saudi Arabia in 2012 (Hilgenfeld and Peiris, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2013</xref>; Paules et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2020</xref>). As with all previous outbreaks of new virus infections, we are being warned of impending doom concerning the new coronavirus, 2019-nCoV, which is now spreading globally.
</p>
