<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">All known porcine coronaviruses (CoVs) belong to the genera 
 <italic>Alphacoronavirus</italic>, 
 <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic> and 
 <italic>Deltacoronavirus</italic> of the subfamily 
 <italic>Coronavirinae</italic>, in the family 
 <italic>Coronaviridae</italic>, of the order 
 <italic>Nidovirales</italic> (de Groot et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2008</xref>) [
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.ictvonline.org/taxonomy-search.asp?msl_id=30" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://data.ictvonline.org/taxonomy-search.asp?msl_id=30</ext-link> (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">4.1</xref>)]. Affections of gastrointestinal, respiratory, peripheral and central nervous systems are usually visualised. Five swine CoVs are recognised: (1) the transmissible gastroenteritis virus (TGEV), first defined in 1946; (2) the porcine respiratory coronavirus (PRCV), a mutant of TGEV, isolated in 1984; (3) the porcine epidemic diarrhoea virus (PEDV), isolated in 1977; (4) the PHEV (porcine haemagglutinating encephalomyelitis virus) isolated in 1962; and (5) the PDCoV (porcine deltacoronavirus) described in 2012. The first two, TGEV and PRCV, belong to the 
 <italic>Alphacoronavirus</italic> 1 species together with closely associated CoVs of cats and dogs, and PEDV and human CoVs (229E and NL63) form distinct species in the 
 <italic>Alphacoronavirus</italic> genus. PHEV and PDCoV belong to the 
 <italic>Beta-</italic> (
 <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic> 1 species) 
 <italic>and Deltacoronavirus</italic> genera, respectively. PDCoV is closely related to the deltacoronaviruses from Asian leopard cats and Chinese ferret badgers (Ma et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117">2005</xref>). While PRCV induces primarily subclinical infections in pigs, enteropathogenic swine alphacoronaviruses (TGEV, PEDV, SeCoV, porcine enteric alphacoronavirus) and PDCoV are allied with a severe enteric disease of variable severity depending on the animal age and immune status. One serotype is recognised for each swine CoV species.
</p>
