<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0060">We chose 5′-PPP-shRNA against NS1 to perform the dual function of NS1 silencing and RIG-I activation rather than other viral structural components because NS1 is the viral virulence factor that suppresses host innate immune responses to facilitate viral replication. A well-conserved NS1 sequence, along with appropriate controls, was selected to distinguish RIG-I-mediated effects versus NS1 silencing effects by m7G-capping of the 5′-PPP group and scrambling the NS1 sequence. Any antiviral strategy should be applicable to the entire population. A significant number of individuals have defects in type 1 IFN pathways resulting in lack of induction of type 1 IFNs and/or absence or suboptimal responses to type 1 IFN-mediated signaling. In this population, RIG-I-mediated antiviral effects via the 5′-PPP group for type 1 IFN induction will not work. Hence we exploited NS1shRNA-mediated silencing of NS1 to protect the population.
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>25</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>26</sup>
 </xref> This has been clearly shown in 
 <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> using Vero cells that are defective in type 1 IFN signaling cascade. Only NS1shRNAs capped or uncapped were able to suppress NS1 expression, and none of the other constructs were able to suppress NS1 expression through RIG-I-mediated effects via 5′-PPP. In a prophylactic model in cell lines, there was a 3.5–4 log reduction in A/Brisbane/59/2007 viral titers when the cells were infected 6, 12, and 24 h post-transfection of shRNA constructs (
 <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>A). Although the dual-functioning RNA, 5′-PPP-NS1shRNA, is most effective, 7mG-capped NS1shRNA and 5′-PPP-scrambled shRNA are also very effective against viral replication. 7mG-capped control 9.2 RNA and 7mG-capped scrambled NS1shRNA lost their effect, indicating the importance of the 5′-PPP group for RIG-I activation. Using small interfering RNA against nucleoprotein (NPsiRNA) of influenza virus, a reduction of 1–2 logs in viral titer has been reported depending on the amount of 5′-PPP-NPsiRNA used.
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>32</sup>
 </xref> In a therapeutic setting,
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>33</sup>
 </xref> there was 3.5–4 log, 3.5 log, and 1–1.5 log reduction if 5′-PPP-NS1shRNA is transfected 6, 12, and 24 h post-infection. A similar trend is seen with m7G-capped-NS1shRNA (
 <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>A). Corresponding increases in IFN-β and RIG-I, and decreases in NS1 mRNA were also observed. An earlier report utilized 5′-PPP-NS1 silencing RNA and demonstrated only 40%–45% reduction in A/PR/8/34 viral titers in contrast with our 3.5 to 4 log reduction in viral titers.
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>33</sup>
 </xref> The observed poor effectiveness of their approach may be caused by the shRNA sequence, time of transfection of shRNA, and/or the viruses and cell lines (MDCK versus A549) used.
</p>
