<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We used the following environmental variables at sample locations: urban versus rural classification of the cluster, population density, proximity to highways, proximity to cities with more than 250,000 inhabitants, proximity to border crossings and major ports, enhanced vegetation index (EVI), and global human footprint (GHF). EVI reflects the vegetation in an area, in which low values represent areas with no or little green vegetation (e.g., urban areas) and high values represent areas where vegetation is more abundant (e.g., agricultural land, forests, grassland), and can be used as a proxy for degree of urbanization [
 <xref rid="pmed.1003042.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. GHF represents the relative human influence and economic activity, incorporating 9 layers covering infrastructure, land use, population density, and access (coastlines, roads, railroads, navigable rivers). Areas of large human influence and high levels of economic activity are characterised by high GHF values. Population density estimates were originally obtained from WorldPop (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.worldpop.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.worldpop.org/</ext-link>), and data from 2010—the most recent year—were utilised. EVI and GHF were available from the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) Earth Observatory Group (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sedac.ciesin.columbia.edu/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://sedac.ciesin.columbia.edu/</ext-link>). EVI data were available for 2010, and GHF data were available for 2005. Because DHS sample locations are, to some extent, randomly displaced, population density, EVI, and GHF at each un-displaced DHS sample location are also made available for each survey. Locations of major cities were extracted from the World Population Review website (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldpopulationreview.com/worldcities/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.worldpopulationreview.com/worldcities/</ext-link>), and highways were derived from GADM national infrastructure shape files (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gadm.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.gadm.org/</ext-link>) based on Google Maps. Locations of border crossings and major ports were obtained through the Southern Africa Integrated Regional Transport Program report (2010) [
 <xref rid="pmed.1003042.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The shortest Euclidean distances from each DHS sample location to the nearest highway, major city, and border crossing or port were calculated. An overview and description of all included variables can be found in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1003042.s017">S1 Table</xref>. Maps of the included environmental variables are provided in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1003042.s004">S2 Fig</xref> to 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1003042.s010">S8 Fig</xref>.
</p>
