<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An unanticipated observation was that HLA footprints in Mexico overall were sparser (we observed 61% fewer HAPs in Mexico than in Canada/United States) and, on average, were weaker (in terms of lower odds ratios and higher 
 <italic>P</italic> values) than those in Canada/United States. While the higher HLA and HIV diversity in Mexico reduces statistical power to identify associations to some extent, in part because of the need to correct for a larger number of HLA/HIV comparisons, this is not the sole explanation. Similarly, challenges associated with HLA typing of the highly genetically admixed Mexican population was also ruled out as an explanation in detailed sensitivity analyses (see Fig. S1 in the supplemental material). Rather, exploration of our data suggested that the sparse HLA footprint on HIV in Mexico is not due to widespread viral preadaptation (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) to HLA class I alleles (although individual exceptions were noted) but rather were due to weaker or less frequent HLA-restricted CTL responses on HIV, and/or less reproducible viral escape from these responses, in the Mexican population. The canonical B*51:01-RT-I135T association provides an example. Despite similar HLA-B*51:01 and RT codon 135 frequencies across cohorts, this association is significantly weaker in Mexico than in Canada/United States. The observation that RT-135T is not as prevalent among B*51:01-expressing persons in Mexico (47.6%) than in those in Canada/United States (72.4%) (note that the same is true when one considers all RT codon 135 variants, i.e., RT-I135X, which occur in 72% of B*51:01-expressing persons in Mexico and 94% in Canada/United States) while the frequency of RT-135T is comparable (∼20%) in individuals lacking B*51:01 across cohorts suggests that the weaker B*51 footprint on this HIV codon in Mexico is due to weaker B*51:01-mediated immune pressure (and/or less reproducible viral escape) in Mexico than in Canada/United States and is not due to accumulation of this variant in circulation. This observation contrasts with those for Japan, where a similarly weak association between B*51:01- and RT-I135T at the population level in this region instead is attributable to the accumulation of this variant in circulation to the point that it has become the consensus (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>).
</p>
