<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par66">M2e-based vaccines are not available commercially, but some are currently undergoing clinical trials (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). For example, the ACAM-FLU-A vaccine, an M2e-HBc fusion protein, based on an idea by Neirynck [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>], has already passed the first phase of double-blind placebo-controlled clinical trial (NCT00819013, Sanofi). Intramuscular administration of ACAM-FLU-A promoted the formation of anti-M2e antibodies in blood sera in 90% of cases and was well tolerated when given alone or with aluminum hydroxide or QS-21 Stimulon adjuvant (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biocentury.com/bc-week-review/clinical-results/2008-01-07/acam-flu-phase-i-data" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.biocentury.com/bc-week-review/clinical-results/2008-01-07/acam-flu-phase-i-data</ext-link>). However, there has been no further progress with this vaccine since then, probably because of the rapid decline in M2e-specific antibody over time [
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic>clinicaltrials.gov</italic>
 </ext-link> NCT00819013]. A similar recombinant protein HBc-based prototype universal influenza vaccine, “Uniflu”, is currently being evaluated in a single-site, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study in Saint Petersburg, Russia [
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic>clinicaltrials.gov</italic>
 </ext-link> NCT03789539]. The vaccine contains four copies of human M2e fused within the immunodominant loop of the HBc antigen [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">122</xref>]. This study involves 54 healthy adult subjects 18–60 years, and the vaccine is administered intramuscularly in two different doses (20 and 40 μg) twice at a 3-week interval. The results of the trial are anticipated in the near future. 
</p>
