<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Some studies have reported that VP2 is not essential for the formation of VLPs (
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). On the contrary, other studies have suggested that this protein stabilizes and coordinates the formation of VLPs (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). Indeed the absence of VP2 decreases the stability and the homogeneity of the size of NV VLP (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). It has been likewise suggested that the internal location of VP2 in the NV particle and its highly basic nature are consistent with the potential role of VP2 in the capsid assembly and the genomic encapsidation of NV (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Furthermore, 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> studies have shown that the co-expression of VP1 and VP2 increased the expression of these proteins compared to when they are expressed individually. This effect occurs independently of the presence of NS proteins (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). Remarkably, in the same study it was reported that the co-transfection of VP1 and VP2 of GII.4, testing different variants, was found in the cell nucleus of human 293T cells. Moreover, it was shown that VP1 was expressed, located throughout the cytosol, in the absence of VP2. In contrast, VP2 was expressed in the absence of VP1 and was observed to be located in the nucleus (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). In support of this notion, a predicted specific nuclear localization signal has been reported in the HuNoV ORF3, suggesting that VP2 could also serve as a VP1 helper protein, directing this protein complex to the nucleus. This complex could play a role in interfering with the normal cellular processes in the cell nuclei, such as transcriptional and chromatin remodeling processes. Further research is still required to confirm these possibilities because these HuNoV proteins were not found in the nucleus of insect cells (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>).
</p>
