<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In December of 2006, the “APHIS Centers for Epidemiology and Animal Health in Fort Collins, Colorado,” hosted a working group meeting comprised of representatives from several academic institutions and government agencies to discuss the state of research and preparedness for RVF (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Participants presented and discussed key research areas to improve the national capacity to respond to an introduction of RVFV, including more research regarding the relative importance of North American mosquitoes to transmission of RVFV, and the role of wildlife species to enzootic maintenance of RVFV circulation. Since the time of this publication, additional research has been conducted on the vector competence of North American mosquito vectors for RVFV (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), and the susceptibility of deer (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Discussion was held on interagency cooperation and collaboration during outbreak events. On the response side, organized vector control in the US is principally concentrated in larger cities with high human densities. Rural landscapes where the enzootic cycle of RVFV is likely to amplify and spill-over into human and animals generally lacks organized vector control. Vector control in large rural landscapes often relies on partnerships with military capability (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). Similarly, there is a deficit in veterinary surveillance, and the tools to perform this type of surveillance safely. Veterinary surveillance is and will be very important for early detection of invasive vectors and pathogens. As an example, observations of Myiasis in Florida key deer populations in 2016 led to the discovery of an invasion of the screw worm fly, 
 <italic>Cochliomyia hominivorax</italic> (Coquerel), which had been eradicated from the US since 1959 (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). Re-eradication of this fly was declared in March of 2017, after 35 releases of sterile flies (
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). Participants of the RVF Working Group recommended training relevant professionals “to recognize the early signs of an RVF epizootic or epidemic,” and identified a shortage in high containment biosafety laboratories to safely conduct the necessary research (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>).
</p>
