<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>FIG 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Biologically contained WSN/33, 2009 pandemic H1N1, and highly pathogenic H5N1 IAVs expressing 
   <italic>Renilla</italic> luciferase. (A and B) Schematic representations of the reporter virus strategy. The HA segment is modified to encode 
   <italic>Renilla</italic> luciferase instead of the glycoprotein HA but retains specific WSN/33 HA segment noncoding and coding packaging sequences, as shown. The original HA start codon is mutated to prevent erroneous translation. All other segments are fully derived from the respective IAV strain: WSN/33 (H1N1) (
   <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>), A/Netherlands/602/09 (Neth/09; pdmH1N1), or A/VietNam/1203/04 (Viet/04; H5N1). (C) Western blot analysis of MDCK and MDCK-HA cell lines stably expressing each strain-specific HA. Specific antibodies were used to detect HA and actin. (D) Indirect immunofluorescence analysis of MDCK and MDCK-HA cell lines stably expressing each strain-specific HA (green). DAPI was used to stain cell nuclei (blue). Bars, 25 μm. (E) Plaque formation assay for each IAV reporter on MDCK and MDCK-HA cell lines stably expressing each strain-specific HA. Each cell line was infected with the same number of PFU, and assays were fixed and stained 36 h later. (F) Passaging of WSN/33 and WSN/33-
   <italic>Renilla</italic> IAV particles, as well as Neth/09 and Neth/09-
   <italic>Renilla</italic> IAV particles, confirms biological containment of the IAV reporters. Data are means and standard deviations of final virus titers on MDCK cells (
   <italic>n</italic> = 3) following three blind passages on MDCK cells (i.e., transferring half the supernatant to fresh cells every 48 h) after an initial infection at an MOI of 0.001 PFU/cell. (G) Relative levels of HA, as determined by quantitative Western blotting of equal PFU of WSN/33 and WSN/33-
   <italic>Renilla</italic> IAVs. Data are means and standard deviations from four independent Western blots and were normalized to WSN/33 levels. (H) Relative levels of NA between equal PFU of WSN/33 and WSN/33-
   <italic>Renilla</italic> IAVs, as determined by an NA-Star influenza virus neuraminidase inhibitor resistance detection kit. Values from three independent replicates, each performed in duplicate, were normalized to the value for WSN/33. Data are means and standard deviations.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="mSphere.00423-20-f0001" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
