<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="fig5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>FIG 5</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Antiviral drug sensitivity and antigenicity of a biologically contained H5N1 IAV reporter with gain-of-function HA amino acid substitutions. Oseltamivir carboxylate and zanamivir sensitivity of Viet/04-
   <italic>Renilla</italic> and Viet/04-T-
   <italic>Renilla</italic> IAV particles (A and B) was measured using the NA-Star influenza virus neuraminidase inhibitor resistance detection kit. Values from three independent replicates, each performed in duplicates, were normalized to the respective untreated control, plotted, and used to calculate IC
   <sub>50</sub>s with GraphPad Prism 7.05. The data line represents the best-fit curve. (C) MDCK cells were infected with Viet/04-
   <italic>Renilla</italic> or Viet/04-T-
   <italic>Renilla</italic> IAV at an MOI of 0.5 PFU/cell and different concentrations of the S20 fusion inhibitor were added together with the EnduRen substrate. Luminescence (in RLUs) was determined directly in live cells every 3 h and normalized to the value obtained under mock-infection conditions. Area-under-the-curve (AUC) values from three independent experiments were plotted and used to calculate IC
   <sub>50</sub>s with GraphPad Prism 7.05. The data line represents the best-fit curve. (D and E) A monoclonal antibody (D) or a polyclonal serum (E) specific for H5 HA was serially diluted and preincubated with fixed amounts of Viet/04-
   <italic>Renilla</italic> or Viet/04-T-
   <italic>Renilla</italic> IAV for 1 h prior to infection of MDCK cells and addition of EnduRen substrate. Luminescence (in RLUs) was determined directly in live cells every 3 h and normalized to the value obtained under mock-infection conditions. AUC values from three independent experiments were plotted and used to calculate IC
   <sub>50</sub>s (D) or the dilution factor for 50% inhibition (E) with GraphPad Prism 7.05. The data line represents the best-fit curve. For all panels, statistical significance was determined for each concentration by an unpaired two-tailed 
   <italic>t</italic> test and marked where thresholds were reached (*, 
   <italic>P &lt; </italic>0.05; **, 
   <italic>P &lt; </italic>0.01; ***, 
   <italic>P &lt; </italic>0.001).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="mSphere.00423-20-f0005" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
