<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Globally, dengue virus (DENV) is the most commonly transmitted arbovirus and infects an estimated 390 million people per year with greater than half the world’s population at risk of infection [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Chikungunya virus (CHIKV) periodically emerges to cause epidemics in populated areas and is maintained in sylvatic cycles [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In domestic settings, both viruses are primarily transmitted by 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Its prolific adaptation to urban environment, its near-exclusive anthropophilic blood-feeding behaviour, and its proclivity to take multiple blood meals during a single gonotrophic cycle make it the ideal domestic vector [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> belongs to the same subgenus (
 <italic>Stegomyia)</italic> and is considered a secondary vector of DENV and CHIKV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], primarily because of its catholic feeding habits and peridomestic (defined here as city parks and green corridors interspersing housing estates) biology. 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> mosquitoes will utilize oviposition sites distant from human habitats [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], but prefer humans as hosts even when other vertebrates are available [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. This species is a biting nuisance [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] and will enter houses and feed indoors [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Both mosquito species are globally distributed and their ranges are expanding [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], facilitating the increasing spread of DENV and CHIKV. With a partially efficacious vaccine against dengue [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] and an absence of curative treatment for both diseases, vector control remains the sole intervention to mitigate these epidemics. However, re-emergence and recent global intensification in the frequency and scale of dengue and chikungunya outbreaks, especially in large cities, [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] have raised concerns about the sustainability of the current approach targeting domestic vectors [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005667.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].
</p>
