<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A novel coronavirus (CoV) was identified in December 2019 in Wuhan, China. This highly contagious and previously unknown pathogen caused complications in the respiratory system and was named severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). WHO first declared the outbreak of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) a six public-health emergency of international concern, before subsequently declaring it a pandemic [
 <xref rid="B1-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Human coronaviruses (HCoVs) are enveloped, non-segmented, positive-sense, single-strand ribonucleic acid (RNA) viruses [
 <xref rid="B2-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. HCoVs can infect animals and humans, causing respiratory, hepatic, and neurologic diseases [
 <xref rid="B3-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. CoVs are divided into four genera: 
 <italic>alpha-coronavirus</italic> (α), 
 <italic>beta-coronavirus</italic> (β), 
 <italic>gamma-coronavirus</italic> (γ), and 
 <italic>delta-coronavirus</italic> (δ) [
 <xref rid="B2-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Human coronaviruses were identified in late 1960 and are known to infect humans, other mammals, and birds. To date, six HCoVs have been categorized. In 2003, a virus was identified in Guangdong province in China causing severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS). Later, the virus was confirmed as a member of the beta-coronavirus family and was named SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. A decade later in 2012, two Saudi Arabian nationals were identified to be infected with another coronavirus. This virus belongs to the 
 <italic>beta-coronavirus (β)</italic> family and was termed the Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV). In 2019, a novel CoV caused the outbreak of a SARS-like illness in the animal market of the Chinese city of Wuhan and was termed severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus-2 (SARS-CoV-2) [
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].
</p>
