<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The source of origination and transmission are relevant factors for the development of preventive strategies and treatment protocols. SARS coronaviruses may have circulated in humans before causing the outbreak in 2003 [
 <xref rid="B8-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. 
 <italic>Rhinolophus</italic> bats were identified as having anti-SARS-CoV antibodies, thus suggesting the bats were a source of the virus [
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The Middle East respiratory syndrome (MERS) coronavirus (2012) in Saudi Arabia is a beta-coronavirus originating from camels as the primary host [
 <xref rid="B10-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In the case of SARS-CoV-2, only bats were identified as key reservoirs [
 <xref rid="B11-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. COVID-19 originated in Wuhan and was carried through migration by the population to different cities and other provinces around Hubei [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Infection rates increased rapidly and were controlled by a rapid and unprecedented lockdown of cities in the Hubei province followed by further control mechanisms for the whole country [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. This unparalleled approach effectively prevented an exponential increase of infection on a national basis in China [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Similar measurements were implemented by many other countries once cases started appearing within their borders. Enforcement methods and periods of implementation varied from country to country and delivered mixed results. Factors influencing transmission, disease progression, susceptibility, and virulence are surfacing slowly [
 <xref rid="B2-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Park et al. studied clinical and demographic characteristics of 44,672 COVID-19 cases in China and noted that everyone without age limitation is susceptible [
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The fatality rate is highest in elderly, immunocompromised individuals with comorbidities [
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The mean or median incubation time of COVID-19 is less than 13 days and should perhaps be considered to be lower than 4–6 days, similar to SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV median incubation times of 4.4 and 5.5 days, respectively [
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. SARS-CoV-2 is highly contagious and infection may occur by respiratory droplets carrying the virus or through contact with infected surfaces (formites) and subsequently touching mouth, nose, and eyes [
 <xref rid="B15-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Liao et al. reported that particles smaller than 1 μm remain in the air for an unknown time and particles larger than 5 μm settle within one hour [
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Particles with sizes larger than 10 μm, also called droplets, settle much more quickly and cause infections through fomites [
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Thus, airborne transmission happens mainly via smaller particles. Fine particles smaller than 5 μm have the highest virulence factor because they remain in the air longer and can easily reach the lower respiratory tract [
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Particles with a size larger than 5 μm can reach the upper respiratory tract [
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Hou et al. showed that the nasal cavity is the first entry and proliferation point of airborne particles [
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Accordingly, they argue, preventive measures such as wearing masks and using complementary therapeutic strategies on the nasal site may help control the spread of SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-17-05616" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].
</p>
