<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza A virus (IAV), the causative agent of influenza, is a major pathogen that causes public health problem and socioeconomic burden world-wide. With waterfowl as the primary reservoir, the virus is able to infect a wide variety of birds and mammals, including humans. Due to this trait, zoonotic spillovers occur occasionally and can lead to pandemics with severe consequences for the human population [
 <xref rid="B1-viruses-12-00225" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-viruses-12-00225" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The avian-origin H5N1 and H7N9 subtypes of influenza viruses are recent examples of animal viruses that acquired the potential to infect and cause disease in humans. H5N1 IAV are often highly pathogenic (HP) avian influenza viruses. In 1997 in Hongkong, six people died out of 18 confirmed human cases with HP H5N1 virus infection [
 <xref rid="B3-viruses-12-00225" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In 2003, novel H5N1 IAV genetic variants circulated in Southeast Asian countries, which led innumerable poultry to death and caused sporadic human infections in the following years. By the end of 2017, 860 laboratory confirmed cases of H5N1 IAV infection from 16 different countries, resulting in 454 deaths, had been reported to the World Health Organization (WHO) [
 <xref rid="B2-viruses-12-00225" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Influenza A viruses mutate easily because of their segmented RNA genome, making it difficult to produce a timely and sufficiently effective vaccine to prevent the potential epidemic outbreaks. Therefore, using anti-influenza agents could be a more efficient approach for prevention and treatment at the beginning of outbreak. To date, two types of anti-influenza drugs have been approved. One type pertains to the M2 ion channel inhibitors, including amantadine and rimantadine, which block the release of viral RNA into the cytoplasm [
 <xref rid="B4-viruses-12-00225" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The others are neuraminidase (NA) inhibitors, including zanamivir, oseltamivir and peramivir, which prevent progeny virus from being released by their host cells [
 <xref rid="B5-viruses-12-00225" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-viruses-12-00225" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, it has been reported that most of the circulating IAV strains are resistant to M2 inhibitors and may rapidly develop resistance to NA inhibitors, which limits the use of those licensed drugs [
 <xref rid="B7-viruses-12-00225" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-12-00225" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-12-00225" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Therefore, it is urgently required to develop novel anti-influenza agents preferentially with novel mechanisms of action to combat influenza, especially the HP influenza.
</p>
