<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21">Besides accentuating HIV-induced neurotoxicity via glial-mediated mechanisms, morphine appears to converge with HIV Tat to dysregulate ion homeostasis and dendritic injury through potential direct actions on neurons, even though some contributions of glia cannot be excluded in this study (Fitting et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR162">2014a</xref>). Combined morphine and Tat exposure accelerates the formation of Tat-induced focal dendritic varicosities/swelling via a MOR-related mechanism that was caused by focal increases in Na
 <sup>+</sup> influx and [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub>, an overload of Na
 <sup>+</sup>/K
 <sup>+</sup>-ATPase, ATP depletion, and a collapse in mitochondrial inner membrane potential (Fitting et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR162">2014a</xref>). Importantly, morphine’s additive effects were mediated via a MOR-related mechanism, as the exacerbating effects of morphine were absent in neurons from MOR knockout mice, thus excluding TLR4 involvement (Fitting et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR162">2014a</xref>). Further, morphine exacerbated Tat-dependent focal losses in ion homeostasis by mobilizing [Ca
 <sup>2+</sup>]
 <sub>i</sub> through ryanodine-2 (RyR2)-sensitive sites (Fitting et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR162">2014a</xref>) (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Although morphine typically acts via MOR in an inhibitory manner by activating G
 <sub>i/o</sub>-proteins (Sharma et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR462">1977</xref>; Moises et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR343">1994</xref>; Al-Hasani and Bruchas 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2011</xref>), MOR-dependent stimulation of PI3-kinase and Ca
 <sup>2+</sup> mobilization (Leopoldt et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR277">1998</xref>) in neurons via the Gβγ protein subunit (Mathews et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR317">2008</xref>) is presumed operative here (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).
</p>
