<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para280">We chose to study the effects of disruptions to 50% of affected populations. We aimed to show the areas that are most susceptible to disruption among the various services that form part of most countries' national HIV responses and our results should not be taken as a prediction that disruption will be as extensive as estimated here. Such an extensive disruption to ART access as estimated here seems unlikely unless, for example, a country's supply of ART drugs is delayed in being dispatched from the factory or in transit. On July 6, 2020, WHO announced that 73 countries have warned that they are at risk of stock-outs of antiretroviral medicines as a result of the COVID-19 pandemic.
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref> As of July 29, 2020, The President's Emergency Plan for AIDS Relief reported that the median delay in reciving ART drugs is 35 days for adults and 29 days for children.
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref> Deliveries of orders for antiretrovirals are delayed because most manufacturers are based in India (which has been under lockdown in response to COVID-19) and transport challenges. Incoming raw materials from China to India have also been reported to be affected by logistical constraints. Anecdotal evidence from Malawi shows relaxation of eligibility criteria for multi-month dispensing of ART drugs, with around 30–40% of people who live with HIV on ART being on a 6-month refill compared with 10% during the pre-COVID-19 era (Chagoma N, unpublished). We did not specifically consider disruptions of services to key populations, such as female sex workers or homosexual men and other MSM but, given the levels of stigma around these populations, they could be particularly susceptible to interruptions in services. Condom access and other prevention services outside health facilities might be particularly affected at times when movement is restricted. Some form of disruptions affecting sections of the population could last longer than 6 months, especially if health systems are severely affected by loss of personnel or fear of returning to health-care settings if personal protective equipment is not available or access is restricted, and monitoring such effects will be important.
</p>
