<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A few limitations should be considered when interpreting the findings of this study. First, the number of potential correlates of HIV testing and care continuum outcomes that could be explored in this study was limited, because this analysis was based on data collected at screening. Second, some observed frequencies are small, resulting in large odds ratios and wide confidence intervals, affecting the statistical power and stability of the tested models. For instance, the odds of never having tested for HIV are higher in all sites compared to Kisumu, Kenya, but only the odds for Cape Town, South Africa are significant; it is likely that with a larger cohort, the other odds would have been significant as well. Third, the discrepancy between the self-reported HIV status and the results of ARV drug testing indicate that the accuracy of self-report is limited [
 <xref rid="pone.0217501.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. This discrepancy also indicates that the number of persons who were previously diagnosed with HIV infection but had not yet started ART, might actually be higher. Our rationale for analyzing self-reported data is that many HIV care and prevention programs rely on self-report when referring persons for HIV care or prevention services (most ARV assays are research-use only and are not generally available). The discrepancies we observed between self-reported data on HIV status and ARV drug detection highlight the need for more research to identify factors associated with the accuracy of self-reported data. Finally, findings from this study cannot be generalized to all MSM&amp;TW in SSA because of the way in which persons were recruited. It is quite likely that the study recruited more easily accessible MSM&amp;TW, who also might have had better access to HIV prevention and care services. This would imply that the actual status of the HIV testing and care continuum may be worse for African MSM&amp;TW than the findings in this report suggest.
</p>
