<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As antigenic drift is driven by selection pressures exerted by previously infected hosts, characterizing HA-antibody interactions is crucial to understand successful immune escape. Caton and coauthors [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007892.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] experimentally determined the regions on the H1N1 HA onto which antibodies bind, and grouped these residues into the Sa, Sb, Ca1, Ca2, and Cb antigenic sites (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007892.g001">Fig 1A</xref>). Individual host immune responses to IAV infections are guided by infection history [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007892.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. A key question is to determine the regions on the HA that are most targeted by antibodies. Hemagglutination inhibition (HI) and enzyme-linked immunosorbent (ELISA) assays can establish an immunodominance hierarchy, indicating which sites are most strongly targeted by host antibodies. With the PR8 H1N1 strain in mice, Angeletti and colleagues [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007892.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] found this hierarchy to be Sb (highest), Sa, Cb, Ca2, and Ca1 (lowest). In humans and with the A/Michigan/45/2015 H1N1 strain, Liu and coauthors [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007892.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] concluded that Sb was the most immunodominant, followed by Sa, Ca1, Ca2, and Cb; Sb and Sa were significantly immunodominant in contrast to Ca1, Ca2, and Cb. In yet another study, Koel and colleagues [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007892.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] used viruses with HA mutants to determine if single amino acid changes could lead to immune escape. These experiments identified sites near the RBS responsible for the strongest reduction in HI titers for H1N1 (before 2009). Furthermore, these results tie to statistical findings with H3N2 data which showed that, in contrast to known epitope designations, two residue-specific covariates were most important to explain dN/dS scores: These factors are a residue’s distance to the RBS, in addition to its relative solvent accessibility which distinguishes surface versus internal residues [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007892.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].
</p>
