<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Two approaches have been used to develop seasonal IAV LAIVs that differ in the MDV: (1) the US A/Ann Arbor/6/60 H2N2 LAIV (AA) that is commercialized under the names of FluMist in the US and Canada, and Fluenz in the European Union; and (2) the Russian A/Leningrad/134/17/57 H2N2 LAIV (Len) that is commercialized under the names Ultravac (Russia) and Nasovac-S (India) [
 <xref rid="B30-viruses-11-00928" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] and also used in China and Thailand [
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-11-00928" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In the case of the US AA MDV, the mutations responsible for the 
 <italic>ts, ca</italic> and 
 <italic>att</italic> phenotype have been mapped to PB2 (N265S), PB1 (K391E, E581G and A661T) and NP (D34G) [
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-11-00928" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-viruses-11-00928" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In the case of the Russian Len MDV, the mutations responsible for the 
 <italic>ts, ca</italic> and 
 <italic>att</italic> phenotype have been mapped to PB2 (V478L), PB1 (K265N and V591I) and NEP (M100I) [
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-11-00928" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Introduction of the US AA MDV mutations into the genomes of IAVs such as A/Puerto Rico/8/34 H1N1 (PR8) [
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-11-00928" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-viruses-11-00928" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], A/canine/NY/dog23/09 H3N8 [
 <xref rid="B11-viruses-11-00928" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-viruses-11-00928" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-11-00928" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] or A/equine/Ohio/1/03H3N8 [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-11-00928" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] resulted in similar 
 <italic>ts, ca</italic> and 
 <italic>att</italic> phenotypes as that of the original US AA MDV. However, introduction of the mutations of the US AA MDV into the pandemic A/California/04/09 H1N1 virus (Cal/09) resulted in reduced 
 <italic>ts</italic> and 
 <italic>ca</italic> in vitro and limited attenuation in vivo [
 <xref rid="B37-viruses-11-00928" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-viruses-11-00928" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-viruses-11-00928" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. These results suggest that the 
 <italic>ts, ca</italic> and 
 <italic>att</italic> phenotypes induced by the mutations of the US AA MDV are influenced by the virus backbone into which they are introduced. Although some groups have generated recombinant viruses by using the internal genes of AA or the Len (with the LAIV mutations) as MDVs with different HA and NA combinations [
 <xref rid="B40-viruses-11-00928" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-viruses-11-00928" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-viruses-11-00928" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], a direct comparison of the contribution of the US and Russian MDVs residues to viral attenuation, immunogenicity and protection efficacy in the same viral genetic background has not been conducted.
</p>
