<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A single dose of vaccine not only partially protected magpies from a lethal WNV infection, but also significantly reduced viremia. Viremia levels were measured at 4 and 7 d.p.i. Only one out of eight (12.5%) vaccinated birds had viremia titres above 10
 <sup>5</sup> pfu/ml, high enough to consider an infected bird as a competent host to transmit the virus to the vector (
 <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Komar et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">Turell et al., 2003</xref>), while seven out of nine (77.7%) vehicle-inoculated birds reached that threshold. One vehicle-inoculated magpie was still viremic at 7 d.p.i. Similarly, detection of virus in follicles of growing feathers, which could also be considered a source of virus transmission (
 <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Banet-Noach et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Docherty et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Jimenez de Oya et al., 2018</xref>), showed that few of the vaccinated magpies were positive, with significantly lower titres, when compared to non-vaccinated ones. In fact, none of the four contact birds housed with vaccinated animals got infected, while three of the six housed with non-vaccinated magpies were viremic, presented infectious virus in feathers, developed neutralizing antibodies, and one of them succumbed to the infection. Therefore, vaccination of the magpies seems to induce herd immunity, diminishing the risk of both host-to-vector and bird-to-bird virus transmission. This could be of importance for the control of WNV persistence if herd immunity is induced in communal roosting species such as magpies and crows, in which bird-to-bird transmission may represent an important mode of viral persistence outside the seasons with vector activity (
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Hinton et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Montecino-Latorre and Barker, 2018</xref>), Therefore, bird vaccination would really impact on virus maintenance especially if effective ways of administration, as oral delivery, are developed.
</p>
