<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Mayor CRESS DNA viruses detected in animals are represented by circoviruses and cycloviruses belonging to the 
 <italic>Circoviridae</italic> family [
 <xref rid="B176-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">176</xref>]. The susceptibility of carnivores to circoviruses infections have been previously demonstrated in domestic and wild canids [
 <xref rid="B177-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">177</xref>,
 <xref rid="B178-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">178</xref>]. In dogs, these viruses have been found in association with clinical disease characterized by hemorrhagic gastroenteritis, severe necrotizing vasculitis, and granulomatous lymphadenitis [
 <xref rid="B179-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>,
 <xref rid="B180-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">180</xref>]. By converse, information on the epidemiology of circoviruses in the feline host is still limited. The identification of CRESS-DNA genomes in stool samples has been reported only on two occasions [
 <xref rid="B15-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. By metagenomic sequencing, the complete genome of a cyclovirus strain (CyCVs-FD) was acquired assessing pooled fecal samples collected from clinically normal cats in a shelter in Davis, California [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. More recently, by molecular screening of twenty stool samples collected from diarrheic and healthy cats from a private cattery in Japan [
 <xref rid="B15-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], viral DNA was detected in 71.4% (10/14) of animals with enteritis signs and in 50% (3/6) of asymptomatic cats. Full-genome sequence analysis of four strains revealed that these novel CRESS-DNA genomes, called feline stool associated circular viruses (FeSCVs), clustered within the family 
 <italic>Circoviridae</italic>, but into a distinct clade to that of circovirus and cyclovirus. Further investigations aimed to acquire information on the genetic features, epidemiology and pathogenesis of these viruses are needed. Polyomaviruses (PyVs), belonging to the 
 <italic>Polyomaviridae</italic> family, are non-enveloped double-stranded DNA viruses with a circular genome of approximately 5.0 kb in length. PyVs DNA have been occasionally identified in fish, birds, rodents, and primates [
 <xref rid="B181-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">181</xref>,
 <xref rid="B182-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">182</xref>]. Interestingly, novel PyVs have been recently found in cat fecal samples during a diarrhea outbreak in Canada by using a metagenomic approach [
 <xref rid="B19-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Upon sequence analysis, the feline PyVs revealed the highest identity (97.0%) to members of the genus 
 <italic>Alphapolyomavirus</italic> detected in saliva and skin samples of human origin [
 <xref rid="B183-viruses-11-00908" ref-type="bibr">183</xref>] and provisionally named Lyon IARC PyVs (LIPyVs). The etiologic role of LIPyV in feline diarrhea should be investigated as well as its zoonotic potential.
</p>
