<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In an international context, the benefit value was applied in the form of the quality-adjusted life years (QALYs) in the CEA. QALYs are stated as the product of the further life expectancy with a disease/treatment success and a value for the quality of life. The SVR itself only describes the cure rate, without considering the patient’s quality of life. The QALYs benefit measurement therefore has a different calculation approach, which makes it difficult to compare the cost–benefit ratio of our study with international studies that use QALYs as a benefit measurement. The identified ICER values are therefore not comparable with the value determined here, but they do allow the results of this study to be placed into some kind of context. The study by Stahmeyer et al. [
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-17-00440" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] analysed the cost effectiveness of DAA therapy regimens in Germany. The model calculated the life cycle costs and QALYs for SOF with LDV compared to alternative treatments. The analyses show that the application of SOF in combination with LDV for patients with treatment experience compared to other alternative therapies was a compelling proposition with an ICER of €26,426/QALY and a willingness to pay of €30,000. The present model assumes a cost effectiveness with a willingness to pay of €35,167 per patient. This value is higher than that of Stahmeyer et al. [
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-17-00440" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. However, it must be considered that the assumed value related to treated patients, not to QALYs. In their efficiency analysis, Mühlbacher and Sadler [
 <xref rid="B47-ijerph-17-00440" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] studied the DAA therapy options currently available on the market in Germany. In a comparison between the various DAA therapy regimens and the interferon-based triple therapy, SOF with LDV and ombitasvir (OBV) + paritaprevir (PTV) + ritonavir (RTV) + dasabuvir (DSV) ± RBV were the most cost-efficient alternatives. The cost effectiveness of SOF + LDV as presented in the Mühlbacher and Sadler study [
 <xref rid="B47-ijerph-17-00440" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] supports the cost-effectiveness findings of the present study regarding DAA treatment compared to triple therapy. On the international level, several studies have analysed the cost effectiveness of DAAs. Younossi et al. [
 <xref rid="B3-ijerph-17-00440" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] came to the conclusion that the treatment of all HCV patients with interferon-free therapy would be the cheapest strategy with an ICER of $15,709/QALY for treatment-naive patients. For the treatment of HCV genotype 1, triple therapy by disease status and independent of disease status was compared with interferon-free DAA therapy by disease status and without. Chhatwal et al. [
 <xref rid="B48-ijerph-17-00440" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] concur with these findings in their study on the cost -effectiveness of SOF with LDV in a study cohort comprising both treatment-naive patients and patients with treatment experience from the USA. SOF-based therapies exhibited cost effectiveness with an ICER of $55,400/QALY. Zhao et al. conducted a study with comparable results to analyse the cost–benefit relationship of second-generation DAAs. The study compared a triple therapy against DAA regimens SOF + LDV, SOF + SMV, OBV + PTV + RTV + DSV ± RBV. For all DAA treatments, a cost effectiveness with an ICER of $50,828/QALY was found in a comparison with interferon-based treatments [
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-17-00440" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Internationally, the majority of the studies stated cost-effectiveness figures regarding treatment with DAAs, in particular treatments using SOF with LDV, compared to interferon-based therapies. In a comparison of CEAs for DAAs, the underlying data must be considered. This study also takes into account indirect costs such as pension payments. The comparability of the results is therefore limited. In the data used in the present study, only occupational disease reports for HP from non-governmental health institutions in Germany are taken into account. Health care systems, supply structures, and pay systems may vary from insurer to insurer and country to country. 
</p>
