<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Taken together, oncolytic viruses have been shown to prevent neoangiogenesis either by direct infection and destruction of the tumor vasculature, concurrently enhancing innate immunity mediated antitumor effects or by exerting antiangiogenic abilities in tumor tissues. However, before oncolytic viruses can be widely used as therapeutic agents for the clinical treatment of human or animal cancer patients, major obstacles, including potential viral toxicity, ineffective delivery of virus to the tumor, and spread of the virus throughout the tumor mass should first be overcome. To resolve these problems, viral RGS approaches have been recently employed to generate attenuated tumor-selective vaccine strains, as well as selectivity- and efficacy-enhanced, oncolytic virus strains. For instance, MeV was first mentioned as a potential oncolytic agent in anecdotal reports regarding the regression of a Hodgkin lymphoma following natural MeV infection in humans [
 <xref rid="B101-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>]. Attenuated MeV, engineered through RGS to express high affinity single chain T-cell receptors (scTCR), was reported to be retargeted to specific major histocompatibility complex (MHC) ligands [
 <xref rid="B102-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. Genetic modifications of the cellular tropism of MeV were achieved by the insertion of tumor-specific ligands at the carboxyl-terminal extensions of the H protein. Single chain antibodies against the carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA), CD20, and CD38 tumor-associated antigens have all been expressed on recombinant MeV strains to facilitate targeted entry to epithelial carcinoma, non-Hodgkin’s lymphoma, and myeloma cells, respectively [
 <xref rid="B103-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>,
 <xref rid="B104-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>,
 <xref rid="B105-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>]. Furthermore, engineering a MeV that could express integrin-binding peptides, cyclic-arginine-glycine-aspartate (RGD) [
 <xref rid="B106-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>], or echistatin [
 <xref rid="B107-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>], has been shown to successfully retarget the virus to endothelial cells of tumor neovessels. To exert the desired therapeutic effects, while reducing its pathogenicity in hosts, a SLAMblind recombinant wild-type MeV strain was rescued and aimed to specifically infect nectin-4 expressing human tumor cells. Results demonstrated that while the SLAMblind MeV maintained an efficient capacity for infection of human breast cancer cells, the virus caused no symptoms, including immunosuppression, in monkeys [
 <xref rid="B108-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>,
 <xref rid="B109-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. Interestingly, a further study also demonstrated that the SLAMblind MeV could infect canine mammary cancer cells, displaying antitumor activity in vitro, in xenografts, and ex vivo [
 <xref rid="B86-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. Since human and dog nectin-4 proteins share high homology, and the domains critical for the binding of MeV are completely conserved in the two species, this virus could also be considered as a good therapeutic candidate for treating the upregulated expression of nectin-4 in adenocarcinomas of canines [
 <xref rid="B40-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B110-viruses-12-00339" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>].
</p>
