<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0010">
 <label>Table 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Maternal and neonatal characteristics detailed for suspected materno-fetal infection with positive neonatal RT-PCR for SARS-CoV2 at birth.</p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text id="at0090">Table 2</alt-text>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th align="left"/>
    <th align="left">Yu N et al. [
     <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]
    </th>
    <th colspan="3" align="left">Zeng et al. [
     <xref rid="bib0140" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]
    </th>
    <th align="left">Wang et al. [
     <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]
    </th>
    <th align="left">Alzamora et al. [
     <xref rid="bib0170" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]
    </th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>N° of patient</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">1</td>
    <td align="left">1</td>
    <td align="left">2</td>
    <td align="left">3</td>
    <td align="left">1</td>
    <td align="left">1</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Age of patiente</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">34</td>
    <td align="left">NS</td>
    <td align="left">NS</td>
    <td align="left">NS</td>
    <td align="left">34</td>
    <td align="left">41</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Gestational age at infection (WG, d)</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">39,3</td>
    <td align="left">40</td>
    <td align="left">40,1</td>
    <td align="left">29,6</td>
    <td align="left">40</td>
    <td align="left">32.3</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Gestational age at admission (WG, d)</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">39,6</td>
    <td align="left">40</td>
    <td align="left">NS</td>
    <td align="left">NS</td>
    <td align="left">NS</td>
    <td align="left">33</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Term of delivery</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">40</td>
    <td align="left">40</td>
    <td align="left">40,4</td>
    <td align="left">31,2</td>
    <td align="left">40</td>
    <td align="left">33</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Infection to delivery interval (days)</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">4</td>
    <td align="left">0</td>
    <td align="left">0</td>
    <td align="left">3</td>
    <td align="left">0</td>
    <td align="left">4</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Maternal clinical characteristics</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">This patient present common COVID-19 disease with only fever as symptom, and abdominal pain (labour).</td>
    <td align="left">Only fever was reported as symptom and pneumonia per computed tomography diagnosis was made. The delivery was by cesarean delivery because of meconium-stained amniotic fluid and confirmed maternal COVID-19 pneumonia</td>
    <td align="left">Only fever and cough are described. Cesarean section was performed because of confirmed maternal COVID-19 pneumonia</td>
    <td align="left">No symptoms was report for COVID-19, only a close contact wit a diagnosed patient. Cesarean section was made after premature rupture of membrane because of fetal distress and confirmed maternal COVID-19 pneumonia</td>
    <td align="left">The pregnant woman developed small amount of per vaginal bleeding and lower abdominal pain. Two hours later, she developed a fever (37.8 °C) and attended to medical care center. Thoracic computerized tomography scan showed ground-glass opacities in the left upper and lower lobes, indicating the possibility of viral pneumonia. Blood tests revealed lymphopenia, neutrophilia and elevated CRP level (11.5 mg/L, normal: &lt;1 mg/L). She was hospitalized for suspected viral pneumonia. On admission, her body temperature was 37.8 °C and her blood pressure was 131/89 mmHg, with respiratory rate of 20 breaths per minute, pulse of 96 beats per minute. She had no cough or sputum. Emergency Cesarean section was performed.</td>
    <td align="left">The patient presented with a 4-day history of general malaise, fatigue, and low-grade fever, and later developed worsening shortness of breath, which prompted her to seek medical attention. In the emergency department, the patient’s pulse was 131 beats per minute, the respiratory rate 38 breaths per minute, and the oxygen saturation 99% with a FiO2 of approximately 90%. Her body mass index (BMI) was 35 kg/m2. Laboratory tests showed metabolic acidosis on arterial blood gases, pancytopenia, elevated C-reactive protein, elevated ferritin, and slightly elevated D-dimer and glucose. The patient was intubated and placed on mechanical ventilation due to severe respiratory insufficiency in the setting of suspected COVID-19. The patient underwent a cesarean delivery due to maternal respiratory compromised status</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Mode of delivery</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">ceasarian section</td>
    <td align="left">ceasarian section</td>
    <td align="left">caesarian section</td>
    <td align="left">caesarian section</td>
    <td align="left">Caesarian section</td>
    <td align="left">Caesarian section</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Maternal RT-PCR in nasopharyngeal swab</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">Positive</td>
    <td align="left">Positive</td>
    <td align="left">Positive</td>
    <td align="left">Positive</td>
    <td align="left">Positive</td>
    <td align="left">Positive</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Maternal RT-PCR + in feces</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Maternal RT-PCR + in vaginal swab</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Maternal RT-PCR + in breast milk</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">0</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">N° of newborn</td>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>1</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">1</td>
    <td align="left">2</td>
    <td align="left">3</td>
    <td align="left">1</td>
    <td align="left">1</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Preventive mesurement</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">All the patients delivered infants by caesarean section, and then the neonates were transferred to the neonatology department.</td>
    <td align="left">Strict infection control and prevention procedures were implemented during the delivery</td>
    <td align="left">The mother had been wearing an N95 mask throughout the operation, and the baby had no contact with the mother after birth. The infant was transferred to neonatology department 10 minutes after birth for close observation and the mother was transferred to the fever ward for isolation after surgery.</td>
    <td align="left">He was immediately separated from his mother and was not exposed to family members, who were at home under strict isolation measures. Due to the maternal condition, maternal medical regimen, breastfeeding was not initiated. He was placed in the neonatal intensive care unit (NICU) with no other COVID-19 cases.</td>
    <td align="left"/>
    <td align="left"/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Neonatal clinical characteristics</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">After ceasarean section, a 3250 g newborn was managed without neonatal complications. The neonate had no fever and cough, with mild shortness of breath. symptoms. Chest x-ray revealed mild pulmonary infection. The shortness of breath relieved quickly under neonatal care and monitoring. The neonate was discharged after 2 weeks following two consecutive negative nucleic acid test results.</td>
    <td align="left">On day 2 of life, the infant experienced lethargy and fever, with unremarkable physical examination results, and was moved to the neonatal intensive care unit. A chest radiographic image showed pneumonia, but other laboratory tests. (except procalcitonin) were normal. Nasopharyngeal and anal swabs were positive for SARS-CoV-2 on days 2 and 4 of life and negative on day 6</td>
    <td align="left">He presented with lethargy, vomiting, and fever. A physical examination was unremarkable. Labora- tory tests showed leukocytosis, lymphocytopenia, and an elevated creatine kinase–MB fraction. A chest radiographic image showed pneumonia. Nasopharyngeal and anal swabs were positive for SARS-CoV-2 on days 2 and 4 of life and negative on day 6</td>
    <td align="left">Resuscitation was required. The infant’s Apgar scores were 3, 4, and 5 at 1, 5, and 10 minutes after birth. Neonatal respiratory distress syndrome and pneumonia confirmed by chest radiographic image on admission resolved on day 14 of life after treatment with noninvasive ventilation, caffeine, and antibiotics. He also had suspected sepsis, with an Enterobacter agglomerates– positive blood culture, leukocytosis, thrombocytopenia (11 cells × 103/μL; to convert to cells × 109/L, multiply by 1.0), and coagulopathy (prothrombin time, 21 seconds; acti- vated partial thromboplastin time, 81.9 seconds), which improved with antibiotic treatment. Nasopharyngeal and anal swabs were positive for SARS-CoV-2 on days 2 and 4 of life and negative on day 7</td>
    <td align="left">a baby boy was delivered, weighted 3205 g. Apgar scores at 1 and 5 minutes were 8 and 9. The infant had no moaning or spitting after birth. The skin was ruddy and the crying was loud. Half an hour after birth, the infant vomitted once after feeding formula, which we considered to be swallowing syndrome. After gastric lavage, the infant could be fed normally. Blood tests of the neonate revealed lymphopenia, deranged liver function tests and elevated creatine kinase level. Intravenous penicillin G and vitamin K1 were given as antibiotic prophylaxis and to prevent coagulopathy, respectively.</td>
    <td align="left">The neonate weighed 2,970 g, with Apgar’s scores of 6 and 8 at 1 and 5 minutes, respectively. The neonate was intubated in another room due to the high level of sedation of the mother. The newborn required ventilatory support for 12 hours, after which he was extubated and placed on continuous positive airway pressure, with favorable outcome and not requiring antibiotic treatment. At the sixth day of life, the newborn presented mild respiratory difficulty and sporadic cough requiring supplemental oxygen with nasal cannula. Imaging and laboratory testing remain normal.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Neonatal RT-PCR in nasopharyngeal swab</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Positive</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Positive</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Positive</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Positive</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Positive</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Positive</bold>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Birth to positive neonatal PCR interval (hours)</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">36</td>
    <td align="left">48</td>
    <td align="left">48</td>
    <td align="left">48</td>
    <td align="left">36</td>
    <td align="left">16</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Neonatal RT-PCR in amniotic fluid</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Neonatal RT-PCR in placenta</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">Negative</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">Negative</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>Neonatal RT-PCR 2 in cord blood</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">Negative</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">Negative</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left">
     <bold>IgM for SARS-CoV-2 in newborn</bold>
    </td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">NP</td>
    <td align="left">Negative</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot>
  <fn>
   <p>NP = not performed / NS= Not stated.</p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
