<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>IRF-9 is a transcription factor essential for IFN signaling and the transcriptional induction of ISGs [
 <xref rid="B60-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. STAT1 and STAT2, when phosphorylated, associate with IRF-9 to form a heterotrimeric ISG factor 3 (ISGF3) complex [
 <xref rid="B60-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], which translocates to the nucleus, and binds ISREs present in the promoters of ISGs, up-regulating their transcription [
 <xref rid="B60-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. A homozygous, loss-of-function mutation in IRF-9 was described in a child born to first-cousin Algerian parents and living in France affected by a severe pulmonary influenza infection [
 <xref rid="B115-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>]. In particular, the homozygous mutation (c.991G&gt;A) occurred in the final nucleotide of exon 7 and disrupted the essential splice site at the boundary of exon 7 and intron 7, leading to deleted IRF-9 proteins. The consequence of this mutation was an impaired activation of IRF-9, and therefore, an impaired transcription of ISGs, many of which show antiviral activities [
 <xref rid="B115-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>]. Similarly, a family in which several members showed a surprising susceptibility to infection by different viruses, including IAV, also showed to be IRF9 deficient [
 <xref rid="B116-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>]. The index patient, a boy with 10 years born at term from healthy consanguineous parents (first cousins of Portuguese origin and residing in Venezuela) encoded a homozygous splicing mutation in the IRF9 gene. The mutation, c.577+1G&gt;T, was located in the donor splice site of introns 5 and 6, leading to transcripts lacking exon 5. IRF9 protein expression was undetectable in cells transfected with the c.577+1G&gt;T IRF9 construct, suggesting that either the protein was quickly degraded or the mRNA was not translated. Again, IRF9-deficient cells showed a profound defect in inducing the expression of multiple ISGs [
 <xref rid="B116-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>]. Collectively, these findings show that human IRF9- and ISGF3-dependent type I and III IFN responsive pathways are essential for controlling viral infections, including IAV.
</p>
