<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par25">The diagnosis of infectious diseases depends on the identification of the pathogen [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]. The identification of pathogens mainly includes “virus isolation” and “nucleic acid detection”, but because “virus isolation” requires a high level of biosafety in the laboratory, it is mainly used in scientific research. Clinical diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2 mainly relies on “nucleic acid testing”. According to the transmission characteristics of SARS-CoV-2, nasopharyngeal swabs, sputum, respiratory secretions, alveolar lavage fluid, blood, feces and other samples of the infected person can be used as the source of samples for viral nucleic acid detection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]. In a study, by detecting the nucleic acid content of novel coronavirus in sputum samples of 92 infected patients, it was found that the virus content in sputum samples of severely infected patients was higher than that of mildly infected patients, among which 11 patients with aggravated illness had higher nucleic acid content of novel coronavirus in sputum samples [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>]. In addition to detecting viral nucleic acids, antibody detection in serum of healthy people is a relatively fast screening method. Studies have shown that IgG and IgM can be detected in the second week after SARS-CoV-2 infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]. At present, SARS-CoV-2 nucleic acid detection kit approved by China national medical products adminstration mainly uses real-time fluorescence quantitative PCR method to detect specific genes of viral nucleic acid [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>]. The detection kits of real-time fluorescence quantitative PCR are mainly divided into two categories: double real-time fluorescence quantitative PCR and triple real-time fluorescence quantitative PCR, both using Taqman probe method. The target genes detected by double method were mainly 1ab and N gene, while those detected by triple method were 1ab, N and E gene. In addition, viral genome sequencing can also identify the sequence and function of SARS-CoV-2. This method is better than the real-time fluorescence quantitative PCR method for the detection of early samples with low virus content, but it is also less applied due to the lack of sequencing equipment and bioinformatics analysts. Therefore, real-time fluorescence quantitative PCR is the main method to detect viral nucleic acid. As a designated hospital for local nucleic acid testing, the department undertakes the testing of most suspicious samples in the region and surrounding areas. In order to ensure reliable test results, we have developed a set of quality control procedures, hoping to provide assistance for nucleic acid testing.
</p>
