<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Antimicrobial resistance (AMR) is the ability of bacteria, parasites, viruses or fungi to grow and spread in the presence of antimicrobial medicines that are normally active against them [
 <xref rid="B1-ijerph-17-01395" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. AMR has currently become an alarming threat for human health in the world. A recent report estimated that 10 million deaths will be attributed to AMR by 2050, and 100 trillion USD of the world’s economic outputs will be lost if substantive efforts are not made to contain this threat [
 <xref rid="B2-ijerph-17-01395" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-ijerph-17-01395" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. According to the World Health Organization (WHO) estimates, there were 460,000 people infected with multi-drug resistant tuberculosis (MDR-TB) in 2017 globally [
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-17-01395" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], and drug resistance continues to complicate the fight against many other infectious diseases, such as HIV, malaria and gonorrhea, as well. As the serious infectious diseases in the world, tuberculosis, HIV and malaria share the common threat of AMR while gonorrhea has been listed as one of the antibiotic-resistant “priority pathogens” by WHO [
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-17-01395" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Resistance to antimalarial drugs has threatened global success in control of malaria since the emergence of resistance to chloroquine in the 1970s [
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-17-01395" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. During the 1990s, sulphadoxine-pyrimethamine was introduced in many African countries to replace chloroquine. However, it encountered drug-resistant parasites about a year after this introduction [
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-17-01395" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Artemisinin combination therapies (ACTs) are now recommended as the first-line treatments for uncomplicated 
 <italic>P. falciparum</italic> malaria worldwide. Unfortunately, emergence of artemisinin resistant parasites had been observed recently in Cambodia, Southeast Asia, potentially fostering an increase in malaria cases and deaths [
 <xref rid="B8-ijerph-17-01395" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Resistance to streptomycin was detected in a large majority of TB patients treated with this drug as early as in 1940s [
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-17-01395" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Shortly afterwards, a spread of this drug-resistant strains was recognized and continued in an ever wider geographic area despite changing the regime by combining this drug with others. MDR-TB is defined as TB caused by strains of 
 <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> that are resistant to at least isoniazid and rifampicin [
 <xref rid="B10-ijerph-17-01395" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Extensively drug-resistant TB (XDR-TB) is caused by 
 <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> resistant to at least isoniazid and rifampicin, to any fluoroquinolone and to at least one of three injectable drugs used in anti-TB treatment (capreomycin, kanamycin, amikacin) [
 <xref rid="B11-ijerph-17-01395" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. HIV strains began to acquire resistance in 1987 when antiretroviral drugs (ARVs) were introduced as therapies for HIV-infected individuals [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-17-01395" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Since then, a multitude of drug-resistant strains have evolved that differ considerably in their susceptibility to three major classes of ARVs: nucleoside reverse-transcriptase inhibitors (NRTIs), non-nucleoside reverse-transcriptase inhibitors (NNRTIs), and protease inhibitors (PIs). These drug-resistant strains are now being transmitted to individuals who have never received ARVs; that is, transmitted drug resistance has arisen.
</p>
