<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>These analyses are computationally demanding and therefore cannot (yet) deal with extremely large datasets. A major argument against the use of historical analyses is that these analyses can potentially identify transmission pairs and thus predict the direction and directness of virus transmission among sampled individuals. As stated above, this knowledge can be extremely important for public health decisions on prevention efforts but can be abused in the wrong hands. It can lead to community distrust, fewer diagnoses, increased stigma, and ultimately more HIV transmissions and fewer people that receive antiviral treatment [
 <xref rid="B6-viruses-12-01018" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In jurisdictions with criminal HIV laws there is also the concern of prosecution of transmitting HIV [
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-12-01018" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. While these analyses are inherently uncertain and are based on probabilities, this distinction is easily lost when communicating the results of these kinds of analyses. It is therefore important to clarify that “who infected whom” is a statistical statement about what the model “thinks” and should not be confused with a legal statement. The colloquial interpretation of probabilities as a form of belief may be at odds with the technical use of probability as a measure of uncertainty, which can lead to unintended implications. However, the reconstructing of epidemiological history from pathogen genetic sequence data is 
 <italic>fundamentally</italic> uncertain in that the genetic sequence data can never in practice perfectly constrain a phylogenetic tree that forms the basis of such a reconstruction. That is, a reconstruction of an epidemiological history based on real data that properly considers uncertainty from all sources such as the uncertainty in the underlaying phylogeny will almost never lead to statements such as “we are 95% certain that A infected B”. We illustrate this idea in the next section where we show how a phylogenetic reconstruction might work and the kinds of information that we would get from such an analysis.
</p>
