<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The rapid influenza diagnostic test (RIDT) offers a faster approach for detecting both influenza A and B viruses. However, it has limited ability to further identify the subtypes of influenza viruses. In addition, its test performance (ie, sensitivity and specificity) varies widely. For example, in November 2009, 290 suspected influenza patients were analyzed using direct antigen EZ Flu A+B kit. The sensitivity and specificity of RIDT were 40.5% and 94.5%, respectively.
 <xref rid="jmv25674-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>45</sup>
 </xref> NAAT assays based on polymerase chain reaction (PCR) detect virus‐specific genetic materials, rather than viral antigens or antibodies. Therefore, optimal extraction of viral genetic materials is required. One of the advantages of NAAT over RIDT is that NAAT is able to identify different subtypes of influenza viruses. Trombetta's group found that NAAT shows much higher sensitivity for both influenza A and influenza B viruses, despite its relative lower specificity.
 <xref rid="jmv25674-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref> A variety of NAAT assays, such as reverse transcriptase‐PCR, loop‐mediated isothermal amplification‐based assay (LAMP), DNA‐microarray‐based and sequencing‐based tests, are appearing for diagnosis of influenza viral infections in humans.
 <xref rid="jmv25674-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref> Using the LAMP approach, Poon's group demonstrated 100% sensitivity for detection of seasonal influenza A H1N1 and H3N2 viruses from clinical specimens with analytical sensitivity of 10 copies per reaction.
 <xref rid="jmv25674-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref> Compared with the RT‐PCR‐based assay, a real‐time reverse transcription LAMP‐based assay (RT‐LAMP) showed a sensitivity of 97.8% and a specificity of 100% for detecting 2009 H1N1 pandemic virus.
 <xref rid="jmv25674-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref> LAMP‐based assays have also been used to detect the highly pathogenic H5N1 and H7N9 avian influenza viruses, having comparable, or higher, sensitivities than RT‐PCR‐based approaches.
 <xref rid="jmv25674-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv25674-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jmv25674-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref> However, the high cost of NAAT, the complexity of the equipment required, and the need for trained professionals make NAAT assays less practical in areas with limited resources.
</p>
