<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The odds of cooking with firewood in the main house were less among patients with arboviral infections than among controls. HAP exposure is likely higher in households with kitchens in the main household rather than in a separate location [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. We did not find associations between arboviral infections and cooking with firewood outside or in a kitchen separate from the main house, implying that any arboviral-protective benefit from smoke exposure might be limited to confined household spaces. In Guatemala, approximately 90% of urban households and 70% of rural households conduct cooking activities inside the main house [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Previous studies have demonstrated that firewood smoke was effective at reducing the number of 
 <italic>Anopheles spp</italic>. found in households [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. To our knowledge, only two studies have assessed kitchen location in relation to mosquitoes or mosquito-borne diseases. In Laos, cooking fires in the main living area or directly underneath houses were associated with fewer 
 <italic>Anopheles spp</italic>. than fires in rooms separate from the house [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In Ethiopia, individuals living in households that had a separate kitchen outside of the sleeping room were at greater risk for malaria [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. However, we are unaware of any studies examining the impact of cooking with firewood on arboviral infections. In Guatemala, cooking activities are carried out for approximately 13 and 14 hours per week in urban and rural areas, respectively [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Additionally, women spend 4.6–6.8 hours in the kitchen per day [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Cooking activities, which are mostly done in the daytime [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], likely have a differential effect on 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic>, which are primarily daytime feeders compared to 
 <italic>Anopheles spp</italic>., which are nocturnal but may include crepuscular feeders [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> preferentially rest indoors in dark places (e.g., on walls, in closets, or underneath furniture) and lay eggs in artificial containers around households [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>], whereas 
 <italic>Anopheles spp</italic>. rest indoors and outdoors, but prefer marshes, trees, swamps, fields, streams, and rivers as oviposition sites [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> are also more likely to bite indoors than outdoors [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>], whereas 
 <italic>Anopheles spp</italic>. mostly bite outdoors [
 <xref rid="pone.0234399.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>].
</p>
