<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In vitro studies are now being performed to evaluate the effects of CQ or HCQ on SAR-CoV-2. One study has concluded that HCQ was found to have more potent antiviral activity as compared to CQ alone [
 <xref rid="B100-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>]. A recent in vitro study has tested the effects of five already available drugs against 2019-nCoV infection, namely ribavirin, penciclovir, nitazoxanide, nafamostat and CQ [
 <xref rid="B91-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. The highlight of their results has found that two of the drugs, ribavirin, and CQ showed excellent potential in blocking virus infection at low drug micromolar concentrations. Another study recommends the usage of CQ phosphate as the potential treatment of COVID-19 in this time as it has exhibited efficiency in treating COVID-19 associated pneumonia presented in patients. In addition, CQ has been considered the potential drug of choice as it can be produced on a larger scale for global distribution compared to other potential drugs against COVID-19 such as Remdesivir [
 <xref rid="B87-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. Moreover, it has a proven safety record for patient usage and is relatively low cost as compared to the other listed drugs. HCQ sulphate has been studied for its antiviral effect on SARS-CoV-2 infection and has been compared with CQ alone for cytotoxicity in vitro using African green monkey kidney VeroE6 cells [
 <xref rid="B87-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. This study has successfully shown that HCQ sulphate is effective in inhibiting SARS-CoV-2 infection and may be a better option for consideration in clinical trials for patient administration as it has a less toxic effect on cells as compared to CQ alone [
 <xref rid="B87-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. In contrast to this result, another study evaluated HCQ sulphate for SARS-CoV-2 antiviral effects and concluded that although overall clinical scores did decrease in COVID-19 positive ferrets after HCQ treatment, little effects were observed in virus titres of nasal washes, stool specimens and respiratory tissues when compared to other treatments or phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) treated groups [
 <xref rid="B95-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. In addition to using HCQ, a study by Gautret et al. evaluated the combination of HCQ in combination with the antibiotic azithromycin. This study has reported that the combination of these two drugs is associated with more efficient viral load reduction and disappearance of COVID-19 in twenty patients [
 <xref rid="B14-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Despite the many studies mentioned here, it is yet uncertain whether CQ or HCQ are indeed completely effective in treating COVID-19 as some trials and studies have yet to conclude the certain effects. As with most drugs in consideration for repositioning, thorough evaluations may take some time in order to declare them safe and effective for treatment. A highly regarded concern that comes along with drug selection are the side-effects or adversities of the drug to be used for treatment. 
 <xref rid="viruses-12-01058-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> summarises the side-effects along with other information for some of the current medications under the drug repositioning spotlight for COVID-19. The side-effects mentioned are specific to observation from COVID-19 patients in each clinical trial or study.
</p>
