<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Understanding mechanisms by which pathogens transmit between hosts is key for defining disease risk and for planning effective control strategies. In addition to direct host‐to‐host or vector‐borne transmission, pathogens can spread through environmental sources, such as through contact with fomites (Allerson, Cardpna, &amp; Torremorell, 
 <xref rid="ece36100-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>), ingestion of contaminated drinking water (Breban, 
 <xref rid="ece36100-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Kraay et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36100-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>), contact with contaminated soil (Turner et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36100-bib-0064" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>), contact with contaminated carcasses (Chenais, Ståhl, Guberti, &amp; Depner, 
 <xref rid="ece36100-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>), or carcass scavenging (Brown &amp; Bevins, 
 <xref rid="ece36100-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Wille et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36100-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). Environmental sources of infection can promote pathogen persistence by increasing their likelihood of contact with susceptible hosts because many pathogens can remain viable in the environment longer than they can keep a host infectious. For example, epidemiological models demonstrate that pathogens can persist in small populations at very low levels of prevalence when infectious agents remain viable in the environment (Breban, 
 <xref rid="ece36100-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). For wildlife populations with seasonally varying densities, environmental sources of infection can ignite seasonal epidemics during low‐density periods when susceptible hosts are not frequent enough to continuously maintain pathogen transmission through direct contact (Sauvage, Langlais, Yoccoz, &amp; Pontier, 
 <xref rid="ece36100-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). The persistence of infectious agents in environmental reservoirs can enable high pathogen reproductive numbers when epidemic growth rates are low by extending the infectious period beyond the life expectancy of the host (Almberg, Cross, Johnson, Heisey, &amp; Richards, 
 <xref rid="ece36100-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). In some systems, environmental transmission mechanisms can explain recurrent epidemics (Towers et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36100-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>), even at intervals that are longer than demographic cycling (Breban, 
 <xref rid="ece36100-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>), as well as amplifying rates of interpopulation transmission by increasing infectious contact opportunity between groups (Kraay et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36100-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). Theoretical metapopulation modeling has shown that accounting for mechanisms of environmental transmission in addition to routes of direct transmission can lead to qualitatively different disease dynamics and predict different animal movement thresholds for metapopulation decline (Park, 
 <xref rid="ece36100-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). Although optimal disease management strategies require knowledge of transmission mechanisms to identify appropriate control points, quantifying the relative role of environmental transmission relative to other transmission mechanisms has been elusive for most host‐pathogen systems (but see Towers et al., 
 <xref rid="ece36100-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>).
</p>
