<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza A pandemics have caused considerable disease and deaths. While influenza A and B cause only acute febrile illness in a majority of infected people, people at high risk, including pregnant women, children below the age of five years, elderly people aged more than 65 years, and persons with chronic medical conditions, can develop severe disease which may be lethal [
 <xref rid="B64-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Influenza infections may promote and intensify numerous conditions like chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) [
 <xref rid="B65-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>] and, asthma [
 <xref rid="B66-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]; They can increase the risk of a cerebro-vascular accident and myocardial infarction [
 <xref rid="B67-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], and fetal loss in pregnant women [
 <xref rid="B68-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Though antiviral therapies, drugs, and vaccines are available, influenza viruses still threaten humans and animals all over the world. The diversity of the virus enables it to have multiple hosts, while antigenic drift and shift play major roles in the wide occurrence of epidemics and pandemics [
 <xref rid="B69-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Mouse models have played a significant role in delineating the pathogenesis of influenza and in the development of vaccines and therapeutics against the different types of the virus. Laboratory inbred strains of mice, such as BALB/c, C57BL/6, and DBA/2j, can be infected with mouse adapted strains of influenza. DBA/2j is highly susceptible to non-adapted influenza strains [
 <xref rid="B72-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. The most common symptoms exhibited by the infected mice include hypothermia, anorexia, and weight loss. However, depending on the dose and the strains of the influenza virus used, the infection might be lethal. The most commonly used mouse adapted strains of influenza include H1N1 influenza A/Puerto Rico/8/34 (PR8) or H1N1 influenza A/WSN/1933 (WSN). However, certain strains, such as the 1918 H1N1 pandemic influenza A and the 2009 H1N1 pandemic influenza A, do not require adaptation to infect mice [
 <xref rid="B72-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-viruses-11-00252" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. The lack of suitable small-animal models for studies of influenza pathogenesis and for the development of vaccines and antivirals is one of the most serious obstacles to progress in research.
</p>
