<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As mentioned above, outpatient visits are the most frequent medically attended events associated with influenza infection. But to measure the impact of influenza vaccination during pregnancy on hospitalizations that could be precipitated by influenza infection is of crucial importance. Four observational studies reported on the impact of maternal vaccination on laboratory-confirmed influenza hospitalizations in infants 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, 
  <xref rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>– 
  <xref rid="ref-63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>
 </sup>. Although there are a number of challenges regarding observational studies, the pooled vaccine effectiveness of influenza vaccination during pregnancy in preventing infant laboratory-confirmed influenza hospitalizations was 72% (95% CI 39%, 87%) 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>
 </sup>. The four randomized controlled trials performed to date were not designed to have individual power to detect an effect of maternal vaccination on hospitalizations for laboratory-confirmed influenza. However, in a 
 <italic>post hoc</italic> analysis of the South African trial, maternal vaccination was associated with a 57% (95% CI 7%, 81%) reduction in all-cause acute lower respiratory tract infection (LRTI) among infants younger than 3 months old. Notably, this observation was independent of identifying influenza virus among the hospitalized cases, suggesting that preventing influenza infection may prevent subsequent LRTI in young infants. The negative polymerase chain reaction (PCR) results for influenza infection among these LRTI hospitalized cases may be partly explained by inadequate sample or imperfect test sensitivity. At least in adults, it has been shown that serologic assays demonstrated higher seropositivity for influenza than molecular testing, suggesting higher exposure than when looking at PCR-confirmed illness only 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>
 </sup>. It is also likely that exposure to the influenza virus initiated a causal chain of events leading to hospitalization for LRTI, even after virus shedding had ceased. Influenza virus infection could have increased the susceptibility to new bacterial nasopharyngeal acquisition, as well as increased the density of existing colonizing bacteria, with disease from these bacteria manifesting only a few weeks after virus clearance 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>– 
  <xref rid="ref-67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>
 </sup>; this is supported by epidemiological studies during the influenza epidemics and animal challenge models that demonstrated that influenza virus infection can enhance the susceptibility to infection with bacteria 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, 
  <xref rid="ref-69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
