<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par49">Construction of dengue and chikungunya consensus genomes was done using ngs_mapper v1.2.4 in-house developed pipeline [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. The consensus genomes were submitted to GenBank under accession numbers MN449007-MN449016 for DENV1, MN462632-MN462637 for DENV2 and MN462638-MN462662 for CHIKV. DENV1 genomes from Ecuador sequenced in this study were aligned to five previously published DENV1 genomes from Ecuador [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] using MEGAv7 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>], and to a set of full genome DENV1 reference genomes representing all genotypes, obtained from 
 <italic>National Center for Biotechnology Information’s</italic> (NCBI’s) curated Virus Variation database [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>], for genotype determination of the new Ecuadorian viruses. This DENV1 reference alignment was subsampled to represent genotype V and the American sub-lineage. The genomes were curated in TempEst [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>] through linear regression of root to tip neighbor joining (NJ) tree distances given genome sampling times. Genomes with too much or too little divergence as would be expected based on their root to tip distance and collection date were considered as outliers and removed from the dataset. In addition, all genomes without collection location or date, or with long stretches of Ns, were removed from the alignment. A set of full genome DENV2 reference sequences was obtained following the same criteria as for DENV1, aligned to the new DENV2 sequenced genomes from Ecuador as well as to the previously published Ecuadorian genomes, and subsampled to the Asian American genotype [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The final DENV1 alignment consisted of 471 genomes, and DENV2 alignment of 655 genomes. In addition, all E gene sequences of DENV1 and 2 were downloaded from the Virus Pathogen Resource (ViPR) curated database [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>], in order to increase the number of analyzed samples. The alignments were built following the same criteria for DENV1 and 2 full genomes, resulting in 1161 E genes of DENV1 and 1113 E genes of DENV2. All available CHIKV full genomes were downloaded from the ViPR curated database [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>] and aligned to the newly sequenced genomes from Ecuador. A Neighbor Joining (NJ) tree was constructed to determine the lineage of the Ecuadorian genomes. Following curation in TempEst and removal of outlier genomes, a full genome alignment of the Asian lineage was constructed using all CHIKV sequences except genomes without collection location or date, or with long stretches of Ns (
 <italic>N</italic> = 352).
</p>
