<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Surfactants are amphiphilic molecules characterized by a hydrophilic (ionic or non-ionic) head group and a hydrophobic tail. Biosurfactants are simply surfactants produced by living organisms. Surfactants are classified based on their head group polarity into non-ionic (uncharged), anionic (negatively charged), cationic (positively charged) and zwitterionic (capable of possessing both positive and negative charge). This complexity of head group leads to a range of adsorption and solution behaviors that facilitates their use across a broad range of industrial sectors. The classic application of surfactants is as surface-active agents (SAAs) which exploits their ability to adsorb to solid surfaces and fluid interfaces by partitioning the hydrophilic part in the aqueous phase and the hydrophobic part in/or at the second phase. This allows SAAs to act as wetting and dispersion agents, emulsifiers, foaming and anti-foaming agents and lubricants in a wide range of consumer and other industrial products such as detergents and soaps, foods, pharmaceuticals, cosmetics and personal care products, herbicides, insecticides and sanitizers [
 <xref rid="B1-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. It has also been realized that their rich and diverse chemistry imparts a range of bioactive properties including anti-microbial, anti-oxidant, anti-viral, anti-inflammatory, anti-cancer and anti-aging. This is important for surfactant manufacturers as it extends the market for SAAs and allows them to be branded as multi-functional ingredients. Similarly, consumer product manufacturers can make additional bioactive claims against products containing surfactants, which enhance the appeal and benefits to consumers and increases sales and market share. As importantly, multi-functional ingredients can lead to potential cost savings for the manufacturers of consumer formulations. For example, SAAs are used as emulsifiers in many foods, as well as cosmetic and pharmaceutical formulations. Having both the surface active as well as the anti-microbial properties of SAAs being exploited, this would remove (or reduce) the need for additional preservatives to be added to the final consumer product(s), with a concomitant decrease in formulation costs.
</p>
