<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To directly test for the requirement of intact membrane SM during IAV infection, we treated cells with exogenous bSMase before infection to deplete membrane SM. Exogenously applied bSMase, specifically hydrolyzes membrane SM into ceramide in the outer leaflet of the plasma membrane (
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 1997</xref>). Depletion of SM within lipid rafts by bSMase was shown to impair multiplication of viruses that require SM during infection such as Ebola virus, Japanese encephalitis virus, Rubella virus, and porcine alphaherpesvirus (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Miller et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Taniguchi et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Otsuki et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Pastenkos et al., 2018</xref>). In line with these studies, we demonstrated that depleting plasma membrane SM by bSMase suppresses IAV infection. The reduction of virus replication upon bSMase treatment was observed both for laboratory H1N1 strain (PR8) and an H1N1pdm09 virus (Cal07), indicating that the effect of SM depletion is not strain-specific. Exogenous bSMase specifically hydrolyzes SM without affecting cholesterol levels within lipid rafts (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Mizuno et al., 2011</xref>), which confirms that the reduction of IAV observed in bSMase-treated cells is explicitly attributed to the loss of SM. In our study, treatment with exogenous SM was found to enhance IAV replication. The modest enhancement of virus infection may be due to the already SM-saturated cellular membrane in A549 cells, as revealed by the lipidomic and sphingolipidomic analysis of A549 cells (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">He et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2018</xref>). This might explain the moderate increase in virus yield observed after SM treatment. Collectively, these results provide strong evidence for the requirement of SM during IAV infection.
</p>
