<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par27">
 <bold>
  <italic>Gene duplication and innovation.</italic>
 </bold> The duplication of restriction factor genes is another evolutionary strategy for accelerating host adaptation to a virus. By duplicating a restriction factor, the host can simultaneously explore multiple evolutionary trajectories. For example, in primate, artiodactyl (cloven-hoofed mammalian), canine and feline species, the APOBEC3 repertoires include many more paralogues than in rodents. In these lineages, the ancestral mammalian state — which was a single APOBEC3 gene — has been expanded to a family of APOBEC3 genes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup>. Most primate genomes now encode seven APOBEC3 gene paralogues, which vary in terms of their antiviral activities and retroelement targets, suggesting that they are adapted to different viruses. Several APOBEC3 genes (including 
 <italic>APOBEC3DE</italic>, 
 <italic>APOBEC3G</italic> and 
 <italic>APOBEC3H</italic>) show evidence of positive selection in primates
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>, but the specific residues that are under positive selection vary between the APOBEC3 genes, further supporting the idea that each paralogue has evolved to target different viruses. In this way, increasing the copy number of a given restriction factor probably gives the host the flexibility to rapidly evolve in response to several different viruses, leading to large families of related restriction factors. Other restriction factor families that are the result of gene duplications include the 
 <italic>Mx1</italic> gene family, which comprises two paralogues in some mice
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup>; the IFITM gene family, which comprises at least four paralogues in humans and five paralogues in mice
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup>; and the 
 <italic>Trim5</italic> gene family, which comprises eight paralogues in mice and cows and three paralogues in rats
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
