<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16">During an acute viral infection, each productively infected cell generates many infectious particles, leading to exponential viral growth. Therefore, restriction factors must have extremely potent antiviral activity to have any significant effect on viral loads (the restriction factors included in 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, for example, decrease viral infectivity by tenfold or more in single-round viral infectivity assays, although the level of restriction observed will vary depending on the system). This antiviral activity can be demonstrated experimentally through overexpression of a restriction factor, which causes a decrease in viral growth, or knockdown of a restriction factor, which causes an increase in viral growth. For example, SAMHD1 (SAM domain- and HD domain-containing protein 1) was recently defined as a restriction factor that is present in monocytes. Decreasing its endogenous expression in monocytes using RNA interference enhanced the replication of HIV-1, and exogenously expressing SAMHD1 in terminally differentiated myeloid cells restricted HIV-1 replication
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup>. In addition, the antiviral activity of restriction factors is sometimes specific to families of viruses. For example, TRIM5α (tripartite motif-containing protein 5α) seems to be active only against retroviruses, because it inhibits viral replication by means of a specific interaction with retroviral capsid proteins
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup>. By contrast, tetherin (also known as BST2) can restrict enveloped viruses across several virus families, because it is nonspecifically incorporated into the cell and virus membranes and prevents efficient viral release by tethering enveloped viruses to the cell
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>
 </sup> (
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).
</p>
