<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">Currently, due to the prevalence of COVID-19 in most parts of the world, one of the primary concerns is the relationship between environmental factors such as rising summer temperatures and the rapid prevalence of coronavirus (Abbasi et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2020</xref>; Wang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2020b</xref>). One study observed the relationship between the numbers of positive daily SARS-CoV-2 cases with three environmental factors: maximum relative humidity, maximum temperature, and maximum wind speed in four cities in China and five cities in Italy. In this study, the relationship between the prevalence of the COVID-19 with maximum air humidity and wind speed was negligible and statistically not significant. Although, in most cases, with increasing humidity and wind speed, the prevalence has decreased. The association between COVID-19 prevalence and maximum ambient temperature was negligible to moderate. Also, with increasing temperature in most of the studied cities, the prevalence of the disease has decreased (Bhattacharjee 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2020</xref>). The study by Chin et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2020</xref>) reported the resistance of the SARS-CoV-2 at 4 °C for a long time, but at 70 °C, its resistance was 5 min. In general, heat, high or low pH, and sunlight make it easier to kill the coronavirus (WHO 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">2020b</xref>). However, the results of a study also showed that the virus is stable at different pHs of 3–10, at room temperature (Chin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2020</xref>). A new study of 24,139 positive SARS-CoV-2 cases was conducted in 26 regions in China. Its results show that with a 1 °C increase of the minimum ambient air temperature, the cumulative number of cases decreases by 0.86% (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) (Wang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2020b</xref>).
</p>
