<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since cell-mediated adaptive immunity is believed to be key in counteracting HCMV infection, adoptive transfer of virus-specific T cells holds promise for antiviral therapy [
 <xref rid="B57-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. In addition, a multitude of antiviral agents from a wide diversity of chemical classes are known to be active against HCMV. The exact mechanism of action is unknown for most of these antivirals, and only a small subset has been tested in clinical trials. Seven anti-HCMV drugs have received approval for various indications: Ganciclovir (GCV), Valganciclovir, Acyclovir, Foscarnet, Cidofovir, Letermovir and Fomivirsen [
 <xref rid="B60-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B61-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Fomivirsen is an antisense oligonucleotide targeting expression of a major IE protein and will be discussed in 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec5dot1-viruses-12-00110">Section 5.1</xref>. GCV, an acyclic analogue of deoxyguanosine, was the first drug approved for the prevention and treatment of HCMV disease. The prodrug Valganciclovir is an orally applicable valine ester that is rapidly metabolized to GCV. Inside cells, GCV is converted to the active triphosphate via initial phosphorylation by the HCMV phosphotransferase (pUL97) and subsequent phosphorylation steps by cellular kinases. GCV inhibits the HCMV DNA polymerase (pUL54) by competing with deoxyguanosine triphosphate for the enzyme’s active site, thus preventing nucleotide incorporation into the elongating viral DNA [
 <xref rid="B60-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. A closely related nucleoside analogue, Acyclovir, is potent against members of the 
 <italic>Alphaherpesvirinae</italic> but exhibits very modest antiviral activity for HCMV [
 <xref rid="B60-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B65-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Thus, GCV and Valganciclovir have been the first line choice for prevention and treatment of HCMV disease. However, GCV is associated with serious toxicity including neutropenia, thrombocytopenia or anaemia [
 <xref rid="B66-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. In addition, the development of GCV-resistant HCMV strains associated with prolonged exposure, severe immunosuppression, suboptimal GCV doses and high viral loads poses a serious challenge. In 90% of all cases, resistance to GCV arises from mutations in conserved regions of either pUL97 or pUL54 [
 <xref rid="B67-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. In such cases, Foscarnet or Cidofovir are the usual alternative treatments. The two drugs do not require phosphorylation by pUL97 for activation and exhibit broad spectrum antiviral activity against DNA viruses. Foscarnet, a pyrophosphate analogue, directly inhibits pUL54 by blocking the enzyme’s pyrophosphate binding site via a non-competitive mechanism. By this mechanism, Foscarnet interferes with cleavage of the pyrophosphate moiety from the nucleotide triphosphate substrate during incorporation into the nascent DNA chain. Cidofovir is an acyclic nucleoside phosphonate and an analogue of deoxycytidine monophosphate. After phosphorylation to the active diphosphate (a deoxycytidine triphosphate analogue) by cellular kinases, competitive incorporation into the elongating DNA chain by pUL54 inhibits viral genome replication. Resistance to Foscarnet and Cidofovir occurs with rates similar to GCV, and the two drugs can select for mutations conferring cross-resistance to GCV. Moreover, lack of oral bioavailability as well as serious side effects including nephrotoxicity have limited their clinical use [
 <xref rid="B66-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B67-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Brincidofovir is a lipid ester prodrug of cidofovir with improved oral bioavailability and reduced toxicity that demonstrated promising results in clinical trials with allogeneic stem cell transplant recipients seropositive for HCMV [
 <xref rid="B67-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Likewise, the benzimidazole L-riboside Maribavir, a highly specific inhibitor of pUL97, has been successfully tested in clinical trials with a similar group of patients [
 <xref rid="B67-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Recently, a number of molecules have been discovered that inhibit the packaging of viral DNA into preformed capsids by the HCMV terminase complex. Letermovir is the first of this class to be approved and reduced the levels of HCMV DNA in stem cell transplant patients in the absence of myelotoxic effects [
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Although successful in immunosuppressed patients, none of the anti-HCMV drugs described above have been approved for use during pregnancy because of their teratogenic or embryotoxic effects in animal studies [
 <xref rid="B60-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>].
</p>
