<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Both angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors (ACEis) and angiotensin receptor blockers (ARBs) increase tissue and plasma levels of renin and Ang I.(50) ACEis inhibit Ang I to Ang II conversion, decreasing serum Ang II levels to baseline and have little to no affinity for ACE2 [
 <xref rid="C56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. At clinical doses, ACEis only partially affect this conversion because 40% of Ang II formation occurs outside the ACE pathway [
 <xref rid="C57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. ACE levels are in turn decreased through a negative feedback in states of high Ang II levels [
 <xref rid="C58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Ang II levels increase in response to ARBs at all levels, except in the kidney. The consequence of this increase is a redirection of Ang II activity through the anti-inflammatory and vasodilatory ACE2 and AT
 <sub>2</sub> receptor pathways [
 <xref rid="C56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. As a result, ACE2, compared to ACE, regulates local levels of both Ang II and Ang-(1–7) to a greater degree [
 <xref rid="C42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Tikellis 
 <italic>et al</italic>. suggest that ARBs, therefore, have a higher potential to favorably rebalance the RAAS pathway compared to ACEi [
 <xref rid="C42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Furthermore, the kallikrein-kinin system is regulated by ACE and ACE2. Increased activity of the kallikrein-kinin system occurs under proinflammatory conditions [
 <xref rid="C59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>], specifically bradykinin and des-Arg-BK
 <sup>9</sup>, which can lead to vascular leakage when unchecked by ACE and ACE2, respectively. This mechanism has been posited to be, at least in part, a cause of cough [
 <xref rid="C60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] and pulmonary edema [
 <xref rid="C61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>], independent of proposed Ang II induced hydrostatic pressure. The dysregulated kallikrein-kinin system's role remains theoretical in COVID-19; however, if true, AT
 <sub>1</sub> receptor blockade may be favored (over ACE inhibition) in an attempt to preserve the regulatory mechanisms of this system [
 <xref rid="C61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. While there may still be a key role for ACE inhibition in the context of the current disease that we will elucidate in the following sections, these observations support our decision to narrow the focus of this review to the downstream RAAS modifiers, ARBs.
</p>
