<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Puma isolates were grouped according to location, while domestic cat FFV isolates were analyzed as a single group in order to best mitigate the effects of sampling bias from puma. The BF supported transitions indicates a high probability of FFV spillover from domestic cats to puma, as well as puma to puma transmission (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="vez058-F5">Fig. 5</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref>). It’s worth noting a flexible non-parametric coalescent model was applied in these analyses, which assumes all organisms are part of the same population. Given the spatial/host dimensions of this analyses this prior although not optimal was the most appropriate currently available. Nonetheless, we found that whilst there was some support for puma to domestic cat cross-species transmission (BF = 20), overwhelmingly the model supported domestic cat to puma transmission (BF = 8,155) (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref>). This is not surprising considering that interactions between the puma predator and domestic cat prey make puma to domestic cat pathogen transmission events for directly transmitted agents biologically implausible. Spatial movement of FFV via puma to puma transmission is strongly supported between urban (FR) and rural (WS) locations (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="vez058-F5">Fig. 5</xref>), which is likely propagated by dispersal of individuals. Our findings support FFV transmission between domestic cat and puma in both urban (California and Colorado FR) and rural (Colorado WS) areas, although the latter appears to be much more strongly supported. There is potentially a high propensity for cross-species transmission in an urban area due to high densities of domestic cats kept as pets (
 <xref rid="vez058-B60" ref-type="bibr">Moss et al. 2016</xref>). High risks for transmission in rural regions may be related to the higher number of outdoor cats in these areas which are at risk for predation.
</p>
