<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ferrets are considered the gold standard for assessing influenza virus zoonotic and pandemic potential in humans and have therefore been utilised to assess the intrinsic and adaptive potential of H9N2 viruses to infect and transmit between humans [
 <xref rid="B169-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">169</xref>]. G1 lineage viruses have been tested for their ferret infectivity, as well as airborne and contact transmission several times. In three separate studies three different G1 ‘Eastern’ sub-lineage viruses and a single G1 ‘Western’ sub-lineage virus were shown to transmit efficiently to direct contact ferrets, but not via airborne transmission to sentinel ferrets [
 <xref rid="B113-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>,
 <xref rid="B170-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">170</xref>,
 <xref rid="B171-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">171</xref>]. Several BJ94 lineage viruses belonging to genotype 57, conversely, have been shown to be able to transmit, with varying degrees of efficiency, by respiratory droplet to contact ferrets [
 <xref rid="B163-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">163</xref>,
 <xref rid="B164-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>]. Several studies have gone further and deliberately adapted H9N2 viruses to ferrets or made reassortants between H9N2 viruses and human strains and then tested these viruses for their infectivity and transmissibility in ferrets. A series of experiments by the Perez group took both these approaches. They initially showed that making a reassortant between a contact transmissible G1 ‘Eastern’ H9N2 virus and a human H3N2 virus was not enough to provide the virus with airborne transmissibility [
 <xref rid="B170-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">170</xref>], therefore 10 ferret passages were performed. After 10 passages, respiratory droplet transmission between ferrets was achieved [
 <xref rid="B172-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">172</xref>]. Furthermore, it was shown that an alternative reassortant containing the six internal genes from a 2009 pandemic H1N1 virus, and either the adapted, or unadapted H9N2 HA and NA were able to transmit between ferrets [
 <xref rid="B173-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">173</xref>]. Overall, these studies indicate that H9N2 viruses are indeed viruses with pandemic potential, however, they would require some adaption and/or reassortment first to become a credible pandemic threat.
</p>
