<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0620">The important problem of viral emergences and reemergences has been treated with emphasis on the concept of complexity. There are multiple interacting influences that converge to produce the emergence or reemergence of a viral pathogen, one of them being the heterogeneity of viral populations at the genetic and phenotypic level. Despite considerable methodological progress, we are still in the realm of uncertainty regarding the prediction of when and where a new viral pathogen will emerge (see Summary Box).
 <boxed-text id="b0020">
  <caption>
   <title>Summary Box</title>
  </caption>
  <p id="bpar0105">
   <list list-type="simple" id="ulist0030">
    <list-item id="u0135">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="bpar0110">Long-term evolution of viruses is the result of a history of virus transmission among hosts. Basic principles of transmission dynamics must take into consideration sampling effects and the inherent heterogeneity of viral populations.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0140">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="bpar0115">Rates of evolution of viruses in nature are extremely high as compared to the estimated rate for their host organisms. Contrary to some tenets of neutral evolution, rates of viral evolution are not constant with time. In particular, several mechanisms explain why intrahost virus evolution is faster than interhost evolution.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0145">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="bpar0120">Several procedures for sequence alignments and derivation of phylogenetic trees allow a partial description of virus diversification in nature.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0150">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="bpar0125">Antigenic diversification of viruses is subjected to constraints that differ among viruses. Some viruses have a single serotype while others have 100 serotypes. Several possible mechanisms may contribute to this difference.</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="u0155">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="bpar0130">The emergence and reemergence of new viral pathogens is a multifactorial event with a clear influence of host and virus population numbers. Several levels of complexity participate in the emergence of a new pathogen, rendering the event highly unpredictable.</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
 </boxed-text>
</p>
