<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Located in Central China, Henan Province has a temperate climate. This was the first dengue outbreak in the Province. Geographically, it was the northernmost place with dengue outbreak in China, which is almost on the same latitude as Madeira, Portugal where dengue outbreak occurred in Europe. Generally, dengue occurs mainly in tropical and subtropical areas, where suitable climatic conditions play great roles in dengue transmission. Liu-Helmersson found that dengue epidemic potential in temperate was increased with increasing diurnal temperature range [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005095.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In addition, human movement plays an important role in dengue outbreak in temperate climate region. The dengue outbreak in Henan occurred in a small village with six porcelain factories. The epidemiological investigation showed that all dengue cases had neither travel history, nor collective activities. However, five people from the village worked in Laos where dengue was endemic. These five people returned to their home village in Henan for their vocational leave in May 2013. Although none of them were reported having dengue, two family members of these five people reporting dengue infections, indicating that they may have picked up the virus from the Laos and transmitted to their family members. In addition, the products of porcelain factories were usually sold to Guangzhou and Yunnan Province where dengue was prevalent in 2013 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005095.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. While phylogenetic and phylogeograhical analyses showed that the Henan strains and Yunnan strains (Xishuangbanna) were separated into different clades with high posterior probability support (Clade 13, 15; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0005095.g008">Fig 8A</xref>). Dengue was epidemic in Laos in 2012–2013 and the epidemic was severe in 2013, which might be attributed to the serotype switch from DENV 1 to DENV 3, and genotype II of DENV 3 was the predominant genotype [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005095.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005095.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The strains detected in Henan Province were genotype II of DENV 3 (Clade 15) and the phylogeographical analysis indicated that the dengue viruses were probably introduced from the Laos with high ancestral location state probability.
</p>
