<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par70">Venezuelan equine encephalitis virus (VEEV) comprises a great public health concern due to its possibility amenability for use as a bioterrorism agent and its severe health consequences in humans. In addition, natural VEEV outbreaks resulted in equine and human infections, provoking high death rates in equines (85%) and chronic neurological complications in humans. A chemical VEEV inhibitor known as ML336 was developed and its effectiveness in VEEV infection was confirmed in preclinical assays. However, the great limitation for ML336 clinical translation consists on its poor solubility and stability in biological media. Taking this into account, LaBauve 
 <italic>et al</italic> . (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR145">145</xref>) designed lipid-coated MSNs (LC-MSNs) as smart nanocarriers for ML336 delivery, as depicted in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>. This nanovehicle was proposed to improve ML336 stability, promoting its controlled release for VEEV treatment. Narrow size distribution (~75 nm) and hexagonal pores structures (average pore size of 2.65 nm) were achieved for MSNs. The lipidic shell consists of a liposome structure composed by 1,2-distearoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (DSPC):Cholestrol:1,2-distearoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphoethanolamine-N-[methoxy(polyethylene glycol)-2000] (DSPE-PEG(2000)), which can enhance colloidal stability, circulation time besides reduce protein adsorption to the nanosystem surface. From electron microscopy analysis, LC-MSNs@ML336 showed a lipid bilayer thickness of 6 nm besides zeta potential of -1.76 mV. 20 μg ML336/mg LC-MSNs were loaded into the nanocarrier showing a ML336 release of 34% over 24 h. TC-83 VEEV infected HeLa cells were treated with LC-MSNs@ML336. Results displayed virus inhibition in a dose-dependent manner, with significantly decreased viral load by 4 orders of magnitude after 24 h and 6 orders of magnitude after 48 and 72 h. From 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> assays, LC-MSNs were considered nontoxic at 0.11 g LC-MSNs/kg mouse dose administered per day during four days. In addition, LC-MSNs@ML336 exhibited significant reduction (about 10-fold) of brain viral titer in VEEV infected mice compared to PBS and other controls. These results highlighted the LC-MSNs@ML336 potential to treat VEEV infections and LC-MSNs as smart nanovehicles for antiviral applications.
</p>
