<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par72">As aforementioned, viruses comprise a harmful pathogen to the humans responsible for millions of people death every year. Despites some therapies such as highly active anti-retroviral therapy (HAART) available to treat human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), the demand for new therapies and vaccines are essential to fight against new viruses. To better understand the mechanism of antiviral MSNs action, Silva 
 <italic>et al</italic> . (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>) developed modified MSNs to evaluate their biocompatibility and their ability to inhibit the virus transduction of target cells. (3-aminopropyl)triethoxysilane (APTES), (3-glycidyloxypropyl)trimethoxysilane (GPTMS) and trimethoxy-(2-phenylethyl)silane (TMPES) groups were used to modified MSNs surface and noted as MSNs-APTES, MSNs-GPTMS and MSNs-TMPES. Spherical-shaped modified MSNs with average size from 354-571 nm and negative surface charge (from -11.2 to -22.8 mV) were fabricated. Cytotoxicity assays were performed for the nanosystems exhibiting cells metabolic activity similar to the control at lower particle concentration (10
 <sup>-5</sup> g mL
 <sup>-1</sup>) and cells nuclei morphology preserved after interaction. The inhibitory potential of the nanosystems to prevent virus transduction was evaluated by using a truncated version of the HIV-gp120 glycoprotein that can interact with cells containing CD4 receptor and VSV-G envelope that can bind on different cell surfaces. When target cell was transduced by virus, GFP is expressed by the infected cell, that means, whether transduction occurs GFP can be detected. In this way, the pseudotyped preparation was treated with the nanosystems. At low concentration, all nanosystems reduced transduction for both recombinant lentivirus with VSV-G and HIV-gp120 envelopes. MSNs-APTES and MSNs-TMPES showed higher transduction reduction for VSV-G (~50%) and HIV-gp120 (~20%) envelopes, respectively. Theoretical studies suggested that higher hydrophobicity could favor interaction with HIV-gp120 whereas hydrophilicity could lead to better interaction with VSV-G, explain the distinct responses. These results provide new insights towards the design of specific MSNs-based nanocarriers as new strategies for viral control and anti-HIV therapy.
</p>
