<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Uncovering those features that facilitate viral spread is an equally important aspect of assessing the landscape. As previously discussed, anthropogenic effects may facilitate the transmission of rabies across a larger scale than natural movements alone allow. The impact of human-mediated dog transport may by explored by phylogenetic analysis, with translocations implicated by the presence of a cluster-specific variant in a distant locality (see David 
 <italic>et al.</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">2004</xref>) and Cohen 
 <italic>et al.</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">2007</xref>), 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab01">Table 1</xref>), essentially an assignment approach (Paetkau 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref55">1995</xref>). While this method is not a definitive measure of a translocation, it can identify the most likely dispersal scenario. Talbi 
 <italic>et al.</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref77">2010</xref>) used Bayesian phylogeographic diffusion models (Lemey 
 <italic>et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46">2009</xref>) in an attempt to quantify the importance of various anthropogenic predictors on the observed spread of rabies cases in North Africa (see 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab01">Table 1</xref>). Model fitting indicated that dispersal patterns among towns were best explained by road distance, consistent with the anticipated role of human movement. Interestingly, further refinements to calculating distance matrices, such as an accessibility index based on road type and travel time, received only limited model support and road distances were only a marginally better predictor than great-circle distances. This may indicate that RABV dispersal follows a rather homogeneous spatial diffusion process, without any particular effect of landscape heterogeneity. More likely however, it means that more useful geographic predictors of human-mediated dispersal have yet to be found. While this was not possible in the Talbi 
 <italic>et al.</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref77">2010</xref>) study, their method can accommodate a wide range of geographical and environmental predictors and thus provides a promising general framework for examining landscape effects in future data sets.
</p>
