<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The analysis of entire 
 <italic>VP1</italic> sequences of chosen strains have shown that genotypes B and C have been cocirculating in the world and are responsible for many E-30 outbreaks (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Maruo et al., 2019</xref>). Genotype C plays a leading role in the transmission of E-30 in China, including the strains of E-30 outbreak reported in this study. It is now evolving and spreading in different provinces of China. Two lineages (lineage 1–2) were formed in China, which have played an causal role in encephalitis outbreaks (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Tao et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al., 2017</xref>). The strains of lineage 2 have been isolated from many provinces of China, such as Zhejiang, Guangdong, Shandong, Henan, Fujian, and Sichuan provinces. This lineage, diffusing in many provinces of China, evolved rapidly and caused several encephalitis outbreaks. For example, 1,681 encephalitis patients were reported in Jiangsu Province in 2003, and E-30 was confirmed as an etiologic agent of the outbreak (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2005</xref>). It was also reported as a major pathogen of encephalitis cases in Shandong Province of China between 2006 and 2012 (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Tao et al., 2014</xref>). From the maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree, spatial transmission events of E-30 were confirmed, and many sublineages cocirculated in several different regions of China. For example, the strains (GenBank accession number 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="JX129864" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">JX129864</ext-link>) isolated from Fujian Province cluster with the strains from Guangdong Province (GenBank accession number 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KC867102" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">KC867102</ext-link>) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref>). This phenomenon was also observed in several other regions of China. The strain of 45R (GenBank accession number 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="LC201508" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">LC201508</ext-link>), which was isolated from Yunnan province in 2016, was encompassed by the strains (GenBank accession number 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KY048011" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">KY048011</ext-link>-
 <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KY048043" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">KY048043</ext-link>) isolated from Shandong Province. The 99.3–100% genome similarity based on the 
 <italic>VP1</italic> genome of this study confirmed the occurrence of collective outbreak, although the strains were isolated from different towns of Gansu province.
</p>
