<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The primary objective of entry screening measures is to prevent or to delay introduction of ill or incubating cases to a country. Evidence for achieving this primary objective is based on the measures implemented in response to the EVD epidemic in West Africa in 2014/2015, SARS, Influenza Pandemic (H1N1) 2009 and Zika virus disease, as well as entry screening measures implemented on a routine basis for Dengue fever and Chikungunya infection. None of the countries that implemented entry screening for SARS detected any case [
 <xref rid="B8-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. For Influenza Pandemic (H1N1) 2009 the detection rate ranged from 0.01 to 2.2 confirmed cases per 10,000 persons screened [
 <xref rid="B20-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. A survey conducted by WHO showed an aggregate rate of 4 confirmed cases per 1,000,000 screened travelers for Influenza Pandemic (H1N1) 2009 in 10 countries [
 <xref rid="B50-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. For EVD, no case was identified through entry screening measures [
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. For Zika virus disease, five cases were identified and more than 21,000,000 persons screened [
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Routine entry screening measures for Dengue fever showed a detection rate of less than 8%. It should be noted that the diseases targeted by entry screenings such as SARS, EVD and the Influenza Pandemic (H1N1) 2009 have a very low prevalence among travelers, therefore the positive predictive value of entry screening is expected to be close to zero [
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Cowling and colleagues compared the dates of the first reported case of Influenza Pandemic (H1N1) 2009 in countries which implemented entry screening measures with countries that did not implement such measures. They concluded that entry screening may delay the introduction of a new influenza strain for about 7–12 days [
 <xref rid="B54-ijerph-16-04638" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. However, it should be noted that it was not possible for the study to assess which measures other than entry screening implemented by the countries have contributed to delaying introduction. 
</p>
