<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par45">SARS-CoV-2, taxonomically, has been classified as 
 <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic> (lineage B) by the WHO (Zhu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121">2020</xref>). Genetic sequence analysis showed more than 50% homology to MERS-CoV and 80% to SARS-CoV and both originate in bats. The differences between the sequences are mainly in the ORF1a gene and the spike gene, encoding S-protein, which is the key protein for the interaction between coronavirus and host cells (Lu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2020</xref>; Zhou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120">2020</xref>; Zhu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121">2020</xref>). The coronaviruses (CoVs) family is a class of enveloped, positive-sense single-stranded RNA viruses having an extensive range of natural roots. These viruses can cause respiratory, enteric, hepatic, and cardiovascular diseases (de Wilde et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2018</xref>; Weiss and Leibowitz 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">2011</xref>; Zheng et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119">2020</xref>). SARS-CoV-2 virion presents a genome size of 29.9 kb [Available via 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nmdc.cn/coronavirus" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://nmdc.cn/coronavirus</ext-link>] with a nucleocapsid composed of genomic RNA and phosphorylated nucleocapsid (N) protein. The nucleocapsid is covered by an envelope with the spike (S) glycoprotein trimmer, which exists in all CoVs, and the hemagglutinin-esterase (HE), only expressed from some CoVs. Moreover, in the viral envelope, located among the S protein, are confined the membrane (M) and the envelope (E) proteins (Wu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">2020</xref>). The SARS-CoV-2 genome contains a variable number of open reading frames (ORFs) (Song et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">2019</xref>) encoding for structural proteins, including S, M, E, N proteins and accessory proteic chains (Lei et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">2018</xref>; Letko et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2020</xref>). To address the pathogenetic and virulence mechanisms of SARS-CoV-2, the role of structural and non-structural proteins (nsps) must be considered (Letko et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2020</xref>). Four structural proteins are essential for virion assembly and infection of CoVs (Di Gennaro et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2020</xref>). S protein, present on the viral surface as a trimer, is the primary determinant of viral tropism and is responsible for receptor binding and membrane fusion (Beniac et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2006</xref>; Delmas and Laude 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">1990</xref>). The M protein has three transmembrane domains. It shapes the virions, promotes the curvature of the membrane, and binds to the nucleocapsid (Nal et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2005</xref>; Neuman et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">2011</xref>). Regarding the E protein, it plays a role in virus assembly, release and viral pathogenesis (DeDiego et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2007</xref>; Nieto-Torres et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">2014</xref>). Finally, the N protein contains two domains, both of which can bind virus RNA genome via different mechanisms. It is reported that N protein can bind to nsp3 protein packaging the encapsidated genome into virions (Chang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2006</xref>; Fehr and Perlman, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2015</xref>; Hurst et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2009</xref>). Moreover, N is also an antagonist of interferon and viral encoded repressor of RNA interference, which appears to be beneficial for the viral replication (Cui et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2015</xref>). Among nsps, most of these proteins, specifically nsp1 to 16, displayed a specific role in CoVs replication and in blocking the host innate immune response (Cascella et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2020</xref>; Guo et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2020</xref>). The pathogenic mechanism that starts with SARS-CoV-2 infection and culminates in pneumonia and heart or other extensive tissue damage seems to be particularly complex and able to produce an overreaction of the immune system associated with a pronounced cytokine storm, also known as cytokine release syndrome (CRS). Clinical features include extremely elevated cytokine levels (IL-6, IL-10, and TNF-α), lymphopenia (in CD4+ and CD8+ T cells), decreased IFN-γ expression in CD4+ T cells, and an increase in Th17 cell proportion. Th17 cells are helper T cells differentiated from Th0 cells mainly stimulated by IL-6 and IL-23. Specifically, IL-6, an important member of the cytokine network and produced by activated macrophages, plays a central role in acute inflammation with its anti-inflammatory and pro-inflammatory effects. Biologically, IL-6 promotes T cell population proliferation and activation and B cell differentiation, regulates acute phase response, and affects the hormone-like properties of vascular disease, lipid metabolism, insulin resistance, mitochondrial activity, neuroendocrine system, and neuropsychological behavior (Chen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2020a</xref>; Pyle et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">2017</xref>). On the other end, IL-6 increases during inflammatory and cardiovascular diseases (myocardial ischemia, coronary atherosclerosis, angina pectoris, congestive heart failure, hypertension), infections, autoimmune disorders, and some types of cancer (Bennardo et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2020</xref>). During the spread of infection, SARS-CoV-2 could cross through the mucous membranes, especially nasal and larynx mucosa; enters the lungs through the respiratory tract (Bennardo et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2020</xref>; Rose-John 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">2018</xref>; Chen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2020b</xref>); and could cause the aggravation of patient’s condition in 7 to 14 days after onset. B lymphocyte reduction may occur early during the disease and may affect antibody production in patients. Elevated IL-6 levels were observed in patients infected by SARS-CoV-2 and were correlated with the exacerbation of the disease around 2 to 10 days after onset (Di Gennaro et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2020</xref>). Excessive IL-6 signaling leads to a many of biological effects, such as maturing naïve T cells into effector T cells, the induction of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) expression in epithelial cells, the increase of vessel permeability, and reducing myocardium contractility, culminating in organ damage (Pathan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">2004</xref>; Tanaka et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">2016</xref>). Since elevated IL-6 levels were consistently reported during COVID-19 and were correlated with higher mortality in these patients, IL-6 might serve as a predictive biomarker for COVID-19 severity.
</p>
