<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The preliminary demonstrations of the efficacy of NFTs to prevent bleeding have raised the question of whether these agents will eventually supplant factor replacement as prophylaxis for patients without inhibitors. Current prophylactic regimens are challenging, with almost 40% of adult patients not routinely receiving prophylaxis 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>
 </sup>. It has also been speculated that subcutaneous delivery of NFTs may allow for earlier initiation of prophylaxis in infants, which could delay factor exposure and potentially prevent inhibitor development 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>
 </sup>. The previous attempt to test this hypothesis, that delaying factor exposure reduces inhibitors through the use of standard bypassing therapy, was unsuccessful owing to breakthrough bleeding 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>
 </sup>, which may be mitigated by increased hemostatic efficacy of new NFTs. However, well-defined relationships between the number of factor exposures and the timing of inhibitor development 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
  <xref rid="ref-84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>
 </sup> support this parameter as being the most important rather than the age of exposure; indeed, emerging evidence suggests that earlier exposure to allergens may be protective 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>
 </sup>. Factor exposure in the setting of immunological “danger signals”, such as traumatic bleeds or surgery, also increases the risk of inhibitor development 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>
 </sup>. As it is unlikely that NFTs will provide sufficient prophylaxis for patients never to require factor products, NFTs could potentially increase the risk by concentrating exposures to situations with immunological “danger signals”. It is possible, however, that the ease of administration of NFTs will attract patients who are currently declining prophylaxis and/or who are noncompliant.
</p>
