<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0155">Bioinformatics and biophysical analysis of HCV G4s has demonstrated the existence of six conserved PQSs throughout the whole viral genome, mostly in the negative strand. The one located in the core gene was characterized as the most stable G4.
 <xref rid="bb0245" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>48</sup>
 </xref> Its stabilization with the G4 ligands TMPyP4 and a PDS derivative (PDP) promoted viral RNA-dependent RNA polymerase stalling, with consequent reduction in HCV core protein levels. 
 <italic>In vivo</italic> analysis revealed that PDP led to G4-mediated antiviral activity in the low micromolar range, by inhibiting intracellular replication of different HCV genotypes.
 <xref rid="bb0250" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>49</sup>
 </xref> A deeper investigation also showed that the HCV core RNA G4 is recognized and bound by the cellular protein nucleolin. This interaction, which has been found to be structure-related, resulted in inhibition of HCV replication in cells. Such activity was counteracted by the employment of G4 ligands such as PDS and PDP, which competed for the same binding site. TMPyP4 did not produce the same effect, however, this last compound is in general less selective for G4s.
 <xref rid="bb0255" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>50</sup>
 </xref> Moreover, HCV infection promoted nucleolin overexpression, which in turn induced a drastic reduction of HCV total RNA levels. Conversely, nucleolin silencing was directly correlated with increased HCV RNA expression.
 <xref rid="bb0245" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>48</sup>
 </xref> These results strongly suggest the existence of a host anti-viral immunity mechanism involving G4 structures. Additional bioinformatic studies based on a different algorithm showed the presence of a very interesting G4-forming sequence in the stem-loop IIy of the HCV negative strand, precisely in the 3’-UTR, which is the initiation site for the (+)-strand replication. The G4 sequence, highly conserved in many different HCV strains, was strongly stabilized by the bisquinolinium derivative PhenDC3 and as a consequence, RNA synthesis was hampered by more than 70%. Moreover, in a luciferase system in which luciferase expression was directly related to viral replication, 60% reduction was observed upon treatment with the compound.
 <xref rid="bb0260" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>51</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
