<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since the viral genome is a positive-sense RNA molecule that acts as mRNA, the next step consists of protein translation and synthesis of the polyprotein. The RNA does not possess the cap structure usually found at the 5′ terminus of cellular mRNAs and which is necessary for the correct binding of ribosomes to the translation initiation site. Contrarily, the viral genome contains an, in comparison with cellular mRNA species, unusual long non-coding sequence (IRES) that is located upstream of the start codon and can comprise up to 1,199 nucleotides. It possesses a strongly pronounced, stable secondary structure with intramolecular double-stranded sequence regions (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig00143" ref-type="fig">14.3</xref>). The IRES facilitates recognition of the picornavirus genome as mRNA by the ribosomal subunits, facilitating their interaction with the start codon to initiate the first steps of the translation. It is assumed that the secondary structure exerts a stabilizing effect on a nucleotide sequence located immediately upstream from the start of the translation and which is complementary to the 18S ribosomal RNA of the small ribosomal subunit. Therefore, the ribosomal RNA can hybridize with the viral genome, guiding the ribosomes to the correct start site for protein synthesis. Cellular proteins are functionally involved in initiating translation. They also bind to the IRES region, influencing thereby the cell and host specificity of the different picornaviruses. One such protein is the La protein (p52), which usually binds to the 3′ termini of transcripts, especially to tRNAs that are synthesized by RNA polymerase III, and regulates their termination. Interestingly, the La protein induces an autoimmune reaction in patients with lupus erythematosus and Sjögren syndrome. Additional IRES-binding components include polypyrimidine tract binding protein, poly(rC)-binding protein 2, poly(A)-binding protein and the Unr factor (upstream of N-ras). In addition to these proteins, also the translation initiation factor eIF-2 and other not yet characterized proteins have been identified as interaction partner of the IRES.
</p>
