<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The formation of a primer molecule, Vpg-pUpU-OH, is necessary for replication of the viral genome, which leads to the generation of a complementary negative-sense RNA molecule as an intermediate product. Mediated by the hydrophobic domain of the 3AB protein, the direct precursor of Vpg, primer synthesis occurs in association with intracellular membrane compartments and is catalysed by 3D
 <sup>pol</sup>. The template for the uridylylation reaction is a conserved sequence motif (AAACA), which is located in the loop of a hairpin structure within the 
 <italic>cis</italic>-responsive element. This 
 <italic>cis</italic>-responsive element is situated in different regions of the genome among the various members of the picornaviruses: in enteroviruses, it is located within the 2C-encoding region (poliovirus 1: nucleotides 4,444–4,505); in rhinovirus A, it resides within the coding sequences for the 2A domain; in parechoviruses and rhinovirus B (rhinovirus 14), it is situated within the VP1-encoding sequences, whereas in rhinovirus C it is found within the sequences encoding VP2. In FMD virus, the 
 <italic>cis</italic>-responsive element is located within the 5′ UTR upstream of the IRES sequences, whereas in hepatitis A virus, it is situated within the 3C-encoding region. Mutations in the 
 <italic>cis</italic>-responsive element lead to a replication failure, which results in an inhibition of negative-strand synthesis owing to the absence of uridylylation. The Vpg-pUpU primer associates with the poly(A) tail at the 3′ terminus of the viral genome and forms the initiation structure with a free 3′-OH end as a recognition site for the RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (3D
 <sup>pol</sup>), which synthesizes the complementary strand (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig00144" ref-type="fig">14.4</xref>). The initiation of negative-sense RNA synthesis is, however, also dependent on the presence of an intact cloverleaf secondary structure at the 5′ terminus of positive strands. This suggests that the positive-sense RNA genomes form a circular structure, at which the negative-strand synthesis is initiated. The circularization is mediated by the interaction of the terminal-binding proteins poly(A)-binding protein and poly(rC)-binding protein 2 as well as by the viral proteins 2C
 <sup>ATPase</sup>, 3CD
 <sup>pro</sup> and 3C
 <sup>pol</sup>, which bind to the 5′ and 3′ ends of the RNA genome. A transitory intermediate double-stranded RNA molecule is formed during the RNA polymerization. The 3′ end of the newly synthesized negative strand contains two adenosine residues. These constitute a perfect structure for the complementary interaction with Vpg-pUpU primers, and initiate the synthesis of new positive-sense RNAs. The synthesis of a complete RNA molecule takes about 45 s. Besides 3D
 <sup>pol</sup> and Vpg-pUpU primers, a cellular protein (67 kDa) is essential for the correct course of this process. Between five and eight positive-sense RNA strands can be synthesized from a single intermediate negative-sense RNA molecule. Only 5–10 % of all viral RNA molecules are negative-sense RNA. New viral polyproteins are translated from the newly synthesized positive-sense RNA strands. In this way, the amount of viral components can rapidly multiply within infected cells. The entire process of polyprotein synthesis and genome replication occurs in the cytoplasm in association with intracellular membrane compartments. The polyproteins become embedded in such compartments by their amino-terminal myristoylation and the hydrophobic 3AB domain. 
</p>
