<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The first infections with SARS-related coronavirus emerged in Foshan and Heyuan in the Chinese province of Guangdong in November 2002. Most patients had direct or indirect contact with animal markets. Until January 2003, the infections spread through human-to-human transmissions to Guangzhou, the capital of Guangdong province, where they affected mainly people who were working in public health services. There was talk of an “infectious atypical pneumonia”, and a number of infectious agents were suspected as possible causes, among others, chlamydia. When the number of patients increased to over 300, including 100 nurses and physicians, and five of them had died, the WHO was informed of this new infection on 11 February 2003. In March 2003, an infected nephrologist from Guangdong province stayed in a hotel in Hong Kong, and verifiably infected at least ten other hotel guests, who in turn carried the infection to various countries, including Singapore, Vietnam, Ireland, the USA and Canada. During a second infection wave in Hong Kong and all the afore-mentioned countries, particularly physicians and nurses were infected, and these in turn passed on the infection in the hospitals and to their families, thus exporting it to other countries. The pathogen arrived in central Europe (Germany) via Singapore. On 10 March 2003, this new disease received the name severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS). In the following months until 5 July 2003, the SARS disease emerged worldwide in 8,400 patients in 29 countries, and about 800 of them died. As a result of massive countermeasures by the WHO, it was possible to control the infection relatively rapidly. These measures included isolation/quarantine, entry bans/travel restrictions and checks at airports, and an open and timely information policy. In March 2003, Christian Drosten of the Bernhard Nocht Institute in Hamburg and other international research groups independently identified a coronavirus as the aetiologic agent of the disease, and determine its entire genome sequence. This facilitated the development of specific diagnostic test systems. At that time, a peculiarity was that all information was made immediately accessible and divulged, e.g. via the Internet.</p>
