<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>With the number of COVID-19 infections flying off the charts, accurate and rapid diagnosis has evolved as a tool to detect and control the virus (
 <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). Currently, various diagnostic tools have been approved by the WHO, which has recommended the collection of upper respiratory specimens using NP swabs. If unavailable, the CDC and WHO recommend the collection of OP specimens, sputum, endotracheal aspirate, bronchoalveolar lavage, blood, stool, and autopsy material and tissue from lungs (
 <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Recently, the WHO has approved the emergency use of qSARS-CoV-2 IgG/IgM rapid serological tests, in which venipuncture blood collected by medical professionals can be used. However, the use of this test is limited to authorized laboratories alone. This test identifies the IgM and IgG antibodies produced by the patient in response to SARS-CoV-2 infection (
 <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Likewise, ICMR has also issued some guidelines for the diagnosis of COVID-19. The ICMR has recommended the use of RT-PCR probes from the USA that are distributed to laboratories in the country. In addition, commercial kits and US FDA EUA/CE IVD-approved kits may be used for diagnostic purposes in India. Further, kits with 100% concordance will also be fast-tracked for use in India; 20 non-US/FDA/EUA/CE/IVD kits have completed evaluation in this regard (
 <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Moreover, the tests available predominantly check for the presence of viral nucleic acid in the specimen through RT-PCR. In order to confirm the diagnosis, a minimum of two targets must be chosen on the SARS-CoV-2 genome, with one being specific for SARS-CoV-2. Otherwise, the test can include a primer specific for beta coronavirus, and the presence of SARS-CoV-2 must be confirmed by sequencing of the genome. Various viral proteins like orf1ab, N, RdRp, S, E, ORF1b, and nsp14, have been targeted for diagnosis in laboratories worldwide. At this point, it is essential to point out that a negative result does not exclude the probability of COVID-19, because such a result can be caused by poor-quality specimens, late or very early collection, improper handling of the sample, and inaccurate testing methods. The commonly available RT-PCR tests that are widely used for detection of COVID-19 take a significant amount of time to give the results and also require trained personnel and well-equipped laboratories for their use. As rapid detection tests appear to be a break-through in COVID-19 diagnosis, fine-tuning of this technique is required to use them as regular diagnostic kits. Although these tests are quick and relatively inexpensive, their accuracy has not been established yet. Another drawback is that antibodies develop only a few weeks after infection, and the levels may be more pronounced in severe cases, increasing the chances of a false negative in patients with mild or asymptomatic COVID-19. For now, we recommend the use of RT-PCR as diagnostic tools for the detection of COVID-19. In addition to these methods, CT scans may aid in the diagnosis of COVID-19, but this method is not recommended for routine screening, because it may not be precise in all patients (
 <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). It is also possible that biochemical assays and blood counts, including lymphocyte levels and C‐reactive protein (CRP) proteins, may serve as useful biomarkers for COVID-19, and these tests can be used as preliminary screening for COVID-19. More research is required to ascertain the value of these tests in this domain. As the global demand for diagnostic tools continues to rise, it is essential to rapidly develop diagnostic kits using various algorithms to successfully identify and contain the virus.
</p>
