<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">Hillaireau et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">2013</xref>) referred about the potential of nanoassemblied nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NRTIs) delivered as squalenoylated prodrugs to enhance their absorption and improve their biodistribution and also to enhance their intracellular delivery and antiviral efficacy toward HIV-infected cells. Biodegradable cationic cholesterol-ε-polylysine nanogel carriers for delivery of triphosphorylated NRTIs demonstrating high anti-HIV activity along with low neurotoxicity, warranting minimal side effects following systemic administration, were prepared by Warren et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR232">2015</xref>). Nanogel modification with brain-specific peptide vectors resulted in efficient central nervous system targeting. Senanayake et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR193">2015</xref>) conjugated succinate derivatives of NRTIs with cholesteryl-ε-polylysine nanogels. Nanogel conjugates of zidovudine (ZDV), LVD, and abacavir demonstrated tenfold suppression of reverse transcriptase activity in HIV-infected macrophages with EC
 <sub>90</sub> drug levels of 2–10, 2–4, and 1–2 μM, respectively, for single nanodrugs and dual and triple nanodrug cocktails, conjugate of LVD being the most effective single nanodrugs (EC
 <sub>90</sub> 2 μM). NPs of 50–60 nm prepared by encapsulation of ZDV in lactoferrin NPs were found to be stable in simulated gastric and intestinal fluids and the anti-HIV-1 activity of drug remained unaltered in nanoformulation in acute infection, the drug release from NPs was constant up to 96 h and bone marrow micronucleus assay showed that nanoformulation exhibited ca. twofold lower toxicity than soluble form (Kumar et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120">2015</xref>). Lactoferrin NPs loaded with a triple drug combination of ZDV, EFV, and LVD showing a diameter of 67 nm and EE &gt;58% for each drug delivered the maximum of its payload at pH 5 with a minimum burst release in vitro, exhibited improved anti-HIV activity, were practically not toxic to the erythrocytes, and reached in in vivo experiment an approx. &gt;4-fold increase in AUC, 30% increase in the 
 <italic>C</italic>
 <sub>max</sub> compared to individual drugs, and &gt;2-fold enhancement in the half-life of each drug. They also showed improved bioavailability of all drugs with less tissue-related inflammation (Kumar et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121">2017b</xref>). Improved HIV-microbicide activity through the co-encapsulation of drugs acting as NRTIs in biocompatible metal organic framework nanocarriers containing iron(III) polycarboxylate NPs was reported by Marcos-Almaraz et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR142">2017</xref>).
</p>
