<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p1025">A major milestone in the biological sciences was the establishment of the tissue culture technique that can both maintain and propagate the growth of living cells under sterile in vitro conditions. Traditional cell cultures, which are two-dimensional (2D), are grown as monolayer cultures on a flat and rigid surface. Since their development, several advancements have been made to improve cell culture media as well as the biological materials used for culturing. The improvements have proven valuable for cell-based study due to their amalgamation of various modern analytical techniques, such as fluorescence, electrochemistry, and mass spectroscopy. 2D cell culture does not provide an adequate in vivo environment, where other cells surround the cells in a three-dimensional (3D) ECM (
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Edmondson et al., 2014</xref>). Cells under in vivo conditions both produce and continuously consume oxygen nutrients and other molecules, and such dynamic distributions are not mimicked in conventional 2D cell cultures. Moreover, 2D cell cultures fail to recapitulate the highly complex 3D environment, function, and physiology of living tissues, the multitudinous regulatory interactions from surrounding tissue cells, the ECM, and other systemic factors that lead to nonpredictive data of an in vivo response (
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2012</xref>). The limitations of 2D cell culture systems have recently become more evident. Recent standard protocol advances in the fields of quantitative and system biology and imaging technology have allowed analysis of individual cells and observation of live individual cells growing in a natural physiological 3D environment. Cells cultured in a 3D model system more closely mimic in vivo conditions. Thus, unlike 2D cell cultures, which can sometimes cause misleading and nonpredictive data of in vivo responses, 3D systems are realistic for translating study findings. Compared to the 2D cell culture system, the 3D cell culture system provides a physiologically relevant and closer biomimetic environment, promotes better cell differentiation, and improves cell function (
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Edmondson et al., 2014</xref>). The 3D culture system holds great promise for applications in various fields, such as cancer cell biology, stem cell research, drug discovery, and various cell-based analyses and devices. While this culturing model offers state-of-the-art technology for facilitating drug development and numerous other applications, several hurdles remain before a universal, standardized, and validated system can be established (
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Sung et al., 2014</xref>). Recent developments in the transition from 2D to 3D cell cultures indicate promising applications for many industries; however, the cost of automation and easy-to-use readout systems are still key concerns.
</p>
