<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Throughout Asia and the Americas, chikungunya virus outbreaks have been associated with unique clinical features [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007065.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], including long-lasting symptoms [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007065.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], and high mortality resulting from complications associated with CHIKV infection [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007065.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007065.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In Brazil, a striking proportion of 68.1 to 75% of the population with positive serological results reporting symptoms contracted a chronic form of the disease [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007065.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007065.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. However, the epidemiological features, genomic diversity, and transmission dynamics of recent CHIKV outbreaks in this country remain poorly understood. Inferences that are based only on clinical-epidemiological notifications are complicated by underreporting of cases by the national reporting system [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007065.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], mostly due to the co-circulation and co-infection with viruses that cause overlapping symptoms, such as Zika and dengue viruses [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007065.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0007065.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Moreover, CHIKV serological tests may cross-react with other alphaviruses, such as Mayaro virus, that circulate in the north and centre-west regions of Brazil [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007065.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007065.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. In this context, it is challenging to use only clinical-epidemiological and serological data to evaluate the true extent of the disease. Moreover, accurate incidence data is critical to forecast and provide prediction of the course of epidemics [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007065.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].
</p>
