<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Enterovirus 71 is a human pathogen that causes hand, foot, and mouse disease and neurological complications. Although members of enteroviruses are extensively investigated, the mechanism of viral replication is unclear. Here we demonstrate that the 3A protein of EV71 mediates viral replication through host ACBD3. ACBD3 is crucial in Aichi virus replication, yet its relation with enteroviruses is a puzzle
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>. A number of studies showed that ACBD3 physically interacts with 3A encoded by enteroviruses, but is dispensable in viral replication
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>. This is evident in cells infected with rhinovirus, poliovirus and coxsakievirus B3. The results present in this work uncovered that EV71 3A associated with and directed ACBD3 to discrete regions in the cytoplasm. This is different from a report that no interaction between EV71 and ACBD3 was detectable
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>. The basis for this discrepancy is not known. Our work suggests that is probably a prerequisite to initiate sites or platforms necessary for RNA replication. Consistent with this interpretation, depletion or knockout of ACBD3 precluded viral RNA replication, protein synthesis and plaque formation. Furthermore, these phenotypes were also noted with several different strains of EV71. Strikingly, a site-specific mutation in 3A of EV71 disrupted the 3A-ACBD3 interaction and viral replication. Therefore, besides an ACBD3 binding site an additional cis-element in 3A may be required. Collectively, these results support the argument that engagement of EV71 3A with ACBD3 dictates viral replication. It remains obscure why ACBD3 is differentially involved in viral replication. As 3A from picornaviruses exhibits only about 42% homology, amino acid sequence variations may have a role. An attractive hypothesis is that 3A may bear distinct features that require or bypass ACBD3. Another possibility is that a separate viral protein may substitute for the function of ACBD3.
</p>
