<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="order">
 <list-item>
  <p>(i) General treatment recommendations:</p>
  <list list-type="simple">
   <list-item>
    <p>(a) Bed rest, supporting treatment, and monitoring vital signs;</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>(b) Routine laboratory tests for blood and urine, C-reactive protein, serum biochemical indexes, and coagulation function;</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>(c) Antiviral therapies with atomized inhalation of α-interferon and lopinavir or ritonavir in suitable patients;</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>(d) Avoid inappropriate and blind administration of antibiotics, especially broad-spectrum antibiotics. However, in patients with sepsis, antimicrobial treatment should be provided within 1 hour of the onset of sepsis;</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>(e) Other treatments: oxygen should be given to patients with a low blood oxygen saturation and avoid the long-term use of corticosteroids for treating viral pneumonia or ARDS.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>(ii) Treatment recommendations for patients in severe or critical conditions:</p>
  <list list-type="simple">
   <list-item>
    <p>(a) General treatment principles: treatment according to the symptoms and the underlying disease (diabetes, hypertension, etc.); preventing secondary infections and complications of the infection;</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>(b) Respiratory support:</p>
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p>Noninvasive ventilation for 2 hours first, withdrawn gradually when the patient shows better signs.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p>Invasive ventilation should be used if the symptoms worsen or the patient shows intolerant of noninvasive ventilation, increased airway secretions, excessive coughing, or hemodynamic instability.</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p>Prone position ventilation; lung recruitment maneuver or extracorporeal membrane oxygenation should be adopted if needed.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>(c) Circulation support: promoting microcirculation with vasoactive agents to replace fluids.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </list-item>
</list>
