<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Vaccines against influenza have been developed empirically (
 <xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr">Siegrist, 2013</xref>), comprising of H1N1, H3N2, and influenza B strains that are predicted to be circulating in the subsequent season, and are not inclusive and protective against pandemic potential viruses, such as H5N1 and the most recent H7N9 (
 <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Meng et al., 2014</xref>). The lengthy process of vaccine strain selection is multifaceted at every stage, and it takes almost four months to select candidate vaccine strains (
 <xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization, 2007</xref>). Moreover, sequence variability poses a significant problem in vaccine design against viruses. For example, a study by 
 <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Park et al. (2004)</xref> to assess the effect of strain heterology showed increased risk of disease for heterologously compared to homologously vaccinated animals. Hence, highly conserved sequences are thought as a solution in selecting vaccine targets that are representative of the majority of influenza viruses. Several studies (
 <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Assarsson et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Cassone &amp; Rappuoli, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Steel et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">Pica &amp; Palese, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Deng et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Huber et al., 2015</xref>) have provided evidence supporting the notion of conserved sequences as universal vaccine targets. 
 <xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Steel et al. (2010)</xref> demonstrated that a vaccine based on the highly conserved HA stalk region was broadly protective in a murine influenza model. Other studies (
 <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Cassone &amp; Rappuoli, 2010</xref>) identified human antibodies that bound to highly conserved epitopes of the HA, NP or the M2 for generation of cross-protective antibodies and cell-mediated immunity. 
 <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Huber et al. (2015)</xref> constructed a peptide-based vaccine of conserved parts (HA, M2, NP, PB1, and M1) of influenza A virus, containing B and T-cell epitopes, which showed promising results in both mice and ferrets. 
 <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Assarsson et al. (2008)</xref> identified 54 conserved IAV epitopes tested against peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) from 44 healthy human blood donors. A few studies have evaluated conserved sequences of the M2e as vaccines in early stage clinical trials (
 <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Deng et al., 2015</xref>). Adjuvants may be used to boost the low immunogenicity of conserved sequences (
 <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Kang, Kim &amp; Compans, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2014</xref>). Our analysis has shown that H5N1 IAV is highly conserved and contains immune targets that are attractive for vaccine design. Notably, we identified 25 sequences that were highly conserved across both avian and human viruses (≥99% incidence), with half (12) universally conserved to several other subtypes (
 <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Heiny et al., 2007</xref>); and 12 of the 25 (of which, eight were both pan-subtype conserved and immune-relevant) matched with 30 reported immunogenic human T-cell epitopes, including many that were promiscuous to multiple HLA alleles allowing for greater population coverage. Although, our selection did not result in any targets of HA and NA sequences, which are important for protective immune response (
 <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Heiny et al., 2007</xref>), the data suggests that they can be selected at a slightly lower, but still highly conserved incidence threshold, such as ≥90%. For example, a reduction of the conservation level to 90% incidence returned nine highly conserved sequences for HA, shared across viruses of both hosts. Further reduction in the conservation threshold (
 <italic>i.e</italic> to ≥ 80%) is expected to provide even more candidates from HA, which may extend to multiple influenza subtypes, though at a lower conservation level. Careful selection of vaccine targets that protect against a broad spectrum of viral variants and are applicable at the human population is an important first step that is critical for the success of the subsequent steps
 <italic>.</italic> This work supports the need for knowledge-based approaches towards the design of universal influenza vaccines (
 <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Gillim-Ross &amp; Subbarao, 2007</xref>).
</p>
