<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The emergence of HIV in humans from the original reservoir(s) in monkeys therefore involved two or three host transfers. Each of those steps involved multiple host barriers on the cellular level that the virus needed to overcome before efficient replication and spread were possible. Known host factors that are involved in cell infection and viral adaptation are the cluster of differentiation 4 (CD4) receptor, C–C chemokine receptor type 5 (CCR5) receptor, Tripartite motif-containing protein 5 α form (TRIM5α), apolipoprotein B mRNA editing enzyme, catalytic polypeptide-like (APOBEC) 3D, APOBEC F, APOBEC G, APOBEC 3H, SAM and HD Domain Containing Deoxynucleoside Triphosphate Triphosphohydrolase 1 (SAMHD1), Tetherin, human silencing hub (HUSH) RanBP2 [
 <xref rid="RSTB20190017C45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Each has a degree of host specificity that required one or more modifications or countermeasures from the virus for successful emergence in one or more of the new hosts. The necessary adaptations were achieved through amino acid changes or by the acquisition or modification of viral accessory protein genes: for TRIM5α, this involved mutations in the capsid protein; for APOBECs, it required the presence of the Vif gene; SAMHD1 was countered by the viral Vpr; Tetherin by Nef and/or Vpu; human silencing hub (HUSH) complex by Vpr; RanBP2 interacted with the capsid protein and was countered by capsid mutations. There was also some specificity of attachment or use of the CCR5 protein co-receptor in different hosts [
 <xref rid="RSTB20190017C49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The number of factors viruses had to overcome or become adapted to indicates the complexity of the host-switching process, particularly for the M and O strains. Analysis of the complete SIV and HIV sequences searching for human-specific mutations has shown very few point mutations—indeed, it appears that there is only a single mutation in the gag protein (matrix—MA) associated specifically with adaptation to the human host [
 <xref rid="RSTB20190017C50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20190017C51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>].
</p>
