<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There is no specific drug or vaccine available for SARS-CoV-2 for use in humans. The present treatment employs two-pronged approach—use of antibiotics to prevent secondary infections and use of available antiviral drugs to eliminate the virus. Although, no antiviral drug has presented conclusive results with sufficient scientific data as a treatment against COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="B43-biology-09-00141" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-biology-09-00141" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Alternatively, repurposing of available antiviral drugs is under trial. WHO has launched SOLIDARITY trials, an internationally coordinated trial to find effective drugs against SARS-CoV-2. It relies on the repurposing of antiviral drugs already approved for use in humans [
 <xref rid="B26-biology-09-00141" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The drugs included in the SOLIDARITY trial are lopinavir and ritonavirplus interferon beta as well as chloroquine, and remdesivir. Lopinavir and ritonavir, remdesivir inhibit viral replication. Patients have shown positive responses to treatments with a combination of lopinavir and ritonavir [
 <xref rid="B2-biology-09-00141" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Remdesivir has shown high efficacy against other coronaviruses which makes it a strong candidate for use against SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B23-biology-09-00141" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Monoclonal antibodies such as Tocilizumab can be useful to counter cytokine storms in severe patients [
 <xref rid="B26-biology-09-00141" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Presently, a number of clinical trials registered on 
 <uri>ClinicalTrials.gov</uri> include immunoglobulins, remdesivir, arbidol hydrochloride combined with interferon atomisation, hydroxychloroquine, ritonavir plus oseltamivir and many more [
 <xref rid="B2-biology-09-00141" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Hydroxychloroquine, an anti-malarial and anti-inflammatory drug inhibits viral replication by increasing the pH of endosomes that house the virus inside the cell and has shown promising results against SARS-CoV-2 in in-vitro studies. Since then, its demand has increased globally [
 <xref rid="B26-biology-09-00141" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. A recent study conducted upon a group of 80 individuals showed improvement in symptoms upon administration of hydroxychloroquine and azithromycin [
 <xref rid="B48-biology-09-00141" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. However, there are still no convincing studies to establish hydroxychloroquine as the therapeutic candidate for SARS-CoV-2 and further investigations are required involving larger groups. The Indian Council of Medical Research (ICMR) has approved the clinical trial of live attenuated Mycobacterium W (
 <italic>Mycobacterium indicus pranii</italic>), commercially available as Sepsivac (Cadila Pharmaceuticals) to be tested on COVID-19 patients, their close contacts and healthcare workers. This has been used previously for leprosy, advanced non-small cell lung cancer and severe gram-negative sepsis.
</p>
