<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0010">Even if different control measures slow down and eventually and locally stop the spread of COVID-19 disease, the successful suppression of this disease still leaves the population at risk of resurgence due to insufficient acquisition of immunity. If herd immunity can be induced, it would act as a barrier to stop the spread of infection (
 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Gomes et al., 2020</xref>). In addition to vaccines, variable susceptibility and exposure largely determine herd immunity. Vaccination of children to induce herd immunity has proven successful in preventing the spread of many infectious diseases, where children have a significant role in transmission. A high level of immunity in one age group, who play a role in transmission, can create herd immunity for others (
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2011</xref>), and it is evident that immunization of children is more effective than vaccination of elderly people, in certain situations, as demonstrated in immunization against influenza (
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">Kim, 2014</xref>), pneumococcal disease (
 <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">Pittet and Posfay-Barbe, 2012</xref>), rotavirus (
 <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">Lopman et al., 2012</xref>) and many others. It is noteworthy that the relative role of different age groups in transmission must be taken into account – for example vaccination of adoelscents and young adults prevents spread of meningococcal disease, but infants and toddlers must be targeted to induce herd immunity for pneumococcal, and Hib disease, and school-age children for influenza transmission. Children may need protection also, as some become ill, although almost never severely. The indirect benefits of COVID-19 vaccination in children may provide or create some protection for older, unvaccinated populations. When children are vaccinated, it will be easier to achieve enough immunity needed for overall protection in a given population.
</p>
