<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Alcoholic liver disease (ALD) foreshadows a wide variety of liver pathologies from basic steatosis to advanced liver injuries such as steatohepatitis and fibrosis/cirrhosis [
 <xref rid="B77-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Steatosis almost always occurs in the hepatocytes of people that consume excessive amounts of alcohol. In 20–40% of heavy drinkers there is progression to steatohepatitis through neutrophil infiltration and related inflammation [
 <xref rid="B78-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Excessive alcohol consumption promotes the production of prooxidants and strengthens the antioxidant mechanism, which leads to hepatocyte injury accompanied by inflammation; this eventually results in liver failure or cancer [
 <xref rid="B79-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. ALD hepatitis is directly related to the toxic effects of alcohol. It is indirectly caused by fecal infection or adipose tissue impairment resulting from bacteria-related endotoxins, including lipopolysaccharides (LPSs). It is also caused by elevated levels of free fatty acids, and by proinflammatory adipokines, which are found in the blood but also regulate liver function. Several authors have reported changes in the levels of ALD-corelated proteins in the serum. TG accumulation in the liver is the first histological change due to alcohol, and is reversible. Trinchet et al. (1994) reported that elevated levels of primary bile acids are associated with alcoholic hepatitis (AH) [
 <xref rid="B80-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Moratti et al. reported that increased plasma levels of protein tyrosine phosphatase receptor type gamma (PTPRG) isoform sPTPRG in EVs excreted from the human hepatocellular carcinoma cell line HepG2 are associated with alcohol-related hepatic injury [
 <xref rid="B81-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. FSP27/CIDEC (fat-specific protein 27/cell death-inducing DNA fragmentation factor alpha-like effector c)—which promotes alcohol-stimulated liver damage—was highly expressed in the hepatocytes of a mice model following chronic and binge alcohol consumption, and in alcoholic hepatitis (AH) patients [
 <xref rid="B82-ijms-21-03732" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. The summary of the liquid factors associated with liver inflammation in ALD as shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijms-21-03732-f003">Figure 3</xref> in advance.
</p>
