<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The proviral activity of rlipase 1 for NHLF cells 
 <italic>ex vivo</italic> further suggests a potential role during human clinical infection, and the enhanced virus replication 
 <italic>in ovo</italic> indicates the relevance of the lipase 1 activity for IAV in a complex 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> environment. Animal models have demonstrated disease exacerbation upon coinfection (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>), and expression of lipase 1, which is widespread in 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. aureus</named-content> (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="figS4">Fig. S4</xref> in the supplemental material), has been suggested to occur during human infection, based on the detection of antibodies (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Accordingly, we suggest that 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. aureus</named-content> superinfection of humans with influenza may lead to a lipase 1-mediated enhancement of virus replication, resulting in a more prolonged and severe infection. Furthermore, the damage caused by the increased IAV replication in fibroblasts in the lung may lead to increased occurrence of fibrosis, which has been demonstrated during bacterial coinfection (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Additionally, IAV-
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. pneumoniae</named-content> coinfection models have demonstrated the viral neuraminidase can cleave sialic acid (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>), which bacteria can utilize as an energy source (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>), and IAV infection also results in an increase in levels of host adhesion molecules, such as fibronectin (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>), that both 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. pneumoniae</named-content> and 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. aureus</named-content> can bind. Therefore, enhanced virus replication could facilitate the spread and replication of bacteria, suggesting an indirect beneficial role for lipase 1 in the pathogenesis of 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. aureus</named-content> during coinfection. Although it is well established that secondary bacterial pneumonia is a major cause of mortality during IAV epidemics, animal models of IAV-
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. aureus</named-content> infection have offered differing pictures of the outcome of coinfection. While some murine models have demonstrated increased severity of 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. aureus</named-content> respiratory disease when preceded by IAV infection (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>), in a cynomolgus macaque model, prior infection with IAV did not predispose the animals to more-severe infection with 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. aureus</named-content> USA300 (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). The authors concluded that the distinct observations made compared to human clinical and rodent model data may have been due to variation in the strain of virus employed or to a host species-specific effect on susceptibility to IAV or 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. aureus</named-content> infection. Alternatively, it was suggested that the findings may indicate that unknown comorbidities are required to promote the synergistic effect of IAV-
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">S. aureus</named-content> coinfection (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>).
</p>
