<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0095">Corticosteroid utilization also requires special attention with respect to COVID-19 disease severity in people with DM 
 <xref rid="b0205" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. Acute lung damage and acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) are partly due to the host immune response and corticosteroids were broadly used in SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV infections 
 <xref rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref> due to their ability to suppress histologically proven virus-dependent lung inflammation with diffuse alveolar damage 
 <xref rid="b0220" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. However, they also inhibit immunity and pathogen clearance and, in the face of very little benefit if so ever, have been associated with delayed viral RNA clearance or increased mortality and rate of complications, including diabetes, psychosis, and avascular necrosis 
 <xref rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. Due to all the above, the interim guidance from the WHO on clinical management of severe acute respiratory infection advises against the use of corticosteroids upon suspicion of SARS-CoV-2 infection outside clinical trials 
 <xref rid="b0225" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, yet corticosteroids were extensively utilized before that in at least 34% of the large number of Northern Italian hospitalized patients 
 <xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. At analysing the growth curve of coronavirus infection in Italy, the massive referral to the hospitals of so many people within a very a short period strikes the eye when compared to the small number of hospitalized patients in the South (Figura 4). In the stormy and overcrowded emergency conditions faced by health professionals at the start of the epidemic in the absence of any experience with treating COVID-19 disease, a broader recourse to high doses of corticosteroids most likely occurred than later on, when in fact better treatment strategies were identified and emergency departments were less congested. It can be assumed that the above mentioned logistic and environmental factors strongly affected clinical course and mortality rates of COVID-19-infected people and even more in those with DM. Indeed, 
 <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> clearly shows that death rate was significantly higher in infected Northern Italy inhabitants than in their Southern counterpart (i.e. 17.2% vs 5.5%, respectively). According to current protocols, subject to the exceptions needed for treatment personalization, the use of corticosteroids is extremely limited if so ever. This might also help healthcare teams adopt an intensive, fully integrated therapeutic approach for their patients with DM, especially those in the ICUs, involving drugs expected to prevent at their best both hypoglycemic events and dramatic hyperglycemic spikes contributing to marked glycemic variability, i.e. a severe mortality risk driver 
 <xref rid="b0235" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref> (see 
 <xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> ).
</p>
