<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Multiplex PCR or RT-PCR is the amplification of multiple targets simultaneously in a single PCR by using several primer pairs specific for each target. Development of a multiplex PCR or RT-PCR assay is often complex since primers must comply with several conditions: i) similar melting temperatures (similar length and G-C content) so that all primers can function under the same PCR conditions; ii) compatibility, avoiding cross-binding and competition; iii) similar sensitivity; and iv) flanking genomic regions of different sizes so that the amplicons of each target can be separated and visualized by gel electrophoresis. The last constriction can be avoided by using primers labeled with different color fluorescent dyes or coupling the PCR with hybridization with specific probes (
 <xref rid="B113" ref-type="bibr">James et al., 2006</xref>). Multiplex PCR or RT-PCR have been used to identify: i) the main viruses infecting a particular crop, such as tomato, tobacco, legumes, potato, ornamentals, cucumber and olive (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Bariana et al., 1994</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Bertolini et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">Dai et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B183" ref-type="bibr">Panno et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">Ge et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Ali et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B180" ref-type="bibr">Pallás et al., 2018</xref>); ii) viruses from the same genus (
 <xref rid="B244" ref-type="bibr">Uga and Tsuda, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">Hu et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B184" ref-type="bibr">Panno et al., 2014</xref>); and iii) different strains of a viral species (
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">Hammond et al., 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B171" ref-type="bibr">Nie and Singh, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Alfaro-Fernández et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Bester et al., 2012</xref>). Multiplex real-time qPCR with Taqman probes labeled with different fluorescent dyes have been used to identify viruses from the same crop (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Abrahamian et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B143" ref-type="bibr">López-Fabuel et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B145" ref-type="bibr">Malandraki et al., 2017</xref>), and strains or isolates from the same viral species (
 <xref rid="B248" ref-type="bibr">Varga and James, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Debreczeni et al., 2011</xref>). The main problem of multiplex PCR is that only a limited number of targets can be amplified simultaneously since the more primers are used, the higher is the probability of incompatibility between some of them. Also, there is a limitation in the number of products of different sizes that can be resolved by electrophoresis or the number of fluorescent dyes that can be used (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Boonham et al., 2007</xref>). Multiplex LAMP has also been developed for the simultaneous detection of some plant viruses (
 <xref rid="B270" ref-type="bibr">Zhang J. et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B262" ref-type="bibr">Wilisiani et al., 2019</xref>). Molecular hybridization with cocktails of probes or polyprobes (probes linked in tandem) has been used to detect different viruses affecting a crop (
 <xref rid="B220" ref-type="bibr">Sánchez-Navarro et al., 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B216" ref-type="bibr">Saade et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">Herranz et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Aparicio et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B153" ref-type="bibr">Minutillo et al., 2012</xref>), although further analyses are necessary to identify each virus.
</p>
