<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Microarray analyses can screen many samples simultaneously. They can be based on serology, but most are based on molecular hybridization (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Boonham et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Boonham et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">Charlermroj et al., 2014</xref>). Capture probes corresponding to different viruses and/or genomic regions are attached to a solid support (usually glass) and the sample to be examined is fluorescently labeled so the identity of the virus or viruses present in the sample is determined by the fluorescent positions on the array. Capture probes can be produced from PCR products (200–1000 bp in length) or synthetic oligonucleotides (20–70 nucleotides in length). Probe design must consider probe length, melting temperature, GC content, secondary structure caused by self-annealing and hybridization free energy since they affect sensitivity and specificity. Short oligonucleotides (15–25 bases) are better to discriminate small sequence differences but exhibit reduced sensitivity. Oligoprobes can be designed for different detection levels (genus, species and strain) by choosing conserved or variable sequence stretches. Sensitivity and specificity can be improved controlling the hybridization temperature and buffer composition (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Boonham et al., 2007</xref>). Microarrays have been used to detect: i) viruses infecting a particular crop, such as tomato, cucurbits, potato and grapevine (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Bystricka et al., 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">Engel et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B231" ref-type="bibr">Sip et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B240" ref-type="bibr">Tiberini et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B239" ref-type="bibr">Tiberini and Barba, 2012</xref>); ii) different viral species of a genus (
 <xref rid="B260" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al., 2009</xref>); and iii) isolates or variants of the same virus (
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Deyong et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B186" ref-type="bibr">Pasquini et al., 2008</xref>). Microarrays have been improved to detect hundreds of plant viruses, including genus-specific oligoprobes (
 <xref rid="B267" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B170" ref-type="bibr">Nicolaisen, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B167" ref-type="bibr">Nam et al., 2014</xref>).
</p>
