<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack>
 <p>The “Global Influenza B Study team” (group authorship) includes the following scientists: Juan Manuel Rudi (
  <email>jmrudi@anlis.gov.ar</email>), National Institute of Respiratory Diseases "Emilio Coni", Santa Fe, Argentina; Dorji Wangchuk (
  <email>dorjiwangchuk@health.gov.bt</email>) and Sangay Zangmo (
  <email>szangmo@health.gov.bt</email>), Royal Centre for Disease Control, Department of Public Health, Ministry of Health, Thimphu, Bhutan; Daiana Araujo da Silva (
  <email>daiana.silva@saude.gov.br</email>), Ministry of Health, Department of Surveillance of Transmissible Diseases, Brasília/DF, Brazil; Winston Andrade (
  <email>wandrade@ispch.cl</email>), Sub-Department of Viral Diseases, Instituto de Salud Pública de Chile, Santiago, Chile; Jiandong Zheng (
  <email>zhengjd@chinacdc.cn</email>) and Ying Qin (
  <email>qinying@chinacdc.cn</email>), Division of Infectious Diseases, Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Beijing, P.R. China; Joanna Ellis (
  <email>joanna.ellis@phe.gov.uk</email>), Public Health England, London, United Kingdom; Simona Puzelli (
  <email>simona.puzelli@iss.it</email>), National Influenza Center, Department of Infectious Diseases, National Institute of Health, Rome, Italy; Caterina Rizzo (
  <email>rizzocaterina@gmail.com</email>), Bambino Gesù Children's Hospital, Rome, Italy; Linus Ndegwa (
  <email>ikf7@cdc.gov</email>), Influenza Program, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Nairobi, Kenya; Marit MA de Lange (
  <email>marit.de.lange@rivm.nl</email>) and Anne C. Teirlinck (
  <email>anne.teirlinck@rivm.nl</email>), National Institute for Public Health and the Environment, Centre for Infectious Diseases, Epidemiology and Surveillance, Bilthoven, The Netherlands; Jeffery Cutter (
  <email>jeffery_cutter@moh.gov.sg</email>) and Raymond Tzer Pin Lin (
  <email>raymond_lin@moh.gov.sg</email>), Public Health Group, Ministry of Health, Singapore, Singapore; Than T. Le (
  <email>lmot82@yahoo.com</email>), National Institute of Hygiene and Epidemiology, Hanoi, Vietnam; Peter Kinuthia 
  <sup>42</sup> (
  <email>polorien@gmail.com</email>), IHRC Inc., Atlanta, USA.
 </p>
 <p>We thank the Australia Influenza Surveillance Network for making their data publically available to researchers. In the Netherlands, we would like to thank the general practitioner network coordinated by Nivel and their patients for participation in the surveillance of influenza-like illness and other acute respiratory infections; the technicians who did all the laboratory analyses of the surveillance specimens; and epidemiologists with which this surveillance collaboratively has been performed (Marit de Lange, MSc; Dr. Anne Teirlinck; Dr. Wim van der Hoek). Influenza surveillance data Turkey were provided by Meral A. Ciblak (Sanofi Pasteur, Lyon, France) while working at the Istanbul University, Istanbul, Turkey. The findings and conclusions in this report are those of the authors and do not necessarily represent the official position of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</p>
</ack>
