<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Coronaviruses (CoVs) are serious pathogens to humans and vertebrates affecting the hepatic, gastrointestinal, respiratory, and central nervous systems [
 <xref rid="B2-ijerph-17-05813" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Coronaviruses belong to the Coronaviridae subfamily of the Nidovirales family. This subfamily is comprised of four genera: α-coronaviruses, β-coronaviruses, γ-coronaviruses, and δ-coronaviruses [
 <xref rid="B3-ijerph-17-05813" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Various CoVs exhibit broad host ranges and tropism of tissue. Mammals typically get infected by α- and β-coronaviruses, whereas γ- and δ-coronaviruses typically affect birds and fish but only occasionally mammals [
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-17-05813" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The world has witnessed a series of coronavirus waves during the past two decades, triggering pandemics that have their perturbations on global health. The first one, named severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS-CoV), had its last outbreak reported in September 2003 after infecting more than 8000 persons and causing 774 deaths with a fatality rate of 9.5 percent [
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-17-05813" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Nine years later, Middle East Respiratory Syndrome (MERS-CoV) triggered a respiratory disease in the Middle East. Even so; MERS-CoV is still ongoing compared to SARS-CoV, and the fatality rate was much higher (about 35%). Since December 2019 a third one called COVID-19 has emerged in Wuhan, Hubei province in China. COVID-19 is widely dispersed in humans and its genome is detached from SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV. China classified COVID-19 as a B-infectious disease according to the surveillance system of infectious diseases, which was updated in 2004, and categorized infectious diseases into classes A, B, and C [
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-17-05813" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Class A is highly infectious and causes massive epidemics within very short timespans, and includes plaque and cholera only. B-infectious diseases might cause epidemics and include acute respiratory syndrome (SARS), acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS), viral hepatitis, poliomyelitis, highly pathogenic avian influenza, epidemic hemorrhagic fever, measles, epidemic encephalitis B, rabies, anthrax, bacillary and amebic dysentery, dengue fever, epidemic cerebrospinal meningitis, pertussis, diphtheria, neonatal tetanus, scarlet fever, brucellosis, gonorrhea, syphilis, leptospirosis, schistosomiasis, malaria, influenza A (H1N1), and typhoid fever. Class C involves less serious and fewer infectious diseases such as rubella, leprosy, mumps, leishmaniasis, and acute hemorrhagic conjunctivitis [
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-17-05813" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The new COVID-19 pandemic caused by SARS-CoV-2 has prevailed rapidly and infected around 17 million individuals worldwide (July 31, 2020) [
 <xref rid="B8-ijerph-17-05813" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The basic reproduction or transmission number (R0 value) was estimated to be between 2 and 3.5, meaning that one patient can transfer the disease to 2 or 3 other individuals with a fatality rate of about 2 to 3%. SARS-CoV-2 caused many more deaths than its coronaviral relatives, while the mortality rates are considerably lower than MERS-CoV infections. The largest contributing factor towards enabling the control of MERS-CoV is the a low basic reproduction number (R0 around 1), indicating that each person transmits it to just one other individual (SARS-CoV R0 was around 4) [
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-17-05813" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The COVID-19 pandemic has posed an eminent threat to many countries. China took into consideration the surveillance role to control and manage epidemics. These rules include: Illustrating the natural history of pathogens, identifying case spread, initiating disease control measures, tracking infection epidemics, forecasting and preventing epidemics, and providing bases for strategy adaptation. Despite the measures, this epidemic caused health (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-17-05813-f001">Figure 1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-17-05813-f002">Figure 2</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B10-ijerph-17-05813" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] and economic losses and led to isolation among the countries of the world and between peoples inside the same state. In response to that crisis, there is an urgent requirement to figure out different impacts of COVID-19 to public health.
</p>
