<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para550">Our recommendations on the use of tracheostomy during the COVID-19 pandemic are presented in the 
 <xref rid="box1" ref-type="boxed-text">panel</xref> . A defining feature of this pandemic is its pervasive and variable character. Increases in the number of patients with COVID-19 who are critically ill can swiftly overwhelm hospitals, particularly because many require extended periods of ventilator support, and many will require tracheostomy to facilitate recovery. Globally, studies of the COVID-19 pandemic have a recurring theme: foresight and planning save lives, whereas inadequate preparedness is associated with overwhelmed health systems. Because tracheostomy is at the intersection of health-care worker safety, resource allocation, and patient-centred care, sound guidance is crucial.
 <boxed-text id="box1">
  <label>Panel</label>
  <caption>
   <title>Summary of recommendations for tracheostomy during the COVID-19 pandemic</title>
  </caption>
  <p id="para10">Tracheostomy has a continuing role in managing weaning from extended periods of mechanical ventilation during the COVID-19 pandemic, but the procedure might not always provide benefit, and tracheostomy and subsequent care pose risks to health-care workers. The consensus working group recommendations are expert opinion (denoted by “we suggest” throughout the text) informed by best available evidence, or published supporting statements (denoted by “we recommend”).</p>
  <p id="para20">
   <bold>Patient selection for tracheostomy</bold>
  </p>
  <p id="para30">
   <list list-type="simple" id="celist10">
    <list-item id="celistitem10">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="para40">We suggest that standard decision making be adapted for the COVID-19 pandemic, taking into account a range of considerations, including potential risks and benefits for the individual patient; risks posed to health-care workers, other patients, and family; and available health-care resources</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
  <p id="para50">
   <bold>Timing of tracheostomy</bold>
  </p>
  <p id="para60">
   <list list-type="simple" id="celist20">
    <list-item id="celistitem20">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="para70">We suggest that tracheostomy be delayed until at least day 10 of mechanical ventilation and considered only when patients are showing signs of clinical improvement</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="celistitem30">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="para80">We recommend a conservative approach to attempted extubation, limited to patients who are predicted to have a high chance of success</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
  <p id="para90">
   <bold>Performance of tracheostomy</bold>
  </p>
  <p id="para100">
   <list list-type="simple" id="celist30">
    <list-item id="celistitem40">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="para110">We suggest that ICU and surgical teams review the optimal location for tracheostomy during the pandemic, balancing the risks to patients and staff and taking into account local facilities and expertise</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="celistitem50">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="para120">We recommend a hierarchical approach to operative location, balancing patient and staff risks (
      <xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">appendix p 1</xref>)
     </p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="celistitem60">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="para130">We suggest use of enhanced PPE, using powered air-purifying respirators, eye protection, fluid-repellent disposable surgical gown, and gloves</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="celistitem70">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="para140">We suggest that operators continue to do tracheostomies using the techniques and equipment with which they are familiar, and confident and experienced in using</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="celistitem80">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="para150">We suggest maintenance of a bloodless field, minimal use of diathermy, and use of a smoke evacuator when using an open surgical approach for tracheostomy</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="celistitem90">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="para160">We suggest preoxygenation, followed by a trial of apnoea in the ICU, with an FiO
      <sub>2</sub> of 1·0 and positive end expiratory pressure of 5 cm H
      <sub>2</sub>O, in patients who are supine before tracheostomy to show physiological readiness to tolerate the procedure, with strategies to mitigate aerosolisation
     </p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
  <p id="para170">
   <bold>Optimal management after tracheostomy</bold>
  </p>
  <p id="para180">
   <list list-type="simple" id="celist40">
    <list-item id="celistitem100">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="para190">Key principles include a focus on essential care and avoidance of unnecessary interventions (especially those that generate aerosols), early recognition of deterioration, and timely responses to emergencies</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="celistitem110">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="para200">We suggest that systems be planned to summon help from adjacent clinical areas during a tracheostomy emergency (staff might already be wearing PPE in preparation for such emergencies)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="celistitem120">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="para210">We suggest reducing the frequency of changing an inner cannula (if used) and cuff pressure checks; these decisions should be made on an individual basis and reviewed daily</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="celistitem130">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="para220">We recommend commencing care after tracheostomy with a simple heat and moisture exchange filter to provide humidification; the requirement for heated, water-based humidification or adjuncts, such as saline or hypertonic saline nebulisers, should be made on an individual basis and reviewed daily</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item id="celistitem140">
     <label>•</label>
     <p id="para230">We suggest that facemasks and tracheostomy shields be used by patients undergoing trials of tracheostomy cuff deflation to mitigate risks of aerosols</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
  <p id="para240">ICU=intensive care unit. PPE=personal protective equipment. FiO
   <sub>2</sub>=fractional concentration of oxygen in inspired air.
  </p>
 </boxed-text>
</p>
