<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Only few variants have been so far identified in ERAP2 sequence. The rs2549782 SNP, encoding the K392N aminoacidic substitution, occurs in most populations with a balanced frequency and modulates the enzymatic activity and substrate specificity of the aminopeptidase [
 <xref rid="B31-cells-09-00720" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Indeed, in vitro studies showed that the N392 variant is much more effective than its 392K counterpart in trimming hydrophobic N-terminal residues [
 <xref rid="B30-cells-09-00720" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Such difference is secondary to changes in the catalytic site and in the binding site of the N-terminal domain. This SNP can lead to a variability in the antigen processing activity among individuals carrying either variant of the enzyme [
 <xref rid="B30-cells-09-00720" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Rs2549782 is in LD with another polymorphism, the non-coding rs2248374 (A/G). Notably, the G allele of this polymorphism is transcribed into a spliced form with an extended exon 10 (56 extra nucleotides) containing two in frame TAG stop codons, which undergoes degradation through nonsense-mediated decay (NMD) process [
 <xref rid="B32-cells-09-00720" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Notably, SNP rs2248374 is in LD with 11 other SNP variants; this allows the definition of two haplotypes, hereafter referred to as HapA (A allele for rs2248374) and HapB (G allele for rs2248374), at intermediate frequency in most human populations [
 <xref rid="B31-cells-09-00720" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The maintenance of both haplotypes with the same incidence suggests that, despite NMD, even transcript(s) derived from HapB could confer fitness advantages, possibly in particular milieus. Indeed, an analysis recently conducted on dendritic cells carrying the G allele of this SNP revealed that two previously unknown short isoforms (ERAP2/ISO3, ERAP2/ISO4) are transcribed from this haplotype following influenza infection, thanks to the creation of a different preferred splice site [
 <xref rid="B33-cells-09-00720" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. This finding suggests how the balancing selection of the rs2248374-tagged haplotypes could be the consequence of variability in ERAP2 expression—including the transcription of alternative forms of the protein—and peptide processing, providing an advantage against viral infections [
 <xref rid="B33-cells-09-00720" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].
</p>
