<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is now becoming more evident that BatIVs may transmit in a different manner than conventional flu strains. It has recently been shown that the H18N11 virus readily transmits between bats (Ciminski et al., 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2019b</xref>). Following experimental intranasal H18N11 infection, the Neotropical 
 <italic>Phylostomidae</italic> bat species 
 <italic>Artibeus jamaicensis</italic> shed high viral loads via the fecal route and were able to infect naïve contact animals (Ciminski et al., 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2019b</xref>). Histopathological analysis of the infected bats indicated that viral replication proceeds in the follicle-associated epithelium of gut-associated lymphoid tissue, suggesting virus uptake from the gastrointestinal lumen (Ciminski et al., 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2019b</xref>), in line with the rich gut epithelial expression of MHC-II (Wosen et al., 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Furthermore, the researchers detected high loads of H18N11 viral transcripts in rectal swabs and excretions (Ciminski et al., 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2019b</xref>). Collectively, these findings imply that an environmental (fecal-oral) mode of BatIVs transmission is more likely than an airborne one, albeit the latter is not yet compellingly disproved. Other infection routes including subcutaneous, transplacental, vaginal, intracranial infections have not yet been reported. In contrast to bats, H18N11 has been reported to have limited replicative ability in laboratory mice and more interestingly in ferrets which share similar lung physiology and SA distributions to humans (Ciminski et al., 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2019b</xref>; Karakus et al., 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; Zhong et al., 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Whether these observations are animal/infection-route-dependent or they actually reflect a low zoonotic risk for BatIVs remains to be seen.
</p>
