<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In absence of conclusive scientific proof, the question remains as to whether BatIVs are confined to a sylvatic transmission cycle and perpetuate in Neotropical bat populations or are capable of urban adaptation. Anthropogenic disruptions of ecological habitats that led to urban transmission of other enzootic bat viruses (i.e., HeV, NiV) have been extensively described in the scientific literature. Despite the increasing disturbances in the fire-prone Neotropical forests, New World bats have not yet been implicated in the transmission of zoonotic viruses, other than rabies, to humans (Moratelli and Calisher, 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Even so, Latin America is home to the richest and most diverse bat fauna in the world (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) including almost 150 
 <italic>Phyllostomidae</italic> species (Jenkins et al., 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) in which BatIVs have been detected. Unlike African and Asian bats which are consumed regularly, New World bats are only eaten by few native indigenous people (Moratelli and Calisher, 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). A possible exposure to infected bat blood and body fluids may hypothetically create a pathway for disease transmission to humans. Another scenario may involve the accidental introduction of BatIVs to the local fauna or other 
 <italic>Phyllostomidae</italic> species such as the widespread blood-eating vampire bat (
 <italic>Desmodus rotundus</italic>), which thrives in both native and anthropogenically transformed ecosystems (Bergner et al., 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Vampire bats have long been suspected of passing on rabies to humans and livestock in Latin America by biting and scratching (Rupprecht et al., 
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). It will be useful to explore in future studies whether haematophagous bats can act as maintenance hosts for BatIVs and if their biting can form a potential zoonotic transmission route either directly or through mammalian intermediate hosts.
</p>
