<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>YFV research is currently limited as it remains challenging and expensive to establish workflows with non-human primates. While YFV has a limited host species-tropism, artificial infection of laboratory mice and hamsters is possible, although the course of disease differs from that observed in humans [
 <xref rid="B144-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">144</xref>]. Nevertheless, a number of studies in genetically modified or humanized mice have yielded insights into YFV infection and dissemination in vivo. Single cell-tracking of YFV-17D dissemination in different mouse models identified novel YFV replication reservoirs in secondary lymphoid compartments, with hematopoietic STAT1 knockout increasing virus-induced pathogenicity [
 <xref rid="B122-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. Double-humanized mice have been developed, possessing both human immune systems and hepatocytes [
 <xref rid="B145-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">145</xref>,
 <xref rid="B146-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">146</xref>], and these animals represent ideal tools for monitoring systemic YFV infection in vivo as both compartments are permissive for YFV. In addition to hepatotropism, YFV can also be neurotropic in rodents, primates and humans [
 <xref rid="B147-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>,
 <xref rid="B148-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">148</xref>]. In contrast to polio virus and reovirus, which infect the brain via the CNS, YFV-17D infects brain tissue by crossing the blood-brain barrier [
 <xref rid="B149-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">149</xref>]. A mouse-neurovirulent strain (SPYF) based on the Porterfield 17D (PYF17D) strain was derived by additional passaging in SCID mice, exhibiting enhanced neurovirulence and neuroinvasiveness. This enhanced neurotopism was correlated with 13 amino acid substitutions, five of which were located in the E protein [
 <xref rid="B80-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Arboviruses can encounter dissemination barriers in mosquitos, restricting the spreading of the virus within the vector species. These include innate immunity related pathways as well as physical tissue barriers associated with the midgut and salivary glands [
 <xref rid="B150-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>,
 <xref rid="B151-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">151</xref>]. However, while patterns of YFV-17D dissemination in immunocompetent mice were restricted, infection of 
 <italic>IFNAR</italic> knockout mice resulted in broad dissemination preceding viral clearance, indicating that no barriers to dissemination exist in the absence of type I IFN [
 <xref rid="B152-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>]. Furthermore, while I and II type IFNs contribute to control of YFV-17D infection, type III IFN was demonstrated to have immunomodulatory functions and was protective against YFV-17D neuroinvasion in mouse models [
 <xref rid="B153-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>]. YFD-17D infection of IFN-α/β receptor and STAT1 signaling molecule deficient mice resulted in systemic viscerotropic infection: a course of disease which resembles that observed in humans rather than the typical encephalitic disease course commonly reported for mice [
 <xref rid="B154-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">154</xref>]. Finally, while many flaviviruses share the common ability to antagonize IFN signaling and therefore enhance viral replication, the YFV NS5 is unable to bind murine STAT2 and in contrast to ZIKV and DENV, is unable to engage human STAT2 in murine cells. Murine STAT2 was demonstrated to repress YFV replication in murine cells, which was correlated with an absence of IFN-α/β-mediated NS5 ubiquitination [
 <xref rid="B155-viruses-11-00960" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>]. Together, these mouse studies enhance our understanding of YFV dissemination and host control in vivo. These findings are useful for the development of the next generation of small animal disease models for YFV, which should endeavor to recapitulate the disease course seen in humans. Thus, the generation of an immunocompetent mouse model would be beneficial, which could be realized by knocking out downstream specific anti-YFV effectors that directly inhibit differential aspects of the YFV lifecycle, rather than upstream master-regulators of the antiviral response. Screening approaches could identify such factors.
</p>
