<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The placenta also contains an extensive number of mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs) of fetal origin, including amnion mesenchymal stromal cells, chorionic villi mesenchymal stromal cells, and decidua mesenchymal stromal cells, which can differentiate into endothelial cells or macrophages known as Hofbauer cells (HCs). Analysis of HCs in Reyes et al. has revealed that these cells are heterogeneous, and the diversity of HCs differs throughout pregnancy, during which the first and third trimesters gave rise to more diverse populations [
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. As antigen-presenting cells of the placenta, HCs, in conjunction with trophoblasts, are mainly responsible for protecting the fetus from pathogens or toxins, and have been shown to adopt an M2 polarity phenotype as opposed to M1, which is characteristic of alternatively activated macrophages [
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. While M1 macrophages are able to kill microbes, M2 macrophages are associated with regulating and inhibiting inflammatory and immune responses as part of the repair machinery following an infection [
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. M2 polarization, therefore, enable HCs to serve as possible reservoirs of pathogens in the placenta, contributing to the vertical transmission of pathogens from the mother to the fetus. In addition to placental immunity, HCs are also important regulators of trophoblast differentiation, vasculogenesis, and angiogenesis through their production of cytokines and growth factors [
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. These placental macrophages are able to fulfil a role in placental development, fetal protection, and intercellular communication through their ability to be motile, phagocytose exogenous antibodies and to associate in groups, as demonstrated by in vitro and in vivo studies using various experimental techniques, such as microscopy, flow cytometry, and immunohistochemistry [
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-12-00005" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].
</p>
