<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For biological activities observed in RS to be effective in humans, this macromolecule must be transported into the blood after its oral intake. As a polymer with a molecular weight of more than 30,000, RS transportation into the blood via oral ingestion has traditionally been considered difficult. Previous studies on fucoidan, a polymeric sulfate polysaccharide similar to RS, may be helpful for elucidating the in vivo absorption of RS. Fucoidan is a dietary fiber that is abundant in viscous matter of brown algae, such as kelp, seaweed, and mozuku (
 <italic>Nemacystus decipiens</italic>). It is mainly a sulfated polysaccharide composed of tens to hundreds of thousands of L-fucose, and its average molecular weight is about 200,000. In a clinical study of fucoidan, about 50 ng/mL of fucoidan was detected in the blood six hours after the single oral administration of the agent [
 <xref rid="B56-marinedrugs-18-00228" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>], demonstrating that fucoidan, despite its small quantity, was absorbed from the intestine and transported to the blood. Although fucoidan and RS are composed of different sugars, their chemical structures are similar, so it is assumed that RS enters the blood in a similar manner. Terasawa et al. showed that FITC-labeled RS colocalized with Peyer’s patch M cells 30 min after oral administration of the RS, indicating that RS could bind to the M cells and become incorporated into Peyer’s patches [
 <xref rid="B13-marinedrugs-18-00228" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Microfold cells (M cells) are a part of the intestinal epithelium that is involved in the selective uptake of antigens, such as polymers and bacteria, from the gut lumen into Peyer’s patches, an intestinal lymphoid tissue [
 <xref rid="B57-marinedrugs-18-00228" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-marinedrugs-18-00228" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B59-marinedrugs-18-00228" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Thus, it is quite possible that orally ingested RS is transported from the gut lumen into the blood via M cells in Peyer’s patches, where it carries out various biological activities.
</p>
