<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Notably, changes in cellular cholesterol are linked with the immune system both as a consequence and as a cause [
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], as a disrupted cholesterol biosynthesis triggers the activation of the IFN-mediated innate immune response [
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Both types of medication interfere with the ergosterol synthesis pathway of the host cell [
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Both compounds inhibit cytochrome P450 (CYP) enzymes, particularly the lanosterol 14α-demethylase, which is not only essential for the ergosterol biosynthesis in fungi but also impairs cholesterol homeostasis and 
 <italic>de-novo</italic> synthesis in mammalian cells. A crucial role of cellular cholesterol in the defense against pathogens, and in particular against many viruses, has been shown in numerous studies [
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Disturbed ergosterol metabolism shifts the tightly balanced type I IFN expression levels [
 <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>] toward induction of a pre-activated state, thereby accelerating the virus-induced host cell response. However, the unaltered cholesterol contents detected in itraconazole and posaconazole-treated cells suggest that the antiviral effect is not due to a disturbed cellular cholesterol biosynthesis. Of note, itraconazole was identified as a small molecule inhibitor of the endosomal cholesterol transporter NPC1 that directly binds to the sterol-sensing domain of NPC1, resulting in cholesterol accumulation in LE/L [
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. To release the viral genome into the cytosol of the host cell, the lipid envelope of IAV fuses with the membrane of the acidified late endosomes [
 <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45–47</xref>]. Exactly at this cellular site, which is critical for the IAV infection, a drug-induced high accumulation of cholesterol was observed, consistent with previous publications [
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. The significance of elevated LE/L cholesterol levels for IAV endosomal escape is still controversially discussed [
 <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. However, there is strong evidence that elevated levels in this compartment negatively impact viral genome transfer into the host cell cytosol [
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Additionally, shifting the cholesterol homeostasis towards the LE/L compartments diminishes the levels of cholesterol in the host cell plasma membrane, causing decreased cholesterol contents in the envelope of the nascent virus progeny, which reduces infectivity of newly released IAV particles [
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. A solid body of evidence has already shown that the balance of cellular cholesterol is a key determinant in the infection of a wide range of viruses [
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10–14</xref>]. In this regard, itraconazole was shown to function as a broad-spectrum inhibitor for enteroviruses through modulation of the host cholesterol homeostasis [
 <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Our data contradict a study by Shim et al. [
 <xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Contrary to our experimental set-up, which measures the inhibitory effect on the exposure to a defined viral load by determining the amount of virus released after 24 h by a plaque assay, in this study an assay based on the reduction of a cytopathic effect (CPE) was used to determine potential inhibitory effects after 2 days of incubation with the virus. It is difficult to evaluate from these data whether the correlation of cell death with virus titers was still in a dynamic range, and an inhibitory effect on viral replication might have remained undetected. In line with this assumption, we also observed a more obvious inhibitory effect at the lower viral doses (0.005 MOI). Furthermore, after 3 additional rounds of replication, even reduced numbers of viral progeny might have been still sufficient to kill nearly the whole population (because viral replication is exponential).
</p>
