<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ticks are major hematophagous arthropod vectors that harbor multiple infectious agents. Some of these agents are known to infect humans, leading to several tick-borne diseases such as Lyme borreliosis (
 <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi sensu lato</italic>), tick-borne encephalitis (due to several flaviviruses such as tick-borne encephalitis virus or Powassan virus), and spotted fever (several 
 <italic>Rickettsia</italic>) (Moyer, 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Nelder et al., 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). However, asymptomatic or pauci-symptomatic infections with non-specific syndromes (for example, asthenia, fever, myalgia, etc.) occurring after tick bites are frequent and have become a serious issue (Moyer, 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). The same situation is observed for domestic animals: since several tick species, mainly ixodid ticks, are able to feed both on domestic animals and humans (Kiewra and Lonc, 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), they can transmit zoonotic pathogens common to animals and humans. Moreover, due to global and local environmental changes, the geographical repartition of ticks is increasing, leading to exposure of naive populations to new pathogens (Ogden et al., 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). The progresses in usage of high-throughput sequencing (HTS) have allowed an increase in the knowledge of infectious agents, and particularly viruses, carried by ticks. Recent studies have indeed reported the identification of new tick-borne viruses, belonging either to known or completely new viral families, for which the potential zoonotic risk for humans or domestic animals is still unknown (Tokarz et al., 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">2014a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Xia et al., 
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Moutailler et al., 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Shi et al., 
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Pettersson et al., 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). For example, among the 
 <italic>Phenuiviridae</italic>, known to contain tick-borne pathogens such as the severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome phlebovirus (SFTS virus) (Silvas and Aguilar, 
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), recent bisegmented phleboviruses have been described, such as Lihan tick phlebovirus (LTPV) primarily identified in 
 <italic>Rhipicephalus microplus</italic> ticks from China, Brazil, and Trinidad and Tobago (Li C. X. et al., 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Souza et al., 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Sameroff et al., 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) and further detected in Turkish 
 <italic>Hyalomma marginatum</italic> (Dinçer et al., 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) and 
 <italic>Rhipicephalus sanguineus</italic> ticks (Brinkmann et al., 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic>-related tick-borne viruses (e.g., Bole tick virus 4, BLTV4) were primarily associated with 
 <italic>Hyalomma asiaticum</italic> and 
 <italic>Rh. sanguineus</italic> ticks (Shi et al., 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Sameroff et al., 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). This virus presents a genome 1.5 times larger than other 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic> tick-borne viruses and could constitute, with other related flaviviruses that present large genomes, at least a new genus among the 
 <italic>Flaviviridae</italic> family. In complement to known rhabdoviruses transmitted by ticks (Labuda and Nuttall, 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>) [including several viruses pathogenic for humans (Menghani et al., 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>)], novel single-stranded RNA (ssRNA) negative-strand viruses belonging to the dimarhabdovirus group within the 
 <italic>Rhabdoviridae</italic> family were also identified in 
 <italic>Rhipicephalus</italic> [
 <italic>Rh. microplus</italic> (Li C. X. et al., 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>), 
 <italic>Rh. annulatus</italic> (Li C. X. et al., 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Brinkmann et al., 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>)] ticks [for example, Wuhan tick virus 1 (WhTV-1)]. In addition to these viral families known to contain tick-borne viruses, new viruses identified by HTS and constituting novel viral families recently recognized by the ICTV were reported. It is the case of the 
 <italic>Chuviridae</italic> family, a group of viruses belonging to the 
 <italic>Jingchuvirales</italic> order [class 
 <italic>Monjiviricetes</italic>, phylum 
 <italic>Negarnaviricota</italic>, (Siddell et al., 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>)] and constituted of circular or segmented ssRNA negative-strand viruses primarily associated with 
 <italic>Dermacentor</italic> sp., 
 <italic>Haemaphysalis parva</italic> (Li C. X. et al., 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Brinkmann et al., 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>), and 
 <italic>Rh. sanguineus</italic> (Sameroff et al., 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>) ticks [e.g., Changping tick virus 2 (CpTV2)] or 
 <italic>Rh. microplus</italic> ticks from China, Brazil, and Trinidad and Tobago [Wuhan tick virus 2 (WhTV2)] (Li C. X. et al., 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Souza et al., 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; Sameroff et al., 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>).
</p>
