<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We hypothesized that currently unknown tick-borne arboviruses could silently circulate in specific biotopes where mammals (including humans) are highly exposed to tick bites and used wide range identification techniques to track them in a tick/mammal interface in Thailand. Despite the fact that the description of the virome of ticks is a prerequisite to the evaluation of the risk of spillover, few studies have tried to go further and characterize, among the viral communities infecting ticks, which viruses would more likely be transmissible to vertebrates. Starting from the inventory of viruses infecting tick vectors, the first step in the understanding of the mechanisms of viral emergence is therefore to identify which viruses can cross the species barrier and infect vertebrates, even without any reported clinical signs. Serological techniques are useful tools for getting insights into arbovirus exposure history of new hosts without the limits of genomic tests, which need to collect biological samples in the course of a viremic phase. However, the recognition of the antigen (Ag) by its specific antibodies (Ab) requires good conservation of epitopes conformation, a problem frequently encountered in solid phase Ab/Ag assays (Burbelo et al., 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). In 2010, Burbelo et al. have established a sensitive liquid phase format assay for profiling Ab responses to various antigens (Burbelo et al., 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Luciferase immunoprecipitation system (LIPS) assays use as antigens viral open reading frames (ORFs) fused to the luciferase (Luc) reporter gene expressed in mammalian cells. Fusion proteins are harvested as cell lysates under native conditions and used as antigens. Mixed with serum samples, the resulting immune complexes are then immunoprecipitated using protein A/G-coated beads and revealed by the substrate of the Luc. The measure of Luc activity is an index of the initial Ab titer. Owing to high affinity to the Fc region of their immunoglobulins to staphylococcal A and streptococcal G proteins, LIPS assay can be performed either on human and several animals sera (such as rabbits, dogs, monkeys, cows, mice, etc.) (Burbelo et al., 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), resulting in the possibility to use one single tool to monitor the viral cycle both in its reservoir (frequently animal) and in its spillover (human) host.
</p>
