<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A diminished relative risk of pulmonary morbidity and nosocomial pneumonia was found in patients receiving 60 IU/L α-tocopherol (vitamin E) and 340 mg/L vitamin C through an oro-gastric tube. There was a lower multiple organ failure. Vitamin E and vitamin C administration also decreased the length of ICU stay. However, no significant alterations in isoprostane concentration, white blood cell count, tumor necrosis factor concentration, IL-1 concentration and IL-6 concentration were found, despite a clear tendency for them to be reduced. This supplementation also increased IL-8 concentration [
 <xref rid="B110-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]. Vitamin E is the most important lipophilic antioxidant in the cell membranes and it prevents lipid peroxidation [
 <xref rid="B111-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. Vitamin C regenerates vitamin E increasing its antioxidant effect, avoiding lipid peroxidation and sequestering fat-soluble ROS. In a double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial [
 <xref rid="B112-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>], the authors found a significant decrease in mortality at 28 days and fewer days of mechanical ventilation in patients treated with vitamin C and vitamin E. Another randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study found a significant decrease in days of mechanical ventilation in patients who were treated with vitamin C and vitamin E [
 <xref rid="B113-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. The combined effect of therapy with vitamin E and vitamin C in severe post-operative patients resulted in a decrease in the incidence of ARDS or pneumonia, a decrease in organ failure and a tendency to decrease mortality at 28 days. The most relevant vitamin E function is its antioxidant effect. However, it has other important effects such as stabilizing the cell membrane and maintaining an adequate immune response to infection [
 <xref rid="B114-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. We believe that the combined treatment with vitamin E and C is a very promising option that can further decrease the organic damage caused by oxidative stress and systemic inflammation in the lung which results from COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="B115-medicina-56-00386" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>].
</p>
