<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="alpha-lower">
 <list-item>
  <p>The carrier must be present and be sufficiently numerous.</p>
  <p>There is sufficient evidence that the rodent population density in Belgium is directly related to the percentage of infected carriers in the population and to the number of infected hosts (Heyman et al., 
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">2002b</xref>). Some hantaviruses can also spill-over to other habitat sharing rodent species (
   <italic>M. glareolus</italic> to 
   <italic>Apodemus sylvaticus</italic> in the case of PUUV; Klingström et al., 
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">2002</xref>; Heyman et al., 
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">2009b</xref>). In some cases the secondary carrier species can be heavily infected and – although there is no proof provided – chances are that both primary and secondary carrier species could infect humans (Klingström et al., 
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">2002</xref>; Heyman et al., 
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">2009b</xref>; Schlegel et al., 
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B144">2009</xref>).
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>The host must have access to the habitat of the carrier or vice-versa.</p>
  <p>In order to infect the host, he must remain in the carrier habitat for a sufficiently long period of time and also be involved in activities that put the host in direct contact with the virus particles. Entering and cleaning long abandoned places (cabins, attics, cellars, etc.) or performing work that disturbs carrier nests (renovation, cleaning, etc.) or other activities that put the host in prolonged contact with the carrier’s habitat (camping, sleeping on the ground, military exercises, etc.; Linard et al., 
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B95">2007a</xref>; Tersago et al., 
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B157">2011a</xref>). This rule is also valid for non-human mammals although the involved species usually are predating on the carrier species (Dobly et al., 
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">2012</xref>). The observation that about 85% of the hantavirus cases occur in the forested South of the country, where wood is commonly used for heating and building, may support this.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>The contact between aerosol and host must take place within a limited time frame, i.e., the virus must still be viable. In a minority of the cases direct contact with rodents through handling dead rodents or rodent’s nesting material of live rodents can play a role.</p>
 </list-item>
</list>
