<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack id="S14">
 <title>Acknowledgements</title>
 <p>The authors thank the governments of Ghana, Tanzania, Malawi, Zambia, Uganda, Equatorial Guinea, and São Tomé and Príncipe for facilitating this research. For their invaluable support in planning and implementing the field work, we also thank the Zambian Wildlife Authority; Kasanka Trust; Malawi Ministry of Tourism, Wildlife and Culture, Malawi Ministry of Agriculture, Irrigation and Food Security; Tanzania Ministry of Livestock Development and Fisheries; Tanzanian Wildlife Research Institute; Sokoine University of Agriculture, Tanzania; Makerere University, Uganda; Equatorial Guinea Ministerio de Agricultura y Bosques; Equatorial Guinea Instituto del Desarrollo Forestal y Gestión de las Áreas Protegidas; Universidad Nacional de Guinea Ecuatorial; São Tomé and Príncipe Ministério de Agricultura, Desenvolivimento Rural e Pesca; Ecosystèmes Forestiers d’Afrique Centrale; Associação Monte Pico, São Tomé and Príncipe; Alex Torrance; Lucrecia Bilé Osa Ahara;Iñaki Rodriguez Prieto; Andrés Fernandez Loras; Heidi Ruffler; Ricardo Castro Cesar de Sa; Ricardo Faustino de Lima; and Mariana Carvalho. Additional genetic samples were provided by Javier Juste, Ivan Kuzmin, Guy-Crispin Gembu Tungaluna and Jean-Michel Heraud. We also thank Daniel Horton and David Selden for constructive discussions and technical assistance, respectively. The work was supported by funding from the University of Cambridge, Institute of Zoology, CSIRO Australian Animal Health Laboratory and the UK Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs. The Charles Slater Trust, Zebra Foundation for Veterinary Zoological Education and Isaac Newton Trust provided grants to AJP. DTSH and KSB were funded by the Wellcome Trust. DTSH, ARF and JLNW are funded by the Research and Policy for Infectious Disease Dynamics (RAPIDD) program of the Science and Technology Directorate, Department of Homeland Security, and Fogarty International Center, USA. DTSH has a David H Smith fellowship. CCB is partially funded by National Institutes of Health, USA, grant AI054715. TL was funded by Lincoln Park Zoo, Chicago, US. ARF was supported by the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Defra) project SEV3500. AAC is supported by a Royal Society Wolfson Research Merit award.</p>
</ack>
