<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">Flaviviruses causing hemorrhagic fever or severe encephalitis (Omsk hemorrhagic fever, Dengue and Yellow fever, Russian spring–summer encephalitis/Tick Borne Encephalitis (TBEV)) are listed as potential biological threat agents (NATO AMed P-6 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>]) and handling requires BSL-3/BSL-4 containment. Flaviviruses are arthropod-borne viruses that are endemic worldwide with virus/vector specific geographical distributions, causing regular outbreaks and fatalities, with 30.000 cases/year through yellow fever in Africa alone [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR149">149</xref>]. Infections with flaviviruses can lead to hemorrhagic fevers (Omsk hemorrhagic fever, yellow fever (YF) and dengue fever with case fatality rates of up to 30%) or affect the CNS, causing encephalitis (e.g., Japanese encephalitis, tick borne encephalitis with case fatality rates up to 20%, Zika and West Nile encephalitis). Human-to-human transmission is not effective. Live vaccines against yellow fever (17D) and Japanese Encephalitis (JE), a number of inactivated TBEV vaccines, and most recently a live Dengue virus vaccine are available. Flaviviruses are a large family of mosquito- or tick-transmitted enveloped viruses with a Group IV positive-sense single-strand RNA genome, using G-protein coupled receptors for entry into host cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. 
 <italic>Anti-flavivirus drugs</italic>. Ribavirin is an effective early treatment for yellow fever under compassionate use protocols, but fails to improve survival of dengue infections in non-human primates (NHP; [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>]. Out of a quite large number of drugs investigated for repurposing against flaviviruses by the FDA (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), the most promising candidate is sofosbuvir [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Sofosbuvir was initially developed and approved by FDA for treatment of hepatitis C. It shows activity against a number of flaviviruses in vitro and in the mouse model [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref>]. Further interesting candidates (13 compounds listed in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) inhibit the viral polymerase [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128">128</xref>]), NS2B/NS3 protease and kinases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]), cell entry and membrane trafficking [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">109</xref>], and other flavivirus targets. The action and the efficacy of most of these compounds in vivo are yet to be determined. The major shortcoming of all candidates so far tested in animal models for the treatment of infections with Usutu (UsutuV), Dengue (DENV) and Zika viruses (ZikaV) is their rather low efficacy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>].
</p>
