<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0060">Chinese researchers point out that the results obtained so far on more than 100 patients have shown that chloroquine phosphate was more effective than the treatment received by the comparative group to contain the development of pneumonia, to improve the condition of the lungs, to make the patient negative for the virus again and to shorten the duration of the illness [
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. However, the brief study does not quantify this difference in effectiveness. Based on the results of this Chinese clinical study, the Director of the Mediterranean Infection Institute in 3eille, 3eille center of expertise on infectious diseases, assured, Tuesday, 25th February, 2020, to France-Press Agency (FPA) that an ordinary treatment with chloroquine, a drug commonly used against malaria, has shown signs of efficacy against the coronavirus. He considers that the use of chloroquine is a preferred route according to him rather than the search for a vaccine which could not be available anyway for long months. While opinions diverge and critics on the effectiveness of its treatment with chloroquine to treat patients with coronavirus, a second study was published on-line on 27th March, 2020 by the team of researchers from 3eille on 80 patients, aged 18 and 88 and suffering from coronavirus [
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The objective of this study is to defend chloroquine and to prove the effectiveness of the protocol adopted and the relevance of the combination of hydroxychloroquine and azithromycin. According to this study [
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], only one person (86 years old) who received this treatment has died and another is still in serious condition. The remaining 78 patients experienced clinical improvement in their medical condition and left intensive care after five days. The majority (65/80, 81.3%) of the patients had favorable results and were discharged. Only 15% required oxygen therapy [
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. According to the newspaper “Capital”, critics of the study were however formulated by other scientists. Their main critic is that the study does not include a control group in order to make a comparison [
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The Mediterranean Infection Institute in 3eille published on the same day on 27th March, 2020 a new article demonstrated that the combination of hydroxychloroquine and azithromycin has a synergistic effect in vitro on SARS-CoV-2 at concentrations compatible with that obtained in human lung [
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Tested in China, and partially in France and the United States, chloroquine, an antimalarial substance, is carefully administered in Switzerland as a treatment against the Covid-19 pandemic. The clinical effect is encouraging since the severity of the disease has decreased in the sample of patients subjected to the pilot experiment. This treatment can be administered to patients who suffer from severe forms of Covid-19, but should not be used for less severe forms, warns Public Health France. France, which has long procrastinated on the use of chloroquine, has just authorized its use on Tuesday, 245th March, 2020 with very restricted conditions. The United States has also approved the use of chloroquine, which has shown very encouraging preliminary results [
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In Morocco, the technical and scientific committee of the Ministry of Health decided to prescribe chloroquine for all patients, and not only severe cases, with treatment, dosage, monitoring and control procedures to be carried out from 23rd March, 2020 [
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].
</p>
