<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0040">
 <italic>Tropheryma whipplei</italic> is the agent of Whipple disease, a chronic disease mainly observed in white men about 50 years old. The disease was first described in 1907, but the bacterium was cultured only in 2000 
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. The high prevalence of asymptomatic carriage of 
 <italic>T. whipplei</italic> in feces and saliva was reported in 2008 in Senegal 
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref> and in 2016 in Ghana 
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. 
 <italic>T. whipplei</italic> was also detected in the blood of febrile Senegalese patients without malaria, with a prevalence of 6.4% (
 <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) 
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. No correlation was reported between the presence of 
 <italic>T. whipplei</italic> in stool and saliva and bacteraemia, but the presence of one significant clinical sign, cough, was observed. 
 <italic>T. whipplei</italic> was also found in important quantities in bronchoalveolar lavage samples in Malawi 
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. In the Sine-Saloum area in Senegal in August 2010, 
 <italic>T. whipplei</italic> was the main detected cause of fever (58.5% in febrile patients in the village of Dielmo and 69% in Ndiop) 
 <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. Most of the cases were grouped in the same households. In addition, the same new 
 <italic>T. whipplei</italic> genotype was detected among patients. Overall, the data show that 
 <italic>T. whipplei</italic> is a cause of epidemic acute fever in Senegal. The examples of 
 <italic>R. felis</italic> and 
 <italic>T. whipplei</italic> support the notion that malaria in people with undifferentiated fever has long been overdiagnosed. They also show that diagnostic tests are essential to improve care, and that targeted surveys have a role to play in providing insight into the causes of the fever in order to suggest the tests to be performed.
</p>
