<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0045">Plague has a remarkable place in history. 
 <italic>Yersinia pestis</italic> has been involved in several pandemics. It is present as a permanent focus in many countries in Africa and is still involved in epidemics (
 <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) 
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. Among recent examples, an epidemic of bubonic plague emerged in Oran (Algeria) in June 2003 
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. The last human cases of plague had occurred in this city in 1946 and in this country in 1950. More recently, in the central highlands of Madagascar, a man visiting Ankazobe district was bitten by a flea in August 2017 
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Within a week, he developed malaria-like symptoms. While travelling to the eastern coast, he took a public taxi to reach the capital, where he died. A week later, an epidemic was officially confirmed. The infection of more than 2348 confirmed, probable and suspected cases was reported in November 2017. Although the disease can be treated with antibiotics if detected early, it is worth noting that more than 200 people have died 
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Overall, the fact that there was a plague outbreak in Madagascar is not astonishing. Indeed, there is an ongoing epizootic that leads to an annual emergence of human infections 
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. This emergence is attributed to seasonal ecologic conditions that cause a decrease in rat populations and then lead fleas to feed directly on humans. The surprising features of this 2017 epidemic are that it appeared earlier than normal; it was predominantly a pneumonic form; and it hit the capital 
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. It is not just bad luck that this plague outbreak emerged in a country with an extremely fragile health system 
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Indeed, poor access to healthcare, the lack of rapid diagnostic tests in many health facilities, the missing link between communities and the frontline health system and national health authorities as well as weakness of supply chains and infrastructure throughout the country are all factors that favour the spread of the bacterium, resulting in a high mortality rate from a treatable disease 
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>.
</p>
