<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28">Unlike the situation for M2 inhibitors, cell culture-based assays have not been validated for detecting phenotypic resistance in clinical isolates, partly because of the differences in cellular receptor specificity between human respiratory epithelium and available cell culture types (reviewed in [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]). In addition, these types of assays are labor intense and require an additional virus titration step, which make these assays unfavorable for high-throughput surveillance. Humanized Madin-Darby canine kidney (MDCK) cell lines that stably overexpress human 2,6-sialyltransferase (SIAT1) to increase alpha 2,6-linked sialic acids may overcome this first limitation. However, these cells have not been widely utilized to date [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>]. Other challenges are the broad variation in morphology of influenza plaques between different influenza types and subtypes and the reduced sensitivity of yield reduction assays. The NA enzyme inhibition phenotypic assays have, therefore, been the preferred assay to screen for clinically relevant NA inhibitor resistance mutations in influenza antiviral resistance surveillance [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>]. Both fluorometric (MUNANA) and chemiluminescent (NA-star) type of phenotypic assays are available. Both assays have the same limitations, such as the necessity of a virus propagation step, and may therefore not reliably detect resistant subpopulations and do not detect HA-mediated NA inhibitor resistance [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>]. To standardize interpretation and reporting of NA inhibitor susceptibility of influenza viruses, clear definitions were formulated in 2012 using 50 % inhibitory concentration (IC
 <sub>50</sub>; the concentration of drug required to inhibit a standardized amount of NA activity by 50 %) fold-change thresholds, compared to the median for viruses from the same type/subtype/lineage showing “normal inhibition” [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">106</xref>].
</p>
