<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A range of small molecule biomarkers in the blood has recently been identified for the COVID-19 detection from patients all around the globe. While many of these biomarkers are not as specific as detecting the viral RNA or DNA directly from the blood or by using RT-PCR, their concentration in the blood is found to be useful for the prognostics of the COVID-19 disease. This is due to the fact that many protein-based molecules in the blood, which eventually serve as the biomarkers of a disease, increase or decrease their levels in order to fight against the infection. Therefore, some of these biomarkers are directly linked to the severity of the infection. Particularly, serum urea, (CREA), C (CysC) serum direct bilirubin (DBIL), (CHE), and lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) concentrations were found to be significantly higher in severe COVID-19 patients than those in mild COVID-19 patients.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref66">66</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref68">68</xref>
 </sup> More recently, smell dysfunction has been proposed as a biomarker for the COVID-19 disease.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref69">69</xref>
 </sup> The mucous secretions from the nose contain many protein molecules that help metabolize xenobiotics and support epithelial integrity required for smell function. Therefore, developing biosensors for the detection of mucous proteins may also be useful for the early detection of the SARS-CoV2 infection. However, it should be noted that these biomarkers may not be specific to COVID-19 as nasal dysfunction is reported in other diseases such as the Parkinson’s disorder.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref70">70</xref>
 </sup> More qualitative and quantitative information regarding the trend of biomarkers for COVID-19 is summarized in 
 <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">Table 
  <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">2</xref>
 </xref>. This certainly provides first-hand information for the designer of a biosensor to develop strategy for selecting either one or multiple candidates to develop test platforms for precise and accurate detection of the COVID-19 disease.
</p>
