<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="discussion"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Lancet Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Lancet Public Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Lancet. Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2468-2667</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2468-2667(20)30058-X</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2468-2667(20)30058-X</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Prisons and custodial settings are part of a comprehensive response to COVID-19</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au10"><name><surname>Kinner</surname><given-names>Stuart A</given-names></name><email>s.kinner@unimelb.edu.au</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au20"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>Jesse T</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">g</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au30"><name><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>Kathryn</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">h</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au40"><name><surname>Southalan</surname><given-names>Louise</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au50"><name><surname>Lopez-Acu&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref rid="aff9" ref-type="aff">i</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au60"><name><surname>Ferreira-Borges</surname><given-names>Carina</given-names></name><xref rid="aff10" ref-type="aff">j</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au70"><name><surname>O'Moore</surname><given-names>&#x000c9;amonn</given-names></name><xref rid="aff11" ref-type="aff">k</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Centre for Adolescent Health, University of Melbourne, Melbourne, VIC 3052, Australia</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Justice Health Unit, Melbourne School of Population and Global Health, University of Melbourne, Melbourne, VIC 3010, Australia</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>School of Public and Population Health, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, BC, Canada</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Mater Research Institute-UQ, University of Queensland, Brisbane, QLD, Australia</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Griffith Criminology Institute, Griffith University, Brisbane, QLD, Australia</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>School of Population and Global Health, The University of Western Australia, Perth, WA, Australia</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>g</label>National Drug Research Institute, Curtin University, Perth, WA, Australia</aff><aff id="aff8"><label>h</label>Centre for International Child Health, University of Melbourne, Melbourne, VIC, Australia</aff><aff id="aff9"><label>i</label>Andalusian School of Public Health, University of Granada, Granada, Spain</aff><aff id="aff10"><label>j</label>Division of Noncommunicable Diseases and Promoting Health through the Life-course WHO European Office for Prevention and Control of Noncommunicable Diseases (NCD Office) Moscow, Russian Federation</aff><aff id="aff11"><label>k</label>National Health &#x00026; Justice Team, Public Health England, Wellington House, London, United Kingdom</aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e188</fpage><lpage>e189</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd. This is an Open Access article under the CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 license</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p id="para110">Prisons are epicentres for infectious diseases because of the higher background prevalence of infection, the higher levels of risk factors for infection, the unavoidable close contact in often overcrowded, poorly ventilated, and unsanitary facilities, and the poor access to health-care services relative to that in community settings.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Infections can be transmitted between prisoners, staff and visitors, between prisons through transfers and staff cross-deployment, and to and from the community. As such, prisons and other custodial settings are an integral part of the public health response to coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19).</p><p id="para120">One of the first documented influenza outbreaks in prison occurred in San Quentin prison in California, USA, during the 1918 influenza pandemic. In three separate instances, infection was introduced by a newly received prisoner, and a single transfer to another prison resulted in an outbreak there. Isolation was central to containment.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> More recently, prison influenza outbreaks have been described in the USA, Canada, Australia, Taiwan, and Thailand.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> We are unaware of any published reports of influenza outbreaks in youth detention or immigration detention centres, although modelling suggests that outbreaks would progress similarly in these settings.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Since early 2020, COVID-19 outbreaks have been documented worldwide, including Iran, where 70&#x02008;000 prisoners have been released in an effort to reduce in-custody transmission.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>
</p><p id="para130">Prisons concentrate individuals who are susceptible to infection and those with a higher risk of complications. COVID-19 has an increased mortality in older people and in those with chronic diseases or immunosuppression. Notably, multimorbidity is normative among people in prison, often with earlier onset and greater severity than in the general population, and prison populations are ageing in many countries.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Furthermore, inadequate investment in prison health, substantial overcrowding in some prison settings, and rigid security processess have the potential to delay diagnosis and treatment.</p><p id="para140">As such, COVID-19 outbreaks in custodial settings are of importance for public health, for at least two reasons: first, that explosive outbreaks in these settings have the potential to overwhelm prison health-care services and place additional demands on overburdened specialist facilities in the community; and second, that, with an estimated 30 million people released from custody each year globally, prisons are a vector for community transmission that will disproportionately impact marginalised communities.</p><p id="para150">What must be done to mitigate the impact of large outbreaks of COVID-19 in prisons? The public health importance of prison responses to influenza outbreaks has been recognised in the USA,<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> where the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention have developed a checklist for pandemic influenza preparedness in correctional settings. WHO has also issued prison-specific guidance for responding to COVID-19 (<xref rid="box1" ref-type="boxed-text">panel</xref>
).<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>
<boxed-text id="box1"><label>Panel</label><caption><title>Prison-specific guidance for responding to COVID-19</title></caption><p id="para10">
<bold>Joint planning</bold>
</p><p id="para20">Include prison health and correctional authorities in the overall public health response, rather than permitting them to plan and operate in isolation.</p><p id="para30">
<bold>Risk management</bold>
</p><p id="para40">Design and implement adequate systems for limiting importation and exportation of cases from or to the community, and transmission and spread within prisons.</p><p id="para50">
<bold>Prevention and control</bold>
</p><p id="para60">Develop protocols for entry screening, personal protection measures, social distancing, environmental cleaning and disinfection, and restriction of movement, including limitation of transfers and access for non-essential staff and visitors.</p><p id="para70">
<bold>Treatment</bold>
</p><p id="para80">Explicitly and transparently align prison health systems with the wider health and emergency planning systems, including transfer protocols for patients requiring specialised care. Isolate cases and contacts if required to control the spread of infection in prisons. However, special consideration of the potentially serious mental health effects of isolation in these settings is essential.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> In high-income countries, maintaining isolation without depriving incarcerated people of human contact might be possible.<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref>
</p><p id="para90">
<bold>Information sharing</bold>
</p><p id="para100">Close collaboration between health and justice ministries should be established to ensure continuity of information, which is a crucial component of an effective, coordinated, whole-of-government response. Governance of prison health by a ministry of health, rather than a ministry of justice or similar, is likely to facilitate timely information sharing.<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref>
</p></boxed-text></p><p id="para160">Prison health is public health by definition. Despite this and the very porous borders between prisons and communities, prisons are often excluded or treated as separate from public health efforts. The fast spread of COVID-19 will, like most epidemics, disproportionately affect the most disadvantaged people. Therefore, to mitigate the effects of prison outbreaks on tertiary health-care facilities and reduce morbidity and mortality among society's most marginalised, it is crucial that prisons, youth detention centres, and immigration detention centres are embedded within the broader public health response.</p></body><back><ref-list id="bibl10"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirtz</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Moazen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global burden of HIV, viral hepatitis, and tuberculosis in prisoners and detainees</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>388</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>1089</fpage><lpage>1102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27427453</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influenza at San Quentin Prison, California</article-title><source>Public Health Rep</source><volume>34</volume><year>1919</year><fpage>996</fpage><lpage>1008</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Besney</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influenza outbreak in a Canadian correctional facility</article-title><source>J Infect Prev</source><volume>18</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28989527</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>W-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C-L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Control of an H1N1 outbreak in a correctional facility in central Taiwan</article-title><source>J Microbiol Immunol Infect</source><volume>50</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26051221</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finnie</surname><given-names>TJR</given-names></name><name><surname>Copley</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Leach</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An analysis of influenza outbreaks in institutions and enclosed societies</article-title><source>Epidemiol Infect</source><volume>142</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23570654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref60"><article-title>UN urges Iran to free political prisoners amid coronavirus spread. Al Jazeera</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2020/03/urges-iran-free-political-prisoners-coronavirus-spread-200310184750920.html" id="interrefs10">https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2020/03/urges-iran-free-political-prisoners-coronavirus-spread-200310184750920.html</ext-link><year>March 10, 2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref70"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kinner</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding and improving the health of people who experience incarceration: An overview and synthesis</article-title><source>Epidemiol Rev</source><volume>40</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29860342</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref80"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maruschak</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabol</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pandemic influenza and jail facilities and populations</article-title><source>Am J Public Health</source><volume>99</volume><issue>suppl 2</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>S339</fpage><lpage>S344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19797746</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref90"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>WHO</collab></person-group><source>Preparedness, prevention and control of COVID-19 in prisons and places of detention</source><year>2020</year><publisher-name>World Health Organization Regional Office for Europe</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Copenhagen</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The psychological impact of quarantine and how to reduce it: rapid review of the evidence</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2020</year><comment>published online Feb 26.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30460-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wildeman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solitary confinement placement and post-release mortality risk among formerly incarcerated individuals: a population-based study</article-title><source>Lancet Public Health</source><volume>5</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>e107</fpage><lpage>e113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32032555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guthrie</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lokuge</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influenza control can be achieved in a custodial setting: pandemic (H1N1) 2009 and 2011 in an Australian prison</article-title><source>Public Health</source><volume>126</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>1032</fpage><lpage>1037</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23083842</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McLeod</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global prison healthcare governance and health equity: a critical lack of evidence</article-title><source>Am J Public Health</source><volume>110</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31944844</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack><p>We declare no competing interests. The authors are responsible for the views expressed in this publication and they do not necessarily represent the decisions or the stated policy of WHO.</p></ack></back></article>