<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
 <label>Figure 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Infectivity of the H3N2, H5N1, and H7N9 influenza A viruses in human immune cells. 
   <bold>(A)</bold> Human monocyte-derived macrophages (Mɸs) were infected with different doses of a seasonal influenza virus A/Beijing/353/89 (H3N2) or human isolates of avian influenza viruses A/Vietnam/1194/2004 (H5N1) or A/Anhui/1/2013 (H7N9) 
   <bold>(A)</bold> for 6 h in the presence of oseltamivir carboxylate to prevent the spread of viruses, or 
   <bold>(B)</bold> for 24 h in the absence of oseltamivir carboxylate. Infected Mɸs were detected with virus protein-specific antibodies by immunofluorescence microscopy. Results represent the mean values of three 
   <bold>(A)</bold> or four 
   <bold>(B)</bold> donors. From each donor at least 200 cells (average ca. 330) 
   <bold>(A)</bold> or 300 cells (average ca. 840) 
   <bold>(B)</bold> were counted. Human dendritic cells [monocyte-derived DCs (moDCs)] were infected with different virus doses 
   <bold>(C)</bold> for 6 h in the presence of oseltamivir carboxylate, or 
   <bold>(D)</bold> for 24 h in the absence of oseltamivir carboxylate. The proportion of infected moDCs was determined after staining the cells with antibodies against respective viral proteins for flow cytometry. From each donor, 10,000 events were analyzed. The mock sample (uninfected cells) was used to separate the uninfected and infected cells. Results are the mean values of four donors 
   <bold>(C,D)</bold> analyzed separately. The infective particles per ml (FFU/ml) were calculated for Mɸs and moDCs separately, and multiplicity of infection (MOI) values was determined afterward. The MOI values in each experiment were calculated based on FFU/ml values determined in panels 
   <bold>(A,C)</bold>. 
   <bold>(E)</bold> Representative images of Mɸs infected with H3N2, H5N1, or H7N9 viruses at MOI 10 or 0.5 stained with virus-specific antibodies and secondary fluorescein isothiocyanate-labeled antibodies.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="fimmu-09-01664-g001" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
