<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16"> An exanthem is a widespread erythematous rash that is accompanied by systemic symptoms such as fever, headache, and malaise. In children, exanthems are usually associated with infections, and viral infections are the most common. Determining the cause of an exanthem is based on the characteristic morphology, distribution and time course of the eruption, and a careful assessment of infectious contacts, immunization status, and aspects of the physical examination. Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows the common skin rash morphologies associated with viral infections, their causative agents, clinical presentation, diagnostic tests needed, treatment and prevention methods, and complications. Although uncommon, serious acute illnesses with skin rash must be identified immediately; for example, a skin rash in a child with meningeal signs is an indicator of life-threatening condition ( meningococcemia) that warrants immediate hospital referral and treatment. Kawasaki disease also is a childhood illness with rash that must be diagnosed and treated early to ensure better prognosis. The classic viral exanthems have been discussed; other important skin rashes related to viral infections and bacterial infections (e.g., scarlet fever), in addition to other noninfectious causes such as drug eruptions, must be considered in the differential diagnosis. New viral-associated exanthems have been identified; papular acrodermatitis of childhood (PAC) is now recognized to be a manifestation of a number of infectious agents, including viruses. The ability to detect parvovirus B19 virus in seronegative patients using PCR has been useful in linking the virus to erythema infectiosum, as well as other viral exanthems. The viral role in another group of exanthematous disease is yet to be fully identified (e.g., Kawasaki disease, pityriasis rosea, and erythema multiforme) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. 
</p>
