<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza epidemics in subtropical Hong Kong are highly diverse and frequent (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi.1007989.g001">Fig 1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1007989.s008">S4</xref>-and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pcbi.1007989.s009">S5</xref> Figs). Nevertheless, 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> estimates across all three types/subtypes are in the range of 1.1 to 2.0, similar to previous estimates in other regions for influenza overall [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007989.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Few studies have estimated 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> for individual influenza types/subtypes, especially for inter-pandemic seasons. Here we estimate that 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> was similar for A(H1N1) and B (range: 1.1–1.8 for both) and was slightly higher for A(H3N2) (range: 1.3–2.0). Estimated simultaneously with 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub>, the infectious period, or generation time, was slightly longer for A(H3N2) and B than A(H1N1); these estimates were very close to those based on viral shedding curves—3.0 vs 3.1 days reported for A(H3N2), 3.1 vs 3.4 days reported for B, and 2.6 vs 2.3 days reported for A(H1N1) [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1007989.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Together, the higher transmissibility of A(H3N2) (i.e., larger 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> and longer infectious period) in part explains its larger seasonal epidemics and resulting lower average population susceptibility (mean: 60.8% for A(H3N2) vs. 66.6% for A(H1N1) and 68.6% for B). Further, these consistent estimates indicate that our strategy using the empirical 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>0</italic>
 </sub> seasonal cycle in the model-inference system is effective in controlling for the elusive influenza seasonality in Hong Kong and allows for estimation of other key epidemiological features. Future studies could apply the same strategy to study the diverse influenza dynamics in other subtropical/tropical regions or other infections with similar challenges.
</p>
