<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0007">Each of the personnel entering the room should be outfitted with PPE, which includes a gown, gloves, face shield, head covering, and either an N95 mask or powered air-purifying respirator.
 <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>22</sup>
 </xref> All published guidelines to date recommend the use of mechanical compression devices in COVID-19 patients
 <xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref> because of their potential to reduce the number of personnel necessary for CPR and limit viral exposure. In the authors’ experience, using a mechanical compression device allows the proceduralist and respiratory therapist to attend to the airway while nursing staff can enable the delivery of resuscitative medications. When mechanical compression devices are not available, additional personnel may be required in the room to assist with manual chest compressions. US Department of Defense guidelines recommend that 2 team members rotate to perform chest compressions on COVID-19 patients when mechanical compression devices are unavailable.
 <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>23</sup>
 </xref> In patients who do not already have this attached, it is the authors’ practice to connect primed intravenous tubing with necessary extensions, from a bag of fluid located outside the room, enabling more remote medication delivery from exterior team members. Depending on the design of the ICU room and the availability of a sufficiently long defibrillator cable, it is possible for the defibrillator to remain outside the room, enabling rhythm monitoring and electrical therapies by the external team. Because survival after ventricular fibrillation decreases by 7% to 10% for each minute that defibrillation is delayed,
 <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> these arrhythmias should be terminated before chest compressions are initiated.
 <xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref> The authors’ group has used the 8-foot therapy cable accompanying the Lifepak 20 defibrillator (Stryker Corporation, Redmond, WA) to terminate arrhythmias remotely without using PPE.
</p>
