<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Broadly protective immunity to influenza could be mediated by a variety of immune responses raised to conserved components of influenza A viruses that circulate in humans (recapitulated in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat.1008583.g002">Fig 2A and 2C</xref>). It is generally accepted that such broad immune responses do not provide sterilizing immunity and cannot prevent infection. However, they can modulate the course of infection by reducing viral titers, disease severity, duration of infection, and onward transmission, as shown by a variety of animal and human studies (See [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] for an illustration of modeling of such data). Plausible mechanisms of broadly protective immunity include antibody responses to the stem of the HA [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], which appears to be more evolutionarily constrained than other parts of the protein, or antibody responses to stable epitopes on the HA head that can persist for decades or reappear [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Further, antibody responses against NA can be broadly protective [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and have been implicated in protection against pandemic viruses [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In addition, it has been long suspected from epidemiological data that T-cell memory responses to conserved proteins of the virus (e.g., nucleoprotein NP, matrix M1 and M2e, and polymerase PB1) may also play an important role in pandemic protection [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. A protective role of T-cell responses is supported by modern immunologic assays in humans [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>] and epidemiological studies reporting how influenza T-cell escape variants can spread in populations [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In addition, non-neutralizing antibody responses to conserved proteins M2 [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] and NP [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008583.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] can contribute to protection.
</p>
