<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A main finding from this study was that sex partners of incarcerated PLHIV represent a sizable at-risk population, composed primarily of women, who may be missed for HIV testing and/or treatment. This finding is consistent with previous research describing the neglected health needs of women with an incarcerated male partner [
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], and of particular relevance in Indonesia, where heterosexual HIV transmission is increasing and women are typically diagnosed only because of a husband’s illness [
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Our sample was comprised entirely of HIV-positive and presumptively cis-gender males, most of whom were sexually active, not receiving treatment with ART, and reported low rates of consistent condom use before incarceration–a time when most were likely already infected with the virus. Nearly half of PLHIV in this sample were diagnosed during the current prison term, yet few had disclosed their HIV status to a sex partner since their diagnosis or indicated that their sex partner had ever received an HIV test. PLHIV in this study identified a total of 469 sex partners in the 6 months before incarceration, including men, women and transgender persons. Although these findings signal an important opportunity to provide partner services, further studies are needed to ascertain the characteristics of partners whom incarcerated PLHIV actually choose to notify, the ability of index patients to provide contact information for their partners, and whether or not PLHIV trust that healthcare providers will maintain strict confidentiality and provide supportive services to their partners. Nevertheless, findings here support the inference that assisted partner services could, in theory, lead to more of these partners being tested, learning their HIV status, accessing treatment in the community, and taking steps to reduce their risk of future exposure.
</p>
