<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Findings here suggest that a substantial proportion of incarcerated PLHIV (72.4%) also may be open to notifying individuals with whom they shared a drug-related exposure before incarceration. This finding has particular significance in Indonesia and other countries where a majority of those in prison are PWID, and drug injection that occurs within prison and after prison release continues to be an important source of new infections [
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. PLHIV in this study were more likely to endorse provider referral to notify drug-injecting partners if they perceived those relationships as close, important, and characterized by frequent interaction. This finding is consistent with previous work suggesting that people are more likely to disclose in close relationships and that disclosure leads to relationship closeness [
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. In this study, few PLHIV with a history of drug injection had disclosed their HIV diagnosis to a drug-injecting partner, perhaps because incarceration made it difficult to contact these partners. Yet, most indicated an interest in disclosing their HIV status to drug-injecting partners in order to allow those partners to receive HIV testing and prevention services. Although few studies have examined partner notification for PWID, a study of outreach-assisted partner notification in the U.S. found that a majority of PWID requested assistance to notify at least one partner [
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Moreover, street-based outreach to partners in that study yielded additional opportunities to provide HIV risk reduction and distribute HIV prevention materials such as condoms and bleach. In Indonesia, a high proportion of PWID practice safe injection [
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. Yet, fewer PWID have accessed opioid agonist treatment or HIV testing, and ART coverage among HIV-positive PWID (27%) also is low [
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. In this context, partner notification could, in principle, supplement existing efforts to achieve more widespread testing of those at risk, the first of the UNAIDS 95-95-95 goals for 2030, and provide earlier treatment to persons already infected [
 <xref rid="pone.0234697.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>].
</p>
