<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Analysis of the magnitude of ZIKV VL in different bodily fluids revealed overall similar VL values in serum/plasma, saliva, and urine specimens, with serum attaining the highest peak VL (8.1 log
 <sub>10</sub> copies/ml), similar to previously reported ZIKV VL levels [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006518.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. ZIKV RNA was detected in all three bodily fluids from the first day of symptom onset, while VL decreased over time. Interestingly, one contact had relatively high serum VL (6.7 log
 <sub>10</sub> copies/ml) two days before symptom onset. This is consistent with the previously estimated incubation period of 3–14 days [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006518.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>], and viremia prior to symptom onset has been reported in blood donors (1–6 days) in Martinique [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006518.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. As for duration, our data revealed detectable viral RNA up to 7 days post-symptom onset in serum/plasma and saliva and up to 22 days in urine. Hence, ZIKV was present the longest in urine, consistent with other publications [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006518.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006518.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006518.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006518.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. While reported duration of ZIKV RNA detection in bodily fluids varies greatly, studies have found detection times up to 29 days post-symptom onset in saliva and urine and up to 14 days in serum [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006518.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006518.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006518.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006518.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0006518.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Given that all captured index cases were symptomatic and that 33 of the 44 rRT-PCR-positive cases were index cases, it is possible that infection rates and viral loads detected differ from studies conducted among asymptomatic cases, such as viremic blood donors.
</p>
