<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para1770">In Australia, hepatocellular carcinoma is the fastest growing incident cancer; it is now in the top 10 causes of total cancer death and the seventh cause of cancer deaths in men.
 <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>71</sup>
 </xref> Between 2011 and 2020, the annual incidence of liver cancer in Australia is projected to increase from 1520 to 2465 cases.
 <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>72</sup>
 </xref> Liver cancer incidence for 1989–90 was also 5–10 times greater in Indigenous than in non-Indigenous Australians, with 12 times higher expected mortality for Indigenous than non-Indigenous people.
 <xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>73</sup>
 </xref> These prevalence estimates seem to have substantially improved on the basis of 2017 data,
 <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>72</sup>
 </xref> in which Indigenous Australians had 2·8 times higher age-standardised incidence and 2·5 times higher mortality than non-Indigenous Australians. Notably, although survival for many cancers has improved over the past two decades in Australia and globally, there has been no improvement in liver cancer prognosis, and hepatocellular carcinoma remains the fastest-growing cause of cancer death in Australia. 5-year survival is just 15% (18% if the cancer is localised and 2% if metastasis occurs).
 <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>72</sup>
 </xref> According to the most recent 2017 estimation,
 <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>72</sup>
 </xref> between 1982 and 2017 the greatest estimated proportional increase in mortality was from liver cancer (from 2·3% to 6·8% per 100 000 individuals).
 <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>72</sup>
 </xref> Currently, more than 1400 Australians die from liver cancer each year and a third of those diagnosed do so within a month of diagnosis.
 <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>72</sup>
 </xref> HBV or HCV is linked to 30% of hepatocellular carcinoma cases in Australia.
</p>
