<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para1810">Similar to Australia, HBV is a major cause of liver disease in New Zealand. In New Zealand, hepatitis B accounted for 35·6% of all deaths due to cirrhosis and other chronic liver diseases, and 31·2% of all deaths due to liver cancer in 2015, according to GHE data (
 <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>).
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> 20·4% and 17·9% of these deaths were due to hepatitis C.
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> Acute hepatitis B and C accounted for 97·1% and 0·009% of all deaths due to acute hepatitis in New Zealand in 2015.
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> The quality of epidemiological data for viral hepatitis from New Zealand is poor compared with that in Australia, probably because viral hepatitis is not a disease for which notification is compulsory in New Zealand. However, in 2012, there were an estimated 50 000 (1·5%) people aged 15 years and older with HCV, and approximately 1000 new cases are identified each year.
 <xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>84</sup>
 </xref> It was estimated that only half of the people in this age group are currently diagnosed and only a quarter are aware that they have the disease.
 <xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>84</sup>
 </xref> Approximately 90 000 individuals are living with chronic HBV infection.
 <xref rid="bib85" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>85</sup>
 </xref> In New Zealand, there was an increase in the incidence of liver cancer, from 145 in 1999 to 253 new registrations in 2009 and high fatality (from 127 to 208 people) in the same period.
 <xref rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>86</sup>
 </xref> There are four main ethnic groups in New Zealand (European, Māori, Pacific Islander, and Asian), with smaller proportions identifying with other ethnic groups. Liver cancer is the fourth most common in incidence and mortality in Māori men. In this group, hepatocellular carcinoma registration and mortality were almost 3·5 times those of non-Māori men in 2010–12,
 <xref rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>87</sup>
 </xref> which has perhaps declined since a study done in 1983–94 that suggested that Māori people had a 7 times higher risk than non-Māori people,
 <xref rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>88</sup>
 </xref> and a further study in 1981–2004 that indicated that risk was 4·79 times higher.
 <xref rid="bib89" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>89</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
