<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para1870">A nationwide study
 <xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>100</sup>
 </xref> that assessed mortality caused by infantile fulminant hepatitis, cirrhosis, and hepatocellular carcinoma (the National Death Certificates Database 1977–2011 was used to calculate mortality) in cohorts of children born before and after the launch of the HBV vaccination campaign in Taiwan in 1984 found that mortality from infant fulminant hepatitis declined significantly for infants born between 1977 and 1980 (5·76 per 100 000 person-years) to 2009–2011 (0·19 per 100 000 person-years). Also, mortality due to cirrhosis and hepatocellular carcinoma in people aged 5–29 years decreased significantly for those born in 1977–80 (0·65 deaths per 100 000 person-years for cirrhosis and 0·81 per 100 000 for carcinoma) to 0·02 deaths per 100 000 person-years for cirrhosis and 0·05 per 100 000 for carcinoma in 2001–04.
 <xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>100</sup>
 </xref> The incidence of HBV infection has decreased markedly, mainly due to the 1984 immunisation campaign.
 <xref rid="bib101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref> The most recent data (from 2016) show that HBsAg positivity in people aged up to 30 years has decreased from more than 11% in 1984 to 0·5% in 2014 (
 <xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">appendix p 5</xref>).
 <xref rid="bib103" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>103</sup>
 </xref> For those older than 30 years, HBsAg positivity was still about 7% in 2016.
 <xref rid="bib103" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>103</sup>
 </xref> Despite active control programmes, the decline of the hepatitis B burden was slow, as shown in a population-based survey with longitudinal follow-up.
 <xref rid="bib104" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>104</sup>
 </xref> An outreach community-based screening in 164 302 adults in Taiwan from 1996 to 2005 estimated that the total number of HBsAg carriers was about 3 million, indicating the carrier loads of hepatitis B had remained substantial.
 <xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>105</sup>
 </xref> Since the 1984 immunisation campaign, the incidences of hepatocellular carcinoma,
 <xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref> cirrhosis,
 <xref rid="bib100" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>100</sup>
 </xref> acute hepatitis B,
 <xref rid="bib107" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>107</sup>
 </xref> and childhood fulminant hepatitis
 <xref rid="bib108" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>108</sup>
 </xref> have decreased.
</p>
