<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para1610">HBV and HCV are major contributors to the liver disease burden in Indonesia, similar to China and India. According to the GHE 2015 dataset, hepatitis B infection in Indonesia accounted for 37·0% of all deaths due to cirrhosis and other chronic liver diseases and for 29·1% of all deaths due to liver cancer, whereas these proportions were 35·8% and 35·2% for hepatitis C (
 <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>).
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> Acute hepatitis B and C infection accounted for 78·1% and 3·1% of all deaths due to acute hepatitis in Indonesia in 2015.
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>1</sup>
 </xref> Information about the prevalence of HBV and HCV in the general Indonesian population is unavailable because of inadequate disease surveillance and probable under-reporting, geographical barriers for collecting data on 250 million people living on more than 17 000 islands, and few testing facilities. The prevalence of HBsAg ranged from 4% to 20·3% in 1990–97,
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>31</sup>
 </xref> making Indonesia a country with intermediate-to-high endemicity of hepatitis B. HBsAg prevalence during that period ranged between 37% and 76% in patients with liver cirrhosis and was 37–68% in patients with hepatocellular carcinoma.
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>31</sup>
 </xref> Efforts to collect national-level data were made in 2007 through Indonesia's Basic Health Research survey (known as RISKESDAS) in 21 of 33 provinces. The prevalence of HBsAg in 2007 was 9·4%, that of anti-HBc was 32·8%, and of anti-HBs was 30·6%.
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> A nationwide study in 2015 covering 33 provinces showed that the prevalence of HBsAg was 7·1%, that of anti-HBc was 31·9%, and of anti-HBs was 35·6%.
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>34</sup>
 </xref> These data showed a decline in the prevalence of HBsAg (9·4% in 2007 to 7·1% in 2013), suggesting that Indonesia has moved from high endemicity to moderate endemicity of hepatitis B (
 <xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">appendix p 1</xref>).
</p>
