<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13">The human-to-human transmission of SARS-CoV-2 is primarily mediated by respiratory droplets or aerosols generated during coughing and sneezing. In the early phase of the infection, SARS-CoV-2 entry by inhalation is facilitated by the high expression of ACE2 in the mouth and on the tongue
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>. In the nasal mucosa, secretory goblet cells express high levels of ACE2 and TMPRSS2, suggesting a potential tropism of SARS-CoV-2 for these cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>. Virus replication can also occur in the throat
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. SARS-CoV-2 generally has an 
 <xref rid="Glos3" ref-type="list">incubation period</xref> of 5 to 6 days
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. Once symptoms appear, peak viraemia occurs within 2–5 days of symptom onset
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. For about 80% of infected patients, COVID-19 is a mild disease that is mostly restricted to the upper and conducting airways. These individuals normally exhibit modest symptoms, similar to the common flu, including fever and a dry cough, which resolve spontaneously within 6–10 days. However, in almost 20% of patients viral infection progresses down the trachea to the lungs
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. Within the alveoli, the epithelial cells lining the lower airways are the main viral targets
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>, owing to their substantial expression of ACE2 and TMPRSS2. SARS-CoV-2 infection induces these epithelial cells to undergo apoptotic cell death as part of the viral replication cycle. This apoptotic response is associated with vascular leakage within alveoli that induces a first wave of local inflammation and recruits immune cells from the blood into the lungs to eliminate extra-cellular virus and destroy virus-infected cells
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>. The increase in pro-inflammatory cytokines within the lung leads to the recruitment of leukocytes, further propagating the local inflammatory response that underlies the pathology of atypical interstitial bilateral pneumonia observed in patients with COVID-19. Histology studies have revealed that the central part of the lung is the most affected region, with pneumocyte injury and diffuse alveolar damage, oedema and alveolar haemorrhage, and the presence of interstitial inflammatory infiltrates
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. During this inflammatory phase in the lungs, the disease can rapidly progress to severe illness characterized by acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), a hyperinflammatory state and multiorgan dysfunction with a fatality rate of nearly 10% among the most severe cases
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>. In this setting, lung-protective mechanical ventilation is the most effective strategy to reduce multiorgan failure and mortality
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
