<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Multi‐compartment models have been the workhorse for modelling infectious diseases since the early 20th century. They are a class of mathematical models used for describing the evolution of masses (in unit of proportions or counts) among the compartments of a varying system, with broad use cases in epidemiology, physics, engineering and information science. This is a dynamic system that is typically represented by a system of ordinary differential equations (ODEs) with respect to time, and, given a starting condition, the mass in each of the components is regulated by a function over time. An ODE is a simple mathematical model to depict a trajectory of a functional trend. One of such examples used extensively in epidemiology is an exponential growth function, 
 <italic>f</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>)=
 <italic>e</italic>
 <sup>
  <italic>t</italic>
 </sup>, which may be viewed as a solution to an ODE of the form: 
 <math id="nlm-math-1">
  <mfrac>
   <mrow>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>f</mi>
    <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
    <mi>t</mi>
    <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
   </mrow>
   <mrow>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
   </mrow>
  </mfrac>
  <mo>=</mo>
  <mi>f</mi>
  <mo stretchy="false">(</mo>
  <mi>t</mi>
  <mo stretchy="false">)</mo>
 </math>, or 
 <math id="nlm-math-2">
  <mfrac>
   <mrow>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>y</mi>
   </mrow>
   <mrow>
    <mi>d</mi>
    <mi>t</mi>
   </mrow>
  </mfrac>
  <mo>=</mo>
  <mi>y</mi>
 </math>, where 
 <italic>y</italic> is a function of time 
 <italic>t</italic>, which obviously is 
 <italic>y</italic>=
 <italic>f</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>)=
 <italic>e</italic>
 <sup>
  <italic>t</italic>
 </sup> with an initial condition 
 <italic>f</italic>(0)=1. It is worth pointing out that this simple ODE explicitly characterises the rate of change (speed or velocity) for function 
 <italic>y</italic>=
 <italic>f</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>), rather than directly specifying a form for the function 
 <italic>f</italic>(
 <italic>t</italic>) itself. Such rate‐based characterisation is termed as ‘dynamics’ in the mathematical literature. Clearly, this ODE is not a statistical model as it does not provide a law of data generation; in other words, there is no randomness in this ODE to reflect sampling uncertainties. A typical multi‐compartment model consists of several ODEs for a vector of rates that are linked each other. This is referred to as 
 <italic>a dynamic system</italic>. The forms of ODEs are specified according to relevant scientific knowledge about the understanding of the underlying dynamic mechanism related to an infectious disease.
</p>
