<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the context of infectious disease modelling, the SIR model is the most basic three‐compartment dynamic system that describes an epidemiological mechanism of disease evolution over time (see Figure 
 <xref rid="insr12402-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). In brief, the model describes the flow of infection states or conditions by (i) moving susceptible individuals to the infectious compartment through a transmission process (the first arrow) and (ii) moving infectious individuals to the removed compartment (either dead or recovered) through a removal process (the second arrow). At a given time, the total population 
 <italic>N</italic> under a study is partitioned into the three compartments, denoted by 
 <italic>S</italic>, 
 <italic>I</italic> and 
 <italic>R</italic>, and their sizes satisfying 
 <italic>S</italic>+
 <italic>I</italic>+
 <italic>R</italic>=
 <italic>N</italic>. With a slight abuse of notation, this notation denotes either the type of compartment or the size of compartment, whichever is applicable in a given context. In other words, 
 <italic>S</italic>, 
 <italic>I</italic> and 
 <italic>R</italic> are used to denote the sizes of the mutually exclusive subpopulations of susceptible, infectious and removed individuals, respectively. This compositional constraint, that is, 
 <italic>S</italic>+
 <italic>I</italic>+
 <italic>R</italic>=
 <italic>N</italic>, may be interpreted in a term of probability (or proportion) as follows: at a given time, an individual in the population is either at risk (susceptible), or under infection by a virus (infectious), or removed from the infectious system due to recovery or death; that is, 
 <italic>θ</italic>
 <sup>
  <italic>S</italic>
 </sup>+
 <italic>θ</italic>
 <sup>
  <italic>I</italic>
 </sup>+
 <italic>θ</italic>
 <sup>
  <italic>R</italic>
 </sup>=1, where 
 <italic>θ</italic>
 <sup>
  <italic>S</italic>
 </sup>, 
 <italic>θ</italic>
 <sup>
  <italic>I</italic>
 </sup> and 
 <italic>θ</italic>
 <sup>
  <italic>R</italic>
 </sup> are, respectively, the probabilities of being susceptible, infectious and removed. This presents the primary constraint for a multi‐compartment infectious disease model. More details of the SIR model will be described in Section 
 <xref rid="insr12402-sec-0005" ref-type="sec">2</xref>.
</p>
