<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P16">Viruses used in this study included ZIKV (PRVABC59; GenBank: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KU501215" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">KU501215</ext-link>), DENV-2 (125270/VENE93; GenBank: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="U91870" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">U91870</ext-link>), and CHIKV (R99659; GenBank: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="KX713902" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">KX713902</ext-link>). C6/36 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> cells were used to amplify ZIKV (final passage history= Vero-3, C6/36–1) and DENV-2 (C6/36–3), CHIKV (Vero-2) were grown in Vero E6 cells, and BHK-21 (clone 15) cells were used to titrate infectious bloodmeals. Cell cultures were maintained in Minimal Essential Medium (MEM) with 10% fetal bovine serum, 100 U/ ml penicillin, 100 mg/ ml streptomycin, L-glutamine, 25 mg/ml amphotericin B, and sodium bicarbonate at 28°C for C6/36 cells or 37° C for Vero and BHK-21 cells with 5% CO
 <sub>2</sub>. C6/36 and BHK-21 cells were confirmed to be clear of mycoplasma. Colonies of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> (Orlando strain, collected from Orlando, FL in 1952 and Poza Rica strain, collected from Poza Rica Mexico in 2016) and 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> (Stratford strain, generation F
 <sub>5,</sub> collected in Stratford, CT, 2015) were maintained on defibrinated sheep’s blood and reared under standard laboratory conditions
 <sup>
  <xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>
 </sup>. Adult mosquitoes were housed at 27°C in environmental chambers with a 14:10 light: dark cycle. Litters of suckling mice (mixed sex) from pregnant CD-1 mice were obtained from Charles River Laboratories (Wilmington, MA). Statistical methods were not used to predetermine sample sizes. Litters of sucking mice were randomly assigned to cohorts of mosquitoes and individual suckling mice were randomly assigned to individual mosquitoes within the respective cohorts for the transmission studies. Similar to the mosquito samples, the right front leg of euthanized mice exposed to CHIKV infected mosquitoes were collected by one group and provided to a second group for processing and data analysis. Group 2 was unaware of the order in which samples were given to them. Only after processing and data analysis were completed for each experimental replicate were the treatments made aware to the sample order. Procedures for handling and care of animals were approved by and performed under the Animal Care and Use Committee at The Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station (Protocol # P28–17).
</p>
