<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several phages have been developed as antigen adjuvant for influenza vaccine development. A previous study incorporated influenza conserved nucleoprotein (NP) into bacteriophage P22 through genetic engineering and immunized mice were able to generate anti‐NP antibodies and CD8+ T‐cell responses specific to NP. The vaccine candidate protected mice against both H1N1 and H3N2 influenza strains that were administered via intranasal challenge.
 <xref rid="irv12697-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">57</xref> Two previous studies, which displayed M2e peptide on T7 and f88 phages, demonstrated that the vaccine candidate elicited protective immune responses after three subcutaneous (SC) immunizations, where a high survival rate was observed after lethal challenge with H1N1 and H2N3 virus.
 <xref rid="irv12697-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">58</xref>, 
 <xref rid="irv12697-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">59</xref> Cross‐linking of M2e peptide to the T7 phage VLPs is essential in promoting this protective response, as M2e peptides that were simply mixed with T7 VLPs did not elicit protection against disease.
 <xref rid="irv12697-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">58</xref> Another study, which genetically fused M2e to bacteriophage Qβ coat protein VLPs, induced a high level of M2e‐specific IgG and IgA antibodies in mice and completely protected the mice against a lethal challenge with the influenza virus PR8.
 <xref rid="irv12697-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">60</xref> An example of bacteriophage VLPs that have been used in human clinical trial is the gH1‐Qbeta vaccine against A/California/07/2009 (H1N1) which employs the use of RNA bacteriophage Qbeta. It was reported to induce higher antibody production compared to the same vaccine that was adjuvanted with alhydrogel, and comparable immunogenicity and safety profile to commercial vaccines.
 <xref rid="irv12697-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">61</xref> However, an important consideration in the design of these vaccines in the future is the possibility of developing anti‐phage antibodies in immunized individuals, hence impacting their overall balance of gut microbiota and health.
 <xref rid="irv12697-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">62</xref>, 
 <xref rid="irv12697-bib-0063" ref-type="ref">63</xref>
</p>
