<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">Currently, norovirus (NoV) is associated with one-fifth of all acute gastroenteritis (AGE) cases worldwide. The NoV GII.17_2014 variant has been associated with gastroenteritis outbreaks in several Asian countries, replacing the previously dominant Sydney 2012 variant. There is limited data about circulation of this new strain in Brazil. This study aimed to describe the phylogenetic and evolutionary characteristics of the GII.17_2014 strains in the Northern region of Brazil.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p id="Par2">NoV was detected by enzyme immunoassay (EIA) in 645 stool samples of AGE cases that were reported in Pará and Amazonas states during 2015–2016. All positive samples were tested for NoV GI and GII by reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) and the amplicons were subjected to genome sequencing. The GII.17-positive samples were retested by PCR using different sets of designed primers, which target a highly conserved capsid gene region. Next, the amplicons were sequenced and phylogenetically analyzed using Bayesian inferences.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p id="Par3">Of the 645 samples tested, 208 (32.2%) tested were positive for NoV by EIA, among which 95 (45.7%) were genotyped. Among the genotyped samples, 12 (12.6%) were characterized as GII.17_2014 with the first case detected in November 2015 (1/30, 3.3%) and the others in 2016 (11/65, 16.9%). All strains found in our study were clustered in clade D (epidemic strain). The uncorrelated log-normal model estimations calculated the rate of evolution for GII-17 strains as 1.95 × 10
   <sup>− 3</sup> (1.28 × 10
   <sup>− 3</sup>–2.63 × 10
   <sup>− 3</sup>). In total, 36 nucleotide changes were observed after analyzing the VP1 sequence, among which 28 occurred in the P2 region.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p id="Par4">These data demonstrate the evolutionary dynamics in NoV GII.17_2014 strains, which indicated high mutation rates with nucleotide substitutions and indels that are related to the elevated levels of antigenic diversity. This partly explains the increase in viral prevalence.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
