<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0135">Inducing passive immunization by infusion of CP is a potential therapeutic option in the absence of a proven anti-viral agent or vaccine. In CP therapy, blood plasma of patients who have recovered from COVID-19 is transfused into patients who are currently ill, in the hope that the freshly-made antibodies will help overcome the virus. Convalescent plasma has previously been used in the treatment of viral diseases such as poliomyelitis, influenza, SARS, and MERS. A case series of five critically ill COVID-19 patients with ARDS reported clinical improvements after the administration of convalescent plasma 
 <xref rid="b0385" ref-type="bibr">[77]</xref>. Another study on ten severely ill patients in China showed that the clinical symptoms improved significantly within three days, and that the viral load was undetectable after seven days of transfusion 
 <xref rid="b0390" ref-type="bibr">[78]</xref>. A recent study on more than 20,000 COVID-19 patients who received CP therapy reported that transfusion of CP is safe and does not heighten the risk of adverse events 
 <xref rid="b0395" ref-type="bibr">[79]</xref>. The study also indicated a reduction in mortality after transfusion of CP. Ianevski et al. reported on the differential nature of immune reactions to COVID-19 in different patients and suggested that the ability of CP to elicit a neutralizing immune response might wane with time 
 <xref rid="b0400" ref-type="bibr">[80]</xref>. More than 130 listed trials are in progress across the world to gather stronger evidence that would warrant the use of plasma therapy. Plasma banks for the transfusion of CP from freshly recovered COVID-19 patients have been set up in several countries, including India, to counter the rapidly increasing number of cases 
 <xref rid="b0405" ref-type="bibr">[81]</xref>. Adverse effects associated with plasma transfusion include pathogen transmission and allergic transfusion reactions. The greatest obstacle for a large scale rollout of plasma therapy is to find prospective donors with high levels of neutralizing antibody titer (&gt;1:640) 
 <xref rid="b0390" ref-type="bibr">[78]</xref>. Studies on SARS have reported that the level of specific neutralizing antibodies titer decreased rapidly within four months of recovery 
 <xref rid="b0410" ref-type="bibr">[82]</xref>, suggesting that immune protection may wane over time. Such short-lasting humoral immune response suggests that plasma from recently recovered patients is more effective for plasma therapy. The presence of antibodies points to a past infection. However, further research is needed to know more about the type and concentration of virus-neutralizing antibodies that protect against a new infection, and the duration for which the immunity might last. Current data is still insufficient on whether mild or asymptomatic infections generate adequate antibody responses or protection to COVID-19.
</p>
