<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although there were no presumptive treatments in 2013 and 2014, cases remained low. In both years, however, the reactive vector suppression treatments in the vicinity of cases continued. Because data more recent than 2014 were not available for analysis, we do not know if cases have gradually increased to levels representative of elsewhere in South Sulawesi. There were also gaps in methodology and inconsistencies in data collection. Methods for intervention did not always remain the same during the eight years; the HI threshold for pre-rainy season fogging became increasingly stringent, decreasing from 40% to 35% to 25%—these changes were based on maximizing available finances and capacity (for fogging) in combination with the reduced number of areas meeting the HI-fogging threshold. The large number of volunteers suggest that in any given year there might have been lack of uniformity in the data on which HI were calculated, however, the large number of intervention units would have reduced the effect of systematic error. No data were collected on adult 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> densities. Reliance on immature indices is typical in most dengue suppression programs but a more direct correspondence between adult vectors and humans would have provided additional insight. Here, the HI (and its consequent spatial and temporal reduction) may be considered reflective of the spatial distribution of blood feeding and egg-laying female Aedes that oviposit around houses. Routine insecticide susceptibility testing would also have been valuable; limited resistance tests performed using CDC bottle assays on local 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> in 2004 and 2006 demonstrated no Malathion resistance (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0007606.s003">S3 Text</xref>). Though insecticide resistance was not observed, the emergence and spread of resistance is an important factor in any control strategy. This can be mitigated by rotating insecticides used or using them in mosaic patterns [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007606.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Volunteers were trained to identify 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> larvae but it was not logistically feasible for the MoH to subsequently confirm them as 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic>, 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic>, or other Stegomyia. Previous data demonstrated that nearly all 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> larvae in the types of containers sampled in the area were either 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> or 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0007606.s004">S4 Text</xref>).
</p>
