<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A homologue of ACE, namely ACE2 was identified in 2000.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr31-0004563220928361" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
 </sup> ACE2 and ACE catalytic domains are 42% identical alluding to two genes from a common ancestor.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr31-0004563220928361" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
 </sup> ACE2 is a type I transmembrane metallopeptidase with its enzymatic domain on the external surface of cells.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr25-0004563220928361" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr31-0004563220928361" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr32-0004563220928361" ref-type="bibr"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr33-0004563220928361" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>
 </sup> It is involved in regulation of cardiac function and blood pressure control, possibly as a counterpart of ACE.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr34-0004563220928361" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>
 </sup> ACE2 regulates the RAS by modulating endogenous concentrations of angiotensin I and angiotensin II.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr25-0004563220928361" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>
 </sup> It cleaves a single residue of angiotensin I to generate angiotensin (1–9) and a single residue of angiotensin II to generate angiotensin (1–7) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0004563220928361">Figure 2</xref>). It possibly cleaves other substrates such as apelin which has cardioprotective properties, des-arginine bradykinin which promotes inflammation and neurotensin involved in the regulation of luteinizing hormone and prolactin.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr26-0004563220928361" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr31-0004563220928361" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
 </sup> Angiotensin (1–9) can also be converted to angiotensin (1–7) by ACE. After binding the MAS receptor, angiotensin (1–7) shifts the balance from vasoconstriction with angiotensin II to vasodilation and gives rise to anti-inflammatory and anti-fibrotic effects, increased NO synthesis and vasodilation.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr26-0004563220928361" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
 </sup> Inactivation of ACE2 leads to increased angiotensin II concentrations and impaired cardiac contractility.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr25-0004563220928361" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
