<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since its discovery in 2010, over 13 thousands reported cases of SFTS have been documented worldwide and more than 8% of those cases have died. There is a significantly increasing trends in all the three mainly affected countries, with above 90% cases occurred in China, while the highest annual increasing rate observed in South Korea, and the highest case fatality rate observed in Japan, which indicates a serious public health concerns, given that no effective treatment or vaccine is available at this moment [
 <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Recent detection of 
 <italic>H. longicornis</italic>, and its quick spread in the United State demonstrated the possibility of the disease to be global rather than regional [
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In this study, we predicted a high receptivity to 
 <italic>H. longicornis</italic> across two continents, including northeastern USA, New Zealand, parts of Australia, and several Pacific islands (New Caledonia, Fiji, Western Samoa, Tonga, and Vanuatu). Our prediction map (
 <xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>) revealed seven countries needed intensive surveillance for 
 <italic>H. longicornis</italic> presence, while there were fifteen countries which had only small and sparse risky areas that needed moderate surveillance. A special situation was observed in the New Zealand, which had reported the presence of 
 <italic>H. longicornis</italic> tick since 1910s, however, no SFTS cases had been reported until now. According to the phylogenetic study in China, SFTSV was suggested to originate 50–150 years ago, and the viral population only experienced a recent growth phase, with the first human infection reported in 2009 in China [
 <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. The SFTSV viral lineage, if already existed in New Zealand, might remained unknown to cause human infection without adequate sampling and tests. On the other hand, the long distance between the New Zealand and Asian countries, together with less population travel or commercial interchange than with the neighbouring countries might lead to the less likelihood of introducing the viral in a short period. All these assumptions call for the necessity of establishing a wide-scope surveillance of SFTSV in this country. Recently another emerging SFTSV-like bunyaviruses, Heartland virus (HRTV) that caused similar severe febrile disease and death in humans was isolated from patients in the United States [
 <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42–44</xref>]. In case the HRTV could be also harboured and transmitted by 
 <italic>H. longicornis</italic>, the possibility of local transmission of HRTV in North America should not be neglected. On the other hand, based on the current BRT Model, the predicted distribution of 
 <italic>H. longicornis</italic> contributed significantly to the SFTS occurrence, further corroborating the vital role of this tick in maintaining and transmitting the disease in natural environment. An intensive vigilance for potential SFTS spread or invasion events should be advocated in the 
 <italic>H. longicornis</italic> receptible countries [
 <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>].
</p>
