<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In this work and in several previous studies (McElhany et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">1995</xref>, Sisterson 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>) preferential attraction of aphids to virus‐infected plants increases the rate of spread of infection early in an epidemic. Later in the epidemic, attraction leads to bottlenecks as virus‐bearing aphids rarely alight on healthy plants, which leads to a lower final disease incidence (summarized in Figs. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>; Appendix 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-sup-0002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref>: Fig. S1, Appendix 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-sup-0007" ref-type="supplementary-material">S7</xref>: Fig. S1). Like McElhany et al. (
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">1995</xref>) and Sisterson (
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>), we find that deterrence against vector feeding (an extreme of plant acceptability VMPP) increases the probability of vectors acquiring the virus when they probe infected plants. But we report an additional benefit of deterrence, which is that late in epidemics, a higher occurrence of rejection of probed plants leads to more sustained feeding dispersals. In another study, Madden et al. (
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>) modeled frequency‐dependent contacts between virus‐bearing vectors and healthy plants. It was concluded by Madden et al. (
 <xref rid="ecy2725-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>) that for NPT viruses, 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> = ϕ
 <sup>2</sup>(
 <italic>A</italic>/
 <italic>H</italic>)(1/
 <italic>Γ</italic>)(1/
 <italic>τ</italic>), where 1/τ is the infectious period of the vector and ϕ represents plants visited per day by an aphid (note that we have set several ancillary parameters to 1 to simplify the expression). Thus, conventional models that do not account for aphid behavior (feeding vs. probing), lead to expressions for 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> for NPT viruses, as for PT viruses, that are proportional to the infectious period of both the host plant and vector, and to the square of the dispersal rate. In contrast, our framework shows that 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> should be proportional to only the plant's infectious period and that it should scale linearly with dispersal rate (Eq. 
 <xref rid="ecy2725-disp-0003" ref-type="disp-formula">(3)</xref>), because, crucially, transmission occurs within individual feeding dispersals as a by‐product of aphids probing infected plants.
</p>
