<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">In Vietnam from 2001 to 2010, the total number of cases reported in 19 provinces was 592,938 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Hanoi is one of the two biggest cities located in the North of Vietnam. In the previous large outbreak in 2009 with 16,263 cases were recorded that spread to all districts and Hanoi recorded 87% of all patients. The number of people infected with dengue in 2009 is 6.7 times higher than in 2008 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. In 2014, Vietnam recorded 43,000 cases in 53 provinces with 28 deaths [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. The unusual epidemic outbreak in 2017 did not occur in the peak season of the disease; however, it reported a high number of cases (183,287 cases and 154,552 hospitalizations) in a short period (from June to August 2017) and occurred in all age groups, ranging from young children, the elderly, adolescents, and adults, to pregnant women [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. In this outbreak, there were 59,063 dengue fever cases in Northern Vietnam, approximately eight times higher than in 2016 with 7289 dengue fever cases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. In this ourbreak in Hanoi, the number of cases was 70 times higher compared to the same period in 2016, with nearly 37,651 people infected and seven deaths [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].. DENV-1 accounted for the largest proportion of detected viruses in the 2017 epidemic besides types 2, 3, and 4 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Previous genetic studies in Vietnam on this virus involved only analysis of the E-gene sequence [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Thus, not much information is available on the genetic diversity of the whole DENV-1 genome over time and the genetic diversity of the DENV resulting due to synonymous and non-synonymous mutations that make the DENV adaptable under selective pressure. Moreover, the construction of the phylogenetic tree of the causative strains of the unusual epidemic in 2017 required the dataset at a global level.
</p>
