<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are several arguments suggesting that SIV has been present in sooty mangabeys and chimpanzees longer than our results indicate. First, coalescent processes or selective sweeps might have removed the deeper lineages from the phylogeny. While we cannot discount the latter, our finding that the SIVsm population has not evolved under a constant size suggests that deep SIVsm lineages may still be present. It remains unclear whether coalescent processes may have removed deep SIVcpz branches. Nevertheless, the full SIV/HIV tree suggests that there is a relatively short period of time between the MRCAs of SIVsm and SIVcpz and the branches that lead to SIVs that infect other primates (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pcbi-1000377-g002">Figure 2</xref>). A second argument is that our sampling was not thorough enough, and deep SIV branches were not included. While possible, other studies that included additional non-dated SIVsm and SIVcpz sequences did not uncover additional deeper branches 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000377-Keele1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000377-Apetrei1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000377-Ling2" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Thirdly, it has been suggested previously that SIV may lack the clock-like signal necessary to draw inference about tMRCAs. As a part of this study, we demonstrated that one major SIV lineage evolves in a clock-like fashion and at a rate indistinguishable from HIV. SIVsm sequences sampled over 30 years contain enough information to calibrate the molecular clock and date the tMRCA of an SIV clade. While we were able to use the SIVsm rate to date the tMRCA of SIVsm/HIV-2, this dating was not possible for SIVcpz. This difference is likely because we had far fewer SIVcpz sequences that were sampled over a relatively small window of time. Lastly, it is possible that our relaxed-clock models are biased and therefore unable to accurately date SIV coalescent events. We cannot dismiss this possibility, but the accuracy of these methods has been previously confirmed by other studies predicting the year of sampling of older HIV isolates from 1959 and 1960 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000377-Korber1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000377-Worobey1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Furthermore, our analyses recovered HIV tMRCA estimates that are in line with those previously inferred for the age of the HIV clades. Conversely, if one were to accept the HIV dates, one would need to provide a compelling reason not to accept the tMRCA estimates for SIVsm and SIVcpz as well. If the SIV tMRCAs are not correct, then we would need to determine what would be biasing their estimates, because it might also be affecting the HIV tMRCAs and those of other RNA viruses.
</p>
