<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32">Epidemiological characteristic and clinical manifestation of HFRS can be determined by virus genotypes which are further influenced by host speicies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. In central China, HFRS has stronger relationship with HTNV carried by striped field mouse [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. It has been shown that HTNV and SEOV simutaneously circulated in most areas of China, such as eastern coastal city, Qingdao [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], central city beside Yangzi River, Wuhan [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] as well as southwestern area [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] and northeastern area [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Uniquely, we have never identified HTNV among rodents and correspondingly the field rat, 
 <italic>A. agrarius</italic> the natural host for HTNV, was also seldom to be found even in the field areas of Hebei province since 2007. However, the house rat, 
 <italic>R. norvegicus</italic> predominantly existed in both residential areas and field areas leading SEOV probably to be sole pathogen for HFRS infection in this northern China province. For the past few years, more and more evidences has proven that due to global warming or the usage of rodenticides the asian house rat, 
 <italic>Rattus tanezumi</italic> which naturally exit in southern China has expanded their vivosphere northward and aggressively influenced local rodent population including 
 <italic>R. norvegicus</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Because so far 
 <italic>R. tanezumi</italic> has not been proven to be a natural host for SEOV, this migration might incompletely explain the shift of HFRS high incidence region of Hebei province. Thus far, in order to comprehensively illustrate the transmission dynamic of HFRS, continuous surveillance of rodent population should be enhanced in the future.
</p>
