<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We thank the reviewers for raising this important issue. In the revised version of our manuscript, we now discuss the findings reported by Martinez-Picado et al.in 2016 in the context of our present study (Discussion, last paragraph). In fact, we previously discussed this issue in length, and we kindly invite the reviewers to read it (Martinez-Picado et al., 2017). Briefly, we previously described a loss-of-function variant in 
 <italic>SIGLEC-</italic>1; a formal analysis of a large cohort of HIV-1-infected individuals identified homozygous and heterozygous subjects, whose cells were functionally null or partially defective for Siglec-1 activity in HIV-1 capture and transmission ex vivo. However, this analysis of the effect of Siglec-1 truncation on progression to AIDS was not conclusive based on the lack of statistical significance. Of note, this does not rule out a role of Siglec-1 in the progression of AIDS. As discussed in Martinez-Picado et al. 2017, there are multiple challenges that explain the lack of conclusive results in our approach to assess the impact of Siglec-1 genetic variants in AIDS progression in the human population. Briefly, the first challenge we encountered was the limited cohort size applied in our original study, which included 4’233 patients (Martinez-Picado et al., 2016). Indeed, power simulations determined that a proper analysis of a rare variant, like the Siglec-1 allele, would require more than 10,000 individuals to uncover a relative risk of 5 at P &lt; 0.05 under a recessive model. Since the proposed effect demands long-term follow-up off therapy, it is very unlikely that a sufficient sample size could be obtained to determine the long-term consequences of the Siglec-1 stop variant on AIDS progression. Second, our original study lacked the seroconvertion date for the majority of the patients that were screened. This is an important issue because HIV-1 disease progression was only monitored from the diagnosis date, which may differ between individuals, especially if they are protected by the beneficial effect of the Siglec-1 stop variant. Third, there was a lack of complete clinical records from key individuals in our original study. For example, one of the homozygous individuals found for the loss-of-function variant in 
 <italic>SIGLEC-</italic>1 had no clinical records for nine years; information for this individual only resumed after antiretroviral treatment initiation, when viral suppression could have masked any potential effect that the Siglec-1 variant might have had on disease progression. Last, but not least, the study of Siglec-1 genetic variants become more complex when considering potential infection by other pathogens that could abrogate any potential beneficial effects against AIDS progression. On this latter point, the reviewer is correct to infer direct influence from tuberculosis disease. For instance, one of the homozygous individuals for the rare Siglec-1 allele had a high CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cell count that dramatically dropped when tuberculosis was diagnosed, suggesting that the absence of a functional Siglec-1 receptor could have had a negative impact on the immune control of the mycobacterial infection. Indeed, in an independent study, we are currently addressing this issue where we suspect that Siglec-1 expression on myeloid APCs could compromise antigen capture 
 <italic>via</italic> exosome or microvesicle transfer and affect the control of the 
 <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> infection (unpublished results). Therefore, these observations argue that the role of Siglec-1 in the progression of AIDS is still a pending issue, and that there is a strong need for future work targeting Siglec-1 to unveil the in vivo contribution of the mononuclear phagocyte system to HIV-1 pathogenesis to fully exploit the therapeutic potential of this receptor.
</p>
