<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although broadly neutralizing antibodies (bnAbs) targeting the S2 domain of SARS-CoV S protein have been studied in the past, Abs are generally not suitable for oral delivery, limiting their potential application.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref99">99</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref100">100</xref>
 </sup> Small molecules mimicking bnAbs as fusion inhibitors have also been described for other viruses such as influenza virus or HIV-1 and represent a promising strategy.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref99">99</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref100">100</xref>
 </sup> Xu et al. developed a two-step screening method to identify inhibitors that potentially block SARS-CoV entry into the host cells.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref99">99</xref>
 </sup> On the basis of this approach, they identified two small molecules, 
 <bold>TGG</bold> (
 <bold>12</bold>, 
 <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="other">Table 
  <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="other">4</xref>
 </xref>) and 
 <bold>luteolin</bold> (
 <bold>13</bold>), that can bind avidly to the SARS-CoV S2 protein and inhibit viral entry of SARS-CoV into Vero E6 cells with IC
 <sub>50</sub> values of 4.5 and 10.6 μM, respectively. Cytotoxicity assay showed that the CC
 <sub>50</sub> of 
 <bold>12</bold> and 
 <bold>13</bold> were 1.08 and 0.155 mM, respectively. Therefore, the selectivity index of 
 <bold>12</bold> and 
 <bold>13</bold> were 240.0 and 14.62, respectively. Further acute toxicity suggested that the 50% lethal doses of 
 <bold>12</bold> and 
 <bold>13</bold> were ∼456 and 232.2 mg/kg, respectively. These indicated that these small molecules could be used at relatively high concentrations in mice.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref98">98</xref>
 </sup>
 <bold>Quercetin</bold> (
 <bold>14</bold>), an analogue of 
 <bold>13</bold>, also showed antiviral activity against SARS-CoV, with an IC
 <sub>50</sub> value of 83.4 μM and a CC
 <sub>50</sub> value of 3.32 mM.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref101">101</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
