<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As a pioneering study in COVID-19, using affinity purification mass spectrometry, Gordon et al. identified 332 high-confidence protein–protein interactions between SARS-CoV-2 and human proteins and suggested druggable targets to treat COVID-19.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref>
 </sup> Using stable isotope labeled Tandem Mass Tag (TMT) MS-based proteomics, Shen et al. identified dysregulation of multiple apolipoproteins including APOA1, APOA2, APOH, APOL1, APOD, and APOM in patient’s sera.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref>
 </sup> Using LC–MS/MS-based proteomics of urine specimens from COVID-19 patients, Li et al. found mild and severe COVID-19 patients with comorbidities were clearly differentiated from healthy patients.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref40">40</xref>
 </sup> This study identified that intracellular cholesterol transporter 2 (NPC2), APOA1, and cubilin (CUBN) were downregulated in severe COVID-19 patients, but cyclic AMP-responsive element-binding protein 3, like protein 3 (CREB3L3), hypoxia up-regulated protein 1 (HYOU1), heparin cofactor 2 (SERPIND1), and complement 3 (C3), were upregulated in mild or severe COVID-19 patients. Using orbitrap MS-based targeted proteomics, Bezstarosti et al. detected tryptic peptides of SARS-CoV-2 proteins (NCAP, VME1) that could be utilized as a diagnostic of COVID-19.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">41</xref>
 </sup> Moreover, proteomics using LC–MS for COVID-19 identified 27 proteins as signatures with disease severity where 22 of them were upregulated, while the remaining 5 were downregulated with increasing severity of COVID-19.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42">42</xref>
 </sup> Over 6739 proteins were identified using LC–MS-based global proteome analysis of PBMCs from COVID-19 patients, and specifically, this study identified that the nsp9 and nsp10 proteins from SARS-COV-2 interact with host NKRF, a NF-kB repressor, and may precipitate the strong interleukin (IL)-8/IL-6 mediated chemotaxis of neutrophils and increased host inflammatory response in COVID-19 patients.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">43</xref>
 </sup> Using nano-HPLC/nano-ESI-Orbitrap-MS/MS, Ihling et al. identified unique peptides originating from SARS-CoV-2 nucleoprotein from a highly diluted gargle solution of COVID-19 patients.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref>
 </sup> A cancer cell model system infected by SARS-CoV-2 followed by LC–MS-based proteomics revealed that diverse nucleic acid metabolism was critical for corona virus replication and suggested an inhibitor of nucleotide pool biosynthesis as a therapeutic for COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">Table 
  <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref>
 </xref>).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref45">45</xref>
 </sup> Using MALDI-MS combined multivariate statistical analysis, Dattero et al. showed the potential of MALDI-MS as a complementary diagnostic tool for discriminating SARS-CoV-2 from other viruses.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46">46</xref>
 </sup> Overall, LC and MALDI-MS based proteomics has shown potential as a key COVID-19 research area; however, development of rapid and sensitive MS techniques along with trials in larger clinical studies are necessary to translate the beneficial aspects of MS-based proteomics in pandemics like COVID-19 disease (
 <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>
 </xref>).
</p>
