<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The developed ABC inference framework for network identification and parameter estimation showed discriminatory power and ability to recover epidemiological parameters when applied to simulated data. The model used for validating the ABC algorithm included stage varying infectivity, individual, and within-host variability. For complex models such as epidemic spreads on networks the likelihood function is computationally costly to evaluate and ABC offered a way to perform likelihood-free statistical inference. Furthermore, the use of summary statistics allowed us to study the relationship between readily measurable tree statistics and complex transmission dynamics. The analysis of the two outbreaks from the Swedish HIV-1 epidemic showed that inference on real datasets is typically much harder. As is to be expected, real world networks do not match perfectly with the simplified models considered in this study, that were chosen for comparability with previous studies [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005316.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005316.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005316.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In fact, in the ABC algorithm, the proposed parameters values are accepted if the simulated data based on them are close enough to the observed data. If the observed data were generated from a rather different or more complex model, then the simulated data from the candidate model probably will be far away from the observed data. Hence, very few proposed parameter values will be accepted. More realistic models, such as dynamic networks, may be able to better capture the features of the outbreaks, especially those occurring over a long period of time. Another class of network models that could be suitable in modelling these outbreaks is the configuration model which is flexible and has been studied extensively in the literature, or exponential random graph models (although in general slower to fit to data) which include a broader spectrum of degree distributions and clustering levels rather than the three simple networks considered here. The ABC inference scheme can also be extended to take into account uncertainty in the phylogenetic reconstruction, as shown in [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005316.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Each summary statistics calculated on the simulated trees would then be compared to the distribution of the same statistics calculated on the posterior distribution of virus genealogies. Romero et al. [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005316.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>] apply this procedure investigating transmission between a heterosexual couple. However, the outbreaks we are analyzing in this paper are bigger in size and the whole algorithm would be more computationally expensive. Lastly, this work could be further extended to integrate other sources of network data coming from social surveys and/or public health intervention studies, as recently outlined in a review paper by [
 <xref rid="pcbi.1005316.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] to improve network analysis in HIV epidemiology.
</p>
