<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Sequences were aligned using BIOEDIT 
 <xref rid="ppat.1002094-Hall1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. We used likelihood ratio tests, Akaike and Bayesian information criteria as implemented in DataMonkey 
 <xref rid="ppat.1002094-KosakovskyPond2" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref> to select the simplest evolutionary model that best fit the different dataset. For the three genes, a Hasegawa–Kishino–Yano (HKY) model with gamma-distributed rates among sites was selected. Rates of nucleotide substitution and time of most recent common ancestors (TMRCAs) were estimated for the three genes using a Bayesian Markov Chain Monte Carlo (BMCMC) method 
 <xref rid="ppat.1002094-Drummond1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> as implemented in the program BEAST 
 <xref rid="ppat.1002094-Drummond2" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. Isolation dates were used to calibrate the molecular clock. Different combinations of molecular clock (strict clock or uncorrelated relaxed clocks 
 <xref rid="ppat.1002094-Drummond3" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>) and demographic models were attempted independently and the best-fit clock and demographic models were selected by performing Bayes factor tests 
 <xref rid="ppat.1002094-Suchard1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. The limited timespan of our samples required the use of a simple model to avoid over-parameterization 
 <xref rid="ppat.1002094-Smith1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>, so we used a single HKY model over all sites in preference to a codon-partitioned model for these analyses. For each dataset, three independent runs were conducted for 60 million generations, sampling every 2,000 generations. Convergences and effective sample sizes of the estimates were checked using TRACER 
 <xref rid="ppat.1002094-Rambaut1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. Trees were summarized in a maximum clade credibility (MCC) tree after a 20% burn-in using TREEANNOTATOR 
 <xref rid="ppat.1002094-Drummond2" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. The resulting time-scaled phylogenetic trees were visualised with FIGTREE 
 <xref rid="ppat.1002094-Rambaut2" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>.
</p>
