<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0060">Epidemics can lead to a significant increase in demand for ICU beds, so reducing the available beds. As an example, the SARS outbreak in Toronto led to closures of 35 ICU beds for ten days, which represented 38% of the tertiary-care university medical-surgical beds of ICU in Toronto 
 <xref rid="b0235" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. Many reasons represent a challenge in caring for patients with COVID-19 with a high risk of exposure for ICU staff. COVID-19 is highly contagious, along with more than one route of transmission. The high exposure dose, long contact hours with cases, some procedures such as noninvasive ventilation, and the length of ICU stay are representing the challenges for ICU staff during the epidemic 
 <xref rid="b0240" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. So, special measures and precautions should be taken in intensive care. For example, cases with COVID-19 should be admitted to single bedded and negative pressure rooms in separate units within intensive care. Clinical engineering should have rapid and special plans to convert standard rooms into ICU rooms. Retrofitting the rooms with externally exhausted HEPA filters may solve the problem 
 <xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. Most of the transplanted patients have multiple comorbidities and organ dysfunction, demanding high appropriate critical care management to support prompt graft recovery and prevent systemic complications 
 <xref rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. The early postoperative period is a critical time. Strict monitoring of vital data, support of cardiorespiratory performance, early assessment of graft function, along with recognition of unexpected complications (medical and surgical) are mandatory. The Intensive care management of liver transplanted patients mainly focuses on rapid hemodynamic stabilization, early weaning from mechanical ventilation, coagulopathy correction, preservation of kidney function, graft rejection prevention, proper fluid administration, and infection prophylaxis 
 <xref rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>.
</p>
