<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">We present the rationale for a novel allo-priming approach to serve the elderly as a universal anti-virus vaccine, as well serving to remodel the aging immune system in order to reverse immunosenescence and inflammaging. This approach has the potential to protect the most vulnerable from disease and provide society an incalculable economic benefit. Allo-priming healthy elderly adults is proposed to provide universal protection from progression of any type of viral infection, including protection against progression of the current outbreak of COVID-19 infection, and any future variants of the causative SARS-CoV-2 virus or the next ‘Disease X’. Allo-priming is an alternative approach for the COVID-19 pandemic that provides a back-up in case vaccination strategies to elicit neutralizing antibody protection fails or fails to protect the vulnerable elderly population. The allo-priming is performed using activated, intentionally mismatched, ex vivo differentiated and expanded living Th1-like cells (AlloStim
   <sup>®</sup>) derived from healthy donors currently in clinical use as an experimental cancer vaccine. Multiple intradermal injections of AlloStim
   <sup>®</sup> creates a dominate titer of allo-specific Th1/CTL memory cells in circulation, replacing the dominance of exhausted memory cells of the aged immune system. Upon viral encounter, by-stander activation of the allo-specific memory cells causes an immediate release of IFN-ϒ, leading to development of an “anti-viral state”, by-stander activation of innate cellular effector cells and activation of cross-reactive allo-specific CTL. In this manner, the non-specific activation of allo-specific Th1/CTL initiates a cascade of spatial and temporal immune events which act to limit the early viral titer. The release of endogenous heat shock proteins (HSP) and DAMP from lysed viral-infected cells, in the context of IFN-ϒ, creates of conditions for in situ vaccination leading to viral-specific Th1/CTL immunity. These viral-specific Th1/CTL provide sterilizing immunity and memory for protection from disease recurrence, while increasing the pool of Th1/CTL in circulation capable of responding to the next viral encounter.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusion</title>
  <p id="Par2">Allo-priming has potential to provide universal protection from viral disease and is a strategy to reverse immunosenescence and counter-regulate chronic inflammation (inflammaging). Allo-priming can be used as an adjuvant for anti-viral vaccines and as a counter-measure for unknown biological threats and bio-economic terrorism.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
