<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In another study, Poland et al. analyzed the immunogenetic relationships between HLA, cytokine and cytokine receptor gene polymorphisms in the induction of antibodies in response to inactivated seasonal vaccines [
 <xref rid="B156-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>]. Authors did not find statistically significant associations between HLA class II alleles and IAV HAI titers. However, they established a positive association of some HLA class I alleles and IAV H1N1 HAI titers, including HLA- A*1101, A*6801, B*3503, B*1401, and C*0802. In contrast, they did not find associations between the HLA-A, B or C alleles and HAI antibody titers for IAV H3N2. In addition, when authors evaluated a panel of 586 cytokine and cytokine receptor SNPs, they identified several significant associations between SNPs, in regulatory or coding regions of cytokine (IL-6, IL-12B) or cytokine receptor (IL-1R, IL-10RB, TNFRSF1A) genes and variations in HAI antibody titers for IAV H1N1 [
 <xref rid="B156-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>] (
 <xref rid="pathogens-08-00168-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Notably, SNPs from three genes, IL-6 (rs1800796), IL-12B (rs3212227) and IL-1R1 (rs3732131) revealed links with IAV H1N1-induced antibody responses in an allele dose-related way. The presence of SNP allele C or G in the IL-12B or IL-1R1genes, respectively resulted in reduced HAI titers. However, high HAI titers in the presence of minor SNP allele G in the IL-6 gene were observed [
 <xref rid="B156-pathogens-08-00168" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>]. SNPs associations between cytokine or cytokine receptor genes and IAV H3N2 HAI titers were also identified (
 <xref rid="pathogens-08-00168-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). For example, a variant GA for non-synonymous SNPs within the IL-12 receptor gene (rs2307153; D465G) and TNF receptor 2 gene (rs5746026; K232E) displayed associations with lower HAI titers, while a minor allele T variant (rs12722605) located in the 3′ region of the IL-2 receptor gene was related with high antibody titers (
 <xref rid="pathogens-08-00168-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). These data suggest that host SNPs affect responses to influenza vaccine.
</p>
