<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<author-notes>
 <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: 
  <email>Gayle.Dolan@hpa.org.uk</email>
 </corresp>
 <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
  <p>
   <bold>Competing Interests: </bold>JSN-V-T has received funding to attend influenza related meetings, lecture and consultancy fees and research funding from several influenza antiviral drug and vaccine manufacturers (F. Hoffmann-La Roche, GlaxoSmithKline, Baxter AG, Novartis, Sanofi-Pasteur MSD, Astra-Zeneca). All forms of personal remuneration ceased in September 2010, but influenza-related research funding from GlaxoSmithKline, F. Hoffmann-La Roche and Astra-Zeneca remains current. He is a former employee of SmithKline Beecham plc (now GlaxoSmithKline), Roche Products Ltd, and Aventis-Pasteur MSD (now Sanofi-Pasteur MSD), all prior to 2005, with no outstanding pecuniary interests by way of shareholdings, share options or accrued pension rights. PRM holds an unrestricted educational grant from F. Hoffman-La Roche Ltd for research in the area of pandemic influenza. RCR has received funding for vaccine-related research from Novartis and travel funding from GlaxoSmithKline. WSL has received unrestricted funding from Pfizer (previously Wyeth) for research in the area of pneumonia. SJB has received consultancy fees from GlaxoSmithKline and Baxter. JEE has received consultancy fees from GlaxoSmithKline, and holds an unrestricted educational grant from Astra-Zeneca for influenza-related research. KGN has received H5 avian influenza vaccines from Novartis and H1N1 pandemic influenza vaccines from GlaxoSmithKline and Baxter to facilitate MRC and National Institute for Health Research-funded trials. He has received consultancy fees from Novartis and GlaxoSmithKline and lecture fees from Baxter AG. A colleague of KGN at the University Hospitals of Leicester Natioanl Health Service Trust was Principal Investigator and recipient of research funding from Roche on antiviral resistance and from Novartis on pandemic H1N1 vaccines. This does not alter the authors' adherence to all the PLoS ONE policies on sharing data and materials. No aspect of the work described in this report was supported or enabled by commercial funding.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="con">
  <p>Analyzed the data: GPD PRM SJB JEE RCR PJMO MGS WSL BLT JMcM KGN BB JSN-V-T. Wrote the paper: GPD PRM SJB JSN-V-T. Conducted the primary analysis: PRM. Contributing to the article and approving the final version: GPD PRM SJB JEE RCR PJMO MGS WSL BLT JMcM KGN BB JSN-V-T.</p>
 </fn>
</author-notes>
