<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>CHIKV are classified in three genotypic groups: East-Central-South Africa (ECSA), West Africa, and Asian. After the 2006 La Réunion outbreak, a new Indian Ocean lineage (IOL) was identified as a monophyletic descendant of the ECSA group [
 <xref rid="B6-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The RNA genomes of ECSA-IOL CHIKV were associated with a genetic mutation in the CHIKV E1 glycoprotein-coding region resulting in a single alanine to valine amino acid change (E1-A226V) that adapted the virus to 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> [
 <xref rid="B9-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Others have reported that ECSA-IOL CHIKV infection of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> virus can be further enhanced by amino acid changes in their E2 glycoprotein [
 <xref rid="B13-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In 2013–2014, CHIKV (Asian genotype) spread to more than 22 countries in the western hemisphere and caused tens of thousands of human cases [
 <xref rid="B14-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. The R99659 CHIKV was isolated from the British Virgin Islands during an epidemic but CHIKVs of the ECSA-IOL genotype were not associated with this outbreak [
 <xref rid="B15-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. However, the ECSA-IOL CHIKV could rapidly spread in the western hemisphere if viremic individuals with the ECSA-IOL CHIKV genotype travel to the United States (U.S.) and infect established 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> populations. Autochthonous transmission of ECSA-IOL CHIKV by 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> could then lead to new outbreaks in CHIKV-naïve human populations [
 <xref rid="B17-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].
</p>
