<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our goal was to analyze salivary gland and the titer of virus in saliva of the two CHIKV isolates, LR2006 OPY1 (ECSA-IOL genotype) and R99659 (Asian genotype), in strains of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> from New Jersey, Florida and Louisiana. We compared infections of these mosquitoes with an 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> strain from La Réunion Island and an 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> strain from Mexico (Poza Rica). The extrinsic incubation period (EIP), the time from initial acquisition of CHIKV by the mosquito until virus transmission ranges from 2 to 9 days [
 <xref rid="B18-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. We analyzed salivary gland and saliva infection status for CHIKV in each infected mosquito at 9 days post-blood meal infection. Typically, CHIKV infects the midgut when the mosquito imbibes a viremic blood meal. The virus then disseminates to other tissues including salivary glands where the virus enters saliva. Virus in saliva is transmitted to a susceptible host during acquisition of a subsequent blood meal. To evaluate dissemination and transmission rates, saliva was collected to determine transmission potential, and then salivary glands were dissected from the same mosquitoes to analyze virus dissemination. Here, we report dissemination rate (DIR) as the percent of total mosquitoes exposed to virus that were positive for virus in the salivary gland and the transmission efficiency rate (TER) as the percent of mosquitoes positive for virus in the saliva that were also positive for virus in the salivary glands. Vector competence was determined here by multiplying DIR × TER. We clearly showed under laboratory conditions that the Louisiana (Lake Charles), Florida, and New Jersey strains of 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> had high DIR values. The TER values for CHIKVs were lower than expected for R99659 virus given the mosquitoes’ high DIRs and suggested the presence of a salivary gland escape barrier (SGEB) for that virus. All mosquitoes were competent to transmit LR2006 OPY1. Of the three U.S. 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> strains, the Louisiana and Florida strains could serve as excellent vectors for CHIKV R99569 (Asian) transmission. The New Jersey 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> strain had the lowest vector competence (DIR × TER) of the three 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> strains for R99569 virus but had statistically similar vector competence as the other strains for LR2006 OPY1 (ECSA-IOL) [
 <xref rid="B19-insects-10-00039" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. 
</p>
