<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">Signs and symptoms of dehydration are important to determine the severity of dehydration. Both the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) and the American Academy of Pediatrics (AAP) recommend using a simple dehydration scale to classify the total body water loss occurring with dehydration as minimal/none (&lt;3 %), mild/moderate (3–9 %), or severe (&gt;10 %). Abnormal capillary refill (&gt;2 s), decreased skin turgor, and abnormal respiratory pattern (hyperpnea) have been the most reliable signs of determining the severity of dehydration. The vast majority of children presenting with acute gastroenteritis do not require serum or urine tests, as they are unlikely to be helpful in determining the degree of dehydration. Laboratory values may be helpful in evaluating severe dehydration, for which intravenous fluids and electrolyte supplementation (especially potassium, bicarbonate, and sodium) are needed [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Prevention of dehydration is the cornerstone of gastroenteritis treatment in children. A child with minimal or no dehydration should be encouraged to continue his or her usual diet plus drink adequate fluids. Early oral rehydration therapy using an oral rehydration solution (ORS), before the child becomes more severely dehydrated, is important and can be done at home.
 <sup>5</sup> The best way to accomplish early treatment is to train the physician’s office staff to explain how to use an ORS when caregivers call for help at the beginning of a child’s illness. Clear liquids, such as water, sodas, chicken broth, and apple juice, should not replace an ORS because they are hyperosmolar and do not adequately replace potassium, bicarbonate, and sodium. These fluids, especially water and apple juice, can cause hyponatremia. An ORS is composed of sodium, dextrose, and bicarbonate in a ratio that does not overwhelm the hyperactive bowel with a hyperosmolar solution, but that replaces the electrolyte loss. In general, antidiarrheal medications should not be used in children with acute gastroenteritis because they delay the elimination of infectious agents from the gastrointestinal tract.
</p>
