<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In fact, the complexity of the contemporary urban environments suggests the need to develop new surveillance tools to replace the current methods, which date back to 80 years ago. A tool commonly used to monitor and control 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> is the oviposition traps or ovitraps,
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref> which have been shown to be more sensitive than searching for larvae and/or pupae that can be spread in a wide range of cryptic breeding sites. In recent years, various traps for capturing 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> adults and/or eggs have been described.
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>17</sup>
 </xref> Studies using traps to monitor 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> populations in several Brazilian cities have revealed high levels of infestation in urban spaces, and reproductively active females were present in more than 60% of the properties fitted with either traps for catching egg-laying females or with ovitraps.
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref> A longitudinal study of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> sympatric populations in seven of the 94 neighbourhoods of Recife city (Brazil), carried out by our group in 2003-2005 based on a network of 465 ovitraps, recorded broad and intensive 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> presence in all neighbourhoods.
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref> The overall infestation index was 98.5% and densities from 100 to 2500 eggs/ovitrap/month were recorded throughout the year, regardless of the different environmental and socio-economic conditions of those neighbourhoods. The present study aimed to investigate the infestation pattern of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> in the Sítio dos Pintos neighbourhood in 2013, compared with a previous assessment of this area
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref> performed in 2005.
</p>
