<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">However, potentially more important clues to actual H5N1 pathogenicity and human case-fatality rates come from epidemiological studies, which taken together suggest to us that H5N1 may not be highly lethal except in people with rare susceptibilities. Forty-six published H5N1 seroprevalence studies of various exposure categories (household contacts, healthcare workers, poultry workers, and so on) show generally low H5N1 seroprevalence (mean, 1.7% of 21,435 persons examined in all 46 studies combined (a bibliography of these studies is available from the authors on request)). Given intense poultry and other exposures in many study areas, these low rates at first seem perplexing, especially when compared to the much higher seroprevalence rates in humans for other avian influenza viruses such as H9N2 (ref. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>). When such information is considered in light of statistically significant clustering of non-human-transmitted (that is, presumably avian-acquired) household cases in genetically related versus unrelated persons
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>
 </sup>, a reasonable explanation seems to us to be that H5N1 is so poorly adapted to humans that exposure does not normally lead to infection or even the development of a detectable immune response
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>
 </sup>, except in persons with specific but undefined genetic susceptibilities, many of whom become cases
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>
 </sup>. There are few data on what the basis of such genetic susceptibilities may be, although recent evidence has linked severe human influenza to a minor 
 <italic>IFITM3</italic> allele
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>
 </sup>, supporting the suspicion that genetic determinants of influenza infection and replication in humans do exist.
</p>
