<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) was first identified in patients with severe respiratory disease in Wuhan, China. The causative agent was a novel coronavirus scientifically named severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) [
 <xref rid="B1-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Since its discovery, more than 2,850,000 cases have been infected, including nearly 200,000 who have died. The worrisome features of COVID-19 are its apparent ability to spread readily and its propensity to cause severe disease in older adults and patients with existing health conditions [
 <xref rid="B3-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Moreover, coronaviruses are well-known to mutate and recombine [
 <xref rid="B5-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The genomic sequence of SARS-CoV-2 has changed since it was first reported. Some scientists believe that these changes have enhanced the virulence of the virus and there are two circulating strains, deadly strain “L”, and less virulent one “S” [
 <xref rid="B6-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Currently, there are no specific antiviral treatments or vaccines available for COVID-19. Treatments are mainly focusing on symptomatic and respiratory support according to protocols issued by the health authority in each country, where many countries are following WHO protocol [
 <xref rid="B3-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Nearly all cases with severe symptoms accept oxygen. In critical cases and life-threatening situations, passive immunization through the convalescent plasma and immunoglobulin G transfusion can be used as a rescue treatment [
 <xref rid="B7-pathogens-09-00331" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Given the current situation, finding a treatment has become a global public health priority. Many companies are working on finding a medication or a viable vaccine for SARS-CoV-2. However, this is not a short process; scientists estimate the period to have one, about 12–18 months.
</p>
