<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">In December 2019, a novel respiratory disease appeared in Wuhan, Hubei, China. Although it is still under debate, there are strong indications that a first cluster of infections occurred at the Huanan seafood market (
 <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). A novel coronavirus, CoV-19, and a later phenotype, CoV-2, were identified as the primary cause for a severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) (
 <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Within a few days, the viral disease spread over all of China, and within the following weeks, the local epidemic grew to a global pandemic with an exponentially growing infection rate. At present, the number of infected humans reached 3,855,788 with a number of 265,862 deaths associated with SARS CoV-19 and CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). This global pandemic will have an unprecedented economic, sociological, and political impact, in contrast to prior outbreaks of CoV-related SARS epidemics (
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Although a huge number of trials are still ongoing to develop a successful vaccination strategy against CoV-2, a direct medication of infected patients can have the potential to save lives and to stabilize the situation. The spike (S) protein of CoV-2 is the major target for the development of a vaccine or a potential strategy to tackle the viral entry into human cells (
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). The S-protein forms trimers at the protrusions of the virus and comprises two functional subunits: S1 and S2. In the cascade of the viral entry, the S1 unit of the spike (S) protein facilitates the attachment of the virus at the surface of the cell (
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). The S2 subunit, responsible for membrane fusion, employs TMPRSS2 for the S-protein priming, whereas it uses angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) as an entry receptor for membrane fusion (
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). One of the key factors for its infectious potential for humans is the high conservation of ACE2 in different mammalian organisms (
 <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), which allows its transmission from animals to humans. The receptor binding domain (RBD) of the S1 subunit contains five antiparallel 
 <italic>β</italic>-strands, whereas 
 <italic>α</italic>-helical and loop motifs form the connecting entities between the 
 <italic>β</italic>-sheets. Between two 
 <italic>β</italic>-sheets, an extended insertion forms the receptor binding motif, which binds to ACE2 at its N-terminal helix (
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Among a large number of potential targets, the inhibition of the direct interaction between ACE2 and the S-protein (SARS CoV-S) provides a suitable strategy to prevent the membrane fusion of CoV-2 and the viral entry into human cells (
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). In a combined experimental and theoretical study, a hexapeptide ((438)YKYRYL (443)) of the receptor domain of SARS CoV S has been identified as an efficient inhibitor of the interaction between the S-protein and ACE2 (
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). In vitro infection of Vero E6 cells by SARS coronavirus (SARS CoV) was blocked by the hexapeptide. It also has been shown that the peptide inhibits the proliferation of CoV-NL63. Interestingly, the fragment (438)YKYRYL (443) carries the dominant binding epitope and binds to ACE2 with a high affinity of K
 <sub>D</sub> = 46 
 <italic>μ</italic>M. Its binding mode was further characterized by saturation transfer difference, NMR spectroscopy, and molecular dynamics (MD) simulations. Based on this information, the peptide can be used as lead structure to design potential entry inhibitors against SARS CoV and related viruses.
</p>
