<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For more than a decade, the pyramid model has been used to illustrate the stages in viral zoonosis (
 <bold>
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.3000217.g001">Fig 1</xref>
 </bold>) [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>–
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. This model, moving upward from base to tip, highlights the steps animal viruses take to adapt to humans. While this concept is very useful, it fails to convey visually how rare zoonosis actually is. Almost all zoonotic viruses emerge from mammals or birds. There are currently 8,615 known species of mammals and 17,413 species of birds [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Assuming, conservatively, that there are 10 enzootic (endemic to animals) viruses per species [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], there are over 86,000 mammalian viruses and 174,000 avian viruses in nature, for a total of 260,000 animal viruses in nature. Recent estimates suggest that the actual number may be much higher, as high as 1.6 million animal viruses in nature [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In contrast, only 219 viruses have ever been documented to infect humans [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. This suggests that far less than 0.1% of the animal viruses in nature have ever caused a known human infection, consistent with other recent estimates [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. A modification of the pyramid model makes it visually apparent that an exceedingly small fraction of animal viruses has any path to replicating in humans (
 <bold>
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.3000217.g001">Fig 1</xref>)
 </bold>. In this pinhole model, one can more readily see why sequencing surveys of viruses in animals will do little to inform us of the ones that are dangerous to humans [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Based on the numbers just discussed, there appears to be a massive bottleneck between all animal viruses in nature and those that can replicate themselves in humans. Far less than 0.1% of animal viruses progress to step 1 in the process (green arrow; 
 <bold>
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio.3000217.g001">Fig 1</xref>
 </bold>). More research is needed, but the bottlenecks leading to the latter two steps don’t seem to be as extreme. One study of zoonotic pathogens (already at step 1) found that 33% are transmissible between humans (step 2), and 3% spread so effectively that they become permanently sustained in humans (step 3) [
 <xref rid="pbio.3000217.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. If initial viral replication in a human is so incredibly rare and the major bottleneck in this process, then how do we identify which viruses have the potential to break through? In this essay, we discuss the reasons why the vast majority of animal viruses in nature have little or no potential to ever replicate themselves in a human host. Then, we will discuss how the exceptions can be identified.
</p>
