<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To understand the temporal dynamics of FFV and to quantify host-switching over time, we constructed time-calibrated phylogenies in BEAST version 1.10 using the 
 <italic>pol</italic> gene only; 
 <italic>env</italic> was excluded from this analyses due to the high level of diversity resulting in a lack of temporal signal. Nonetheless, we do estimate the sub/site per year for both 
 <italic>pol</italic> and 
 <italic>env</italic> genes. Host and location were analyzed as discrete traits (
 <xref rid="vez058-B26" ref-type="bibr">Drummond and Rambaut 2007</xref>). Based on the two factors 1, domestic cat FFV likely represents a global endemic viral population due to domestic cat movement across the globe, and 2, we have a smaller relative representation of FFV from domestic cats compared with puma, we assigned sequences from domestic cats to one trait. To assess FFV movement between domestic cat and pumas across locations, FFV sequences from puma were assigned as traits based on their location (FR, WS, California, and Florida). We used a symmetric trait substitution model in which transition rates are assumed to occur at the same rate. Bayesian stochastic search variable selection procedure was employed to estimate host transition rates. SpreaD3 (
 <xref rid="vez058-B8" ref-type="bibr">Bielejec et al. 2016</xref>) was used to calculate Bayes Factor (BF) support for the most likely host transitions. Additionally, we used the same parameters but with a discrete trait asymmetrical model to test if cross-species transmission was more likely from domestic cat to puma or 
 <italic>vice versa</italic> (i.e. we only used domestic cat and puma as traits, this data is shown as 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref>), well-sampled puma populations were used for this, California and Florida puma were therefore excluded to simplify. Support for events with BF 3–10 = substantial, 10–30 = strong, 30–100 = very strong support, and &gt;100 = decisive (
 <xref rid="vez058-B38" ref-type="bibr">Jarosz and Wiley 2014</xref>).
</p>
