<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>JE is a natural focal disease. The 2018 Ningxia JE outbreak may have been the consequence of many factors such as mosquito vectors, host animals, local immunity, and local climate. The first factor maybe mosquito vectors. Ningxia (also known as the Yellow River Irrigation Area) located in northern China (35° 14’–39° 23’ N, 104° 17’–107°39’ E), is rich in water resources due to the irrigation of the Yellow River, the second largest river in China. As such, rice has gradually become a major crop in the area [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008312.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008312.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The cultivation of rice provides a favorable natural environment for the propagation of 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>tritaeniorhynchus</italic>, the main vector of JEV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008312.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In this study, 17,4000(
 <xref rid="pntd.0008312.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>) 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>tritaeniorhynchus</italic> mosquitoes (dominant, accounting for 70% of mosquitoes locally) were collected from Tongfu Township, Pingluo County, Shizuishan City, where a large number of JE cases occurred, and a large number of JEV-positive mosquitoes were detected (
 <xref rid="pntd.0008312.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Rice cultivation in Ningxia may provide a suitable natural environment for the breeding and reproduction of local 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>tritaeniorhynchus</italic>, and may facilitate the spread of JEV. The second factor maybe host animals. With the acceleration of urbanization in China, the number of urban areas in Ningxia is expanding. To supply the growing demand for pork, both the number of pig farmers and the size of pig farms in Ningxia are expanding [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008312.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Both rice paddies and pig farms exist around the residences of the JE cases reported in Ningxia. There are approximately 13 thousand square meters of rice paddies 20 meters away from the residence of one patient, and two large pig farms with 1000 pigs approximately 300 meters away from the residence of another patient. 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>tritaeniorhynchus</italic> and a large number of pigs provide an excellent natural environment for the circulation of JEV in local environment, and both pig farming in courtyards and living near pig farms can increase exposure to JEV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008312.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The third factor maybe the low immune barrier. Ningxia has been a low-endemic area of JE, with an incidence of less than 0.1 per 100,000 from 1997 to 2006 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008312.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008312.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. In particular, no cases of JE were reported in Ningxia during the 10-year period from 2006 to 2016 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008312.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008312.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Since the Chinese government implemented the EPI administration of the JE vaccine in 2008, children under 15 years old can receive a free JE vaccination; however, the local population born before 2008 was not vaccinated against JE, thus a large number of JEV susceptible individuals may accumulate among local adults (persons born before 2008). The fourth factor maybe climate impact. According to Ningxia meteorological monitoring data, the temperature of Ningxia in the summer of 2018 was the highest since 1961 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008312.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], and the summer temperature was 0.8°C higher than the perennial temperature (an increase in temperature reduces the diurnal temperature difference, which is conducive to mosquito activity and breeding). In addition, the amount of summer precipitation in Ningxia in 2018 increased, with a wide range and high intensity, and the annual precipitation in 2018 was 38% greater than the perennial period. Thus, the special climatic condition in Ningxia in 2018 may also be an important promoter of the local JE epidemic.
</p>
