<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As mentioned, JE is a vaccine-preventable disease, and vaccination has almost eliminated JE cases in Japan, South Korea, and Singapore, where JE is traditionally endemic [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008312.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Between 2008, when China included the JE vaccine in EPI, and 2013, the incidence of JE dropped to 0.56/ 100,000[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008312.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008312.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. However, the genotype of JEVs in Asia has changed from genotype III to genotype I in recent years [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008312.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008312.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In addition, JEV GV remerged in mainland China and South Korea in 2009 after about 60 years of silence[
 <xref rid="pntd.0008312.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0008312.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Therefore, whether the current JE vaccine (inactivated vaccine and live attenuated vaccine are both from JEV GIII) can effectively protect against the newly emerged JEV genotypes is a concern in the field of virology and public health. In one study, neutralizing antibody titers against JEV GI (GZ56, shown to be JEV Ib in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pntd.0008312.g003">Fig 3</xref>), GIII and GV of 26 pairs of serum samples before and after JE vaccination were compared. After vaccination, neutralizing antibodies against JEV GIII showed 100% positive seroconversion rate (SCR), with the highest neutralizing antibody titer reaching 1:1280. The SCR was 96% against GI JEV, with the highest neutralizing antibody titer reaching 1:640. Only a SCR of 35% (9/26) was observed against G5 JEV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008312.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] The above results suggest that the current JE vaccine is less protective against JEV GI and JEV GV infection than against JEV GIII. Furthermore, it is unclear whether people vaccinated with JE vaccine could be infected with JEV Ib or JEV GV. It can be seen that the change of JEV genotype and the emergence of JEV GV pose a challenge to the effectiveness of current JE vaccines in the prevention and control of JE.
</p>
