<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Though the etiology of HSP is not clear yet, it is thought to be caused by an immune complex that forms after an infection by a bacteria, virus, or protozoa.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
  <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]
 </sup> The most common finding is deposition of IgA, and therefore, HSP is presumed to be a disease mediated by IgA immune complexes.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]
 </sup> Recent studies have looked into the genetic basis of susceptibility to HSP.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]
 </sup> It is known that the HLA-B34 and HLA-DRB1∗01 alleles are associated with HSP patients.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
  <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]
 </sup> Nevertheless, approximately 50% of the patients with HSP have been infected with upper respiratory tract infections and have been reported to be associated with streptococci, adenovirus, parvovirus, and mycoplasma.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
  <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
  <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]
 </sup> Since HSP occurs mainly after an upper respiratory tract infection, it is relatively more frequent in late autumn, winter, and spring when these infections are common, compared with summer.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
  <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
  <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]
 </sup> However, there have been no studies using national health big data showing a direct relationship between HSP and various infectious diseases. In South Korea, HSP is a relatively common disease, but reports on the overall developmental patterns in children and adolescents in recent years are lacking, and only studies that investigate its epidemiology in individual hospitals are available.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]
 </sup> Direct comparison between the prevalence of HSP and the incidence of respiratory and enteric infections in South Korea have not been reported.
</p>
