<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Apparent viral extinctions and reinvasions might alternatively arise from cryptic, enzootic circulation of viral lineages, with periodic detection driven by fluctuating incidence in bat populations or inconsistent surveillance effort through time. Indeed, a variety of factors have been suggested to alter VBRV incidence in bats or spillover to humans or livestock, including temperature and precipitation associated with El Niño oscillations, changes in prey availability or quality, and age-structured transmission [
 <xref rid="RSPB20191527C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20191527C39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>–
 <xref rid="RSPB20191527C41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Here, phylogeographic signals of international viral spread, temporal structuring of viral clades and statistical evidence for prolonged absences of each virus lineage at different time points make cryptic viral persistence unlikely. Moreover, VBRV disappeared from the entire Caribbean coast of Costa Rica in 2008, suggesting an extinction over a large geographical scale which lasted at least 10 years (electronic supplementary material, figure S1). Given the characteristic clinical signs of rabies in cattle (hind limb paralysis, rapidly followed by death), it is unlikely that outbreaks would be completely unnoticed over a decade if they had occurred. An important consequence of extinction–reinvasion dynamics is that environmental or demographic factors alone cannot directly trigger spillover by increasing bat population density, reducing immunity or altering feeding behaviour since the virus will often not be locally present to respond to these potential drivers. Increases in transmission might instead be explained by environmentally or anthropogenically driven increases in bat dispersal that connect VBRV-free to nearby VBRV-infected populations [
 <xref rid="RSPB20191527C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. For example, seasonal births create pulsed availability of susceptible vampire bats, but few studies have detected seasonal spillover to livestock [
 <xref rid="RSPB20191527C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20191527C39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20191527C42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20191527C43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Our findings reveal that birth pulses will only be important in times and places when the virus is present or if they promote mixing of infected and uninfected colonies. Consistent with the latter possibility, seasonal spatial expansions of VBRV have been attributed to annual expulsions of maturing male bats from maternity roosts [
 <xref rid="RSPB20191527C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].
</p>
