<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20">SMARCA2 (also named BRM) is one of two mutually exclusive ATPase subunits of the evolutionary highly conserved BAF chromatin remodeling complex (also known as the SWI/SNF complex), which has been shown to be involved in regulation of gene expression, cell cycle control and tumorigenesis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup>. Interestingly, the human lung adenocarcinoma cell line, A549, used in our study does not express the other ATPase subunit, SMARCA4 (or BRG1)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup>. Loss or mutation of SMARCA4 seems to be a relatively frequent event during tumorigenesis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>
 </sup> and SMARCA2 can at least partially compensate for the loss of SMARCA4
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup>. Suffice to say that by using A549 cells we could study the role of SMARCA2 specifically. We were unable to generate A549 SMARCA2 CRISPR knockout cells as cell proliferation was inhibited, which agrees with previous reports
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>
 </sup>. However, with transient knockdown we found that SMARCA2 depletion decreased the ability of IFN-treated A549 cells to establish an antiviral state. This is in agreement with previous findings that the BAF complex is required for induction of a subset of IFN-α-inducible genes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>
 </sup>, although in these studies SMARCA4/BRG1 was the focus. Surprisingly, however, MxA expression is unaffected by SMARCA2 depletion, suggesting that reduced MxA antiviral function is due to the absence of one or more SMARCA2-regulated factors. Flow cytometry experiments support this by demonstrating that SMARCA2 depletion leads to an elevated number of cells positive for both viral antigen (NP) and MxA in IFN-pretreated A549 cells. These results also provide strong support to the findings of Xiao and colleagues that additional ISGs are required for full MxA activity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup> and further show that these ISGs are probably regulated by SMARCA2. Alternatively MxA may interact with SMARCA2, although this is unlikely as neither SMARCA2 nor any other BAF component was identified as an MxA-interacting candidate in our mass spectrometry analysis. Also, SMARCA2 is a nuclear protein unlike MxA
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
