<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Some limitations of this study should be acknowledged. First, the imported CHIKV cases used in this analysis were only from laboratory confirmed individuals and therefore did not include infected persons who were asymptomatic or suffered only mild symptoms and thus did not seek medical advice. Second, the data by countries of acquisition were only publicly available for annual imported cases from 2013 to 2017. Therefore, we could not provide the spatiotemporal distribution of imported CHIKV cases by countries across the whole study period. We were also unable to calculate monthly incidence rates (numbers of imported cases over overseas arrivals) for each particular country over the study period, as the latter set of data were not publicly available. Third, the impact of ENSO could result in varying climate conditions in different parts of the world. Using aggregated data on monthly imported CHIKV cases from all source countries in the study could not fully reveal the associations between ENSO behaviours and imported CHIKV cases. Future studies may address the problem by using the imported CHIKV cases by countries or by a group of countries where they have the same weather conditions when the data are available. Additionally, future studies should investigate whether there are differences in the effects of different ENSO events, such as El Niño and La Niña, on local CHIKV transmission in endemic countries. The overall trend of increased number of CHIKV imports suggests that Australia remains at risk of a CHIKV outbreak. The patterns of importation we observed for Australia are likely to be mirrored in other countries that are non-endemic for CHIKV and have strong travel links with the countries of acquisition identified here. Australian health authorities have acknowledged the increasing risk of local CHIKV outbreaks, particularly in North Queensland, through the development of the Queensland Chikungunya Management Plan in 2014 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007376.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>].
</p>
