<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The most common pathologic viruses in infancy include respiratory syncytial virus (RSV), parainfluenza virus (PIV), adenovirus (AdV), influenza virus (InfV), human metapneumovirus (hMPV), and less so coronavirus (CoV), rhinovirus (RhV), and bocavirus (BoV) (Tregoning and Schwarze 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2010</xref>; Hammond et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2007</xref>; Chong et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2009</xref>). RSV remains the most prevalent and most severe of the neonatal LRTI’s (Coffin 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2005</xref>; Hammond et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2007</xref>; Chong et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2009</xref>; Chang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2009</xref>; Fitzgerald 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2011</xref>). Studies indicate that 20–67 % of children less than 1 year of age will be infected by RSV, with infection rates up to 95 % by age 2 years (Tregoning and Schwarze 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2010</xref>; Hammond et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2007</xref>; Fitzgerald 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2011</xref>; Johnson et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2007</xref>). PIV commonly occurs within the first 6 months of life with 50 % of patients affected by the first year of life (Hammond et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2007</xref>). Recently updated diagnostic technologies, including multiplex polymerase chain reaction (PCR) methods, have offered more accurate and faster diagnostic methods allowing appropriate treatments and patient management. Importantly, PCR for DNA viruses and reverse transcriptase PCR (RT-PCR) for RNA viruses also have allowed identification of viruses which are difficult to culture, such as hMPV and BoV, allowing better delineation of multi-agent respiratory viral infections (Tregoning and Schwarze 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2010</xref>). The most common synchronously occurring respiratory viruses are RSV and RhV (Tregoning and Schwarze 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2010</xref>; Chong et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2009</xref>; Garcia et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2010</xref>). In the last decade, hMPV, BoV, CoV, and RhV are increasingly recognized as causes of lower respiratory viral infections in children (Hustedt and Vazquez 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2010</xref>). Together, hMPV and BoV account for approximately 13 % of previously undiagnosable acute respiratory infections (Hustedt and Vazquez 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2010</xref>). Relative incidence and mean age at diagnosis for infantile respiratory viral infections in the United States are summarized in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">17.1</xref>. 
</p>
