<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0110">By this time, through various studies, it is evident that to infect humans, SARS-CoV-2 uses ACE2, which is the same receptor used by SARS-CoV for infecting human cells [
 <xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. A recent study showed that the expression of ACE-2 in kidney cells is similar to that in the lungs, esophagus, small intestine, and colon [
 <xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>]. It has been suggested that the kidneys serve as an essential target organ for SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="bb0270" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>] and the SARS-CoV-2 virus [
 <xref rid="bb0195" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Previously published reports during the outbreak of SARS and MERS-CoV infections claim that ARI was observed in 15% cases with a high mortality rate of 60%–90%. However, in the case of COVID-19, low incidence (3%–9%) of ARI was observed in early reports to date [
 <xref rid="bb0275" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Recently, a study carried out on 193 patients with COVID-19, between January to February 2020 including 28 pneumonia patients (15 viral pneumonia and 13 mycoplasma pneumonia patients) concluded that proteinuria was observed in 59% cases, hematuria in 44%, elevated levels of blood urea nitrogen in 14%, and high serum creatinine levels in 10% cases, which is significantly worse as compared to the other pneumonia cases (
 <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). A univariate Cox regression analysis was carried out and found that all elevated factors were significantly linked with high mortality in COVID-19 patients [
 <xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>]. Also, it has been suggested that COVID-19 patients with developed ARI are at 5.3-times more risk of those without ARI and even much higher than those with comorbid chronic illnesses [
 <xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>]. Similarly, another study was carried out on 701 patients (367 men and 334 women) for the assessment of the prevalence of ARI in COVID-19 patients as well as for the evaluation of the relationship between abnormal kidney function markers and fatality in COVID-19 patients with a median age of 63 years. The study concluded that proteinuria and hematuria were found in 43.9% and 26.7% patients, respectively, whereas high plasma creatinine and blood urea nitrogen was observed in 14.4% and 13.1% patients, respectively at the time of admission to hospitals. In addition, data analysis has revealed that there is a significantly higher risk for in-hospital death of patients with renal complications [
 <xref rid="bb0265" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Moreover, the same study concluded that the prevalence of renal complications during hospital admission as well as the development of ARI during hospitalization in COVID-19 patients, is high and is associated with high in-hospital mortality [
 <xref rid="bb0265" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>].
</p>
