<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The disease was first reported in 2012 in the Middle East and since then multiple introductions to the human population have occurred from the dromedary, the only known animal reservoir of MERS-CoV (
 <xref rid="ref156" ref-type="bibr">Wernery et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref75" ref-type="bibr">Jordan et al., 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref110" ref-type="bibr">Paden et al., 2018</xref>). The majority of the 2,374 cases reported up to date (
 <xref rid="ref161" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization, 2019</xref>) have occurred in Saudi Arabia (1983 cases). The disease has been reported in 27 countries from different continents with most of them associated with recent travel to the Arabic peninsula (
 <xref rid="ref112" ref-type="bibr">Park et al., 2019</xref>). Person-to-person transmission has been well documented especially in health care workers and family members and may lead to large outbreaks with a significant impact on public health as observed in the Middle East and Korea (
 <xref rid="ref80" ref-type="bibr">Ki, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref99" ref-type="bibr">Mo and Fisher, 2016</xref>). People from any age can be infected with the virus, although the majority of cases have been observed in adults (
 <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 2017</xref>). Clinical features range from asymptomatic or mild to severe disease and death (
 <xref rid="ref174" ref-type="bibr">Zumla et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref118" ref-type="bibr">Rabaan, 2017</xref>). Symptoms may include respiratory illness that can lead to acute respiratory distress syndrome (
 <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Assiri et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref98" ref-type="bibr">Memish et al., 2013</xref>) and digestive symptoms including nausea, vomiting, and diarrhea (
 <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 2017</xref>) with some patients developing renal failure (
 <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Bermingham et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref75" ref-type="bibr">Jordan et al., 2018</xref>). The case fatality rate worldwide is 34.6%, while in Saudi Arabia it is 37.5% (
 <xref rid="ref161" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization, 2019</xref>).
</p>
