<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Optimizing HCV screening holds the key to disease identification, yet effective screening has persistently been a challenge in the United States. A recent study of screening strategies identified that reflex nucleic acid testing after a positive serum antibody result was cost‐effective and adequately sensitive for viremia.
 <xref rid="hep41480-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">12</xref> However, identifying who to screen has been challenging. Most current screening recommendations until recently had called for both risk‐factor and cohort‐based approaches. The American Association for the Study of Liver Diseases (AASLD) currently recommends one‐time screening for individuals with associated risk behaviors (PWID or with intranasal drug use) or risk exposures (hemodialysis, unregulated parenteral exposure, health care workers with exposure to HCV‐infected blood, children born to HCV‐infected women, prior recipients of transfusions or organ transplants, and history of incarceration) and for those in the birth cohort (born between 1945 and 1965), regardless of the presence of risk factors.
 <xref rid="hep41480-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">13</xref> However, due to the expanding young population and the anticipated aging of the baby boomer generation, the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force is in the process of expanding its recommendations to screen to all adults aged 18 to 79 years, a screening recommendation that is distinct from other organizations, and potentially cost‐effective compared with birth cohort screening.
 <xref rid="hep41480-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="hep41480-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">15</xref> Although a monumental step forward, this one‐time screen runs the risk of missing individuals screened before engaging in high‐risk behaviors. Additionally, targeted micro‐elimination may be an effective strategy to reduce HCV disease burden on those at high risk for disease, and has been reported to be cost‐effective in the U.S. prison population,
 <xref rid="hep41480-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">16</xref> men who have sex with men, injection drug use, and maternal‐to‐child transmission.
 <xref rid="hep41480-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="hep41480-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">18</xref> Although guideline recommendations are important for guiding practices, they will ultimately need to be adopted by both practitioners and medical societies.
</p>
