<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Over the past 50 years, Alaska's average annual temperature has increased by 1.6
 <bold>°</bold>C which is more than twice the rate of the rest of the United States. Observed effects include an increase in precipitation, and length of frost-free growing season, a decrease in sea ice, glacial and snow cover, an increase in sea level, an increase in river outflow, changes in plant and vegetation cover with an increase in shrubs and vascular plants and change of tundra and permafrost to a wetlands ecology, and a decrease in permafrost in some regions with consequential damage to built infrastructure (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0001">1</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0002">2</xref>). These changes are of concern to those residents of Alaska who depend on the local environment for water, key subsistence food wildlife species, such as terrestrial and marine mammals (caribou, reindeer, moose, muskoxen seal and walrus), fish, water fowl and plants) for their health and cultural well-being. Climate and weather also affect the distribution, and risk of many helminthic, bacterial, viral and protozoan parasitic diseases as well as insect and ectoparasitic vectors affecting both animals and humans. However, the interaction of hosts, vectors, pathogens and the environment are poorly understood in the Arctic (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CIT0003">3</xref>). While most pathogens are species-specific, that is, restricted to either certain animals or humans, some, i.e. the zoonoses, are transmissible from animals to humans, often through close contact with animals or food products derived from these animals. Zoonotic infectious diseases may be climate sensitive. Warmer temperatures may allow a parasite to survive in the environment for longer periods, increase an insect replication cycle, allow an infected host animal species to survive winters in larger numbers, increase in population and expand their range of habitation, thus increasing the opportunity for transmission of the infection to humans. Subsistence hunting, gathering, food preparation and preservation methods may also place people at risk for acquiring zoonotic infections. Known zoonotic diseases that occur in Alaska include brucellosis, toxoplasmosis, trichinellosis, giardiasis, cryptosporidiosis echinococcosis, rabies and tularemia. This article reviews what is known about the potentially climate-sensitive zoonotic infectious diseases of concern in Alaska, identifies common gaps in our knowledge of these pathogens and recommends actions that will begin to address earlier disease detection, research and prevention and control of these potential zoonotic disease threats in the context of a changing Alaskan climate.
</p>
