<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F9" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>FIG 9</label>
 <caption>
  <p>G protein-coupled receptor kinases (GRKs) are required for IAV replication. (A) A549 cells were transfected with siRNA targeting 
   <italic>GRK2</italic>, 
   <italic>GRK3</italic>, 
   <italic>GRK5</italic>, or 
   <italic>GRK6</italic> for 48 h. The levels of mRNA of the indicated gene in the cell lysates were determined by qRT-PCR and standardized to those of the scrambled siRNA-treated cells. ***, 
   <italic>P &lt; </italic>0.001. (B) A549 cells were treated with siRNA targeting 
   <italic>GRK2</italic>, 
   <italic>GRK3</italic>, 
   <italic>GRK5</italic>, or 
   <italic>GRK6</italic> for 48 h, and cell viability was measured by using the CellTiter-Glo assay. (C) HEK293T cells were treated with siRNA targeting 
   <italic>GRK2</italic>, 
   <italic>GRK3</italic>, or 
   <italic>GRK5</italic> or with scrambled siRNA for 12 h and then transfected with the corresponding Myc-tagged protein expression construct for 36 h. Whole-cell lysates were collected and analyzed by Western blotting with a mouse anti-Myc mAb. Separately, A549 cells were transfected with 
   <italic>GRK6</italic> siRNA or scrambled siRNA for 48 h, and whole-cell lysates were collected and analyzed by Western blotting with a rabbit anti-GRK6 pAb. (D) A549 cells were transfected with siRNA targeting 
   <italic>GRK2</italic>, 
   <italic>GRK3</italic>, 
   <italic>GRK5</italic> or 
   <italic>GRK6</italic> or with scrambled siRNA for 48 h and then infected with AH05 (H5N1) virus (MOI = 0.1). Supernatants were collected at the indicated time points, and virus titers were determined by means of plaque assays on MDCK cells. *, 
   <italic>P &lt; </italic>0.05; **, 
   <italic>P &lt; </italic>0.01; ***, 
   <italic>P &lt; </italic>0.001. (E) BiFC analysis to examine the interaction between FFAR2-VN and GRK2-VC, GRK5-VC, or GRK6-VC in HeLa cells. Cotransfection of vector VN and vector VC served as a negative control.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="JVI.01707-19-f0009" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
