<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0135">An American biotechnology company Gilead Sciences developed the antiviral drug Remdesivir (GS-5734) against Ebola virus [
 <xref rid="bb0520" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. It is also found to be effective in treating single-stranded RNA viruses such as pneumovirus, Lassa fever virus, Junin virus, Nipah virus, Hendra virus, and the CoVs [
 <xref rid="bb0525" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0530" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]. Remdesivir exerts broad-spectrum antiviral activity and showed beneficial results in SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV induced respiratory infections. It has been recommended to administer to SARS-CoV-2 infected patients in United States of America, Europe, and Japan, where physicians found the beneficial results [
 <xref rid="bb0535" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>]. But it is not yet approved by the drug regulators for treating the patients who are suffering from SARS-CoV-2. Gilead has started the clinical trials for the potential treatment of COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="bb0540" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. Remdesivir is a prodrug and is metabolised to its active form GS-441524, which is a nucleotide analogue inhibitor of RNA-dependent RNA polymerases [
 <xref rid="bb0545" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. It interferes with the viral RNA polymerase activity and further inhibits the viral exoribonuclease involved in proofreading and ultimately causes the deprivation of viral RNA production [
 <xref rid="bb0550" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]. Remdesivir was tested in clinical isolates of SARS-CoV-2 in vitro, where it exhibited significant antiviral activity. Further, it was also tested in combination with Chloroquine and found to be effective against COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="bb0395" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. However, the data available is limited on Remdesivir and further studies need to be conducted to prove its essential role in treating COVID-19 along with its drug-drug interactions and contraindications.
</p>
