<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In cases where a cluster of patients with similar symptoms presents itself, there can be an investigation to look for epidemiological clues of the link between the cases. Additional information is garnered from the use of viral genome sequencing, making it possible to track origins of outbreaks, and to estimate how much of the observed human disease is attributable to foodborne infection by computerized linking of epidemiologic data to aligned viral genomic sequences (
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">Verhoef et al., 2011</xref>). However, often the original source or evidence of it being food- or waterborne cannot be found, which means that outbreaks often are merely registered. Of the 941 viral disease outbreaks reported as foodborne in the joint ECDC-EFSA surveillance report of 2015, only 9.1% had robust evidence of food- or waterborne transmission (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Eurosurveillance editorial team, 2015</xref>). Routine application of genotyping of HAV in newly diagnosed cases quadrupled the number of cases in which food was the most likely source of infection a 3 year enhanced surveillance study in The Netherlands, but this is not commonly done (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">Petrignani et al., 2014</xref>). In an investigation of 1794 food- and waterborne outbreaks in Korea, roughly 75% of the outbreaks reported in schools and public restaurants were attributed to an unknown origin (
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Moon et al., 2014</xref>). Availability and costs of molecular testing combined with sequencing, additional to the limited success of virus detection in food products, are likely further limiting their use in food and water surveillance. This is demonstrated by the fact that formal confirmation of a viral outbreak associated with food- and waterborne transmission still requires extensive epidemiological analysis or confirmation of a virus in the infected individual, or both (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">ESFA, 2016</xref>). However, due to the increase of genomic information of viruses, sequence data is increasingly used to support and strengthen outbreak investigations. Nevertheless, the surveillance programs for these viruses in the human food chain is limited, in contrast with the American CDC
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn01">1</xref>
 </sup> and the European ECDC
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn02">2</xref>
 </sup> surveillance programs for bacteria and parasitic pathogens causing food- and waterborne diseases (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Deng et al., 2016</xref>) and does not have widespread coverage. As an example, to comply with European food safety regulations, shellfish, a well-known source of foodborne pathogens, need to be tested for enteric bacteria. However, it has been well documented that shellfish that pass quality control based on bacterial counts may still contain human pathogenic viruses (
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">Rodriguez-Manzano et al., 2014</xref>). To be able to recognize food- waterborne viral disease outbreaks and stop underestimation of its disease burden there should be innovations in the current foodborne surveillance system.
</p>
