<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Sulfonamides constitute an important class of drugs containing many types of pharmacological agents with broad-spectrum bacteriostatic activity. Sulfonamides interrupt the synthesis of folic acid, interfering with the dihydropteroate synthase and dihydrofolate reductase enzymes of bacteria (and protozoa) and inhibiting bacterial growth [
 <xref rid="B179-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>,
 <xref rid="B180-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">180</xref>]. The sulfadoxine-pyrimethamine combination is used in some settings for the treatment of uncomplicated malaria in pregnant women, and it is the only drug currently recommended for intermittent preventive therapy during pregnancy [
 <xref rid="B181-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">181</xref>]. A study investigated the effect of this combination on HIV replication. Experiments were conducted in vitro using peripheral blood mononuclear cells, MT-2 cells, MT-4 cells, and a latently infected cell line named U1. The results showed that the sulfadoxine-pyrimethamine combination combined with antiretroviral therapy significantly enhanced HIV replication in MT-2 cells, while it inhibited HIV replication in peripheral blood mononuclear cells [
 <xref rid="B23-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Moreover, recent studies have demonstrated that sulfonamides can act on latent herpesviruses, such as EBV and Kaposi sarcoma herpesvirus (KSHV) [
 <xref rid="B182-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">182</xref>,
 <xref rid="B183-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">183</xref>]. Furthermore, a work conducted by Angius and colleagues reported that sulfonamide antibiotics suppressed the KSHV latent state in permanently infected lymphoma cells [
 <xref rid="B183-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">183</xref>]. This result suggested that sulfonamides might play a potential role in clearing KSHV-infected lymphoma cells. Since conventional antiherpes drugs are able to slightly suppress viral replication in the lytic phase but do not clear the latent state, the finding of potential new small molecules, such as sulfonamides drugs, could initiate a promising program of studies on both oncogenic and degenerative diseases, in which herpesvirus latency is suspected to be involved [
 <xref rid="B184-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">184</xref>,
 <xref rid="B185-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">185</xref>,
 <xref rid="B186-microorganisms-08-00085" ref-type="bibr">186</xref>].
</p>
