<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par41">miRNAs are a class of endogenous small non-coding RNAs (20–25 nt) and play significant roles in the post-transcriptional regulation of target genes in multiple metabolic processes by cleavage of target mRNAs or repression of mRNA translation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Similar to the siRNA pathway, the miRNA pathway starts with cleavage of the dsRNA into small dsRNA, which is loaded into the RISC and serves as a guide-strand to detect and degrade cognate viral ssRNA. The differences between the siRNA and miRNA pathways are the cellular compartments and the effector proteins involved in the pathways [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The transcription, cleavage and processing of siRNA mainly take place in the cytoplasm while the miRNA genes are transcribed into primary miRNA (pri-miRNA) by host polymerase II and are processed into precursor miRNA (pre-miRNA) by Drosha in the nucleus. The pre-miRNA is then exported into the cytoplasm and further processed into a mature miRNA by Dicer-1 and is loaded into Ago-1 of the RISC, which guides the binding of the complex to complementary mRNA for degradation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. The antiviral role of miRNAs in mosquitoes has not been reported as it was assumed that RNA viruses do not generate miRNAs. This is because of a lack of access to the Drosha for miRNA processing in the nucleus as replication of most RNA viruses occurs in the cytoplasm [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. However, miRNAs from a number of arbovirus mosquito vectors have been shown to play a critical role in modulating host genes to control viral infection. For example, several miRNAs specific for innate immunity and multiple metabolic processes required for viral replication and dissemination were modulated during ZIKV [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>], DENV [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>] WNV [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>] and ONNV infections [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>].
</p>
