<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par42">Besides the well-studied siRNA pathway, recent studies have highlighted the importance of the piRNA pathway in the mosquito antiviral response [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Interestingly, the piRNA pathway can mount an antiviral defense with a defective siRNA pathway, indicating the redundancy of RNAi-mediated antiviral immune responses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. In contrast to siRNAs, the biogenesis of piRNAs does not require Dicer and the size distribution of piRNAs is around 24–30 nt [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. In 
 <italic>Drosophila</italic>, the biogenesis of piRNAs involves three Piwi proteins, including the P-element induced wimpy testis (Piwi), Aubergine (Aub) and Argonaute 3 (Ago3), to form a piRNA-induced silencing complex (piRISC) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. The biogenesis starts with the primary processing pathway, which is the synthesis of primary piRNA pool from single-stranded precursors. The primary piRNAs can be associated with the Aub and Piwi protein. Interestingly, the primary pool of piRNAs can undergo an amplifying process known as the ‘ping-pong’ cycle to further amplify the Aub-bound piRNAs to refine the piRNA pool. This amplification process serves to ensure an efficient piRNA-mediated silencing of target RNA [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. The presence of virus-specific piRNAs was detected in 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> during CHIKV infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>] and in SINV infected 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> cells [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Deep sequencing data reported the presence of SFV-derived piRNAs and silencing of PIWI 4 protein resulted in increased SFV replication and virion production, suggesting the importance of the piRNA pathway in antiviral immunity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>].
</p>
