<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recent studies also demonstrated that some antibiotics potentially inhibit 2019-nCoV replication. Anderson et al. (preprint) recently developed the first bat genome-wide RNA interference (RNAi) and CRISPR libraries and identified MTHFDI as the critical host factor for viral infections [
 <xref rid="B190" ref-type="bibr">190</xref>]. MTHFDI is a trifunctional enzyme involved in the one-carbon (C1) metabolic pathway, participating in the cellular production of purine, dTMP, and methyl groups [
 <xref rid="B191" ref-type="bibr">191</xref>]. Anderson et al. demonstrated that purine synthesis activity of MTHFDI is an essential activity for viral replication, making MTHFDI a potential target for developing antiviral drugs [
 <xref rid="B190" ref-type="bibr">190</xref>]. They further explained that an MTHFD1 inhibitor, carolacton, restricts replication of influenza virus, mumps virus, Melaka virus, Zika virus, and, most importantly, 2019-nCoV [
 <xref rid="B190" ref-type="bibr">190</xref>]. Carolacton is a secondary metabolite derived from the mycobacterium 
 <italic>Sorangium cellulosum</italic>. It is a macrolide ketocarbonic acid. Carolacton has been studied as an antibacterial compound against biofilms of pathogenic 
 <italic>Streptococcus mutans</italic> and growth of pathogen 
 <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic> [
 <xref rid="B192" ref-type="bibr">192</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B193" ref-type="bibr">193</xref>]. It has no toxic effect against eukaryotic cells [
 <xref rid="B194" ref-type="bibr">194</xref>]. It has recently been identified as a potent inhibitor of MTHFDI, and its mechanism of action is presumably due to the ability of carolacton to bind with MTHFDI [
 <xref rid="B194" ref-type="bibr">194</xref>]. More research is needed to validate the mechanism of action, efficacy, and safety of carolacton as a possible treatment for COVID-19. On the other hand, ivermectin is originally a medication used to treat parasite infestation. It comprises different analogs of avermectin: 22,23-dihydroavermectin B1a and 22,23-dihydroavermectin B1b, at a ratio of 4 : 1 [
 <xref rid="B195" ref-type="bibr">195</xref>]. They are macrolide antibiotics isolated from the fungus 
 <italic>Streptomyces avermitilis</italic>. It has reportedly stopped HIV-I proliferation by inhibiting interaction of the retroviral integrase protein with adapter protein (importin), responsible for the nuclear protein import cycle [
 <xref rid="B196" ref-type="bibr">196</xref>]. Caly et al. reported that ivermectin successfully inhibited 2019-nCoV 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> but the mechanism of action is unclear [
 <xref rid="B197" ref-type="bibr">197</xref>]. Since ivermectin is an approved drug, it shows great potential as a therapeutic agent for COVID-19. 
 <italic>In vivo</italic> work or clinical trials need to be done to confirm its efficacy and safety for treatment against COVID-19. Potential drugs for COVID-19 are summarized in 
 <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.
</p>
