<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Next, we sought to determine if 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> infection of BMEC was accompanied by alterations in endothelial permeability. 
 <italic>In vitro</italic> endothelial integrity studies were performed using between 10
 <sup>3</sup> or 10
 <sup>6</sup> copies of ZIKV at MOI 0.01 or 10, respectively. In addition, 10
 <sup>7</sup> PFU of ZIKV were employed for 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> BBB permeability assays. We did not observe any disruption of the endothelial barrier function as determined by FITC-dextran flux after ZIKV-U, ZIKV-PR, or ZIKV-H infection, even at MOI of 10 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>). Nevertheless, we did not perform Electronic Cell-Substrate Impedance Sensing (ECIS) studies that allow real-time measurements of TEER for detection of short-lived permeability changes. In addition, permeability assessments were performed only at 2 dpi, when the changes in TJ protein expression were the most pronounced but were not continued at later stages of infection. These factors constitute limiting aspects of our 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> ZIKV model. Similar lack of endothelial permeability changes was reported for the ZIKV-U and a ZIKV strain from Brazil (PE243) (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Papa et al., 2017</xref>). These strains also productively infected primary human BMECs but without enhancing endothelial permeability. One caveat of that report was that endothelial permeability was assessed by the translocation of FITC-tagged BSA (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Papa et al., 2017</xref>), i.e., a method suitable to detect only very substantial permeability changes. In our study, we used different molecular weight FITC-tagged dextran molecules (10 kDa and 20 kDa) that were smaller than BSA (67 kDa). Thus, our assay was more sensitive, strengthening the conclusion that ZIKV is able to reach the CNS without disrupting the BBB. Instead, invasion of the CNS by ZIKV might be associated with endothelial transcytosis (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Papa et al., 2017</xref>).
</p>
