<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>However, the population struggles to comply with certain measures such as the closing of shops and the travel limitations. In fact, 92.4% of people active in West Africa work in the informal sector as trading and businesses, transport and restoration. These jobs are not subject to any national legislation and are not subject to any social protection [
 <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. All these people are forced to go to work every day in order to support their families and in the absence of robust economic packages to help them to stay at home physical distancing measures are doomed to failure. Otherwise million people in West Africa lack access to clean water and communal water and sanitation facilities are not always accessible which makes certain hygiene measures recommended to fight against the SARS-CoV-2 epidemic difficult. For example, 63% of people in urban areas, or 258 million people, lack access to handwashing [
 <xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. According to UNICEF data from 2017, the majority of people did not have basic handwashing facilities available at home. Only Ghana, Mali, Mauritania and Nigeria were above the global average of 60% of people with access to basic facilities. The situation was particularly bad in small countries such as Benin, Gambia, Guinea-Bissau, Liberia and Togo where at least three-quarters of the population had no handwashing facility at home [
 <xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Quality masks are not always accessible to the population. Some countries (Senegal, Nigeria and Mali) have invested in the production and local distribution of masks [
 <xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. However, the quality of these masks is often lacking. For example, in Benin buying a quality mask in pharmacies subsidised at 30 cents is still too expensive for some people. People then flock to masks sold on the street at half price, with a single layer of fabric and without any filter [
 <xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. The average size of households in certain West Africa countries is estimated at 7.2 members per household which mean that several family generations live and interact under the same roof (concession) [
 <xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. This makes it difficult to comply with self-containment and distancing measures. The difficulty in applying all these preventive measures could be a factor favouring the spread of the virus in these countries.
</p>
