<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30">Using state of the art phylogeographic methods, this study analysed the movement and dissemination of the major HCV subtypes in Cyprus (1a, 1b, and 3a) to answer two questions: what are the global geographic patterns of HCV transmission into and out of Cyprus and what are the patterns of transmission among the general and high-risk populations within Cyprus? To frame the both elements of the work within a maximally comprehensive global context, the analyses included all sequences available on public databases as references. Given the large number of sequences analyzed, statistical phylogeography was used due to the long computation time required for Bayesian methods. One of the potential limitations in this study is the lack of available HCV sequences from many geographic locations. To improve the analytical capacity of the existing data, inferences were performed in 2 different partial genomic regions (Core-E1 and NS5B) and merged migration events from both regions. This study highlights the complexity of HCV dissemination within, into, and out of Cyprus. While the movement of HCV does not follow a specific pattern like the HIV-1 epidemic, Cyprus, as an island at the geographic crossroads of three continents, is a powerful place to begin unraveling the intricacies of the patterns of global HCV transmission. This complexity likely reflects the different routes for HCV epidemic transmission and dispersal, including blood and blood product transfusions, iatrogenic transmissions, and drug injections. Because these transmission mechanisms are often associated with different subtypes, phylogeographic analysis is a powerful tool for mapping how and where HCV subtypes are transmitted. As more sequences are made available from wider geographic regions, phylogeographic analysis will more effectively describe the complex patterns of the dissemination of HCV and other viral diseases so more informed approaches can be made to combatting these epidemics.</p>
