<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0040">The recent characterization of the closest known genetic relative of the human HCV [
 <xref rid="bib0420" ref-type="bibr">84
  <sup>••</sup>
 </xref>] and enteric Aichi viruses in canine samples [
 <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0425" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>] point to dogs as a potential zoonotic origin of these now common human infections. The direction of transmission (dogs to human or human to dogs) cannot be revealed by genetic similarities alone and future viral discoveries may reveal yet closer relatives of these and other human viruses [
 <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. As sampling of animal viruses increases, a complex network of past cross-species transmission will likely emerge. For example until recently only a single species of astrovirus (HAstV) and of parvovirus (B19) were known to infect humans. Viral survey in human have now shown that multiple genera and species within the 
 <italic>Parvoviridae</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib0230" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0430" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0435" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0440" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0445" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>] and 
 <italic>Astroviridae</italic> [
 <xref rid="bib0450" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0455" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0460" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>] can infect humans. Multiple lineages of these viral families can also be found in pigs and other animals [
 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">15•</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] (
 <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> ). Distinct phylogenetic clades within a viral family also include viruses found in different mammal hosts, likely reflecting cross-species transmission of parvoviruses [
 <xref rid="bib0465" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0470" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0475" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0480" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>] (as was recently documented for the feline to canine CPV2 transfer in the 1970s) and of astroviruses (
 <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>) [
 <xref rid="bib0450" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0455" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0460" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>].
</p>
