<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">Acute myocardial injury, as evidenced by elevated levels of cardiac biomarkers or electrocardiogram abnormalities, was observed in 7–20% of patients with COVID-19 in early studies in China
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. The presence of myocardial injury was associated with a significantly worse prognosis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>. In the initial report of 41 patients with COVID-19 in Wuhan, 5 patients had myocardial injury with elevated levels of high-sensitivity cardiac troponin I (&gt;28 pg/ml), and 4 of these 5 patients were admitted to an ICU
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>. In a multicentre cohort study of 191 patients with COVID-19, 33 patients (17%) had acute cardiac injury, of whom 32 died
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. In a subsequent study of 416 patients hospitalized with COVID-19, 82 patients (20%) had evidence of cardiac injury, which was associated with a 5-fold increase in the need for invasive mechanical ventilation and an 11-fold increase in mortality
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>. Of note, cardiac injury was found to be an independent risk factor for in-hospital mortality
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>. Another study confirmed this finding and reported that the rate of death in patients with elevated levels of cardiac troponin T was 37.5%, whereas, in patients with underlying cardiovascular comorbidities plus elevated levels of cardiac troponin T, it was almost double (69.4%)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup>. Furthermore, a subsequent study demonstrated that markers of myocardial injury were predictive of the risk of in-hospital mortality in patients with severe COVID-19 (ref.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup>). The area under the receiver operating characteristic curve of the initial cardiac troponin I level for predicting in-hospital mortality was as high as 0.92. Other predictors of myocardial injury include advanced age, presence of comorbidities and high levels of C-reactive protein.
</p>
