<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1">
 <sec>
  <title>Background</title>
  <p id="Par1">Lassa fever, killing thousands of people annually, is the most reported viral zoonotic disease in Nigeria. Recently, different rodent species carrying diverse lineages of the Lassa virus (LASV) in addition to a novel Mobala-like genetic sequence were detected within the country. Here, screening 906 small mammal specimens from 11 localities for IgG antibodies and incorporating previous PCR detection data involving the same populations, we further describe arenavirus prevalence across Nigeria in relation to host species and geographical location.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p id="Par2">Small mammals were trapped during the period 2011–2015 according to geographical location (endemic and non-endemic zones for Lassa fever), season (rainy and dry seasons between 2011 and 2012 for certain localities) and habitat (indoors, peridomestic settings and sylvatic vegetation). Identification of animal specimens from genera such as 
   <italic>Mastomys</italic> and 
   <italic>Mus</italic> (
   <italic>Nannomys</italic>) was assisted by DNA sequencing. Small mammals were tested for LASV IgG antibody using an indirect immunofluorescence assay (IFA).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Results</title>
  <p id="Par3">Small mammals were infected in both the endemic and non-endemic zones for Lassa fever, with a wider range of species IgG-positive (
   <italic>n</italic> = 8) than those which had been previously detected to be PCR-positive (
   <italic>n</italic> = 3). IgG-positive species, according to number of infected individuals, were 
   <italic>Mastomys natalensis</italic> (
   <italic>n</italic> = 40), 
   <italic>Mastomys erythroleucus</italic> (
   <italic>n</italic> = 15), 
   <italic>Praomys daltoni</italic> (
   <italic>n</italic> = 6), 
   <italic>Mus baoulei</italic> (
   <italic>n</italic> = 5), 
   <italic>Rattus rattus</italic> (
   <italic>n</italic> = 2)
   <italic>, Crocidura</italic> spp. (
   <italic>n</italic> = 2), 
   <italic>Mus minutoides</italic> (
   <italic>n</italic> = 1) and 
   <italic>Praomys misonnei</italic> (
   <italic>n</italic> = 1)
   <italic>.</italic> Multimammate mice (
   <italic>Mastomys natalensis</italic> and 
   <italic>M. erythroleucus</italic>) were the most ubiquitously infected, with animals testing positive by either PCR or IgG in 7 out of the 11 localities sampled. IgG prevalence in 
   <italic>M. natalensis</italic> ranged from 1% in Abagboro, 17–36 % in Eguare Egoro, Ekpoma and Ngel Nyaki, up to 52 % in Mayo Ranewo. Prevalence according to locality, season and age was not, however, statistically significant for 
   <italic>M. natalensis</italic> in Eguare Egoro and Ekpoma, localities that were sampled longitudinally.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p id="Par4">Overall, our study demonstrates that arenavirus occurrence is probably more widely distributed geographically and in extent of host taxa than is currently realized. This expanded scope should be taken into consideration in Lassa fever control efforts. Further sampling should also be carried out to isolate and characterize potential arenaviruses present in small mammal populations we found to be seropositive.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
