<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0040">Corona viruses (CoVs) are the largest group of viruses that can infect mammals and various other species. The name “coronavirus” is derived from Latin, where the meaning is “crown” or “wreath”. The name refers to the characteristic appearance of virions that have a lipid envelope studded with club-shaped fringe projections creating an image resembling solar corona [
 <xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. These viruses belong to the order 
 <italic>Nidovirales</italic> which include the family 
 <italic>Coronaviridae</italic>, and subfamily 
 <italic>Orthocoronavirinae</italic>. The 
 <italic>Orthocoronavirinae</italic> are further subdivided into four groups based on the genera that include the alpha, beta, gamma, and delta CoVs. The viruses from 
 <italic>nidovirales</italic> order possess a 5′ capped, enveloped, non-segmented, single-strand positive-sense RNA viruses with unusually large RNA genome∼30 kb with typical sizes ranging from 80 to 120 nm [
 <xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. These viruses are generally characterized by their spikes that protrude from their surface and follow unique replication strategy [
 <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The RNA genome in CoVs is composed of six to ten open reading frames (ORFs) that encode the replicase proteins and four main structural proteins that include spike, membrane protein, envelope protein, and nucleocapsid proteins, all of which are encoded within the 3′ end of the viral genome. Where the spike proteins are involved in the viral entry and in determining host range, both membrane and envelope proteins are crucial for virus assembly. Besides, some CoVs also contain a gene which encodes hemagglutinin esterase (HE), which is a glycoprotein of approximately 60–65 kDa. This enzyme possesses an acetyl-esterase activity that disrupts sialic acid receptors that present in the host cell surface and help in the invasion and attachment that enhance the infectious properties of the virion. However, the more precise function of HE is still enigmatic [
 <xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The presence of helically symmetrical nucleocapsid is a distinct feature of CoVs, which is infrequent among positive-sense RNA viruses, but far more usual for negative-sense RNA viruses [
 <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. CoVs infect a substantial number of species and cause wide diseases such as pneumonia, hepatitis, enteritis, encephalomyelitis, nephritis, reproductive diseases, sialodacryoadenitis, polyserositis, and various other disorders [
 <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The first member of CoV strain was identified in poultry flocks that caused infectious bronchitis and it was reported in 1930s [
 <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].
</p>
