<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In the two decades since WNV became established in the US, limited progress has been made in controlling transmission of the virus. Thus, renewed investment in understanding the fundamental aspects of endemic WNV transmission and innovative research directions are needed to mitigate the public health burden of WNV for the next 20 years. For example, advances in virus sequencing and phylogenetic analysis (comparing genetic variation over space and time) have transformed our ability to map the spread and evolution of viruses [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Such “genomic epidemiology” approaches, for example, were recently deployed to reconstruct the emergence of Zika virus in the Americas [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] and revealed the sources causing the yellow fever outbreaks in Brazil [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. For WNV, virus genomics played a central role in uncovering how the virus emerged and became endemic in a new region after its introduction in the US (e.g., [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]), and more detailed studies may identify transmission networks and source areas of potential reemergence to be targeted during future interventions [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. While powerful, these phylogenetic tools require technical expertise and computing resources that make them out of reach for some groups. To fill this need, Nextstrain (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nextstrain.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">nextstrain.org</ext-link>) [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008042.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] was created to provide everyone the ability to explore pathogen spread and evolution using genomic epidemiology. In this review, we use Nextstrain to uncover key epidemiological and evolutionary processes during the emergence and establishment of WNV in the Americas (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nextstrain.org/WNV/NA" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">nextstrain.org/WNV/NA</ext-link>) and discuss collaborative opportunities to advance this work for future outbreak control.
</p>
