<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The creation of the Joint FAO/IAEA Division in 1964 was a significant event in assisting developing countries to improve their livestock and agriculture to enable greater productivity and improved food security. Since that time, the Joint Division has sought to introduce innovative technologies, based on nuclear techniques that will allow farmers to provide safe, healthy food in often harsh environment and in the face of serious infectious diseases that compromise productivity. Among the earliest efforts in animal health specifically to seek answers to the problems caused by infectious diseases were the efforts to develop irradiated vaccines. Interest in this technology was eventually superseded by alternative technologies that were deemed likely to provide solutions more rapidly. These techniques, employing various molecular methods involving recombinant antigens, have not delivered as expected and attention is once again focusing on the potential of irradiated vaccines. Complementary to control of diseases is the need to be able to accurately identify infected animals quickly and simply. Nuclear techniques were in the forefront of a number of highly sensitive and specific tests for diagnosing infections. Although for the most part such tests using radioisotope labels have been replaced, the tests that have been developed rely in their inception on the radiolabeling methods that preceded them, so they are still very much nuclear-related. Opportunities have arisen recently to consider the use of stable isotope analysis in understanding the migration of wild birds and their involvement in the spread of Highly Pathogenic Avian Influenza, and these safe, non-radioactive isotopes may even be of use in diagnosis of disease or in typing pathogenic organisms. The latter could be of use when considering the storage and sequestration of pathogens, for use as a method of identifying the source of an accidental release, or a deliberate act of bioterrorism. This review highlights the various nuclear techniques that have been employed in the field of animal health and highlights the potential for further research and development.</p>
