<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par60">From the perspective of a rheumatologist, there are concerns regarding compelling actions and future preparedness for facing COVID-19 and its after effects. We have always considered rheumatic musculoskeletal diseases (RMDs) as conditions that are precipitated when a genetically susceptible host encounters specific environmental triggers. Our firsthand knowledge of the host-environment interaction in RMD until now was limited to epidemiological studies related to small infectious outbreaks like the Chikungunya epidemic which has given us insights into various post-infectious RMD manifestations. The COVID-19 pandemic, in contrast to these relatively small occurrences, is a mammoth event in the history of humankind. The infection has spread across all large countries affecting people from all age groups. Such an infection is likely to have long-term consequences, and RMDs could be a major fallout given the quantum of immune dysregulation the virus is known to cause [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. There are already reports of post-COVID-19 autoimmunity with an increase in the incidence of Kawasaki disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] and Guillain-Barré syndrome [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. In a global attempt to curb this pandemic, a variety of drugs with varying mechanisms of action are being tried. While some of these drugs are known to cause adverse effects mimicking RMDs and other autoimmune diseases, there is a lack of information for the majority of them. There are also concerns regarding the right approach to treat existing rheumatic diseases and about the outcome of infection among those on immunosuppressive agents. This and many more challenges faced by patients with RMDs and their care providers during the COVID-19 pandemic are being addressed by the Global Alliance Registry and the COVID-19 database of the European League Against Rheumatism (EULAR); mining these data will serve as a guide in the future for the management of patients with RMDs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].
</p>
