<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Determining the age of SIV would provide perspective on the spread of the virus among African primate species and the subsequent zoonoses. Knowing the age may also have implications for the evolution of pathogenicity and virulence in HIV. AIDS-like symptoms have rarely been observed in non-human African primates infected with SIV 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000377-Ling1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000377-TrainaDorge1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. Historically, this lack of disease was attributed to the codivergence and coevolution of SIV and their primate hosts over millions of years 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000377-Muller1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref> (we use the term codivergence instead of cospeciation, because codivergence considers phylogenetic congruence irrespective of species classification, whereas cospeciation implies that SIVs infecting different primates can be classified as species complexes). Although there is significant correspondence between the SIV and host phylogenies, detailed analysis of this relationship suggested that a preferential host switching model, in which cross-species transmissions of SIV are more likely to occur between closely related primates, could account for this correspondence 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000377-Charleston1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. Furthermore, subsequent analysis of SIV infecting various African green monkey species, thought to be exemplary of codivergence, demonstrated a lack of evidence for host-virus codivergence 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000377-Wertheim1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. In addition, the codivergence hypothesis does not account for the observation that SIV is geographically confined and naturally infects only African primates. Finally, even with biologically unrealistic assumptions about a molecular clock, Sharp 
 <italic>et al.</italic> were unable to push the tMRCA of all SIV beyond 2500 years 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000377-Sharp1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. If it were demonstrated that SIV has evolved in a clock-like manner, then we might be able to accurately determine the age of SIV.
</p>
