<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
 <label>Figure 1</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Induction of interferons (IFN) and signaling by the type I and III IFN receptors. The presence of microbial or self nucleic acid in the cytosol or within the endosomal compartment activates pattern recognition receptors (PRR)s. RNA activates retinoic acid-inducible receptor (RIG)-I in the cytosol and Toll-like receptor (TLR)3 and TLR7 in the endosomal compartment. These events trigger signaling pathways through the adaptor molecules mitochondrial antiviral signaling protein (MAVS), TIR-domain-containing adapter-inducing interferon-β (TRIF), and Myeloid differentiation primary response (MyD)88 leading to phosphorylation and activation of the TANK binding kinase (TBK)1, which in turn phosphorylates the transcription factors IFN regulatory factor (IRF)3 and IRF7. Whereas IRF3 is constitutively present, IRF7 is only expressed at low levels but may be secondarily induced by Type I IFN. Phosphorylation of IRF3 and IRF7 leads to homodimerization, nuclear translocation, and expression of Type I IFNs (IFNα and IFNβ) and type III IFNs (IFNλ) acting on neighboring cells with type I and III IFN receptors, respectively. Type I IFN binds to IFNα/β receptor composed of IRFNAR1 and IFNAR2, whereas type III IFN binds to the IFNλ receptor composed of IFNLR1 and IL10Rβ. These events activate the downstream receptor-associated Janus-associated kinase (JAK)1 and tyrosine kinase (TYK)2 and subsequent tyrosine phosphorylation of STAT1 and STAT2. These activated transcription factors together with IRF9 form the heterotrimeric transcription factor IFN-stimulated gene factor (ISGF)3 complex which binds to IFN-stimulated regulatory elements (ISRE) in DNA. In addition, STAT1 homodimers form the IFN-γ-activated factor (GAF) complex which binds to γ-activated (GAS) sequences. Altogether, these transcription factors induce a broad spectrum of IFN-stimulated genes (ISG)s that mediate the complex “antiviral state” of IFNs.</p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="fimmu-11-01606-g0001" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
