<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fn-group>
 <fn id="d33e432">
  <label>☆</label>
  <p id="npar0005">Pre-Report of the French National Academy of Medicine written in April 2020 by a working group.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="fn0005">
  <label>1</label>
  <p id="npar0010">After several weeks of containment, since it appears that the first two criteria for moving to phase II have been met and that the last two are in the process of being met, it was decided, barring any incident in recent days, to begin phase II on May 11.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="fn0010">
  <label>2</label>
  <p id="npar0015">A contact is defined as a face to face beyond a few minutes.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="fn0015">
  <label>3</label>
  <p id="npar0020">Also known as SARS-CoV-2, or Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome CoronaVirus-2.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="fn0020">
  <label>4</label>
  <p id="npar0025">The expression “social distancing” should be avoided as it has negative connotations. The term “physical distancing” is preferable and often used abroad. In the following, no qualifier will generally be added to the term “distancing”.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="fn0025">
  <label>5</label>
  <p id="npar0030">Widely implemented by France</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="fn0030">
  <label>6</label>
  <p id="npar0035">A notice of home confinement in a region is stipulated in case of doubling of affected subjects every three to five days and following the recommendations of representatives of the State and local authorities. The trigger for the recommendation to move from home confinement to a “slowing the spread” board is a steady decrease in the number of new cases reported, nationally or regionally, for 14 days (i.e., an incubation period) and the opportunity to test for symptoms of COVID-19 on all individuals in need of care.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="fn0035">
  <label>7</label>
  <p id="npar0040">These phase I measures include, among others:</p>
  <p id="npar0045">closure everywhere of public gathering places (schools, restaurants, museums, etc.;</p>
  <p id="npar0050">closing of dining halls, but leaving them open for delivery and take-away services;</p>
  <p id="npar0055">teleworking for employees whose presence on company premises is not essential;</p>
  <p id="npar0060">limiting national or international travel;</p>
  <p id="npar0065">cancellation or postponement of meetings and mass gatherings;</p>
  <p id="npar0070">recommend or require home containment in hot spots where transmission is intense;</p>
  <p id="npar0075">wearing of masks (to be made mandatory away from home);verification of public adherence to physical distance notices, compliance incentives.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="fn0045">
  <label>9</label>
  <p id="npar0085">11 For the US, the recommendation is to increase the current capacity from 2.8 intensive care beds per 10,000 adults to 5–7 beds per 10,000 adults in the event of an outbreak or other emergency, taking into account regional variations.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="fn0050">
  <label>10</label>
  <p id="npar0090">For the US, the recommendation is to increase them from 3 per 10,000 adults to a target of 5 to 7 ventilators per 10,000.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="fn0055">
  <label>11</label>
  <p id="npar0095">Estimated for the US to be at least 30 per 10,000 adults.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="fn0060">
  <label>12</label>
  <p id="npar0100">In the US, current CDC guidelines recommend a seven-day isolation period.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="fn0065">
  <label>13</label>
  <p id="npar0105">As defined by the CDC in the United States</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="fn0070">
  <label>14</label>
  <p id="npar0110">Defined as a face-to-face of a few minutes without a mask and at less than one metre away.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="fn0075">
  <label>15</label>
  <p id="npar0115">For example, a member of a large family may wish to recover in a hotel room that has been refurnished rather than to risk infecting family members.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="fn0080">
  <label>16</label>
  <p id="npar0120">The “hospital hotels” whose experimentation in 2017 was not finally supported by the CNAM could have been of great service from the start of the pandemic.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="fn0085">
  <label>17</label>
  <p id="npar0125">Facial masks will be all the more effective in slowing the spread of COVID-19 if they are widely used, as is the case in some countries that have successfully managed their epidemics, such as South Korea and Hong Kong. WHO has recommended that the public use facemasks in the event of a severe influenza pandemic. However, personal protective equipment should be reserved for health professionals in case supplies are insufficient. For this reason, in public spaces, in the event of a shortage of so-called surgical masks, the public should wear non-medical, cloth facemasks, whose design guidelines are published and which consumers may be able to make themselves 
   <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="fn0100">
  <label>20</label>
  <p id="npar0140">Case of Singapore which, on 11 April 2020, had to initiate phase I after successfully containing the spread (Phase II) for almost two months.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="fn0105">
  <label>21</label>
  <p id="npar0145">OPECST published on March 30 a note on possible treatments and ongoing clinical trials, including the European trial, DisCoVeRy, under the guidance of the REACTing network: “Coronavirus epidemic — Update on treatments, vaccines…”</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="fn0120">
  <label>24</label>
  <p id="npar0160">A recent, as yet unpublished study in New York shows that 20% of the sampled population (1000 people) is seropositive, while in New York State the rate is much lower at around 3%.</p>
 </fn>
</fn-group>
