<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">TCM is composed of many antiviral active components including alkaloids, flavonoids, glycosides, volatile oil, phenols, etc. Polyphylla saponin-I has antiviral effects on the influenza A virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Ginsenosides has a protective effect on the lethal infection of a Hemagglutinating virus of Japan (HVJ), as well as has antiviral activity on the hepatitis A virus, coxsackievirus B3, enterovirus 71, and human rhinovirus 3 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Ginsenoside Rg3 attenuates hepatitis B virus DNA replication through the degradation of TRAF6/TAK1 and the inhibition of JNK/AP-1 signaling [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], and Rg3 inhibits hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection via restoring the HCV-induced dynamin-related protein 1-mediated aberrant mitochondrial dynamics [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Glycyrrhizic acid is effective against infection of coxsackievirus A16 and enterovirus 71 while Glycyrrhizin has an inhibition effect on the replication of the SARS-associated virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Radix Glycyrrhizae restricts infection of the human respiratory syncytial virus through preventing viral attachment, internalization, and by stimulating the secretion of IFN [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Flavonoids are a class of ingredients with good anti-inflammatory and antiviral activities and widely found in varieties of TCM and natural medicine. Houttuynia cordata is a traditionally used medicinal plant for the treatment of pneumonia, and flavonoids are one of the main antiviral bioactive constituents including quercetin and isoquercetin. Houttuynia cordata Thunb (HCT) blocks HSV infection through inhibition of NF-κB activation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. HCT water extract exhibited significant inhibitory effects on SARS-CoV and regulates immunity through stimulating the proliferation of mouse splenic lymphocytes, increases the proportion of CD4
 <sup>+</sup> and CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells, and the secretion of IL-2 and IL-10 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. HCT alleviates H1N1-induced acute lung injury in mice by inhibition of influenza neuraminidase activity and Toll-like receptor signaling. Baicalin, a flavonoid, inhibits the influenza virus by modulating NS1-mediated cellular innate immune responses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Baicalein triazole inhibits respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) -infection and prevents pulmonary airway inflammation through the activation of the IFN signaling pathway. Moslae herba flavonoids attenuate IAV-induced barrier dysfunction by inhibiting NOX4/NF-κB/MLCK pathway [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].
</p>
