<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are several limitations to this study. Although the Indiana Network for Patient Care covers multiple health systems, it is not a true population-based cohort and does not have complete coverage of Indiana. However, it is the nation’s oldest, largest, and most comprehensive regional health information exchange, and its inclusion of multiple payers including Medicare and Medicaid makes it a unique data source to follow a large, diverse population longitudinally. This is in contrast to other studies that are limited to single payers or health systems.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="zoi190254r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
  <xref rid="zoi190254r38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>
 </sup> In addition, although Indiana has relatively high rates of alcohol use disorders and alcoholic cirrhosis–associated mortality, the state is not an outlier compared with other states, which further enhances the generalizability of the findings. We used diagnostic and procedural codes to identify cirrhosis and other factors that can be associated with misclassification errors. However, when possible, we used codes that had been previously validated. Furthermore, limiting the cohort to only incident cirrhosis diagnoses (with a 1-year run-in period) does not represent the entire population with cirrhosis. Indeed, the observed low transplant rate likely reflects that most patients with cirrhosis receive a diagnosis shortly after entering the health care system. However, specifying the cohort in this way allows for the identification of incident diagnoses more accurately than including all cirrhosis diagnoses, and it provides a more robust way to assess outcomes. Notably, the mortality estimates in this study are similar to those of prior natural history studies of cirrhosis.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="zoi190254r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
 </sup> Other strengths of the study include the large sample size, broad geographic representation throughout Indiana, and linkage to the Social Security death index, which supports accurate mortality estimates.
</p>
