<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par49">This may be the reasons why LNVs have been continuously isolated from 12 species of mosquitoes belonging to four genera in different geographical and climatic regions in Australia, during the last 30 years [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. However, in China the LNV has only been isolated from a long and narrow region restricted from 31°N to 48°N, where belongs to the north temperate zone with cold climate, less rain and low species diversity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. What is more, after transmission from Australia to China, the genotype 1 LNV population gradually adapted to the local natural environment and evolved new strains with regional genetic characteristics. The newly evolved LNVs (genotypes 2 and 3) contain 20 amino acid mutations compared with the initial LNVs (genotype 1) in the cell attachment protein (VP10), which altered the structure and electrostatic presentation influencing the binding properties to host vectors. This might be one of the reasons why the newly evolved LNVs (genotyp 2 and 3) were restricted to a relative narrow range of vectors and habitat. Compared with genotype 1 and genotype 2, the genotype 3 which located in the central part of China contains 2 unique amino acids, which were identical with genotype 1 but different from genotype 2,indicating that this lineage is at evolutionary transitional position which preserved the genetic information of the original LNV population and also evolved novel genetic information sites during spread to new locations. When compared with original LNV population, the genotype 2 LNVs in Xinjiang province contained the the maximum numbers of amino acid mutations thus it was the the most divergent lineage and formed a independed evolutionary branch. The genetic informative sites of the entire LNVs population confirmed its transmission path from north to south, and then from east to west.
</p>
