<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The FDA-approved library was purchased from Selleck Chemicals (USA), which consists of 1430 drugs. Prior to use, 4 μL of each 10 mM drug was transferred into 156 μL maintenance medium in a new 96-well plate for preparing a 250 μM stock solution. Firstly, 86 μL of F81 cells (2.5 × 10
 <sup>4</sup> cells/well) were pretreated with 4 μL of each stock solution to obtain a final concentration of 10 μM for 1 h, then the drug-treated F81 cells were infected with 10 μL CPV at a multiplicity of infection (MOI) of 0.076. Normal and the CPV SD6-infected F81 cells containing a final concentration of 0.1% DMSO were used as positive and negative control, respectively. Cell viability was examined by TransDetect
 <sup>®</sup> Cell Counting Kit (TransGen Biotech, Beijing, China) at 40 h postinfection. Optical density (OD) at 450 nm wavelength was collected using a SYNERGY H1 microplate reader (BioTek Instruments Inc., Winooski, VT, USA). OD
 <sub>450</sub> values of wells without CPV infection served as a positive (cell) control indicating 100% CPE inhibition, and OD
 <sub>450</sub> values of wells with SD6 infection served as a negative (virus) control indicating 0% CPE inhibition [
 <xref rid="B14-viruses-11-00742" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. The percentage inhibition was calculated using the formula: percentage CPE inhibition = (OD
 <sub>450</sub> of drug treated cells − OD
 <sub>450</sub> of negative control)/(OD
 <sub>450</sub> of positive control − OD
 <sub>450</sub> of negative control) × 100 [
 <xref rid="B20-viruses-11-00742" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-viruses-11-00742" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. All drug plates were set-up in duplicates for primary screening, and drugs show greater than 20% CPE inhibition from the primary screen were used for second round of screening. The further validation of identified drugs was conducted in triplicates, and drugs show greater than 50% CPE inhibition were used for further analysis.
</p>
