<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Chikungunya virus (CHIKV) is an emerging mosquito-borne alphavirus. Since 2004, CHIKV caused several large outbreaks in Africa, the Indian Ocean islands, Asia, Europe, and the Americas[
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. In an urban transmission cycle, humans are the major hosts and mosquitoes of the genus 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> are vectors[
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. Although chikungunya fever is usually benign, prolonged polyarthralgia may lead to considerable disability in a significant proportion of patients[
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Atypical manifestations include meningoen-cephalitis, myocarditis, respiratory, renal and hepatic failure[
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>,
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Laboratory diagnosis is accomplished by detection of CHIKV RNA and/or detection of IgM and IgG antibodies[
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. Few data exist regarding the clinical characteristics of CHIKV infections in the transplant population[
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>-
 <xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. In one case series of SOT recipients from Colombia with confirmed CHIKV infection, most patients had a benign clinical course with no severe complications[
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. A study from Brazil analyzed clinical symptoms of chikungunya in four kidney transplant recipients. The clinical picture was typical, none of patients developed any severe manifestations and all recovered fully with no complications[
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Another Brazilian study showed similar results. SOT recipients with CHIKV infection seem to have a clinical presentation and course similar to those seen in the general population, with no apparent damage to the graft. Among liver transplant recipients, elevation of liver enzymes was not observed, and there was no clinical impact on graft function. Among kidney transplant recipients, only a few had a slight increase of serum creatinine levels, without acute kidney failure or dialytic support[
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Although reports on the chikungunya in the transplant population are rare, the transplant community must be reminded that the risk of CHIKV infection should be considered in deceased organ donor candidates recently returned from travel to endemic areas[
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>].
</p>
