<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0030">According to the research by the team of academician Zhong Nanshan, the incubation period of COVID-19 ranges from 0 to 24 days, with a median incubation period of 3 days. The population is generally susceptible to infection or infectious during the incubation period [
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. COVID-19 is highly contagious among humans, and older individuals and people with underlying diseases are especially affected. Based on the published data, the median patient age was 47–59 years in COVID-19 (similar to SARS and MERS), and 54.3−58.1% of patients were male in COVID-19 (the male-to-female ratio of 1:1.25 in SARS, and 1.82:1 in MERS) [
 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Some studies have reported that 1.2–2% of COVID-19 patients were children (6% in SARS and 2% in MERS) [
 <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>]. According to the available data, children appear to be at lower risk for COVID-19 than adults and children are less symptomatic with less fatality, which is concordant to earlier epidemic outbreaks of SARS-CoV respectively [
 <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. On March 4, 2020, the national health commission issued the diagnosis and treatment program of COVID-19 pneumonia (trial seventh edition) [
 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], which indicated that transmission through respiratory droplets and close contact was the main transmission route of SARS-CoV-2. The virus can be spread by aerosol when an individual is exposed to a high concentration of aerosolized virus for a long time in a relatively closed environment. Since SARS-CoV-2 can be isolated from feces and urine, attention should be paid to aerosol or contact transmission from feces, urine or environmental pollution; other avenues of spread are not entirely clear [
 <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. A paper published in the 
 <italic>Lancet</italic> argues that transmission through the conjunctiva of the eye cannot be ignored [
 <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Other studies have suggested that there may be mother-to-child transmission (vertical transmission) [
 <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In summary, to date, the transmission route of SARS-CoV-2 has not been completely clarified, and relevant protective measures and attention should not be reduced [
 <xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Regardless of the exact mechanisms by which SARS-CoV-2 was naturally selected, the ongoing surveillance of pneumonia in humans and other animals is clearly of utmost importance. According to a report published in 
 <italic>Nature</italic> on March 20, 2020, 30%–60% of newly infected people have no symptoms or mild symptoms; however, their ability to spread the virus is not low, and covert coronavirus infections could be seeding new outbreaks. There is growing evidence that some infected people are highly contagious when their symptoms are mild or asymptomatic [
 <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Understanding the proportion of cases of asymptomatic or mild illness is important for us to understand the cause of this particular pandemic, as indicated by Michael Osterholm, director of the center for infectious disease research and policy at the University of Minnesota [
 <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].
</p>
