<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several nucleic acid vaccines are currently under development for COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="B83-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Recombinant viral vector vaccines utilize the backbone from a genetically modified virus, such as adenoviruses, poxviruses, and Vesicular stomatitis virus, having insertion sites for genes of the target pathogen, which becomes expressed intracellularly in the host upon vaccination [
 <xref rid="B83-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. This approach may encounter the generation of immunity toward the vector that could hinder the vaccine specific response after boost vaccination. Further, human adenoviruses (hAds) can circulate at high frequency, thus pre-existing immunity may reduce vaccine efficacy. In this regard, chimpanzee adenoviruses can elicit a similar or superior immunogenicity to hAds. Imophoron at Bristol University is developing an adenovirus-based SARS-CoV2 VLP vaccine (ADDomer© VLP, Bristol, UK) at present in preclinical assessment which presents rapid development and self-adjuvant characteristics without cold-storage requirement (
 <uri xlink:href="https://www.bristol.ac.uk/news/2020/april/codid-19-vaccine-platform.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.bristol.ac.uk/news/2020/april/codid-19-vaccine-platform.html</uri>, accessed on June 2020). In the UK, the Jenner Institute and the Oxford vaccine group (
 <uri xlink:href="https://covid19vaccinetrial.co.uk" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://covid19vaccinetrial.co.uk</uri>, accessed on June 2020) has produced the ChAdOx1 nCOV-19 vaccine that employs the replication-deficient chimpanzee adenoviral vector isolate Y25. This vectored vaccine encodes a codon-optimized full-length S-protein with a human tPA (tissue plasminogen activator) leader sequence. Preclinical studies have already demonstrated that it is immunogenic in mice by eliciting a strong humoral and not Th2 dominated cell-mediated response. A single vaccination was effective in rhesus macaques. A reduced viral load was observed in bronchoalveolar lavage and respiratory tract of vaccinated animals respect to controls [
 <xref rid="B86-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. This vaccine has recently entered a Phase I/II clinical trial, already involving 900 volunteers aged 18–55 that received 5 × 10
 <sup>10</sup> viral particles (clinicaltrials.gov: NCT04324606). Vaccination with a lipid nanoparticle-encapsulated mRNA-1273 encoding SARS-CoV2 S-protein developed by Moderna (NCT042283461) [
 <xref rid="B83-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>,
 <xref rid="B85-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>] prevented viral replication in the lungs of mice challenged with CoV2. Neutralizing titers in Phase 1 trial participants receiving 2 µg and 100 µg doses were consistent with those protective in the mouse challenge model. Phase I/II trials are currently ongoing (
 <uri xlink:href="https://investors.modernatx.com/news-releases/news-release-details/moderna-announces-positive-interim-phase-1-data-its-mrna-vaccine/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://investors.modernatx.com/news-releases/news-release-details/moderna-announces-positive-interim-phase-1-data-its-mrna-vaccine/</uri>, accessed on June 2020). Adenovirus type 5 vector expressing S-protein (Ad5-nCoV) from CanSino Biological (NCT04313127) is in Phase I. Participants with pre-existing Ad5 neutralizing antibodies exhibited lower humoral and cellular responses. BNT162 (produced by BioNTech, Mainz, Germany) employed a modified RNA delivered in a lipid nanoparticle [
 <xref rid="B83-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. The bacTRL platform exploited by Symvivo Corporation (Canada) utilizes engineered probiotic 
 <italic>Bifidobacterium longum</italic> to deliver CoV2 S-protein into intestinal cells (NCT 04334980) [
 <xref rid="B83-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Among the other candidates, INO-4800 produced by Inovio Pharmaceuticals (NCT04336410) is based on a DNA plasmid encoding S-protein [
 <xref rid="B87-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. Preclinical studies have assessed immunization of mice and guinea pigs with INO-4800 measuring antigen-specific T cell responses, functional antibodies that neutralize the SARS-CoV2 infection, and block binding of spike glycoprotein to ACE2 receptors. Presence of SARS-CoV2 antibodies in the lungs was also demonstrated [
 <xref rid="B88-ijms-21-05145" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. Shenzhen Geno-Immune Medical Institute has generated dendritic cells (DCs) (LV-SMENP-DC in Phase 1, NCT042276896) and artificial APCs (aAPCs) modified with a lentiviral vector expressing a synthetic minigene based on parts of selected viral proteins (pathogen-specific aAPC, Phase I, NCT04299724).
</p>
