<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34">The intervention to improve IPT completion was part of a wider continuous quality improvement effort at scale in Uganda following the roll out of the consolidated guidelines for prevention and treatment of HIV in Uganda. The intervention was implemented as a national QI collaborative since January 2019 and covered all regions of Uganda. The intervention was led by the AIDS Control Program, Ministry of Health (MoH) while USAID RHITES N-Acholi provided QI technical support. The PEPFAR implementing partners (IPs) rolled out the collaborative activities for IPT through the regional and district coaches. Regional and district coaches were identified among public health workers by IPs and District Health Teams with a basic selection criterion being public health worker with knowledge or previous experience in QI for HIV. The coaches were trained in QI and their roles followed by monthly coaching visits to health facilities to support improvement activities for IPT among other interventions such as viral load suppression and retention. The coaches supported sites quality improvement teams (QITs) to identify and address gaps for IPT and review progress in addressing barriers to the completion of INH. document improvements in initiation and completion. Depending on context and root cause analysis, different changes for improvement were tested to address gaps for IPT. Quarterly review meetings were held for IPs and regional coaches by MoH to share experiences and spread learning. District learning sessions were organized by IPs for health facilities. We present outcomes from a prospective longitudinal cohort of patients initiated on IPT in January 2019. The purpose of this study was to document retention, adherence, development of active TB disease, possible side effects and completion. For study purposes, the primary outcomes were IPT completion defined as having received and consumed a 6-month course of INH and the development of active TB disease.</p>
