<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pntd.0007625.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0007625.g003</object-id>
 <label>Fig 3</label>
 <caption>
  <title>
   <italic>Post-mortem</italic> examination of fulminant yellow fever cases performed by ultrasound-guided minimally invasive autopsy (MIA-US) and conventional autopsy (CA).
  </title>
  <p>(A-D) 
   <italic>Kidneys</italic>: nephromegaly detected by US (A); H&amp;E slide, at low magnification, showing kidney samples collected by MIA-US (B); gross examination of kidneys showing edema and icterus (C); microscopy showing mesangial cell hyperplasia and acute tubular necrosis (D). The inset shows typical 
   <italic>Aspergillus</italic> hyphae invading an interstitial arterial vessel in the renal parenchyma, diagnosed in the left kidney from one case, only in the MIA-US sample (reticulin stain). (E-H) 
   <italic>Lungs</italic>: lung hepatization detected by US (E); H&amp;E slide, at low magnification, showing lung samples collected by MIA-US with foci of pneumonia (arrows) (F); gross exam of lungs with red hepatization and edema (G); microscopy of lungs (H) showing alveolar hemorrhage (HE, left), invasive pulmonary aspergillosis (Grocott stain, right top) and pneumonia with colonies of Gram-positive cocci (H&amp;E, right bottom). (I-L) 
   <italic>Heart</italic>: a concentrically hypertrophic left ventricle detected by US (I); H&amp;E slide, at low magnification, showing heart samples collected by MIA-US (J); gross exam of a heart exhibiting left ventricle hypertrophy (arrow) and subendocardial hemorrhages (K); microscopy showing hypertrophic cardiomyocytes and interstitial edema (L). (M–P) 
   <italic>Spleen</italic>: an image of MIA-US at the moment of needle insertion in splenic mass (arrow) to collect post-mortem samples (M); H&amp;E slide, at low magnification, showing spleen samples collected by MIA-US (N); gross exam of the spleen showing diffuse congestion on the cut surface (O); microscopy revealing splenitis, hemorrhage, and lymphoid hypoplasia (P). (Q-T) 
   <italic>MIA-Us of a pregnant woman</italic>: the US image shows the uterus, placenta, amniotic fluid and fetus (Q); H&amp;E slide, at low magnification, showing the placental samples collected by MIA-US (R); histology of placenta with maternal decidua and villi (S); the fetal liver sampled by MIA-US showing ischemic damage and extramedullary hematopoiesis (T).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pntd.0007625.g003" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
