<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The evolutionary genomics of OROV in the Americas appears to be driven by a complex combination of factors that are associated with viral life cycle and the nature of the OROV genome. Phylogenetic analysis of the three OROV genome segments reveals different evolutionary histories, with a stronger topological concordance between the M and L segments, than between those two segments and the S segment. Many of these incongruencies likely represent the different evolutionary histories of each segment, arising from reassortment. The occurrence of reassortment events appears to be relatively common for OROV in the Americas and may be currently underestimated because (i) there are likely to be many undiscovered OROV lineages and (ii) the virus likely circulates widely in one or more as-yet-uncharacterized reservoir populations in the Amazonian forest. Although we found similarities between the M and L segment phylogenies, a previous study of the Bunyamwera group has suggested linkage between the L and S segments (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>), and different reassortment patterns have been reported for other bunyaviruses such as La Crosse virus and snowshoe hare virus (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). The reassortment of OROV is in line with the observation of naturally occurring reassortant viruses (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>), a phenomenon that has been linked to the coinfection of hosts or arthropod vectors. The latter provide a good opportunity for reassortment to occur, since an infected vector can feed on a second vertebrate host infected with a distinct viral strain within a 2- to 3-day time window and become coinfected (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). On a broader scale, reassortment events could play a crucial role in the evolution of bunyaviruses in general, and it has been suggested that an increasing number of the recently described species are reassortants (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>).
</p>
