<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For infection, 6000 Vero E6 cells were seeded in flat-bottom 96-well plates in 100 µL medium, incubated overnight, and then topped to 180 µL medium. ZIKV stocks were diluted to the desired multiplicity of infection (MOI). In the “virion treatment” setting, virus was then mixed (1:1) with serially titrated breast milk samples and incubated for 10 min at room temperature. Then, cells were inoculated with 20 µL of the mixture in triplicates (resulting in a 10-fold lower concentration of the milk samples) and incubated for 2 h before the medium was replaced by fresh medium. Alternatively, cells were first incubated with the breast milk samples for 10 min, followed by ZIKV inoculation (“cell treatment”). Two days post infection, the flavivirus E protein content in the cells was quantified by cell-based immunodetection assay as described [
 <xref rid="B38-viruses-11-00591" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. To this end, the medium was removed, and the plates were washed with PBS once before fixing the cells with 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) for 20 min at room temperature. After aspirating PFA, cells were permeabilized by incubation with 100% ice cold methanol for 5 min, and again washed with PBS. Then, cells were incubated with the mouse anti-flavivirus protein E antibody 4G2 (Absolute Antibody #Ab00230-2.0, Redcar, Cleveland, UK) in antibody buffer (PBS containing 10% (
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>) FCS and 0.3% (
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>) Tween 20) at 37 °C. After 1 h, the cells were washed three times with washing buffer (0.3% (
 <italic>v</italic>/
 <italic>v</italic>) Tween 20 in PBS) before a secondary anti-mouse antibody conjugated with horseradish peroxidase (HRP) (Thermo Fisher #A16066, Waltham, MA, USA) was added and incubated for 1 h at 37 °C. Following four times of washing, the TMB peroxidase substrate (Medac #52-00-04, Wedel, Germany) was added and the reaction was stopped with 0.5 M H
 <sub>2</sub>SO
 <sub>4</sub> after 5 min of light-protected room temperature incubation. The optical density (OD) was recorded at 450 nm and baseline corrected for 650 nm using the VMax Kinetic ELISA microplate reader (Molecular Devices, San José, CA, USA). 
</p>
