<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>EHL–rFIX products have successfully decreased infusion frequency from twice weekly to every 10–14 days using fusion to Fc–IgG1 or albumin or PEGylation technologies 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
  <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
 </sup>; however, EHL–rFVIII products have only decreased infusions from about three to about two times per week 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>– 
  <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
 </sup>. Efforts are underway to understand why EHL–rFVIII products have not been more successful. Clearance of FVIII from the circulation occurs mostly in complex with von Willebrand factor (VWF); the half-life of VWF ranges from 4–26 hours, with an average of approximately 15 hours 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
 </sup>. The prevailing theory is that the half-life of VWF imposes an upper limit on FVIII half-life prolongation. Two recent studies evaluating the biochemical interaction between VWF and FVIII demonstrated that it was dependent upon the VWF D’D3 and FVIII C1 domains 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
  <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>
 </sup>. Preclinical studies are now assessing VWF D’D3 and/or FVIII protein modifications to enhance VWF binding or half-life 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
  <xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
 </sup>. All licensed EHL products recommend tailoring the dose to the individual patient’s pharmacokinetic response. Hence, for each individual patient, a particular product may not offer significant half-life extension and therefore may be less effective from a cost and convenience standpoint. However, EHL products might afford clinicians the ability to customize a patient’s dose and frequency for a higher goal factor trough that minimizes bleeding and maximizes compliance. Indeed, post-hoc analysis of rFVIII–Fc trials demonstrates improved bleeding rate with similar or increased physical activity 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>
 </sup> and improved joint arthropathy scores in patients treated with rFVIII–Fc either prophylactically or on demand 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
 </sup>. These benefits likely reflect higher troughs and improved compliance secondary to decreased infusion frequency with EHL products.
</p>
