<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Influenza vaccines and antiviral drugs are effective in preventing infection or ameliorating disease severity (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Vasileiou et al., 2017</xref>). However, influenza infection, as an acute respiratory disease caused by seasonal outbreaks and, periodically, pandemics of influenza viruses and accounting for up to 650,000 annual deaths globally (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization [WHO], 2018</xref>), remains a serious public health concern. This is partly due to the fact that current influenza vaccines can target only selected strains based on annual surveillance and prediction, which does not always match the circulating strains, leading to a sharp drop in vaccine efficacy (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">de Jong et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Nachbagauer and Krammer, 2017</xref>). Moreover, emergence of drug resistance strains of influenza A viruses (IAVs) reduces the effectiveness of the current anti-influenza therapies. The three clinically available classes of antivirals for treatment and prevention of influenza infections are the viral ion channel M2 blockers (amantadine and rimantadine), neuraminidase (NA) inhibitors (oseltamivir, zanamivir, peramivir, and laninamivir), and most recently the licensed baloxavir marboxil, which is an oral cap-dependent endonuclease inhibitor of influenza virus polymerase inhibitor (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Alves Galvao et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Alame et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Kashiwagi et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Heo, 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Noshi et al., 2018</xref>). However, high levels of resistance to M2 channel blockers and NA inhibitors have emerged, undermining the efficacy of these drugs (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Hata et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Samson et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">van der Vries et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Lackenby et al., 2018</xref>). Moreover, mutations responsible for reduced susceptibility of influenza A/H3N2 virus to baloxavir have been detected already (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Takashita et al., 2019</xref>). Therefore, the development of antiviral drugs with different mechanisms of action is urgently needed against influenza viruses.
</p>
