<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We propose trehalose as a practical and affordable safe treatment for the prevention and containment of COVID-19. Trehalose could potentially affect cellular organelles required for viral replication. We would recommend a large community trial comprising of healthy adults, healthcare workers, asymptomatic, and mild symptomatic COVID-19 patients (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). The Centers for Disease Control (CDC) has recently reported the transmission of SARS-CoV-2 during the presymptomatic stage of the infection; therefore, trehalose treatment as a prophylactic approach would be advisable (
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>). Family members of patients testing positive for COVID-19 will be recommended to undergo trehalose treatment and stay at home in self-quarantine, as the secondary attack rate of SARS-CoV-2 transmission within a household is 16.3% (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>) (
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>). Unlike adults, children have a low observed case rate of COVID-19. Children are mostly asymptomatic, or the symptoms are mild to require medical attention unless an underlying health-compromising condition exists (
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>). More recently, pediatric hospitals are confirming cases of children suffering from a severe Kawasaki-like disease related to COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>). This is a significant concern when countries are trying to reopen their education system, and the long term effects of SARS-CoV-2 infection are still unknown in children. Clinical studies on the oral supplementation of trehalose (100 g/day) for the improvement of vascular function has been carried out in healthy adults aged 50–77 years (
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>). Although trehalose has proven to be safe, it would be inappropriate or approached with caution when evaluating the efficacy of trehalose in seniors and the elderly, as a large number of this population suffer from chronic diseases. By treating healthy adults with trehalose, population-level resistance to the infection will block the chain of transmission. As a result of this treatment, the risk of transmission to seniors and medically compromised individuals will be drastically reduced as they are indirectly protected from the infection (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>) (
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>). Furthermore, trehalose can activate TFEB and could subsequently promote cross-presentation (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Therefore, trehalose could have another benefit to accelerate herd immunity against SARS-CoV-2, especially in the phase of encountering a second wave of COVID-19 cases. We believe that this treatment strategy can be more beneficial to countries that do not have the resources to conduct antiviral clinical trials.
</p>
