<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap position="float" id="t0010">
 <label>Table 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Attributes, advantages, and limitations of NERD.</p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text id="al0010">Table 2</alt-text>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th colspan="2">Major potential advantages of NERD for two test groups</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td>Significant correlation of drug having higher usage among patients with: NEGATIVE TEST for active SAR-CoV-2 coupled with POSITIVE TEST for antibodies (Option #1)</td>
    <td>Could reveal those drugs with PROTECTIVE or THERAPEUTIC POTENTIAL for Covid-19, with minimal adverse side effects.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Significant correlation of drug having higher usage among patients with: POSITIVE TEST for active SAR-CoV-2 (Option #2)</td>
    <td>Could reveal potential contraindications and warn of those drugs to AVOID during Covid-19 treatment.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">  </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">Additional potential advantages of NERD include</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">• Any knowledge of the pathogen itself or disease progression would not be needed because NERD would rely solely on real-time, real-world evidence for selecting drug candidates. Because of this natural process of drug selection, any selected drug candidates for repurposing would have a higher probability of success in phase 3–4 clinical trials or for compassionate use.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">• As testing of a population expands, the test population size could be orders of magnitude larger than possible in any clinical trial.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">• The predictive power of NERD would increase as the incidence of testing covers an increasingly larger percentage of the randomly selected general population.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">• The approach naturally incorporates its own inherent natural control group as a result of the diagnostic testing - namely, the negative-test group with positive antibody test.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">• A major advantage might be the ability to reveal combinations of drugs that could possess synergistic therapeutic potential. Potential combination drug treatments are extremely difficult to predict with virtual screening approaches.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">• Association with the positive-test group might indicate a drug that makes Covid-19-positive individuals more susceptible to developing serious morbidities. This would allow for more vigilance against pathogen exposure if the drug is medically necessary or in cessation of the drug if possible.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">• Unproven off-label drug therapies that could cause harm (such as during compassionate use) could be potentially avoided; some possible examples include the use of IL-6 inhibitors and steroids for end-stage Covid-19 (e.g., see: [
     <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]). Furthermore, by revealing combinations of drugs that significantly correlate with the positive-test group, further harmful experimental therapies could be avoided.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">  </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">Complications and confounding factors include</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">• One of the major obstacles to implementing NERD would be the practical difficulties in collecting the needed drug usage information from each patient during or after Covid-19 testing. Collecting drug usage information has long been the initial step in the conduct of “medication reconciliation” reviews between the physician and patient during normal visits. The collection step has been problematic [
     <xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. One possible means of addressing this weakness would be public service announcements urging everyone to maintain a list of all medications used in the preceding months during epidemics.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">• As with many epidemics, a major problem is inaccurate case counts and under-reporting [
     <xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. With overwhelmed health care systems, an unknown but possibly very large percentage of positive cases will go undetected. Many will die from unknown causes (because of unavailable testing) and many cases will be endured solely at home, with only mild symptoms. Very valuable data are therefore lost simply because of incomplete medical records and lack of widespread testing [
     <xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Many mild cases can be missed when they are advised to avoid testing because testing is in short supply.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">• In the absence of widespread randomized testing of the asymptomatic population, drug usage data from a large percentage of the population belonging to test Option #1 would never be acquired. This reduces the predictive value of NERD for potentially beneficial drugs.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">• NERD as presented here makes a liberal assumption that the total population has full access to Rx and OTC drugs. This is overly simplistic for populations under-served by healthcare.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">• For some pathogens, specific sub-groups of the population can be more susceptible or less susceptible to serious complications or higher death rates, often because of added risk factors. This means that those drugs having higher usage rates among those vulnerable groups could bias the results for negative- and positive-test groups unless the drug usage data collected from patients were also coded for the known risk factors.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">• NERD would not be suitable for screening of those drugs where efficacy is determined by the timing of administration. Examples for Covid-19 are drugs used for reducing lung inflammation and damage, such as those required to fight cytokine storm (e.g., [
     <xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]). This is especially true if premature timing could worsen clinical outcomes. This could confound NERD's usefulness for these types of drugs.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">• The collection of usage data on biologics and biosimilars, which continue to be a rapidly growing class of therapeutics, could prove difficult, if not just for the fact that the naming conventions are complex [
     <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">• For drugs associated with the positive-test group, they might simply be serving as PROXIES for co-morbidities that make patients more vulnerable to Covid-19.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">• A very important factor that NERD would not be able to address is whether a drug might have an impact on increasing or decreasing the overall level or rate of virus shedding, which is a key parameter in inter-individual transmission.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">• Because the more limited classes of drugs used in pediatric populations, it would probably be more representative to normalize group drug-usage rates against pediatric and non-pediatric populations.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">• As the ranked, overall nation-wide usage rate for each drug trends downward, the confidence intervals for distinguishing significant differences between the tested groups will increase accordingly, simply because there would be less collected drug usage data. So it would become increasingly more difficult to detect associations for drugs with less market penetration.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">• All types of diagnostic tests have a range of rates for false-negatives and false-positives. This could be a major contributor of error in the confidence of any NERD conclusions regarding drug usage rates.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="2">• Among the active infection test group, a very small portion of the negative-test group may actually comprise newly infected cases (covert virus) whose viral titers are insufficient to meet the minimum sensitivity for a positive test (resulting in a false-negative test); re-testing these cases days later can yield a positive test.</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
