<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Brunker 
 <italic> et al.</italic> have presented a very detailed and thorough description of an end-to-end workflow for generation and bioinformatic analysis of rabies virus whole genome sequences using Nanopore technology and its validation in resource-limited settings. By including in-country training and involving local scientists in their validation they demonstrated the feasibility of the approach under realistic conditions and were able to identify typical challenges. The manuscript is very well written and the level of detail provided in describing the methods (e.g. the specifications for the computer used) is appreciated. The work presents a strong case for the use of in-country sequencing to inform rabies elimination programmes. I have only a few suggestions / comments: 
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p>Page 11 - The authors mention that workshop participants (presumably all 21) were asked to submit research proposals and commitment from their institutions to support MinION genomic work in order to obtain MinION starter kits. They then state that four MinION starter kits were provided to groups "to kickstart the application of their new training skills for genomic research". To provide readers with a better idea of the impact of the training, it would be helpful to know how many of the participants actually submitted proposals (with institutional commitment) as well as how many "groups" received kits. Also, is there information on whether any of the proposed projects have been initiated? </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Figure 5 - Although it is indicated in the table within Figure 5a and highlighted in the phylogeny in Figure 5b, I would suggest including the name of the Tanzanian whole genome sequence in the figure legend i.e. "...for a Tanzanian RABV whole genome sequence (tvla1_tz_Rab16031);"</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Figure 6 - It would be useful to know the regions from which the Genbank sequences in the phylogeny originated (do they overlap with any of those sampled in the study?). I would also like to see a fully annotated tree (perhaps as extended data) that included bootstrap values, sequence IDs and the regions and years associated with all the sequences.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Figure 7 - As for Figure 6 a fully annotated tree (as extended data) would be a helpful addition.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Figure 8 - It is unclear whether the data in this figure is hypothetical or real data from a specific country? Please clarify in the Figure title or legend.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
