<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Efficient nuclear import and assembly of the polymerase subunits (PB2, PB1, and PA) are necessaries steps during viral replication. Da Costa et al. used circular dichroism analysis to study the PA linker structure of WSN, showing that it is a structurally disordered domain [
 <xref rid="B150-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>]. Moreover, they reported that some of the PA linker mutants (T210P, K213P, D216P, L219P, L219A, P221A, N222P, F223P, S225P, and L226P) exhibited a ts phenotype (reduced viral growth at 39.5 °C versus 37 °C or 33 °C) (
 <xref rid="viruses-10-00560-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), which was suggested to be a consequence of altered folding kinetics [
 <xref rid="B150-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>]. Moreover, using a minigenome system, the ts phenotype of the PA mutants T210P, K213P, D216P, F223P, and L226P was associated with a reduced efficiency in viral replication/transcription [
 <xref rid="B150-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>]. Immunofluorescence assays also suggest an inefficient recruit of PB1 to the nucleus at restrictive temperatures (39.5 °C) when co-expressed with PA mutants L214P or D216P, L219P, or F223P. Importantly, some of the ts viruses (D216P and L219P) were attenuated in a mouse model of infection and D216P was still able to induce strong humoral response, suggesting that this strategy could be used to develop novel IAV LAIV candidates. Interestingly, revertants for the ts phenotype were selected by serial passages of the ts mutants at 39.5 °C. Authors identified three groups of reversions (
 <xref rid="viruses-10-00560-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, black): changes in other amino acids of the PA protein (E377K), reversions at the residue that was initially mutated, or amino acid substitutions in other components of the viral polymerase complex such as PB2 (R136G) or PB1 (R287M). Therefore, the isolation of revertant mutants in ts viruses allowed the identification of compensatory changes located in one of the three-polymerase subunits, which could be important to understand the interactions between the components of the viral polymerase complex [
 <xref rid="B150-viruses-10-00560" ref-type="bibr">150</xref>]. These data demonstrate the importance of studying the IAV polymerase complex to understand the mechanism behind the ts and ca phenotypes in order to design improved LAIV approaches. Furthermore, the study of potential revertant viruses could assist researchers in elucidating the mechanism of viral replication and transcription as well as the mechanism(s) of attenuation. Most importantly, the genetic stability of ts LAIV should be closely evaluated as part of the att safety profile of new potential IAV LAIV.
</p>
