<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0190">PEDV remains a threat to the swine industry in the US and worldwide because no effective vaccines are currently available. Regardless of the genogroup, PEDV can be deadly in pig populations with no immunity or low immunity or health status. The extent of PEDV transmission and PED on farms has a reverse relationship with the levels of biosecurity. High biosecurity to control PED should be practiced prior to seasonal or expected epidemics. Concurrently, pregnant sows are immunized by either feedback or vaccination. However, the current feedback or vaccination protocols are frequently inefficient or unsafe, due to: 1) no standardized protocol for feedback; 2) poor capacities of current IM vaccines (live or killed) to induce lactogenic immunity; 3) antigenic differences of vaccine 
 <italic>vs</italic>. epidemic strains; and 4) possibility of continuous re-infection by PEDV used for feedback within herds. In addition, current live vaccines, which were generated by conventional cell culture-adaptation methods, may revert to virulent PEDV or recombine with field PEDV strains to generate new strains after they are applied in the field. Therefore, better vaccination protocols and vaccine strains (attenuated oral vaccines) are required for prevention and control of PED. PEDV-specific IgA memory B cells in orally primed sows play a critical role in boosting lactogenic immunity of sows and passive protection of piglets when piglets are exposed to PEDV during the suckling period. Feedback can be replaced by oral immunization with live attenuated PEDV vaccines that are minimally replicative, but immunogenic in the intestine of pregnant sows, thereby inducing PEDV-specific IgA memory B cells in the GALT or other mucosal and systemic lymphoid tissues and lactogenic immunity. Lastly, ideal live attenuated vaccines should not revert to virulent PEDV or recombine with field PEDV strains to generate new virulent PEDV strains, which remains an obstacle in vaccine development (
 <xref rid="bib0240" ref-type="bibr">Hou and Wang, 2019</xref>).
</p>
