<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Edelfosine (1-
 <italic>O</italic>-octadecyl-2-
 <italic>O</italic>-methyl-
 <italic>rac</italic>-glycero-3-phosphocholine; ET-18-OCH
 <sub>3</sub>) is a synthetic surface-active alkyl-lysophospholipid which is also considered as a selective anti-tumor agent [
 <xref rid="B162-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>]. In a previous study, edelfosine induced apoptosis through loss of Δ
 <italic>Ψ</italic>m potential and caspase-3 activation in both Jurkat (T-lymphoid leukemia) and HL-60 (acute leukemia) cells [
 <xref rid="B163-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">163</xref>]. Moreover, it was shown to induce apoptosis in MM144, MMIS, MM1R (human multiple myeloma) and T-lymphoid Jurkat/B-lymphoid JY (leukemia) cells. Specifically, it promoted apoptosis in MM144 multiple myeloma cells via the recruitment of the Fas/CD95 death receptor and TRAIL receptors DR4, DR5. In this way, the recruitment of Bid (a linker molecule between death receptor and mitochondria apoptotic pathways) into lipid rafts (membrane microdomains, enriched in cholesterol, sphingolipids and gangliosides) facilitated the Fas/CD95- and mitochondria-mediated apoptotic death [
 <xref rid="B164-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>]. A similar anti-cancer mechanism was reported against Jurkat cells [
 <xref rid="B165-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>] and CD138+ malignant cells derived from multiple myeloma patients. [
 <xref rid="B166-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">166</xref>]. Additionally, edelfosine was found to enhance the sensitivity of SNU638 and AGS gastric cancer cells, against recombinant human tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-related apoptosis-inducing ligand (rhTRAIL)-induced apoptosis. The underlying anti-cancer mechanism appears to involve the up-regulation and/or translocation of death receptor 5 (DR5) into lipid rafts and the kinase p38-mediated loss of Δ
 <italic>Ψ</italic>m [
 <xref rid="B167-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>]. Moreover, the compound was shown to induce apoptosis in U118 glioblastoma cells through the activation of caspases-3 and -8 and the disruption of ΔΨm, followed by caspase-9 activation [
 <xref rid="B168-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">168</xref>]. In addition, H-ras-transformed human breast epithelial cells (MCF10-
 <italic>ras</italic>) were also led to apoptosis, following edelfosine treatment, viathe inhibition of ERK1/2 and Akt kinases activity and the reduction of nuclear factor-kappa B (NF-κΒ) expression levels, probably through the induction of a cyclooxygenase-2 (COX-2) expression [
 <xref rid="B169-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">169</xref>]. Likewise, edelfosine was able to induce apoptotic death in another two prostate cancer cell lines, LNCaP and VCap, through the differential regulation of p-AKT and activated transcription factor 3 (ATF3), respectively [two known regulators of androgen receptor (AR) activity]. Moreover, the in vivo anti-tumor activity of edelfosine was confirmed in prostate LNCaP [
 <xref rid="B170-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">170</xref>] and glioma C6 [
 <xref rid="B171-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">171</xref>] xenografts as well. Finally, a recent report indicated an in vitro anti-metastatic capacity of edelfosine, against RT112 muscle-invasive urothelial cancer cells, mediated through the inhibition of the small conductance calcium-activated potassium channel 3 (SK3; a metastasis inducer). Similarly, edelfosine inhibited the invasive ability of RT112-derived tumors, in vivo, using a modified chicken chorioallantoic membrane (CAM) model [
 <xref rid="B172-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">172</xref>]. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pharmaceutics-12-00688-f003">Figure 3</xref> illustrates suggested the anti-cancer mechanisms activated by the different synthetic surfactants. 
</p>
