<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Sophorolipids extracted from the yeast strain 
 <italic>Wickerhamiella domercqiae</italic> Y2A isolated from oil-contaminated wastewater were noticed to present anticancer activity as described by Chen et al. [
 <xref rid="B176-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">176</xref>]. SL was tested against four cancer cell lines, H7402 (liver), A549 (lung), HL60 and K562 (leukaemia) and showed a significant inhibitory effect on cell proliferation on all the tested cell lines. What is more, the authors observed a direct dependence of inhibition on the surfactant’s concentration, where 0% cell viability was recorded for the sophorolipid concentration above 62.5 µg mL
 <sup>−1</sup>. A cytotoxic effect of lactonic SLs against breast adenocarcinoma lines MDA-MB-231 was described by Ribeiro et al. [
 <xref rid="B177-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">177</xref>]. Moreover, a correlation between a cytotoxic effect and surfactant’s critical micelle concentration CMC was observed, in other words, when the surfactant’s concentrations were in the range of its CMC, a higher cytotoxic effect was observed. The authors observed a greater anticancer effect of diacetylated lactonic SLs compared to acidic SLs. Similar conclusions were drawn by Shao et al. [
 <xref rid="B178-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">178</xref>] who tested the effects of ten structurally different SLs on two human oesophageal cancer cell lines, KYSE 109 and KYSE 450. They observed the diacetylated lactonic SL to be the most efficient at inhibiting two oesophageal cancer cell lines, while acidic sophorolipids hardly indicated any anticancer activity. SLs have also shown anticancer activities towards the human cervical cancer cell line HeLa, as presented by Nawale et al. [
 <xref rid="B179-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>] and Li et al. [
 <xref rid="B180-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">180</xref>] The latter also presented a relationship between the cytotoxicity of diacetylated lactonic SLs of different unsaturation degrees and their carbon chain length. The longer the chain length, the stronger the cytotoxicity of SLs observed. Apart from the aforementioned anticancer activities towards breast, cervical, lung, liver and oesophageal cancer, SLs were also found to show cytotoxic properties against human pancreatic cancer cell lines [
 <xref rid="B181-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">181</xref>] and glioma cell line LN-229 [
 <xref rid="B182-pharmaceutics-12-00688" ref-type="bibr">182</xref>].
</p>
