<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to evidence for Chagas disease in post-Katrina Louisiana as described above, the US borderlands with Mexico have also emerged as an endemic region 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Beard1" ref-type="bibr">[97]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Tobler1" ref-type="bibr">[109]</xref>. Because of concerns about the risk of new contamination of the national blood supply with 
 <italic>T. cruzi</italic>
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Bern1" ref-type="bibr">[98]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Centers5" ref-type="bibr">[100]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Dodd1" ref-type="bibr">[101]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Leiby1" ref-type="bibr">[103]</xref>, with a recent estimate that between 1 in 4,655 and 1 in 25,000 US blood donors are seropositive for 
 <italic>T. cruzi</italic> antibodies and presumed infected 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Centers5" ref-type="bibr">[100]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Tobler1" ref-type="bibr">[109]</xref>, there is great interest in expanding current blood screening efforts 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Bern1" ref-type="bibr">[98]</xref>. In 2006, the US Food and Drug Administration approved a new commercial ELISA test for blood donation screening that utilizes parasite lysate antigens for detection of antibodies 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Bern1" ref-type="bibr">[98]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Centers5" ref-type="bibr">[100]</xref>. Estimates of the prevalence of Chagas disease along the Mexico border and in the US vary widely. Previously, it was estimated that 50,000 to 100,000 Latin American immigrants in the US are infected 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Leiby1" ref-type="bibr">[103]</xref>, but more recently it was found that of 10,192 blood specimens from El Paso, Texas, of which 73% were from donors of Hispanic origin, three donors were positive 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Tobler1" ref-type="bibr">[109]</xref>. With an overall prevalence of 0.03% 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Tobler1" ref-type="bibr">[109]</xref> and 10 million people living in the US–Mexico borderlands 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Glasmeier1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, I estimate that approximately 3,000 people have Chagas disease in the region. Other estimates are considerably higher. Milei et al. argued that there are 370,000 
 <italic>T. cruzi</italic>–infected individuals in the US during the 1990s 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Milei1" ref-type="bibr">[105]</xref>, while Hanford et al. revised these estimates to suggest that over one million Hispanics in the US have Chagas disease (with almost 270,000 in Texas alone) and that at least 150,000 Latin America–born immigrants are expected to develop clinically apparent chronic Chagas disease 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Hanford1" ref-type="bibr">[102]</xref>. Congenital Chagas disease may also occur 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Bern1" ref-type="bibr">[98]</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Muoz1" ref-type="bibr">[110]</xref>. Of particular concern is the possibility that 
 <italic>T. cruzi</italic> transmission to humans today occurs in the US–Mexico borderlands. In South Texas and elsewhere along the US–Mexico borderlands, dogs and coyotes are seropositive and there is a domestic canine transmission cycle 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Beard1" ref-type="bibr">[97]</xref>. In addition, wood rats are common hosts, and the infection occurs among domestic cattle, horses, and sheep 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Hanford1" ref-type="bibr">[102]</xref>. Infected vectors or hosts are present in 64 of the 254 counties in Texas 
 <xref rid="pntd.0000256-Hanford1" ref-type="bibr">[102]</xref>, so people living in the estimated 30,000 poor-quality dwellings in the borderlands region are at high risk for transmission.
</p>
