<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par7">MERS-CoV was first found in 2012 in a lung sample from a 60-year-old patient who died of respiratory failure in Jeddah, Saudi Arabia. On 15 September 2012, a similar type of virus named human coronavirus was isolated from a patient with severe respiratory infection. Cases have also been reported in other countries.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup> MERS has a 35% mortality rate, and since it emerged in the human population in June 2012, it has caused substantial morbidity and mortality.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup> From 2012 until January 15, 2020, the total number of laboratory-confirmed MERS-CoV infection cases reported globally to the World Health Organization (WHO) was 2506, with 862 associated deaths, covering 27 countries (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/csr/don/31-january-2020-mers-united-arab-emirates/en" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.who.int/csr/don/31-january-2020-mers-united-arab-emirates/en</ext-link>). Cases of MERS from other countries were linked to travel to the Middle East.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup> MERS-CoV was identified from the saliva of a patient with acute pneumonia and renal failure in Jeddah (KSA). MERS-CoV can be detected in respiratory tract secretions, as well as in feces, serum, and urine.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup> In addition, it has been isolated from environmental objects such as bedsheets, bedrails, intravenous fluid hangers, and X-ray devices.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup> In the case of known camel infection, MERS-CoV was transmitted from a camel to a human, which was confirmed by RNA sequencing.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
