<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<app-group>
 <app id="app1-viruses-11-00791">
  <title>Supplementary Materials</title>
  <p>The following are available online at 
   <uri xlink:href="https://www.mdpi.com/1999-4915/11/9/791/s1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.mdpi.com/1999-4915/11/9/791/s1</uri>: Figure S1: Spatial distribution of 613 taxa included in the final dataset sampled in India between 2009 and 2017 by S/UT. Figure S2: Root-to-tip regression over time of 613 H1N1pdm09 isolates sampled from India between 2009 and 2017 inclusive. Figure S3: Maximum clade credibility tree (MCC) of 613 A/H1N1pdm09 taxa sequenced for HA between 2009 and 2017 inclusive from 14 states and union territories (S/UT) in India. Figure S4: Definitively supported (BF &gt; 100) routes of A/H1N1pdm09 transmission between S/UT in India from 2009 to 2017 based on five randomly subsampled datasets. Table S1: Global dataset of HA sequences by year and region for comparative analysis. Table S2: Substitution model and clock prior testing results using path sampling (PS) and stepping-stone sampling (SSS) of log marginal likelihoods. Table S3: Interpretation of computed BF values. Table S4: Subsample of HA sequences by year and S/UT included for replicate analysis. Table S5: dN/dS rate ratios and 95% BCI of all positively selected HA sites among Indian (n = 613) and International (S1 and S2) taxa of H1N1pdm09 detected using BRC. Table S6: Codon sites under pervasive positive selection as identified using Bayesian Renaissance Counting (BRC), two-rate fixed effects likelihood (FEL) and single-likelihood ancestor counting (SLAC) in India. Table S7: Statistically supported routes for A/H1N1pdm09 transmission in India between 14 S/UT from 2009 to 2017 based on the average of five randomly subsampled sequence datasets (n = 259). Table S8: Statistically supported routes for A/H1N1pdm09 transmission in India between 14 S/UT discrete locations from 2009 to 2017. Table S9: Distribution of A/H1N1pdm09 viruses belonging to clade 6B by year and S/UT in India between 2009 and 2011. Acknowledgment 
   <xref rid="viruses-11-00791-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>: GISAID EpiFlu™ Database Acknowledgment Table. Datafile 1: Alignment of 613 A/H1N1pdm09 HA isolates.
  </p>
 </app>
</app-group>
