<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In most viral illnesses, viremia peaks in the first week of infection. The patient then develops a primary immune response by Day 10 to Day 14, followed by virus clearance. Arabi et al.
 <xref rid="trf15797-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">18</xref> studied the time course of specific antibody response and found that those antibodies peaked 1 week after the inoculation and then began declining. Therefore, convalescent plasma should be more effective when given early during the course of infections. SARS patients whose clinical condition deteriorated after receiving ribavirin and methylprednisolone had a higher discharge rate by Day 22, a shorter hospital stay, and a lower mortality rate when convalescent plasma was administered before Day14 of illness onset.
 <xref rid="trf15797-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">5</xref> In a study of patients with Lassa fever in Nigeria, all eight patients who received convalescent plasma before Day 10 of illness recovered and survived, while only three of eight patients who received plasma after Day 10 survived.
 <xref rid="trf15797-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">13</xref> The latest research proved that the positive rate of IgG reached 100% at around 17 to 19 days after symptom onset, while the IgM seroconversion rate reached its peak of 94.1% at around 20 to 22 days after symptoms onset. During the first 3 weeks of symptom onset, there was an increase in the titer of IgG and IgM antibodies to SARS‐CoV‐2. All those patients achieved a seroconversion of IgG or IgM within 20 days after symptom onset. The median day of seroconversion for both IgG and IgM was 13 days (after symptoms onset). The IgG levels in all the patients reached the platform in 6 days after the first positive points. It means that we should use convalescent plasma within 3 weeks after symptoms onset.
 <xref rid="trf15797-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">33</xref> These findings suggest that early initiation of convalescent plasma treatment may be of critical importance to reduce mortality in patients with SARS or other pathogen infection.
 <xref rid="trf15797-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">31</xref> However, a report showed that, when convalescent plasma transfusions were initiated on the day of diagnosis or up to 2 days later, the risk of death on Day 3 to Day 16 was nonsignificant.
 <xref rid="trf15797-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">4</xref> Therefore, whether earlier use of convalescent plasma is better need more evidences.
</p>
