<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>These poultry data, collected from sub-national livestock census data and corresponding to administrative boundaries, were converted into densities by excluding the areas unsuitable for livestock. The poultry density data were downloaded from GeoNetwork (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork/srv/en" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.fao.org/geonetwork/srv/en</ext-link>), and collated to raster grids with each pixel value representing actual density per km
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pone.0029617.e054.jpg" mimetype="image" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>. Population density was chosen as an indicator of the volume of viral traffic 
 <xref rid="pone.0029617-Gilbert1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. The 2010 estimate of population density, produced by the Center for International Earth Science Information Network (CIESIN), Columbia University and the United Nations Food and Agriculture Programme (FAO), were downloaded from the CIESIN (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ciesin.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.ciesin.org</ext-link>). Railways and roads were chosen because these two variables were used as surrogate indicator of long-range movements of human and poultry. The shape data for the two transport networks were provided by GIVA-GIS (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.diva-gis.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.diva-gis.org</ext-link>), an open source for mapping and geographic data. The area and line-based data, including inland water bodies, coastline, and migratory bird pathways, downloaded from the GIVA-GIS, were used to determine the association between birds and the outbreaks. The migratory bird pathways were specified by 70 km buffers on each side because of uncertainty about the behavior of migrating birds. All shapes were converted to binary lattice data indicating presence or absence. In addition average elevation data [90_m resolution Digital Terrain Model from the Shuttle Radar Topography Mission data, STRM V3 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://srtm.csi.cgiar.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://srtm.csi.cgiar.org</ext-link>)] were used to capture topographic features that might be associated with the establishment of an H5N1 epidemic 
 <xref rid="pone.0029617-Gilbert1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>.
</p>
