<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>WNV is maintained and amplified in an enzootic cycle involving birds and mosquitoes from the 
 <italic>Culex</italic> genus as vectors. WNV is transmitted to different animal species (mainly mammals but also reptiles and amphibians) through the bite of infected mosquitoes. Horses and humans are highly susceptible to WNV infection but are considered as dead-end hosts owing to limited and short viremia that does not sustain transmission to naïve mosquitoes. In both species, asymptomatic infections are the most common, but in rare cases (approximately 1 out of 140 infections in humans and up to 10% infected horses), neuroinvasive forms with meningitis, encephalitis or myelitis may occur [
 <xref rid="B113-viruses-12-00023" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>,
 <xref rid="B114-viruses-12-00023" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. WNV is the most widely distributed arbovirus that induces equine encephalitis (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-12-00023-f007">Figure 7</xref>). Over the last 15 years, WNV has been repeatedly reported in Europe with a high frequency in the Mediterranean region and in Eastern Europe. This virus was first described in France, Portugal and Cyprus in the 1960s [
 <xref rid="B115-viruses-12-00023" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>]. After a silence of more than 30 years, WNV lineage 1 strains resurfaced in North Africa (in Morocco (1996), Algeria (1994) and Tunisia (1997)), as well as in Western and Eastern Europe (Romania (1996), Italy (1998), Russia (1999) and France (2000)) [
 <xref rid="B116-viruses-12-00023" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-viruses-12-00023" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>,
 <xref rid="B118-viruses-12-00023" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. WNV strikingly exemplified how fast and unpredictable flaviviruses can emerge when the virus was introduced in New York City in 1999. It produced large and dramatic outbreaks in humans and horses and rapidly spread, in less than 4 years, throughout the United States of America, causing more than 30,000 cases and 1200 deaths in humans and more than 24,000 cases in the equine population for the United States only over a 10-year period [
 <xref rid="B119-viruses-12-00023" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. Interestingly, in Europe the epidemiological scenario in 1996–2010 was quite different from the one in North America as epidemics were irregular and limited in time and space. Nevertheless, a revival of WNV activity in Europe has been associated in particular with the introduction in 2004 of a new WNV strain within lineage 2, most likely originating from Africa [
 <xref rid="B120-viruses-12-00023" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>]. This WNV lineage 2 was initially identified in Hungary and then spread to the eastern part of Austria and to southern European countries including Greece in 2010 and Italy in 2011 [
 <xref rid="B121-viruses-12-00023" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>]. Unprecedented WNV transmission seasons in Europe were registered in 2010, 2012, 2013, or 2015, in association with climatic and environmental conditions sustaining mosquito activity and close mosquito-bird contact rates. Nevertheless, these recent transmission seasons were in no way comparable to the exceptional transmission wave experienced in 2018. Indeed, 2018 showed a 7.2-fold increase of reported cases compared to the 2017 transmission season and a final total number of reported autochthonous infections in humans (
 <italic>n</italic> = 2083) higher than the cumulative number from the previous seven years (
 <italic>n</italic> = 1832) [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-12-00023" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The highest increase compared to 2017 was observed in Bulgaria (15-fold) followed by France (13.5-fold) and Italy (10.9-fold). The number of European equine WNV outbreaks doubled in 2018 (
 <italic>n</italic> = 285) in comparison with earlier WNV transmission seasons (
 <italic>n</italic> = 97–191 in 2013–2017, with on average 145 equine cases reported annually for this period) [
 <xref rid="B17-viruses-12-00023" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The second remarkable pattern was the reporting in 2018 for the first time of WNV in northern Europe, with several bird species and two horses found infected by WNV lineage 2 in Germany [
 <xref rid="B122-viruses-12-00023" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. In Australia, specific virus variants called Kunjin virus and classified into WNV lineage 1b, recently caused unprecedented epizootics of neurological disease in horses in Southeast Australia, resulting in almost 1000 cases and a 9% case fatality rate in 2011; unusual climatic conditions, as well as enhanced virus transmission by infected mosquitoes, could have contributed to the phenomenon [
 <xref rid="B123-viruses-12-00023" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>].
</p>
