<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS), Middle East Respiratory Syndrome (MERS), Nipah (NiV), Hendra (HeV), and Ebola (EBOV) viruses' outbreaks confirmed the inextricable nature of human and bat health and disease and highlighted that focusing on the “spillover” potential of known, and novel, bat viruses is critical to predict and prevent pandemics. The remarkable ability of bats to coexist with a wide range of viruses that would be pathogenic in flightless mammals (Fl
 <sup>−</sup>M) is not yet fully understood but possibly relates to their unique, flight-adapted antiviral immunity (Calisher et al., 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Hayman et al., 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Intriguingly, genetic material from viruses that resemble influenza type A viruses has been recovered from asymptomatic fruit bats of the Neotropic bat family 
 <italic>Phyllostomidae</italic> (
 <italic>Sturnira lilium</italic> and 
 <italic>Artibeus planirostris</italic>) in several countries of Central and South America (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) (Tong et al., 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Campos et al., 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). Influenza A viruses (IAVs) are orthomyxoviruses with eight single-stranded negative-sense viral RNAs (vRNAs) encapsidated into viral ribonucleoproteins (vRNPs). IAVs emerge from aquatic birds, 
 <italic>via</italic> genome reassortment and mutation, and are able to cause epidemics (and sporadic pandemics; Simonsen, 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>) in humans, lower animals and birds (Simonsen, 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>). The bat influenza viruses (BatIVs) are phylogenetically distinct from the conventional IAVs and they were designated as H17N10 and H18N11 (
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Bats in Latin America, but not in Central Europe, have been found seropositive for BatIVs (Tong et al., 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Fereidouni et al., 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Antibodies against human H2N2 and H3N2, as well as classical H9, have also been found in bats elsewhere (L'vov et al., 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">1979</xref>; Kelkar et al., 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">1981</xref>; Isaeva et al., 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">1982</xref>), suggesting they are susceptible to IAV infection. The epithelial kidney cells of flying foxes (
 <italic>Pteropus alecto</italic>) co-express both avian (α2,3-Gal) and human (α2,6-Gal) sialic acid (SA) receptors (Chothe et al., 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) and are thus susceptible to infection by both avian and human IAVs, but more importantly they allow reassortment between co-infecting influenza viruses (Dlugolenski et al., 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). The N-terminal domain of the H17N10 PA subunit of the influenza virus polymerase complex possesses endonuclease activity comparable to that of IAVs (Tefsen et al., 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Equally intriguingly, in the position 627 of the polymerase gene PB2, one of the most commonly identified IAV virulence markers, BatIVs have a serine compared to glutamic acid in avian and lysine in mammalian influenza strains, suggestive of an alternative evolutionary pathway for avian IAV's adaptation in mammals (Mehle, 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). This all raised the question whether novel IAVs could emerge from bats to which human and animal populations would be immunologically “naïve,” causing pandemics.
</p>
