<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>N</italic>. 
 <italic>meningitidis</italic>, the bacterium that causes invasive meningococcal disease (IMD), spreads primarily by droplet transmission and infection of respiratory mucosa. Approximately 5%–10% of healthy adults are nasopharyngeal carriers. 
 <italic>N</italic>. 
 <italic>meningitidis</italic> has been isolated from men with urethritis [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. A 1972 study described the transmission of 
 <italic>N</italic>. 
 <italic>meningitidis</italic> from a male chimpanzee’s nasopharynx to his own urethra via oral-genital autoinoculation [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The authors concluded that 
 <italic>N</italic>. 
 <italic>meningitidis</italic> in the human urogenital tract might be the result of oral-genital sexual contact. Dyad and cluster analyses showing related strains of meningococci among partners epidemiologically linked by female-to-male oral sex strengthen the argument for sexual transmission leading to meningococcal urethritis [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Recent molecular analyses suggest that 
 <italic>N</italic>. 
 <italic>meningitidis</italic> has genetically adapted to the urogenital tract [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Recent IMD outbreaks among MSM in Europe, Canada, and the US have also raised questions about the role that sexual networks play in 
 <italic>N</italic>. 
 <italic>meningitidis</italic> transmission [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>–
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Droplet transmission within MSM sexual networks could explain consistently higher 
 <italic>N</italic>. 
 <italic>meningitidis</italic> nasopharyngeal carriage rates relative to heterosexual men [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pmed.1002474.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. It remains challenging, however, to determine whether the primary mode of transmission in IMD outbreaks among MSM is oral-genital contact, open-mouth kissing, or droplet transmission via “close contact,” including the sharing of living and sleeping spaces.
</p>
