<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>During its infectious cycle, influenza A virus (IAV) has to cross the plasma membrane during entry and budding from host cells. Therefore, the membrane properties and integrity are important determinants of efficient infection. IAV has been shown to selectively bind to host membrane lipid rafts (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Eierhoff et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Verma et al., 2018</xref>). These specialized membrane microdomains are formed from the preferential association of cholesterol with sphingolipids (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2009</xref>). Additionally, sphingolipids have been implicated during different aspects of the viral life cycles including attachment (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Puri et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Rawat et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Grassme, 2005</xref>), entry (
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Nieva et al., 1994</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Miller et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">Shivanna et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Drake et al., 2017</xref>), replication (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Weng et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Martín-Acebes et al., 2016</xref>) and budding (
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Nguyen and Hildreth, 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Ono and Freed, 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Tafesse et al., 2013</xref>). As such, they are considered a promising therapeutic target against viral infections (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Yager and Konan, 2019</xref>). Several studies have demonstrated a pivotal role for sphingolipids in regulating IAV life cycle. Sphingosine-1-phosphate- (S1P) metabolizing enzymes have been shown to modulate influenza infection 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Seo et al., 2010</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">Xia et al., 2018</xref>). Sphingosine kinase 1 (SK1) enhances viral replication through regulating viral RNA synthesis and export of nuclear viral ribonucleoprotein complex (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">Seo et al., 2013</xref>). Glucosylceramidase is critical during infection by controlling the successful trafficking of influenza virus to the late endosome and its subsequent fusion and entry (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Drews et al., 2019</xref>). We have previously demonstrated that 
 <italic>de novo</italic> ceramide plays a protective antiviral role against IAV infection (
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">Soudani et al., 2019</xref>). Furthermore, exogenous short-chained ceramide enhances the maturation and activation of dendritic cells in response to IAV infection, thus blocking its replication (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Pritzl et al., 2015</xref>). Therefore, the sphingolipid biosynthesis is a promising host target for developing novel therapeutic approaches against influenza infection.
</p>
