<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>At present, it remains to be concretely demonstrated that bats and pangolins are the possible natural reservoirs and intermediate animal species for HCoV-19 related viruses. However, whether there exist any other animal species that may also play an intermediate role in the interspecies spread of HCoV-19 remains unknown. The recent report for detection of SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing serum antibodies in cats from Wuhan, Hubei Province, indicated that cats were infected during the COVID-19 outbreak (
 <xref rid="bZhang2020b" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2020b</xref>). Direct inoculation of HCoV-19 to a variety of animals showed that ferrets and cats are highly susceptible to this virus, whereas dogs have a low genetic susceptibility, and pigs, chickens and ducks could not be infected (
 <xref rid="bShi2020" ref-type="bibr">Shi et al., 2020</xref>). In particular, cats could transmit the virus via respiratory droplets (
 <xref rid="bShi2020" ref-type="bibr">Shi et al., 2020</xref>), which would pose difficulties for the control of the virus. Other studies showed that Syrian hamsters (
 <xref rid="bChan2020" ref-type="bibr">Chan et al., 2020</xref>) and monkeys (
 <xref rid="bBao2020" ref-type="bibr">Bao et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bLu2020b" ref-type="bibr">Lu et al., 2020b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bMunster2020" ref-type="bibr">Munster et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bRockx2020" ref-type="bibr">Rockx et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bShan2020" ref-type="bibr">Shan et al., 2020</xref>) are susceptible to HCoV-19 infection and may be promising as potential animal models for COVID-19, indicating a possibility of interspecies spread of HCoV-19 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Figure1">Figure 1A</xref>). Anecdotal reports in a variety of news media reported that tigers in a New York Zoo tested positive for HCoV-19, in which these animals exhibited symptoms of the illness (https://www.nationalgeographic.com/animals/2020/04/tiger-coronavirus-covid19-positive-test-bronx-zoo/). These reports suggested that there may be more animals susceptible to HCoV-19 than previously thought (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Figure1">Figure 1A</xref>). 
</p>
