<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Respiratory droplets that spread every time while breathing, coughing, or sneezing are the main route of transmission of SARS‐CoV‐2. Therefore, attachment of the virus to ACE2 expressed on the respiratory tract is the first step enabling entry into host cells. Therefore, COVID‐19 primarily affects the respiratory system and secondary acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) is quite prevalent in COVID‐19 patients (Cheng et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>; Zhou, Yang, et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0091" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). In this respect, the comparison with epidemiological evidence from influenza outbreaks and pandemics is very interesting. Opposite to COVID‐19, in influenza, morbidity and mortality are often higher for women than men. Moreover, during influenza, “cytokine storms” do not clearly differ between men and women (Klein, Hodgson, &amp; Robinson, 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). On the other hand, COVID‐19 elderly male patients have a greater inflammatory reaction, with higher levels of interleukins, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/LigandDisplayForward?ligandId=5074" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">TNF‐α</ext-link>, LDH, ferritin and hsCRP, thus developing a “cytokine storm,” which may lead to ARDS, multiple organ failure and, ultimately, death (Moccia et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>; Qin et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0068" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>). Of note, serum levels of interleukins (s
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/ObjectDisplayForward?objectId=2297%26familyId=305%26familyType=CATALYTICRECEPTOR" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">IL‐2R</ext-link>, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/LigandDisplayForward?ligandId=4998" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">IL‐6</ext-link>, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/LigandDisplayForward?ligandId=821" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">IL‐8</ext-link>, and 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.guidetopharmacology.org/GRAC/LigandDisplayForward?ligandId=4975" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">IL‐10</ext-link>) and TNF‐α were measured in women and men with and without apparent comorbidities. Male COVID‐19 patients displayed an exaggerated production of inflammatory cytokines and proteins (Qin et al., 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0068" ref-type="ref">2020</xref>), including the anti‐inflammatory IL‐10 (Iyer &amp; Cheng, 
 <xref rid="bph15207-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>).
</p>
