<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0095">As aforementioned, COVID-19 induces a state of the infection-induced intense inflammation and hemodynamic alterations, which is likely to augment the risk of plaque rupture in susceptible individuals.
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> However, many investigators across Europe have reported a reduction in patients admitted for ACS after the COVID pandemic began.
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> These decreased numbers are more likely secondary to people preferring to stay at home in the wake up of strict travel restrictions, lockdowns, and hospital emergencies being filled with patients with COVID.
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>34</sup>
 </xref> People may have a fear they will catch COVID-19 if they call an ambulance or end up in the emergency department.
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>34</sup>
 </xref> Consequently, the number of patients with delayed presentation and ACS-related complications is bound to be higher. In a recently published report from the province of Bergamo, Italy, there was an increase in late presentations (+25%) of patients with ACS in the province in March 2020, as compared with the monthly average of the previous year.
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>34</sup>
 </xref> Extensive infarctions, heart failure, high coronary thrombus burden, and no reflow were more frequent.
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>34</sup>
 </xref> Similarly, delays in presentation and management of patients with ST-elevation myocardial infarction were recorded in a small observational study in Hongkong, China.
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>36</sup>
 </xref> Thus, early reports have suggested a decrease in hospital admissions for ACS, but this is mainly because of the over occupancy of the health-care system with patients with COVID-19 and fear of contracting infection among patients. There is no apparent reason for a decline in the incidence of ACS.
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> However, there appears an increase in the ACS-related complications and subsequent mortality owing to delays in presentation and management of patients with ACS in the COVID-19 era.
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>34</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>36</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
