<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In these last years, the increasing obesity incidence in canine species has enshrined its relevance as an important worldwide disease. Recently, obesity has been associated with impaired immunity and chronic low‐grade inflammation in humans as well as mouse models. Increased concentration of leptin and other pro‐inflammatory cytokines have been described in obese dogs. A reduced number of T regulatory cells (Treg) has been reported in visceral adipose tissue and blood of obese humans, and recently also in Labrador retriever obese dogs. Moreover, some evidences addressed the possible impact of obesity on cardiovascular apparatus in dogs. The aim of this study was to investigate the effect of a weight loss program on metabolic and immunological profile, blood leptin level and cardiovascular parameters in obese dogs. Ten overweight dogs (OB) (BCS &gt; 7/9) were recruited into the study, and they underwent blood testing (complete blood count, serum biochemistry, blood level assay of CD3 + CD4+, CD3 + CD8+ T cells, CD4/CD8 ratio, CD21+ B cells, Treg cells by immune‐fluorescence and flow cytometry and measurement of serum leptin by species‐specific ELISA kit) and assessment of cardiovascular function (blood pressure measurement, electrocardiography and echocardiography) before (T0) and after five months (T1) of commercially available weight loss diet. Ten normal weight (BCS 4‐5) healthy dogs represented a control group (CTR). Regarding metabolic profile, a mild no significant decrease in total cholesterol but a significant decrease in triglycerides serum levels (
 <italic>P &lt; 0.05</italic>) were observed in the obese dogs at T1. There were no significant differences in the other biochemical parameters as well as in haematological values between the two observation times. Concerning the cardiovascular parameters, no significant differences were observed at T1, and particularly systolic arterial blood pressure values were in the reference range in both times. OB had elevated serum leptin concentrations that decrease significantly (
 <italic>P &lt; 0.005</italic>) after weight loss, however remaining higher compared to CTR. OB dogs showed significant low levels (
 <italic>P &lt; 0.005</italic>) of Treg compared to CTR but they did not increase after weight loss. Our data suggested that a deranged immune‐regulation, combined with high leptin levels, might characterize obese dogs in the absence of cardiovascular alterations. Furthermore, on the basis of our results we may suggest that probably in dogs a greater reduction in fat mass, and long‐term weight loss programs, are necessary in order to restore immunological balance.
</p>
