<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Viral dissemination, but not transmission, of AC were lower than IOC two days following ingestion of infectious blood by both 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic>. However, transmission was similar or higher for both mosquito species after five days of extrinsic incubation to AC than to IOC (Tables 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005724.t002">2</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pntd.0005724.t004">4</xref>). Viral dissemination and transmission was higher in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> than 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> which is consistent with other studies comparing the vector competence of these two species for the Asian lineage of CHIKV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005724.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005724.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005724.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Although viral dissemination rates of AC and IOC were high for most mosquito populations, transmission was lower, suggesting substantial salivary gland infection or escape barriers [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005724.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Viral dissemination and transmission of AC decreased from 5 to 12 days of extrinsic incubation, suggesting that transmission risk declines with length of infection. Interestingly, the decline in transmission of AC was less in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> than 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic>, suggesting that older 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> females are relatively more competent vectors than similar aged 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> females. Older mosquitoes represent a greater epidemiological threat, because they are more likely to have ingested a virus-infected blood meal and completed the extrinsic incubation period and are more likely capable of transmitting the virus during these advanced stages of infection [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005724.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Our observations that transmission efficiency declines with length of infection are likely to mitigate age-enhanced transmission potential. Indices of risk of transmission, such as vectorial capacity, do not consider that different species or genotypes of pathogens are affected differently by time since infection, irrespective of daily vector survivorship. Existing models of vector-borne arboviruses could be used to determine whether the pattern of transmission is altered by the addition of time-dependent transmission efficiency during the lifespan of the vector, or by species-specific variation in EIP, transmission or mosquito life history traits. Preliminary studies using a model to investigate the likelihood of CHIKV epidemics in FL after introductions showed differences in the outcome when species-specific variation in vector competence for CHIKV, mosquito mortality and human biting frequency were considered. Ongoing research is investigating effects of the variation in EIP observed in this study and will be published elsewhere. One plausible mechanism that would account for decline in transmission efficiency with length of infection is virus modulation of the infection by the mosquito [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005724.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. This hypothesis predicts that reduced viral titer in mosquito tissues would be observed on day 12 compared to day 5 because of the observed decline in transmission at the later time point. We would thus expect to see changes in leg viral titers in association with changes in saliva infection over time. The observed reduction in leg viral titer, in association with reduction in transmission, for AC supports this hypothesis. Further support comes from the observation that saliva infection did not decline over time in IOC, and neither did leg viral titer. Salazar et al. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005724.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] showed that after ingestion of dengue-2 virus, peak virus titer in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> was observed after 7–10 days of extrinsic incubation followed by a steady decline later during infection. Although the molecular mechanism responsible for reduced virus load was unclear, the authors suggested several potential means including physiologically compromised epithelial cells, post-transcriptional or post-translational repression, or an antiviral response [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005724.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Similar observations were made with 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> infected with dengue-2 by Sánchez-Vargas et al. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005724.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] in which they showed that dengue infection and viral titer in 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> were modulated by the RNAi defense system. Additional experiments are needed to identify the mechanism(s) responsible for modulation of infection observed in the current study.
</p>
