<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> presents the events in the DES model, with estimates of the probabilities based on the limited available evidence and judgment. For each block, we generate the monthly number of births (b) over time based on demographic data [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. Using the estimated fraction of births with PIDs (Ppid), the model generates the total number of newborns in each month with a genetic predisposition of each PID category (CVID or oPIDs) using a random draw from a Poisson distribution with rate b × Ppid. The model differentiates CVID from oPIDs because it assumes that only CVID patients may develop chronic poliovirus excretion. This level of stratification combines all oPIDs into one category, despite the wide spectrum of conditions, disease severity, treatments, survival, and possibly also different abilities to become infected and/or clear poliovirus, because insufficient data exist to separately model all PID defects. At birth, we also randomly determine whether each PID patient will become a long-term excretor if infected with OPV after onset of clinical symptoms resulting from the PID (upper section of Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The probability of potential long-term excretion (i.e., if infected with OPV after PID onset and surviving long enough) represents a key uncertain input. Although we do not know whether individual host properties or random events associated with the OPV infection (e.g., the replication site) determine the ability to excrete long-term, we assume a pre-determined patient-specific ability to excrete long-term, if surviving long enough and infected after clinical PID onset. In the absence of resource constraints and practical considerations, the ideal screening study would follow a large number of PID patients over many years after PID onset to determine when they become infected with OPV and when they recover. The existing screening studies in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> only provide a cross-section of PID patients and identified individuals excreting at a given point in time, with limited follow-up of only those found excreting. Depending on the interpretation of the data discussed above, estimates of the rate of long-term excretion per PID patient may range from approximately 0.1 % (i.e., the proportion of all PIDs found to excrete poliovirus during follow-up of cross-sectionally screened PID patients) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>] to approximately 10 % (i.e., the proportion of surviving patients with poliovirus excretion at time of cross-sectional screening found to excrete long-term) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>] or as high as almost 20 % (i.e., the proportion of surviving immunodeficient VAPP patients found to excrete long-term) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. The first estimate provides a lower bound of potential long-term excretors because it excludes excretors who did not yet become infected at the time of screening or who already stopped excreting. The 10 % estimate may represent an overestimate of the true proportion because its denominator skews towards long-term excretors (since they remain more likely to excrete poliovirus at the time of screening). The 20 % estimate provides an overestimate if VAPP is more common for long-term than typical excretors with a PID, which appears plausible given that long-term excretors cannot rapidly clear polioviruses and a longer infection implies a greater chance of the virus entering the central nervous system. We assume that 1 % of PID patients may become a prolonged excretor if infected and surviving (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Although close to half of the identified CVID patients with long-term excretion exhibit chronic excretion, we assume that relatively more prolonged than chronic excretors with CVID go undetected due to their shorter period of excretion, implying a smaller probability (0.5 %) of a CVID patient becoming a chronic excretor if infected and surviving.
</p>
