<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An EM is a tool that uses a beam of accelerated electrons as a source of illumination. Due to the short wavelength of electrons in comparison with visible light photons (up to 100,000 times), the resolving power of EM is higher than optical microscopes and can visualize the structure of particles at nanometer scales. The capability of EM to reveal the structures of nanoparticles makes it a powerful instrument for detection, diagnosis, and analysis of viruses (as viruses are of the same scale as that of many inorganic nanoparticles such as gold, extensively used in research). In comparison, with the molecular and serological approaches used for virus diagnosis which require specific probe to recognize virus, EM methods do not need organism-specific reagents for recognizing the pathogenic agent. It means for the case of an unknown disease, molecular tests need information about the potential agents to determine the appropriate tests, while EM provides an open view of whatever might be present in a given sample under investigation.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref237">237</xref>
 </sup> Besides the capability of EM in direct detection of virus by visualization, it provides information about the ultrastructure of the virus, its structural dynamics related to the attachment, and replication processes. This makes EM a useful tool in the discovery and design of antiviral agents and vaccines.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref236">236</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref238">238</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref242">242</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref243">243</xref>
 </sup> The main techniques of EM microscopy to analyze the virus structures are negative staining, thin sectioning, immune electron microscopy (IEM), cryoelectron microscopy (cryo-EM), tomography, and scanning electron microscopy (SEM). In negative staining, the background is stained, leaving the actual specimen untouched and thus visible. Thin sectioning is used to reduce the viruses into thin layers to be transparent for electrons. The principle of IEM is the formation of immune complexes of the virus with its associated antibody. The cryo-EM is an imaging procedure used to generate high-resolution 3D images of samples, commonly biological materials and cells. In this method, a series of two-dimensional (2D) images of sample are captured while it is tilted at different angles, and then, the 2D images are merged to reconstruct 3D image.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref243">243</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref245">245</xref>
 </sup> On the other hand, SEM has also been used for virus quantification procedures.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref246">246</xref>
 </sup> It should be noted that SEM if combined with the abilities of transmission electron microscopy (TEM) can also provide high-resolution images of virus structure with minute structural details for improved characterization of viruses.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref237">237</xref>
 </sup> In the past using EM techniques, SARS was classified as a coronavirus.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref247">247</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref248">248</xref>
 </sup> EM was used in the recognition of MERS,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref249">249</xref>
 </sup> and the image of COVID-19 virus was taken by TEM,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref250">250</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref251">251</xref>
 </sup> see 
 <xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>
 </xref> for more details.
</p>
