<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Genomic sequence studies displayed that the spike protein of SARS‐CoV‐2 has high identity with that of SARS and MERS, which might indicate the similarity of immune evasion mechanism among SARS‐CoV‐2, SARS and MERS.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0104" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>104</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0105" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>105</sup>
 </xref> On the basis of knowledges obtained from SARS and MERS vaccine development, several research groups have announced to start SARS‐CoV‐2 vaccine R&amp;D immediately after the global outbreak.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0106" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>106</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0107" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>107</sup>
 </xref> As was reported, receptor‐binding domain in full‐length spike (S) or S1 was crucial for SARS‐CoV‐2 entry into the host cell.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>25</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0107" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>107</sup>
 </xref> This protein is a good vaccine antigen‐inducing neutralizing antibodies to prevent host cell attachment and against coronavirus infection.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0108" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>108</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0109" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>109</sup>
 </xref> Live attenuated vaccines and inactivated vaccines are based on whole virion.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>37</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0110" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>110</sup>
 </xref> During Zika virus outbreak, DNA vaccine was the first vaccine candidate that entered clinical trial.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0111" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>111</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0112" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>112</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0113" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>113</sup>
 </xref> So far, WHO has listed the detailed information of 86 vaccines under development worldwide, including DNA, RNA, adenoviral vector and recombinant protein vaccine, and six of them have entered into clinical trial (Supplementary Table). To develop SARS‐CoV‐2 vaccine successfully, important information related to vaccine development and evaluation should be well defined, including targeted antigen(s), immunization route, related immune protection, animal models, outbreak forecasting and targeted population.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0113" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>113</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0114" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>114</sup>
 </xref> However, the production process and preclinical information of vaccines should be assessed to ensure volunteers’ safety prior to clinical testing.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0114" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>114</sup>
 </xref> In a recent interview of the Harvard Office of Technology Development (OTD), researchers suggested that further research and development on a class of molecules called bisphosphonates might turbocharge a vaccine against SARS‐CoV‐2 and help bring immunity to huge populations more quickly.
 <xref rid="jcmm15364-bib-0115" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>115</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
