<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The PCA was performed using R software to preselect the environmental variables that had the greatest influence on the distributions of each disease [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005959.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. The PCA approach was used for two reasons. First, PCA facilitates the identification and elimination of covariant variables, which is a key procedure for avoiding analytical artefacts. Second, PCA has been widely used in equivalent studies and then facilitates comparisons, reproducibility, and future meta-analysis. After the PCA, we selected the four most representative eigenvectors of the variables for each disease, which were used for Maxent analysis (version 3.3.3 k: a machine learning algorithm for modeling species distributions based on existing data and environmental variables) [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005959.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005959.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The data selection was performed according to the criterion of maximum entropy, with the original variables that reached maximum and minimum values within the ordered ranking of each principal component, because they describe the full range of data variation. The Maxent model may be expressed as: 
 <disp-formula id="pntd.0005959.e001">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="pntd.0005959.e001.jpg" id="pntd.0005959.e001g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M1">
    <mi mathvariant="bold">p</mi>
    <mo>[</mo>
    <mrow>
     <msub>
      <mrow>
       <mi mathvariant="bold">f</mi>
      </mrow>
      <mrow>
       <mi mathvariant="bold">j</mi>
      </mrow>
     </msub>
    </mrow>
    <mo>]</mo>
    <mo>=</mo>
    <mfrac>
     <mrow>
      <mn mathvariant="bold">1</mn>
     </mrow>
     <mrow>
      <mi mathvariant="bold">N</mi>
     </mrow>
    </mfrac>
    <mrow>
     <munderover>
      <mo stretchy="false">∑</mo>
      <mrow>
       <mi mathvariant="bold">i</mi>
       <mo>=</mo>
       <mn mathvariant="bold">1</mn>
      </mrow>
      <mrow>
       <mi mathvariant="bold">N</mi>
      </mrow>
     </munderover>
     <mrow>
      <msub>
       <mrow>
        <mi mathvariant="bold">f</mi>
       </mrow>
       <mrow>
        <mi mathvariant="bold">i</mi>
       </mrow>
      </msub>
      <mo>(</mo>
      <msub>
       <mrow>
        <mi mathvariant="bold">x</mi>
       </mrow>
       <mrow>
        <mi mathvariant="bold">i</mi>
       </mrow>
      </msub>
      <mo>)</mo>
     </mrow>
    </mrow>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </disp-formula> Where: x
 <sup>*</sup> = the geographical region of interest; x = {x
 <sub>1</sub>,x
 <sub>2</sub> …, x
 <sub>N</sub>} with x ∈ x
 <sup>*</sup>; x → observed points at x
 <sup>*</sup>; f
 <sub>j</sub> = f
 <sub>1´</sub>, f
 <sub>2´</sub> …,f
 <sub>m</sub> (environmental variables); N = the number of observed cases; and p = the probability of disease occurrence. The model was run 25 times, while withholding a difference of 10% of the localities for each run to estimate the parameters and its precision. The potential distribution maps were created by interpolating the occurrence points and the similarity measures of the environmental variables in each pixel (i.e., a known observation probability value can be assigned to each pixel by calculating a probability whose exponent is a quadratic function). To describe the temperature change patterns in Brazil during the sampled 50 years, we used the kriging method [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005959.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005959.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] and data from approximately 250 monitoring stations throughout Brazil. This approach generated a map by estimating the value at each node of a regular grid, which was superimposed over the area of interest, and then a contouring program was applied to draw iso-level curves. We used a 250 × 250 grid of Brazil map, which provides 62,500 sections, because it was the maximum map resolution with a minimum required amount of computational time. R software [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005959.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] was also used to evaluate the temporal trend in temperature during the last five decades.
</p>
