<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Future climate data were integrated using two global climate models (GCMs): the HadGEM2-ES [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005959.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] and MIROC-5 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005959.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], which were selected for their different strengths. The HadGEM2-ES model is a stable model that represents a realistic state of the climate, vegetation, and oceanic biology, without the need for artificial corrections. On the other hand, the MIROC-5 model also includes components of the Earth’s system and climate change, in relation to anthropogenic radiation. The advantage of using this model is that it increases the accuracy of short-term climate prediction, as it can be affected by both anthropogenic and intrinsic fluctuations of the climate system. The spatial resolution of the GCMs was the same as that of the environmental variables (30 arc-seconds, approximately 1 km). The comparison method was the same as for the Maxent model, although the probability calculation for the GCMs incorporated a comparison of the present and future environmental conditions. To obtain future climate scenarios using GCMs, it is also necessary to choose a condition for evolution of the greenhouse gas emissions (GGE), during the period when the future climate is projected. In our prediction we used two different scenarios: low emission (RCP 2.6) and very high emission (RCP 8.5), detailed in the Special Report on Emissions Scenarios by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005959.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. In the first case, the global temperature tends to increase by 1.0°C and can reach a temperature anomaly ranging from 0.4 to 1.6°C and 0.3 to 1.7°C between 2046–2065 and 2081–2100, respectively [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005959.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. In the second scenario, with high GGE, the global temperature tends to increase 2.0 to 3.7°C and can reach to a thermal anomaly ranging from 1.4 to 2.6°C and 2.6 to 4.8°C between 2046–2065 and 2081–2100, respectively [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005959.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0005959.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>].
</p>
