<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0020">There is insufficient information on population-based molecular and sero-surveillance approaches alongside longitudinal or cohort molecular and immunological studies. There is an urgent need to establish the link between the spectrum of risk factors of Zika epidemics and/or other arbovirus-vectors and disease transmission dynamics, resurgence and spread, as well as immune status and acquired immune response either locally, regionally or globally (
 <xref rid="bb0230" ref-type="bibr">Petersen et al., 2016a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">Diagne et al., 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr">Musso et al., 2015a</xref>). There is also insufficient indication on previous studies aiming at understanding of the interaction between the 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> vector and pathogen in relation to the exposure frequency and duration and its impact on vector competence, virus abundance, virulence and related severity (
 <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">Diagne et al., 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Kean et al., 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">Bogoch et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">Baba et al., 2013</xref>). It is well documented that prior viral innate and acquired immune-stimulatory responses play a vital role in subsequent exposure or population protection and defense against foreign pathogens including ZIKV and other related arboviral diseases (e.g.: Dengue virus (DENV), Chikungunya virus (CKHIKV), Yellow fever (YF), Rift valley Fever (RVF), Encephalitis) (
 <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">Bogoch et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">Baba et al., 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0185" ref-type="bibr">Meister et al., 2008</xref>). However, there is need to assess the new Zika virus public health threat in the context of evolving transmission and dual burden with other viral/immunocompromized diseases such as Dengue and HIV/AIDS to measure associated intervention programs effectiveness (e.g. molecular epidemiology approaches) in arbovirus affected countries (
 <xref rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr">Musso et al., 2015a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr">Papa et al., 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed and Broor, 2014</xref>). Moreover, comprehensive quality data and information is required to strengthen local and/or national ZIKV surveillance for preparedness, prevention and improved emergency response capacity, improved integrated vector control programs, management in guiding informed-decision making policies, innovative programs and measuring effectiveness of interventions for effective outcomes and more informed public health choices (
 <xref rid="bb0235" ref-type="bibr">Petersen et al., 2016b</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0185" ref-type="bibr">Meister et al., 2008</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr">Papa et al., 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">Kam et al., 2015</xref>).
</p>
