<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0360">Different researches also focused on the administration of LPV/RTV with other drugs to improve their efficacy in COVID-19 patients. A randomized clinical assay in six hospitals in Hong Kong conducted by Hung et al.
 <xref rid="b0865" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>173</sup>
 </xref> investigated whether the administration of LPV/RTV plus interferon beta-1b and ribavirin could present better outcomes than the treatment with LPV/RTV alone. The 127 adult patients were randomly divided into two groups: the combination group was given LPV/RTV (400 mg/100 mg respectively) every 12 h, ribavirin (400 mg) each 12 h and subcutaneous injections of 1–3 doses of interferon beta-1b (1 mL) in alternate days. Control group was given lopinavir/ritonavir (400 mg/100 mg respectively) every 12 h. Both groups were medicated for 14 days. The treatment that combined the three drugs suppressed viral loads in all clinical samples (nasopharyngeal, saliva from the throat, back of the oropharyngeal and faeces) after 8 days of treatment whereas the control group suppressed viral load after 12 days of treatment in average. The triple combination also achieved relief of symptoms at day 4, as well as reduction of IL-6 levels and shorter hospital stays. Adverse effects in both groups involved diarrhoea and vomiting. Therefore, the therapeutic efficacy of the triple combination was confirmed, and demands clinical trials. The mechanism of actions responsible for the good results of LPV/RTV against SARS-CoV-2 are not fully elucidated. The 
 <italic>in-vitro</italic> assays that analysed the effects of LPV/RTV and two coronavirus proteases, endopeptidase C30 (a homo-dimer with no ligand, built by taking PDB:4MDS 3CL
 <sup>pro</sup> as template) and papain like viral protease (PLVP), suggest that effects of Kaletra are related to protease C30 inhibition with consequent antiviral effects through inhibition of SARS-CoV-2 protein synthesis.
 <xref rid="b0870" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>174</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
