<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The high prevalence (∼60%) of FFV identified in Colorado puma population’s documents endemic infection in this region (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="vez058-F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). This prevalence is on the high end of what has been reported in domestic cat populations (range 8–80%, (
 <xref rid="vez058-B85" ref-type="bibr">Winkler, Löchelt, and Flower 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vez058-B64" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura et al. 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="vez058-B70" ref-type="bibr">Powers et al. 2018</xref>). Reported seroprevalence was even higher (77.3%) which is likely due to higher sensitivity of ELISA compared with PCR (
 <xref rid="vez058-B39" ref-type="bibr">Kechejian et al. 2019</xref>). Identification of FFV positive pumas from Florida and California indicates this virus is not limited to Colorado puma populations, and is widely spread across free-ranging populations. We found little statistical support for increased infection rate with sex (GLMM pMCMC &gt; 0.05) or age (GLMM pMCMC &gt; 0.05), indicating that FFV is readily transmitted between the sexes, and is not age dependent—providing strong support for social transmission mechanisms such as grooming. Although sex and age were not found to be risk factors for FFV infection, their inclusion in our GLMMs improved model fit suggesting they may still influence FFV transmission. Recent work by our research group has indicated age and/or sex to be risk factors that vary by population (
 <xref rid="vez058-B39" ref-type="bibr">Kechejian et al. 2019</xref>), so the impact of these factors on risk of infection has yet to be fully elucidated. Juvenile-originating FFV sequences were dispersed throughout the phylogeny, and commonly nested most closely to those from adults, a pattern suggesting transmission from parent to offspring (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="vez058-F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Additionally, lack of phylogenetic stratification by sex indicates transmission between males and females occurs commonly (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="vez058-F2">Fig. 2</xref>).
</p>
