<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>COVID-19 is a new strain of coronavirus not previously identified in humans.
 <xref rid="dyaa033-B36" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>36</sup>
 </xref> Coronaviruses are zoonotic and are a large family of viruses that cause illness ranging from the common cold to more severe diseases, such as MERS and SARS.
 <xref rid="dyaa033-B21" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>21</sup>
 </xref> Initially, many of the patients in the outbreak in Wuhan reported some link to a large seafood and live-animal market, suggesting zoonotic transmission. Scientists also believe that an animal source is ‘the most likely primary source’, and human-to-human transmission has occurred, with growing numbers of cases reportedly without exposure to animal markets.
 <xref rid="dyaa033-B3" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> Early in the outbreak, a top Chinese government-appointed expert stated a mysterious respiratory illness had killed at least four people with evidence of human-to-human transmission, heightening public concern.
 <xref rid="dyaa033-B36" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>36</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="dyaa033-B37" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>37</sup>
 </xref> It is likely that person-to-person spread will continue to occur, and similarities can be drawn more closely to SARS than MERS, because of the virus’ rapid rate of infection.
 <xref rid="dyaa033-B38" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>38</sup>
 </xref> When person-to-person spread occurred with SARS and MERS, it is thought to have happened via respiratory droplets produced when an infected person coughs or sneezes, similar to how other respiratory pathogens spread.
 <xref rid="dyaa033-B12" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="dyaa033-B29" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>29</sup>
 </xref> This is the same hypothesized mechanism of transmission for COVID-19. The spread of MERS and SARS between people has generally occurred between close contacts, similar to the current epidemic in China. According to the WHO, common signs of COVID-19 infection include respiratory symptoms, fever, cough, shortness of breath and breathing difficulties. Serious cases can lead to pneumonia, severe acute respiratory syndrome, kidney failure and death.
 <xref rid="dyaa033-B39" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>39</sup>
 </xref> The WHO has advised avoidance of ‘unprotected’ contact with live animals, to thoroughly cook meat and eggs, and avoiding close contact with anyone with cold or flu-like symptoms. Additionally, the CDC issued a travel statement to avoid all non-essential travel to China (Level 3 Travel Notice).
 <xref rid="dyaa033-B40" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>40</sup>
 </xref> Control measures have been put into effect, although the timing of these measures and the relatively rapid spread of the current virus suggests that lessons from the previous SARS and MERS epidemics were not heeded.
</p>
