<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24">For the planning and execution of control programmes against viral disease, it is necessary to fully understand the disease, particularly the interaction between the host and the pathogen as well as between the pathogen and the host vis-à-vis the environment. This knowledge should include the duration of incubation period; pathogenesis; route of entry of virus in the host species; extent and duration of excretion of the virus from the host; reservoir and carrier hosts; duration and mechanism of interepidemic survival of the virus; survival of the virus in nature including its susceptibility to high and low temperature, freezing and thawing, acid and alkaline pH and disinfectants; survival in body fluids; and antigenic variations, such as types, subtypes, clades and genotypes, particularly in RNA viruses. Appropriate knowledge of these parameters will be very useful in planning and implementing cost-effective disease control programmes. For example, in case of equine influenza, the knowledge that the virus is excreted for not more than 10 days from the infected animal can be used with advantage to check the spread of infection by restricting animal movements from infected to healthy premises and vice versa for 2 weeks. Similarly, all direct and indirect contacts between the sick and healthy animals and farms need to be avoided, besides symptomatic palliative treatment and complete rest to the sick animal to avoid secondary bacterial complications. In case the fever lasts for more than 3 days, antibiotic therapy should be considered to combat secondary bacterial infections. A three-day rest is recommended for each day of fever the animal had run in equine influenza. Influenza virus is highly susceptible to freezing and thawing and common disinfectants, such as Dettol, Savlon, 70% alcohol, phenyl, KMNO
 <sub>4</sub>, ultraviolet light and sunlight, but fairly resistant to sodium carbonate (Na
 <sub>2</sub>CO
 <sub>3</sub>) and sodium hydroxide (Yadav et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">1993</xref>). Thus, suitable cost-effective disinfectants may be used for decontamination of the stables and adjoining premises, ropes of animals, hands, shoes and clothing of animal attendants. The outbreaks of influenza, which are more common during winters, fade away in summer due to the susceptibility of the virus to high ambient temperatures.
</p>
