<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The first step was intended to clarify the influence of the rodent community composition on the occurrence of HFRS. Matrix 
 <italic>β</italic> represented an influencing parameter that, can be calculated from matrices 
 <italic>R</italic> and 
 <italic>C</italic>. In detail, 
 <italic>R</italic> represents a matrix comprising the proportions of HFRS cases among the different land-use types in different years, whose rows represent the proportions of HFRS cases for one land-use type in different years and whose columns represent the proportions of HFRS cases in the same year for the different land types. Matrix 
 <italic>C</italic> was built using the rodent surveillance data. We calculated the proportion of different rodent species (
 <italic>R</italic>. 
 <italic>norvegicus</italic>, 
 <italic>M</italic>. 
 <italic>musculus</italic>, 
 <italic>R</italic>. 
 <italic>flavipectus</italic>, and other rodent species, mainly 
 <italic>R</italic>. 
 <italic>losea</italic> and 
 <italic>Microtus fortis calamorum</italic>) each year and arrange them as matrix 
 <italic>C</italic>, with the rows representing the proportions of the same rodent species in different years and the columns representing the proportions of different rodent species in the same year. We then used the following formula to calculate matrix 
 <italic>β</italic> so as to determine how the rodent community composition influenced the occurrence of HFRS in the different land-use types: 
 <disp-formula id="pntd.0006881.e002">
  <alternatives>
   <graphic xlink:href="pntd.0006881.e002.jpg" id="pntd.0006881.e002g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M2">
    <mrow>
     <msub>
      <mi>R</mi>
      <mrow>
       <mi>i</mi>
       <mi>j</mi>
      </mrow>
     </msub>
     <mo>=</mo>
     <mstyle displaystyle="true">
      <munderover>
       <mo>∑</mo>
       <mrow>
        <mi>k</mi>
        <mo>=</mo>
        <mn>1</mn>
       </mrow>
       <mi>K</mi>
      </munderover>
      <mrow>
       <msub>
        <mi>β</mi>
        <mrow>
         <mi>i</mi>
         <mi>k</mi>
        </mrow>
       </msub>
       <mo>×</mo>
       <msub>
        <mi>C</mi>
        <mrow>
         <mi>k</mi>
         <mi>j</mi>
        </mrow>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
     </mstyle>
    </mrow>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
  <label>(2)</label>
 </disp-formula> where 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>ij</italic>
 </sub> is the proportion of HFRS cases in area 
 <italic>i</italic> in year 
 <italic>j</italic>, 
 <italic>β</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>ik</italic>
 </sub> is the potential contact probability between human and rodent species 
 <italic>k</italic> in area 
 <italic>i</italic>, and 
 <italic>C</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>kj</italic>
 </sub> is the proportion of rodent species 
 <italic>k</italic> in year 
 <italic>j</italic> (
 <italic>i</italic> = 1,2,…,5; 
 <italic>j</italic> = 1,2,…,10; 
 <italic>k</italic> = 4).
</p>
