<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The first and major control measure should be to take precautions so that an Avian Influenza virus does not cross the “species barrier” and infect human. If it crosses the “species barrier” and infects people, then the medical doctor should be contacted to take the proper medicine and suggestion for precautions. The persons dealing with poultry or poultry products should take the following prevention measures:
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p>Practice proper sanitation and good hygiene handling of poultry and poultry products,</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Wear masks, rubber gloves, and safety glasses,</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Avoid unnecessary contact with live, sick, or dead birds,</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Keep hands away from face and mouth when handling birds,</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Practice proper hand washing, cleaning and disinfection procedures, and avoid touching mouth or eyes. Indirect contact with door knobs, toilet knobs, taps, hand shaking etc., is another possible method of transmission,</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Wash eggs thoroughly with soap water, rinse, and thoroughly cook at the temperature more than 74 °C, cook chicken until boiling temperature or when cooking temperature exceeds 165 °F (74 °C), because H5N1 viruses are killed at this temperature,</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Store and prepare raw chicken and eggs separately from other food items to avoid cross contamination,</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Clean kitchen utensils and surfaces before and after use,</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>There should be routine tests for AIV in poultry and if any positive case is seen, the entire poultry flock and poultry products should be destroyed and should not be consumed by the public at any cost.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Report any unusual death or illness of chickens and other birds to the Dead Bird Hotline (888) 551-4636 and report illness among workers in poultry farms to the Health Department.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
