<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Indian J Med Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Indian J. Med. Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJMR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Indian Journal of Medical Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0971-5916</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer - Medknow</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6886132</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31719291</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJMR-150-217</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ijmr.IJMR_2034_18</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Perspective</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Influenza pandemic preparedness: A special challenge for India</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fedson</surname><given-names>David S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">57 chemin du Lavoir, 01630 Sergy haut, France <email xlink:href="davidsfedson@gmail.com">davidsfedson@gmail.com</email></aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>150</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2019 Indian Journal of Medical Research</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0"><license-p>This is an open access journal, and articles are distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as appropriate credit is given and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p>This past year, we commemorated the 100<sup>th</sup> anniversary of the 1918 influenza pandemic, which is estimated to have killed 50-100 million people worldwide<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>. Its impact in India was especially severe; 10-20 million people may have died<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>. Since 1997, influenza scientists and public health officials have been concerned about a potential pandemic caused by the highly virulent avian influenza A(H5N1) virus<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>. More recently, concern has been shifted to the H7N9 virus. In one study of 1241 hospitalized H7N9 patients in China, 70 per cent were treated with antiviral agents, but the overall case fatality rate was still 40 per cent<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>. A recent study has estimated that during the next pandemic, almost 33 million people will die during the first six months<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>. Thus, regardless of which new influenza virus emerges, the risk of a devastating global pandemic is alarmingly real.</p><p>Currently, public health officials are counting on vaccines as the first line of pandemic defence. The World Health Organization (WHO) has led a vigorous effort to expand seasonal influenza vaccine production in low- and middle-income countries, including India<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref><xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>. Seasonal influenza is responsible for appreciable morbidity and mortality in developing countries<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, and expanded vaccine production might reduce this burden by improving vaccination rates. International trends, however, are not encouraging. An ongoing survey of 201 countries has shown that annual influenza vaccine distribution rates in many countries have plateaued, and in some, the rates are actually falling<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>. In the countries of Southeast Asia, the eastern Mediterranean and Africa, which account for at least half the global population, hardly any seasonal influenza vaccine is used. Moreover, it will take time to produce pandemic vaccines, so they will not be available in any country during the first six pandemic months<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>.</p><p>Physicians count on antiviral drugs to treat individual patients<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>. Anti-neuraminidase inhibitors are only modestly effective in reducing mortality due to seasonal influenza, and antiviral resistance is always a threat. Newer antiviral drugs are being developed, but even if they are efficacious, they may be no more effective than the current antivirals. In addition, the development of antiviral resistance is also a possibility. Thus, given the absence of both pandemic vaccines and highly effective antiviral treatments, it takes little imagination to recognize that human experience during the next pandemic could be similar to what it was 100 years ago<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>.</p><p>Not everyone infected with influenza virus dies. In the 1918 pandemic, approximately one-third of the human population was infected but a much smaller proportion died. Moreover, pandemic mortality was much higher in young adults than in children. Thus, for each individual, the host response seems to be a central determinant of disease severity<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>. This gives us reason to be hopeful; instead of targeting the virus with vaccines and antivirals, physicians might be able to improve survival by treating patients with drugs that modify the host response to infection.</p><p>The idea of treating the host response is &#x0003e;10 yr old<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, and it is supported by a large body of experimental evidence and several observational studies<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref><xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref><xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>. The host response may involve mechanisms that enhance resistance (which reduces pathogen burden) or tolerance (which reduces the impact of infection). In 1918, mortality rates were much lower in children than those in young adults, but the better survival of children was not unique: similar age-related mortality differences have been seen with other virus and bacterial diseases<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>. Recently, this difference has been experimentally reproduced in pre- and post-pubertal mice that were either infected with an influenza virus or treated with endotoxin<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>. Because influenza virus titres and endotoxin levels were similar in both groups, the better survival of pre-pubertal mice suggested that they were more tolerant, not more resistant. Their better tolerance likely reflects the heritage of evolution.</p><p>Among the drugs that have received attention for host response treatment are statins and angiotensin receptor blockers (ARBs). During the Ebola outbreak in Sierra Leone in 2014, combination treatment with these two drugs apparently led to &#x0201c;remarkable improvement&#x0201d; in the patient survival<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>. These drugs have multiple beneficial effects on the host response, including the restoration of endothelial barrier integrity, a central abnormality in the pathogenesis of acute lung injury<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref><xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>. They also accelerate the return of mitochondrial biogenesis, affect T-cell and macrophage polarization and modify the 'cytokine storm'<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref><xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>. Their potential effectiveness in treating human influenza has been suggested by the activity of an experimental drug that specifically restored endothelial barrier integrity in a mouse model of influenza<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>. In this study, drug treatment significantly improved survival without affecting virus replication, whereas antiviral treatment alone was ineffective. Other investigators have shown that not only do statins and ARBs restore endothelial barrier integrity, they reduce virus replication<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref><xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>. Other generic drug combinations might also be used to treat the host response to influenza<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> and sepsis<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>.</p><p>The idea of treating the host response to pandemic influenza has a highly plausible scientific rationale, but for global public health it is overwhelmingly compelling: simply put, there is no available practical alternative that physicians might use to reduce pandemic mortality. Many of the drugs being considered are produced as inexpensive generics in developing countries, including India. These drugs are widely available and are used by physicians in the daily care of patients. In spite of this, influential influenza scientists and health officials (including those at WHO) have shown no interest in this idea. Several reasons have been invoked to explain their lack of interest, including herding behaviour and social bias<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>. The idea of treating the host response means they risk losing power, influence, reputation and financial support<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>.</p><p>In the absence of interest on the part of the usual authorities, people everywhere need to ask 'who is responsible for global pandemic preparedness?' Should we depend on a 'top down' process in which a small group of elite scientists and health officials decide which interventions to study in the hope that one or more of them might affect the course of the next global pandemic? Should these elites be allowed to exclude from consideration an alternative 'bottom up' approach to patient care that is scientifically plausible, eminently practical and could have an immense impact on global health, equity and security? The answer to this question is obvious. If treatment with inexpensive and widely available generic drugs could be convincingly shown to work, patients in any country with a basic healthcare system could be treated on the first pandemic day. It follows that in the absence of support for this idea, clinicians might have to undertake studies on their own to show that treating the host response is effective<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>. This includes physicians in India. An agenda for this research has been published (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table</xref>)<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table</label><caption><p>An agenda for Indian physicians who will undertake research on treating the host response to pandemic influenza and other emerging virus diseases</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Choose drugs that are</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Known to modify mechanisms involved in the host response to infection</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Safe in patients with critical illness</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Produced as inexpensive generics</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Widely available in low- and middle-income countries</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Familiar to practicing physicians</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Likely to affect important outcomes (<italic>e.g</italic>., 28 days&#x02019; all-cause mortality)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before the emergence of a new virus</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Undertake observational studies and prospective clinical trials of treatment in patients hospitalized with everyday illnesses, for example, seasonal influenza, community-acquired pneumonia and sepsis</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study outcomes in children and adults</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evaluate outcomes in hospitalized patients who are treated with these drugs, both individually and in combination</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plan observational and prospective studies to be undertaken when a new virus emerges</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prepare for clinical studies to be undertaken when a new influenza or other virus emerges</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plan observational studies of treatment effectiveness</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Consult with scientists who understand the biology of the host response (<italic>e.g</italic>., vascular biology, mitochondrial biogenesis and immunometabolism)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Choose two or three drugs for clinical trials, especially in combinations</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prepare clinical trial protocols for children and adults</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Consult with statisticians on a study design and a plan for evaluating results</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Involve a local ethics review committee</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organize a data safety monitoring board</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obtain logistical and financial support</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">If needed, assemble networks of physicians who will participate in multicentre trials</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plan what to do with the results</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Identify local sources of supply for potentially efficacious drugs, quantities usually supplied, capacities for surge production and distribution, need for stockpiling and logistics for delivery</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Determine drug costs for public programmes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prepare plans to communicate trial results to physicians, public health officials and the public</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic>Source</italic>: Ref <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, reproduced with permission</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>It is important to recognize that treating the host response is an approach that might be used in patients with other forms of acute critical illness. It appeared to work in patients with Ebola<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> and it would probably work in any illness that involves endothelial dysfunction and the loss of vascular barrier integrity, for example, other emerging virus diseases, sepsis, community-acquired pneumonia and even sporadic illnesses like Hantavirus infection<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>. It could also be considered for treating patients with Nipah virus infection, a recent problem in India<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>. This disease is characterized by endothelial dysfunction<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, and statins and ARBs have beneficial effects on endothelial cells, including those in the brain<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref><xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>.</p><p>There is no guarantee that treating the host response will be effective, but we urgently need to find out. If a highly virulent and easily transmissible pandemic influenza virus emerges, it will spread rapidly throughout the world, overwhelming healthcare systems everywhere. In the absence of pandemic vaccines and effective antiviral treatments, the only way Indian physicians might reduce pandemic mortality will be to treat seriously ill patients with easily administered inexpensive generic drugs that are already available and that modify the host response to infection. In countries like India, the challenge of the next pandemic must make this the central element of preparedness planning.</p></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold><italic>Conflicts of Interest</italic>:</bold> None.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Feehan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimation of potential global pandemic influenza mortality on the basis of vital registry data from the 1918-20 pandemic: A quantitative analysis</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2006</year><volume>368</volume><fpage>2211</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17189032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The 1918-1919 influenza pandemic &#x02013; The Indian experience</article-title><source>Indian Econ Soc Hist Rev</source><year>1986</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11617178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kassens-Noor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The evolution of pandemic influenza: Evidence from India, 1918-19</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>510</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25234688</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fedson</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunnill</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Commentary: From scarcity to abundance: Pandemic vaccines and other agents for &#x0201c;have not&#x0201d; countries</article-title><source>J Public Health Policy</source><year>2007</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17717543</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Uyeki</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of avian influenza A H7N9 virus in human beings across five epidemics in mainland China, 2013-17: An epidemiological study of laboratory-confirmed case series</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>822</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28583578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gates</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Innovation for pandemics</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2018</year><volume>378</volume><fpage>2057</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29847763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gellin</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Qadri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preparing for the unpredictable: The continuing need for pandemic influenza preparedness</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><year>2016</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>5391</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27682508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>World Health Organization</collab><source>Global influenza strategy 2019-2030. License: CC BY-NY-SA 3.0 IGO</source><year>2019</year><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iuliano</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Roguski</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Muscatello</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Palekar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tempia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Estimates of global seasonal influenza-associated respiratory mortality: A modelling study</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2018</year><volume>391</volume><fpage>1285</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29248255</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palache</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abelin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollingsworth</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cracknell</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Survey of distribution of seasonal influenza vaccine doses in 201 countries (2004-2015): The 2003 World Health Assembly resolution on seasonal influenza vaccination coverage and the 2009 influenza pandemic have had very little impact on improving influenza control and pandemic preparedness</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><year>2017</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>4681</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28754488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>World Health Organization</collab><source>Influenza vaccine response during the start of a pandemic. Report of a WHO informal consultation</source><year>2015</year><publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc><publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treating influenza infection, from now and into the future</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1946</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30250466</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Starr</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influenza in 1918: Recollections of the epidemic in Philadelphia 1976</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>138</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16801626</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pirofski</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Casadevall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The damage- response framework as a tool for the physician-scientist to understand the pathogenesis of infectious diseases</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2018</year><volume>218</volume><fpage>S7</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30124977</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fedson</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pandemic influenza: A potential role for statins in treatment and prophylaxis</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2006</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16779747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fedson</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treating influenza with statins and other immunomodulatory agents</article-title><source>Antiviral Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23831494</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fedson</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How will physicians respond to the next influenza pandemic?</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2014</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24145877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fedson</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treating the host response to emerging virus diseases: Lessons learned from sepsis, pneumonia, influenza and Ebola</article-title><source>Ann Transl Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>421</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27942512</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fedson</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influenza, evolution, and the next pandemic</article-title><source>Evol Med Public Health</source><year>2018</year><volume>2018</volume><fpage>260</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30455951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hough</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Gusarova</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endothelial mitochondria determine rapid barrier failure in chemical lung injury</article-title><source>JCI Insight</source><year>2019</year><volume>4</volume><comment>pii: 124329</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Leong-Poi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Advani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Tie2-agonist Vasculotide rescues mice from influenza virus infection</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>11030</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26046800</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehrbod</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hair-Bejo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tengku Ibrahim</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>El Zowalaty</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ajdari</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Simvastatin modulates cellular components in influenza A virus-infected cells</article-title><source>Int J Mol Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24788303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Angiotensin II receptor blocker as a novel therapy in acute lung injury induced by avian influenza A H5N1 virus infection in mouse</article-title><source>Sci China Life Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25655897</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>IFN</given-names></name><name><surname>To</surname><given-names>KKW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>JFW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>VCC</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>KSH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of clarithromycin-naproxen-oseltamivir combination in the treatment of patients hospitalized for influenza A(H3N2) infection: An open-label randomized, controlled, phase IIb/III trial</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>2017</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>1069</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27884765</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marik</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Khangoora</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hooper</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Catravas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrocortisone, vitamin C, and thiamine for the treatment of severe sepsis and septic shock: A retrospective before-after study</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>2017</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>1229</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27940189</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baddeley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Herding, social influences and behavioural bias in scientific research: Simple awareness of the hidden pressures and beliefs that influence our thinking can help to preserve objectivity</article-title><source>EMBO Rep</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>902</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26169390</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fedson</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinician-initiated research on treating the host response to pandemic influenza</article-title><source>Hum Vaccin Immunother</source><year>2018</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>790</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29058516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donaldson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhancing preparation for large Nipah outbreaks beyond Bangladesh: Preventing a tragedy like Ebola in West Africa</article-title><source>Int J Infect Dis</source><year>2018</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29879523</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maisner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Neufeld</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Weingartl</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Organ- and endotheliotropism of Nipah virus infections <italic>in vivo</italic> and <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title><source>Thromb Haemost</source><year>2009</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>1014</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19967130</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao-Ping</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Atorvastatin prevents angiotensin II-induced high permeability of human arterial endothelial cell monolayers via ROCK signaling pathway</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2015</year><volume>459</volume><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25712521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kono</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Omote</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hishikawa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neurovascular protection by telmisartan via reducing neuroinflammation in stroke-resistant spontaneously hypertensive rat brain after ischemic stroke</article-title><source>J Stroke Cerebrovasc Dis</source><year>2015</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25534368</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>