<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Most of the rare diseases correspond to orphan disease, but not always. One of the prime examples of the rare orphan disease is the Tuberous sclerosis complex [
 <xref rid="B68-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. It is a rare autosomal dominant genetic disease resulting from the mutations in the 
 <italic>TSC1</italic> and 
 <italic>TSC2</italic> genes, which encode for hamartin and tuberin, respectively [
 <xref rid="B69-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. This hamartin-tuberin complex regulates the mammalian target of Rapamycin (mTOR), which acts as a tumour-growth suppressor, controlling the cell growth and proliferation. It is highly associated with many non-cancerous tumours, known as hamartomas [
 <xref rid="B70-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. The prevalence of this genetic disorder is 1 in 6000 new-borns, where the genetic aberrant induces hyperactivity of the mammalian target of Rapamycin (mTOR) [
 <xref rid="B71-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>] and subsequently causes a spur of multiple hamartomas in organs such as the brain, kidneys, skin, lungs, eyes and heart [
 <xref rid="B71-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. These hamartomas can affect the function of many vital organs which result in symptoms including seizures, intellectual disability, developmental delay, behavioural problems, skin abnormalities, lung disease, kidney disease and even death. Everolimus is a drug that addresses this perturbing and fatal genetic disease. Everolimus was first approved in the 1960s to prevent solid organ transplant rejection, augment anticancer treatment regimens and to prevent neovascularisation of artificial cardiac stents. The FDA later approved the use of Everolimus in 2010, and 2012 for TSC-related subependymal giant cell astrocytoma and renal angiomyolipoma, respectively [
 <xref rid="B72-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. This drug successfully helped TSC patients by inhibiting the mTOR pathway, thus preventing the growth of the life-threatening hamartomas. Moreover, Everolimus has shown promising results in several clinical trials on the manifestation of TSC, such as facial angiofibroma, cardiac rhabdomyomas and lymphangioleiomyomatosis (LAM) [
 <xref rid="B72-viruses-12-01058" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>].
</p>
