<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="viruses-11-00190-f009" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 9</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Single-cycle infectious IAV (sciIAV) as LAIV: Schematic representation of sciIAV based on deletions in the PB2 (
   <bold>A</bold>), PB1 (
   <bold>B</bold>), HA (
   <bold>C</bold>), or NA (
   <bold>D</bold>) viral proteins. SciIAV based on a modified uncleavable HA (
   <bold>E</bold>) or a non-functional M2, M2SR (
   <bold>F</bold>) are also indicated. The packaging signals located at the 3’and 5’ ends of each vRNA are indicated with white boxes (
   <bold>A</bold>–
   <bold>F</bold>). Lines at the end of each vRNA indicate the 3’and 5’ NCRs (
   <bold>A</bold>–
   <bold>F</bold>). Striped boxes represent an internal deletion of the PB2 (
   <bold>A</bold>), PB1 (
   <bold>B</bold>), HA (
   <bold>C</bold>), or NA (
   <bold>D</bold>) ORF. A black line represents an amino acid substitution (R325T) in the cleavage site of HA that results in an uncleavable HA protein (
   <bold>E</bold>). A black box represents the deletion of the M2 transmembrane domain (amino acids 25 to 53) that together with the insertion of two stop codons (black lines) downstream of M1 ORF abolish M2 expression (
   <bold>E</bold>). In the case of ∆PB2 (
   <bold>A</bold>), ∆PB1 (
   <bold>B</bold>), ∆HA (
   <bold>C</bold>), uncleavable HA (
   <bold>E</bold>), and M2SR (
   <bold>F</bold>) sciIAVs, efficient viral replication is accomplished by complementation, 
   <italic>in trans</italic>, of the deficient (
   <bold>A</bold>–
   <bold>C</bold>) or mutated (
   <bold>E</bold>–
   <bold>F</bold>) viral proteins by constitutively expressing PB2 (
   <bold>A</bold>), PB1 (
   <bold>B</bold>), HA (
   <bold>C</bold>,
   <bold>E</bold>), or M2 (
   <bold>F</bold>) using stable cell lines. In the case of the ∆NA sciIAV (
   <bold>D</bold>), exogenous NA is provided in the tissue culture supernatant for the efficient release of infectious viral particles.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="viruses-11-00190-g009" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
