<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>COVID-19 fatality rates vary significantly depending on the country; it was 0.06% in Qatar and 16.25% in Belgium as of May 26, 2020 [
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. This variation in fatality rates may be due to differences in healthcare adequacy and/or epidemiological characteristics of patients; the frequency of diagnostic screening in asymptomatic or mildly symptomatic patients may also influence the rate [
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. However, there is a consistent and clear pattern of an age-based exponential increase in fatality rate, regardless of the geographic region. According to the Korea Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, the overall case fatality rate (CFR) was 2.37% in 11,344 patients with confirmed cases on May 28, 2020, but it was much higher in the elderly (10.9% in patients aged 70 – 79 years and 26.6% in patients ≥80 years) [
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In another analysis of 44,672 cases in China diagnosed as of February 11, 2020, the overall CFR was 2.3%. However, the CFR was 8.0% in patients aged 70 – 79 years and 14.8% in patients aged ≥80 years [
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In the report released by the Higher Institute of Health of Italy, the overall CFR on March 26, 2020, was 9.2%, which was four times higher than that in Korea or China; however, the pattern of increasing fatality with age was similar to that in Korea and China. The CFR was &lt;1% in the age group of &lt;50 years and rapidly increased in the age group of ≥60 years, reaching 16.9% and 24.4% in the age group of 70 – 79 years and ≥80 years, respectively (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In terms of death per 100,000 individuals in the population (as of May 11, 2020, data from the New York City Department of Health and Mental Hygiene, and as of May 8, 2020, data from the Office for National Statistics of United Kingdom), clear patterns of age-based exponential increase in fatality has been observed (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].
</p>
