<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Investigating the susceptibility to infection, unlike mortality or case fatality, in the general population is more complicated because mildly symptomatic or asymptomatic patients may not have been tested and there is an uneven chance of being exposed to the source of infection depending on the groups (closure of child care facilities, preschools, and schools 
 <italic>vs</italic>. non-closure of long-term care facilities). The case rate of COVID-19 by age has been reported to have wide regional variability. According to New York City data (as of May 11, 2020), the CFR of COVID-19 in the general population (cases per 100,000) seemed to increase with age (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Contrarily, in Korea (as of May 10, 2020), where diagnostic tests were performed intensely in groups associated with certain religious gatherings, regardless of any symptoms, the CFR seemed to be highest in the 20 – 29-years age group (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Natale 
 <italic>et al</italic>. have compared the relative illness ratio (RIR) by age between different countries (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In their study, as of Mar 30, 2020, the RIR in Spain and Italy increased with age, while in China and Korea [
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], middle or younger age groups seemed to have a higher RIR. This could be explained by more extensive testing performed in China and Korea than in other countries, which would help to better measure the morbidity among young age groups. In Italy and New York City, where there was a surge in the number of COVID-19 patients in a short period, it is likely that the viral test was performed first in individuals with more apparent or severe symptoms, while asymptomatic or mildly symptomatic patients were not tested. Overall, these findings suggest that susceptibility to symptomatic infection seems to increase with age, but susceptibility to infection is probably similar among different age groups.
</p>
