<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Emerging or re-emerging disease outbreaks caused by arboviruses are increasing in Europe. Usually confined to tropical or subtropical countries, their risk of occurrence in Europe (especially in the countries of Western Europe) was considered as relatively low. In a context of global change, with an increase in travel, arboviruses can more easily expand outside of their historical range. Over the last two decades, arboviruses such as dengue, Zika or chikungunya achieved incursions in European countries [
 <xref rid="B1-viruses-11-01059" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-viruses-11-01059" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-viruses-11-01059" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], causing autochthonous human infections [
 <xref rid="B4-viruses-11-01059" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-viruses-11-01059" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-viruses-11-01059" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Susceptible vertebrate hosts and competent vectors can interact, under appropriate environmental and climatic conditions, to cause outbreaks. Knowledge about the vector competence of native species and their distribution, however, remains limited. As such, overwintering thermophilic species are less likely to establish in northern European countries, as the annual isotherm becomes colder. At the present time, 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> is considered as the vector species in autochthonous outbreaks of dengue and chikungunya in France [
 <xref rid="B5-viruses-11-01059" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. While the vector competence of invasive species is widely studied [
 <xref rid="B7-viruses-11-01059" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-11-01059" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-viruses-11-01059" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-viruses-11-01059" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-viruses-11-01059" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], only a few studies are available on native species [
 <xref rid="B12-viruses-11-01059" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Competent native mosquitoes might have the potential to contribute to or to cause local outbreaks in addition to the risk related to invasive species [
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-11-01059" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].
</p>
