<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>NDV strains are categorized based on their pathogenicity in chickens as highly virulent (velogenic), intermediately virulent (mesogenic) or nonvirulent (lentogenic). These levels of pathogenicity can be differentiated by the amino acid sequence of the cleavage site in the fusion protein (F0). Lentogenic NDV strains have dibasic amino acids at the cleavage site whereas the velogenic strains contain polybasic residues. Meng et al. studied the changes in virulence of NDV strains, leading to a switch in lentogenic variant (JS10) to velogenic variant (JS10-A10) through 10 serial passages of the virus in chicken air sacs [
 <xref rid="B128-ijms-20-04657" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. However, the lentogenic variants (JS10) remained lentogenic after 20 serial passages in chicken embryos (JS10-E20). The nearly identical genome sequences of JS10, JS10-A10 and JS10-E20 showed that after passaging, both variants were directly generated from the parental strain (JS10). Genome sequence analysis of the F0 cleavage site of the parental strain and the passaged variants revealed that the rise in virulence observed in the parental strain (JS10) stemmed from a build-up of velogenic quasispecies population together with a gradual disappearance of the lentogenic quasispecies. The decline of the lentogenic F0 genotypes of 
 <sup>112</sup>-E(G)RQE(G)RL-
 <sup>117</sup> from 99.30% to 0.28% and the rise of the velogenic F0 genotypes of 
 <sup>112</sup>-R(K)RQR(K)RF-
 <sup>117</sup> from 0.34% to 94.87% after 10 serial passages in air sacs was hypothesized to be due to the emergence of velogenic F0 genotypes. Subsequently, this led to the enhancement of virulence in JS10-A10. The data indicated that lentogenic NDV strains circulating among poultry could lead to evolution of the velogenic NDV strain. This velogenic NDV strain has the potential to cause outbreaks due to the difficulty in preventing contact between natural waterfowl reservoirs and sensitive poultry operations. 
</p>
