<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0115">In an interview on March 18, the WHO representative in China, Dr. Colliers, said that China has shown the world that the trajectory of the epidemic can be changed. Typically, an epidemic grows exponentially, peaks, and then gradually begins to decline after all susceptible people have been infected or become ill. But that has not occurred in China. The epidemiological curve in China is irregular, the epidemic has been snuffed out in its growth phase, and the transmission of the virus has been blocked, as is clearly shown by both the collected data and the observed social reality. The national emergency response appears to have delayed the growth and limited the size of the COVID-19 epidemic in China, averting hundreds of thousands of cases by 19 February (day 50) [
 <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Chinese experience shows that not all infectious diseases need to manifest as large outbreaks that overwhelm health systems. Every country can learn from this experience and apply the obtained knowledge on its own terms.
 <list list-type="simple" id="lis0005">
  <list-item id="lsti0005">
   <label>(1)</label>
   <p id="par0120">Early detection: Viral detection reagents play an important role in this process. Early in the outbreak, a community in the heart of the Italian epidemic conducted an experiment in controlling the epidemic and was able to stop the rise in cases (all residents were tested repeatedly for the virus, regardless of whether they had symptoms). After the infection is confirmed, strict quarantine measures are imposed on contacts. This highlights the importance of detecting and isolating carriers of the virus. Various measures should be taken to strengthen the effective control of the source of infection.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0010">
   <label>(2)</label>
   <p id="par0125">Early diagnosis: Integrated medical thinking is required because viruses involve the respiratory system, oral cavity, digestive tract, eyes, skin, genital tract, and central nervous system.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0015">
   <label>(3)</label>
   <p id="par0130">Early quarantine: The population is generally susceptible, regardless of race, with slightly more males than females affected, with more older patients and fewer pediatric cases.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0020">
   <label>(4)</label>
   <p id="par0135">Early treatment: Importance should be attached to the use of TCM. In response to this new epidemic, TCM has demonstrated its ability to treat acute and critical diseases, showing that its clinical efficacy is not inferior to that of Western medicine and highlighting the characteristics and advantages of TCM. The role of TCM is also reflected in the whole process of fighting against the epidemic, including prevention, treatment and rehabilitation.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
