<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par58">While hepatitis C surveillance data can serve many useful public health purposes, these data must be collected, stored, shared, and used in a way that protects the identity of infected individuals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]. Countries with a well-established hepatitis C surveillance system may have data security and confidentiality policies and procedures in place while countries that are still developing their surveillance system may not. In general, there are guiding principles [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>] that can be followed by all countries in order to guarantee security and confidentiality of public health data. These principles are summarized below:
 <list list-type="bullet">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par59">Data collection and use policies should respect the rights of individuals and community groups and minimize undue burden.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par60">Program officials should be active, responsible stewards of public health data.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par61">Programs should:
    <list list-type="bullet">
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par62">Require that public health data be acquired, used, disclosed, and stored for legitimate public health purposes</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par63">Collect the minimum amount of personally identifiable information necessary to conduct public health activities</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par64">Have strong policies to protect the privacy and security of personally identifiable data</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par65">Have policies and procedures to ensure the quality of any data they collect or use</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par66">Have the obligation to use and disseminate summary data to relevant stakeholders in a timely manner</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par67">Have public health data maintained in a secure environment and transmitted through secure methods</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par68">Share data for legitimate public health purposes and establish data-use agreements to facilitate sharing data in a timely manner</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item>
      <p id="Par69">Minimize the number of persons and entities granted access to identifiable data</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
