<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">A surveillance program of influenza and other acute respiratory infections (PIDIRAC) was initiated in Catalonia in the 1999–2000 season, based on a network of sentinel primary care physicians (general practitioners and paediatricians) who report influenza-like activity detected in their reference population daily. The aim is to study the behaviour of influenza, detect the beginning of epidemics and characterize the circulating viruses in a representative sample of the population
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>. Since the 2005–2006 season, the PIDIRAC has formed part of the Spanish influenza surveillance sentinel system, coordinated by the National Center for Epidemiology and the National Center for Microbiology, both of the Carlos III Health Institute
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>
 </sup> and which, since 2008 is part of the European Influenza Surveillance Network (EISN) coordinated by the European Center for Disease Control (ECDC) which is responsible for influenza surveillance in Europe. As a result of the 2009 pandemic, in the 2010–2011 season, the surveillance of severe hospitalized cases of confirmed influenza was introduced, using a sentinel hospital system that at that time included 12 hospitals geographically distributed throughout all Catalan health care regions. In Catalonia influenza vaccination is not recommended in childhood except if they have chronic disease that increases the risk of complications. The aim is to determine the activity of influenza viruses and the severity of hospitalized cases
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup>. Various studies have analysed the distribution of influenza in the general population, vaccine effectiveness and hygienic preventive measures in our setting, but the characteristics and distribution of severe disease in children are not known
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup>. The main objective of this study was to describe and analyse the epidemiological and clinical characteristics of children hospitalized due to confirmed influenza A or B virus infection in the sentinel hospitals in the six post-pandemic seasons in Catalonia.
</p>
