<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24">All participants were screened for 
 <italic>T. pallidum</italic> antibody using the Syphilis Antibody Rapid Test (Colloidal Gold) (Acon Biotech Co. Ltd., Hangzhou, China), which has a sensitivity of 99.5% and a specificity of 99.0%. Anti-HIV antibodies were tested with the Diagnostic Kit for HIV (Colloidal Gold) (Livzon Pharmaceutical Group Inc., Zhuhai, China). Each participant had a finger prick and provided about 1 mL of blood by using the Diagnostic Kit for HBV surface antigen (Colloidal Gold) (product of Livzon Pharmaceutical Group Inc., Zhuhai, China), together with HCV antibody (Colloidal Gold) (product of Livzon Pharmaceutical Group Inc., Zhuhai, China). Product specifications show that the sensitivity and specificity of the colloidal gold kits are both higher than 95%. Immunochromatographic assay strips are simple, inexpensive, rapid, robust and equipment free, which have been widely used for sexually transmitted diseases screening in many resource-constrained settings [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. All strips were within the period of validity indicated by the manufacturer. Screening procedures were carried out strictly according to the manufacturer’s instructions. We collected a 5 mL blood sample from those with a positive result, immediately transported it to local township hospitals. Whole blood was centrifuged at 1000 rpm for 5 min and plasma was separated and stored at the constant temperature of − 20 °C within 8 h, and then were transported in ice to Shanghai. Plasma aliquots were tested for viral load by real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR). The application of real-time PCR assays with a high specificity (98.0%) for secondary syphilis can detect the pathogen directly, and avoid the modification of HIV status [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Also, there was no further need to consider the syphilis serological window period [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. We applied the diagnostic kit for the quantification of 
 <italic>T. pallidum</italic> DNA, HBV DNA, HCV RNA, and HIV-1 RNA (PCR-Fluorescence Probing) (DaAn Gene Group Inc., Zhongshan, China) for Plasma viral loads in the Center for Tropical Disease Research at Fudan University. HCV RNA in serum was detected for the majority (95%) of patients with antibodies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].
</p>
