<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is well accepted that the main clinical hallmarks of HFRS are renal failure and hemorrhagic manifestations, and that the disease is characterized by laboratory findings indicating renal function impairment, thrombocytopenia, and elevated ALT levels. Indeed, thrombocytopenia, some degree of renal function impairment, and elevated ALT levels were observed in almost all our patients. Thrombocytopenia was usually present on admission (5 days after onset of illness) and lasted for 4 (1–16) days. The lowest platelet count (median 55 x 10
 <sup>9</sup>/L) was on day 5 of illness, at the end of fever; thereafter, no further decline in platelet count occurred. In contrast to the laboratory findings, only 28% of our patients had clinically overt renal failure manifested as oliguria or anuria (21% with PUUV, 67% with DOBV). This finding is in accordance with several [
 <xref rid="pone.0197661.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0197661.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0197661.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] but not all previous reports; for example, in a German study oliguria was described in as many as 32/75 (43%) patients with PUUV infection [
 <xref rid="pone.0197661.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Nevertheless, in the present study the frequency of oliguria was even lower than the occurrence of blurred vision, which is the result of transient myopic shift due to lens thickening, and is considered a pathognomonic sign of HFRS. The reported rates of blurred vision vary considerably: from 22% to 87% in patients with PUUV infection [
 <xref rid="pone.0197661.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0197661.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0197661.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0197661.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0197661.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In our study, acute myopia was reported by 35% of patients. It appeared 2–12 (median 5) days after the onset of illness and was of short duration (median 2 days). Similar findings were obtained for sinus bradycardia, another striking but rarely reported transient manifestation of HFRS [
 <xref rid="pone.0197661.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0197661.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] that is usually associated with hypotension [
 <xref rid="pone.0197661.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In the present study it was detected in 28/81 (35%) patients, but started later in the course of illness than blurred vision and was mostly of short duration (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0197661.t002">Table 2</xref>).
</p>
