<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par9">In 2004, since the SARS-CoV-1 outbreak in Asia, the coronavirus has been shown to use ACE2 proteins in the epithelial cell membrane in the lung alveoli as a receptor. The viral spike(S) glycoprotein attaches to the ACE2 proteins which have been shown to facilitate viral entry and in theory, make the patient vulnerable to lower respiratory tract infection or viral pneumonia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Since the COVID-19 outbreak, role of ACE2 in the pathophysiology of COVID-19 has drawn a lot of interest in the social media world as well as scientific groups due to the growing concerns that increased expression of ACE2 may increase the risk for severe COVID-19. In a recent report, the main receptor of the spike (S) glycoprotein of SARS-CoV-2 is ACE2 and its affinity has been reported to be higher than that of SARS-CoV 1 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. So the key point of concern is that RAS inhibitor (ACE inhibitor, angiotensin receptor blocker), a drug commonly used in hypertensive patients, can theoretically raise ACE2 expression by a classical feedback system in the biochemical pathway when an enzyme or receptor was blocked (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, a). When ACE2 is activated, Angiotensin 1–7 is increased instead of Angiotensin II. Angiotensin 1–7 is known to have an effect of protecting cardiovascular diseases by binding to the receptor Mas receptor to promote vasodilation, antioxidant and anti-inflammatory effects [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. On the other hand, when it comes to COVID-19, the possibility exists that ACEI or ARB can be an exacerbation factor by increasing the expression of ACE2. As such, there have been increased incidence where patients or physicians change the antihypertensive medications to other drugs or discontinue the drugs due to concerns about the concerns, whether real or not, for increased risk of severe COVID-19. However, the Korean society of Hypertension would like to emphasize that currently, there is no scientific basis for taking such measures. First, there is no epidemiologic evidence for increased severe COVID-19 or mortality in patients who were taking RAS inhibitors. Second, it is still unclear whether or not RAS inhibition results in increased expression of ACE2 in systemic level and/or tissue including epithelial cells (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Even though there are reports that the concentration of ACE2 in the blood rises after administration of the first RAS blockade, there are conflicting reports that also suggest otherwise [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Third, since ACE2 is a receptor for SARS-CoV-1 and 2, if RAS blockade does indeed exacerbates corona virus infection, obvious increase in mortality and severe infection in patients receiving RAS inhibitor should have been reported during the SARS-CoV-1 epidemic. As we all know, this was obviously not the case. On the contrary, it has been reported that ACE2 protects against severe acute lung injury. Study by Deshotels et al. have shown that Angiotensin II, which is highly activated in severe infection, results in increased ACE2 internalization and ACE2 degradation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. This has importance implications as the interaction between ACE2 and SARS-CoV-1 is very complex and the net expression of ACE2 cannot be predictable in a real patient (Fig 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, b) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Moreover, in vivo studies have shown that decreased ACE2 during SARS-CoV-1 infection exacerbated acute lung injury. Imai et al. conducted experiments by inducing acute lung injury through gastric acid aspiration in mice. In ACE knockout mice, acute lung injury was significantly inhibited, whereas in ACE2 knockout mice, acute lung injury worsened compared to wild type. On the other hand, acute lung injury was significantly improved by recombinant ACE2 administration, demonstrating the protective effect of ACE2 in acute lung injury [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. In addition, Kuba et al. conducted experiments with the mice SARS-CoV-1 model. The spike protein of SARS-CoV-1 attaches to ACE2 and downregulates ACE2 and activates Angiotensin II to exacerbate acute lung injury. In contrast, RAS blockade with losartan 15 mg/kg had a protective effect against acute lung injury caused by SARS-CoV-1 infection (Fig 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, b). Given that COVID-19 has similar pathophysiological mechanisms to SARS-CoV-1 infection, increase in ACE2 or RAS blockade might even be protective against severe infection or death. 
</p>
