<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10">In summary, 1) the prevalence of hypertension in patients with severe COVID-19 is high. However, it is more likely due to the fact that severe patients tend to be older and commonly have complications of hypertension, such as heart failure, coronary artery disease, stroke and CKD. Currently, there is no scientific evidence that hypertension is an independent risk factor for severe infection or death until proven otherwise. 2) Regarding the concerns for increased risk of severe infection or death due to the theoretical concerns that taking RAS inhibitors may increase lung ACE2, there is no clinical evidence to suggest that patients taking RAS inhibitors may have adverse prognosis during COVID-19. In fact, it is possible that RAS blockade has protective effect against severe COVID-19 based on previous reports of their protective effect in animal models of SARS-CoV-1 infection. 3) If RAS inhibitors administered due to high blood pressure or other cardiovascular disease were stopped abruptly, there is risk for excessive increase in blood pressure that may precipitate cardiovascular complications. However, we do acknowledge that the above-mentioned issues are valid concerns that deserve more research as quickly as possible. But without any scientific evidence to suggest otherwise, we the Korean Society of Hypertension endorse the recent recommendation by the European Society of Cardiology and recommend 1) In hemodynamically stable patients who were taking RAS inhibitors to be maintained on RAS blockade 2) In hemodynamically stable, treatment naïve patients who have compelling indication for using RAS inhibitors to be administered with RAS inhibitors according to the current guidelines 3) In patients without COVID-19 to be prescribed with RAS inhibitors if there are clinical indications to do so. 4) In hemodynamically unstable patients with COVID-19, prudent reduction or withdrawal of antihypertensive medications can be considered with consideration for the comorbidities and the indications for using the drug(s) before the infection.</p>
