<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pcbi.1005749.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005749.g002</object-id>
 <label>Fig 2</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Seasonal epidemics produce a pandemic refractory period.</title>
  <p>
   <bold>A</bold>: Actual 2008-2009 epidemic curve (solid black line) and 200 stochastic simulations of seasonal epidemics for each network (green for empirical; purple for homogeneous), assuming transmission parameters estimated from 2008-2009 data. 
   <bold>B</bold>: The probability of pandemic emergence upon the introduction of a single infected individual, assuming that the pandemic virus has the same transmission rate as the seasonal virus. Probability is estimated as the proportion of introductions that subsequently infected at least 5% of the overall population out of the 5,000 simulations. Horizontal dashed lines indicate the emergence probabilities in a completely susceptible population calculated with 
   <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pcbi.1005749.e014">Eq 2</xref>. The pandemic refractory periods (shaded regions) are expected to occur during and immediately following the seasonal epidemic peak. 
   <bold>C</bold>: Underestimation of pandemic 
   <italic>R</italic>
   <sub>0</sub>. Assuming that the emerging pandemic has an 
   <italic>R</italic>
   <sub>0</sub> = 2.5 in a naïve population (dashed horizontal line), we plot the median (points) and interquartile range of the measured 
   <italic>R</italic>
   <sub>eff</sub>, for each introduction time and each network. For example, if a pandemic with 
   <italic>R</italic>
   <sub>0</sub> = 2.5 emerged in March of 2009 and we did not account for population immunity, we would interpret the 
   <italic>R</italic>
   <sub>eff</sub> as the 
   <italic>R</italic>
   <sub>0</sub> and considerably underestimate the true transmission rate (
   <italic>R</italic>
   <sub>0</sub> ≈ 2), regardless of our contact network assumptions.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1005749.g002" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
