<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In order to better understand the potential molecular mechanisms of these differentially expressed miRNAs that occur during EV71 and CA16 infection, we carried out GO and pathway analysis of the predicted target genes of the 30 differentially expressed miRNAs identified in trend analysis. Using KEGG pathway analysis and GO annotation for target genes can offer a comprehensive understanding of the target genes at th
 <bold>e</bold> pathway, molecular, cellular, and biological levels. The observed changes in biological processes (especially related to immune system processes and biological adhesion), molecular function (especially with reference to binding), cellular components (especially linked to cell junctions) and pathways (especially associated with immune pathways, such as apoptosis signaling pathways, the Toll-receptor signaling pathway, T-cell activation, interleukin signaling, inflammation mediated by chemokine and cytokine signaling, B cell activation, the JAK/STAT signaling pathway, etc., and adhesion pathways, such as the cadherin signaling pathway, cytoskeletal regulation by Rho GTPase, the Wnt signaling pathway, etc.) suggested that these differentially expressed miRNAs might play important roles in immune and adhesion responses in HUVECs infected with EV71 and CA16. Nevertheless, the success of pathogens in entering host cells largely depends on their invasion strategies, including impeding the activation of the host immune system, destroying intercellular junctions, triggering excess apoptosis, and so on[
 <xref rid="pone.0177657.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Furthermore, biochemical and genetic studies have clarified that miRNAs, as key regulators, participate in the regulation of immune function, such as antigen presentation (e.g., miR-155), T-cell receptor signalling (e.g., miR-181a), Toll-like receptor signalling and the ensuing cytokine responses (e.g., miR-146), etc.[
 <xref rid="pone.0177657.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], and cell-cell contact, such as urothelial permeability (e.g., miR-199a-5p), etc[
 <xref rid="pone.0177657.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Additionally, it has been demonstrated that EV71 infection can affect the p38 MAPK signaling pathway, which may be associated with the secretion of inflammatory cytokines and host-cell apoptosis; these mechanisms may be implicated in inflammation of the CNS and disorders such as encephalitis or meningitis[
 <xref rid="pone.0177657.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Similarly, in our study, the p38 MAPK signaling pathway was also changed by pathway enrichment analysis. Moreover, the predicted target genes were also enriched into specific neuronal cellular components, such as synapses, and neuronal function-related pathways, such as axon guidance mediated by Slit/Robo, netrin, or semaphorins, etc. Thus we hypothesized that the differing pathogeneses of EV71 and CA16 infections are partly attributable to the regulatory roles of the oppositely expressed miRNAs involved in the immune response, intercellular junctions, and neurological symptoms that might lead to the malfunction of host cells or favor the viral life cycle. Next, the associations of the identified miRNAs with target genes, GOs, pathways and co-expression genes were further visualized by creating regulatory networks.
</p>
