<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat.1007601.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007601.g003</object-id>
 <label>Fig 3</label>
 <caption>
  <title>Several clinically approved and experimental drugs block multiple round and primary infection of IV.</title>
  <p>(A &amp; B) For determination of virus replication, A549 cells were pre-treated with small molecules at different concentrations for 2 h. Cells were infected with IV strain WSN and cultivated for 36 h in presence of small molecules. Finally, virus titers in supernatants were determined and the infection rate was selected as read-out. IC
   <sub>50</sub>: half maximal inhibitory concentration of drug in virus replication assay. For determination of cell viability, A549 cells were cultivated for 36 h in presence of small molecules at different concentrations prior to conduction of WST-1 assay. Data represent signal in WST-1 assay relative to the vehicle control expressed as mean ± SEM of n = 3 technical replicates. CC
   <sub>50</sub>: half maximal inhibitory concentration in WST-1 assay. (A) Regorafenib. (B) Sorafenib. (C) A549 cells were pre-treated with small molecules at non-toxic concentrations (regorafenib &amp; sorafenib, 3 μM; zanamivir, 1 μM) for 2 h. Cells were infected and cultivated for 48 h in presence of small molecules. Virus load was assessed in 12-hour intervals by plaque assay. Data represent mean ± SD of technical replicates. l.o.d.: limit of detection. Log-transformed virus titer for zanamivir treatment was compared to control using multiple linear regression. The titer for DMSO exceeds the one for zanamivir treatment significantly by a factor of 10
   <sup>4</sup> (p &lt; 0.001; 95%CI: 10
   <sup>2</sup> to 10
   <sup>6</sup>). (D) A549 cells were treated with small molecules (same doses as in C) either starting 2 h prior to infection (preventive, black bars) or 4 h post-infection (therapeutic, grey bars) with WSN. Infected cells were cultivated for 36 h in presence of small molecules and virus load was assessed by plaque assay. Data represent mean ± SD of technical replicates. Log-transformed virus titer data were analysed with a linear model. The titer for preventive treatment exceeds the titer for therapeutic treatment (p = 0.041). It was lower for zanamivir treatment compared to DMSO (p ≤ 0.001). For preventive treatment with sorafenib and for both treatments with regorafenib the titer was below the limit of detection (l.o.d). Please note that zanamivir was applied at suboptimal concentration in (C) and (D).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1007601.g003" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
