<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat.1007601.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007601.g005</object-id>
 <label>Fig 5</label>
 <caption>
  <title>UBKIs block cellular pathways important for fusion and downstream processes.</title>
  <p>(A and B) A549 cells were pre-treated with Hoechst to stain the nuclei (blue) and either small molecules (regorafenib and sorafenib: 3 μM, bafilomycin A1: 200 nM) or an equivalent amount of DMSO for 30 min before incubation at 4°C with IAV strain PAN labeled with DiOC18 (green) and DiI (red). Virus-containing medium was exchanged against media containing either small molecules or DMSO only, and cells imaged at 37°C for 65 min. In (A), representative images for the DiOC18 and the merge of the DiOC18 and the DiI signal acquired 60 min post infection are shown. Scale bar = 10 μm. In (B), micrographs were quantitatively analyzed and the change of the DiOC18 signal intensity is shown for individual time points. Data represent mean (n = 3) ± SEM of independent experiments. (C and D) A549 cells were pre-treated as described for A and B, incubated at 4°C with IAV strain PAN (MOI 5) and then cultivated for 3 h at 37°C in the presence of small molecules and cycloheximide before staining for DNA with DAPI (blue) and IAV M1 protein (green), and subjected to microscopic and flow cytometry analysis. (C) Representative images of three independent experiments. (D) Quantitative analysis. Data represent mean ± SEM of n = 3 independent experiments (mean values are significantly different: one-way ANOVA: p ≤ 0.0001; Dunnett´s multiple comparison test for comparison with DMSO control: **** indicates p
   <sub>adjusted</sub> = 0.0001). (E) A549 cells, pre-treated as described for (A and B), incubated at 4°C with IAV strain PAN (MOI 5) and cultivated for 4.5 h at 37°C in the presence of small molecules and cycloheximide before staining for DNA with DAPI (blue) and IAV NP protein (green), and subjected to microscopic analysis. Representative micrographs of the z-axis of individual cells are shown. (F) A549 cells were pre-treated with small molecules at 3 μM or an equivalent amount of DMSO for 2 h. Subsequently, the cells were infected with IAV strain WSN and cultivated for 4 h in presence of small molecules. RNA was extracted and the relative amount of the NP, M1, and M2 mRNAs determined by qRT-PCR. Data represent mean ± SEM of n = 3 independent experiments. Significance was calculated based on the one sample t-test for comparison with DMSO control: *: p-value ≤ 0.05, **: p-value ≤ 0.01, ****: p-value ≤ 0.0001. (G) A549 cells were pre-treated with small molecules at non-toxic concentrations (regorafenib &amp; sorafenib: 3 μM, bafilomycinA1: 1 μM) for 2 h. Cells were infected and cultivated for 6 h in presence of small molecules before staining for viral nucleoprotein (NP). Data represent mean ± SEM of n = 3 independent experiments of the fraction of NP-positive cells relative to the vehicle control. Significance was calculated based on the one sample t-test for comparison with DMSO control: *: p-value ≤ 0.05, **: p-value ≤ 0.01.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1007601.g005" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
