<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat.1007601.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007601.g006</object-id>
 <label>Fig 6</label>
 <caption>
  <title>UBKIs possess broad antiviral activity, are effective in primary cells, and impose a barrier against resistance development.</title>
  <p>(A) A549 cells were pre-treated with 3 μM of small molecules or an equivalent amount of DMSO for 2 h, infected and cultivated for 6 h in presence of small molecules before staining for viral NP protein. Data represent mean ± SEM of n = 3 independent experiments of the fraction of NP-positive cells relative to DMSO. (B) A549 (CPXV, HSV1, VSV) or HEL cell-derived megakaryocyte (HTV) cells were pre-treated as in (A). Cells were infected for 6 h (VSV), 18 h (CHIKV) or 24 h (CPXV, HSV1, HTV) prior to fixation. Presence of viral antigens (HTV: N protein; VSV: NP protein; all other viruses: green fluorescent protein (GFP) was detected by fluorescence microscopy. Data represent mean ± SEM of n = 3 independent experiments of the fraction of viral antigen-positive cells relative to DMSO. Significance in (A) and (B) was calculated based on the one sample t-test for comparison with DMSO control. *: p-value ≤ 0.05, **: p-value ≤ 0.01, ***: p-value ≤ 0.001. (C) Experiments were conducted as in (A) but with hAECB. Zanamivir was applied at 1 μM. (A, B, C) Data represent DMSO-normalized mean ± SEM of n = 3 independent experiments. Indicated p-values based on the one sample t-test describe the difference compared to the DMSO control. (D) hAECB were treated with small molecules at 5 μM. Infected cells were cultivated for 48 h in presence of small molecules and virus load was assessed every six hours by plaque assay. Data represent mean ± SEM of n = 3 technical replicates. Virus titers were analysed by mixed effects models for clustered data where treatment group and time were fixed effects. In the random intercept model residuals associated with different plates were specified to have different residuals. The calculation of p-values revealed a significant decrease of log-transformed virus-titers in the regorafenib and sorafenib-treated groups relative to the DMSO control at the indicated time points: *: p-value ≤ 0.05. (E) MDCK cells were pre-treated with sorafenib (3 μM), zanamivir (0.3 μM), amantadine (3 μM) or an equivalent amount of DMSO for 2 h, infected with MOI 0.001 of IV strain A/England/195/2009–M2
   <sub>N31S</sub> and cultivated for 24 h in presence of reagents. Virus titer in tissue culture supernatants was determined and the supernatants were used for inoculation of the next passage. The experiment was terminated after 8 passages. Data represent mean ± SD of technical replicates.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1007601.g006" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
