<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<boxed-text id="pone.0217455.box002" position="float" orientation="portrait">
 <sec id="sec008">
  <title>Box 2. CDC/CSTE Acute Hepatitis C Case Definition</title>
  <p>Clinical Criteria for Diagnosis</p>
  <p>An acute illness with a discrete onset of any sign or symptom* consistent with acute viral hepatitis (e.g., fever, headache, malaise, anorexia, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, and abdominal pain), and either a) jaundice, or b) elevated serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT) levels &gt; 400 IU/L.</p>
  <p>Laboratory Criteria for Diagnosis</p>
  <p>One or more of the following three criteria:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>Antibodies to hepatitis C virus (anti-HCV) screening-test-positive with a signal to cut-off ratio predictive of a true positive as determined for the particular assay as defined by CDC. (URL for the signal to cut-off ratios: 
     <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/hepatitis/HCV/LabTesting.htm" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.cdc.gov/hepatitis/HCV/LabTesting.htm</ext-link>), OR
    </p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Hepatitis C Virus Recombinant Immunoblot Assay (HCV RIBA) positive, OR</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Nucleic Acid Test (NAT) for HCV RNA positive (including qualitative, quantitative or genotype testing)</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>AND, if done meets the following two criteria:</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>Absence of IgM antibody to hepatitis A virus (if done) (IgM anti-HAV), AND</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Absence of IgM antibody to hepatitis B core antigen (if done) (IgM anti-HBc)</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>Confirmed Case Classification</p>
  <p>A case that meets the clinical case definition, is laboratory confirmed, and is not known to have chronic hepatitis C.</p>
  <p>SOURCE: CDC/CSTE 2012 Case Definition for Acute HCV Infection.</p>
  <p>*A documented negative HCV antibody laboratory test result followed within 6 months by a positive test (as described in the laboratory criteria for diagnosis) result does not require an acute clinical presentation to meet the surveillance case definition.</p>
 </sec>
</boxed-text>
