<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<boxed-text id="pone.0217455.box004" position="float" orientation="portrait">
 <sec id="sec010">
  <title>Box 4. CDC/CSTE Chronic Hepatitis C Case Definition</title>
  <p>Clinical Criteria for Diagnosis</p>
  <p>No symptoms are required. Persons with chronic hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection may have no evidence of liver disease or may have a spectrum of disease ranging from chronic hepatitis to cirrhosis or liver cancer.</p>
  <p>Laboratory Criteria for Diagnosis</p>
  <p>One or more of the following three criteria (except in persons less than 18 months of age, for whom only criteria 3 would meet the case classification criteria):</p>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>Antibodies to hepatitis C virus (anti-HCV) screening-test-positive with a signal to cut-off ratio predictive of a true positive as determined for the particular assay as defined by CDC. (URL for the signal to cut-off ratios: 
     <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/hepatitis/HCV/LabTesting.htm" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.cdc.gov/hepatitis/HCV/LabTesting.htm</ext-link>), OR
    </p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Hepatitis C virus recombinant immunoblot assay (HCV RIBA) positive, OR</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Nucleic acid test (NAT) for HCV RNA positive (including qualitative, quantitative or genotype testing).</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
  <p>Probable Case Classification</p>
  <p>A case that does not meet the case definition for acute hepatitis C, is anti-HCV positive (repeat reactive) by EIA, and has alanine aminotransferase (ALT or SGPT) values above the upper limit of normal, but the anti-HCV EIA result has not been verified by an additional more specific assay or the signal to cut-off ratio is unknown.</p>
  <p>Confirmed Case Classification</p>
  <p>A case that is laboratory confirmed and does not meet the case definition for acute hepatitis C</p>
  <p>SOURCE: CDC/CSTE 2012 Case Definition for Chronic HCV Infection.</p>
 </sec>
</boxed-text>
