<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>CD8
  <sup>+</sup> T cell:
 </italic> CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells control viral infections by triggering apoptosis of infected cells through perforin- or Fas ligand-dependent pathways or producing antiviral cytokines (e.g., IFN-γ and TNF-α). CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells are essential in protecting from WNV infection. Early studies using rag-deficient mice that lack all T cells and B cells, CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cell and MHC class Ia-deficient mice demonstrated a protective role in clearing WNV infection in the CNS and peripheral tissues [
 <xref rid="B100-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>,
 <xref rid="B111-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. In addition, WNV infection of mice deficient in perforin, fas ligand and TRIAL that are the vital elements for CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cell killing resulted in the increased mortality following infection [
 <xref rid="B82-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>,
 <xref rid="B112-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>,
 <xref rid="B113-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. Furthermore, WNV-infected mice deficient in chemokine CXCL10 and its receptor CXCR3, which are essential for CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cell chemotaxis to the CNS, especially cerebellum, increased in viral burden in the brain and enhanced morbidity and mortality [
 <xref rid="B114-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>,
 <xref rid="B115-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>]. Polarized expression of CXCL12 and its receptor CXCR4 at the BBB localizes infiltrating mononuclear cells to the perivascular spaces of the CNS microvasculature, therefore limiting their entry into the CNS parenchyma [
 <xref rid="B116-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>]. A study showed that antagonism of CXCR4 significantly improved survival through enhanced intraparenchymal migration of WNV-specific CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells within the brain [
 <xref rid="B117-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]. Moreover, enhanced CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells cytotoxicity through a supplement of IL-17A has been shown to increase the survival of the mice from WNV infection [
 <xref rid="B118-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. Collectively, the results from these studies indicated that CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells play an important protective role in controlling WNV infection. However, studies also showed a potential pathogenic role for CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells in WNV infection. High doses (10
 <sup>8</sup> PFU) of Sarafend strain of WNV infection in 
 <italic>CD8
  <sup>−/−</sup>
 </italic> mice lead to the increased survival, while low doses (10
 <sup>3</sup> PFU) of infection resulted in more severe infection, indicating that CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells are involved in both recovery and immunopathology in WNV infection [
 <xref rid="B119-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. Additionally, when mice lacking the interferon-stimulated gene Ifit1 were depleted with CD8 antibody, they survived better than the isotype control mice following a mutant WNV (E218A) infection, in which NS5 lacks 2′-O methyltransferase activity, indicating CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells contribute to mortality [
 <xref rid="B120-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>]. Therefore, while CD8 T cells are required for control of WNV infection, they may also contribute to immunopathogenesis in some situations.
</p>
