<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P38">Genomic DNA was extracted from 
 <italic>E. helvum</italic> tissues using DNeasy Blood and Tissue Kits (QIAGEN Ltd., Crawley, West Sussex, UK) and was supplied for one 
 <italic>E. dupreanum</italic> bat from Madagascar by the Institut Pasteur de Madagascar. Multiplexed genotyping was performed using 18 loci in six multiplexed reactions (TSY, FWB, MNQX, AgPK, AcAfAi, AdAh) using a Type-it Multiplex PCR Master Mix (QIAGEN Ltd.). From twenty 
 <italic>E. helvum</italic> loci developed in a previous study
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>
 </sup>, Loci E and Ae were discarded due to difficulty in scoring or high error rates and data were locus Ag were re-binned and re-scored, correcting earlier issues with allelic dropout. Positive and negative controls were included on each plate. Amplification of mtDNA cytb gene fragments from continental samples used generic primers L14722 (5′-CGA AGC TTG ATA TGA AAA ACC ATC GTT G)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref>
 </sup> and H15149 (5′- AAA CTG CAG CCC CTC AGA ATG ATA TTT GTC CTC A)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref>
 </sup> in 20μl reactions, containing 0.1–1ng template DNA, 0.2μM of each primer, 0.25mM of each dNTP, 1.5mM MgCl
 <sub>2</sub>, 0.25μl of 
 <italic>Taq</italic> polymerase (Invitrogen), and 0.2μl 10× reaction buffer and with the following conditions: 5 min at 94°C; 40 cycles of 1 min at 93°C, 1 min at 54°C, and 2 min at 72°C; then 7 min at 72°C. Although these generic primers were adequate with continental samples (8% PCR failure), amplification from isolated Gulf of Guinea island samples was less successful (48% PCR failure). Shortened primers (EhM2814 (5′-GCT TGA TAT GAA AAA CCA TCG TTG) and EhM2815 (5′-CAG CCC CTC AGA ATG ATA TTT GT) resulted in successful amplification when using Microzone MegaMix-Gold reagent (Microzone Ltd, UK). PCRs were performed in 20μl reactions, containing 2ng template DNA, 0.25μM of each primer, and 10μl MegaMix-Gold, using the following conditions: 5 min at 95°C; 33 cycles of 30 sec at 95°C, 30 sec at 53°C, and 45 sec at 72°C. PCR products were sequenced in both directions, aligned, manually checked and trimmed to 397 bp. No sequence differences were detected in 38 samples sequenced using both primer pairs, so data were combined.
</p>
