<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0155">Unbiased ascertainment of anti-HDV prevalence requires large sample sizes to identify the subset with HBV, which poses a particular problem in regions with low HBV prevalence. In these regions, samples derived from settings that are enriched with HBsAg-positive people are often used to study anti-HDV prevalence, such as patients sampled within hepatology clinics. Current guidelines recommend HDV testing in selected patients with specific risk factors
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>28</sup>
 </xref> or do not explicitly recommend universal testing.
 <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>29</sup>
 </xref> As a result, in many centres, newly diagnosed HBsAg-positive individuals are not tested for anti-HDV as part of routine practice. Clinician-driven testing carries a risk of introducing an ascertainment bias. Specialist referral to a hepatology clinic may be the result of patients developing characteristics of liver disease. The resulting population may therefore be more likely to test anti-HDV positive and may not be fully representative of the general population. As such, to reduce the risk of overestimating HDV prevalence, studies based in hepatology clinic settings were considered separately from those of general populations. Furthermore, we only included samples that were representative of the target population and decided to exclude many laboratory-based samples or samples that relied on clinician-instigated testing. A previous systematic review estimated a global anti-HDV prevalence among people with HBsAg of 10.6%.
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref> However, as we previously noted, the analysis included data from sources at high risk of bias such as laboratory-based studies, analysed hepatology clinic data together with data from general populations, did not consider the size of the population represented by the included samples, and used data from small isolated communities to produce estimates for general populations.
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>24</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>25</sup>
 </xref> Our study has considered each of these issues and as a result we estimate a lower anti-HDV prevalence among the general population and provide a distinct estimate for hepatology clinic populations.
</p>
