<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18">Dozens of pharmaceutical companies are targeting this key to unlock a SARS-CoV-2 vaccine. Different strategies are being worked upon. It was recently discovered that ACE receptors are present not only on lung, heart, gut, and kidney cells but also on the nose. Using ACE receptors in therapeutics holds a contrasting version. Some research teams undermine its potentials citing that non-steroidal inflammatory drugs may spoil the show by increasing the expression of ACE receptors, while others emphasize that using a floating enzyme strategy may prove effective. These ACE receptor mimics may befool viruses and make them latch on (Apeiron Biologics, an Austrian pharmaceutical company). We propose that a gene variation study of the ACE-2 gene specific to lung tissue can be instrumental in discovering effective drugs against viral entry since this gene deals with the production of surfactant for the lungs. Any defect or overexpression of this gene may either prevent viral entry into the host cell or may make it detrimental for the host. One such research to support our proposal is the CCR5 gene on blood cells. Genetic analysis revealed that people with defective CCR5 gene prevented HIV from entering the host cell [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. Thus, in this case, a defective gene was at an advantage since it made some people immune to HIV infection by preventing viral entry. One of the observed trends in COVID-19 is the cytokine storm (similar to the one observed in H1N1 flu). This also results from some impaired gene which causes a hyperexpressive immune response. Thus, a genetic variation study among populations would help figure out who is less vulnerable and who is more prone to such deadly viruses. The viral genomics and proteomics studies would help to discover some relevant transcription factors that induce overexpression of the host immune system. In a recent proteomics study of SARS-CoV-2-infected host cells, a fresh understanding of some gene therapies effective against COVID-19 was hinted. It includes the modulations in the host cell pathway infected with SARS-CoV-2 in human cell culture studies and suggests that effective therapy can be blocking these pathways by some inhibitor molecules that would halt the process of viral multiplication.
</p>
