<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par65">Two major epidemics in the last two decades have established CoVs as dangerous pathogens that can disease in humans. The SARS epidemic was subdued with strict management, but the second epidemic of MERS soon spread from the Middle Eastern countries, followed by a second wave of infection in South Korea. In both of these viral outbreaks, high mortality and contagion of disease were observed, which made the spread hard to curb. The lack of approved vaccines and antiviral drugs was also a problem at that time, and infected patients were treated using convalescent sera. This led to many types of research investigating their potential as an effective treatment option. A study conducted in Hong Kong investigated the effect of treatment with convalescent sera on in SARS patients. Upon administration, the individuals treated on day 14 after disease onset, as well as those who tested positive by PCR but were serologically negative for CoV demonstrated better recovery, which resulted in their subsequent discharge from the hospital in a couple of days, indicating the effectiveness of early treatment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR150">150</xref>]. Another study highlighted the decrease in the viral titer, thus enabling the survival of infected patients after they were given about 0.5 L of serum antibodies from convalesced patients [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR151">151</xref>]. However, there are limitations to the use of convalescent serum, as some convalescent patients may not produce enough antibodies to inactivate the virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR152">152</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR153">153</xref>]. This may be due to a decrease in the antibody titer with time or to the fact that not all recovered patients have an elevated titer of neutralizing antibodies in their serum [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134">134</xref>]. However, it is known that the production of non-neutralizing antibodies can also contribute to immunity to and recuperation from many viral diseases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR154">154</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR156">156</xref>]. In the case of SARS-CoV-2, there were several published accounts of the use of convalescent serum therapy for the treatment of infected patients in China [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR157">157</xref>], which shed light on its effectivity and safety for use against COVID-19. Still, more studies can add more weight to the research findings.
</p>
