<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Ross River virus (RRV) is a positive-sense, single-stranded RNA virus in the Alphavirus genus of the 
 <italic>Togaviridae</italic> family. RRV circulates in Australia and Papua New Guinea and is transmitted through the bite of 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> and 
 <italic>Culex</italic> mosquitos. Typical signs and symptoms of infection include rash, fever, and most prominently, debilitating muscle and joint pain that persists for 3 to 6 months [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008517.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–
 <xref rid="ppat.1008517.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. RRV is an Australian nationally notifiable disease, and since reporting began in 1993, a mean number of 4,600 cases has been reported in Australia each year [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008517.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In addition, the economic burden, including diagnosis, treatment and lost wages, has been estimated to be as much as 5 million Australian dollars annually [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008517.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008517.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. RRV was first isolated from human serum using suckling mice in 1972, but was not connected with symptoms until large epidemics in the South Pacific islands in 1979–1980, in which approximately 70,000 people were infected [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008517.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008517.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008517.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Traditionally, reservoirs of RRV were thought to be maruspials endemic to Australia, such as kangaroos and wallabies [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008517.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008517.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. However, recent evidence indicates that other mammalian species such as rodents, rabbits, and flying foxes can act as reservoirs for the virus and contribute to its spread [
 <xref rid="ppat.1008517.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="ppat.1008517.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. This finding suggests that RRV may have the potential to spread to regions outside of Australia and the Pacific Islands and raises concerns about future epidemic transmission. Currently, there are no approved vaccines or specific therapies targeting RRV.
</p>
