<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The average monthly NDVI, an index of the amount and productivity of vegetation, was derived from satellite data and was generated as follows: NDVI = (NIR—VIS)/(NIR + VIS), where VIS and NIR stand for the spectral reflectance measurements acquired in the visible (red) and near-infrared regions, respectively [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006198.ref082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. NDVI values for farmland were obtained from 9 sampling sites (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat.1006198.g001">Fig 1A</xref>) during 1984–2014 using AVHRR GIMMS 15-day composite NDVI products [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006198.ref083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. The TVDI, based on an empirical parameterization of the relationship between surface temperature and NDVI, was used in monitoring soil moisture and drought regionally [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006198.ref084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. The TVDI is estimated using the following equation: TVDI = (
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>s</sub>—
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>s min</sub>)/(
 <italic>T</italic>s max—
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>s min</sub>), where 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>s</sub> is the observed land surface temperature at a given pixel, and 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>s min</sub> is the minimum surface temperature in the triangle (
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>s min</sub> = a
 <sub>1</sub> + b
 <sub>1</sub>(NDVI)). 
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>s max</sub> is the maximum surface temperature observation for a given NDVI (
 <italic>T</italic>
 <sub>s max</sub> = a
 <sub>2</sub> + b
 <sub>2</sub>(NDVI)). 
 <italic>a</italic>
 <sub>1</sub> and 
 <italic>a</italic>
 <sub>2</sub> are the intercepts, and 
 <italic>b</italic>
 <sub>1</sub> and 
 <italic>b</italic>
 <sub>2</sub> are the slopes for the dry and wet edges. The value for TVDI is higher for dry conditions and lower for wet conditions, and varies between 0 and 1. Climatic data, including temperature and rainfall, were obtained from a local meteorological station from 1984–2014.
</p>
