<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The HA head domain was also reported to contain conserved epitopes outside the RBS. Different broadly neutralizing antibodies recognized the conserved regions located in HA head domain and neutralized multiple influenza viruses without detectable HI activity (Iba et al., 
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Raymond et al., 
 <xref rid="B201" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Generally, neutralization breadth of head antibodies was considerably variable to each other, ranging from pan-subtype (covering the same subtype) to pan-type (covering both group 1 and 2) coverage, indicating the presence of variably conserved regions. Additionally, a novel class of cross-reactive antibodies was discovered in humans vaccinated with seasonal TIV (Lee et al., 
 <xref rid="B145" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). These antibodies were shown to bind to a highly conserved region located on the HA RBS that was occluded in the HA trimer, conferring protective immunity against H1N1 and H3N2 strains 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>, without neutralizing activity 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>. Furthermore, a novel class of antibodies targeting vestigial esterase (VE) domain in HA has been characterized. The VE domain consists of two non-continuous sequences in HA head domain, which together forms a structurally distinct subdomain from the RBS and HA stalk domain (Zheng et al., 
 <xref rid="B257" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). The VE domain of the HEF protein of ICV is responsible for cleaving the host receptor to facilitate viral release, whereas in IAVs and IBVs the same receptor cleaving function is provided by a separate NA. The VE domains are found in both IAVs and IBVs, although their functions are not well-defined. The VE domains are highly conserved within a subtype of IAV but are variable among different subtypes (Ha et al., 
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). Monoclonal antibodies to the VE domain of H5N1 virus demonstrated broad neutralization against multiple clades of H5N1 subtype by preventing viral entry into cells (Oh et al., 
 <xref rid="B179" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). To date, different monoclonal antibodies have been isolated and they bind to different epitopes in the VE domain of H5N1 viruses, suggesting the presence of multiple neutralization epitopes in the VE domain (Paul et al., 
 <xref rid="B184" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). The VE-binding antibodies are reported to mediate ADCC for 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> protection via FcR-Fc interaction (Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="B241" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Besides H5N1, several monoclonal antibodies neutralizing H3 or H7 of IAVs or IBVs have also been recently characterized (Tan et al., 
 <xref rid="B224" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Chai et al., 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Bangaru et al., 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Taken together, possibility remains to identify conserved neutralizing epitopes in the head domain in HA, in addition to extensively characterized HA stalk. Activation of these epitopes via antigen processing machineries (Lee et al., 
 <xref rid="B149" ref-type="bibr">2018b</xref>) may offer an option for enhancing the potency of cross-protection.
</p>
