<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Vaccination campaigns aimed at both protecting threatened species and decreasing public health risks via animal vaccination have taken place. Swiss health officials were pioneers in this field, using oral vaccines to control rabies in wild red foxes (
 <italic>Vulpes vulpes</italic>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b87-viruses-03-00379">87</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b88-viruses-03-00379">88</xref>]. These vaccines were inserted into chicken heads which were distributed in the wild beginning in 1978 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b88-viruses-03-00379">88</xref>]. As can be observed from the supplemental movie (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Video S1</xref>), their initial barrier approach evolved into a large-scale treatment of infected areas and resulted in rabies being successfully pushed back to and then eliminated from the Swiss Alps [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b87-viruses-03-00379">87</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b88-viruses-03-00379">88</xref>]. Following the success of these trials, campaigns were conducted in Western Europe [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b89-viruses-03-00379">89</xref>] and Canada [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b90-viruses-03-00379">90</xref>] with similar results, though the situation in the United States has proven more challenging. Other successful vaccination examples include canine distemper virus in black-footed ferrets (
 <italic>Mustela nigripes</italic>; [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b91-viruses-03-00379">91</xref>]) and Ethiopian wolves (
 <italic>Canis simensis</italic>; [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b92-viruses-03-00379">92</xref>]), as well as rabies in Florida panthers (
 <italic>Felis concolor coryi</italic>; [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b93-viruses-03-00379">93</xref>]) and African wild dogs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b94-viruses-03-00379">94</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b95-viruses-03-00379">95</xref>]. A caveat to this success is that there is growing evidence that vaccination against a specific strain of pathogen can result in inadvertent selection for related co-infecting strains. Thus vaccination can influence the dynamics of a pathogen [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b96-viruses-03-00379">96</xref>].
</p>
