<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to amino acid-based inhibitors, monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) have attracted attention due to their use in infectious and chronic disease treatments (
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">Green et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">Haynes et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B164" ref-type="bibr">Pettitt et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">D’Amato et al., 2014</xref>), overcoming drawbacks caused in polyclonal Abs therapy, such as those related to donor compatibility (
 <xref rid="B142" ref-type="bibr">Marasco and Sui, 2007</xref>). Human neutralizing Abs against human CoVs have been generated, targeting S glycoproteins to impair viral entry (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Belouzard et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B179" ref-type="bibr">Reguera et al., 2012</xref>). Notably, several mAbs were identified as inhibitors of MERS-CoV and SARS-CoV infections both 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>, protecting cells and animals when administered 24 h prior to or post-infection (
 <xref rid="B134" ref-type="bibr">Lip et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B257" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Agnihothram et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B196" ref-type="bibr">Shanmugaraj et al., 2020</xref>). The mAbs are developed by merging B lymphocytes and myeloma cells, producing hybridomas capable of recognizing antigens and producing a single Ab class to bind specific epitopes (
 <xref rid="B136" ref-type="bibr">Lipman et al., 2005</xref>). For that reason, mAb cross-reactivity among different coronaviruses seems to be ineffective (
 <xref rid="B219" ref-type="bibr">Totura and Bavari, 2019</xref>). In the particular case of SARS-CoV-2, Wang and coworkers produced mAbs using 51 lineages of SARS-S hybridoma cells and identified 47D11 H2L2-neutralizing Ab through ELISA assays. This antibody was produced using mice cells; therefore, it was further modified to produce a fully human immunoglobulin IgG1, producing the human monoclonal antibody 47D11. The results showed that 47D11 bound to the RBD region and inhibited SARS-CoV-2 entry in Vero cells with an EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 0.57 μg mL
 <sup>−1</sup> (
 <xref rid="B231" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2020a</xref>). In this context, this mAb can be used alone or in association with other compounds to treat COVID-19.
</p>
