<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="ppat.1007691.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007691.g006</object-id>
 <label>Fig 6</label>
 <caption>
  <title>UL42 impairs the trafficking of MITA by promoting p62-LC3B- mediated autophagy degradation of TRAPβ.</title>
  <p>(A) UL42 impairs cGAMP-triggered trafficking of MITA. UL42 stably-transduced 
   <italic>MITA</italic>
   <sup>-/—</sup>MLF-MITA-Flag cells (2x10
   <sup>5</sup>) were transfected with cGAMP (0.1 μg) for 4 hr before confocal microscopy. (B) Association of UL42 with MITA, TRAPβ, and iRhom2. HEK293T cells (2x10
   <sup>6</sup>) were transfected with the indicated plasmids (5 μg each) for 20 hr before coimmunoprecipitation and immunoblotting analysis with the indicated antibodies. (C) UL42 is co-localized with the ER and TRAPβ. HEK293 (5x10
   <sup>4</sup>) were transfected with UL42-RFP, TRAPβ
   <bold>-</bold>GFP or ER-GFP (1 μg each) as indicated for 18 hr before confocal microscopy. (D) UL42 promotes degradation of TRAPβ but not TRIM38, TRIM32, TRIM14, and iRhom2. HEK293T cells (2x10
   <sup>5</sup>) were transfected with the indicated plasmids (2 μg each) for 20 hr before immunoblotting analysis with the indicated antibodies. (E) HCMV-WT but not HCMV-ΔUL42 induced degradation of TRAPβ. The HFF-TRAPβ cells (4x10
   <sup>5</sup>) were infected with wild-type or UL42-deficient HCMV (MOI = 1) for the indicated times before immunoblotting analysis with the indicated antibodies. (F) Effects of different inhibitors on UL42-mediated destabilization of TRAPβ. HEK293 cells (5x10
   <sup>5</sup>) were transfected with the indicated plasmids (2 μg each) for 12 hours and then treated with the indicated inhibitors for 6 hours before immunoblotting analysis with the indicated antibodies. (G) UL42 increases the association of TRAPβ with LC3B and p62. HEK293T cells (5x10
   <sup>6</sup>) were transfected with the indicated plasmids (5 μg each) for 20 hrs before coimmunoprecipitation and immunoblot analysis with the indicated antibodies.(H) Knockdown of p62 or LC3B inhibits UL42-mediated destabilization of TRAPβ. The HEK293T-control, HEK293T-LC3B-shRNA, or HEK293T-p62-shRNA cells (5x10
   <sup>5</sup>) were transfected with the indicated plasmids (2 μg each) for 12 hours and then treated with the indicated inhibitors for 6 hours before immunoblotting analysis with the indicated antibodies.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ppat.1007691.g006" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
