<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0175">Another notably explored chemical class is exemplified by hexamethylene amiloride (HMA, 
 <bold>23</bold>), an amiloride-based compound which is reported to block viroporins and/or replication of IAV, hepatitis C virus, HIV-1, Dengue virus, and severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV; 
 <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Gazina and Petrou, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib91" ref-type="bibr">Pervushin et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr">Premkumar et al., 2004</xref>). However, HMA has several off-target effects and is cytotoxic at low micromolar concentrations (
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Jalily et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib98" ref-type="bibr">Premkumar et al., 2004</xref>). Recently, a series of HMA derivatives were designed through iterative medicinal chemistry and electrophysiological testing approaches (
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Jalily et al., 2016</xref>). Among these compounds, 
 <bold>24</bold> exhibited activity against WT M2 in single electrode voltage clamp (SEVC) experiments, which was comparable to amantadine in these studies (IC
 <sub>50</sub> 0.2 μM vs 0.6 μM), but was not obviously toxic to cells. While 
 <bold>24</bold> was found to be active against WT M2 only, an elongated derivative (
 <bold>25</bold>) exhibited dual-inhibitory effects against WT and Ser31Asn M2 in SEVC (respective IC
 <sub>50</sub>s = 0.6 μM and 4.4 μM) and PRA (respective EC
 <sub>50</sub>s = 40 μM and 18 μM). Additionally compound 
 <bold>26</bold>, although inhibiting WT M2 with lower efficacy (20% inhibition at 100 μM) than 
 <bold>25</bold> in SEVC, was more effective at inhibiting viruses encoding WT and Ser31Asn M2 in PRA (EC
 <sub>50</sub>s = 6.9 and 1.5 μM, respectively). Preliminary data indicate that 
 <bold>23</bold> exhibits stability in human microsome assays (t
 <sub>1/2</sub> = 70 min) and mouse plasma following injection 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> (t
 <sub>1/2</sub> = 60 min). Moreover, injection of compound 
 <bold>23</bold> at 2 mg/kg did not affect the monitored ECG or hemodynamic parameters in mice, and 200 μM of cumulative dosing of 
 <bold>23</bold> over a course of 3 h did not cause obvious cardiac toxicity (P. Jalily, I. Tietjen, M. Pourrier, and D. Fedida, unpublished data).
</p>
