<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>DENV has been the cause of a Brazilian catastrophe, with more than 10 million cases reported over the last 33 years. These viruses were introduced into the most populated areas of the country at different times, DENV-1 in 1986, DENV-2 in 1990, and DENV-3 in 2000, all of which were first reported in Rio de Janeiro. In contrast, DENV-4 genotype II was introduced into Roraima State in Northern Brazil in 2010, and, in the same year, produced large outbreaks throughout the country (Fonseca and Figueiredo, 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Currently, DENV 1, 2, 3, and 4 are all fostering alternated or simultaneous epidemics in different regions of Brazil. Regarding the sylvatic maintenance cycles, DENV 1-4 were reported to have infected neotropical forest mammals such as rodents, marsupials, and bats, in French Guyana (Thoisy et al., 
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), and in the Caribbean region of Colombia, and DENV-2 was reported infecting bats (
 <italic>Carollia perspicillata</italic> and 
 <italic>Phyllostomus discolor</italic>) (Calderón et al., 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). In Brazil, 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic>, a species of mosquito that frequently inhabits the backyards of human houses but easily spreads into rural, semi-rural, and wild environments, has been found infected with DENV-3 in São Paulo State. Meanwhile, in the State of Bahia, the sylvatic vector 
 <italic>Haemogogus leucocelaenus</italic> was found to be infected with DENV-1 (Figueiredo et al., 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). In another study carried out in the Atlantic Forest of Bahia, primates (
 <italic>Leontopithecus chrysomelas</italic> and 
 <italic>Sapajus xanthosternos</italic>) were found with antibodies for DENV-1 and 2 and YFV, and sloths (
 <italic>Bradypus torquatus</italic>) had antibodies for DENV-3 (Catenacci et al., 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Therefore, despite not clearly shown, it is possible that sylvatic cycles of DENV occur in South America, although more studies are required to prove such a hypothesis.
</p>
