<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="jia225048-abs-0001">
 <title>Abstract</title>
 <sec id="jia225048-sec-0001">
  <title>Design</title>
  <p>Universal voluntary 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">HIV</styled-content> counselling and testing followed by prompt initiation of antiretroviral therapy (
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">ART</styled-content>) for all those diagnosed 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">HIV</styled-content>‐infected (universal test and treat, 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">UTT</styled-content>) is now a global health standard. However, its population‐level impact, feasibility and cost remain unknown. Five community‐based trials have been implemented in sub‐Saharan Africa to measure the effects of various 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">UTT</styled-content> strategies at population level: 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">BCPP</styled-content>/YaTsie in Botswana, 
   <italic>Max</italic>
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">ART</styled-content> in Swaziland, 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">HPTN</styled-content> 071 (Pop
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">ART</styled-content>) in South Africa and Zambia, 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">SEARCH</styled-content> in Uganda and Kenya and 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">ANRS</styled-content> 12249 TasP in South Africa. This report describes and contrasts the contexts, research methodologies, intervention packages, themes explored, evolution of study designs and interventions related to each of these five 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">UTT</styled-content> trials.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="jia225048-sec-0002">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>We conducted a comparative assessment of the five trials using data extracted from study protocols and collected during baseline studies, with additional input from study investigators. We organized differences and commonalities across the trials in five categories: trial contexts, research designs, intervention packages, trial themes and adaptations.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="jia225048-sec-0003">
  <title>Results</title>
  <p>All performed in the context of generalized 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">HIV</styled-content> epidemics, the trials highly differ in their social, demographic, economic, political and health systems settings. They share the common aim of assessing the impact of 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">UTT</styled-content> on the 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">HIV</styled-content> epidemic but differ in methodological aspects such as study design and eligibility criteria for trial populations. In addition to universal 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">ART</styled-content> initiation, the trials deliver a wide range of biomedical, behavioural and structural interventions as part of their 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">UTT</styled-content> strategies. The five studies explore common issues, including the uptake rates of the trial services and individual health outcomes. All trials have adapted since their initiation to the evolving political, economic and public health contexts, including adopting the successive national recommendations for 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">ART</styled-content> initiation.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="jia225048-sec-0004">
  <title>Conclusions</title>
  <p>We found substantial commonalities but also differences between the five 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">UTT</styled-content> trials in their design, conduct and multidisciplinary outputs. As empirical literature on how 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">UTT</styled-content> may improve efficiency and quality of 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">HIV</styled-content> care at population level is still scarce, this article provides a foundation for more collaborative research on 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">UTT</styled-content> and supports evidence‐based decision making for 
   <styled-content style="fixed-case">HIV</styled-content> care in country and internationally.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
