<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Present distributions, diversity and compartmentalization of lyssaviruses, and the empiric observation of viral genome conservation reveal great contrast to the suggested recent age of their MRCA. If one entertains that the published suggested timescale estimates of lyssaviruses are fallacious, restricted by analysis of limited sets of available isolates, one can use several other lines of evidence to hypothesize their origin and longer-term evolution. All the diversity of lyssaviruses is represented in bats (except for MOKV and IKOV, for which the reservoir hosts are yet to be established definitively), whereas carnivores maintain perpetuation of several lineages of RABV only. As such, it is commonly accepted that bats are the primary evolutionary hosts of lyssaviruses 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, 
  <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
  <xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
 </sup>. Lyssaviruses of multiple species (with the notable exception of RABV) circulate in Old World bats, but only RABV circulates in New World bats. Furthermore, RABV lineages present in New World bats, along with a few lineages circulating in skunks and raccoons (the so-called “indigenous American” RABV), are paraphyletic to the RABV lineages circulating in carnivores in the Old World and to the “cosmopolitan” canine lineage, which (as believed) was dispersed worldwide with human migrations across the globe 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
 </sup>. Nevertheless, all RABV lineages are monophyletic when compared with lyssaviruses of other species and demonstrate a greater sequence identity between each other than to lyssaviruses of other species 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
 </sup>. From this evidence, it is tempting to speculate that an ancient RABV ancestor (already distinct from lyssaviruses of other species) circulated in early bats in the territory of Gondwana, as bats presumably originated in the region of modern Africa 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
 </sup>. A bat morphologically similar to extant bats, 
 <italic>Onychonycteris</italic>, lived about 52.5 million years ago 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>
 </sup>. Other related species might have existed earlier. Molecular inferences suggested that the MRCA of present bats existed at least 80 million years ago, potentially pushing bat origins into the Cretaceous period 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
  <xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>
 </sup>. Such an ancient chiropteran origin of RABV might explain the existence of the independently evolved “indigenous American” virus lineage and the absence of similar RABVs in related bat species between the Americas and the Old World (for example, in 
 <italic>Myotis</italic> spp. and 
 <italic>Eptesicus</italic> spp.). South America and Africa split from each other between 100 and 84 million years ago and were separated by the South Atlantic Ocean. Ancient bats are hypothesized to have spread from Africa to South America slightly later, via island hopping or direct intercontinental flight 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
 </sup>. Perhaps, at that time, bats were already infected with a progenitor of the “indigenous American” RABV ( 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>). This virus might be well adapted to bat hosts (for example, owing to substitutions such as S 
 <sub>242</sub> in the viral G protein) and compartmentalized in numerous bat species, such as the indigenous phyllostomatids, across the Americas, with a later host shift to other bat species, skunks, and raccoons. Phylogenetic analysis suggested rapid diversification of bats, with all families having evolved before the late Eocene epoch 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>
 </sup>, and the same might be true for the viruses that co-evolved with their hosts, followed by millions of years characterized by stasis and slow genetic drift under constraints of purifying selection. Possibly, RABV lineages that continued to evolve in the Old World did not obtain such favorable substitutions and could not colonize multiple bat species as in the Americas but rather switched to carnivores as a comparatively recent event. Of course, this hypothesis does not explain the absence of RABV in Old World bats. However, given the less-than-ideal level of surveillance in the Old World tropics, it is possible that bat RABV does exist there but is undiscovered. Considering that four new lyssaviruses were described during the last decade (including Bokeloh bat lyssavirus in Western Europe, where surveillance is quite adequate) and that the most recent of these, Gannoruwa bat lyssavirus, was described in Sri Lanka in 2016 only 
 <sup>
  <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
 </sup>, one should expect further discoveries of lyssaviruses in the Old World. The absence of non-RABV lyssaviruses in the Americas can be explained at least in part by the fact that even at present these viruses have a limited geographic distribution and host ranges compared with RABV. If these characteristics were similar in the past, such viruses might not spread to the territory of the present Americas once Africa and South America drifted further apart ( 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>).
</p>
