<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="viruses-12-00228-f002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
 <label>Figure 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Ectopic expression of PX protein in LMH cells induced apoptosis. (
   <bold>a</bold>) Schematic diagram of recombinant eukaryotic expression vector pRK5-FLAG-viral genes. We constructed a total of 11 structural proteins into the eukaryotic expression vector pRK5-FLAG. (
   <bold>b</bold>) Ectopic expressions of FLAG-viral protein recombinants in LMH cells. Recombinant plasmids (pRK5-FLAG-hexon, -fiber1, -fiber2, -pIIIa, -IVa2, -pTP, -pVI, -pVII, -pVIII, -pX and -penton base) were individually transfected into LMH cells using the jetPRIME
   <sup>TM</sup> transfection reagent. Forty-eight hours after transfection, cells were harvested and examined with Western Blot using anti-FLAG antibodies. (
   <bold>c</bold>,
   <bold>d</bold>) Twenty-four or 48 h after transfection as above described, cells were harvested, stained with Annexin V-PE and 7-AAD, and analyzed by flow cytometry. Empty plasmid-transfected cells were used as controls (
   <bold>c</bold>). The percentage of apoptotic cells 48 h post-transfection (as in 
   <bold>c</bold>) was quantified (
   <bold>d</bold>). (
   <bold>e</bold>) Inhibition of PX-induced apoptosis by caspase inhibitors. LMH cells were seeded on 12-well plates and cultured overnight. Caspase inhibitors (z-VAD-fmk, z-DEVD-fmk, z-IETD-fmk and z-LEHD-fmk) were added to cell culture for 2 h prior to transfection with pRK5-FLAG-pX. Six hours after transfection, cells were again cultured with a caspase inhibitor. Forty-eight hours after transfection, LMH cells were harvested, stained with Annexin V-PE and 7-AAD, and analyzed by flow cytometry. The percentage of apoptotic cells in (
   <bold>e</bold>) was quantified (
   <bold>f</bold>). (
   <bold>g</bold>) Comparison of PX expressions in LMH cells by pRK5-FLAG-pX transfection with that of FAdV4 infection. LMH cells were seeded on 12-well plates and cultured overnight, followed by transfection with pRK5-FLAG-pX at 1μg per well (the same amount as that used in 
   <bold>c</bold>) or infection with FAdV4 at an MOI of 0.01, 0.1, 1 or 10. Forty-eight hours after infection or transfection, cell lysates were prepared and analyzed by Western Blot using an anti-PX specific monoclonal antibody. Results are representative of three independent experiments. Data are presented as mean ± SD, 
   <italic>n</italic> = 3. The significance of the differences between the groups was performed by one-way ANOVA (*** stands for 
   <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="viruses-12-00228-g002" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
