<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several methods have been implemented based on actual infection control and segregation to control the transmission of COVID-19. WHO and CDC published guidelines for the prevention and control of the infection. For instance, individuals should wash their hands with alcohol-based sanitizers on a routine basis. Touching of nose, mouth, and eyes should be avoided as they are the critical part for holding the infection. Moreover, a distance of approximately of 1 m from those who are sneezing and coughing should be maintained. People should uphold respiratory hygiene, such as covering nose and mouth during coughing. Individuals should wear a mask while meeting with other persons or going outside. Individuals are supposed to sanitize their workplaces [
 <xref rid="B135-ijerph-17-05904" ref-type="bibr">135</xref>]. Medical teams are supposed to cover their nose and mouth by licensed N95 masks. In some areas, the availability of the N95 mask is limited; in this case, the use of surgical masks while treating suspected and confirmed patients should be ensured. Proper use and disposal of the surgical mask is necessary to minimize the risk of transmission [
 <xref rid="B136-ijerph-17-05904" ref-type="bibr">136</xref>,
 <xref rid="B137-ijerph-17-05904" ref-type="bibr">137</xref>]. As there are clinical trials of vaccines underway, for now, the most effective prevention for the entire population is to minimize the exposure to the virus. Center for Disease Control, USA, WHO, and the Chinese CDC have provided proper guidelines to enhance awareness among the population about the prevention of COVID-19. The main emphasis of the guidelines includes awareness on how to wear a face mask, appropriate hand washing techniques, preventive measures at home and workplaces, and disinfection procedures and protocols. Furthermore, the guidelines are available on the treatment, prevention, and control of COVID-19. The guidelines also endorse ways of minimizing the fear of COVID-19 among the overall population [
 <xref rid="B138-ijerph-17-05904" ref-type="bibr">138</xref>]. Considering all the nonpharmaceutical measures assist the maintenance of the public outcomes of the pandemic to be in control, because of several financial reasons, the numbers are again elevating. There are multiple steps involved in preparation for personal protection equipment (PPE), including identifying PPE and to ensure a proper gown size, performing hand hygiene using hand sanitizer, wearing proper masks, put on face shield or goggles, and gloves in areas that could be necessary. The guidelines could be different based on the profession, location, and severity of the disease.
</p>
