<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The cost of medicine plays only a modest role in the overall cost of health care in Western countries. The capitalistic approach to health care has already unfortunately resulted in the exclusion of a large number of citizens in these countries, and it will be interesting to see how governments will deal with this growing problem. Will they shift their focus from sustaining a too expensive health care system or will they start to investigate any and all possible methods to improve the health of their citizens and reduce the cost, even if this means using inexpensive medicinal plants. In this chapter, we used 
 <italic>A. annua</italic> as an example of how quick a potential lead can be found with the use of the reverse pharmacology approach. The scientific investigation into the medicinal properties of this remarkable plant is unfortunately very limited for the reasons stated above. We do, however, know that this plant has been used for hundreds of years for the treatment of various ailments without any reports of serious side effects or toxicity. This plant is currently being used for the treatment of malaria (approved by the WHO) and HIV (ethnobotanical use), and there are also reports that people have started to use 
 <italic>A. annua</italic> for the treatment of various forms of cancer (Anamed). Lui et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2011b</xref>) have recently shown that artemisinin does indeed show selective action against breast cancer cell lines, and this selectivity should be more than enough reason to study this plant in more detail. We can conclude that the development of new drugs is prohibitively expensive, and that many lead compounds fail during clinical trials. With 
 <italic>A. annua,</italic> we have an uncontrolled clinical trial happening in exactly the right place—in countries suffering the most under the burden of HIV. It is therefore important to put health before short-term profits as this will lead to long-term profits. We are therefore calling for performing an in-depth scientific study into the traditional formulation consisting of 
 <italic>A. annua</italic> for the treatment of HIV, malaria and also certain forms of cancer. This medicinal plant definitely has the potential to have a global impact on our approach to health care, but importantly we also have to be honest. After scientific scrutiny of 
 <italic>A. annua,</italic> it might turn out not to work in the way we expect—only time will tell. 
</p>
