<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0095">
 <list list-type="simple" id="lis0020">
  <list-item id="lsti0060">
   <label>1</label>
   <p id="par0100">If technical facilities are available [
    <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
    <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>];
    <list list-type="simple" id="lis0025">
     <list-item id="lsti0065">
      <label>a</label>
      <p id="par0105">It is necessary to select plasma, those with anti-SARS-CoV-2 titers with a neutralizing antibody level 1:80 or above, or those with antibody level above this threshold level after the threshold level defined in the literature by ELISA test corresponding to this threshold level, (retention sample should be stored from the CCP donation for to test antibody titers at a later time when it is available),</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item id="lsti0070">
      <label>b</label>
      <p id="par0110">In order to maximize transfusion safety, it is recommended to subject the received plasma to “Pathogen Inactivation”.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0075">
   <label>2</label>
   <p id="par0115">Plasma should be collected via apheresis from 200 to 600 mL ignoring the amount of anticoagulant solution. In case of plasma is collected more than 200 mL the plasma should be divided to 200 mL volum and be labeled individulally including unique idenfification number(s),</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0080">
   <label>3</label>
   <p id="par0120">Collected plasma component should be labeled spesific (COVID-19 Immune Plasma) by using ISBT 128 Coding System. Blood centers except than Turkish Red Crescent (TRC) that are collecting CCP should provide the provision of TRC before the collection of CCP,</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0085">
   <label>4</label>
   <p id="par0125">In terms of traceability witness sample should be stored in accordance with the National Regulation,</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0090">
   <label>5</label>
   <p id="par0130">CCP should be irradiated if the collected plasma would be used without freezing within 6 h after collection,</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="lsti0095">
   <label>6</label>
   <p id="par0135">CCP should be stored for one year of expiration date at −18 °C or cooler circumstances.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
