<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Two drugs constituted the main arsenal against HAT (sleeping sickness) in Central Africa, until the Second World War: 
 <italic>atoxyl</italic>, administered intramuscularly, which had little therapeutic value, and 
 <italic>tryparsamide</italic>, administered intravenously, which permitted cures in advanced disease. Other intravenous drugs were used in the 1930s, but their combined number of injections was considerably lower than that of 
 <italic>tryparsamide</italic>. In AEF, Belgian Congo, and German Kamerun (we will use this spelling to refer to Cameroon under German colonization, 1884–1916), 
 <italic>atoxyl </italic>started to be used around 1907–1909 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72-viruses-04-01950">72</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B106-viruses-04-01950">106</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B107-viruses-04-01950">107</xref>]. Colonial doctors believed that 
 <italic>atoxyl </italic>could clear the peripheral blood from trypanosomes and thus, injecting rural people on a large scale would prevent the spread of the epidemic. They performed numerous “
 <italic>tournées d'atoxylization</italic>” in many rural areas of Central Africa in the two decades following 1907, administering usually one or two injections to each person infected or suspected to be infected [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72-viruses-04-01950">72</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B108-viruses-04-01950">108</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B109-viruses-04-01950">109</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B110-viruses-04-01950">110</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B111-viruses-04-01950">111</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B112-viruses-04-01950">112</xref>]. Several injection campaigns were performed by the French in Haute Sangha (including Nola) in the period 1907–1913 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83-viruses-04-01950">83</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B109-viruses-04-01950">109</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B112-viruses-04-01950">112</xref>]. Others were performed by the Germans in the Nola region (which was annexed to Kamerun in the period 1911–1914 following a Franco-German agreement) and in neighboring southeast Kamerun, where the disease was observed on the banks of the Ngoko [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72-viruses-04-01950">72</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B113-viruses-04-01950">113</xref>]. These 
 <italic>tournées</italic> were very irregular: some interior regions were not visited at all for many years; and, particularly in the 1920s, some regions were visited often, causing some people to receive six and sometimes more injections per year [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72-viruses-04-01950">72</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B114-viruses-04-01950">114</xref>].
</p>
