<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As suggested above, screening drugs for adverse toxicity against mitochondria is vital for their safe use. However, many drugs have been discovered with interesting modulating properties that potentially could prove useful in the clinic or as research tools. The concern in the pharmaceutical industry to screen out drugs with dangerous adverse side effects may have led to the rejection of many beneficial drugs. Research has revealed over the past decade a dependency of many cancer types on mitochondrial function. These dependencies can be shown to be a liability in some cases as selective targeting of the mitochondria has proved efficacious in these studies. Potentially useful new therapeutic cancer agents such as the common antibiotic doxycycline with only mild mitochondrial effects [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>,
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>] might have been discarded at the initial drug-screening phase if put through these. The benefit of drug-targeting mitochondria is particularly relevant to the treatment of cancer. Recent research has demonstrated that cancer cells have a strong reliance on mitochondrial function particularly in the area of metastatic disease [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>–
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. The new cancer drug ONC201 [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], which has demonstrated efficacy in cell culture and animal models, is currently being tested against multiple cancer types and could have been discarded if put through a mitochondrial toxicity screen. ONC201 was identified from a screen for compounds that induced the transcription of tumour necrosis-related apoptosis-inducing ligand (TRAIL), an inducer of apoptosis [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. Follow-up studies discovered that ONC201 did not directly activate TRAIL in all of the cancer cells in which it was effective but was impairing mitochondrial function [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Recent data from two studies identified the target of ONC201 as being the mitochondrial CLPP protease which is activated by ONC201 and results in increased cancer cell killing [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>,
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>].
</p>
