<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17">A proportion of the patients showed no symptoms at enrollment as they were at very early stage of the diseases. These patients could either recover without developing symptom or would continue to develop symptoms. However, the former group of patients never have any symptoms or signs, but their respiratory tract specimens are PCR positive for the virus. The exact number of the proportion of asymptomatic patients requires longitudinal study with repeated PCR tests. In a study that followed 13 patients in Wuhan, China, 31% of them never developed symptoms
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>. In another study performed on the Diamond Princess cruise ship, repeated PCR testing of 3711 quarantined passengers and crew members showed that asymptomatic proportion is around 18%
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>
 </sup>. More recently, the proportion of infected people have mild or asymptomatic were estimated to represent some 60% of all infections
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>
 </sup>. Notably, asymptomatic and symptomatic patients show comparable viral load, suggesting that these patients have strong transmission potentials
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. Indeed, viral transmission from asymptomatic carriers have been reported
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>
 </sup>. In a recent study from China, Chen et al. followed up 2147 close contactors of 191 patients (161 symptomatic and 30 asymptomatic). They found that the infection rates of transmission rate in symptomatic cases was 6.3% comparing with 4.1% in asymptomatic patients, indicating the importance of identification and isolation of asymptomatic patients in the effort of containment the spread of the virus
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. Importantly, for large-scale screening, antibody testing should be combined with PCR to avoid asymptomatic viral spreading.
</p>
