<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another important step in the development of the permissive mouse genetic background for human HSC engraftment went through the development of mouse defective or carrying a mutation into the common gamma chain of the Interleukin (IL)-2 receptor (IL2Rγ) [
 <xref rid="B240-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">240</xref>]. IL2Rγ is a receptor for multiple cytokines such as IL-2, 4, 7, 9, 15 and 21. Disruption of IL-15-mediated signaling induces severe deficiencies in NK cell development and maturation, leading to a more severe immunodeficiency and more permissive environment for human HSC engraftment in adult 
 <italic>RAG2
  <sup>-/-</sup>
 </italic> supplemented or unsupplemented by the exogenous administration of human cytokines [
 <xref rid="B241-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">241</xref>,
 <xref rid="B242-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">242</xref>], and in adult 
 <italic>NOD-SCID</italic> mice [
 <xref rid="B243-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">243</xref>]. Another important step that followed was the demonstration that the intrahepatic injection of human CD34+ cells into newborn 
 <italic>Rag2
  <sup>−/−</sup> IL2Rγ
  <sup>null</sup>
 </italic> and 
 <italic>NOD-SCID IL2Rγ
  <sup>null</sup>
 </italic> mice led to the induction of low, albeit significant, functional adaptive responses in these mice [
 <xref rid="B244-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">244</xref>,
 <xref rid="B245-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">245</xref>], which opened the door to novel investigations of human immunity in vivo. An alternative model to the 
 <italic>NOD-SCID IL2Rγ
  <sup>null</sup>
 </italic> mice, namely 
 <italic>NOD-SCID JAK
  <sub>3</sub>
  <sup>null</sup>,
 </italic> has also been reported. In this model, 
 <italic>JAK
  <sub>3</sub>
 </italic>, a gene encoding for a tyrosine kinase critical for IL2Rγ-mediated signaling is knocked-out instead of 
 <italic>IL2Rγ</italic>, resulting in a complete lack of B, T and NK cells [
 <xref rid="B246-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">246</xref>].
</p>
