<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Genotypes of DENV-1 (genotype V) and DENV-2 (cosmopolitan genotype) circulating in Bhutan were found different from the DENV-1 (genotype I) and DENV-2 (Asian I genotype) strains in the components of Dengvaxia vaccine, the first licensed tetravalent dengue vaccine, respectively. Previous study investigating the association between DENV genotypes and level of vaccine efficacy from the two phase III efficacy trials of the Dengvaxia vaccine including CYD14 trail in the Asia-Pacific region and CYD15 trial in Latin America, revealed the various association in each serotype [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008165.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Different level of vaccine efficacy against the three DENV-1 genotypes was not found. Among DENV-2 genotypes, the vaccine efficacy against Asian I genotype was significantly lower than that against the American-Asian and Cosmopolitan genotypes. Vaccine efficacy against DENV-4 genotype I was significantly lower than that against genotype II in participants of all ages, but among participants 9–16 years of age, the vaccine efficacy were similarly high between the two DENV-4 genotypes. For DENV-3, the association between vaccine efficacy and genotype was still uncertain [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008165.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Post-licensure research of this vaccine and other vaccines in the future is necessary to enhance understanding of this association. Continued investigation of DENV genetic epidemiology is critical to provide genetic background information of viral populations that would imply the vaccine efficacy, and benefit in providing and/or managing vaccine program in the country. We have several limitations in this study. The surveillance being a passive one, many pertinent demographic and epidemiological data could not be captured. We lack information on the days of infection (DOI) and details of symptoms presented. We were unable to establish the actual laboratory cases of the total suspected cases since due to lack of standard protocol and shortage of test kits for performing either IgM/gG or NS1 tests to screen all the cases. Thus we have no information on seroprevalence of DENV.
</p>
