<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par46">It should be mainly differentiated from viral pneumonia, bacterial pneumonia and pulmonary edema. Chest X-ray demonstrates viral pneumonia mainly as interstitial pneumonia and bronchial pneumonia. In its early stage, chest X-ray demonstrates enhanced but poorly defined lung markings, predominantly both lower lung fields, with increased density like GGO. In its progressive stage, the lung fields are demonstrated with reticular opacity or reticular nodules and the nodules commonly distribute in the both lower lung fields and around the hilum, with a diameter of less than 5 mm. It its advanced stage, bronchiolar inflammatory occlusion causes cystic changes in different sizes to show honeycomb like lung, with shrinkage of lung, elevated diaphragm and shift of interlobar fissure. CT scan demonstrates small nodular opacity, ground glass opacity, tree-buds sign and mosaic like perfusion in lungs. Chest X-ray demonstrates bacterial pneumonia mainly as alveolar pneumonia or bronchial pneumonia. Alveolar pneumonia is demonstrated as lobar consolidation with high uniform density or consolidation with high uniform density occupying part of lung lobe, with air bronchogram inside and one or multiple lung lobes involved. Bronchial pneumonia is demonstrated as thickened lung markings, poorly defined nodular or flakes of opacity in a diameter of 6–8 mm. Bronchial occlusion by mucus can be demonstrated as lobular atelectasis or focal emphysema in the diseased area. The lesions are commonly located in the medial part of both lower lung fields, with more in the posterior lung lobe than in the anterior lung lobe, that distribute along bronchial branches. And the segmental and lobar bronchi show smooth air flow. CT scan demonstrates consolidations with uniform shape and lobar distribution, with air bronchogram inside, and poorly defined nodular or patches of opacities of different sizes along bronchial bundles as well as lobular atelectasis and focal emphysema. Pulmonary edema and acute or chronic systolic or diastolic heart dysfunction due to various etiological factors can lead to increased pressure in the pulmonary vein and pulmonary capillaries as well as pulmonary congestion. The liquid firstly accumulates in the perivascular sheath in lungs and interlobular space to cause pulmonary interstitial edema, which then flow into the alveolar cavity to cause pulmonary parenchyma edema. Chest X-ray demonstrates interstitial edema as thickened, deranged and re-ranged lung markings, thickened but poorly defined vascular markings in both upper lung fields, enlarged and dense hilar opacities in both lungs, thickened and dilated but poorly defined vascular markings in the middle and medial parts of both lung fields. However, chest X-ray demonstrates interstitial edema with fine vascular markings in peripheral lung field and well defined peripheral lung field. Its further progression can be demonstrated with flakes of opacity in both lungs with butterfly wing like shape and concentric distribution. Chest X-ray demonstrates alveolar edema as initially poorly defined flakes of opacities in different sizes with sporadic distribution in both lungs. Along with its progression, chest X-ray demonstrates large flakes of high density opacity after fusion, which extends from the hilum to the peripheral lung with gradually light density, in typical butterfly wing like sign.</p>
