<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">SARS-CoV is a coronavirus with a diameter of approximately 100 nm. Coronaviruses are the largest +ssRNA viruses and contain at least 14 ORFs,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>
 </sup> among which five main ORFs encode the replicase (Rep), and the S, E, M, and N proteins.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>
 </sup> Similar to other coronaviruses, there is a wide array of spike proteins on the envelope of SARS-CoV that resemble a corona. With its unique RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp), SARS-CoV often switches template strands during replication. Thus, if a cell is infected with several coronaviruses, RNA recombination may occur. The N protein combines with viral RNA to form a nucleocapsid, which is involved in the replication of SARS-CoV and is the most abundant protein in virus-infected cells.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>
 </sup> The M protein is a membrane glycoprotein that is involved in budding and envelope formation. The S protein of SARS-CoV is a type I transmembrane (TM) glycoprotein that is responsible for viral binding, fusion and entry into cells, as well as antibody induction.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>
 </sup> The S protein contains a signal peptide (SP: amino acids 1–12) and three domains called the extracellular domain (amino acids 13–1193), the TM domain (amino acids 1194–1215) and the intracellular region (amino acids 1216–1255).
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup> The extracellular domain consists of two subunits: S1 and S2. The fragment located in the middle region of the S1 subunit (amino acids 318–510) is the angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) receptor-binding region. The S2 subunit comprises a fusion peptide (FP) and two x 7-valent element repeats (HR1 and HR2) that are responsible for fusion between the virus and the target cell membrane.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>
 </sup> Thus, the S protein may be key to develop a vaccine to generate antibodies and block virus binding and fusion in the coronaviruses (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).
</p>
