<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">SARS-CoV-2, which causes COVID-19, is a spherical betacoronavirus with a diameter of 60–140 nm and unique spikes ranging from 9 to 12 nm.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup> Its RNA has the typical betacoronavirus organization, containing a 5′ UTR, a gene encoding the replicase complex (ORF1a/b), the S gene, E gene, M gene, and N gene, a 3′ UTR, and several unidentified nonstructural ORFs.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>
 </sup> The length of the sequences is 265 nt for the 5′ terminal region, 229 nt for the 3′ terminal region, 3822 nt for the S gene, 228 nt for the E gene, 669 nt for the M gene, and 1260 nt for the N gene.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>
 </sup> The 21,291-nt-long ORF1a/b gene contains 16 predicted NSPs.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>
 </sup> Similar to SARS-CoV, there is a predicted ORF8 gene that is 366 nt in length and located between the M and N ORF genes.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>
 </sup> Nucleotides 1, 1029, and 1652 may be the recombination breakpoints because based on the fragments from nt 1 to nt 1029 and nt 1652 to the end, SARS-CoV-2 seems to be related to bat-SL-CoVZC45 and bat-SL-CoVZXC21; however, when considering the region from nt 1030 to nt 1651, SARS-CoV-2 is mostly likely to be grouped with SARS-CoV and bat SARS-like CoVs. More research is required to analyze the recombination of the genome as a whole.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>
 </sup> With over 10% of its conserved replicase complex being different from those of other betacoronaviruses, SARS-CoV-2 solely occupies a newly created subclade within the 
 <italic>Sarbecovirus</italic> subgenus.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>
 </sup> Bats may be its natural host, but owing to several arguments including the complicated environment in the wet markets in Wuhan, this remains unclear, and further research is needed.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>
 </sup> The free energy of the spike protein of SARS-CoV-2 is much lower than that of SARS-CoV, indicating that SARS-CoV-2 is more stable than SARS-CoV.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>
 </sup> The high similarity of the RBD sequences and of the spike protein structures between SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>
 </sup> also the simulation of the spike protein of SARS-CoV-2 binding to ACE2,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>
 </sup> the receptor of SARS-CoV, and results shown that ACE2 plays a vital role in SARS-CoV-2 entry into HeLa cells,
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>
 </sup> indicating that SARS-CoV-2 also uses ACE2 for cell entry. Structural modeling of the ACE2-B0AT1 complex (B0AT1 is used to obtain stable ACE2) suggests that the complex can bind two S proteins simultaneously, providing important clues to the molecular basis of coronavirus recognition and infection.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>
 </sup> The RBD-ACE2 binding free energy for SARS-CoV-2 is significantly lower than that for SARS-CoV, in accordance with the fact that SARS-CoV-2 is more infectious than SARS-CoV.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>
 </sup> A recent study found that CD147, a kind of TM glycoprotein, facilitates cell entry of SARS-CoV-2 functionally, and its affinity constant with the S protein is 1.85 × 10
 <sup>−7</sup> M.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>
 </sup> Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> shows a comparison of the structures of SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV, and SARS-CoV-2. The specific function of the SARS-CoV-2 proteins, including S, E, M, and N proteins, need further study.
</p>
