<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par35">Parasitic infections having a serious impact on the health, worldwide [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>]. Many of the drugs used today are not very effective and some of them can cause severe complications, so trying to find novel agents to control parasitic infections has great attention [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>]. There are various strategies on the development of parasite-specific aptamers. They can prevent the interaction between the parasite and the host
 <italic>. Trypanosoma cruzi</italic> is a parasite that invade host cell. Ulrich, et al. identified an aptamer that could block receptor-ligand interactions between 
 <italic>T. cruzi</italic> and epithelial monkey kidney LLC-MK2 host cells and thus, inhibit cell invasion [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>]. Aptamers can inhibit the function of proteins [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>]. Erythrocyte membrane protein 1 (EMP1) is a key factor in the pathogenicity of the 
 <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic>. This protein involved in parasite adhesion to erythrocytes. Specific RNA aptamers are able to detect this protein on the surface of infected erythrocytes. So the aptamers act as an anti-rosetting drug [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>]. Other aptamers that target protein are AptLiH2A#1 and AptLiH2A#2 that distinguished the LiH2A protein. These ssDNA aptamers bind to 
 <italic>Leishmania infantum</italic> H2A with high affinity and does not identify other 
 <italic>Leishmania</italic> proteins [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>]. Another example for the inhibition of the function of proteins are poly (A)-binding protein (PABP) DNA aptamers (ApPABP#3, ApPABP#7 and ApPABP#11). They were able to bind PABP that is an essential protein for 
 <italic>leishmania infantum</italic> survival. ApPABP#11, degrades the binding of PABP to poly(A), this feature may be applied in regulating the function of PABP in vivo [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>]. EhCFIm25 is critical for parasite virulence and survival, EhCFIm25 silencing could reduce parasite mobility and induced cell death. RNA aptamers (C4 and C5) containing the GUUG motif were isolated, which inhibited 
 <italic>Entamoeba histolytica’s</italic> growth by blocking of EhCFIm25 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>]. Several aptamers developed against parasitic infections are summarized in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. 
</p>
