<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Several 
 <italic>Leishmania</italic> species are transmitted zoonotically, and in the case of 
 <italic>L. infantum</italic>, dogs are the main reservoir. In many settings, dogs may serve as a link between sylvatic and domestic cycles of visceral leishmaniasis. Dogs can cross forest-edge boundaries, thereby potentially bringing parasites to or from sylvatic systems and to and from other potential mammalian hosts (such as foxes, rodents, and opossums) (
 <xref rid="B242" ref-type="bibr">242</xref>). In Yucatan, Mexico, the prevalence of 
 <italic>L. mexicana</italic>, 
 <italic>L. infantum</italic>, and 
 <italic>L. braziliensis</italic> in dog sera (
 <italic>n</italic> = 218) was 30.2, 11.9, and 8.2%, respectively (
 <xref rid="B257" ref-type="bibr">257</xref>). Antibody based prevalence of 10.5% for 
 <italic>L. mexicana</italic> and 11.57% for 
 <italic>L. braziliensis</italic> has also been reported in cats (
 <xref rid="B258" ref-type="bibr">258</xref>). Vertical transmission of leshmaniasis has been characterized for dogs and people, causing an increased risk for infants born to parasitemic mothers (
 <xref rid="B259" ref-type="bibr">259</xref>). There have also been a number of non-travel-associated reports of cutaneous leishmaniasis in companion animals in Texas (
 <xref rid="B250" ref-type="bibr">250</xref>). Many of these cases of zoonotic cutaneous leishmaniasis were in cats, which may be associated with an outdoor life-style (
 <xref rid="B250" ref-type="bibr">250</xref>). Until recently, visceral leishmaniasis was thought to be primarily an imported disease in North America. Infected dogs had usually been imported from regions in Southern Europe or South America where 
 <italic>L. infantum</italic> and 
 <italic>L. chagasi</italic> were enzootic (
 <xref rid="B260" ref-type="bibr">260</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B261" ref-type="bibr">261</xref>). Additional risk factors for humans are related to their immunologic status and their ability to clear infection or maintain an asymptomatic state. These factors include concurrent infection with HIV, co-infections with helminthic parasites, drug abuse, and other immunosuppressive conditions (
 <xref rid="B262" ref-type="bibr">262</xref>).
</p>
