<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="simple">
 <list-item>
  <label>1.</label>
  <p>
   <bold>Funders of studies should be more explicit in their guidance to awardees about requirements to release specimens utilized for the study as soon as any primary or secondary aims of the initial study are complete</bold>, and this should be completed within a defined timeframe. ‘Ownership’ of specimens collected through studies is a significant hurdle to overcome in the development of a consolidated repository. Understandably, individuals typically do not want to release specimens held in their archives without guarantees that the work performed on them is going to be valuable, and institutions worry about yielding control of specimens under their purview. Indeed, specimens in a consolidated repository may be used in ways that diverge from the expertise of the researchers who were instrumental in their collection, often leading to further reluctance to collaborate. Funders should also look across the repertoire of studies they fund, to help identify where specimens may be available and how specimens collected from one study may be beneficial to others.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <label>2.</label>
  <p>
   <bold>In developing ethical approval for studies, more emphasis should be placed on ensuring that specimens collected can be used for other, perhaps currently unknown, purposes.</bold> This may mean setting a period of time for the study after which anonymization of specimens is routinely conducted so they may be broadly shared. It will also likely require that further explanation of the potential uses of specimens be given to study participants at the time of consent.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <label>3.</label>
  <p>
   <bold>Journals should come to some general consensus about the best mechanisms for acknowledging researchers who contributed specimens that were later used for a secondary study.</bold> In a large repository with rapid turnover of specimens, inclusion of all researchers contributing specimens into the authorship list of any subsequent papers is likely impractical. Yet especially in academia, where a publication record is typically a major factor in continued employment and promotion, rights to authorship is critical currency when determining whether specimens should be shared with a repository system for future use. Recognition of the hard work that went into specimen acquisition and initial maintenance – as well as incentivization for collegial relationships between researchers – would be an important way to ensure successful construction of a consolidated repository.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <label>4.</label>
  <p>
   <bold>Major funders should ensure that studies collect as much ancillary data around the work they do as possible without infringing on the rights of study participants.</bold> While most researchers work to minimize and streamline data collection to improve participant enrollment rates (i.e. not requiring participants to disclose full medical histories), there are many simple factors of study protocol or process that could help with the effective use of specimens for subsequent analyses. One clear example of this is the type of assay used to confirm an infection, which due to different sensitivities and specificities may, over time, affect how an assay result may be interpreted or how a specimen may be categorized.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <label>5.</label>
  <p>
   <bold>Leadership of a consolidated repository should be supported by the endorsement of major funders and normative agencies.</bold> With international, influential commitments to the development and use of a major repository to address upcoming challenges to HIV diagnostics, the ease of securing appropriate specimens will dramatically increase. The repository should be open internationally, with its use based on scientific need, with clear systems and guidelines for specimen access. Further, management of the repository should not just include physically obtaining, storing, and shipping specimens, but should also involve skilled support for data analysis, to help guide users in proper application of the specimens and their associated information. Standards should be set for commercial use of specimens, such that for-profit development is allowed with an appropriate exchange of funding that helps the repository be sustained for the future.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <label>6.</label>
  <p>
   <bold>Repository owners should attempt to develop an ROI methodology.</bold> To assist with sustainable funding for useful consolidated repositories, a mechanism to fairly track investments, expenses, and returns is imperative. Such a system will help potential funders see the benefits of their investments in these projects, and should also include metrics to determine whether a repository should continue or whether the ROI has fallen to a point such that future funding should cease and specimens should be disseminated for storage in other more productive settings.
  </p>
 </list-item>
</list>
