<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Current evidence suggests that SARS-CoV-2 is likely to have a natural origin [
 <xref rid="B11-viruses-12-00526" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] and is primarily transmitted via inhalation of droplets expelled when an infected patient coughs. Fomite-mediated transmission is another important source of transmission when hands which have touched surfaces contaminated by droplets are used to touch the face, eyes, or nose. Modeling of SARS-CoV-2 spread estimation from multiple studies suggests that the basic reproduction number (R
 <sub>0</sub>) ranges from 2.2 to 5.7 depending upon the population [
 <xref rid="B12-viruses-12-00526" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-viruses-12-00526" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] (see 
 <xref ref-type="boxed-text" rid="viruses-12-00526-box001">Box 1</xref>). This reported R
 <sub>0</sub> is higher than seasonal influenza, indicating the potential for sustained human-to-human transmission within a population unless strict containment and public health measures are implemented and sustained. As a new coronavirus, there is currently insufficient data to reach a consensus on the potential for seasonality of SARS-CoV-2 transmission since the human population is completely naïve to this virus. Keeping this factor aside, two major factors that may have an influence on seasonality are changes in environmental parameters and human behavior [
 <xref rid="B14-viruses-12-00526" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Specifically, outdoor (e.g., temperature, humidity, sunlight/vitamin D status) and indoor environmental factors (e.g., temperature, humidity, air change rate, etc.) influence both virus transmission parameters (e.g., virus viability, airborne aerosolization, droplet spray, and direct contact) and host defenses (e.g., airway antiviral immune defense and efficiency of nasal and bronchial mucociliary clearance). Although the seasonality has not been confirmed for SARS-CoV-2, there is now accumulating evidence that climate variables might play a role in transmission [
 <xref rid="B15-viruses-12-00526" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-12-00526" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].
</p>
