<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Most clinical trials originally came from China, whereas they were mainly focused on lung damage leading to death in COVID-positive patients from severe respiratory failure. Upon SARS-CoV-2 arrived in Europe and around the world, the virus was found also to target many other organs. Therefore, from a clinical point of view, COVID-19 would be defined as the “COVID Planet” because of the multifaceted clinical and laboratory aspects of the disease, related to the large number of tissues involved by SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="B70-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. The initial stages of COVID-19 infection are nonspecific and include symptoms typical of multiple respiratory illnesses (
 <xref rid="microorganisms-08-01228-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Most cases are mild (81%), being the symptoms usually self-limiting with the recovery occurring in two weeks [
 <xref rid="B71-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. In fact, on the basis of existing Chinese data published so far, 80.9% of patients infected with the virus develop mild infection and include symptoms nonspecific and typical of multiple respiratory illnesses, viral and bacterial. Some of these, which may occur simultaneously with COVID-19, should be considered in the differential diagnosis (
 <xref rid="microorganisms-08-01228-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In agreement with Chinese studies, patients develop severe pneumonia in 13.8% of cases, respiratory failure in 4.7%, and septic shock or even multi-organ failure in 5%. Of these, 3% are fatal [
 <xref rid="B31-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B70-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>,
 <xref rid="B71-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>,
 <xref rid="B72-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. The cause of death among infected patients is severe respiratory failure. Patients with severe presentation, closely resembles SARS-CoV-1 and/or MERS-CoV infections [
 <xref rid="B73-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], may develop ARDS and require ICU admission, although oxygen therapy and assisted intubation may not be useful because of pulmonary and generalized venous thromboembolism [
 <xref rid="B66-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,
 <xref rid="B74-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. 
</p>
