<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The range age of hospitalized patients is 57–79 years, with 1/3–1/2 affected by an underlying illness. In general, there is a higher risk of death for males at 2.8%, while it remains at 1.7% for females [
 <xref rid="B19-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B75-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. Available data suggest that COVID-19 has an incubation period of ~5–7 days (range 2–14 days). The complete clinical profile of COVID-19 is not fully understood. Symptoms may appear in as few as 2 days or after as many as 14 (estimated ranges vary from 2–10 days, 2–14 days, and 10–14 days), during which the virus is contagious, but the patient does not display any symptom (asymptomatic transmission). The most common symptoms [
 <xref rid="B19-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B68-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>,
 <xref rid="B69-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>] are fever, cough, pharyngitis, dyspnea, rarely kidney failure, suggesting fever is dominant, but not the main symptom of infection (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="microorganisms-08-01228-f002">Figure 2</xref>). A small number of patients can have headache/hemoptysis/diarrhea and even be relatively asymptomatic [
 <xref rid="B42-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Patients with chronic underlying diseases, including hypertension, cardio-cerebrovascular diseases, and diabetes or other conditions that may compromise their immune systems, may increase the risk of SARS-CoV-2 infection [
 <xref rid="B48-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Smoking may be a negative prognostic indicator for COVID-19 [
 <xref rid="B48-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. As for SARS, no deaths have been reported in the pediatric age group, especially under the age of 10 years old [
 <xref rid="B76-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. If in adults the virus triggers an abnormal and disproportionate immune system reaction in critical cases, in children the immune response is more balanced towards infection and there is often an optimal recovery within a week, as respiratory involvement, when present, tends to be more benign [
 <xref rid="B31-microorganisms-08-01228" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].
</p>
