<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Previous studies have implied that the unavailability of ample vsiRNAs in virus-infected–differentiated mammalian cells is probably due to the presence of potent VSRs (
 <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>14</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>16</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>18</italic>
 </xref>), and thus, disabling VSR may be a useful way to assess whether RNAi exerts antiviral effect against certain viruses (
 <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>12</italic>
 </xref>). Similar with the well-characterized VSR–EV-A71 3A, flaviviral NS2A is also a small (~22 kDa) transmembrane protein, which participates in viral RNA replication and virion assembly, and antagonizes IFN response (
 <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>25</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>31</italic>
 </xref>); and ZIKV NS2A has been recently found to interact with and deplete adherens junction proteins in radial glial cells (
 <xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>32</italic>
 </xref>). On the other hand, the VSR activity of flaviviral NS2A was not assessed before. In the current study, we first identified DENV2 NS2A as a potential VSR via a set of in vitro assays. Then, when NS2A’s VSR activity was disabled by reverse genetics, VSR-deficient DENV2 induced abundant vsiRNA production and antiviral RNAi response in infected mammalian somatic cells, resulting in attenuated viral replication and infection compared to the WT. The replication defect caused by disabling VSR can be rescued by impairing the RNAi machinery in an IFN-irrespective manner, demonstrating that RNAi does exert antiviral effect against DENV2 infection in differentiated mammalian cells. NS2A also acts as a bona fide VSR during DENV2 infection of 
 <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquito cells. Using NS2A as VSR is a common strategy for multiple flaviviruses to evade antiviral RNAi.
</p>
