<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0110">While an exact evolutionary driver is unclear, several potential selective advantages conferred by a shift to favor high-mannose glycosylation in human IAVs can be observed. For example, modeling analyses suggest that high-mannose type glycans mostly favor close packing against the HA surface. Glycans in such a conformation have potential as a steric shield, and are suggested here since almost all glycosites with significant oligomannose fractions map to functionally important regions of HA such as key antigenic sites, and the interface of the head and stem domains which houses the membrane-fusion machinery (
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Blijleven et al., 2016</xref>) (
 <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). Steric blocking at this interface region, which has high sequence homology across all HA subtypes, would likely confer advantage on human seasonal IAV strains, biasing antibody responses to more exposed areas of the viral surface with greater tolerance to antigenic drift. Additionally, the altered presentation of glycoepitopes where high-mannose glycans are attached might also reduce immunogenicity by altering or inhibiting antibody recognition of the more recessed carbohydrate component. Increased high-mannose glycosylation may also provide a replicative advantage during infection, since treatment of MDCK cells with the ER α-mannosidase inhibitor kifunensine has been shown to lead to enhanced growth and replication (
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Elbein et al., 1982</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">Pan et al., 1983</xref>). One recent report has suggested that this effect may center around specific induction of the ER-associated protein degradation (ERAD) pathway, directly targeting HA biosynthesis as a potential antiviral mechanism (
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Frabutt et al., 2018</xref>). Thus, evolution of glycosites with reduced accessibility of nascent glycans to mannosidases and mannosidase-like proteins could inhibit this pathway, leading to enhanced replication. Presence of oligomannose glycans on human IAV HAs may also be relevant to localization of infection within respiratory tissues. IAV infection in humans is typically initiated through exposure to airborne respiratory droplets, resulting in virus binding to α2-6-linked receptors on the surface of epithelial cells in the upper airway (
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Connor et al., 1994</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Peng et al., 2017</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Rogers and Paulson, 1983</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Shinya et al., 2006</xref>). It is now well established that primary innate immune defenses against influenza in the respiratory tract consist of secreted host factors, including calcium-dependent (C-type) surfactant proteins SP-A and SP-D (
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Hartshorn et al., 1994</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Nayak et al., 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Ng et al., 2012</xref>). Notably, SP-D binds specifically to high-mannose type N-glycans (
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Goh et al., 2013</xref>), particularly Man
 <sub>9</sub>, and confers protection against pathogens containing oligomannose. However, gene expression studies have revealed that SP-D is mainly isolated to the lung and lower respiratory tissues (
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">Su et al., 2004</xref>), thus human-adapted IAVs that primarily target the upper respiratory tract are able to increase high-mannose N-glycan expression while still evading host immune defenses.
</p>
