<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <italic>WNV infection and autonomic nervous system:</italic> To date, there are very few reports on WNV-related autonomic nervous system dysfunction or the role that dysautonomia plays in the morbidity and mortality of human WNV infection. Yet, symptoms of dysautonomia are commonly observed during the acute WNV infection and in WNV survivors recovered from the acute illness. In one study of 44 WNV patients that reported prolonged (&gt; 6 months) post-infectious symptoms, gastrointestinal symptoms (abdominal pain, bloating or diarrhea) were reported by 21 (48%), night sweats in 20 (45%), increased anxiety in 14 (32%) and irregular heartbeat in 9 (20%) [
 <xref rid="B30-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. In our initial series of 54 WNV patients from 2002 to 2006 who had extensive electrodiagnostic evaluation and four additional autopsies, 12 (22%) had clinical findings of dysautonomia and autonomic instability (cardiac dysrhythmias, marked fluctuations in blood pressure, gastrointestinal complications including gastroparesis) or pathologic alterations in sympathetic ganglia or brainstem [
 <xref rid="B25-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Post-mortem disappearance of neurons in the sympathetic ganglia offers a plausible explanation for the cardiac instability observed in some human cases [
 <xref rid="B29-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Labile vital signs, hypotension, and potentially lethal cardiac arrhythmias have also been observed by other clinicians [
 <xref rid="B31-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In rodents, WNV can lead to autonomic dysfunction by infecting neurons controlling gastrointestinal and cardiac function. In infected hamsters with distension of the stomach and intestines, myenteric neurons that innervate the intestines and neurons in the brainstem were identified to be infected with WNV [
 <xref rid="B33-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The authors concluded that that infected neurons controlling autonomic function were the cause of GI dysfunction in WNV-infected hamsters. Dysautonomia was also noted on electrocardiograms and on measures of heart rate variability in WNV-infected hamsters and cardiac histopathology was identified in the sinoatrial (SA) and atrioventricular (AV) nodes [
 <xref rid="B33-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. WNV infection of hamsters has also been reported to cause electrophysiologic suppression of the diaphragm either directly by producing neuronal injury in the brainstem and cervical spinal cord or indirectly by altering vagal afferent function [
 <xref rid="B34-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], although subsequent investigations suggested that respiratory deficits primarily may be due to loss of lower motor neurons in the cervical cord [
 <xref rid="B35-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Bladder dysfunction and changes in sweating, including hyperhidrosis, anhidrosis and segmental changes in sweating, have also been observed in patients with WNV infection [
 <xref rid="B36-pathogens-08-00193" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Hence, both human and animal data suggest that WNV can cause dysautonomia, supporting the concept that the neurotropism of WNV may extend to autonomic neurons in the CNS and autonomic ganglia.
</p>
