<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">Effective antiretroviral therapy (ART) has prolonged the lifespan of PLWH. In the United States, 1.2 million people are living with HIV. Of these, more than 50% are 50 + years of age, and many physical complications related to long-term ART use and aging have arisen [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Older PLWH, in particular, have a higher risk of non-communicable comorbidities, including diabetes, hypertension, cardiovascular disease, and chronic lung disease than uninfected individuals of similar age [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Putative mechanisms for these comorbidities include aging itself and chronic inflammation caused by HIV and/or ART [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Epidemiologic evidence suggests that both older age and a number of comorbidities, including hypertension, diabetes, and chronic obstructive lung disease, are risk factors for severe COVID-19 disease [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. While limited data are available on COVID-19 and HIV-coinfection as of early April 2020 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], and on the potential protective effects of HIV antivirals [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], the interaction between these comorbidities nonetheless lends itself to an understanding through a syndemic framework [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Expression of the angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2), identified as a crucial factor that facilitates SARS-CoV-2 virus to bind and enter host cells, is substantially increased in patients with diabetes and hypertension, who are often treated with ACE inhibitors and angiotensin II type-I receptor blockers [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Further, there is a concern that individuals with severe immunodeficiencies, such as HIV, may be at risk for a severe course of COVID-19 disease.
</p>
