<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>All pandemic influenza viruses, like those of 1918, 1957, 1968, and 2009, ultimately acquired some or all of their gene segments from the avian IAV gene pool.
 <xref rid="b4" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>4</sup>
 </xref> Additionally, zoonotic infections with both low pathogenicity (LPAI) and HPAI viruses have sporadically occurred.
 <xref rid="b5" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>5</sup>
 </xref> Diverse IAV are widely distributed in their natural reservoir, numerous wild avian species – especially the aquatic 
 <italic>Anseriformes and Charadriiformes</italic> waterfowl – around the world,
 <xref rid="b6" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="b7" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>7</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="b8" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="b9" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="b10" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>10</sup>
 </xref> where they infect predominantly the lower intestinal tract
 <xref rid="b9" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="b11" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>11</sup>
 </xref> and are transmitted via the fecal‐oral route. Although not reservoir hosts of avian IAV, domesticated 
 <italic>Galliformes</italic> (e.g., chickens, turkeys, quails) are susceptible, after adaptation, to infection with wild bird‐derived IAV.
 <xref rid="b12" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>12</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="b13" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>13</sup>
 </xref> Avian IAV are antigenically and genetically diverse; all 16 identified hemagglutinin (HA) and nine neuraminidase (NA) subtypes have been identified in a great variety of combinations.
 <xref rid="b8" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>8</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="b9" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>9</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="b14" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref> The existence of a large number of different HA–NA subtype combinations, without evidence of genetic linkage among the specific segments, indicates that mixed IAV infection and reassortment in wild birds is extremely common
 <xref rid="b15" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="b16" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>16</sup>
 </xref>, and it further suggests that in wild birds IAV exist as transient genome constellations.
 <xref rid="b15" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>15</sup>
 </xref> It is also likely that IAV can be maintained in the environment, e.g., in pond water and mud;
 <xref rid="b17" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>17</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="b18" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>18</sup>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="b19" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>19</sup>
 </xref> the significance of this in relation to the complex ecobiology of IAV is still poorly understood
 <xref rid="b14" ref-type="ref">
  <sup>14</sup>
 </xref> but remains an important subject for further research.
</p>
