<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although agreement has been found between in vivo and in vitro studies, discrepancies have also arisen. Sabin type 1 OPV is attenuated in vitro upon exposure to high temperatures (&gt;37 °C), unlike its parental strain, Mahoney. However, genetic determinants of temperature sensitivity do not contribute to viral attenuation in transgenic mouse models [
 <xref rid="B152-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">152</xref>,
 <xref rid="B153-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">153</xref>]. Additionally, while most NYCBH-derived LAV strains examined by Lee et al. replicated to wild-type levels in vitro, their replication in mouse epithelium differed greatly from wild-type vaccinia virus, and their immunogenic effect was dose-dependent [
 <xref rid="B154-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">154</xref>]. Other categories of discrepancies have also been reported. For instance, the route of administration seems to affect virus protein roles during vaccinia virus infection [
 <xref rid="B155-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">155</xref>], or BCG-induced immune responses in NHPs [
 <xref rid="B156-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">156</xref>]. Moreover, multiple studies have found greater IFN production in MV-LAV strains [
 <xref rid="B157-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">157</xref>,
 <xref rid="B158-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">158</xref>,
 <xref rid="B159-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">159</xref>,
 <xref rid="B160-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">160</xref>,
 <xref rid="B161-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">161</xref>], but the potential presence of 5’ copy-back defective interfering (DI) RNAs in laboratory virus stocks, which increase interferon (IFN) and interferon-stimulated gene (ISG) levels (among multiple other effects), may have confounded previous results [
 <xref rid="B162-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">162</xref>]. Disparities between in vivo models have also been observed. Mice defective for type I interferon signaling have been suggested to be a relevant system to investigate YFV-17D-induced protective immunity [
 <xref rid="B147-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">147</xref>]. However, an important number of genes upstream and downstream of the type I interferon signaling pathways are upregulated upon YFV-17D vaccination in humans [
 <xref rid="B163-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">163</xref>]. Furthermore, although the authors reported that mouse CD8+ T cells do not contribute to protection in mice defective for type I interferon signaling, multiple studies have described the critical mobilization of human CD8+ T cells toward the robust effector and memory phenotypes during YFV-17D vaccination in human vaccinees [
 <xref rid="B164-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">164</xref>,
 <xref rid="B165-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">165</xref>,
 <xref rid="B166-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">166</xref>,
 <xref rid="B167-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>]. Finally, discrepancies have also been observed in the cytokine response of human and rhesus macaques MoDCs upon YFV-17D infection [
 <xref rid="B140-vaccines-08-00036" ref-type="bibr">140</xref>]. 
</p>
