<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While genes encoding components of the type III secretion systems (T3SS) 1 and 2 apparatus were never HDCS, several genes encoding effector proteins secreted by them were (
 <italic>sseI</italic>, 
 <italic>sseK2</italic>, 
 <italic>sseK3</italic>, 
 <italic>avrA</italic>, 
 <italic>sseL</italic>, 
 <italic>sseJ</italic> and 
 <italic>gtgE</italic>). The 
 <italic>sseI</italic> gene is inactivated in ST313 due to insertion of a transposable element, and results in hyper dissemination of these strains to systemic sites of the host via CD11b
 <sup>+</sup> migratory dendritic cells [
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. The 
 <italic>sseK2</italic>, 
 <italic>sseK3</italic>, 
 <italic>avrA</italic> and 
 <italic>sseL</italic> genes each encode effectors that inhibit the NFκB signalling pathway thereby modulating the proinflammatory response during infection [
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>–
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Furthermore, these effectors are commonly absent or degraded in serotypes of 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> serotypes associated with disseminated disease [
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], suggesting that altered interaction with the macrophage is essential for disseminated disease in diverse 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> variants and hosts. In addition, several genes encoding components of fimbrial or afimbrial adhesin systems (
 <italic>sadA</italic>, 
 <italic>ratB</italic>, 
 <italic>lpfD</italic>, 
 <italic>stfD</italic>, 
 <italic>stbD</italic>, 
 <italic>safC</italic>, 
 <italic>fimH</italic>, 
 <italic>siiC</italic> and 
 <italic>siiE</italic>), or anaerobic respiration (
 <italic>ttrB</italic>), and chemotaxis (
 <italic>tsr</italic>) were HDCS in one or more isolates. Many of these genes have been implicated in intestinal colonisation [
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>–
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>], suggesting that their inactivation in host adapted variants may be associated with a loss of selection for functions no longer required in a reduced host range or where intestinal colonisation is no longer critical to transmission. The 
 <italic>sadA</italic> and 
 <italic>katE</italic>, genes are involved in multicellular behaviour, biofilm formation and catalase activity that protects against oxidative stress during high density growth functions, respectively, and are commonly affected by genome degradation in host adapted pathovars of 
 <italic>Salmonella</italic> [
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pgen.1008850.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>].
</p>
