<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We would like to note that our ‘
 <italic>three-in-one</italic>’ assay and the results described in our paper may have certain limitations. As specified in the WHO 
 <italic>Manual for the Laboratory-based Surveillance of Measles, Rubella, and Congenital Rubella Syndrome</italic>, EIA/ELISA testing may be used for the detection of the presence (or absence) of anti-viral IgG antibodies of individuals, as well as to perform population-level immunity estimations. In case of population-based seroprevalence studies, ELISA/EIA results can help characterise the immune profile of target populations; however, there are important limitations. When applying commercial assays, we used cut-offs and calculation methods as per kit manual, without changing or reinterpreting default thresholds. Each commercially available kit (listed in Materials and methods section) specified one particular method for quantitative (and qualitative) result calculation, with no distinction between periods with or without epidemics, or samples collected with the purpose of clinical diagnosis or population-level survey. However, according to the literature, thresholds for commercial IgG ELISAs/EIAs were determined with the purpose of individual patient management, rather than with population-level antibody prevalence calculations [
 <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. A positive result of virus-specific IgG clearly demonstrates an immune response, in contrast, given that commercial immunoassays are capable only of humoral antibody detection, a negative or equivocal result cannot be considered as an absolute proof for lack of immunity [
 <xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. The functional characteristics and the ‘quantity’ of antibodies may be highly correlated with protection or synergistic with other functions (e.g. with cellular immunity). The correlates of vaccine-induced immunity are often a matter of debates; for some vaccines, we have no true correlates, but only useful surrogates [
 <xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. As far as Plotkin's definitions are considered normative [
 <xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], entire antigen repertoire-based ELISA/EIA methods of measles, mumps and rubella IgG antibody detection are considered rather than a good surrogate marker for immunity. This is especially true for our test, since our cut-off calibration was based on multiple measurements with independent, commercially available assays, and with indirect immunofluorescent microscopy. The diagnostic ability of our test is calculated based on the results obtained by kits capable of humoral antibody detection, and not on neutralising antibody titres that could serve as an absolute correlate of protection.
</p>
