<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We first reconstructed time-calibrated phylogenetic trees from the Odessa dataset and estimated the time to the most recent common ancestors (TMRCA) of all identified transmission clusters using BEASTv1.10.4 [
 <xref rid="B31-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. First, we used path-sampling [
 <xref rid="B32-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] and stepping stone [
 <xref rid="B33-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] marginal likelihood estimators (MLE) to select the most appropriate coalescent model. The non-parametric Bayesian skyline plot (BSP) model [
 <xref rid="B34-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] was selected over the constant population size and exponential growth models (see 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-viruses-12-00469">Table S2</xref>) and was therefore used in further analyses. For the subsequent BSP analyses, we used an HKY nucleotide substitution model with gamma-distributed rate variation among sites (HKY+G). Given the poor molecular clock signal in our dataset (as assessed using TempEst [
 <xref rid="B35-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]), we relied on previously published estimates of the evolutionary rate to calibrate the molecular clock. Specifically, we used a lognormal relaxed molecular clock model with a continuous-time Markov chain (CTMC) prior on the mean (constrained to values between 1 × 10
 <sup>−3</sup> – 3 × 10
 <sup>−3</sup>) and a normal prior on the standard deviation (mean = 5 × 10
 <sup>−4</sup>, standard deviation = 5 × 10
 <sup>−4</sup>), as previously reported in [
 <xref rid="B36-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. We also used a normal distribution prior for the TMRCA of the tree (mean = 35, standard deviation = 5). We used the same nucleotide substitution and molecular clock models for all subsequent phylodynamic analyses. Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) sampling was performed for 300 × 10
 <sup>6</sup> iterations (with 20% removed as burn-in). We used Tracer [
 <xref rid="B38-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] to visually inspect the convergence of the MCMC runs for all BEAST analyses and to ensure a minimum effective samples size of 200, as is standard practice [
 <xref rid="B4-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-viruses-12-00469" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].
</p>
