<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">The use of nanomaterials as carriers for controlled drug release has increasingly been explored due to their small size, high surface area and ability to pass through epithelial and endothelial barriers increasing drugs permeability without change its pharmacological properties (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>). These nanosystems can reach the action site with considerable drugs concentration increasing their specific retention time reducing side effects (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>). Nanoparticles can be produced from various materials such as amphiphilic structures, lipids, biodegradable polymers and inorganic compounds (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>). Specifically, inorganic platforms as mesoporous silica nanoparticles (MSNs) comprise a potential nanosystem for healthcare applications due to interesting characteristics such as easy functionalization, large surface area, high chemical and physical stabilities and hydroxyl groups available in their surface/pores. In addition, MSNs tunable morphology, size, surface charges and pores make them carriers with good biocompatibility and biodegradability, low toxicity, good biodistribution and elimination (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>). Drugs loaded into MSNs pores leading to pharmacological properties maintenance besides protection against degradation and immediate drug release (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>).
</p>
