<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A549 cells infected with the viruses at MOI of 5 in 6-well plate were cultured for 16 h at 37 
 <sup>o</sup>C. Cells were lysed with 300 ul of IP lysis buffer (Pierce) and reacted with 20 ul of Dynabeads (Invitrogen) reacted with 2 ul of anti-NS1 Ab (NR44426, BEI resources). Bound protein were eluted with SDS-PAGE sample buffer and analyzed by Western blotting. Immunoprecipitated proteins or cell lysates were applied to a 12% SDS-PAGE gel and transferred onto a polyvinylidene difluoride (PVDF) membrane (Millipore). The blot was blocked with 2% dry milk in Tris-buffered saline with Tween 20 (TBST) and then incubated with primary antibodies as follows: rabbit anti-TRIM25 monoclonal antibody (mAb) (1:1,000, abcam), rabbit anti-NS1 polyclonal antibody (1:500, Invitrogen), and mouse anti-β-actin mAb (1:5,000; Cell Signaling). After washing, cells were incubated with horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated goat anti-mouse IgG (1:10,000; Santa Cruz) or anti-rabbit IgG (1:5,000; Thermo Fisher). Target proteins were visualized using SuperSignal West Femto maximum sensitivity substrate (Thermo Scientific). Images were captured using the ChemDoc XRS system (Bio-Rad) and analyzed using Quantity One 1-D analysis software (Bio-Rad). For the analysis of IRF3 activation, A549 cells in 6-well plate were infected with the viruses at MOI of 5 and cultured for 6 h at 37 
 <sup>o</sup>C. Cells were lysed with the IP lysis buffer and analyzed for IRF3 activation using mouse anti-IRF3 (1:500; eBioscience), rabbit anti-IRF3 (phospho S386)(1:500; abcam), mouse anti-SeV NP cocktail (1:1,000; [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007465.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]), and mouse anti-M1 mAb (1:1,000; Abcam). For the analysis of viral protein level, mock- and virus-infected cells in 12-well plate were lysed with 100 ul of cell lysis buffer (20 mM HEPES [pH 7.5], 1.5 mM MgCl2, 500 mM NaCl, 0.2 mM EDTA, 1% Triton X-100, and 20% glycerol). Fifteen ul of the cleared lysates were analyzed by Western blotting using a cocktail of mouse anti-influenza A HA mAb NR42019, NR42020, NR28666, NR28667, and NR28668 (1:1,000; BEI Resources), and mouse anti-influenza A NS1 [10C7] mAb (1:1,000; Kerafast).
</p>
