<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Specific viral genetic differences have not been implicated in the explanation of the disparate phenotypes displayed by WNV and SLEV in birds. Data presented here clearly demonstrate that the non-structural (NS) genetic elements of WNV confer an elevated avian host competence phenotype in three different Passeriform hosts, HOFIs, HOSPs and AMCRs. In species like the California HOFI, incorporation of WNV NS elements resulted in a significantly higher mortality rate as well. In the AMCR model, SLEV NS elements ablated virus replication completely clearly showing that competence of AMCRs for SLEV replication is dependent on SLEV NS elements. This extends previous 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> findings where viral growth kinetics in DEF cells and cytopathogenicity profiles in Vero cells were found to be enhanced by WNV NS viral genetic elements [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006302.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Studies investigating the specific genetic determinants of differential avian virulence between different WNV strains previously have been assessed. Notably, altering the amino acid identity at the 249 position in the helicase domain of the NS3 protein from a threonine to a proline (NS3-T249P) conferred elevated viremias and subsequent virulence modulation in AMCRs and HOSPs [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006302.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006302.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006302.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Polymorphisms at this loci also were associated with modulated 
 <italic>ex vivo</italic> AMCR PBMC growth competence that were associated with 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> AMCR virulence phenotypes [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006302.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Modification of this locus with the SLEV backbone failed to generate viable virus (Dietrich EA, personal communication). However, the results from 
 <italic>ex vivo</italic> WNV studies indicated that peripheral leukocytes were likely a key cell population for high viremia production, and differential intracellular growth potential modulated by the NS proteins of WNV and SLEV could be a factor limiting peripheral viremias elicited in SLEV infected avian hosts. NS1’, a translational extension of the native NS1 due to ribosomal frame-shifting, has been implicated as a determinant of elevated viremia production in HOSPs in addition to a requisite for murine neuroinvasiveness [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006302.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0006302.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Production of the NS1’ has been implicated with the maintenance of a specific stoichiometric relationship between structural and nonstructural elements leading to an overexpression of structural proteins [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006302.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Mutant WNV viruses that were defective in producing the NS1’ protein have been shown to exhibit decreased viral titers in HOSPs in comparison with wild-type WNV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006302.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. As the NS1’ protein has not been predicted to be formed by SLEV due to the lack of a heptanucleotide slippery sequence motif that is a requisite for ribosomal frame-shifting [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006302.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]; the absence of this protein or the lack of stoichiometric imbalance that would be predicted to result from SLEV replication could have contributed to the overall lower levels of SLEV replication observed both 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic>.
</p>
