<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An alternative treatment for COVID-19 is the utilization of convalescent plasma (CP) (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Chen L. et al., 2020</xref>). This treatment refers to plasma therapy based on plasma or plasma derivatives, obtained from donors who were previously infected and have developed antibodies. This plasma/derivative is, in its turn, transfused into individuals with acute SARS-CoV-2 infection (
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Garraud, 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Cao and Shi, 2020</xref>). Even though the mechanism of action of convalescent plasma therapy is not fully understood, it presented great results in the treatment of patients with SARS during the SARS-CoV outbreak in Hong Kong in the early 2000s (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al., 2005</xref>). It is possible that the efficacy of CP therapy is due to the fact that the antibodies from convalescent plasma might suppress viremia (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Chen L. et al., 2020</xref>). Duan and colleagues reported CP transfusion to rescue ten severe cases of SARS-CoV-2 adult patients. The study showed that one dose (200 mL) of CP significantly increased or maintained the neutralizing antibodies at a high level, leading to the disappearance of viremia in 7 days. Clinical symptoms rapidly improved within 3 days, and radiological examination showed varying degrees of absorption of lung lesions within 7 days. According to these results, CP can also provide a promising rescue option for severe COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Duan et al., 2020</xref>). However, the author suggested key points to guarantee the effectiveness of CP therapy: Ab titers and the treatment time point. Firstly, taking into consideration previous knowledge from MERS-CoV CP therapy, Abs in plasma donor must have a titer equal or higher of 1:80 (
 <xref rid="B120" ref-type="bibr">Ko et al., 2018</xref>). This titer is only found in recently recovered patients, since antibody levels decrease 4 months after the disease. Secondly, patients receiving CP treatment prior to 14 days post-infection responded better than patients treated after 14 days (
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">Duan et al., 2020</xref>).
</p>
