<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another two candidates are Lopinavir and Ritonavir, which are protease inhibitors used in association to treat HIV infections (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">Cvetkovic and Goa, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B149" ref-type="bibr">Mills et al., 2009</xref>). Lopinavir demonstrated antiviral activities, protecting cells from MERS-CoV infection (EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 8 μM) and reducing viral loads in animal assays (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">de Wilde et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B117" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2015</xref>). Ritonavir also demonstrated anti-MERS-CoV activities with an EC
 <sub>50</sub> of 24.9 μM (
 <xref rid="B198" ref-type="bibr">Sheahan et al., 2020a</xref>). It is important to point out that these results do not agree with another work that was unable to demonstrate 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> antiviral activity of Lopinavir against MERS-CoV (
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Chan et al., 2013</xref>). In clinical assays for MERS-CoV, the association of Lopinavir with Ritonavir reduced adverse clinical outcomes and viral load in infected patients (
 <xref rid="B198" ref-type="bibr">Sheahan et al., 2020a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B250" ref-type="bibr">Yao et al., 2020a</xref>). In particular, for SARS-CoV, Lopinavir and Ritonavir presented a low to medium antiviral activity 
 <italic>in vitro</italic>, and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> assays have not been performed yet (
 <xref rid="B250" ref-type="bibr">Yao et al., 2020a</xref>). In addition, Lopinavir and Ritonavir played an important role in the clinical outcome of SARS-CoV-infected patients by reducing symptoms and the period of hospitalization, representing a possibility for the treatment of SARS-CoV-2 (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">Chu et al., 2004</xref>). Cao and collaborators conducted a randomized clinical trial with 199 patients with severe COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Cao et al., 2020b</xref>). Treatment of the patients with the association Lopinavir/Ritonavir did not improve symptoms, nor impaired detectable viral RNA when compared to standard care (supplemental oxygen, noninvasive and invasive ventilation, antibiotic agents, vasopressor support, renal-replacement therapy, and extracorporeal membrane oxygenation). Additionally, the treatment generated relevant adverse effects in some of the patients (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Cao et al., 2020b</xref>). The authors proposed that the low efficacy of Lopinavir with Ritonavir might be associated with the time of administration, since individuals that were treated at the onset of the disease had improved clinical results (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Cao et al., 2020b</xref>). Later, it was shown that the association of lopinavir and ritonavir with interferon-β1 and ribavirin to treat mild to moderate COVID-19 patients alleviated symptoms and decreased the durations of viral infection and hospital stay (
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">Hung et al., 2020</xref>). This might be related to their inducing cellular immune response, impairing virus replication.
</p>
