<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The type 1 interferons (IFN-I) have also been employed in clinical trials. These proteins belong to the cytokine family and are associated with the immune response in viral infections, thus playing major roles in antiviral immunity due to their immunomodulatory properties (
 <xref rid="B189" ref-type="bibr">Samuel, 2001</xref>). Therefore, they are commonly employed in the treatment of several diseases such as Hepatitis C (
 <xref rid="B121" ref-type="bibr">Kobayashi et al., 1993</xref>). There are two subtypes of IFN-I, alpha (IFN-α) and beta (IFN-β) (
 <xref rid="B189" ref-type="bibr">Samuel, 2001</xref>). IFN-β is associated with more potent activity (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Chan et al., 2015</xref>) and is therefore capitalized on in the treatment for multiple sclerosis patients (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Axtell et al., 2010</xref>). Due to its more potent inhibition profile, it was associated with potent antiviral effects against SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV, MHV, and HCoV-229E 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> (
 <xref rid="B206" ref-type="bibr">Sperber and Hayden, 1989</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B226" ref-type="bibr">Vassão et al., 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">Hensley et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">Falzarano et al., 2013a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Chan et al., 2015</xref>). IFN-β, in particular, has a protective effect in endothelial cells, up-regulating CD73 and consequently stimulating the anti-inflammatory molecules and maintenance of endothelial barrier (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Bellingan et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B188" ref-type="bibr">Sallard et al., 2020</xref>). However, a clinical trial with 301 patients showed that this effect was not sufficient to decrease mortality in SARS patients (
 <xref rid="B178" ref-type="bibr">Ranieri et al., 2020</xref>). Therefore, in SARS-CoV-2, IFN-β has been associated with other drugs in clinical trials, improving outcomes in COVID-19 patients as in lopinavir or ribavirin (
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">Hung et al., 2020</xref>).
</p>
