<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="f5">
 <label>Figure 5</label>
 <caption>
  <title>
   <italic>In vitro</italic> validation of selected chemical inhibitors and proviral factors.
  </title>
  <p>(
   <bold>a</bold>–
   <bold>g</bold>) Infection rate and cell viability for compounds specific to vATPase (bafilomycin, 
   <italic>n</italic>=12, 6, 12 and 6 for all conditions at increasing concentrations), calmodulin (pimozide, 
   <italic>n</italic>=12, 12, 12 and 9 for all conditions at increasing concentrations and W7, 
   <italic>n</italic>=9 for all data sets), fatty acid synthesis (cerulenin, 
   <italic>n</italic>=9, 6, 6 and 9 for all conditions at increasing concentrations), FLT4 (tivozanib, 
   <italic>n</italic>=12, 6, 9 and 12 for all conditions at increasing concentrations) and KAT5 (anacardic acid, 
   <italic>n</italic>=9 for all data sets) administrated to CHIKV-infected HEK-293T cells as indicated. Cells were treated 2 h before (solid lines) or 2 h after (dashed lines) infection with CHIKV C21 (MOI 40) and left until 8 h p.i. to avoid multiple cycles of infection. Viral infectivity and cell viability were then measured by flow cytometry after intracellular staining of CHIKV capsid (CHIKV-C, see 
   <bold>a</bold> for an example). Equal amounts of supernatants from the 2 h post treatment conditions were measured for viral infectivity on Vero cells (dotted lines) to detect eventual defects in viral release. (
   <bold>h</bold>,
   <bold>i</bold>) Quantitative PCR with reverse transcription quantification of cell- (
   <italic>n</italic>=20, 9, 9, 12, 12 and 9 in displayed order) (
   <bold>h</bold>) and supernatant-associated (
   <italic>n</italic>=18, 6, 6, 12, 12 and 9 in displayed order) (
   <bold>i</bold>) vRNA performed on RNA extracts of HeLa cells infected with CHIKV C21 (MOI: 50) for 1 h and treated with cerulenin (50 μM), TOFA (25 μM), pimozide (pimo, 10 μM), W7 (20 μM), tivozanib (tivo, 5 μM) or vehicle alone for an additional 7 h. (
   <bold>j</bold>) Cell viability measured at the end of the experiment shown in 
   <bold>h</bold>, using the CellTiter-Glo kit (
   <italic>n</italic>=9 for all data sets). (
   <bold>k</bold>,
   <bold>l</bold>) Cell- and supernatant-associated vRNA measured on CHIKV-infected HeLa cells treated with the indicated drugs from 6 to 8 h p.i. (
   <italic>n</italic>=18, 9, 8, 9, 9 and 9 for 
   <italic>m</italic> and 
   <italic>n</italic>=18, 9, 9, 9, 9 and 9 for 
   <italic>n</italic> in displayed order). Data represent mean+s.e.m. of at least three independent experiments, analysed by one-way analysis of variance with Tukey's post test (***
   <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001; 
   <sup>NS</sup>
   <italic>P</italic>≥0.05).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ncomms11320-f5" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
