<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Rev Lat Am Enfermagem</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Rev Lat Am Enfermagem</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">rlae</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Revista Latino-Americana de Enfermagem</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0104-1169</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1518-8345</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Escola de Enfermagem de Ribeir&#x000e3;o Preto / Universidade de S&#x000e3;o
Paulo</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7417131</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">00376</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1518-8345.4584.3354</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>COVID-19 pandemic and the judicialization of health care: an
explanatory case study<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn_ast1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
</article-title><trans-title-group xml:lang="es"><trans-title>Pandemia de la Covid-19 y la judicializaci&#x000f3;n de la salud: estudio
de caso explicativo </trans-title></trans-title-group><trans-title-group xml:lang="pt"><trans-title>Pandemia da COVID-19 e a judicializa&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o da sa&#x000fa;de: estudo de caso
explicativo </trans-title></trans-title-group></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1099-370X</contrib-id><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>Elo&#x000e1; Carneiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5591-1838</contrib-id><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>Pedro Hugo Dantas de Oliveira</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9389-1161</contrib-id><name><surname>Varella</surname><given-names>Thereza Christina M&#x000f3; y M&#x000f3; Loureiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2936-3468</contrib-id><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>Norma Val&#x000e9;ria Dantas de Oliveira</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5752-265X</contrib-id><name><surname>de Farias</surname><given-names>Sheila Nascimento Pereira</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9133-7044</contrib-id><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>Samira Silva Santos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>Universidade do Estado do Rio de Janeiro, Faculdade de Enfermagem,
Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil.</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>Petr&#x000f3;leo Brasileiro S/A, Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, RJ,
Brazil.</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro, Escola de Enfermagem Anna
Nery, Rio de Janeiro, RJ, Brazil.</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c01"> Corresponding author:Elo&#x000e1; Carneiro CarvalhoE-mail:
<email>eloacarvalhogrossi@gmail.com</email>
https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1099-370X </corresp><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Associate Editor: Andrea Bernardes</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>10</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>28</volume><elocation-id>e3354</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2020 Revista Latino-Americana de
Enfermagem</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Revista Latino-Americana de Enfermagem</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is
properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Objective</title><p> to identify the reasons that led to the judicialization of health care in
the context of the COVID-19 pandemic; describe the outcomes of lawsuits
concerning health care involving the COVID-19; and analyze the cases of
health care judicialization intended to ensure the population&#x02019;s right to
health.</p></sec><sec><title>Method</title><p> qualitative, explanatory case study. Data were collected from the websites
of the Federal Prosecution Service, Regional Labor Court (1<sup>st</sup>
Region), and the Court of Justice of Rio de Janeiro. The inclusion criterion
was public civil actions that concerned health care and situations involving
the COVID-19 pandemic. Two categories emerged from data analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p> four cases were identified.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p> the judicialization of health care consists of obtaining assets and rights
in the courts. These assets and rights are essential to ensure the health of
citizens but have been denied in various instances, often due to the
omission of the executive and legislative powers. Analyzing the
judicialization of health care amidst the pandemic brings focus and
highlights the importance of giving voice and visibility to the enormous
contingent of the Brazilian society unassisted by public authorities.</p></sec></abstract><trans-abstract xml:lang="es"><sec><title>Objetivo</title><p> determinar las razones que han llevado a la judicializaci&#x000f3;n de la salud en
relaci&#x000f3;n con la pandemia de la Covid-19, describir el resultado de las
acciones judiciales en materia de atenci&#x000f3;n sanitaria que abarcan la Covid-19
y analizar los casos de judicializaci&#x000f3;n de la salud relacionados con la
pandemia de Covid-19 con vistas a garantizar el derecho a la salud de la
poblaci&#x000f3;n.</p></sec><sec><title>M&#x000e9;todo</title><p> cualitativo, del tipo estudio de caso explicativo. Los datos fueron
recogidos en los sitios web de la Fiscal&#x000ed;a P&#x000fa;blica, del Tribunal Regional
del Trabajo (1&#x000aa; Regi&#x000f3;n) y del Tribunal de Justicia del Estado de R&#x000ed;o de
Janeiro. Para cumplir con los criterios establecidos, se seleccionaron las
acciones civiles p&#x000fa;blicas relacionadas con la salud y la pandemia de
Covid-19 con decisiones. El an&#x000e1;lisis de los datos culmin&#x000f3; en la elaboraci&#x000f3;n
de dos categor&#x000ed;as.</p></sec><sec><title>Resultados</title><p> fueron captados cuatro casos.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusi&#x000f3;n</title><p> la judicializaci&#x000f3;n de la salud consiste en obtener bienes y derechos en los
tribunales, que son importantes para la garant&#x000ed;a de la salud del ciudadano
que, en diversas situaciones, ha sido negada, generalmente por la omisi&#x000f3;n de
los poderes ejecutivo y legislativo. Con la pandemia, analizar la
judicializaci&#x000f3;n podr&#x000ed;a poner de relieve y plantear al debate la importancia
de dar voz y visibilidad al enorme contingente de la sociedad brasile&#x000f1;a que
no es asistido por el poder p&#x000fa;blico.</p></sec></trans-abstract><trans-abstract xml:lang="pt"><sec><title>Objetivo</title><p> identificar as raz&#x000f5;es que conduziram &#x000e0; judicializa&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o da sa&#x000fa;de relativas &#x000e0;
pandemia da COVID-19, descrever o desfecho das a&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es judiciais relacionadas
&#x000e0; assist&#x000ea;ncia em sa&#x000fa;de abrangendo a COVID-19 e analisar os casos de
judicializa&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o da sa&#x000fa;de relacionados &#x000e0; pandemia da COVID-19 com vistas &#x000e0;
garantia do direito &#x000e0; sa&#x000fa;de da popula&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o.</p></sec><sec><title>M&#x000e9;todo</title><p> trata-se de um estudo qualitativo, do tipo estudo de caso explicativo. A
coleta foi efetuada nos <italic>sites</italic> do Minist&#x000e9;rio P&#x000fa;blico
Federal, do Tribunal Regional do Trabalho (1&#x000aa; Regi&#x000e3;o) e do Tribunal de
Justi&#x000e7;a do Estado do Rio de Janeiro. Para atender aos crit&#x000e9;rios
estabelecidos, selecionaram-se as a&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es civis p&#x000fa;blicas relacionadas &#x000e0; sa&#x000fa;de
e &#x000e0;s situa&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es da pandemia da COVID-19 com decis&#x000f5;es. A an&#x000e1;lise dos dados
culminou na elabora&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de duas categorias.</p></sec><sec><title>Resultados</title><p> captaram-se quatro casos.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclus&#x000e3;o</title><p> a judicializa&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o na sa&#x000fa;de consiste em obter bens e direitos nos tribunais,
os quais s&#x000e3;o importantes para a garantia da sa&#x000fa;de do cidad&#x000e3;o que, em
diversas situa&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es, vem sendo negada, geralmente pela omiss&#x000e3;o dos poderes
Executivo e Legislativo. Com a pandemia, analisar a judicializa&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o poder&#x000e1;
colocar foco e trazer &#x000e0; discuss&#x000e3;o a import&#x000e2;ncia de dar voz e visibilidade ao
enorme contingente da sociedade brasileira que n&#x000e3;o &#x000e9; assistido pelo Poder
P&#x000fa;blico.</p></sec></trans-abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Health&#x02019;s Judicialization</kwd><kwd>Right to Health</kwd><kwd>Coronavirus</kwd><kwd>Unified Health System</kwd><kwd>Public Policy</kwd><kwd>Nursing</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group xml:lang="es"><kwd>Judicializaci&#x000f3;n de la Salud</kwd><kwd>Derecho a la Salud</kwd><kwd>Coronavirus</kwd><kwd>Sistema &#x000da;nico de Salud</kwd><kwd>Pol&#x000ed;tica P&#x000fa;blica</kwd><kwd>Enfermer&#x000ed;a</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group xml:lang="pt"><kwd>Judicializa&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o da Sa&#x000fa;de</kwd><kwd>Direito &#x000e0; Sa&#x000fa;de</kwd><kwd>Coronav&#x000ed;rus</kwd><kwd>Sistema &#x000da;nico de Sa&#x000fa;de</kwd><kwd>Pol&#x000ed;tica P&#x000fa;blica</kwd><kwd>Enfermagem</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="29"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Health is generally conceived as the greatest asset of human beings. Such
understanding is based on the fact that, in the absence of health, one cannot remain
active and functioning in society.</p><p>The concept of health involves objective and subjective aspects. In this sense, it is
characterized as a balance between human beings and the environment, enabling people
to play their social, familial and occupational roles, a situation in which
physical, biological and psychosocial aggressors are either contained or
eliminated<sup>(<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>From the perspective of its objectivity, health is the expression of quality of life,
resulting from one&#x02019;s eating habits, housing, education, income, environment, work,
transportation, employment, leisure, freedom, access to and possession of land, and
access to health services. Thus, the results of the social organization of
production may generate inequalities in terms of living standards, leading to
illness, sequelae, and even death<sup>(<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>The health of individuals is an essential condition for society to keep growing,
developing, and progressing. In this sense, healthy life requires more than people
complying with their responsibilities at an individual level; it also requires
protection from the part of public authorities.</p><p>In Brazil, the Federal Constitution (FC) from 1988 incorporated the recommendations
of the Brazilian health movement that resulted from extensive discussions with the
organized civil society. The Section dealing with health contains the entrenched
clause, Article 196 in which &#x0201c;health is the right of all and a duty of the
State&#x0201d;<sup>(<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>)</sup>, and establishes
how the health system is organized and financed.</p><p>Based on constitutional principles, the Brazilian Unified Health System (SUS) is
responsible for promoting health, preventing and curing diseases, and promoting the
rehabilitation of people, while the private sector can provide complementary health
services. The private sector, however, assumed new contours and arrangements that
resulted on it providing Supplementary health services<sup>(<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>The SUS, regulated by Laws No. 8080/1990 and No. 8.142/1990, is one of the largest
and most complex public health systems in the world, the ideological principles of
which are universality, integrality, and equity for the entire population. It
involves the three levels of the Federation: Union, States and Cities. The network
composing the SUS encompasses primary, secondary, tertiary and quaternary care;
urgent and emergency services, hospital care, and epidemiological, health and
environmental surveillance actions, in addition to pharmaceutical care<sup>(<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Supplementary healthcare is regulated by Law No. 9.656 from 1998, which determined
the creation of the <italic>Ag&#x000ea;ncia Nacional de Sa&#x000fa;de Suplementar</italic> (ANS)
[National Supplementary Health Agency]. Supplementary healthcare is an alternative
for people to obtain health services, involving the operation of private care plans
and insurances<sup>(<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>This sector is regulated by the government through its regulating agency &#x02013; ANS and
operators comprise specialized health insurers, group medicines, cooperatives,
philanthropic and self-managed institutions, which in turn, demand financial
payment, that is, affiliates have to pay for the services<sup>(<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Note that, due to different reasons, both the public and private health systems
present problems in the delivery of healthcare, problems that compromise the quality
of care delivery and lead users to become dissatisfied.</p><p>At the public level, problems involve the precariousness and dismantling of physical
structures; lack of material and human resources; and a decreased number of health
units, hindering the access of the population to diagnostic and therapeutic methods.
These problems originate from liberal ideas implemented in work organizations, the
most devastating principle of which is the insufficient dimensioning of the public
structure, transferring fewer and fewer funds that would enable its functioning,
restricting or making public tenders unfeasible<sup>(<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>)</sup>. Such a context tends to worsen with the Constitutional
Amendment Proposal No. 55 from 2016, which prevents investments in health and
education for 20 years<sup>(<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>At the same time, social inequality, economic recession, new forms in which work is
organized and explored in the Brazilian society have increasingly put pressure on
SUS. There are two ends that do not meet: on the one hand, there is a system that
lacks financing and is vilified by inconsequential governments, and on the other
hand, there are growing misery and illnesses<sup>(<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Therefore, negative unfolding impacts the quality of care delivery, causing suffering
to people and worsening their health conditions, leading to dissatisfaction and
causing psychophysical illnesses among workers, as well as absenteeism and
presenteeism<sup>(<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Supplementary healthcare services also present problems, involving increasingly
higher financial payments, with often abusive adjustments of prices, without,
however, providing services that correspond to the increase in monthly fees.
Additionally, there are frauds, an excessive number of exams, and unnecessary
procedures. At the same time, health workers, especially non-physicians, are
dissatisfied with salaries that do not keep up with inflation, undersized staff,
pressure, and increased demand for productivity and the need to meet increasingly
higher goals<sup>(<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Such a context compromises the quality of services and results in ill workers, who
experience psychological distress due to hierarchical relationships permeated by
moral harassment that cause fear, while not fully meeting the health needs of
patients<sup>(<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Therefore, the public and private sectors present contexts that negatively impact and
prevent the healthy progress of actions developed within SUS and the supply of
services to meet the health demands of the Brazilian population. Therefore, these
services are subject to legal actions, so that both patients and workers have their
rights fulfilled, according to what is provided by the Constitution and
complementary laws<sup>(<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>The COVID-19 pandemic has bluntly revealed social ills and health system problems.
The collapse of the latter, due to the growing number of people infected and due to
the aggressiveness nature of the SARS-CoV-2, is already a reality for some Brazilian
states, while other states are heading towards it. The demand for complex care, the
use of diverse technologies, an insufficient number of personal protective equipment
(PPE), lack of hospitalization beds, and insufficient quality and number of health
workers explain the dire situation health services face<sup>(<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>-<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>The population and workers alike will grow dissatisfied with the Brazilian health
system and its working conditions. From this perspective, the judicialization of
health care is likely to magnify during the epidemic.</p><p>Such reflections and concerns encouraged this paper, the object of which deals with
the judicialization of health care related to COVID-19 cases. The following problem
was selected: what are the reasons and outcomes of the judicialization of cases
related to COVID-19, as well as the impacts on the fulfillment of the fundamental
right to health?</p><p>This study&#x02019;s objective is threefold: i) to identify the reasons that led to the
judicialization of healthcare related to the COVID-19 pandemic; ii) to describe the
outcome of lawsuits related to care delivery concerning COVID-19; and iii) to
analyze judicialization cases related to the COVID-19 pandemic in order to ensure
the population&#x02019;s right to health.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Method</title><p>This is a qualitative, exploratory case study. Case studies are intended to explain,
explore or describe current phenomena inserted in their own context. Thus, it is
appropriate to understand how and the reasons that led to certain
decisions<sup>(<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>-<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Secondary data were collected, specifically from the sites of the Federal Prosecution
Service, Regional Labor Court &#x02013; 1<sup>st</sup> Region (Rio de Janeiro) and the Court
of Justice of the state of Rio de Janeiro, which are public and, therefore, dispense
institutional review board approval. Additionally, information was collected from
documents related to laws and legal decisions.</p><p>The option to investigate the cases that took place in the state of Rio de Janeiro
was based on the following: i) Rio de Janeiro is one of the states most severely
affected by the epidemic; ii) it was the first to adopt social isolation measures;
and iii) the phenomenon was identified by researchers in the region.</p><p>Data were collected in April 2020 using a form addressing the following information:
places where lawsuits were filed; dates on which lawsuits were filed; case numbers;
reasons justifying the lawsuits; parties involved in the court lawsuits; and
respective outcomes.</p><p>The cases were chosen based on the following criteria: being public civil actions
related to health and situations related to the COVID-19 pandemic, which contained
decisions, albeit of a precarious nature, considering it was a preliminary (not
definitive) pronouncement. Four cases met this criterion.</p><p>Data analysis was based on the following procedures: synthetic description of
selected cases, focusing on content that enabled understanding the problem;
comparison of content of legal decisions according to law and jurisprudence; and the
establishment of two analytical categories that permitted discussing the cases in
the light of the literature.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title> Case 1 &#x02013; Process No. 0084141-46.2020.8.19.0001 </title><p>On April 22<sup>nd</sup>, 2020, the Public Prosecutors Office of the state of Rio
de Janeiro (MPRJ) filed a public civil action against the City Hall of Barra
Mansa, RJ because, on April 21<sup>st</sup>, 2020 it announced on social media
the relaxation of social isolation measures, including the reopening of the
local business starting on April 27<sup>th</sup>, 2020.</p><p>In addition to this fact, one should consider the situation of this city&#x02019;s health
system, that is, the number of Intensive Care Unit (ICU) beds and mechanical
ventilators in the city and in the region&#x02019;s referral hospital was insufficient
to support a decision to relax the social isolation.</p><p>Therefore, the Judicial Power had to intervene in order to avoid the relaxation
of social isolation measures in the city and prevent the dissemination of the
virus in the region. Hence, urgent protection was requested, determining social
restriction measures to remain.</p><p>Even though the judge of the Judicial Notary Office 7 &#x02013; Volta Redonda and
adjacent areas, considered both the citizens&#x02019; right to health and economic
issues, as the suspension of economic activities for extended periods may harm
the economy, she accepted the arguments presented by the Public Prosecutors
Office to <italic>grant</italic> urgent protection in order to keep social
isolation measures in the city of Barra Mansa-RJ.</p><p>The judge understood that the stir involving the disease lies in the fact that it
causes an exponential increase in the demand for health services (it spreads
very easily and rapidly), so that the public system &#x02013; whether in its public or
private branch &#x02013; is not capable to provide appropriate care, as it would involve
not only consultations and medical diagnoses, but also ICU hospitalization for
the most severe cases with the provision of mechanical ventilators, which are
currently very scarce.</p></sec><sec><title> Case 2 &#x02013; Process No. 0100300-73.2020.5.01.0047 </title><p>The Rio de Janeiro Nurses Union filed a public civil action in the Labor Court
(1<sup>st</sup> Region &#x02013; Rio de Janeiro) on April 13<sup>th</sup>, 2020, to
obtain a court order for nurses providing care in the health services of the
city of Rio de Janeiro who belonged to risk groups, to be liberated and allowed
to work in a home office regime during the pandemic.</p><p>The lawsuit was filed because the city, through the General Coordination of Human
Resources, issued an Official Notice (CVL/SUBSC/CGRH/CTNRH No. 04/2020) on March
18<sup>th</sup>, 2020, establishing the rules to release employees from work
due to the coronavirus, but had not, up to that time, commented on the employees
hired by social organizations to provide health care in the city.</p><p>The union argued that these workers are more likely to progress to a more severe
condition due to the infection, considering they are in direct and continuous
contact with infected patients and exposed to risks. It also claimed there was a
lack of PPE, and for this reason, many health workers had been contaminated with
COVID-19, exponentially raising the risk of illness.</p><p>In this context, the Judge of the 47<sup>th</sup> Labor Court of Rio de Janeiro,
granted on April 20<sup>th</sup>, 2020, the request for urgent relief requested
by the Union to grant the interruption of provision of services on the part of
health workers without interrupting the payment of their salaries.</p><p>The judge based his decision on Articles 5<sup>th</sup> and 230<sup>th</sup> of
CF/88, which ensure that the right to life and human dignity is a duty of the
state. Unsatisfied, the state of Rio de Janeiro and <italic>Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o
Sa&#x000fa;de</italic> [Health Foundation] requested the order to be suspended in
court. Among the reasons provided, it stand out that the decision did not take
into account the multiple aspects that accrue from the absence of health workers
belonging to risk groups from work that harm the health system.</p><p>In this context, they argued, based on technical precepts, that most of those
involved in the combat against the COVID-19 pandemic are health workers older
than 60 years old, with professional experience and occupying strategic
positions. They also note that the provisional emergency protection interferes
with public health policies implemented by the Executive Power, interfering in
its autonomy.</p><p>Thus, the Chief Justice of the Regional Labor Court - 1<sup>st</sup> Region
decided to suspend the decision of the judge of the first instance court.
Consequently, the nurses belonging to risk groups should return to work. The
decision was based on the impact it would cause, such as a decrease in the
number of nurses, which would impair the delivery of care.</p><p>Additionally, Decree No. 10.282/2020, regulated the essential activities for the
purposes set out in Law No. 13.979/2020, providing for measures dealing with the
public health emergency accruing from COVID-19, establishing that health care
services are essential to meet the needs of the population.</p></sec><sec><title> Case 3: Process No. 42.2020.8.19.0001 </title><p>The Public Prosecutors Office and Public Defense from the state of Rio de Janeiro
filed, on April 17<sup>th</sup>, 2020, a public civil action against the city
and state of Rio de Janeiro, aiming to obtain a preliminary order to unblock all
the beds reserved for ICUs and Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (ICU/SRAG) in
the state and city of Rio de Janeiro, as provided in the State Contingency Plan
&#x02013; except those in Field Hospitals (scheduled to open on April 30<sup>th</sup>,
2020).</p><p>The lawsuit was filed because the Public Prosecutors Office, in consultation with
the National Regulation System, verified that a portion of the ICU/SRAG beds,
which are considered necessary to provide care to patients suspected and
infected with COVID-19, was not yet effectively available.</p><p>The argument was that, even though both the state and city of Rio de Janeiro had
previously developed a contingency plan, it had not been effectively
implemented. Additionally, they warned about the factors increasing the demand,
such as the fact that the city of Rio de Janeiro has a historical deficit of 263
adult ICU beds; the possibility of insufficient ICU/SRAG beds and, as a
consequence, that the health system would collapse before the field hospitals
became available (scheduled to open on April 30<sup>th</sup>, 2020); the
exponential increase (from three cases in March to 11 at the beginning of April)
of individual demands in the defense office, aimed at obtaining emergency access
to ICU beds by citizens suspected or confirmed of having COVID-19.</p><p>In the first instance court, the judge of the 14<sup>th</sup> Public Finance
Court dismissed the preliminary request based on the argument that an
intervention on the part of the judicial branch would offend the principle of
separation of powers (the judiciary cannot interfere in political decisions of
the other powers, except in exceptional cases), also considering the principle
of possible reserve (i.e., as the budget is finite, managers, based on technical
evidence, make political decisions to allocate resources the best way possible).
Additionally, he maintained that other diseases could not be ignored.</p><p>The Public Prosecutors Office appealed the decision, and upon arriving at the
second instance, the judge of the Second Chamber decided to comply with the
request, determining that the state and city put all the ICU/SRAG beds into
operation within five days, in accordance to the State Contingency Plan, with
exception of those reserved for the Field Hospitals (with opening scheduled for
April 30<sup>th</sup>, 2020).</p><p>The judge also determined that all material and human resources necessary to
fulfill and enable immediate functioning would be organized. He argued that the
beds were not reserved for other purposes and the federated entities were not
complying with the commitment they assumed to implement the Contingency Plans
and that the principle of possible reserve did not apply in this case,
considering that the federated entities committed themselves to implement health
measures and to create the ICU/SRAG beds indicated in the Contingency Plan of
the state of Rio de Janeiro.</p></sec><sec><title> Case 4: Process No. 64.2020.8.19.0001 </title><p>This public civil action was issued by the Public Prosecution Office of Rio de
Janeiro, against the state and city of Rio de Janeiro, on April 8<sup>th</sup>,
2020, to obtain an order to prevent the dissemination of the new coronavirus in
Long-Stay Institutions for the Elderly (LSIEs).</p><p>The lawsuit was filed to ensure the fundamental rights to health and life of the
most vulnerable population, that is, elderly individuals living in these
institutions.</p><p>The Public Prosecutors Office justifies the demand because of a lack of a
contingency plan intended to prevent the dissemination of the coronavirus in
LSIEs, as well as an increase in the number of cases reported among elderly
individuals living in LSIEs and their employees, along with a lack of
medications, PPE, personal hygiene and cleaning products, as recommended by the
State Department of Health, Health Surveillance and ANVISA (Brazilian Health
Regulatory Agency).</p><p>In the first instance court, the judge of the 15<sup>th</sup> Public Finance
Court partially accepted the request and sentenced the defendants to:</p><list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>Provide a reserved place to accommodate the elderly (sheltered)
individuals suspected or contaminated by SARS-CoV-2, who do not require
hospitalization, as well as provide health workers, general services,
support, medication, PPE, personal hygiene and cleaning products, as
recommended by the resolutions and technical notes issued by the State
Department of Health, Municipal Department of Health, and Sanitary
Surveillance;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Ensure a differentiated flow for the primary care provided to sheltered
elderly individuals immediately after reporting the suspected cases to
the Health Surveillance. Public authorities have to provide immediate
care, sending a team of health and social workers to the shelter,
occasion when testing must be carried out; and</p></list-item><list-item><p>Ensure that these institutions receive PPE and essential hygiene and
cleaning items as well as providing training to those working in these
places, with continuous education and monitoring of their
procedures.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Category 1 &#x02013; Application of the human dignity principle in times of
pandemic</title><p>The principle of human dignity guides the entire Brazilian legal system. It is at
the highest level and validates all the remaining rules. By putting human beings
as the reference of the Brazilian law, the FC/88 shows that all people are
endowed with fundamental rights, especially the right to Health, which should be
appreciated in all analyzes<sup>(<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Therefore, when considering concrete cases, the principle of human dignity in the
Brazilian state should illuminate both jurists and politicians. In this sense,
it has the ability to protect individuals and their vulnerabilities, influencing
legal decisions when there is conflict regarding such a subject.</p><p>This basic principle, found in Article 1<sup>st</sup>, item III of the 1988
Constitution, is considered one of the foundations of the democratic state
governed by the rule of law, and must minimally ensure the preservation and
appreciation of human life<sup>(<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Currently, there is a pandemic marked in the Brazilian context by great political
instability, social disparities, unequal access to the health system<sup>(<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>)</sup>, and inappropriate working
conditions (low salaries, precarious PPE, and insufficient material) faced by
health workers, especially nurses<sup>(<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>)</sup>, which
result in inadequate work organization.</p><p>This problem is mainly due to the sudden increase in the number of patients in
intensive care units, which are invariably overcrowded, with an insufficient
number of care devices, overloading the health system. This situation affects
health workers who are dealing with exhausting working hours, negatively
influencing their physiological and psychological needs, in addition to the
safety at work<sup>(<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>The protection of workers has been identified as a primary and strategic measure
to face the pandemic. An efficient strategic plan was established in the United
Kingdom to ensure workers have PPE<sup>(<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>)</sup>. In Russia, on the other hand, the lack of PPE is
marked by a growing number of health workers becoming infected<sup>(<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>In Brazil, insufficient PPE is a problem to be combated due to the growing number
of deaths among health workers, especially nursing workers<sup>(<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>)</sup>. From this perspective, this scarcity results in a
more significant number of infected cases and deaths, compromising the human
dignity of patients and workers, who face precarious working conditions and a
higher risk of death. This situation is aggravated even more with the political
and economic stability Brazil is experiencing<sup>(<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>To apply the principle of human dignity means to ratify the democratic rule of
law; valuing this principle implies respecting human beings, whose lives are
their greatest asset. In this context, lawsuits have been filed to ensure
rights, especially the right to health.</p><p>Therefore, it is important to highlight the need for discussing the
judicialization of healthcare, addressing two contents: right and health, having
as framework social and economic aspects, all integral and necessary to the
establishment of Public Health Policy<sup>(<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>)</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Category 2 &#x02013; Fight the pandemic as a fundamental aspect of right to
health.</title><p>As for the pandemic that currently plagues the state of Rio de Janeiro, some
measures were taken as a pressing need to decrease contagion by the coronavirus,
such as social isolation measures.</p><p>This status was also declared by the Federal Union as well as by the World Health
Organization as National Public Health Emergency<sup>(<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>)</sup>, which reiterates the adoption of strategic
measures intended to suppress or reduce the circulation of the virus, due to the
expressive number of cases and compromised capacity of the state to respond to
the epidemic.</p><p>Hence, the Judicial Power is in favor of keeping social isolation as a way to
safeguard the fundamental right to health, considering it one of the main
measures to combat the virus.</p><p>At the same time, the fragility of the SUS in the face of the universalization of
health services, the need to equally include the entire population in the
system, with an emphasis on the performance of highly complex procedures, and
ultimately, the use of ICU beds, which are expensive equipment with high
technological density, becomes apparent. The relationship between demand and
supply is compromised, generating long waiting lines<sup>(<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Due to the worsening of the epidemiological expectation in Brazil for the coming
weeks and months, it is necessary that extraordinary measures be adopted in the
context of the pandemic. One of these measures is to break the barrier between
the private and public sectors at a hospital level, especially to make beds
available, improving the capacity to respond to the situation of calamity.</p><p>Hence, the Ministry of Health, the city and state Departments and regulatory
agencies need to urgently standardize national regulations regarding access to
beds in the exceptional case of the pandemic. Note that it is vital that a
single line for ICU beds is created for the severe cases of COVID-19 due to the
public, transitory and urgent need, in order to prevent hospitals keep beds
idle, and ensure the fundamental right to health. This proposition is based on
Article 5<sup>th</sup>, item XXV of the FC/988, and law 8080/1990, in its
Article 15, item XIII<sup>(<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Another aspect refers to the imminent risk of contagion and the growing need of
the population for health care, a situation in which nurses need to work despite
a pre-existing precarious context at all levels of health care, which has become
increasingly acute as the numbers of COVID-19 cases increase.</p><p>The Brazilian Federal Council of Nursing (Cofen) recommends that nursing workers
belonging to the risk groups avoid working at the front line to fight COVID-19.
The reason is that nursing workers are in direct contact with infected
individuals, which increases the risk of potential contagion. The situation
worsens with the Provisional Measure 927/2020, issued by the President of the
Republic, which allows the extension of working hours and the reduction of
mandatory rest for these workers<sup>(<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Note that in Brazil, according to Cofen, 98 nursing workers had died by May
7<sup>th</sup>, 2020, surpassing the number of deaths in the United States
where, according to the National Nurses United, a total of 91 nursing workers
had died. According to the International Council of Nurses (ICN), 260 workers
have lost their lives in the service of saving others worldwide<sup>(<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Therefore, in order to ensure the right to health and life for these workers,
allowing those who belong to risk groups to be absent from work is a sound
measure that should be standardized and adopted in the entire country.</p><p>In Brazil, the adoption of measures is not uniform. In Esp&#x000ed;rito Santo, for
instance, a technical note was issued that recommended that nursing workers
consider leaving work, however, when not possible, preferably be assigned to
administrative tasks rather than directly providing care to patients infected
with coronavirus<sup>(<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Therefore, adopting protective and work organization that includes preventive
measures is essential in the contemporaneous context. One should continually
assess the health profile of these workers because the goal is to save lives,
including those of health workers, and ensure human dignity.</p><p>The COVID-19 pandemic has enabled assessing various healthcare segments in
different contexts. This is a time to assess, to establish national and
international cooperation, and to understand that all lives are valuable and
one&#x02019;s life is as important as someone else&#x02019;s life<sup>(<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>In this line of reasoning, thinking about the elderly is urgent, considering that
the virus is more lethal among those of advanced age. Hence, preserving life and
thinking about those living in collective spaces is extremely important and
urgent in order to ensure the health and protection of those living in long-stay
institutions.</p><p>In Brazil, an LSIE is defined by ANVISA, in Collegiate Board Resolution 283, as
governmental or non-governmental institutions, the purpose of which is to
shelter people aged 60 or over, granting them dignity and citizenship rights, in
order to provide social and health services<sup>(<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>Therefore, ensuring safe conditions to elderly individuals and workers in these
spaces is essential. The provision of PPE to workers and inputs to protect the
residents of LSIEs is a condition necessary to promote the constitutional right
of human dignity.</p><p>We need to have focus and discipline to face the adversities accruing from
SARS-CoV-2, which in Brazil are inserted in a context of social inequality,
decreased investment in science (such as drastic cuts in research funding), in
social security and in public services in general<sup>(<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>There is an international appeal for society to invest in science, incorporating
the knowledge produced in research in the public policies of countries and in
international treaties<sup>(<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>)</sup>.</p><p>This study&#x02019;s contributions include the analysis of concrete cases involving the
judicialization of health care in the face of the COVID-19 pandemic, bringing to
light measures that need to be considered and adopted to ensure the right to
health. Additionally, this study presents some public civil actions filed thus
far, as well as situations that require attention considering the crisis of the
health sector, which demand that changes be implemented in the public and
private health systems.</p><p>This study&#x02019;s limitations include the fact that data were collected only in Rio de
Janeiro and also that at least three or more triangulation techniques were not
adopted. The reason is due to the context of the pandemic itself, which hindered
access to the context of care provided to patients with COVID-19 to collect
data.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The analysis of the cases led to the conclusion that the objective of the
judicialization of health care was to ensure that the public authorities would
comply with the fundamental rights of citizens, as well as with technical and
scientific recommendations and measures intended to protect the population during
the pandemic.</p><p>In this sense, the synthesis of the results is linked to the need to protect the
fundamental rights established in entrenched clauses of the Federal Constitution,
guided by the principle of human dignity, a guiding command of the entire legal
system.</p><p>Analyzing the judicialization of health care at this time of the pandemic brings to
light the fact that there is a huge contingent of the Brazilian society that is not
properly assisted by public authorities, highlighting the fragility of the system,
the potential for the pandemic to worsen, as well as a potential increase in the
number of deaths due to COVID-19.</p><p>The judicialization of health care reveals a lack of compliance with constitutional
prerogatives concerning right to health and human dignity as well the state&#x02019;s
inability to fulfill the right of citizens who become invisible in a society marked
by inequality and enormous wealth concentration.</p><p>From this perspective, the government, at its three levels, should commit to the
enforcement of constitutional rules, making effective and materializing fundamental
rights in order to enable health workers and the population to have a healthy life.
These measures ensure not only the compliance of rights, but also evidence the
ethical duty of government officials and the need of a state that is capable to
promote equity.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other" id="fn_ast1"><label>*</label><p> This article refers to the call &#x0201c;COVID-19 in the Global Health Context&#x0201d;.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>MJS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schraiber</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mota</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The concept of health in Collective Health: contributions from
social and historical critique of scientific production</article-title><source>Physis</source><comment>Internet</comment><year>2020</year><date-in-citation content-type="cited-date">cited 2020 May,
12</date-in-citation><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e290102</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0103-73312019290102</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>ABRB</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Acidentes, adoecimento e morte no trabalho como tema de estudo da
Hist&#x000f3;ria</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="compiler"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><role>org</role></person-group><source>Trabalho e trabalhadores no Nordeste: an&#x000e1;lises e perspectivas de
pesquisas hist&#x000f3;ricas em Alagoas, Pernambuco e Para&#x000ed;ba</source><comment>Internet</comment><publisher-loc>Campina Grande</publisher-loc><publisher-name>EDUEPB</publisher-name><year>2015</year><date-in-citation content-type="cited-date">cited 2020 May,
12</date-in-citation><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://books.scielo.org/id/xvx85/pdf/oliveira-9788578793333-09.pdf">http://books.scielo.org/id/xvx85/pdf/oliveira-9788578793333-09.pdf</ext-link><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>240</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>BRASIL</collab></person-group><source>Constitui&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o da Rep&#x000fa;blica Federativa do Brasil</source><comment>Internet</comment><publisher-loc>Bras&#x000ed;lia</publisher-loc><day>5</day><month>10</month><year>1988</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Acesso 12 mai
2020</date-in-citation><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.planalto.gov.br/ccivil_03/constituicao/constituicaocompilado.htm">http://www.planalto.gov.br/ccivil_03/constituicao/constituicaocompilado.htm</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="compiler"><name><surname>Godoy</surname><given-names>CVC</given-names></name><role>organizador</role></person-group><source>Ag&#x000ea;ncia. Conhecimento cient&#x000ed;fico e regula&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o: contribui&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es para a sa&#x000fa;de
suplementar</source><comment>Internet</comment><publisher-loc>Rio de Janeiro</publisher-loc><publisher-name>ANS</publisher-name><year>2019</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Acesso 12 mai
2020</date-in-citation><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ans.gov.br/images/LIVRO_de_MONOGRAFIAS_PREMIADAS.pdf">http://www.ans.gov.br/images/LIVRO_de_MONOGRAFIAS_PREMIADAS.pdf</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Viacava</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>RAD</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Laguardia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellida</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SUS: oferta, acesso e utiliza&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de servi&#x000e7;os de sa&#x000fa;de nos &#x000fa;ltimos
30 anos</article-title><source>Cienc Saude Coletiva</source><year>2018</year><volume>23</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1751</fpage><lpage>1762</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1413-81232018236.06022018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>NVDO</given-names></name><name><surname>Gon&#x000e7;alves</surname><given-names>FGA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pires</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>HMSL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neoliberalist influences on nursing hospital work process and
organization</article-title><source>Rev. Bras. Enferm</source><year>2017</year><volume>70</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>912</fpage><lpage>919</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0034-7167-2016-0092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28977215</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dweck</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impactos do novo regime fiscal na sa&#x000fa;de e
educa&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o</article-title><source>Cad Saude Publica</source><comment>Internet</comment><year>2016</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Acesso 23 jan
2020</date-in-citation><volume>32</volume><issue>12</issue><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.scielo.br/pdf/csp/v32n12/1678-4464-csp-32-12-e00194316.pdf">http://www.scielo.br/pdf/csp/v32n12/1678-4464-csp-32-12-e00194316.pdf</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hone</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirelman</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasella</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Paes-Sousa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Barreto</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Effect of economic recession and impact of health and social
protection expenditures on adult mortality: a longitudinal analysis of 5565
Brazilian municipalities</article-title><source>Lancet</source><comment>Internet</comment><year>2019</year><date-in-citation content-type="cited-date">cited 2002 May,
20</date-in-citation><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e1575-83</elocation-id><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.thelancet.com/action/showPdf?pii=S2214-109X%2819%2930409-7">https://www.thelancet.com/action/showPdf?pii=S2214-109X%2819%2930409-7</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31607469</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Desafios da enfermagem frente ao enfrentamento da pandemia da
Covid-19</article-title><source>Rev Min Enferm</source><year>2020</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>e</fpage><lpage>1302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5935/1415-2762.20200032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pimenta</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>EF</given-names><suffix>J&#x000fa;nior</suffix></name><name><surname>Pires</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiengo</surname><given-names>PCS</given-names></name><name><surname>Paula</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influ&#x000ea;ncia da precariza&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o no processo de trabalho e na sa&#x000fa;de do
trabalhador de enfermagem</article-title><source>Rev Enferm UFSM</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>758</fpage><lpage>768</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5902/2179769230180</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amaral</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direito &#x000e0; sa&#x000fa;de: Dilemas do fen&#x000f4;meno da judicializa&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o da
sa&#x000fa;de</article-title><source>Cad. Ibero-Amer Dir Sanit</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17566/ciads.v8i2.530</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Agenzia Nazionale Stampa Associata &#x02013; Sociedade Cooperativa</collab></person-group><source>Mais de dois mil m&#x000e9;dicos e enfermeiras contra&#x000ed;ram v&#x000ed;rus na
It&#x000e1;lia</source><publisher-name>Ag&#x000ea;ncia Italiana de Not&#x000ed;cias</publisher-name><comment>Internet</comment><year>2020</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Acesso 24 abr
2020</date-in-citation><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ansabrasil.com.br/brasil/noticias/italia/noticias/2020/03/16/mais-de-2-mil-medicos-e-enfermeiras-contrairam-virus-na-italia_010f1866-3b04-402f-8e07-6461e179a2b9.html">http://ansabrasil.com.br/brasil/noticias/italia/noticias/2020/03/16/mais-de-2-mil-medicos-e-enfermeiras-contrairam-virus-na-italia_010f1866-3b04-402f-8e07-6461e179a2b9.html</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="report"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Conselho Federal de Enfermagem (BR)</collab></person-group><source>Brasil tem 30 mortes na Enfermagem por Covid-19 e 4 mil profissionais
afastados</source><comment>Internet</comment><year>2020</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Acesso 30 abr
2020</date-in-citation><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cofen.gov.br/brasil-tem-30-mortes-na-enfermagem-por-covid-19-e-4-mil-profissionais-afastados_79198.html">http://www.cofen.gov.br/brasil-tem-30-mortes-na-enfermagem-por-covid-19-e-4-mil-profissionais-afastados_79198.html</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><source>Estudo de Caso: planejamento e m&#x000e9;todos</source><edition>4</edition><publisher-loc>Porto Alegre</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Bookman</publisher-name><year>2010</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruoff</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Piccoli</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>ACM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>O estudo de caso como m&#x000e9;todo de pesquisa em enfermagem: uma
revis&#x000e3;o integrativa</article-title><source>Texto Contexto-Enferm</source><year>2017</year><volume>26</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e5360016</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0104-07072017005360016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemos</surname><given-names>EP</given-names><suffix>Junior</suffix></name><name><surname>Brugnara</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>O princ&#x000ed;pio da dignidade da pessoa humana no ordenamento jur&#x000ed;dico
brasileiro</article-title><source>RFD - Revista da Faculdade de Direito da UERJ</source><comment>Internet</comment><year>2017</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Acesso 1 mai
2020</date-in-citation><issue>31</issue><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12957/rfd.2017.26639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>COVID-19 in Brazil: &#x0201c;So what?</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2020</year><volume>395</volume><size units="pages">1461</size><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)31095-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names><suffix>Filho</suffix></name><name><surname>Assun&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Algranti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Worker&#x02019;s health and the struggle against COVID-19</article-title><source>Rev Bras Saude Ocup</source><comment>Internet</comment><year>2020</year><date-in-citation content-type="cited-date">cited 2020 May,
20</date-in-citation><volume>45</volume><elocation-id>e14</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/2317-6369ed0000120</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sohrabi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Alsafi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Neill</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerwman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Jabir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>World Health Organization declares global emergency: A review of
the 2019 novel coronavirus (COVID-19)</article-title><source>Int J Surg</source><comment>Internet</comment><year>2020</year><date-in-citation content-type="cited-date">cited 2020 May,
19</date-in-citation><volume>76</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijsu.2020.02.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32068179</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Covid-19: Covid-19: Cases rise in Russia as health workers pay
the price for PPE shortage</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2020</year><volume>369</volume><size units="pages">m1975</size><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.m1975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Minist&#x000e9;rio da Sa&#x000fa;de (BR)</collab></person-group><article-title>Portaria n&#x000ba; 188, de 3 de fevereiro de 2020. Declara Emerg&#x000ea;ncia em
Sa&#x000fa;de P&#x000fa;blica de import&#x000e2;ncia Nacional (ESPIN) em decorr&#x000ea;ncia da Infec&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o
Humana pelo novo Coronav&#x000ed;rus (2019-nCoV)</article-title><comment>Internet</comment><source>Di&#x000e1;rio Oficial da Rep&#x000fa;blica Federativa do Brasil</source><publisher-loc>Bras&#x000ed;lia (DF)</publisher-loc><year>2020</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Acesso 21 mai
2020</date-in-citation><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.planalto.gov.br/ccivil_03/portaria/prt188-20-ms.htm">http://www.planalto.gov.br/ccivil_03/portaria/prt188-20-ms.htm</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldwasser</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lobo</surname><given-names>MSC</given-names></name><name><surname>Arruda</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelo</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lapa e Silva</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Salles</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Difficulties in access and estimates of public beds in intensive
care units in the state of Rio de Janeiro</article-title><source>Rev Saude Publica</source><year>2016</year><volume>50</volume><size units="pages">19</size><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1518-8787.2016050005997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Universidade de S&#x000e3;o Paulo</collab><collab>Grupo de Estudos sobre Planos de Sa&#x000fa;de</collab><collab>Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro</collab><collab>Grupo de Pesquisa e Documenta&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o sobre Empresariamento na Sa&#x000fa;de
Instituto de Estudos em Sa&#x000fa;de Coletiva da UFRJ</collab></person-group><source>Nota t&#x000e9;cnica: as empresas de planos de sa&#x000fa;de no contexto da pandemia do
coronav&#x000ed;rus: entre a omiss&#x000e3;o e o oportunismo</source><comment>Internet</comment><year>2020</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Acesso 11 mai
2020</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://analisepoliticaemsaude.org/oaps/documentos/noticias/coronavirus-planosdesaude-pdf/">https://analisepoliticaemsaude.org/oaps/documentos/noticias/coronavirus-planosdesaude-pdf/</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="report"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Conselho Federal de Enfermagem (BR)</collab></person-group><source>Recomenda&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es Gerais para Organiza&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o dos Servi&#x000e7;os de Sa&#x000fa;de e Preparo
das Equipes de Enfermagem</source><comment>Internet</comment><year>2020</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Acesso 12 mai
2020</date-in-citation><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.juntoscontracoronavirus.com.br/cartilha.pdf">http://www.juntoscontracoronavirus.com.br/cartilha.pdf</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="report"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Secretaria Estadual de Sa&#x000fa;de (ES)</collab></person-group><source>Nota T&#x000e9;cnica COVID-19 n&#x000b0; 03/2020 - Defini&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es de afastamento laboral
para profissionais de servi&#x000e7;os essenciais</source><comment>Internet</comment><year>2020</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Acesso 10 mai
2020</date-in-citation><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://coronavirus.es.gov.br/Media/Coronavirus/NotasTecnicas/NOTA%20T%C3%89CNICA%20COVID.19%20N.%2003.20.%20Defini%C3%A7%C3%B5es%20de%20Afastamento%20Laboral.pdf">https://coronavirus.es.gov.br/Media/Coronavirus/NotasTecnicas/NOTA%20T%C3%89CNICA%20COVID.19%20N.%2003.20.%20Defini%C3%A7%C3%B5es%20de%20Afastamento%20Laboral.pdf</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brugnara</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Marx</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Act now! Covid-19 pandemic: the coordinated support of the
international community to low- and middle-income countries is needed
immediately</article-title><source>Int Qual Health Care</source><comment>Internet</comment><year>2020</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">cited 2020 May,
23</date-in-citation><size units="pages">mzaa047</size><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7239130/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7239130/</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Minist&#x000e9;rio da Sa&#x000fa;de (BR)</collab><collab>Ag&#x000ea;ncia Nacional de Vigil&#x000e2;ncia Sanit&#x000e1;ria</collab></person-group><source>Resolu&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o &#x02013; RDC n&#x000ba; 283. Regulamento t&#x000e9;cnico para o funcionamento das
institui&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es de longa perman&#x000ea;ncia para idosos</source><comment>Internet</comment><publisher-loc>Bras&#x000ed;lia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>ANVISA</publisher-name><year>2005</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Acesso 18 mai
2020</date-in-citation><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bvsms.saude.gov.br/bvs/saudelegis/anvisa/2005/res0283_26_09_2005.html">https://bvsms.saude.gov.br/bvs/saudelegis/anvisa/2005/res0283_26_09_2005.html</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fenster</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Gropp</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the Importance of Science to Society: A Call for Government
Action</article-title><source>BioScience</source><comment>Internet</comment><year>2020</year><date-in-citation content-type="cited-date">cited 2020 May,
18</date-in-citation><volume>70</volume><issue>5</issue><size units="pages">371</size><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/biosci/biaa047</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>