<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">It is well known that cytokines play an important role in the pathology of a systemic viral illness. A well-coordinated immune response is a part of the first line innate immunity against most viral infections. However, an uncoordinated response results in the hyper-secretion of cytokines and chemokines which further lead to immune related end-organ damage 
 <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. HCoV (human coronavirus) infection triggers the release of cytokines (IL-6, IL-1B and TNF) and chemokines (CCL-2, CCL-3, and CCL-5) from respiratory epithelial cells, dendritic cells (DCs) and macrophages 
 <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Rapidly increasing cytokines and chemokines attract inflammatory cells such as neutrophils and monocytes, causing excessive infiltration of inflammatory cells in lungs and other organs. Through a positive feedback mechanism, the rapid infiltration of monocytes into organs triggers the elevation of proinflammatory cytokines (TNF, IL-6, IL1B and iNOS) which subsequently intensifies the systemic inflammatory response. Additionally, these mononuclear macrophage-derived proinflammatory cytokines induce apoptosis of T cells, which further decreases the viral clearance and results in propagation of the disease 
 <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Another consequence of rapid viral replication, inhibition of viral clearance and the over-abundance of inflammatory cytokines is the induction of apoptosis of end organ epithelial and endothelial cells through FAS-FAS ligand (FASL) or TRAIL-death receptor 5 (DR5) 
 <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. These mechanisms lead to severe end organ damage including, but not limited to, Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS).
</p>
