<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While public/patient involvement in research planning is widely recommended [
 <xref rid="pone.0205737.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0205737.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], a study logo may be seen as a relatively trivial aspect of research design that does not require community consultation. However, evidence from social psychology indicates the importance of branding, and in particular the strength of visual images [
 <xref rid="pone.0205737.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The need to develop appropriate logos is widely recognised in commercial marketing: an effective logo builds positive consumer perceptions and trust in the company and its products [
 <xref rid="pone.0205737.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0205737.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The same may apply in health research. Evidence suggests that community decisions on engagement can depend on their perceptions of the research institution more than their knowledge of study aims [
 <xref rid="pone.0205737.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0205737.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Study logos are an important part of institutional identity and image, and as such logos can affect decisions around participation. For example, in Kenya images of snakes in a study logo led to negative rumours about the research, concerns among communities and a lack of trust in both the study and the research institution [
 <xref rid="pone.0205737.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. For community members, the snakes depicted in the logos symbolised devil worship, a belief strengthened by the prominence of drawing blood as one study activity. In the UK, researchers for a cohort study among young people with cancer found that involving potential participants in study branding, including logo selection, appeared to increase acceptability and improved both participation and retention [
 <xref rid="pone.0205737.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].
</p>
