<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Given the importance of study logos for community perceptions and engagement, we sought feedback from potential research participants on the logo for a programme of influenza research in Malawi. Seasonal influenza epidemics are estimated to cause 250,000–500,000 deaths each year worldwide [
 <xref rid="pone.0205737.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Difficulty in identifying influenza and limited surveillance systems mean the extent of influenza in sub-Saharan Africa is not fully known. However, available data suggest influenza causes significant morbidity and mortality in the region, particularly amongst young children and people with HIV [
 <xref rid="pone.0205737.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0205737.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Surveillance data from 15 African countries found that 10% of severe acute respiratory infections were associated with influenza viruses [
 <xref rid="pone.0205737.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. An estimated 99% of deaths from influenza-associated acute lower respiratory infection in children under five occur in developing countries [
 <xref rid="pone.0205737.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Annual influenza vaccination is recommended for preventing influenza virus infection and its complications [
 <xref rid="pone.0205737.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and the World Health Organization's Strategic Advisory Group of Experts recommends influenza vaccination for children under 5 years, the elderly, pregnant women, individuals with high-risk underlying conditions and healthcare workers [
 <xref rid="pone.0205737.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Assessment and introduction of vaccination requires further evidence on the extent of influenza and effectiveness of vaccination in African countries, particularly in populations with high rates of HIV, malaria and malnutrition. To improve the evidence base for potential introduction of an influenza vaccine, the Malawi-Liverpool-Wellcome Trust Clinical Research Programme (MLW) is undertaking a programme of studies on influenza through support from a CDC Influenza Division Research co-operative agreement. This includes research to examine the severity and extent of influenza among high risk groups, including children, pregnant mothers and HIV-infected adults, the effectiveness of an influenza vaccine in children living in malaria endemic areas, and the acceptability of influenza vaccination. This research programme includes work in urban Blantyre, including hospital-based surveillance studies, and in rural Chikhwawa District.
</p>
