<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0060">MERS-CoV and SARS-CoV are considered extremely pathogenic and were transmitted by palm civets or dromedary camels to humans by means of bats. The characterization and genomic sequencing of the SARS-CoV-2 showed that the novel CoVs was 88% identical to the two earlier reported bat-derived SARS-like CoVs but were different from SARS-CoV (by 79%) and MERS-CoV ( by 50%), indicating that it evolved from bats but the intermediate source is not yet known. The phylogenetic analysis revealed that SARS-CoV-2 belonged to the genus 
 <italic>Betacoronavirus</italic> and was genetically dissimilar from MERS-CoV and SARS-CoV [
 <xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The size of the coronavirus genome varies from approx. 26,000 to 32,000 bases and contains a 6 to 11 number of ORFs. The first ORF that encodes 16 non-structural proteins comprises of approx. 67% of the total genome while remaining ORF encodes the structural protein and accessory proteins. Among the four major structural glycoproteins (as shown in 
 <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> [
 <xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]), spike glycoprotein(S) plays a vital part in binding to the host receptor. Homology modeling showed that SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV enter the lung and utilize the same human cell receptor i.e. ACE-2 despite amino acid variation at key residues, while MERS-CoV enters the host cell via DPP4 [
 <xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Six mutations arose in the variable sections of the receptor-binding domain (RBD) of SARS-CoV-2, but no amino acid replacements were observed in RBD that directly interacts with ACE-2 receptors of the host cell [
 <xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Receptor affinity analysis claims that the SARS-CoV strain binds less efficiently than the novel SARS-CoV-2 strain, and further mutation in the nucleotide sequence of RBD may increase its pathogenicity [
 <xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. It is uncertain whether higher SARS-CoV-2 affinity to ACE-2 receptor than SARS-CoV could lead to more severe lung connection. This should be further investigated since in vitro studies by inoculating SARS-CoV-2 in human airway epithelial cells have shown a cytopathic effect with the cessation of cilia movements [
 <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Other than the lung, the ACE-2 receptors are highly expressed in the small intestine, kidney, testis, and liver, hence, these organs may also get affected by SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].
</p>
