<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The highly pathogenic A (H5N1) virus presents many more problems in vaccine development and evaluation. The first one, already solved, involves removal of the molecular motif of high pathogenicity, the multibasic cleavage site, from the hemagglutinin. The virus is then reassembled by using reverse genetics, but on a background of the high-growth type A virus, PR8 (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">
  <italic>18</italic>
 </xref>). Producing vaccine by using this engineered virus can then proceed without high-level containment. However, we know from previous work with a less pathogenic influenza, A (H5N3) that antibody response to this avian subtype is not good and that adjuvants and multiple doses are required (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">
  <italic>19</italic>
 </xref>
 <italic>,</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">
  <italic>20</italic>
 </xref>). The A (H5N3) vaccine was given to only small numbers of healthy adults. Response did not occur in persons given &lt;30 μg of antigen alone but did in persons given the antigen with the MF-59 adjuvant. However, after 16 months, essentially no antibody was seen even in those who received the vaccine with adjuvant. On revaccination with the same preparation, persons previously given the vaccine with adjuvant had an anamnestic response, while persons given the unadjuvanted vaccine again had a poor response. Measuring and evaluating the meaning of the antibody response to some avian viruses is also an issue. Even infection with the A (H5N1) virus does not produce a good HAI antibody response; the antibody needs to be detected with a neutralization test (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">
  <italic>21</italic>
 </xref>). Similarly, neutralization testing is necessary to detect response to vaccine; however, a specific level of HAI antibody has been associated with protection, but no similar correlate of neutralization antibody has yet been developed (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">
  <italic>5</italic>
 </xref>).
</p>
