<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0450">The acute and latency phase of HIV infection is shown in 
 <xref rid="f0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 49.5</xref> .
 <xref rid="bib115" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>115</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup>,</sup>
 <xref rid="bib116" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>116</sup>
 </xref> Without combined antiretroviral therapy (cARV), CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cell counts progressively decrease, and the host usually succumbs to infections with opportunistic organisms that occur because of HIV-induced secondary immune deficiency. Specific anti-HIV, CD4
 <sup>+</sup>, and CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells, and neutralizing anti-HIV antibodies develop, however, these responses are eventually overcome by viral escape strategies.
 <xref rid="bib105" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>105</sup>
 </xref> Patients can present with constitutional symptoms, such as fever, weight loss, diarrhea, lymphadenopathy, secondary opportunistic infections, and viral skin infections, heralding the presence of an immunocompromised immune system. Peripheral CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cell counts of &lt;200 cells/mL herald the development of AIDS. This T cell depletion predisposes patients to develop opportunistic infections including, but not limited to, cytomegalovirus, 
 <italic>Herpes simplex</italic>, varicella zoster virus, 
 <italic>Pneumocystis jirovecii</italic> pneumonia, histoplasmosis, toxoplasmosis, coccidioidomycosis, 
 <italic>Cryptosporidium</italic>, 
 <italic>Nocardia</italic>, 
 <italic>Mycobacterium avium</italic> complex, salmonella, and 
 <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic>. If HIV-infected patients do not receive antiretroviral treatment, repeated infections with these opportunistic secondary infections ultimately lead to death. Thus, HIV infection exhausts the adaptive immune system, leading to chronic depletion of CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells and immune dysfunction of the multiple effector immune responses that are required to prevent secondary bacterial, viral, fungal, and protozoan infections.
</p>
