<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0015">Both SARS-CoV and SARS-CoV-2 can infect host cells when the viral spike protein binds to its cell surface receptor angiotensin-converting enzyme II (ACE2). With the exception of human coronavirus (hCoV) NL63, the seven other hCoVs have other host cell receptors (also exopeptidases). ACE2 is a homolog of angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE), the central enzyme in the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (RAAS), which is crucial for the physiology and pathology of all organs (
 <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Gheblawi et al., 2020</xref>). ACE2 maintains the homeostasis of RAAS as a negative regulator. Virus entry also requires cleavage of the spike protein (priming) by a type II transmembrane serine protease called TMPRSS2. This priming step is essential for fusion of the viral and cell membranes (
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Matsuyama et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Hoffmann et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2020a</xref>). Additional proteases (including furin) might be involved in SARS-CoV-2 priming (
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Coutard et al., 2020</xref>). SARS-CoV-2’s binding affinity for human ACE2 is 10 to 20 times greater than that of SARS-CoV; this disparity might result from differences in spike protein methylation and/or cleavage sites (
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Jin et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2020b</xref>). Hence, the expression of ACE2 is essential for SARS-CoV-2’s entry into host cells. As discussed later, changes in ACE2’s functional activity might critically affect the disease outcome. In humans, ACE2 and TMPRSS2 are strongly expressed in lung tissue in general and by epithelial cells in particular. This strong expression explains why the lung appears to be the most vulnerable target organ during COVID-19. A recent single-cell analysis revealed that more than 80% of ACE2-expressing pulmonary cells were type II alveolar cells (
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr">Zhao et al., 2020</xref>); hence, this cell type might have a crucial role in coronavirus invasion and replication. Bronchial transient secretory cells (with a phenotype between those of goblet cells and ciliated cells) also express high levels of ACE2 (
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Lukassen et al., 2020</xref>). Furthermore, epithelial cells in the upper respiratory tract (specifically nasal goblet/secretory cells and ciliated cells) express both ACE2 and TMPRSS2 (
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Sungnak et al., 2020</xref>). This combined expression in the upper airways may be correlated with enhanced transmission of the virus. ACE2 is also expressed in many extrapulmonary tissues, including the heart, liver, kidney, and intestine (
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Crackower et al., 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Hamming et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hashimoto et al., 2012</xref>). In the latter, high levels of ACE2 are found on the luminal surface of differentiated epithelial cells in the small intestine, whereas levels are lower in the crypt cells and in the colon (
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hashimoto et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Liang et al., 2020</xref>). Human proximal and distal enterocytes coexpress dipeptidyl peptidase-4 (the receptor for MERS-CoV) and alanine aminopeptidase (the receptor for hCoV-229E) (
 <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Liang et al., 2020</xref>). In the intestine, ACE2 acts as a coreceptor for nutrient uptake and especially amino acid absorption from food (
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Hashimoto et al., 2012</xref>). On the one hand, the gut might be a major entry site for SARS-CoV-2; this would suggest that consumption of contaminated food can propagate the virus in humans. On the other hand, the intestinal expression of ACE2 might have essential implications for fecal-oral transmission and thus the containment of viral spreading. As seen during previous coronavirus outbreaks, around half of all COVID-19 patients have detectable SARS-CoV-2 RNA in their stools—even when it is no longer found in the respiratory tract (
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Xiao et al., 2020b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2020c</xref>). The virus has also been detected in gastrointestinal histological samples and by endoscopy (
 <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">Xiao et al., 2020a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2020</xref>). Importantly, infectious viruses were detected in fecal samples of COVID-19 patients, suggesting that the digestive tract might be a site of viral replication and activity (
 <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">Xiao et al., 2020b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2020c</xref>). Several studies using human small intestinal organoids have shown that SARS-CoV-2 replicates in enterocytes (
 <xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2020c</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">Zang et al., 2020</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Lamers et al., 2020</xref>). The presence of virus in the stools and its fecal persistence suggest that fecal-oral transmission is possible. A study (mouse system) reported that intragastric inoculation of SARS-CoV-2 causes productive infection and leads to pulmonary pathological changes (
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2020</xref>). Collectively, the lung is not the only site targeted by SARS-CoV-2, and enteric infection occurs. Here, we review gastrointestinal disorders in patients with COVID-19, suggest hypothetical mechanisms leading to gut symptoms, and discuss the potential consequences of gastrointestinal disorders on the outcome of the disease.
</p>
