<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since the eradication of polio, GBS has become the most common cause of acute flaccid paralysis. GBS is an autoimmune disorder affecting the Schwann cells of the PNS. This immune-mediated demyelinating neuropathy can rapidly evolve over a period of few days or more and can lead to paralysis or even death.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_ref_005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
  <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_ref_006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
  <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_ref_007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]
 </sup> The initial symptoms of GBS include muscle weakness that starts from distal limbs which subsequently progresses to proximal limbs.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_ref_008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]
 </sup> GBS may lead to respiratory failure requiring mechanical ventilation over 15% of cases.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_ref_009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]
 </sup> In some cases, GBS can affect the heart rate and changes the blood pressure by disrupting the autonomic nervous system.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_ref_010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]
 </sup> The disease can be self-limiting, with muscle strength reaching a lowest point in few days, followed by a partial or full recovery over weeks to months. Diagnosis of this syndrome is based on the clinical signs and symptoms and through rule out of other differential diagnoses as shown in 
 <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_tab_001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The treatment includes administration of intravenous immunoglobulins or plasmapheresis, and supportive therapies. Although most people have an uneventful recovery, up to one-third of the cases are left with severe neurological deficits.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_ref_011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
  <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_ref_012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]
 </sup> The mortality rate of the disease is approximately 8% in developing world, but much lower in developed countries.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_ref_013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]
 </sup> The incidence of GBS increases with age, and people older than 50 years are at greatest risk for developing GBS. The estimated risk of developing GBS in the world is one to two cases per 100,000 people per year.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_ref_014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]
 </sup> Severe autoimmune responses resulted from infections by external infectious agents are considered as major initiating factors of the syndrome.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_ref_015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
  <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_ref_016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]
 </sup> Infection by 
 <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> is identified as the most common inciting event although other agents such as herpes simplex virus (HSV), cytomegalovirus (CMV), Epstein–Barr virus (EBV), Zika virus (ZIKV), 
 <italic>Mycoplasma pneumoniae, Haemophilus influenza</italic>, and influenza have been reported.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_ref_007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, 
  <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_ref_017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
  <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_ref_018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
  <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_ref_019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
  <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_ref_020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,
  <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_ref_021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
  <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_ref_022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]
 </sup> Vaccination to influenza has been implicated in GBS, although the evidence for this link is controversial.
 <sup>[
  <xref rid="j_jtim-2019-0028_ref_023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]
 </sup>
</p>
