<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Phylogenetic techniques, in particular coalescent-based models, have also been used to estimate the ages of filoviruses. Interestingly, common ancestor age estimates have ranged from thousands to millions of years [
 <xref rid="B12-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], suggesting both novel techniques and increased sample sizes are needed, and that better understanding of filovirus evolution (e.g., purifying selection, integration into host genomes, 
 <italic>etc.</italic>) must be gained before reliable dates can be obtained. For individual species, some models have suggested 
 <italic>Zaire ebolavirus</italic> viruses diverged from a common ancestor very recently [
 <xref rid="B24-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Recent analyses using Bayesian coalescent phylogenetic analyses on 97 whole-genome sequences have been able to estimate nucleotide substitutions/site/year for different viruses (ranging from 0.46 × 10
 <sup>−4</sup> for 
 <italic>Sudan ebolavirus</italic> to 8.21 × 10
 <sup>−4</sup> for 
 <italic>Reston ebolavirus</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The analysis by Carroll 
 <italic>et al.</italic> estimates recent common ancestry (approximately 50 years ago) for 
 <italic>Reston ebolavirus</italic> and 
 <italic>Zaire ebolavirus</italic>, and the authors suggest these species may have experienced recent genetic bottlenecks. 
 <italic>Marburg marburgvirus</italic> and 
 <italic>Sudan ebolavirus</italic> species were estimated to have common ancestors less than 1000 years ago (approximately 700 and 850 years ago, respectively), whereas the 
 <italic>Filoviridae</italic> were estimated to share common ancestry 10,000 years ago [
 <xref rid="B8-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].
</p>
