<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A common feature of cardiac glycoside treatment is reduction in IE1/2 protein levels [
 <xref rid="B362-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">362</xref>,
 <xref rid="B363-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">363</xref>,
 <xref rid="B365-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">365</xref>]. Mechanism of action studies demonstrated that convallatoxin does not inhibit IE2 mRNA levels but instead inhibits global translation of viral and host cell proteins [
 <xref rid="B363-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">363</xref>]. Cellular translation machinery is not directly inhibited by convallatoxin; instead the compound reduces methionine transport into the cell, limiting the intracellular pool of this essential amino acid for translation. Convallatoxin has been proposed to mediate this indirect mechanism of translation inhibition by its ability to bind to and inhibit the cellular sodium-potassium ATP pump (NA
 <sup>+</sup>,K
 <sup>+</sup>-ATPase) [
 <xref rid="B363-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">363</xref>]. In this model, inhibition of the pump causes a reduction in the sodium gradient across the cell membrane, leading to a decrease in sodium-dependent methionine transport [
 <xref rid="B363-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">363</xref>]. Despite inhibition of global translation, minimal cellular cytotoxicity was observed at the nanomolar concentrations of convallatoxin required for antiviral effect. This observation suggests that, whilst the cell can tolerate a reduction in protein synthesis, HCMV is unable to compensate for reductions in viral protein levels, particularly in IE proteins which are required for early and late protein production and are thus essential for virus replication [
 <xref rid="B363-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">363</xref>]. Convallatoxin-induced inhibition of viral protein translation by methionine transport reduction is not the only mechanism attributed to the antiviral activity of cardiac glycosides. Alternate mechanisms of action are based on the ability of these compounds to modulate cell signalling pathways [
 <xref rid="B370-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">370</xref>]. For example, cardiac glycoside digitoxin has been reported to inhibit HCMV through induction of cellular autophagy following activation of the regulatory kinase AMPK via a novel NA
 <sup>+</sup>,K
 <sup>+</sup>-ATPase subunit α1-AMPK-ULK1 pathway [
 <xref rid="B173-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">173</xref>]. In addition to inhibiting HCMV, cardiac glycosides act as antivirals against a range of clinically important DNA and RNA viruses. This broad-spectrum activity has been attributed to a range of host-directed mechanisms [
 <xref rid="B371-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">371</xref>]. 
</p>
