<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Vector competence studies have been performed in other countries [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008303.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>] with varying results due in part to the non standardization of protocols, making their comparison difficult. Field 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> populations were mainly used in these studies, but the DENV strains used were mostly old strains, with an overrepresentation of DENV-2 strains [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008303.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>–
 <xref rid="pntd.0008303.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Nevertheless, the infection rates of NC 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> we report here are lower compared to those reported in studies in Africa [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008303.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008303.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], in South East Asia [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008303.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] or in the Caribbean [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008303.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], suggesting that NC 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> are less susceptible to DENV infection. Many intrinsic and extrinsic factors [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008303.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] are involved in the modulation of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> vector competence, as early at the midgut infection phase. Indeed, genetic variants from both 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> population and the virus can play a role in vector competence, whereby the outcome of the infection depends on the specific combination of mosquito and virus genotypes [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008303.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008303.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The susceptibility of mosquitoes to infection can also be influenced by the insect microbiome [
 <xref rid="pntd.0008303.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0008303.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] and the microbiota interplays in the activation of mosquito immune responses. Although we evidenced moderate infection rates, the dissemination and the transmission rates are similar to those found in the different studies. The extrinsic incubation period for 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> from NC, however, seems to be shorter, with transmission observed from 7 dpi for DENV-1 and DENV-4.
</p>
