<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In a recent study, S. Liu et al. investigated the impact of ERAP1 and ERAP2 variants on HCV chronic infection in a cohort of 376 Han Chinese with chronic HCV infection and 324 healthy controls [
 <xref rid="B46-cells-09-00720" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Allelic and genotypic frequencies of rs27044, rs30187, rs26618, and rs26653 in the ERAP1 gene and rs2248374 and rs2549782 in the ERAP2 gene were compared between the case and control groups. Notably, the allelic distribution of rs26618 highly deviated in HCV-infected patients compared to controls, revealing that the C-allele carriers had an increased risk of susceptibility to HCV chronicity compared to the T-allele carriers. According to these results, the authors assumed that the rs26618 polymorphism may affect either the enzymatic activity or the structure of ERAP1, leading to alterations in the HCV antigen presentation pathway, and in turn to increased susceptibility to this infection. The allelic distribution of rs2248374 was different in the case and control groups as well. In particular, the A allele caused a slightly higher risk of susceptibility to HCV chronicity compared to the G allele. As previously reported, the G-allele for this SNP leads to NMD and hampers ERAP2 protein expression [
 <xref rid="B32-cells-09-00720" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. On the other hand, individuals who are homozygous for the A-allele present about 50% more enzyme in comparison to individuals with the heterozygous haplotype, suggesting that rs2248374 may be a marker of ERAP2 protein expression. Taking this into account, this study suggests that the A-allele for this SNP may be associated with increased expression of ERAP2 in HCV chronically infected individuals, therefore affecting the antigen presentation process and leading to a greater risk of susceptibility to HCV chronicity [
 <xref rid="B36-cells-09-00720" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. In addition, given the role of ERAP2 as a promoter of ERAP1 activity—through the formation of heterodimers with increased trimming efficacy—it has been observed that combination of rs26618-C/rs2248374-A on the two genes also provides a greater risk of susceptibility to HCV chronicity in Han Chinese population [
 <xref rid="B46-cells-09-00720" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>].
</p>
