<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Engagement of civil societies in the conduct of clinical trials should not preclude engagement of community members in the trials. Members’ engagement in COVID‐19 research will help address the many myths and misconceptions about that research. Efforts must be taken to prevent rumors from impeding well‐designed studies. The formation of community advisory boards (CAB), made up of representatives from the communities that are targeted for research and who serve as liaisons between the research team and the community,
 <fn id="dewb12283-note-1047">
  <label>47</label>
  <p>Mlambo, C.K., Vernooij, E., Geut, R., et al. (2019). Experiences from a community advisory Board in the Implementation of early access to ART for all in Eswatini: a qualitative study. BMC Med Ethics. 20, 50.</p>
 </fn> is a population approach for trials of HIV vaccine and treatment. The CAB can strengthen relationships between researchers and the community;
 <fn id="dewb12283-note-1048">
  <label>48</label>
  <p>Maung Lwin, K., Cheah, P.Y., Cheah, P.K., et al. (2014). Motivations and perceptions of community advisory boards in the ethics of medical research: the case of the Thai‐Myanmar border. BMC Med Ethics. 15(1), 12; Nyirenda, D., Sariola, S., Gooding, K., et al. (2017). We are the eyes and ears of researchers and community’: understanding the role of community advisory groups in representing researchers and communities in Malawi. Dev World Bioeth. 1–9.</p>
 </fn> educate community members about the research;
 <fn id="dewb12283-note-1049">
  <label>49</label>
  <p>Mlambo, C.K., Vernooij, E., Geut, R., et al. (2019). Experiences from a community advisory Board in the Implementation of early access to ART for all in Eswatini: a qualitative study. BMC Med Ethics 20, 50.</p>
 </fn> and review research protocols, study materials, and informed consent tools, with the aim of ensuring that socio‐cultural contexts and concerns are addressed when designing and conducting the studies and disseminating the findings.
 <fn id="dewb12283-note-1050">
  <label>50</label>
  <p>Ceasar, J., Peters‐Lawrence, M.H., Mitchell, V., et al. (2017). The communication, awareness, relationships and empowerment (C.a.R.E.) model: an effective tool for engaging urban communities in community‐based participatory research. Int J Environ Res Public Heal Artic. 14(11), 1422.</p>
 </fn>
</p>
