<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Particulate vaccines are capable of forming a close contact with the epithelial cells in the mucosa via included anchoring devices with adhesive properties (lectins, specific Abs) or included immunomodulating factors (TLR ligands, TLR ligand binding receptors) [
 <xref rid="B83-viruses-12-00862" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>,
 <xref rid="B121-viruses-12-00862" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>]. The above formulation involves virus-like particles (VLPs), biodegradable microparticles, and nanoparticles including lactide-co-glycolide-based microparticles. VLPs are generated by viral structural proteins alone without any genomic composition. These non-replicating particles are characteristic of retaining virus morphology and antigenicity. Therefore, they are capable of activating innate immune responses. Oral administration of influenza VLPs was found to induce serum IgG and S-IgA responses [
 <xref rid="B122-viruses-12-00862" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. VLPs were identified to be promising for “universal” vaccines with broad cross-protection, and triple-subtype vaccine (H5, H7, and H9) had the capacity to protect chickens against heterologous virus challenge including HPAI H5N2, HPAI H7N3, and LPAI H9N2 [
 <xref rid="B123-viruses-12-00862" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>]. Nanoparticle-based vaccines have the potential advantage in overcoming the low immunogenicity and inefficient delivery, while maintaining slow antigen release and promoting antigen presentation for desired immune responses. Multiple studies reported that NLRP3-associated inflammasome can be activated by nanoparticles such as carbon black, poly-lactic-co-glycolic acid (PLGA) and polystyrene, TiO2, SiO2, and aluminum oxyhydroxide [
 <xref rid="B124-viruses-12-00862" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]. For instance, PLGA nanospheres were proved to be good candidates for AIV defenses, as PLGA-based vaccines induced serum IgG and S-IgA as well as a mixed Th1/Th2 response [
 <xref rid="B125-viruses-12-00862" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>,
 <xref rid="B126-viruses-12-00862" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>].
</p>
