<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10">The “Viral Manipulation Hypothesis” states that by modifying the production of certain volatiles, the plant host will be more attractive to the virus’ vectors (Gutiérrez et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2013</xref>). Vector transmission mechanisms of plant viruses influence the effects the virus has on the plant host, with persistently transmitted viruses tending to either improve the host quality for the vector or mimic high quality, and nonpersistantly transmitted viruses lowering quality to facilitate the rapid dispersal of the viruliforous insect to neighboring plants (Mauck et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">2012</xref>). Host manipulation is seen in unrelated families of plant viruses, implying convergent evolution (Wu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120">2014</xref>). 
 <italic>Barley yellow mosaic virus</italic> (BYDV) is persistently transmitted by the aphid 
 <italic>Rhopalosiphum padi</italic>. Virus-free aphids have a feeding preference for BYDV-infected plants, while the reverse is true for BYDV-carrying aphids (Ingwell et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2012</xref>). 
 <italic>Cucumber mosaic virus</italic> (CMV), a member of the 
 <italic>Bromoviridae</italic> family, increases the release of volatiles that mimic healthy plants, attracting vectors despite the low quality of the plant for the aphids (Mauck et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">2015b</xref>). Additionally, CMV effects other non-vectoring insects, repelling some while attracting others, in the absence of aphids (Mauck et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">2015a</xref>). In mixed infections, competition can favor one microbe over another, as seen with the potyvirus, 
 <italic>Zucchini yellow mosaic virus</italic> (ZYMV) out-competing another potyvirus, 
 <italic>Watermelon mosaic virus</italic> (WMV). ZYMV and WMV are very similar viruses, in terms of genetics, hosts, and vectors. These similarities places them in direct competition with each other. One important difference is in vector manipulation; ZYMV manipulates the host-aphid relationship, while WMV does not. When co-infecting a plant, ZYMV will maintain its typical level of replication, while the replication of WMV is reduced. Despite this, WMV is still transmitted from a mixed infection, taking advantage of ZYMV host manipulation that attracts the aphid vectors (Salvaudon et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">2013</xref>). In an analysis of genetic turnover during transmission, several clones containing the same mutation leading to a premature stop codon was found within a plant. Further transmissions using this experimental isolate lost this mutation, but this suggests that ZYMV has the ability to complement defective ZYMV genomes in the aphid vector (Simmons et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">2011</xref>).
</p>
