<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Niger Med J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Niger Med J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">NMJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nigerian Medical Journal : Journal of the Nigeria Medical Association</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0300-1652</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2229-774X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer - Medknow</publisher-name><publisher-loc>India</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">NMJ-60-149</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/nmj.NMJ_74_19</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Impact of 6-month Micronutrient Supplementation on Viral, Immunological, and Mental Health Profile of a Cohort of Highly Active Antiretroviral Therapy-Naive HIV-Positive Patients in Northern Nigeria</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Olisah</surname><given-names>Victor Obiajulu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abiola</surname><given-names>Tajudeen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Okpataku</surname><given-names>Christopher I.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Obiako</surname><given-names>Reginald O.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Audu</surname><given-names>Ishaq A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yakasai</surname><given-names>Bashir A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">4</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Department of Psychiatry, Ahmadu Bello University Teaching Hospital, Zaria, Nigeria</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>1</label>Department of Clinical Services, Medical Services Unit, Federal Neuropsychiatric Hospital, Kaduna, Kaduna State, Nigeria</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>2</label>Department of Psychiatry, College of Health Sciences, Bingham University, Jos, Plateau State, Nigeria</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>3</label>Department of Medicine, Ahmadu Bello University, Zaria, Nigeria</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>4</label>Department of Internal Medicine, Kaduna State University, Kaduna, Kaduna State, Nigeria</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr. Victor Obiajulu Olisah, Department of Psychiatry, Ahmadu Bello University Teaching Hospital, Shika, Zaria, Kaduna State, Nigeria. E-mail: <email xlink:href="olisahvictor@yahoo.com">olisahvictor@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>May-Jun</season><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>60</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2019 Nigerian Medical Journal</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0"><license-p>This is an open access journal, and articles are distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 License, which allows others to remix, tweak, and build upon the work non-commercially, as long as appropriate credit is given and the new creations are licensed under the identical terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>Background:</title><p>HIV is a chronic disease with inflammatory reactions involving numerous elements of the immune system, resulting in an increased risk for other physical and psychiatric morbidities. Micronutrients, some of which possess anti-inflammatory properties, may help prevent the development of psychological disorders such as anxiety and depression in people living with HIV disease.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>Objectives:</title><p>This study examined the profile of viral load, CD4 cell count, C-reactive protein, anxiety, and depression among highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART)-naive HIV-positive patients receiving micronutrient supplementation over a 6-month period.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>Materials and Methods:</title><p>A total of ninety HAART-na&#x000ef;ve HIV-infected patients completed the Hospital Anxiety Depression Scale. Their blood samples were taken for serum viral load, CD4 cell count, and C-reactive protein at baseline. They all received a micronutrient supplement for 6 months, and 68 participants who remained in treatment at 6 months were reassessed with the same parameters.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>Results:</title><p>After 6 months of micronutrient supplementation, the participants were found to have statistically significantly lower mean scores on the anxiety (<italic>t</italic>-test = 2.970, <italic>P</italic> = 0.003) and depression (<italic>t</italic>-test = 3.843, <italic>P</italic> = 0.001) subscales. They also had statistically significantly lower median CD4 cell count (<italic>P</italic> = 0.00) and C-reactive protein serum measures (<italic>P</italic> = 0.04). The median viral load decreased although the difference was not statistically significant.</p></sec><sec id="st5"><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Micronutrient supplementation may reduce inflammatory reactions, anxiety, and depression in HAART-naive HIV-infected persons.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Anxiety</kwd><kwd>CD4 count</kwd><kwd>depression</kwd><kwd>highly active antiretroviral therapy-naive</kwd><kwd>HIV</kwd><kwd>micronutrients</kwd><kwd>Nigeria</kwd><kwd>viral load</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>I<sc>NTRODUCTION</sc></title><p>Nigeria has the second largest HIV epidemic in the world<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> and about 3.2 million people were living with HIV in 2016.<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Despite this large number, most of the research work have centered around disease prevalence and physical complications rather than their mental health burden. Several studies have shown that deficiencies of serum micronutrients are common among HIV-infected persons, especially those in developing countries.<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref><xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> Micronutrient deficiencies have been found to occur at the early stages of HIV infection, and are associated with an increased risk of HIV disease progression and mortality.<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Micronutrient deficiencies may contribute to the pathogenesis of HIV infection through increased oxidative stress and compromised immunity.<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Micronutrient supplements can delay HIV disease progression and reduce mortality in HIV-positive persons not receiving highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART).<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> With the transition to more universal access to HAART, a better understanding of micronutrient deficiencies and the role of micronutrient supplements in HIV-positive persons, especially in relation to disease progression and psychological well-being, has become a priority.</p><p>Furthermore, studies have provided evidence that micronutrients directly intervene in immunological regulatory systems and participate in the regulation of inflammatory reactions, hence combating the incidence and progress of some physical and psychological disorders such as diabetes, atherosclerosis, anxiety, and depression, in which inflammatory processes have been found to play a role in their pathogenesis.<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> In addition to the immune-modulatory potential of beta-carotene and the anti-inflammatory properties of Omega-3 fatty acids and Vitamin D, the antioxidant Vitamins C and E could be important because there appears to be a connection between oxidative stress and inflammation.<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Oxidative stress plays an important part in the onset and persistence of chronic inflammatory processes which can damage blood vessels and other tissues in the long term: A high concentration of oxygen radicals leads to the increase in the serum concentration of certain pro-inflammatory proteins such as C-reactive protein and interleukins which are indicator proteins for inflammation.<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Antioxidant micronutrients can bind and neutralize oxygen radicals and thus combat the initiation of inflammation.</p><p>The levels of C-reactive protein have been found to be associated with HIV disease progression independent of CD4 lymphocyte counts and HIV RNA levels. In addition, regardless of progression to AIDS, HIV-infected individuals have a significant increase in C-reactive protein over time.<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Studies have found that elevated levels of C-reactive protein are associated with an increased risk for psychological distress, anxiety, and depression in the general population.<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref><xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> A study found that anxiety as well as co-morbid anxiety and depression can be associated with an increased risk for low-grade inflammation in males at population level.<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> Hence, micronutrients with anti-inflammatory properties may reduce inflammation in patients with HIV and consequently reduce anxiety and depression that are prevalent in these patients.<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></p><p>CD4+ T-cells are fundamental to the development of specific immune responses to infection, particularly intracellular pathogens. As the primary target of HIV, depletion of CD4+ T-cells severely limits the host response capacity.<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> The CD4+ T-cell count is the most significant predictor of disease progression and survival.<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref><xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> Lower CD4 counts are associated with greater risk of disease progression over time. The value of HIV viral load measurement as a prognostic marker has long been established.<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> An approximately inverse relationship to the CD4 cell count and survival time has been observed in around 80% of patients.<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Higher viral load levels are associated with more rapid decline of CD4 cells, assisting prediction of the rate of CD4 count decline and disease progression.</p><p>More recent evidence on brain metabolism suggests that nutritional deficiencies of certain micronutrients can influence the development and progression of mental illnesses.<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref><xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> Some studies have shown that the intake of antioxidant micronutrients (zinc, selenium, and Vitamin C) correlated negatively with the development of anxiety, depression, and stress in HIV-positive individuals.<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Folic acid and Vitamin B6 help combat depression.<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref><xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Zinc and Vitamin B12 deficiency has been associated with the development of several psychiatric disorders such as depression, bipolar disorder, panic disorder, schizophrenia, and phobias.<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref><xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></p><p>Therefore, micronutrient supplementation should be seen as an important aspect of HIV treatment and support in a resource-poor country like Nigeria where significant gaps persist in providing antiretroviral treatment to all who are in need. Less than 60% of the people living with HIV in sub-Saharan Africa have access to antiretroviral therapy (ART).<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Most times, patients had to wait until their CD4 counts drop below 200 before the commencement of ART and to this end, micronutrient supplementation could serve as a pragmatic stop gap.</p><p>However, most studies on micronutrient supplementation in HIV/AIDS have focused on its effect on the physical outcomes of the disease rather than psychological. People living with HIV are about two to three times more likely to experience mental health disorders during the course of their illness, especially anxiety and depression, than the general population which, in turn, reduce their quality of life and adherence to antiretroviral treatment and contribute significantly to disease progression and premature deaths.<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> For these reasons, it is important that physicians in the care of patients with HIV/AIDS should not neglect their mental health.</p><p>In this study, we looked at what happens to the viral load, CD4 cell count, C-reactive protein (biomarker for inflammation), anxiety, and depression among HAART-naive HIV-positive patients receiving micronutrient supplementation over a 6-month period in Northern Nigeria.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>M<sc>ATERIALS AND</sc> M<sc>ETHODS</sc></title><p>This study was part of a larger study on the effects of micronutrients on immunological outcomes of HAART-naive patients with HIV infection in Kaduna State conducted by some physicians at a tertiary health institution in Nigeria.</p><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Sample size and technique</title><p>A minimum sample size of 88 was determined from the Fisher's sample size formula for longitudinal studies, as follows:<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
<italic>N</italic> = <italic>Z</italic><sup>2</sup>
<italic>P</italic> (1 &#x02212; P)/<italic>d</italic><sup>2</sup> &#x000d7; 1 (1 &#x02212; f), where <italic>N</italic> = desired sample size when population is over 100,000; <italic>Z</italic> = confidence interval at 95% (1.96); <italic>P</italic> = prevalence rate of HIV infection in Kaduna State, Nigeria (5.1%);<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>
<italic>d</italic> = sampling error at 5% (0.05); and <italic>f</italic> = attrition rate of 10%. However, in order to increase the power of the study, ninety HIV-positive HAART-na&#x000ef;ve adult patients, aged 18&#x02013;59 years, were recruited at baseline through consecutive sampling of every eligible patient meeting the inclusion criteria at the clinics during the study period. The research lasted for 3 years, from September 2013 to September 2016.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Study design</title><p>A longitudinal study.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Study population</title><p>The study participants were ninety HAART-na&#x000ef;ve and newly diagnosed HIV-infected patients who were not eligible for ART medication on the basis of their CD4 count of 500 and above. They were recruited from HIV clinics of two major hospitals in Kaduna State, Nigeria, namely the Nasara HIV Treatment and Care Centre at Ahmadu Bello University Teaching Hospital, Zaria, and the Caritas Catholic Relief Foundation (CCRF) HIV Centre at Saint Gerard's Catholic Hospital, Kaduna State, Nigeria. Both the centers provide free ART to eligible patients and supportive care to ART-ineligible patients. All the patients presenting to the study centers during the period of the study who met the inclusion criteria were recruited until the sample size of ninety participants was attained.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Inclusion criteria for the ninety HIV-infected patients</title><p>Participants were aged 18&#x02013;59 years, were physically fit, and were mentally alert, without evidence of physical deformity. Other eligibility criteria were HAART na&#x000ef;ve, being in the WHO clinical Stages I and II, and CD4+ count &#x0003e;500 cells/&#x003bc;l.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Exclusion criteria</title><p>Participants were excluded from the research if they had a history of alcohol and substance abuse, past psychiatric history, chronic hepatitis B or C or HIV-2 infection, vegetarian diet, chronic hypertension, and immunosuppressive illnesses (such as diabetes mellitus, chronic renal disease, malignancy, and sickle cell anemia). Other exclusion criteria were refusal to give consent to participate, pregnancy, presence of AIDS-defining illness, and default from one clinic visit.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>Enrollment and evaluations of HIV-infected antiretroviral therapy-na&#x000ef;ve patients</title><p>At the various enrollment centers, all the patients meeting the inclusion criteria were educated and counseled on the various aspects of HIV care and support by nurse HIV counselors, before the research objectives and protocol were explained to them, with emphasis on the voluntary nature of the study and assurance of the confidentiality of their data. After signing an informed written consent, the sociodemographic data and a history of illness were obtained from all patients, and they completed the Hospital Anxiety Depression Scale (HADS). 20 ml of whole venous blood samples was collected from each patient for plasma HIV RNA load; CD4+ T-cell counts; serum zinc, copper, and Vitamin B12 levels; and C-reactive protein at baseline. All the participants received daily doses of one capsule of a micronutrient supplement for 6 months and were reassessed with the same instruments and laboratory parameters at 6 months. Blood samples were also collected from ninety healthy HIV-negative volunteers and were assayed for serum levels of Vitamin B12, zinc, and copper.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-7"><title>Instruments of study</title><sec id="sec3-1"><title>Sociodemographic questionnaire</title><p>A sociodemographic questionnaire containing sociodemographic data and illness-related information was designed by the authors.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title>Hospital Anxiety Depression Scale</title><p>The HADS is a portable, easy-to-administer measure that screens for the presence of anxiety or depressive state of both clinical and nonclinical population. It consists of seven depression items and seven anxiety items and has been validated for use in Nigeria.<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> A score of 8 and above on either of the two components is regarded as case.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2-8"><title>Micronutrient supplements</title><p>The micronutrient supplement used in the study was a capsule containing a mixture of 11 vitamins (A, B1, B2, B3, B6, B12, biotin, folate, pantothenate, C, and E), 6 trace elements (selenium, copper, zinc, ferrous, molybdenum, and manganese), 2 electrolytes (potassium and magnesium), 2 essential amino acids (L-glycine and L-lysine), and 1 peptide (choline bitartarate).</p></sec><sec id="sec2-9"><title>Ethical certification of research proposal</title><p>The research proposal was reviewed and approved by the Institutional Health Research Ethical Committee of the two hospitals.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-10"><title>Data analysis</title><p>The IBM-SPSS version 21 (IBM SPSS Inc. 2012, Armonk, New York) statistical package was used for data entry and analysis. Data were analyzed by descriptive statistics including frequencies, percentages, means, and standard deviation. The Chi-square test was used to characterize the significance of the difference between categorical variables, whereas <italic>t</italic>-test statistics was used to characterize the significance of the difference between mean scores. All statistical evaluations were considered significant at <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, two tailed.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3"><title>R<sc>ESULTS</sc></title><p>A total of ninety participants were recruited for the study at baseline, but only 68 (75.6%) of them completed the study at 6 months. Twenty-two participants were unable to complete the study at 6 months for various reasons including loss to follow-up, default from a clinic visit, drop in CD4 count below 500 cells/&#x003bc;l, and pregnancy.</p><p>Majority of the participants at baseline were &#x0003c;41 years in age (62.2%), belong to female gender (76.7%), were of the Christian faith (81.1%), had at least 12 years of formal education (88.9%), currently unmarried (53.3%) as at the time of assessment, and gainfully employed (75.6%). There was no significant difference between the sociodemographic characteristics of participants at baseline and at 6 months as shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Sociodemographic characteristics of HIV-infected, highly active antiretroviral therapy-na&#x000ef;ve patients at baseline and at 6 months of treatment with micronutrient supplementation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">At baseline (<italic>n</italic>=90; 100.0), <italic>n</italic> (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">At 24 weeks (<italic>n</italic>=68; 75.6), <italic>n</italic> (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup>, <italic>P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age group (years)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02264;20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.284, 0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;21-40</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (60.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (42.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;41-60</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (37.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (31.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (76.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (56.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.432, 0.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (23.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (18.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Religion</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Christianity</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (81.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57 (63.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.336, 0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Islam</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (18.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (12.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marital status</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Married</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (46.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (33.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.101, 0.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Never married</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (28.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (22.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Widowed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (15.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (12.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Divorced/separated</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (8.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (7.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Secondary</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (51.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (38.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.391, 0.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Tertiary</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (37.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (26.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Primary</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (11.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (10.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Occupation</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Self-employed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (35.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (31.1)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.315, 0.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Government worker</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (23.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (17.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Private business worker</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (16.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (8.9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Not employed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (24.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (17.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The median serum levels of Vitamin B12, copper, and zinc of the HIV-positive, HAART-naive participants at baseline were significantly lower than those of the HIV-negative control group. After 6 months of supplementation, the levels of micronutrients among the HIV-positive, HAART-naive participants increased statistically significantly (Vitamin B12: <italic>P</italic> = 0.02, copper: <italic>P</italic> = 0.00, and zinc: <italic>P</italic> = 0.00), as shown in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Serum levels of zinc, copper, and Vitamin B12 of HIV-infected, highly active antiretroviral therapy-na&#x000ef;ve patients at baseline compared with the levels after 6 months of micronutrient supplementation and the levels of HIV-negative healthy volunteers</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nutritional variable</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIV-infected patients at baseline (<italic>n</italic>=90; 100), median (IQR)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value for HIV-infected patients at baseline versus healthy volunteers</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIV-infected patients at 6 months (<italic>n</italic>=68; 75.6), median (IQR)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value for HIV-infected patients at baseline versus those at 6 months</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zinc (ppm)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 (0.01-0.03)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 (0.21-0.27)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Copper (ppm)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.4 (&#x02212;0.5-0.03)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 (0.02-0.03)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vitamin B12 (ng/L)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0 (9.9-39.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0 (17.8-50.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 (0.00)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic>P</italic> values for median at baseline versus 6 months were calculated using independent samples median test; independent samples Moses test of extreme reaction was used to calculate <italic>P</italic> values for ranges at baseline versus 6 months. <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 is statistically significant. IQR - Interquartile range</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The point prevalence of anxiety and depression among participants at baseline was 23.2% and 23.2%, respectively. After 6 months of micronutrient supplementation, the point prevalence of anxiety and depression was 13.2% and 4.4%, respectively, as shown in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Prevalence of anxiety and depression at baseline and after 6 months of micronutrient supplementation among HIV-infected, highly active antiretroviral therapy-na&#x000ef;ve patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Noncase (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cases (%)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (%)</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">HADS depression subscale</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (76.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (23.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 (100)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (95.6)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (100)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>HADS anxiety subscale</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (76.7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (23.3)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 (100)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 months</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 (86.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (13.2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (100)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>HADS - Hospital Anxiety Depression Scale</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>A cross tabulation of the mean scores for anxiety and depression at baseline and after 6 months of micronutrient supplementation among the participants showed a statistically significantly lower HADS mean scores for anxiety (<italic>P</italic> = 0.003) and depression (<italic>P</italic> = 0.001), as shown in <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Cross tabulation of mean scores for anxiety and depression at baseline and after 6 months of micronutrient supplementation among HIV-infected, highly active antiretroviral therapy-na&#x000ef;ve patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline (preintervention)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After 6 months (postintervention)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic>-test</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HADS</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Depression</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.66 (4.91)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.12 (2.71)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.843</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Anxiety</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.40 (5.13)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.12 (4.28)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.970</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>HADS - Hospital Anxiety Depression Scale</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The initial HIV RNA load, CD4 cell count, and C-reactive protein median values were compared with the values obtained after 6 months of micronutrient supplementation and a drop was found in the viral load although the difference was not statistically significant (<italic>P</italic> = 0.32). There was a significant drop in the CD4 count (<italic>P</italic> = 0.00) and C-reactive protein levels (<italic>P</italic> = 0.04), as shown in <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T5" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Initial HIV RNA load, CD4+ T-cell count, and C-reactive protein of HIV-infected, highly active antiretroviral therapy-na&#x000ef;ve patients compared with those values after 6 months of micronutrient supplementation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Immunological variables of patients</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIV-infected patients at baseline (<italic>n</italic>=90; 100), median (IQR)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIV-infected patients at 6 months (<italic>n</italic>=68; 75.6); median (IQR)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> Baseline versus 6 months</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIV RNA (copies/mL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,105.0 (6346.0-955,514.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,227.5 (6,266.0-73,146.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 (0.35)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD4+ count (cells/&#x000b5;L)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">704.5 (600.0-880.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">561.0 (500.0-700.0)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRP (ng/mL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.4 (12.3-68.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.2 (8.8-46.8)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 (0.9)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic>P</italic> values for median at baseline versus 6 months were calculated using independent samples median test; independent samples Moses test of extreme reaction was used to calculate <italic>P</italic> values for ranges at baseline versus 6 months. <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 is statistically significant. IQR - Interquartile range; CRP - C-reactive protein</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title>D<sc>ISCUSSION</sc></title><p>This study examined the impact of 6-month micronutrient supplementation on viral, immunological, and mental health profile of a cohort of HAART-naive HIV-positive patients in Northern Nigeria and found a decrease in the experience of anxiety and depression and a reduction in C-reactive protein (a pro-inflammatory biomarker).</p><p>The sociodemographic characteristics of the participants at baseline did not differ significantly from the values at 6 months. Most participants were aged between 21 and 40 years, with a preponderance of female gender, similar to the findings from other related studies among adult HIV-positive population in Africa.<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></p><p>The median serum levels of micronutrients such as Vitamin B12, zinc, and copper of the HIV-positive, HAART-naive participants at baseline were significantly lower than those of the healthy HIV-negative control group. Similarly, the levels of micronutrients among the HIV-positive, HAART-naive participants increased significantly after 6 months of supplementation. This finding implied that the micronutrient supplementation was effective in improving the levels of these micronutrients in the HIV-positive participants.</p><p>The point prevalence of anxiety and depression among participants at baseline was 23.2% and 23.2%, respectively. After 6 months of micronutrient supplementation, the prevalence of anxiety and depression was 13.2% and 4.4%, respectively. The differences in both psychological parameters between baseline values and after 6 months of micronutrient supplementation were statistically significant. This finding is similar to those from other studies.<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref> Previous studies have shown that micronutrients, especially folic acid, Vitamins B6 and B12, zinc, and some amino acids, play a role in anxiety and depression. Low levels of folic acid and Vitamin B12 have been found in studies of depressive patients, and a targeted intake of these micronutrients may have prophylactic or therapeutic effects on some mental disorders including anxiety and depression, as suggested in this study.<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref><xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></p><p>The significantly lower prevalence of anxiety and depression after 6 months of micronutrient supplementation can also be viewed from the area of inflammation. Inflammatory processes have been found to play a role in the pathogenesis of anxiety and depression.<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Increased levels of C-reactive protein (a marker of inflammation) have been found to be associated with HIV disease progression,<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> which correlates with the increase in the prevalence of anxiety and depression as the disease progresses.<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref><xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> This study found a significant reduction in C-reactive protein levels after 6 months of micronutrient supplementation. The anti-inflammatory and antioxidant properties of micronutrients may reduce inflammation that occurs naturally with HIV disease and consequently reduce C-reactive protein levels. The reduction in the inflammatory processes also has the potential to reduce the prevalence of anxiety and depression.<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></p><p>This study showed that CD4 cell count dropped significantly over a 6-month period in spite of the micronutrient supplementation. Previous studies have shown that the CD4+ T-cell count is the most significant predictor of disease progression and survival.<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref><xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> The implication here is that micronutrients though useful in many immunological processes in patients with HIV/AIDS, may not be very effective in treatment when used alone in slowing the fall in CD4 count during the course of HIV infection. This supports the current recommendation that people living with HIV start antiretroviral treatment as soon as possible, which is being implemented in an increasing number of countries.<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> In some countries like Nigeria, the decision about when to start treatment is still largely dependent on a CD4 count even though the updated HIV treatment guidelines in Nigeria recommend starting antiretroviral treatment regardless of CD4 count levels.<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> The best approach to treatment should be to commence micronutrient supplementation once diagnosis is made and in the dire situation where HAART is not available and when available, should at least be used as an adjunct in persons taking HAART, as both therapies have been found to be synergistic.<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> This is more so, in view of the observation in this study that micronutrient supplementation improved other important outcome measures such as mental health. An improved mental health may translate into better lifestyle, higher quality of life, and improved drug adherence, with attendant multiplier effect on slower HIV disease progression. In addition, this study showed that the median viral load of participants decreased after 6 months of micronutrient supplementation, although the difference was not statistically significant. This finding is important when taking into account the fact that viral load increases over time in the natural history of HIV infection. The reduction in viral load observed in this study over a 6-month period of micronutrient supplementation may be related to the fact that micronutrients have antiviral activity either directly or indirectly through immune modulation.<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref><xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec1-5"><title>C<sc>ONCLUSION</sc></title><p>This study provides preliminary evidence that micronutrients positively influence the psychological well-being and reduce the experience of anxiety and depression that is common in recently diagnosed patients with HIV. The anti-inflammatory property of micronutrients was observed through the significant reduction in C-reactive protein levels. Micronutrient supplementation did not seem to significantly slow the decline in CD4 T-cell count during the period of treatment, and this supports the current recommendation to commence HAART as early as possible. The data obtained from this study are compelling enough to warrant further studies with more appropriate design investigating the role that micronutrients might play in reducing mental illness in people living with HIV/AIDS in the community.</p><p>Even with the availability of HAART in many African societies and the current recommendation to commence treatment as early as possible in the course of the disease, complementary micronutrient supplementation should be viewed as an important and integral part of HIV and AIDS treatment to improve the general, physical, and mental health status of people living with HIV.</p><p>The study is limited by the relatively small sample size and hospital-based study design, so findings cannot be generalized to the entire population of people living with HIV. The instruments were not administered to a control group who did not receive micronutrient supplementation, and diagnostic instruments for anxiety and depressive disorders were not used.</p><sec id="sec2-11"><title>Financial support and sponsorship</title><p>Nil.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-12" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>There are no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>We are grateful to the doctors and nurses at the Ahmadu Bello University Teaching Hospital, Zaria, HIV/AIDS Treatment and Care Centre, and the Saint Gerald's Catholic Hospital HIV treatment unit (CCRF HIV Centre) for their help during data collection.</p></ack><ref-list><title>R<sc>EFERENCES</sc></title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>National Agency for the Control of AIDS</collab><source>&#x02018;Nigeria GARPR 2015 Report. National Agency for the Control of AIDS</source><year>2015</year><date-in-citation>Last accessed on 2016 Nov 14</date-in-citation><comment>Available from: <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://naca.gov.ng/nigeria_garpr_2015_report">https://naca.gov.ng/nigeria_garpr_2015_report</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><source>UNAIDS &#x02018;AIDS info'</source><year>2016</year><date-in-citation>Last accessed on 2017 Sep 14</date-in-citation><comment>Available from: <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.unaids.org/en/regionscountries/countries/Nigeria">https://www.unaids.org/en/regionscountries/countries/Nigeria</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olaniyi</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Arinola</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential trace elements and antioxidant status in relation to severity of HIV in Nigerian patients</article-title><source>Med Princ Pract</source><year>2007</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>420</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17917440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bilbis</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Idowu</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Saidu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Njoku</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serum levels of antioxidant vitamins and mineral elements of human immunodeficiency virus positive subjects in Sokoto, Nigeria</article-title><source>Ann Afr Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20935424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kupka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Msamanga</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiegelman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mugusi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Selenium status is associated with accelerated HIV disease progression among HIV-1-infected pregnant women in Tanzania</article-title><source>J Nutr</source><year>2004</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>2556</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15465747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jamali</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Izadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalili</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Garmaroudi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlation between daily dietary micronutrients intake and mental health outcomes in Iranians living with HIV infection</article-title><source>J Assoc Nurses AIDS Care</source><year>2016</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>817</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27481230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fawzi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Msamanga</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiegelman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies of vitamins and minerals and HIV transmission and disease progression</article-title><source>J Nutr</source><year>2005</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>938</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15795466</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montero-Vega</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The inflammatory process underlying atherosclerosis</article-title><source>Crit Rev Immunol</source><year>2012</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23339672</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phospholipase A (2) enzymes in metabolic and cardiovascular diseases</article-title><source>Curr Opin Lipidol</source><year>2012</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22327613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pepys</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirschfield</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>C-reactive protein: A critical update</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2003</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>1805</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12813013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nordestgaard</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does elevated C-reactive protein cause human atherothrombosis? Novel insights from genetics, intervention trials, and elsewhere</article-title><source>Curr Opin Lipidol</source><year>2009</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19667982</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharrett</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kingsley</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Post</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Palella</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Visscher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>C-reactive protein is a marker for human immunodeficiency virus disease progression</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16401812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wium-Andersen</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000d8;rsted</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordestgaard</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Elevated C-reactive protein levels, psychological distress, and depression in 73, 131 individuals</article-title><source>JAMA Psychiatry</source><year>2013</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23266538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gimeno</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kivim&#x000e4;ki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Elovainio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De Vogli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Steptoe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Associations of C-reactive protein and interleukin-6 with cognitive symptoms of depression: 12-year follow-up of the Whitehall II study</article-title><source>Psychol Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18533059</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puustinen</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Koponen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kautiainen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000e4;ntyselk&#x000e4;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanhala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychological distress and C-reactive protein: Do health behaviours and pathophysiological factors modify the association?</article-title><source>Eur Arch Psychiatry Clin Neurosci</source><year>2011</year><volume>261</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20711599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liukkonen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000e4;s&#x000e4;nen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jokelainen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Leinonen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x000e4;rvelin</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer-Rochow</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The association between anxiety and C-reactive protein (CRP) levels: Results from the Northern Finland 1966 birth cohort study</article-title><source>Eur Psychiatry</source><year>2011</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21570260</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><source>WHO HIV/AIDS and Mental Health Report by the Secretariat; 20, November 2008</source><date-in-citation>Last accessed on 2017 Sep 14</date-in-citation><comment>Available from: <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://apps.who.int/gb/archive/pdf_files/EB124/B124_6-en.pdf">http://apps.who.int/gb/archive/pdf_files/EB124/B124_6-en.pdf</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Molecular virology and immunology of HIV infection</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2002</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12170257</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundgren</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The CD4 lymphocyte count and risk of clinical progression</article-title><source>Curr Opin HIV AIDS</source><year>2006</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19372783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pezzotti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><collab>CASCADE Collaboration</collab><article-title>Short-term risk of AIDS according to current CD4 cell count and viral load in antiretroviral drug-naive individuals and those treated in the monotherapy era</article-title><source>AIDS</source><year>2004</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15090829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lyles</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazmi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Detels</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinaldo</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Natural history of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 viremia after seroconversion and proximal to AIDS in a large cohort of homosexual men. Multicenter AIDS cohort study</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2000</year><volume>181</volume><fpage>872</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10720507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thi&#x000e9;baut</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellegrin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ch&#x000ea;ne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Viallard</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleury</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Immunological markers after long-term treatment interruption in chronically HIV-1 infected patients with CD4 cell count above 400&#x000d7;10(6) cells/l</article-title><source>AIDS</source><year>2005</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15627033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hinze-Selch</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollm&#x000e4;cher</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thiamine treatment in psychiatry and neurology</article-title><source>Fortschr Neurol Psychiatr</source><year>2000</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10758842</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akhondzadeh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerbarg</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutrients for prevention and treatment of mental health disorders</article-title><source>Psychiatr Clin North Am</source><year>2013</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23538074</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crellin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bottiglieri</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Folates and psychiatric disorders. Clinical potential</article-title><source>Drugs</source><year>1993</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>623</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7686459</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role for Vitamin B-6 as treatment for depression: A systematic review</article-title><source>Fam Pract</source><year>2005</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>532</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15964874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vitamin B12, folic acid, and the nervous system</article-title><source>Lancet Neurol</source><year>2006</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>949</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17052662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Moxey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Vashum</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>McEvoy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The efficacy of zinc supplementation in depression: Systematic review of randomised controlled trials</article-title><source>J Affect Disord</source><year>2012</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>e31</fpage><lpage>e39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21798601</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Araoye</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name></person-group><source>Research Methodology with Statistics for Health and Social Sciences</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Ilorin</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Nathadex Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>20</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>Federal Ministry of Health</source><year>2010</year><date-in-citation>Last accessed on 2013 Feb 08</date-in-citation><publisher-loc>Abuja</publisher-loc><comment>Available from: <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.nigeriaaids.org/documents/2010_National%20HIV%20Sero%20Prevalence%20Sentinel%20Survey.pdf">http://www.nigeriaaids.org/documents/2010_National%20HIV%20Sero%20Prevalence%20Sentinel%20Survey.pdf</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abiodun</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A validity study of the hospital anxiety and depression scale in general hospital units and a community sample in Nigeria</article-title><source>Br J Psychiatry</source><year>1994</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7866683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olisah</surname><given-names>VO</given-names></name><name><surname>Baiyewu</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheikh</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adherence to highly active antiretroviral therapy in depressed patients with HIV/AIDS attending a Nigerian university teaching hospital clinic</article-title><source>Afr J Psychiatry (Johannesburg)</source><year>2010</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chowta</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramapuram</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Udupa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of Vitamin B12 and folic acid supplementation on neuropsychiatric symptoms and immune response in HIV-positive patients</article-title><source>J Neurosci Rural Pract</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>362</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27365952</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fava</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacques</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Selhub</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Depression and folate status in the US population</article-title><source>Psychother Psychosom</source><year>2003</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12601225</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>World Health Organization</collab><source>Guideline on When to Start Antiretroviral Therapy and on Pre-Exposure Prophylaxis for HIV</source><year>2015</year><month>9</month><date-in-citation>Last accessed on 2019 Jul 14</date-in-citation><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name><comment>Available from: <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/hiv/pub/guidelines/earlyrelease-arv/en/">https://www.who.int/hiv/pub/guidelines/earlyrelease-arv/en/</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><source>Guideline on HIV Treatment in Nigeria 2016 Report</source><date-in-citation>Last accessed on 2019 Jun 25</date-in-citation><comment>Available from: <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://aidsfree.usaid.gov/sites/default/files/2016_nigeria_natl_guidelines_hiv_treat_prev.pdf">https://aidsfree.usaid.gov/sites/default/files/2016_nigeria_natl_guidelines_hiv_treat_prev.pdf</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sprietsma</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cysteine, glutathione (GSH) and zinc and copper ions together are effective, natural, intracellular inhibitors of (AIDS) viruses</article-title><source>Med Hypotheses</source><year>1999</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10459834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cunningham-Rundles</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McNeeley</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of nutrient modulation of the immune response</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2005</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>1119</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15940121</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>