<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since the launch of global efforts to accelerate initiatives to identify potent vaccines to control the scourge of Ebola, there have been growing controversies about the appropriate study design to adopt in achieving this.
 <xref rid="bib68 bib69" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>68,69</sup>
 </xref> Although RCTs are widely accepted as the gold standard to provide credible evidence for vaccine efficacy and subsequent licensing, experts have argued that RCTs are ethically inappropriate because of the lack of effective Ebola treatments, very high mortality rate, and almost comatose health systems in the affected countries. The experts proposed a parallel evaluation of different experimental interventions at different sites while concurrently documenting mortality rates after use of “standard” care.
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>69</sup>
 </xref> An emerging body of knowledge advocates a prospective cohort, stepped-wedge design. This design is used when ethical, financial, or logistic constraints prevent the use of individual RCTs.
 <xref rid="bib70 bib71" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>70,71</sup>
 </xref> In this design experimental vaccines/interventional treatments would be sequentially rolled out randomly to communities as they become available. Time periods before the community intervention serve as controls, and efficacy is estimated based on having concurrent preintervention and postintervention follow-up time periods.
 <xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>71</sup>
 </xref> This approach requires close interactions with major stakeholders, including regulators, investigators, affected communities, and the WHO. If backed with robust data collection, this design could be acceptable to regulators to support licensure. It also offers a unique opportunity for governments, manufacturers, Ebola-affected countries, and funders to work harmoniously together to develop a viable vaccine or treatment that could make the present Ebola epidemic the last in medical history.
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>62</sup>
 </xref> Apart from this approach, a ring-vaccination strategy is also planned to evaluate Ebola vaccine in an affected West African country. In line with this strategy, when an Ebola case is confirmed, the affected patient's family members, friends, neighbors, and community will be vaccinated, thereby forming a ring of resistance around the patient to prevent further spread of the infection. This strategy was successfully used to eradicate smallpox globally.
 <xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>72</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
