<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>HCMV reactivation and replication are typically linked to a strong inflammatory host response that involves numerous cytokines and chemokines, which often contributes to pathogenesis [
 <xref rid="B27-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B275-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">275</xref>]. Despite their roles as intrinsic and innate immune antagonists (see 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot3-viruses-12-00110">Section 3.3</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot4-viruses-12-00110">Section 3.4</xref>), the major IE proteins may also facilitate inflammation, most obviously by driving HCMV replication. However, IE1 and IE2 may promote inflammation even in the absence of viral replication [
 <xref rid="B223-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">223</xref>,
 <xref rid="B276-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">276</xref>,
 <xref rid="B277-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">277</xref>,
 <xref rid="B278-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">278</xref>,
 <xref rid="B279-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">279</xref>,
 <xref rid="B280-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">280</xref>,
 <xref rid="B281-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">281</xref>]. Consistent with this idea, the IE1-specific host cell transcriptome is largely characterized by downregulation of genes responsive to IL6-type cytokines and upregulation of ISGs normally induced by IFN-γ (see 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot1-viruses-12-00110">Section 3.1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B222-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">222</xref>,
 <xref rid="B223-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">223</xref>]. IE1-dependent gene activation proved to be independent of IFN-γ and other IFNs, yet required phosphorylated STAT1. Accordingly, IE1 induced phosphorylation, nuclear accumulation and binding of STAT1 to type II ISG promoters. Moreover, the repression of STAT3- and the activation of STAT1-responsive genes by IE1 turned out to be coupled. By targeting STAT3, IE1 rewires upstream STAT3 to downstream STAT1 signalling. Consequently, genes normally induced by IL6 are repressed while genes normally induced by IFN-γ become responsive to IL6 in the presence of IE1. Thus, IE1 merges two central cellular signalling pathways diverting cytokine responses relevant to inflammation and (neuro)pathogenesis [
 <xref rid="B222-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">222</xref>,
 <xref rid="B282-viruses-12-00110" ref-type="bibr">282</xref>].
</p>
