<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To determine the theoretical importance of a mosquito to RVFV transmission it is important to consider contact rates between vectors and vertebrate hosts. The amplification fraction estimates the number of infectious mosquitoes resulting from feeding on a particular host and can be utilized as an index to compare the relative role of various vectors in transmission. In the WNV system, the relative number of infectious (transmitting) mosquito vectors resulting from feeding on a vertebrate host was estimated by Kent et al. 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003163-Kent1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref> utilizing the following equation: 
 <italic>F
  <sub>i</sub>
 </italic> = B
 <italic>
  <sub>i</sub>
  <sup>2</sup>
 </italic> * C
 <italic>
  <sub>i</sub>
 </italic> where 
 <italic>F
  <sub>i</sub>
 </italic> = the relative number of infectious mosquitoes resulting from feeding on each vertebrate species 
 <italic>i</italic>, where B
 <italic>
  <sub>i</sub>
 </italic> = the proportion of blood meals from species 
 <italic>i</italic> and C
 <italic>
  <sub>i</sub>
 </italic> = reservoir competence. This equation was modified from Kilpatrick et al. 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003163-Kilpatrick3" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref> which estimated the fraction of WNV-infectious mosquitoes, 
 <italic>F
  <sub>i</sub>
 </italic>, resulting from feeding on each avian species, 
 <italic>i</italic>, as the product of the relative abundance, the vertebrate reservoir competence index, C
 <italic>
  <sub>i</sub>
 </italic>, and the mosquito forage ratio. Kent et al. 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003163-Kent1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref> found that the relative abundance of each avian species cancelled out when multiplied by the forage ratio, of which the denominator is relative abundance. 
 <italic>F
  <sub>i</sub>
 </italic> as defined by Kilpatrick et al. 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003163-Kilpatrick3" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref> was therefore reduced to the product of C
 <italic>
  <sub>i</sub>
 </italic> and the proportion of blood meals from species 
 <italic>i</italic>. Because the viremia-vector competence relationship used in this analysis is based on data from multiple mosquito species, Kent et al's 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003163-Kent1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>
 <italic>F
  <sub>i</sub>
 </italic> equation was modified to multiply by the mosquito's vector competence value (
 <italic>C
  <sub>v</sub>
 </italic>) to account for the differences observed in mosquito vector transmission competence across species. The modified equation is referred to as the vector amplification fraction (
 <italic>F
  <sub>vi</sub>
 </italic>) and provides a theoretical means to compare the role of various vector species in the transmission of RVFV.
 <disp-formula id="pntd.0003163.e001">
  <graphic xlink:href="pntd.0003163.e001.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </disp-formula>In the 
 <italic>F
  <sub>vi</sub>
 </italic> equation, the number of infectious mosquitoes resulting from feeding on a vertebrate host, 
 <italic>F
  <sub>vi</sub>
 </italic>, is equal to vertebrate host competence (
 <italic>C</italic>
 <sub>i</sub>), multiplied by the vector competence (
 <italic>C
  <sub>v</sub>
 </italic>), multiplied by the fraction of the total blood meals from host 
 <italic>i</italic> squared (
 <italic>B
  <sub>i</sub>
 </italic>
 <sup>2</sup>) 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003163-Hamer2" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003163-Kent1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. 
 <italic>B
  <sub>i</sub>
 </italic> represents the number of blood meals taken from a vertebrate host species divided by the total blood meals taken. 
 <italic>B
  <sub>i</sub>
 </italic> is unique to each mosquito species and is used as an indicator of exposure to RVFV and as an indicator of potential RVFV-infectious bites received by a host species, or taxonomic group 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003163-Muoz1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. Mosquito host feeding data from 39 studies were combined to generate a robust estimate of mosquito feeding patterns at the taxonomic resolution of Class and Order compiled into 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0003163.s003">Table S2</xref>. Vertebrate hosts fed on by mosquitoes lacking a competence index (C
 <italic>
  <sub>i</sub>
 </italic>) were assigned the closest taxonomic mean 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003163-PerezRamirez1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. Only mosquito species with over 40 recorded blood meals to calculate vertebrate host feeding proportions (
 <italic>B
  <sub>i</sub>
 </italic>) were included in this analysis. When vector competence data were missing for a given mosquito species, vector competence values were substituted based on the taxonomic subgenus average (
 <italic>Aedes</italic>- 
 <italic>Ochlerotatus</italic>: 0.15; 
 <italic>Culex</italic>- 
 <italic>Melanoconion</italic>: 0.04, 
 <italic>Culex</italic>: 0.11), genus average (
 <italic>Anopheles</italic>: &lt;0.01; 
 <italic>Psorophora</italic>: 0.18, 
 <italic>Mansonia</italic>: 0.07) or family average (
 <italic>Culicidae</italic>: 0.15). To include 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> in this analysis host-feeding patterns were estimated based on mosquito feeding patterns in Puerto Rico 
 <xref rid="pntd.0003163-Barrera1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>.
</p>
