<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Model variables and parameters are presented in 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000346-t001">Tables 1</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pcbi-1000346-t002">2</xref>, respectively. We use capital subscripts to denote the season (i.e., 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1000346.e049.jpg" mimetype="image" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula> for the breeding season and 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1000346.e050.jpg" mimetype="image" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula> for the wintering season) and lower case superscripts for geographical location (i.e., 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1000346.e051.jpg" mimetype="image" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula> for the breeding grounds and 
 <inline-formula>
  <inline-graphic xlink:href="pcbi.1000346.e052.jpg" mimetype="image" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula> for the wintering grounds). For a deep understanding of the system, we develop two versions of the model: (i) a deterministic system, with continuous state variables, and (ii) a hybrid framework that consists of discrete population variables, and stochastic demographic and transmission transition probabilities together with deterministic virus kinetics. The transmission dynamics within the continuous model are expressed as coupled ordinary differential equations and are useful in examining the underlying deterministic clockwork of the system. Not surprisingly, however, this framework often predicts biologically unrealistic fractional numbers of infecteds (Mollison's so-called “atto-fox” phenomenon 
 <xref rid="pcbi.1000346-Mollison1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>). Since we are particularly interested in the processes of extinction and persistence of AIV, we further refined our study by constructing a stochastic model, where the host population variables are integer-valued.
</p>
