<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Human use of preparations to prevent specific infections have been described since 1500 AD, beginning in China (
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">Needham, 2000</xref>) where smallpox was prevented by variolation, which is the introduction of material from scabs into the skin. In 1796 in the United Kingdom, Edward Jenner observed the immunity to smallpox of milkmaids having previously had natural infection with cowpox (
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">Jenner, 1798</xref>). He determined that inoculating small amounts of pus from the lesions of cowpox, presumably containing a virus related to vaccinia, into susceptible hosts rendered them immune to smallpox. The vaccine against smallpox was developed in 1798. The next phase of scientific developments involving the manipulation of infectious agents to extract suitable vaccine antigens took almost a century of research. Louis Pasteur’s work with attenuation by oxygen or heat led to live-attenuated chicken cholera, inactivated anthrax and live-attenuated rabies vaccines at the turn of the 20th century (
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">Pasteur, 1880</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">1881</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">1885</xref>). Alternative methods of attenuation using serial passage of 
 <italic>Mycobacterium bovis</italic> led to the live Bacille Calmette-Guerin (BCG) (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Calmette, 1927</xref>) vaccine, still in use today for the prevention of tuberculosis. Serial passage was also used in the development of yellow fever vaccines (
 <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr">Theiler and Smith, 1937a</xref>) which are grown in chicken embryo tissues (
 <xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr">Theiler and Smith, 1937b</xref>). Whole cell killed bacterial vaccines were developed when methods to treat and kill bacteria through heat or chemicals were established and whole cell typhoid, cholera and pertussis vaccines resulted at the end of the 19th Century. In 1923, Alexander Glenny and Barbara Hopkins developed methods to inactivate bacterial toxins with formaldehyde, leading to the diphtheria and tetanus toxoid vaccines (
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">Glenny and Hopkins, 1923</xref>).
</p>
