<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Many arboviruses are expected to shift poleward under climate change, due to increasing temperatures. Migratory birds with antibodies to WNV already arrive in northern Europe (Sweden) [
 <xref rid="B236-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">236</xref>], demonstrating that dispersal is not limiting arboviral activity in these locations. WNV is expected to increase in Europe, even in locations where it is already present, under future climate change [
 <xref rid="B209-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">209</xref>], and to increase in range and intensity in Canadian prairies under a range of future climate conditions [
 <xref rid="B211-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">211</xref>]. Increased drought expected under climate change has the potential to triple WNV cases over a 30-year time frame in locations where there is low human immunity [
 <xref rid="B229-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">229</xref>]. In contrast, increased rainfall has been predicted to lead to decreased WNV in some regions despite temperature increases [
 <xref rid="B208-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">208</xref>]. Increasing temperatures associated with climate change may have facilitated arboviral spread up elevation gradients. For example, JEV has recently expanded into Tibet where it was formerly thought to be excluded due to high elevation [
 <xref rid="B237-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">237</xref>]. RRV is expected to increase in temperate areas, but decrease in tropical areas where it is endemic due to increases in temperature [
 <xref rid="B167-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">167</xref>]. In contrast, MVEV is predicted to decrease in summer and autumn in Western Australia due to higher temperatures decreasing vector survival [
 <xref rid="B238-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">238</xref>]. Risk for BFV has also been assessed and was not expected to change much when both temperature and rainfall were included in the model [
 <xref rid="B169-viruses-11-01013" ref-type="bibr">169</xref>].
</p>
