<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In recent years, the role of the mosquito microbiome in vector competence has gained increasing attention. Mosquitoes are colonized with a multitude of microbial gut flora such as bacteria and fungi early in development [
 <xref rid="B108-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. The mosquito microbiome can be influenced by that of its parents (vertical transmission), sex, larval environment, life stage, geographic origin, etc. It is increasingly understood that an individual mosquito can be considered a single holobiont unit, where the mosquito, its microbiome, and a given arbovirus maintain a reciprocal tripartite interaction [
 <xref rid="B109-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. The relationship between the mosquito microbiome and arboviruses is largely mediated via the mosquito’s innate immune system, which is hypothesized to be stimulated to a basal level of activation by the presence of the microbiome [
 <xref rid="B109-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. Here, we review the midgut microbiome and its role in arbovirus vector competence and mosquito immunity, although this is by no means an exhaustive treatment, as mosquitoes contain microbiota associated with other discrete organs/tissues (e.g., salivary glands, hemocytes, reproductive tissues) [
 <xref rid="B108-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>,
 <xref rid="B110-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]. The interactions between the mosquito, microbiome, and arbovirus vector competence are especially relevant in the context of the above discussion of laboratory colonization. A recent study utilized 16S sequencing to determine the diversity, abundance, and community structure of the midgut microbiome of six geographically distinct 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> colonies (Australia, Cambodia, French Guiana, Gabon, Guadeloupe, and Uganda) of relatively low generations (≤F10), and demonstrated striking similarities among all [
 <xref rid="B111-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. Along with other analyses demonstrating that field caught (F0) mosquitoes (
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>, 
 <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>, and 
 <italic>Cx. quinquefasciatus</italic>) have disparate microbiome constituents compared to their colonized counterparts [
 <xref rid="B112-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>], these findings suggest that the laboratory colonization of mosquitoes can inadvertently alter their microbiomes. With respect to the effects of the microbiome on vector competence, substantial work has been conducted utilizing 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and DENV-2. For example, in an elegant study conducted on ROCK 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>, the role of microbiome in vector competence was demonstrated via the comparison of midgut titers of conventionally raised mosquitoes and aseptic mosquitoes in which the microbiome was depleted via a sterile housing and antibiotic cocktail treatment post-eclosion. This analysis demonstrated that, compared to their aseptically raised counterparts, conventionally reared mosquitoes demonstrated elevated levels of several Toll pathway-regulated antimicrobial peptides (defensin, cecropin, attacin, and gambacin) and had two-fold lower DENV-2 titers in the midgut [
 <xref rid="B113-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. Additional analyses demonstrated that silencing Cactus via siRNA (thereby transiently activating Rel 1, a transcription factor regulating transcription of Toll effectors) was associated with a four-fold reduction in midgut titers compared to control (GFP-dsRNA treated) mosquitoes. The contribution of the Toll pathway was further demonstrated by siRNA silencing of the upstream adaptor MyD88, inhibiting the activation of downstream Toll pathway elements and reducing by &gt;2.5-fold DENV-2 midgut titers, while silencing the adaptor Caspar of the IMD pathway failed to significantly alter midgut titers. These results highlight the functional importance of the Toll pathway in attenuating DENV infection [
 <xref rid="B113-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. As an emerging field within the vector competence literature, the role of the microbiome on the mosquito innate immune pathways and the consequences for vector competence are wide and varied. Individual bacterial species (
 <italic>Chromobacterium Csp_P</italic>, 
 <italic>Proteus</italic>, 
 <italic>Paenibacillus,</italic> and 
 <italic>Wolbachia</italic>) have been associated with decreasing the transmission competence of 
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> for DENV-2 [
 <xref rid="B109-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>,
 <xref rid="B110-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,
 <xref rid="B114-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>], while in other analyses, 
 <italic>Wolbachia spp</italic>. and 
 <italic>Serratia spp</italic>. have been demonstrated to increase the transmission of WNV (by 
 <italic>Cx. tarsalis</italic>) and DENV-2 (
 <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B115-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>,
 <xref rid="B116-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>]. Even more critically, given the role of the microbial flora in the basic physiology of individual mosquitoes (e.g., nutrient exchange, immunity, longevity, and reproduction) [
 <xref rid="B109-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>,
 <xref rid="B117-viruses-11-00867" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>], there could be major effects on vectorial capacity. As such, the role of the microbiome should receive increased attention in analyses of vector competence, and manipulation of the microbiome to alter competence could be a promising strategy for the control of arboviral diseases. Although standardization of the microbiome would be ideal, but is probably not feasible in most laboratories, samples should at least be collected from mosquito populations for which vector competence is reported in the literature.
</p>
