<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Apart from the survey in Athens, another questionnaire was also designed for a nationwide web-based survey aimed at eliciting citizens’ opinions regarding certain socioeconomic aspects of the mosquito problem. Its particular focus was to examine and then to validate at the national level a set of parameters related to: a) private prevention costs for IMS, and b) individual preferences among various mosquito control programs. The questionnaire was distributed through a popular meteorological data website (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.meteo.gr" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.meteo.gr</ext-link>) with a high daily number of visitors [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007467.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. For the purpose of our survey, a special banner appeared on the home page, from which visitors followed a link to the web survey. The banner appeared randomly to visitors, but a selection bias could arise due to (i) the non-representative nature of the internet population, and (ii) self-selection of participants (the `volunteer effect') which was possibly related to their interest in mosquito control. The first set of questions focused on the respondents’ knowledge of the Asian tiger mosquito. Subsequent questions concerned: (a) the current perceived level of nuisance during the day and separately at night, both rated using a 5-point Likert scale (nuisance impacts from the Asian tiger mosquito and from other species were estimated by attributing the nuisance during the morning and late afternoon hours to the former and the nuisance during the evening and night hours to native mosquito species), (b) the period (months/year) with significant mosquito nuisance, (c) the monthly household expenditure for private prevention measures, and (d) the main reasons for taking individual prevention measures (i.e. they had to choose between health risk reduction and nuisance reduction). The survey took place in September and October 2016 with a total of 1,220 responses from all over the country.
</p>
