<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The rapid development of diagnostic technology is an essential component of an epidemic preparedness strategic plan (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Accordingly, the technological landscape of the development of COVID-19 diagnostics is rapidly evolving, with new information being generated on a daily basis. Different platforms for open and fast data sharing have been contributing to this rapid diagnostic development, that include: fast availability of genomic data in public sequence repositories (e.g., 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gisaid.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">gisaid.org</ext-link>); open collaboration in preliminary data analysis using science community blogs and discussion forums (e.g., 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://virological.org/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">virological.org</ext-link>); publication of periodic reports by universities and international organizations (e.g., the WHO); real-time sharing of diagnostic validation results (e.g., 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.finddx.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">finddx.org</ext-link>); and particularly the use of preprint servers for early publication of research studies (e.g., medRxiv and bioRxiv). Recent studies have shown that these fast publication platforms are driving much of the debate about the COVID-19 pandemic, despite the intrinsic limitations associated with the unregulated sharing of research results at such fast pace (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Therefore, to ensure the integrity and quality of rapidly shared studies, the research community is already putting into practice several control mechanisms, at various levels (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>–
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). From researcher-led initiatives, that include the creation of open peer-review platforms for improving the quality of COVID-19-related preprints (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>), to publisher-led initiatives, such as the fast peer-review of research studies previously posted to non-peer reviewed platforms, these mechanisms will altogether contribute to guarantee the credibility of speedy information delivery during the pandemic (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>–
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).
</p>
