<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) is an infectious disease caused by a novel coronavirus which was first detected in Wuhan city, China, in December 2019 (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). The virus was named severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). The World Health Organization (WHO) declared COVID-19 a pandemic on March 11, 2020 (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Since the first SARS-CoV-2 case came to light, real time reverse transcription PCR (rRT-PCR) kits have been approved for use in Korea under Emergency-Use-Authorization (EUA). A total of 4 commercial SARS-CoV-2 rRT-PCR kits have been released to the market until 15 March 2020. As a result, 369,530 people were tested for SARS-CoV2 via rRT-PCR and 9,645 laboratory-confirmed COVID-19 cases were diagnosed nationwide until March 28 (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). The number of tests conducted was the highest in the world at the time and exceeded those conducted by China and Italy, the 2 countries with the highest number of COVID-19 patients. WHO emphasized the importance of laboratory diagnostics to control COVID-19 (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Unlike China and Italy, rapidly expanding laboratory testing capabilities may have played an important role in mitigating the outbreak of COVID-19 in Korea (
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). SARS-CoV-2 rRT-PCR is the most effective testing system available to counter epidemics when potent treatments and vaccines are unavailable. Therefore, commercial SARS-CoV-2 rRT-PCR kits have been approved by the EUA without clinical validation (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), because measures needed to counteract the COVID-19 pandemic require urgent deployment. However, all EUA kits should be prepared for clinical validation to obtain Ministry of Food and Drug Safety approval for the 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> diagnostic kit before the end of the COVID-19 pandemic. It is, thereby, essential to evaluate their performance timely when the COVID-19 is less likely to end. The purpose of this study was to analytically and clinically validate 4 commercial kits approved by EUA in Korea.
</p>
