<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Use of digital technologies, especially smartphone-based applications to identify the presence of infected cases, both active and recovered, has also been implemented successfully to manage the spread of COVID-19.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref51">51</xref>
 </sup> Ferrite 
 <italic>et al</italic>.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref52">52</xref>
 </sup> recently developed an application for contact tracing, see more in 
 <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 
  <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>
 </xref>. In this application, the main idea is to replace a manual contact tracing with instantaneous transmission of signals to and from a central server. Essentially, the SARS-CoV2 virus cases are directly communicated to the server, which enables recommendation of risk-stratified quarantine and social distancing measures in those now known to be possible contacts. This is done by preserving absolute anonymity of the infected person. In addition, tests can also be requested by symptomatic individuals through the developed application. One of the pros of such software-based technology is that it can easily be tuned to be more informative, for example, quarantining areas if the disease spread in that area becomes uncontrolled, quarantining specific flats or families, or performing second or third degree contact tracing if number of cases rise. Another advantage of contact tracing is the accessibility of technology with members of the community. In the past few years there has been a steady rise in the adoption of smartphones and mobile internet which could potentially facilitate a coordinated response during pandemics. One main limitation of contact tracing is that to harness the full potential of the technology, it is also necessary to increase the number of diagnostic tests. Another limitation such as privacy consideration also exists, which with changing time and circumstances are becoming more acceptable within the community members.
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref53">53</xref>
 </sup> The use of contact tracing however is still useful for members of a community to track the movement of people who came in contact with the infected, including the asymptomatic ones.
</p>
