<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para360">Rapid, cost-effective molecular techniques allow broad-scale screening of samples, and pathogen discovery could be a strategy in wildlife to pre-empt pandemic zoonotic disease emergence through early identification. This strategy might be particularly effective when enhanced by hotspot modelling, which allows targeting of specific regions with the highest spillover risks. Historically, most surveillance efforts have been designed to detect individual pathogens in natural reservoirs, vectors, or at-risk human or animal populations through use of individual (so-called singleplex) PCR assays or serology. However, the costs for multiplex PCR, microarrays, and high-throughput sequencing continue to fall, and thus these assays are increasingly used as primary techniques for syndromic surveillance and studies of microbial diversity and discovery.
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> The challenge with any of these technologies is determination of the relevance of a microbial signature. 5000 species of mammals and 10 000 species of birds are known, each of which probably has at least several unique endemic viruses. Therefore the total number of new pathogens awaiting discovery is probably far higher than the 2000 to 3000 characterised. When other vertebrate-associated microbes are also considered, clearly the unfocused application of high-throughput screening could rapidly exhaust resources without substantively reducing pandemic risk. Therefore, discovery efforts need to be directed toward reservoirs and vectors where human being–animal interfaces
 <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>6</sup>
 </xref> and hotspot modelling
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>3</sup>
 </xref> or other information suggest an increased risk of transmission. In the past few years, the abundance and availability of molecular sequence data have made possible the identification of unknown microbes in nature based on similarities to the sequences of known organisms, even in crude nucleic acid extracts (so-called metagenomics).
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> This approach has clear value during the early stages of emergence. However, sequence data became available while an epidemic was still in progress for the first time only during the West Nile outbreak in 1999, and then again during the 2003 SARS outbreak and the 2009 influenza H1N1 pandemic. This information was invaluable for rapid development of diagnostics, identification of the source of the infection, and pathogen discovery. However, the rapid sequencing and identification of new pathogens before large-scale spread remain a substantial challenge.
</p>
