<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To date, two phase-one clinical studies have been initiated to investigate the potential toxicity of GRFT in healthy populations [
 <xref rid="B61-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. The first study aimed to evaluate the safety of GRFT in a CG gel used vaginally for a single dose and then for 14 consecutive days in healthy women [
 <xref rid="B61-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. This was a two-part study with the first part consisting of a single-dose and an open-label design, and the second part consisted of a multiple-dose, randomized, placebo-controlled study design. During the second part, 30 subjects were administered a placebo and 30 subjects were given the GRFT gel. In this study, the pharmacokinetic behavior of GRFT was also analyzed by forming a time-concentration curve of GRFT in blood samples. However, rising dose tolerance was not studied because of the minimal systemic absorbance of GRFT, which was reported in preclinical studies. Although the official study results are not available yet, the Population Council website reported GRFT to be safe for vaginal use for up to 14 days with potent anti-HIV activity in cell-based assays and cervical explants up to 8 h after receiving the dose [
 <xref rid="B63-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. In 2014, another phase-one clinical study for GRFT started as an integrated preclinical/clinical program. This program, which was named PREVENT (pre-exposure prevention of viral entry), aimed to provide a comprehensive set of data to facilitate an informed decision on whether GRFT should progress within the topical microbicides pipeline [
 <xref rid="B62-marinedrugs-17-00567" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. This was a randomized, double-blind phase-one safety and pharmacokinetic study of GRFT enema administered rectally to HIV-1 seronegative adults who practice URAI. The number and frequency of adverse events, the blood concentration of GRFT, and changes in humoral antibody response were analyzed. This on-going clinical study will be completed in 2021.
</p>
