<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>DNA vaccine platforms, which are developed using plasmid-encoding viral antigens, could produce cellular and humoral immunity (for reviews, see [
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51–55</xref>]). A DNA vaccine-encoding SARS-CoV N protein has been developed to avoid antibody-dependent enhancement (ADE) phenomenon, which was reported with the antibodies of SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV S protein [
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. During ADE, the virus-specific antibodies that are released in response to vaccines help in the viral entry to host cells, thereby increasing incidence of infection [
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Additionally, protective effects are obtained with N-specific CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cells against other CoVs [
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. S protein as the main immunodominant antigen has been involved in the design of many DNA vaccines. A DNA plasmid encoding SARS-CoV-2 S protein was developed and the preclinical data revealed T-cells activation [
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Currently, INO-4800 construct (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>) is a DNA vaccine targeting SARS-CoV-2 S protein engineered by Inovio Pharma in similar way to their prior MERS-CoV vaccine and it is currently undergoing clinical studies [
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Furthermore, a recombinant adenovirus Type 5 vectored COVID-19 vaccine (Ad5-nCoV), which expresses S protein of SARS-CoV-2, has been developed by CanSino Biologics and has entered Phase II clinical trials (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Shenzhen Geno-Immune Medical Institute has two universal vaccine candidates for COVID-19 in the clinical phase, LV-SMENP-DC and pathogen-specific artificial antigen-presenting cells (aAPC; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Innovative COVID-19 synthetic minigenes have been engineered based on multiple conserved domains of structural proteins and a polyprotein protease, using lentiviral vectors (LVs) to express viral proteins and immune modulatory genes. In case of LV-SMENP-DC vaccine, these viral proteins and immune modulatory genes are able to modify dendritic cells (DCs) or to modify aAPC in case of COVID-19/aAPC vaccine.
</p>
