<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10">ACE2 can also be regulated in several cardio-pulmonary disease conditions like COPD, pulmonary hypertension, asthma and after viral infections with influenza H1N1, H5N1, H7N9 as well as in sepsis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. ACE2, potentially by degrading maladaptive angiotensin II and stimulating anti-inflammatory responses through the MAS receptor [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], has been shown to improve lung injury after viral infections of clinical injuries [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. Furthermore, ARDS is not prominent after RS virus infections, when the ACE2 is knocked out [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. In addition, recombinant human ACE2 has been tested in a pilot study in human ARDS and has been shown to reduce circulating interleukin-6 concentrations accompanied by increases of Ang 1–7 and reductions of angiotensin II [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Therefore, ACE2 might be crucial for the entry of CORONA viruses into the cells and, hence, infectivity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]; however, it might also mediate beneficial effects on pulmonary complications after infection [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. The fact that the major risk factor for adverse outcomes in COVID-19 is age, and ACE2 is downregulated in the aging population, argues in favor of its role in poor outcome of that risk group [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Furthermore, drugs like chloroquine and indometazine [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] as well as ACE inhibitors and ARBs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] have been shown to upregulate ACE2 in the human heart and in the systemic as well as pulmonary vasculature [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] with association to outcomes in heart failure [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], atrial fibrillation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>] and pulmonary hypertension [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. These findings highlight the complex interaction of COVID-19 and ACE2 inhibition. We would thus raise the hypothesis that pathophysiological conditions or drugs enhancing ACE2 expression might lead to greater infectivity, but, at the same time potentially reduce mortality due to lung complications (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).
</p>
