<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The pandemic has disrupted the agriculture activities and supply chains. The monetary loss occurred to the agricultural sector in India amidst the outbreak of COVID‐19 has been tremendous. The nationwide lockdown has put the future prospectus of the agriculture sector at stake. Amidst the uncertainty, the sector has been encountering several challenges as the labor mobility and movements of goods have been affected. Nonavailability of migrant labors is causing problems in harvesting activities. The north and west region encountered significant problems as wheat and pulses are not being harvested on time. There have been disruptions occurred in supply chains also because of the 21‐day lockdown in the country and subsequent bans on transportations and other activities. It is being predicted that the sector is likely to get a double hit due to the recent uneven monsoon and economic contagion that the sector is facing. As Ravi harvest season is approaching, farmers across the states are worried about their crops lying unharvested in the field. The cultivation of wheat, pulses, and mustard has already witnessed a decline in its productions owing to untimely and heavy rainfall. With the cases farmers and agricultural laborer are fleeing to their homes in the wake of this coronavirus lockdown, farmers income is going to be affected severely. Following are the points through which we will highlight the negative effect of COVID‐19 on Indian agricultural sector. First, the supply chain of agricultural products will be heavily affected due to the coronavirus lockdown in India. The 21‐day lockdown nationwide has created hindrance in the interstate movements of trucks carrying the essential agricultural commodities. Owners of warehouse and cold storage have complained over the lack of available labor supply in the agricultural sector. Second, the outbreak can also affect agriculture and allied activities through its effect on the poultry sector, the fastest growing sector in the Indian agriculture ecosystem. Apparently, India ranks third in terms of egg production and fifth in terms of the producers of broilers. However, due to the misinformation spread on social media and linking meat consumption to the coronavirus disease, the sector is facing huge losses on a daily basis. There has been a sudden fall in demand for poultry products, and farmers are facing lower prices for their poultry products. Third, as the restaurants and hotels are shut down, the demand for agricultural products are plummeting in India. As a result, there has been a fall in the prices of farm products by 15–20% in the time of this uncertainty in exports.
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="pa2157-note-0005">5</xref>
</p>
