<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Whereas most (&gt;90%) of children experienced mumps infection by age 20 in pre-vaccine era, number of mumps cases declined sharply after introduction of mumps vaccine globally (
 <xref rid="ijerph-17-01686-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Incidence of MuV infection among vaccinated school- and high school-age children increased in the late 1980s, followed by sustained decrease in incidence after children were recommended to receive a second dose of MMR vaccine at four six years of age [
 <xref rid="B41-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. However, resurgence of outbreaks of MuV infection continues to occur in developed countries in recent years [
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Based on the previous studies [
 <xref rid="B77-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,
 <xref rid="B83-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>,
 <xref rid="B85-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>], the vaccine has proven itself to be highly efficacious. What factors contribute to the occurrence of mumps cases? There are several hypotheses to explain the increasing number of mumps outbreak: (1) antigenic differences between 1967 vaccine strain and contemporary circulating strains might permit immune escape. However, this theory seems unlikely given that sera collected from individuals shortly after vaccination have been shown to effectively neutralize a mass array of genetically disparate virus strains [
 <xref rid="B122-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]; (2) waning of vaccine-induced immunity have been proposed as a likely contributor of mumps outbreaks [
 <xref rid="B88-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. Several studies have shown time after vaccination with declining concentrations of mumps virus-specific antibodies, decreased vaccine effectiveness, and increased risk of suffering from mumps virus infection [
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B123-ijerph-17-01686" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>].
</p>
