<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In just the past few years, antibody reactive with 
 <italic>Reston ebolavirus</italic> and 
 <italic>Zaire ebolavirus</italic> antigen have been detected in bats from the Philippines, China, Bangladesh, and orangutans from Indonesia (as previously mentioned). Though not conclusive evidence of the presence of these infections, the presence of these or related viruses are not entirely surprising considering the recent discoveries of 
 <italic>Marburgvirus</italic> and 
 <italic>Ebolavirus</italic> from congeneric species (
 <italic>Rousettus spp.</italic>) in Africa, and considering the large and overlapping geographic ranges for many of these bat species (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="viruses-06-01759-f003">Figure 3</xref>). 
 <italic>Rousettus amplexicaudatus</italic> bats in the Philippines were found seropositive for 
 <italic>Reston ebolavirus</italic> and implicating as the potential reservoir host for this virus in Asia [
 <xref rid="B64-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Additional efforts to identify more solid evidence for 
 <italic>Reston ebolavirus</italic> bat reservoirs in the Philippines and to understand the ecology of bats in this region are underway [
 <xref rid="B83-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. In Bangladesh, Olival 
 <italic>et al.</italic> found serological evidence to both 
 <italic>Reston</italic> and 
 <italic>Zaire ebolavirus</italic> in 
 <italic>Rousettus leschenautii</italic> [
 <xref rid="B63-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. This was the first evidence for a filovirus infecting wildlife in mainland Asia and suggested that an as-of-yet identified virus, perhaps genetically intermediate between 
 <italic>Reston</italic> and 
 <italic>Zaire ebolavirus</italic>, may be circulating in bat populations there. This Bangladesh bat species was also of particular interest because, along with several other frugivorous bat species in the region, it has close contact with humans and a potential transmission interface through a shared food resource (date palm sap) [
 <xref rid="B63-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="B84-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Yuan 
 <italic>et al.</italic> similarly found 
 <italic>R. leschenautii</italic> to be seropositive for 
 <italic>Reston</italic> and 
 <italic>Zaire ebolavirus</italic> antibodies in China, along with several other insectivorous bat species (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="viruses-06-01759-t001">Table 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="B80-viruses-06-01759" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. 
</p>
