<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
 <caption>
  <title>Key questions</title>
 </caption>
 <sec>
  <title>What is already known?</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>There has been an increase in the number of serious infectious disease outbreaks worldwide in recent years.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Rapid response time is critical for epidemic-prone diseases, and short delays to outbreak response result in preventable morbidity and mortality.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Risk analysis can be used to prioritise a response to an epidemic by examining the potential impact of the infectious disease outbreak.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>What are the new findings?</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>EpiRisk provides rapid risk prediction of outbreaks that will assist decision makers in epidemic management.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>Both pathogen and country parameters have a significant impact on the risk of infectious disease outbreaks in particular countries or regions.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>EpiRisk provides an individualised approach where specific input data for a country and disease can be used, rather than a standard ‘one size fits all’ approach that would be less generalisable.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
 <sec>
  <title>What do the new findings imply?</title>
  <list list-type="bullet">
   <list-item>
    <p>The development of a simple risk analysis tool will be useful for global epidemic control. This tool can be used to rapidly predict the risk of outbreaks, which is useful when planning and prioritising interventions or for epidemic preparedness.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item>
    <p>An appropriate and timely intervention can help governments and public health professionals prevent catastrophic outcomes.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
</boxed-text>
