<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There has been a growing concern whether the increased incidence of mortality or myocardial injury in COVID-19 patients with pre-existing CV disorders (HT, DM, and CAD) is due to the use of ACE-inhibitor (ACE-I) and angiotensin-receptor blocker (ARB) [
 <xref rid="B90-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>,
 <xref rid="B91-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>,
 <xref rid="B92-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. A question arose whether RAAS inhibition may increase risk of adverse outcomes of COVID-19 through upregulation of ACE2 and increase viral load. In animal models, increased expression and activity of ACE2 in various organs including the heart were found in connection with ACE-I and ARBs administration [
 <xref rid="B93-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>,
 <xref rid="B94-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. In contrast to animal experiments, there are few studies in humans regarding the effects of RAAS inhibition on ACE2 expression, showing conflict results [
 <xref rid="B95-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>,
 <xref rid="B96-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>,
 <xref rid="B97-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. Moreover, data showing the effects of ACE-I, ARBs, and other RAAS inhibitors on lung-specific expression of ACE2 in experimental animal models and in humans are lacking. Furthermore, there is no evidence providing a causal relationship between ACE2 activity and increased viral load in a critical way. On the contrary, there is abundant evidence of the mortality-lowering effects of RAAS inhibitors in CV disease. Abrupt withdrawal of those drugs in high-risk patients, including those who have heart failure or prior myocardial infarction, may result in clinical instability and adverse outcomes. Consistently, a recent propensity-adjusted retrospective study of 1128 patients with HT and COVID-19 evidenced a reduced mortality rate in patients with ACE-I and ARB therapies [
 <xref rid="B98-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. In response, a number of different societies [
 <xref rid="B99-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>,
 <xref rid="B100-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>,
 <xref rid="B101-jcm-09-01407" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>] suggest patients to continue their current ACE-I and ARBs therapies. Two trials of losartan are being conducted among COVID-19 patients who are naïve to RAAS inhibitors and are either hospitalized (NCT04312009) or not hospitalized (NCT04311177).
</p>
