<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32">In this study, we investigated the antiviral activity of seven Thai medicinal plant extracts against PRRSV by assessing the inhibition of PRRSV infection and replication in MARC-145 cells. The range of plant extract concentrations was determined based on their CC
 <sub>50</sub> values. 
 <italic>P. emblica</italic> extract inhibited PRRSV infection in MARC-145 cells and in vitro. 
 <italic>P. emblica</italic> extract at a concentration of 78 μg/ml inhibited PRRSV infectivity at a virus titer of 4.5 TCID
 <sub>50</sub>/ml (log
 <sub>10</sub>). In this study, 
 <italic>P. emblica</italic> extract showed the highest cytotoxicity to MARC-145 cells with CC
 <sub>50</sub> of &lt; 100 μg/ml. Therefore, the antiviral activity of other plant extracts were investigated in this study. We found that 
 <italic>T. triandra</italic> extract at a concentration of 1250 μg/ml significantly inhibited PRRSV infectivity at a virus titer of 3.5 TCID
 <sub>50</sub> (log10). While 
 <italic>T. triandra</italic> extract has been used as anti-inflammatory [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], anticancer [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], and antimicrobial agents against 
 <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], its antiviral activity, particularly against PRRSV, has not been investigated previously. Therefore, this is the first report to indicate that 
 <italic>T. triandra</italic> extract could significantly prevent the entry of PRRSV into MARC-145 cells. However, 
 <italic>T. triandra</italic> extract was not found to be effective in inhibiting PRRSV replication. All studied plant extracts could inhibit PRRSV replication when applied at high concentrations, as shown by the linear regression model from 24 to 72 hpi after incubation with PRRSV. 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>sappan</italic> extract at a concentration of 625 μg/ml could inhibit PRRSV replication as 72 hpi [virus titer 2.7 TCID
 <sub>50</sub> (log10)]. Although the antiviral activity of 
 <italic>C. sappan</italic> extract against the influenza virus [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] and the antimicrobial properties of 
 <italic>C. sappan</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] have previously been investigated, this is the first study to reveal the inhibitory activity of 
 <italic>C. sappan</italic> extract on PRRSV replication in MARC-145 cells.
</p>
