<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The P1 genes of PV-1 Mahoney and PV57δ were optimized according to 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">P. pastoris</named-content> preferred codon usage, synthesized (GeneART), and inserted into the pPink-HC expression vector multiple cloning site (MCS) using EcoRI and FseI (New England Biolabs [NEB]). The 3CD gene was also codon optimized for 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">P. pastoris</named-content> and designed to include a noncleavable sequence to reduce the potential toxic effects of 3C in a heterologous expression system (
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). The 3CD gene then was cloned into the pPink-HC expression vector MCS using EcoRI and FseI (NEB). For the coexpression of P1 and 3CD, a number of approaches were taken. For the dual promoter constructs, the region from position 1 of the 3CD pPink-HC to position 1285 was amplified by PCR, with the primers inserting a SacII restriction site at both the 5′ and 3′ ends of the product. The P1 expression plasmid was linearized by SacII (NEB), and then the 3CD PCR product was inserted into SacII-linearized P1 plasmid. Clones then were screened for directionality, ensuring the promoters for each protein were in the correct orientation. The PV57δ-2A-3CD plasmid was constructed through a series of overlapping PCRs. Briefly, the TaV 2A peptide sequence was inserted upstream of 3CD through overlapping PCR. A second PCR produced the PV57δ P1 with a 3′ nucleotide tail designed to be complementary to the 5′ sequence of TaV 2A. These two products then served to prime each other, in a third PCR, for 10 cycles prior to the addition of external primers. This PCR product then was inserted into pPink-HC using EcoRI and FseI (NEB). The RhPV IGR IRES (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>) (GenBank accession no. 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AF022937.1" assigning-authority="genbank" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">AF022937.1</ext-link>, nucleotides 6576 to 7103) was synthesized (GeneART). The PV57δ-IRES-3CD also was introduced by overlapping PCR using the same steps as those described for PV57δ TaV 2A. All PCR steps were carried out with Phusion polymerase (NEB) using the manufacturer’s guidelines.
</p>
