<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para420">PREDICT is active in 20 developing countries in emerging infectious disease hotspots and focuses on surveillance at human being–animal interfaces where cross-species transmission is most likely. Infection in the natural or reservoir hosts is often asymptomatic,
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">
  <sup>20</sup>
 </xref> and thus testing of seemingly healthy animals is essential, but might be resource intensive, and unproductive if done randomly. To avoid this issue, PREDICT uses a combination of risk modelling to target locations, interfaces, and host taxa, and computerised data collection and analysis and active wildlife field sampling at high-risk sites to collect and identify viruses that might transfer from wildlife and cause disease. The programme partners with national and local governments, in-country scientists, and other local specialists who are active in outbreak reporting, microbial characterisation, and pathogen discovery, in collaboration with other US Agency for International Development Emerging Pandemic Threats projects as appropriate. These partnerships are intended to ensure the longevity of the programme by building capacity in the most in-need regions. The programme's scale gives some indication of how feasible this type of approach is for identification of the many thousands of novel pathogens that are probably in wildlife globally. In the first two years of the programme, around 100 000 samples from 20 000 animals (mainly bats, rodents, and non-human primates) in 20 countries have yielded 150 novel viruses from families known to harbour zoonoses. These data will be used to further refine global hotspot mapping and modelling strategies and test hypotheses about zoonotic transmission. They will also be shared as open source information, after the appropriate country clearances, through an interactive application at 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HealthMap.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">HealthMap.org</ext-link>. In selected high-risk regions, the associations between viral diversity, biological diversity, patterns of human contact with wildlife and livestock, and changes in land use are being explored to decipher the rules that govern disease emergence.
</p>
