<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Both the M protein and SLO enhance virulence by decreasing the susceptibility of GAS to killing by immune effector cells such as macrophages and neutrophils [
 <xref rid="pone.0235139.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0235139.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Passive antibody treatment can decrease disease by two or more mechanisms. First, antibodies can promote opsonophagocytosis, which is consistent with our interpretation of results assessing the survival of GAS incubated with antibodies to the M protein and suspended in whole blood (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0235139.g002">Fig 2</xref>). In this regard, serotype-specific opsonic antibodies to the cell wall localized M protein have been known for decades to be important in the clearance of GAS and are typically protective [
 <xref rid="pone.0235139.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. In contrast, SLO is an exoprotein that disrupts the integrity of cholesterol-containing cell membranes [
 <xref rid="pone.0235139.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], which can induce caspase-dependent apoptosis in neutrophils, macrophages [
 <xref rid="pone.0235139.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], and epithelial cells [
 <xref rid="pone.0235139.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Antibody-mediated neutralization of SLO [
 <xref rid="pone.0235139.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] can decrease toxin-mediated apoptosis of immune effector cells and thereby increase the killing of GAS. Similarly, antibodies to the exoprotein streptolysin S enhanced GAS killing by neutralizing the cytolytic activity of the toxin [
 <xref rid="pone.0235139.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. Finally, active vaccination of non-human primates with an SLO toxoid (also containing other GAS antigens) induced non-opsonizing SLO-specific antibodies and decreased pharyngitis [
 <xref rid="pone.0235139.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Thus, the antisera to the M protein and SLO likely enhanced opsonophagocytosis (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0235139.g002">Fig 2</xref>) and neutralized cytolytic activity (
 <xref rid="pone.0235139.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), respectively.
</p>
