<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>HA is located on the surface of the influenza virus and it facilitates viral entry into the host cell by binding to sialic acid on the host cell surface.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr33-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>
 </sup> Avian-adapted strains of influenza virus preferentially bind to N-acetylneuraminic acid with α-2,3-sialic acids.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr34-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>
 </sup> These sialic acids are located in the gut and the digestive tract of avian species and in the lower respiratory tract of humans.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr35-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr36-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>
 </sup> HA is synthesized as polypeptide chain-encoded domains HA1 and HA2, co-translationally translocated into the lumen of the endoplasmic reticulum and eventually to the surface.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr37-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>
 </sup> The HA protein contains a cleavage site between the HA1 and HA2 domains, cleavage is essential for infectivity and allows the HA molecule to undergo an irreversible conformation change in acidic endosomes. This cleavage is performed by cellular proteases to create two subunit HA1 and HA2 domains linked by disulfide bonds.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr38-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>
 </sup> The cleavage nature of H5 HA proteins is achieved when virions are incubated with trypsin. This results in the conversion of HA to HA1 and HA2. The cleavage of HA can be blocked by a protease inhibitor.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr37-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>
 </sup> HA is expressed on the virion as a trimeric protein that is stabilized by residues on the HA2 region. The HA ectodomain is composed of two regions, a stem region and a globular head region.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr39-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>
 </sup> Neutralizing antibodies directed to the globular head of HA are critical for reducing viral infection and disease.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr40-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>
 </sup> An important factor affecting viral pathogenicity depends upon the sequence of the amino acids in the HA0 cleavage site.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr41-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr42-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>
 </sup> HA proteins from HPAIVs contain a multibasic cleavage site that is cleaved by the ubiquitous furin cellular protease.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr42-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr43-2515135518821625" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>
 </sup> In contrast, in low pathogenic avian influenza viruses (LPAIVs), that contain only one basic amino acid, the cleavage of HA is tissue specific, which results in a lower clinical manifestation in poultry.
</p>
