<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12">The production of AgNPs and their use as antiviral therapeutics against pathogenic viruses was reviewed by Galdiero et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">2011</xref>). Ag nanocomplexes with anionic linear globular dendrimers that were assessed against HIV replication pathway in vitro showed also good ARV activity with nonsevere toxic effects in comparison with nevirapine as the standard drug in positive control group (Ardestani et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2015</xref>). Polyvinylpyrrolidone (PVP)-coated AgNPs were found to be a promising microbicidal candidate for use in topical vaginal/cervical agents to prevent HIV-1 transmission (Lara et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124">2010</xref>). Inactivation of microbial infectiousness by AgNPs-coated condom as a new approach to inhibit HIV- and HSV-transmitted infection was proposed by Fayaz et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">2012</xref>). At treatment of HIV-1 infected cells with curcumin-stabilized AgNPs of 45 nm reduced replication of HIV by inhibition of NF-B nuclear translocation and the downstream expression of the pro-inflammatory cytokines interleukin-1β, tumor necrosis factor-α, and interleukin-6 was estimated and no similar biological effects were observed with curcumin alone and conventional AgNPs capped with citric acid (Sharma et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR197">2017a</xref>). Stable and crystalline AgNPs fabricated using the aqueous leaf extract of mangrove (
 <italic>Rhizophora lamarckii</italic>) with particle sizes ranging from 12 to 28 nm inhibited HIV type 1 reverse transcriptase activity (IC
 <sub>50</sub> of 0.4 μg/mL on the HIV-1) showing the promising potential to be used in the fight against HIV and other viruses of public health importance (Kumar et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122">2017a</xref>). AuNPs capped with sulfate-ended ligands that are able to bind HIV envelope glycoprotein gp120 and inhibit in vitro the HIV infection of T cells at nanomolar concentrations were reported by Di Gianvincenzo et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2010</xref>). AuNPs inhibiting HIV entry by binding with gp120 and preventing CD4 attachment were described by Vijayakumar and Ganesan (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR227">2012</xref>). HIV-1 peptides loaded onto AuNPs bearing high-mannoside-type oligosaccharides increased HIV-specific CD4
 <sup>+</sup> and CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T cell proliferation and induced highly functional cytokine secretion compared with HIV peptides alone and elicited a highly efficient secretion of pro-Th1 cytokines and chemokines, a moderate production of pro-Th2, and considerably higher secretion of pro-inflammatory cytokines such as tumor necrosis factor-α and interleukin-1β, suggesting that AuNPs that could simultaneously deliver HIV-1 antigens and high-mannoside-type oligosaccharides could be utilized as a superb vaccine delivery system (Climent et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2018</xref>).
</p>
