<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0035">Our study has several limitations. We did not simulate drug resistance due to non-adherence to ART regimens, and this should be evaluated in future studies. However, with the scale-up of DTG-based regimens, it is possible that drug resistance will greatly decline. Further, since AYA adherence is expected to be higher under LA-ART 
 <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, it is possible that drug resistance using LA-ART will be lower than oral regimens. However, when long-acting ART is stopped, it is followed by a long tail of subtherapeutic drug levels which could lead to drug resistance. In order to combat this, individuals who discontinue LA-ART may need to take daily oral ART until the LA-ART drug concentration falls 
 <xref rid="bib0039" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. This could decrease the proportion of individuals who adopt LA-ART as their primary therapy strategy, as well as increase drug resistance for those who do not take oral ART after discontinuation of LA-ART. To our knowledge, no LA-ART trials are currently planned in AYA populations. We administered LA-ART only to AYA because we predicted that they may receive the most benefit. Although other age groups may also experience declines in morbidity and mortality from LA-ART, the cost-threshold for AYA is likely lower than other age groups. LA-ART administration may therefore be rolled out to this priority population first, reflecting our model assumptions. Our model results are specific to Kenya, but we expect our overall findings can be applicable to other settings in SSA with generalized HIV epidemics. Lastly, we have presented the results from the programmatic perspective, i.e. the Ministry of Health, and included only costs incurred or averted by the health system. However, the societal perspective would capture client preferences and the trade-offs they would be willing to make for the convenience of LA-ART. LA-ART will likely reduce costs to patients who will require fewer clinical visits, and using a societal perspective would therefore increase the cost threshold of LA-ART for AYA in Kenya.
</p>
