<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Bicolored white-toothed shrews are widely distributed in central Europe 
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Corbet1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. They are usually found below 1000 m in elevation except in the Alps, where they may be found as high as 1600 m 
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Hilbe1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. These facts fit to the features of BD which has been reported to occur at elevations lower than 700 meters above sea level in Germany 
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Zimmermann1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref> and at higher elevations in the Alps 
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Hilbe1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. The northern distribution range of this species in central Europe is restricted to a line from Oldenburg, Bremen over the district of Salzwedel to Potsdam, southern Berlin (in Germany) and to Warsaw and Bialystok (in Poland) 
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Richter1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. Investigations by Martens and Gillandt in 1978/79 
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Martens1" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref> and by Weber in 1983 
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Weber1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref> revealed a further extension of the northern distribution of 
 <italic>C. leucodon</italic> during the last decades. Whereas this northern distribution border fits well to the occurrence of BD in endemic regions, it is the limited distribution of BD itself which is in contrast to the wide distribution of bicolored white-toothed shrews in Europe, especially in western and eastern Europe, where no clearly confirmed BD cases have been reported so far. In western Europe 
 <italic>C. leucodon</italic> is distributed in the eastern parts of France and in eastern Europe it populates habitats of the countries of the Balkan peninsula, Poland and Ukraine 
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Herter1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. Investigations by Richter 
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Richter1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref> in the eastern part of Germany have shown that the bicolored white-toothed shrew is more common in regions of the lowlands of Thuringia and Saxony-Anhalt. These regions fit exactly to the distribution of BD in horses and sheep (especially in eastern Germany the maps of distribution of BD - shown by Dürrwald, see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093659-g002">Figure 2</xref> of reference 
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Drrwald4" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref> - fit exactly to the distribution frequencies of 
 <italic>C. leucodon</italic> - data by Richter, see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0093659-g005">Figure 5</xref> of reference 
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Richter1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>). In other regions especially in northwestern Germany 
 <italic>C. russula</italic> is more common and BD is rare. 
 <italic>C. russula</italic> (greater white-toothed shrew) is mainly distributed westwards of the Rhine and southwards of the Alps, but occurs also between Rhine and Elbe together with 
 <italic>C. leucodon</italic>. 
 <italic>C. suaveolens</italic> (lesser white-toothed shrew) is widely distributed in the eastern part of Europe and not competing with 
 <italic>C. leucodon</italic> in the endemic areas of BD in Thuringia and Saxony-Anhalt, but well-distributed in Bavaria, where 3 
 <italic>Crocidura</italic> species exist 
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Kraft1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Kraft2" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>. Regions of Bavaria in which BD occurs fit to the distribution area of 
 <italic>C. leucodon</italic>
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Reichelt1" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>. Mean annual precipitation lower than 900 mm, mean annual temperatures of 8°C, elevation lower than 350 m, low forest cover and urban environment were determined to be optimal habitats for 
 <italic>C. leucodon</italic>
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Encarnao1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>. In 2012 two BDV positive bicolored white-toothed shrews were found in farms in Bavaria with recent cases of BD in horses 
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Bourg1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. BDV sequences from shrew and horse of the same stable were identical indicating transmission between both species 
 <xref rid="pone.0093659-Bourg1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. Despite the wider distribution of 
 <italic>C. leucodon</italic> compared to the BD endemic areas the population density of this species may play a role in virus transmission. Shrews found in southern Saxony-Anhalt were dominated by 
 <italic>C. russula</italic> (this study) which may explain the low detection rate of BDV.
</p>
