<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The relationship between health and the economy is bidirectional, whereby economic growth enables funding in investments that improve health; and a healthy population contributes to and enhances an economy. These benefits of vaccinations and other public health interventions including sanitation, clean water, and antibiotics, are important for social as well as economic reasons. It has been suggested that the economic impact of vaccines should be considered more broadly than just the averted healthcare costs from prevented illness episodes and associated carer costs (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Deogaonkar et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Barnighausen et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Bonanni et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Gessner et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr">Wilder-Smith et al., 2017</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Bärnighausen et al. (2011)</xref>, set out a framework to consider productivity gains measured by: outcome and behavior; community health and economic externalities; risk reduction; and health gains. Healthy children demonstrate improved educational attainment at school through better attendance and better cognitive performance (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Barham and Calimeria, 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">Bloom et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Deogaonkar et al., 2012</xref>). The impact of hearing loss from mumps, rubella or pneumococcal infections, or visual impairment from measles may require specific educational support, whereas the cognitive deficits from those childhood infections may require substantial remedial input. As more children survive to adulthood, a larger adult workforce is available, who when healthy can work for longer and more productively both physically and mentally (
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Bloom and Canning, 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Bloom et al., 2005</xref>); though to date this has been observed largely following other health improvements, not vaccination specifically (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Jit et al., 2015</xref>). As a result of vaccination healthy and economically successful populations have lower fertility rates and smaller families (
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">Sah, 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Andre et al., 2008</xref>). With improved health and therefore life expectancy, there is a wider effect on families who may choose to invest more money in their future, for example to enhance their education or through savings (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">Jit et al., 2015</xref>). Overall, vaccine programs should be viewed as an investment in human capital, providing enduring impact on economies worldwide.
</p>
