<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A working list of RNA viruses associated with human pathologies was obtained from the ViralZone web resource (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://viralzone.expasy.org/all_by_species/678.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://viralzone.expasy.org/all_by_species/678.html</ext-link>) 
 <xref rid="pone.0078122-Hulo1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. For each virus, we attempted to gather as many sequences as available covering a region of the genome with extensive genetic variation, based on prior knowledge or phylogenetic studies in the literature. When available, we used curated virus-specific sequence databases. HIV-1 
 <italic>nef</italic> gene sequences were obtained from the Los Alamos National Laboratory (LANL) HIV Sequence database (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hiv.lanl.gov/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.hiv.lanl.gov/</ext-link>) using subtype-specific search queries excluding sequences annotated as recombinants, and restricting the result to one sequence per patient. Further screening for HIV-1 recombinant sequences was carried out using SCUEAL (Subtype Classification Using Evolutionary ALgorithms) 
 <xref rid="pone.0078122-KosakovskyPond1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. Hepatitis C virus E1 sequences were obtained from the LANL HCV sequence database (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hcv.lanl.gov" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://hcv.lanl.gov</ext-link>) 
 <xref rid="pone.0078122-Kuiken1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref> using genotype-specific search queries excluding recombinants. Search results were reduced to one sequence per patient based on patient clone annotation in the sequence headers using a custom Python script, as this functionality was not available for the LANL HCV sequence database. Influenza A virus hemagglutinin (HA) sequences were obtained from the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID) Influenza Research Database (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fludb.org" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.fludb.org</ext-link>), using subtype-specific search queries excluding isolates from non-human hosts and laboratory strains.
</p>
