<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The S protein is a trimeric spike glycoprotein located on the envelope of the virus [
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Initially, the S protein is in a metastable prefusion state. The S1 subunit triggers viral envelope fusion with the cell membrane via the endosomal pathway. This results in shedding of S1 from the prefusion conformation and allows S2 to attain a stable postfusion state [
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19–21</xref>]. The cleavage of S protein of SARS-CoV-1 is triggered by transmembrane protease serine-2 (TMPRSS2) and cathepsin. However, the exact molecules facilitating endocytosis of SARS-CoV-2 are yet to be fully elucidated [
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Furthermore, clathrin-dependent and clathrin-independent endocytosis may also be involved in mediating the viral entry [
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Following cellular entry, the virus then releases the genome RNA into the host cell which get translated into viral replicase polyproteins pp1a and 1ab [
 <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. These proteins are further cleaved into small particles by viral proteinases. The polymerase produces more subgenomic mRNAs in a serial manner that are ultimately translated into the relevant viral proteins that are assembled in the endoplasmic reticulum and Golgi apparatus, along with the genome RNA into virions. The virions are then released via vesicles out of the cell (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) [
 <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Evidence regarding the affinity of SARS-CoV-2 to ACE2 binding is inconclusive. One study suggests that SARS-CoV-2 S proteins bind to ACE2 with 10 to 20 times higher affinity compared with SARS-CoV-1, whereas another study reported that SARS-CoV-2 receptor biding domain binds to ACE2 with a similar affinity to the SARS-CoV-1 [
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Although human autopsy studies have shown that SARS-CoV-1 RNA is seen only in cells expressing ACE2, there is some evidence that the RNA material is also seen in cells lacking ACE2, indicating that there may be factors other than ACE2 playing a role in entry of these coronaviruses into the host cell [
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Nevertheless, there is sufficient evidence in favor of ACE2 as the mediator of viral entry into alveolar cells, and local harmful activation of the RAAS, such that treatment with recombinant ACE2 is being considered as a serious therapeutic option.
</p>
