<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Interferons (IFNs) are polypeptide molecules with various biological functions [
 <xref rid="B94-vetsci-02-00456" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. They play an important role in mediating antiviral and antigrowth responses and in immune response modulation [
 <xref rid="B95-vetsci-02-00456" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. They can be divided into type I and type II IFNs, both of which have antiviral properties. Type I IFNs, including IFN-α, IFN-β, and IFN-ω, are produced by virus-infected cells [
 <xref rid="B94-vetsci-02-00456" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>,
 <xref rid="B96-vetsci-02-00456" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>], whereas type II IFN, consisting of only IFN-γ, is produced by activated T lymphocytes and natural killer cells in response to recognition of virus-infected cells [
 <xref rid="B97-vetsci-02-00456" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. IFNs act in an autocrine or paracrine fashion [
 <xref rid="B98-vetsci-02-00456" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>] inducing an anti-viral state in non-infected cells. IFNs bind to specific cell surface receptors and result in the transcription of IFN-stimulated genes. The products of these genes are proteins with potent anti-viral properties that interfere with various stages of viral replication [
 <xref rid="B98-vetsci-02-00456" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. Several studies suggest that retroviral protein synthesis is not affected by IFNs and therefore conclude that the antiviral activity of IFNs is mainly related to interference with later stages of the viral replication cycle such as virion assembly and release [
 <xref rid="B94-vetsci-02-00456" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>,
 <xref rid="B99-vetsci-02-00456" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. Interferons also trigger virus-infected cells to undergo apoptosis by activating gene expression for apoptosis [
 <xref rid="B97-vetsci-02-00456" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>,
 <xref rid="B99-vetsci-02-00456" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>], which prevents the spread of virus from infected cells and aids in the clearance of virus infection [
 <xref rid="B97-vetsci-02-00456" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. Human IFNs have been manufactured by recombinant DNA technology and are available commercially. Recombinant feline IFN-ω is on the market in Japan, Australia, and many European countries and is licensed for use in cats and dogs.
</p>
