<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To evaluate the internalization of DENV NS1 proteins in HPMEC, we used Western blot and IFA. Briefly, confluent monolayers (pre-chilled for 10 minutes at 4°C) grown on culture plates and/or glass coverslips were exposed to 10 μg/ml of different NS1 proteins (as indicated above) and incubated for 45 minutes at 4°C to facilitate NS1 protein adsorption but not internalization. Cultures were then transferred to 37°C to allow protein internalization. For the internalization kinetic experiments, cells were washed twice with PBS, before transfer to 37°C, to remove any unbound NS1. One hour later (or at the indicated times for kinetic analysis), cell supernatants were removed, and cell monolayers were rinsed 3X with PBS and detached with trypsin-EDTA, which also removed any surface-bound, non-internalized NS1 proteins from the outer cell membrane. Cells were pelleted and lysed using SDS gel loading buffer, then the cell lysate was separated using an SDS-PAGE gradient gel (4–20%) and visualized by Western blot with primary anti-NS1 mAbs (1G5.3 and 1H7.4, obtained from Paul Young, University of Queensland, Australia) [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007938.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] and secondary anti-mouse antibody conjugated to Alexa 750 (ab175740, Abcam). α-Tubulin was used as a protein loading control (anti-α-tubulin ab4074, Abcam), and Rab5 was used as an early endosome marker (ab18211, Abcam). Anti-rabbit IgG conjugated to Alexa 680 was used as secondary antibody (ab175773, Abcam). Images were acquired and processed using a LI-COR Odyssey system and ImageJ software, respectively. For the internalization Western blot, at the indicated time post temperature shift, cell monolayers were rinsed 3X with PBS and then 2X with pre-chilled acid wash buffer (glycine 100 mM, and 150mM NaCl, pH 2.5), which removed any surface-bound, non-internalized NS1 proteins from the outer cell membrane. Cells were then collected in western blot sample buffer.
</p>
