<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The MERS-CoV agent is a betacoronavirus first described in September 2012 from a patient in Saudi Arabia [
 <xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. It is related to the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS) that from 2002 to 2003 resulted in over 8000 infections in 17 countries (including Macau and Hong Kong) with a 10% fatality rate [
 <xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In the case of SARS, bats were confirmed as the natural reservoir although the introduction of the agent to humans was likely through contact with animals (masked palm civets) held in southern Chinese markets where the disease was first recognized in Nov 2002 [
 <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus also likely represents a zoonotic agent that infected humans via viral adaptions or a species jump through an intermediate host. Bats are suspected as the ultimate reservoir with camel infection as the most likely link to human infection, but these theories at present are unproven. The majority of cases are associated with severe disease of the lower respiratory tract resulting in pneumonia and multi-organ failure; the most susceptible to clinical disease and death are those with pre-existing co-morbidities [
 <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Other chronic conditions have been reported in 96% of clinical cases including diabetes, hypertension, heart disease and kidney disease. It is unclear whether persons with these specific conditions are disproportionately infected or have more severe disease. To 30 November 2013, as reported by the US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) and the World Health Organization (WHO), ten countries have reported 160 clinical cases with 68 deaths. All cases and transmissions have been associated with the Arabian Peninsula where the vast majority of cases and deaths have occurred; travel of infected patients with limited person-to-person transmission are responsible for cases reported elsewhere. Although it appears that there is limited person-to-person transmission, clusters of cases have been described. A cluster of 21 human cases occurred associated with four hospitals in Eastern Saudi Arabia that was ultimately sourced to one community-acquired case [
 <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Updated MERS-CoV rapid risk assessments are routinely published by the European Centres for Disease Control (ECDC). Regarding actions with respect to blood safety, careful surveillance is required as risk involving MERS-CoV is rapidly evolving at present. To date, only one study has reported testing blood donors including 110 in Saudi Arabia; all were nonreactive for MERS-CoV neutralizing antibodies [
 <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. There is no evidence of transfusion transmission.
</p>
