<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Researchers around the world are working hard to develop a potential vaccine candidate so as to stop the deadly pandemic caused by SARS-CoV-2. However, vaccine development is not an easy task, as a number of successful clinical trials are required before approval for patients. Different approaches are being utilized for designing a specific vaccine targeting either the structural proteins or viral replication process, which eventually results in the inhibition of viral growth and its further transmission. The common strategies involve the use of live attenuated vaccine (LAV), inactivated virus, subunit vaccines, monoclonal antibody vaccine, virus vectors, protein vaccines, and DNA/RNA-based vaccines (
 <xref rid="B171" ref-type="bibr">171</xref>–
 <xref rid="B174" ref-type="bibr">174</xref>). There are numerous subunit vaccines targeting all or a part of S protein that have already been tested for SARS and MERS in animal models (
 <xref rid="B175" ref-type="bibr">175</xref>) and could be potential candidates for testing against SARS-CoV-2. A recent pilot study with a purified inactivated SARS-CoV-2 virus vaccine displayed very promising outcomes in different animal models. The neutralizing antibodies generated after vaccination were able to effectively target 10 different strains of SARS-CoV-2 without developing any ADE of infection (
 <xref rid="B176" ref-type="bibr">176</xref>). Various randomized controlled trials (NCT04327206, NCT04328441) are also underway to evaluate the effectiveness of the BCG vaccine against SARS-CoV-2 for healthcare professionals. An adenovirus vector-based vaccine candidate, ChAdOx1 (presently AZD1222), developed by Oxford University (licensed to AstraZeneca) for use against SARS-CoV-2 has been reported to activate both the humoral and cell-mediated immune response when tested in rhesus monkey (
 <xref rid="B177" ref-type="bibr">177</xref>). The phase I clinical trial to confirm its potency is also in progress (NCT04324606). Another group has followed a similar approach by using a recombinant adenovirus type 5 (Ad5-nCoV) vector-based vaccine for COVID-19. The full report from the phase I clinical trial (NCT04313127) of Ad5-nCoV shows that it is very effective in generating both humoral and rapid T-cell response post immunization. The group is now ready for the next clinical trial phase to further strengthen the effectiveness of the Ad5-nCoV vaccine (
 <xref rid="B178" ref-type="bibr">178</xref>). It should be noted that there are potential risks associated with the usage of live attenuated viruses, for example, complications resulting in lung damage by infiltrating eosinophils, as seen in 
 <italic>in vivo</italic> models (
 <xref rid="B179" ref-type="bibr">179</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B180" ref-type="bibr">180</xref>). However, eosinophil immunopathology due to SARS-CoV vaccine could be reduced by using TLR4 agonist as an adjuvant (
 <xref rid="B181" ref-type="bibr">181</xref>). Viral neutralizing antibodies specifically targeting various regions of S, i.e., S1-RBD, S1-NTD, or the S2 region, and blocking the interaction of virus with the receptor are well-known for SARS and MERS (
 <xref rid="B182" ref-type="bibr">182</xref>). These neutralizing antibodies could prove to be the best and potential candidate for cross-neutralization of SARS-CoV-2. Despite being structurally related, some of the SARS-CoV neutralizing monoclonal antibodies failed to interact with the S-protein of SARS-CoV-2, which could be attributable to the substantial differences in their RBD (
 <xref rid="B183" ref-type="bibr">183</xref>). A recent study reported the presence of high titres of neutralizing anti-S-RBD IgG antibodies, but no antibodies were detected against the N protein in recovered COVID-19 patients, suggesting that anti-S IgG persists longer than does anti-N IgG. Along with the humoral immune response, they also observed an S protein-specific T cell-population producing IFN-γ, which further contributes to conferring protective immunity against SARS-CoV-2 infection (
 <xref rid="B184" ref-type="bibr">184</xref>). Recently, a monoclonal antibody (47D11) has been identified from 51 SARS-Spike hybridomas that targets the conserved S-RBD region (residue 338–506) and therefore can very effectively neutralize SARS-CoV-2 along with SARS-CoV (
 <xref rid="B185" ref-type="bibr">185</xref>). On similar lines, a group has isolated a single-domain antibody from a phage display library targeting the S-RBD region of SARS-CoV-2. The fully humanized single-domain antibody was able to neutralize the virus by interacting with a cryptic epitope in S protein (
 <xref rid="B186" ref-type="bibr">186</xref>). These mAb and single-domain antibodies could be used to treat as well as to design quick diagnostic kits for COVID-19.
</p>
