<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="Tab4">
 <label>Table 4</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Solutions to PEARLES challenges encountered</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <bold>Political and economic solutions identified</bold>
    </td>
    <td>
     <bold>Challenges encountered</bold>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Strengthen global collaborations and coalitions</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Ensure global political awareness of infectious disease threats.</p>
     <p>  -Strengthen collaborations between international organisations, national leaders, public, private and local stakeholders.</p>
     <p>  -WHO to set out overarching research governance framework for research in outbreaks.</p>
     <p>  -Integrate research in international outbreak response.</p>
     <p>  -Ensure interventions are supported by all stakeholders, including national and local stakeholders.</p>
     <p>  -Close collaboration between local and international researchers from research inception, tied to capacity building and be genuinely collaborative.</p>
     <p>  -Research led by national teams.</p>
     <p>  -Invest in national public health research institutes globally, targeting epidemic-prone regions.</p>
    </td>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Geopolitical</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Ineffective global coordination and collaboration.</p>
     <p>  -Research not integrated into national outbreak response.</p>
     <p>  -Establishing outbreak as international concern may depend on the ability of LMICs to raise international interest.</p>
     <p>  -Lack of compliance with WHO core capacities to detect, assess, report and respond.</p>
     <p>  -Need for political approval.</p>
     <p>  -Political unrest.</p>
     <p>  -Research priorities dictated by funding bodies.</p>
     <p>  -Lack of communication and engagement between stakeholders.</p>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Funding</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Establish dedicated funding sources in inter-epidemic times.</p>
     <p>  -Establish international agreements on financial mechanisms for rapid release of funding and for addressing clinical trial liability coverage.</p>
     <p>  -National governments to strengthen investments in preparedness and response.</p>
     <p>  -Coordinate funding to ensure it is rapid and sufficient by using international coalitions and economies of scale.</p>
     <p>  -Ensure sufficient, specific and flexible funding for research staff to avoid healthcare opportunity costs.</p>
     <p>  -Explore industry funding to complement public funding.</p>
     <p>  -Provide appropriate compensation for participation in research.</p>
    </td>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Funding</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Insufficient funding resources.</p>
     <p>  -Delays in identifying funding.</p>
     <p>  -Weak funding mechanism and implementation for research in emergencies and neglected and tropical disease.</p>
     <p>  -Funding not mobilisable at sufficient pace.</p>
     <p>  -Limited national health budgets dedicated to research response efforts.</p>
     <p>  -Opportunity costs and competing interests.</p>
     <p>  -Over-reliance on unpaid staff doing research in addition to normal duties, with risk to care, staff and research.</p>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Health systems and infrastructure</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Strengthen health systems and research capacity.</p>
     <p>  -Strengthen supporting infrastructure, targeting regions vulnerable to epidemics.</p>
     <p>  -Expand critical care resources.</p>
     <p>  -Develop clinical research facilities in predicted ‘hot spot’ regions.</p>
    </td>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Health systems and infrastructure</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Limited healthcare systems.</p>
     <p>  -Limited supporting infrastructure, electricity and water supply and technical resources.</p>
     <p>  -Lack of national health research institutes.</p>
     <p>  -Competing interests of resources.</p>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <bold>Administrative, regulatory and logistic solutions identified</bold>
    </td>
    <td>
     <bold>Challenges encountered</bold>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Human resources and research capacity</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Ensure capacity to respond to outbreaks across departments, particularly in predictable epidemic-prone regions.</p>
     <p>  -Ensure sufficient support for ethics review boards.</p>
     <p>  -Identify and utilise existing skills and talents, re-deploy existing research staff.</p>
     <p>  -Fund dedicated study teams to avoid additional burden on other staff.</p>
     <p>  -Ensure adequate, sustained research training for staff, particularly during stable periods.</p>
     <p>  -Establish clinical research networks that are incentivised and prepared to respond to outbreaks and politically supported.</p>
     <p>  -Form research response teams, with dedicated research coordinators.</p>
     <p>  -Recruit additional staff from outside of the epidemic area to reduce strain.</p>
     <p>  -Set up mobile research teams to reach large areas.</p>
     <p>  -Improve staff perception of research as a core role of healthcare professionals.</p>
    </td>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Human resources and research capacity</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Limited number of staff.</p>
     <p>  -Risk of already scarce staff becoming overwhelmed and additional burden of research activities across services.</p>
     <p>  -Training of staff in research not seen as a priority.</p>
     <p>  -Lack of research coordinators.</p>
     <p>  -Increased workload from study protocol risk negatively affecting patient care.</p>
     <p>  -Difficulties in deploying staff internationally sufficiently rapidly in the context of an outbreak.</p>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Communication</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Establish direct stakeholder communication channels.</p>
     <p>  -Develop harmonised, coordinated communication activities with shared oversight structures and joint management.</p>
     <p>  -Establish detailed communication and dissemination plans and templates.</p>
     <p>  -Provide continuous updates on research activity to stakeholders as appropriate through a variety of channels.</p>
     <p>  -Set up ‘pandemic champions’ to establish links with sites, to facilitate coordination and to raise awareness.</p>
    </td>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Communication</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Data stored in countries other than that affected, disempowers the national team.</p>
     <p>  -LMICs unable to access trial results after the study is completed.</p>
     <p>  -Challenges for LMICs to gain international interest from study results.</p>
     <p>  -Challenging to control the interpretation of research output by the media and political leaders.</p>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Frameworks</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Establish a normative framework for research and development.</p>
     <p>  -Create frameworks and governance charts for clear decision-making procedures, standard operational procedures and administrative infrastructures.</p>
     <p>  -Prioritise research questions, pre-design study protocols and training materials in advance, ready to be deployed.</p>
    </td>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Frameworks</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Lengthy process of planning, formalising and gaining approval of study protocol.</p>
     <p>  -Lack of integrated standards for data collection and infrastructure for data sharing.</p>
     <p>  -Delays in obtaining inter-institutional data sharing agreements.</p>
     <p>  -Time lag for distant reference lab results.</p>
     <p>  -No apparent benefit to those affected to share data.</p>
     <p>  -Delayed data sharing due to academic competition culture.</p>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Data and sample sharing</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -International agencies (e.g. WHO) to establish international data sharing frameworks.</p>
     <p>  -Refinement of international agreements, such as the Declaration of Helsinki to include instructions on how to handle benefit sharing for sponsor and host countries.</p>
     <p>  -Develop templates and platforms for data and sample sharing.</p>
     <p>  -Enhance the value of research output dissemination to all stakeholders through long-term collaboration and health system improvements.</p>
     <p>  -Funding approvals to incorporate agreement on data dissemination.</p>
     <p>  -Establish data sharing ahead of emergencies.</p>
     <p>  -Develop a mechanism to manage intellectual property and data governance.</p>
     <p>  -Establish standard to reduce uncredited secondary analysis to facilitate data sharing.</p>
     <p>  -Ensure global sharing of data with fair distribution.</p>
     <p>  -Enhance the value of the research to each beneficiary through fair dissemination of knowledge, product development, long-term research collaboration, and/or health system improvements.</p>
    </td>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Data and sample sharing</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Data collection and sharing on paper records sometimes not possible due to infection control and confidentiality issues.</p>
     <p>  -Loss of control and ownership of data following dissemination.</p>
     <p>  -Data not made available during outbreaks and long delays in publishing data after outbreaks.</p>
     <p>  -Issues around maintaining participant confidentiality when sharing data.</p>
     <p>  -Lack of control of communication.</p>
     <p>  -Confidentiality requirements imposed by commercial entities.</p>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Publication standards</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Agree open data sharing and publication standards.</p>
     <p>  -A shift in paradigm to a common goal of data sharing rather than publication.</p>
     <p>  -Ensure pre-prints of novel data are available prior to publication.</p>
     <p>  -Develop and use an ‘emergency research pledge’ by journals.</p>
     <p>  -Ensure researchers, including local collaborators, are credited for their work.</p>
    </td>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Traditional publication process</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Traditional journal review processes are too slow to inform emergency outbreak response strategies.</p>
     <p>  -Publication authorship imbalances.</p>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Pathways for regulatory and ethics approvals</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Establish accelerated regulatory pathways and expedited ethical review processes for emergencies.</p>
     <p>  -Establish institutional review boards in epidemic ‘hot spot’ regions.</p>
     <p>  -Enable single portals for applications.</p>
     <p>  -Establish joint ethics review committees.</p>
     <p>  -Enable parallel submission of ethical, financial and scientific approvals.</p>
     <p>  -Develop pre-approved study protocols with agreed acceptable study design modifications.</p>
     <p>  -Develop pre-approved site agreements, between multiple sites and organisations, in geographically strategic regions.</p>
     <p>  -Consideration of the management of bio-samples should be part of the ethical and protocol review.</p>
    </td>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Pathways for regulatory and ethics approvals</bold>
     </p>
     <p>
      <bold>-</bold>Delays caused by existing ethical frameworks.
     </p>
     <p>  -Complex ethic committee forms and inconsistencies between forms.</p>
     <p>  -Variation in REB responses to the same study.</p>
     <p>  -Lack of framework to fast-track vaccine trials or drug testing.</p>
     <p>  -Existing frameworks not fit for emergency research
      <bold>.</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Lengthy time taken to gain research approvals during epidemics and pandemics.</p>
     <p>  -Requirement of approval from multiple entities (including political) and variations between countries.</p>
     <p>  -Reluctance from national officials to approve trials.</p>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Drug and vaccine licencing and access</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Form Joint Scientific Advisory and Data Safety Review Committees for all studies linked to a specific intervention or group of interventions.</p>
     <p>  -Global regulatory agencies should collaborate to ensure accelerated licensure strategy.</p>
     <p>  -Contracts with multiple manufacturing and distribution units to improve resilience in the supply of medicines to participating trial site.</p>
     <p>  -Primary role of authorising use of investigational vaccines and drugs should be given to the affected countries.</p>
    </td>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Drug and vaccine licencing and access</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Length of time for drugs and vaccines to be approved.</p>
     <p>  -Lack of framework to fast-track vaccine trials and drug testing.</p>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Research support systems</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Provide sufficient funds for the renovation of study facilities and provide supportive infrastructure.</p>
     <p>  -Strengthen satellite and wireless internet access in epidemic-prone regions.</p>
     <p>  -Use existing infrastructure, e.g. from other disease programmes.</p>
     <p>  -Set up logistical support platforms.</p>
     <p>  -Ensure flexible solutions that can be readily adaptable depending on the context.</p>
    </td>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Research support systems</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Rudimentary and overwhelmed healthcare facilities.</p>
     <p>  -Technical resource limitations.</p>
     <p>  -Limited access to freezer storage facilities.</p>
     <p>  -Difficulty reaching remote field sites.</p>
     <p>  -Lack of effective personal protective equipment</p>
     <p>  -Poor safety for staff and participants.</p>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <bold>Ethical and social solutions identified</bold>
    </td>
    <td>
     <bold>Challenges encountered</bold>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Standards</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Develop standards for the conduct of research in emergencies, including frameworks for the inclusion of vulnerable groups and appropriate study designs.</p>
     <p>  -Ensure equitable access to best available evidence-based care for all patients, regardless of consent to participate.</p>
     <p>  -Ensure appropriate compensation for participation in research.</p>
    </td>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Standards</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Lack of uniform standards for research ethics committees.</p>
     <p>  -Lack of international consensus about research groups’ obligations to provide trial participants health benefits.</p>
     <p>  -Non-transparent ethical approval processes.</p>
     <p>  -Exclusion of pregnant women and children from trials.</p>
     <p>  -Expedited review might pose a risk to patients.</p>
     <p>  -Research perceived as the only way to access care/treatment.</p>
     <p>  -Lack of agreement on appropriate study designs for emergencies.</p>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Consent methods</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Evaluate alternative consent methods proposed during emergencies.</p>
     <p>  -Ensure consent methods are culturally appropriate.</p>
    </td>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Consent methods</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Obtaining complex informed consent, from severely ill patients and from relatives.</p>
     <p>  -Verbal proxy consent contested at later date.</p>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Community engagement</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Invest in community engagement from inception.</p>
     <p>  -Explore outbreak and community context, and use the findings to inform the study design, set-up, delivery and dissemination.</p>
     <p>  -Ensure protocol and consent forms are consistent with community values and internationally accepted ethical principles.</p>
     <p>  -Build trust through understanding and respect of different cultures.</p>
     <p>  -Ensure study design meets cultural needs.</p>
     <p>  -Manage expectations of all stakeholders.</p>
     <p>  -Facilitate community empowerment.</p>
     <p>  -Provide outreach community information sessions.</p>
     <p>  -Establish community advisory boards.</p>
     <p>  -Use social messaging and informational materials to improve the knowledge and perception of the study and disease and to address rumours.</p>
     <p>  -Ensure effective consultation and communication with affected or at-risk communities, for example, through community liaison teams.</p>
     <p>  -Involve social scientists and medical anthropologists to help understand the concerns and needs of the community.</p>
     <p>  -Translate social science research into practice.</p>
     <p>  -Facilitate relationships between groups with cultural differences.</p>
    </td>
    <td>
     <p>
      <bold>Community engagement</bold>
     </p>
     <p>  -Mistrust, suspicion and rumours around clinical trials, national and international response, sometimes due to local media and other sources.</p>
     <p>  -Poor understanding of how to address rumours.</p>
     <p>  -Fear of the disease.</p>
     <p>  -Cultural perceptions of tissue and blood sampling.</p>
     <p>  -Poor understanding of how to respect different cultures.</p>
     <p>  -Lack of community engagement and poor perception of power dynamics.</p>
     <p>  -Perception of research being unfair.</p>
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
