<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0060">We outlined how cytokine assays and transcriptomic estimates of immunity and inflammation in particular are measurable with a minimum of invasion, based on swabs or dried blood, towards predicting age-related outcomes regarding disease manifestation, hospitalization and long-term health deterioration after respiratory infection such as COVID-19. As already pointed out in the introduction, aging-related processes are an important contributor to inferior COVID-19 outcomes. Here, we describe how immunity and aging are related; see supplement 2 for more details. In brief, aging is 
 <italic>the</italic> primary risk factor for all chronic diseases, and for inferior outcomes in infectious diseases, and COVID-19 is no exception. In people with chronic respiratory disease such as asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, this risk is attributed to chronic inflammation of the airways, dominated by CD4
 <sup>+</sup> T cells and eosinophils in case of asthma and by CD8
 <sup>+</sup> T lymphocytes, macrophages and neutrophils in case of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (
 <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">Cukic et al., 2012</xref>), exacerbated by respiratory infection (
 <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Barnes et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr">Holgate et al., 2015</xref>). Far less is known about COVID-19, and about its chronic long-term consequences. The heterogeneity of responses to infections such as COVID-19 depends not only on the general health condition, predisposition on the genetic level, and the disease history, but in particular on the individual immunobiographies (
 <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">Franceschi et al., 2017b</xref>). Knowledge of the individual life experience, surrounding ecosystem, cultural habit, history of natural infections, vaccinations or allergies should thus additionally be collected. Interestingly, important mechanisms underlying acute severe adult COVID-19 pneumonia cases are a reduction in CD4+ and CD8 + T cells and a decrease in regulatory T cells (
 <xref rid="bib0310" ref-type="bibr">Scarpa et al., 2020</xref>). As the thymus is a central lymphoid organ responsible for the release of T lymphocytes, inflammaging associated with the absence or a marked reduction of thymopoiesis could be a predisposing condition that also sustains the cytokine release storm observed in many older patients with severe clinical courses (
 <xref rid="bib0310" ref-type="bibr">Scarpa et al., 2020</xref>). In accordance with this assumption, the clinical manifestations are relatively mild in children. With ageing, antigen stimulation and thymic involution lead to a shift in T cell subset distribution and loss of expression of co-stimulatory molecules such as CD27 and CD28, with increased susceptibility to infections, and a (putatively compensatory) upregulation of cytokines. On the other hand, reduced killing ability by T cells at an early stage after birth could explain susceptibility to SARS-CoV-2 in very young infants (
 <xref rid="bib0370" ref-type="bibr">Yuki et al., 2020</xref>).
</p>
