<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The whole world is currently confronting a crisis situation that first appeared in late December 2019 as merely a few cases of pneumonia in Wuhan, China. The patients were exhibiting common symptoms like fever, dry cough, sore throat, breathlessness, and fatigue. Sample swabs from the oral cavity and anal region were collected along with the blood and Bronchoalveolar Lavage Fluid (BALF) from all seven of the patients, irrespective of their age and gender, which were then sent to the Wuhan Institute of Virology for further examination. As the outbreak initiated at the seafood market with the onset of winter, similar to that of the previous Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS) infection, the scientists first screened the samples using pan-CoV qPCR primers. Surprisingly, five samples were reported positive for coronavirus. Thorough investigation employing next-generation sequencing and phylogenetic analysis led to the identification of the causative agent of this respiratory disease, a novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). As more cases started to appear around the world, on February 11, 2020, the World Health Organization assigned a name, 
 <bold>CO</bold>rona 
 <bold>VI</bold>rus 
 <bold>D</bold>isease 20
 <bold>19</bold> or COVID-19, to the disease and declared it a pandemic on March 11, 2020. The virus was renamed from 2019-nCoV to SARS-CoV-2 by the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses on the basis of its genetic similarity to a previously known coronavirus, Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus (SARS-CoV) (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Transmission of SARS-CoV-2 occurs when a healthy individual inhales or comes into contact with respiratory droplets from an infected person. The average incubation period before patients exhibit disease symptoms ranges from 2 to 14 days (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Before the spread of COVID-19, SARS emerged as an epidemic in 2003, followed by Middle East respiratory syndrome (MERS) in 2012, both caused by a novel coronavirus of zoonotic origin and assigned to the genus Betacoronavirus (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). The worldwide outbreak of SARS-CoV-2 has put life on hold, having a major impact on the world's economy, and has claimed ~436,167 lives globally as of June 15, 2020 (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Unlike previous episodes of coronavirus spread, where it took months to identify the cause of infection and perform genome sequencing (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), advancement in science and technology made it possible to identify the causative organism swiftly. Within a few weeks of the outbreak, different laboratories across the world had sequenced the whole viral genome and had also provided structural and functional insights into the essential proteins required by the virus for its survival. These immediate scientific inputs helped with developing diagnostic kits and defining treatment strategies for effective prognosis and prevention (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>–
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). In this review, we are emphasizing the immunological aspect of SARS-CoV-2 pathogenesis by taking into consideration the previous experimental and clinical knowledge obtained from the coronaviruses that were responsible for causing SARS and MERS. This approach will assist in utilizing immunotherapies, repurposing the previously approved antiviral drugs, and developing therapeutic vaccines specific to novel coronavirus more effectively.
</p>
