<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="Tab5">
 <label>Table 5</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Lassa fever clinical research priorities identified</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th>Clinical phenotype and natural history of disease</th>
    <th>RRNA</th>
    <th>Expert panel</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td> Which are the populations at risk?</td>
    <td>✓</td>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> What is the true incidence of asymptomatic infection; is the reported 85% of asymptomatic infections true or is there a diversity of clinical presentation?</td>
    <td/>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> What are the clinical characteristics of Lassa fever in different at-risk populations?</td>
    <td>✓</td>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> What are the long-term health sequelae and what is their frequency, severity, and duration?</td>
    <td>✓</td>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> What are the underlying pathophysiological mechanisms of death and are these preventable e.g. acute kidney injuries? What is the cause of platelet dysfunction in acutely ill Lassa patients?</td>
    <td>✓</td>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> What is the clinical and epidemiology relevance of Lassa virus sequence heterogeneity?</td>
    <td/>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="3">Transmission and prevention</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> What are the risks of person-to-person transmission associated with different types of exposure e.g. to what extent and how does human-human transmissions account for disease transmission? What is the risk of transmission from different body fluids and organs?</td>
    <td>✓</td>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> Does disease severity vary with route of transmission?</td>
    <td>✓</td>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> Does genetic differences within and between Lassa virus strains results in differences in transmission and in disease phenotype?</td>
    <td/>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> Who are the target population for a Lassa vaccine, e.g. does asymptomatic infection protect against re-infection? Does presence of antibodies protect from re-infection?</td>
    <td>✓</td>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> Does ribavirin PEP reduce the risk of Lassa virus disease, or more severe disease?</td>
    <td>✓</td>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> What is the optimal route and dosing for post-exposure prophylaxis with ribavirin (e.g. oral vs. intravenous)?</td>
    <td>✓</td>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> How diverse does a vaccine need to be to protect against all strains of Lassa virus?</td>
    <td/>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="3">Diagnostics</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> Can we develop a diagnostic test that is highly sensitive and specific for all lineages?</td>
    <td>✓</td>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> How does sequence variation/heterogeneity impact diagnostic methods and accuracy?</td>
    <td/>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> What is the optimal sampling time frame for diagnostics using RT-PCR? How many days after symptoms does Lassa virus become detectable by PCR?</td>
    <td>✓</td>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> Can we develop a validated point-of-care test for use in different healthcare settings, including rural health posts?</td>
    <td>✓</td>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="3">Immune response</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> What are the dynamics of resistance to re-infection? What is the average kinetics of antibody responses following acute Lassa fever virus infection and what is the variability between individuals and by age?</td>
    <td>✓</td>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> In what sites and for how long does virus persist? What are the risk factors for virus persistence?</td>
    <td/>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> Does previous exposure to Lassa virus result in more severe disease upon subsequent re-exposure (e.g. vaccine) as a result of antibody-dependent enhancement of infection, i.e. could a vaccine do harm?</td>
    <td/>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> What immunological end-points should be used for Lassa virus vaccine trials?</td>
    <td>✓</td>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="3">Drug therapy and supportive care</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> What is the true efficacy and safety of ribavirin for the treatment of Lassa? Can we transition acutely ill Lassa patients to oral ribavirin once viral loads are decreasing?</td>
    <td>✓</td>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> Does the use of ribavirin in acute Lassa fever virus infection improve clinical outcomes compared to supportive care alone?</td>
    <td>✓</td>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> What is the optimal approach to supportive care for acutely ill patients with Lassa and other VHFs?</td>
    <td/>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> What is the target therapeutic plasma and CSF concentrations of ribavirin for the treatment of Lassa fever virus infection? Do current oral and IV treatment regimens achieve these target concentrations?</td>
    <td>✓</td>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> Can type 1 interferon therapy boost the efficacy of ribavirin? Is there a role for therapies directed at host immunopathology in the management of Lassa fever?</td>
    <td/>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td colspan="3">Risk factors for more severe disease</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> Are reported differences in CFR attributable to differences in case mix (e.g. illness severity on presentation to a healthcare facility), differences in the underlying prevalence of risk factors for death, or differences in the care provided?</td>
    <td>✓</td>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> Are there clinical features or biomarkers of the risk of progression to severe disease that have clinical utility?</td>
    <td>✓</td>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td> Do genetic differences within and between Lassa strains results in differences in disease phenotype and disease severity?</td>
    <td/>
    <td>✓</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
