<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Furthermore, defective mitochondria can activate immune responses through a variety of different mechanisms (
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). The cytosolic release of mtDNA can exert potent immunostimulatory effects. Mitochondrial dysfunction or MOMP caused by pathogenic infection or toxic drugs can result in the release of mtDNA [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>,
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>], which acts as a damage-associated molecular pattern and engages with pattern recognition receptors (PRRs) [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>] to activate immune responses. The predominant immunomodulatory action of cytosolic mtDNA is through the activation of the STING pathway, a critical antiviral regulatory system activated by viral dsDNA during infection [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>]. During an infection, viral pathogens can cause mitochondrial dysfunction within infected cells. This is achieved by viral interference with mitochondrial signalling pathways and dynamics to favour viral proliferation and commonly occurs through the inhibition of apoptosis or the innate immune response [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>]. The pathogen-induced dysfunction increases the production of ROS or the release of mtDNA, where both may act as mediators for the STING pathway [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C120" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>]. The activation of the STING pathway leads to increased expression of IRF3, IRF7 and nuclear factor kappa-light-chain-enhancer of activated B cells (NFκB) transcription factors that control the expression of type I interferons (IFN-I) and interferon-stimulated genes, which directly restrict viral replication [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C121" ref-type="bibr">121</xref>]. Drugs which induce mtDNA release or enhance ROS may therefore mimic this effect and lead to up-regulation of antiviral pathways independent of infection, making them useful for both priming the innate immune system or for increasing the efficiency of viral clearance. mtDNA also contains a regulatory D-loop which allows it to act as a ligand for PRRs causing the activation of immune responses [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>,
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>]. In endosomal vesicles, this orchestrates signalling through Toll-like receptor 9 (TLR9) for the activation of both pro-inflammatory and antiviral effector responses in a variety of human immune cells [
 <xref rid="BST-47-1757C123" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>]. TLR9 is also expressed on the outer surface of cells, allowing free mtDNA present in extracellular fluid to also activate the pathway. Similar to the STING pathway, TLR9 signalling can also activate IRF7 and NFκB transcription factors. Among the inflammatory cytokine proteins up-regulated are TNF-α (tumour necrosis factor alpha) and IFN-I (interferon type I) which increase both pro-inflammatory and antiviral responses. 
</p>
