<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In February of 2013, a new atypical influenza virus, H7N9, was first reported in an 87-year-old male in Shanghai, China and the case was confirmed by the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention on 29 March 2013.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr10-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr11-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr12-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
 </sup> H7N9 is an emerging avian influenza A virus owing to genetic reassortment.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr13-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
 </sup> This virus was first identified as having low pathogenicity and was associated with asymptomatic or mild disease in poultry, causing sporadic human infections.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr12-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr14-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr15-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr"/>
  <xref rid="bibr16-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr17-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>
 </sup> A clinical survey of human infections with H7N9 viruses revealed characteristics of upper and lower respiratory tract illnesses that varied from mild to moderate (conjunctivitis or uncomplicated influenza-like illness) and could result in hospitalization.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr18-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr19-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr20-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>
 </sup> These novel H7N9 AIVs were reported to have gradually developed into highly pathogenic avian influenza (HPAI) viruses,
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr21-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr22-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
 </sup> indicating multiple increased polybasic amino acids at the hemagglutinin (HA) cleavage site (PEVPKRKRTAR/GL).
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr22-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
 </sup> High mortality rates of about 50% are reported in human cases.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr18-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr22-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>
 </sup> Phylogenetic analysis of HA sequences in H7N9 isolates indicates that two major lineages of H7N9 have been established, including the Yangtze River Delta lineage and the Pearl River Delta lineage.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr23-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>
 </sup> Reports indicate that the Yangtze River Delta lineage is broadly dispersed and was the original source of the H7N9 outbreaks in humans.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr23-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr24-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>
 </sup> China is currently facing its sixth epidemic of H7N9 human infection since 2018, and there has been a total of 1566 laboratory-confirmed human cases reported since 2013.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr25-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>
 </sup> The World Health Organization (WHO) reports that three subtypes of AIVs are currently known to cause human infection, namely, H5, H7, and H9.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr26-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>
 </sup> Among them, H5N1 and H7N9 have caused the most human infections.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr27-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>
 </sup> This implies a challenge for global public health services in controlling emerging influenza viruses, even though the number of human infections with the H7N9 influenza virus has gradually decreased with treatment.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr28-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>
 </sup> At present, there is no prophylactic vaccine against H7N9 AIV infection licensed for use in humans. The vaccine candidates currently under investigation include HA/NA peptide, plasmid-based, baculovirus-insect and mammalian protein expression system, and virus-like particle (VLP) vaccines.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr29-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr30-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr"/>
  <xref rid="bibr31-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr"/>
  <xref rid="bibr32-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr"/>
  <xref rid="bibr33-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr"/>
  <xref rid="bibr34-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr35-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>
 </sup> Some developed candidate vaccines are moving on to clinical trials. In addition, accurate and prompt diagnostic methods that have high sensitivity and specificity are essential for H7N9 influenza disease control and prevention. Several modified, advanced, conventional, and molecular diagnostic assays have been developed to enhance the capability of detecting H7N9 antigen or antibody.
 <sup>
  <xref rid="bibr36-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>
  <xref rid="bibr37-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr"/>
  <xref rid="bibr38-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr"/>
  <xref rid="bibr39-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr"/>–
  <xref rid="bibr40-0300060519845488" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>
 </sup> In this study, we conducted a systemic literature review of the emergent H7N9 AIVs in China, mainly focusing on pathogenesis, vaccine development, and diagnosis of human infection.
</p>
