<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21">The standard form was used to collect the data of each TB patient during the study period. The record system in CPHMC includes age, gender, occupation, living region, ethnicity, symptoms, and drug-related hepatotoxicity, viral hepatitis, TB type, and HIV infection. Observational variables in this study included demographic and clinical characteristics of the patients and factors associated with DR-TB and TB/HIV co-infection. Several definitions related to TB were used in this study. DR-TB consists of MR-TB, MDR-TB, XDR-TB, PDR-TB, RR-TB, and Hr-TB in our study. Mono-resistant TB (MR-TB) refers to 
 <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> strains with resistance to one first-line anti-TB drug [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]
 <bold>.</bold> MDR-TB is defined as TB that is simultaneously resistant to the two most powerful anti-TB drugs, RFP and INH, with or without resistance to other first-line drugs and requires treatment with second-line drugs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]
 <bold>.</bold> XDR-TB is defined as MDR-TB plus resistance to at least one drug in both fluoroquinolones and second-line injectable agents (amikacin, capreomycin, or kanamycin), which are the two most important classes of medicines in MDR-TB treatment [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]
 <bold>.</bold> Poly-drug-resistance (PDR-TB) refers to resistance to more than one first-line anti-TB drug, other than isoniazid (INH) and RFP [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]
 <bold>.</bold> RR-TB is considered susceptible to INH, resistant to INH, or resistant to other first-line TB drugs or second-line TB drugs that also require treatment with a second-line regimen [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]
 <bold>.</bold> INH-resistant TB (Hr-TB) refers to 
 <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> strains with resistance to INH and susceptibility to RFP confirmed in vitro [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]
 <bold>.</bold> The results of this study were reported following the Strengthening the Reporting of Observational studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) statement for reports of observational studies.
</p>
