<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue http://null/schema/dtds/document/fulltext/xcr/xocs-article.xsd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType schema?><?SourceDTD.DTDName xocs-article.xsd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName ftrr2jats.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">New Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">New Sci</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>New Scientist (1971)</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0262-4079</issn><issn pub-type="epub">0262-4079</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Published by New Scientist Limited.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7130656</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S0262-4079(20)30477-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0262-4079(20)30477-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>World braces for economic impact</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au10"><name><surname>Vaughan</surname><given-names>Adam</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>6</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>7</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>245</volume><issue>3272</issue><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 </copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license><license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="ceab10"><p>The repercussions for businesses, workers and supply chains could be severe</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p id="para10">GLOBAL economic growth could halve this year in a worst-case scenario for the covid-19 outbreak, the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) said on Monday, as the financial impact of the disease becomes clearer.</p><p id="para20">At one point last week, $5 trillion was wiped off share markets globally in their worst week since the 2008 financial crash, although shares had since begun to rebound as <italic>New Scientist</italic> went to press.</p><p id="para30">The OECD downgraded its global GDP forecast for 2020 from 2.9 per cent to 2.4 per cent, but warned that a more intense and longer-lasting outbreak might restrict growth to just 1.5 per cent.</p><p id="para40">A pandemic lasting six months could knock $1.1 trillion off the expected growth of global GDP, according to a report by UK research firm Oxford Economics.</p><p id="para50">Consumers will spend less, people will be unable to work, travel and tourism will drop sharply and investment will fall, said the firm, which based its analysis on past outbreaks including SARS and swine flu.</p><p id="para60">&#x0201c;$1.1 trillion would be much less than the financial crash impact, the world economy would still be growing. Our forecast is 2.3 per cent GDP growth,&#x0201d; says Ben May at Oxford Economics.</p><p id="para70">Calculating the economic damage so far is hampered by a lack of data, he says. Figures for industrial activity emerge slowly and efforts to extrapolate from what is happening in China are made harder by the changing timings of Chinese New Year &#x02013; the initial outbreak in Wuhan coincided with the annual holiday.</p><p id="para80">However, there is evidence from some sectors, such as travel and tourism. Thailand, which normally gets just over a quarter of its visitors from China, saw numbers down 70 per cent in the first 10 days of February, compared with that period in 2019.</p><p id="para90">&#x0201c;Clearly there will be big impacts on tourism, which we are seeing,&#x0201d; says May. &#x0201c;You will also see weaker trade, which will lead to supply chain issues. Some businesses will be fine, others badly affected.&#x0201d;</p><p id="para100">Airlines anticipate that demand will drop 4.7 per cent this year, which would be the first overall decline in global air travel since the 2008 crash. Around $29 billion is expected to be wiped off airlines' global revenues this year, with those in Asia-Pacific most affected, said trade body the International Air Transport Association.</p><p id="para110">Car firms have seen demand hit, says David Bailey at the University of Birmingham, UK, who notes that companies like Jaguar Land Rover have said they aren't currently selling any cars in China. &#x0201c;We might even see global car sales decrease this year for the first time in many years,&#x0201d; says Bailey.</p><p id="para120">Although car manufacturers use a &#x0201c;just-in-time&#x0201d; production model, meaning parts arrive at a factory shortly before they are needed rather than being stored on site, those in the UK source relatively few components from Asia, less than 10 per cent.</p><p id="para130">However, they could still face disruption, as shown by Jaguar Land Rover flying parts from China to the UK in suitcases. If and when production restarts in Chinese factories that have currently downed tools, there will still be a delay to restoring supply chains because parts take six to seven weeks to reach Europe.</p><p id="para140">The effect on the UK economy remains to be seen, but health secretary Matt Hancock has told firms to issue sick pay to staff who self-isolate from the virus on National Health Service advice.</p><p id="para150">Sickness from the outbreak could cost the UK billions, a Department of Health report suggests. Though only illustrative, the 2011 analysis of a potential flu pandemic found that GDP would take a &#x000a3;28 billion hit if half of employees had to be absent from work.</p><p id="para160">Depending on how long a pandemic lasts, the economic fallout for some could be lethal. Aaron Reeves at the University of Oxford, who was part of a team that found the financial crash was linked to an extra 10,000 suicides in Europe and North America, says the recent stock market fall could result in additional suicides.</p><p id="para170">&#x0201c;There is a real chance this leads to rises in unemployment in the next three to six months,&#x0201d; he says. &#x0201c;We would expect some mental health implications, and the hard edge of that is suicide.&#x0201d;</p><p id="para180">
<disp-quote><p><bold>$5 trillion</bold> Amount wiped off global share markets last week</p></disp-quote>
</p><p id="para190">It would be surprising if a coronavirus pandemic led to as many suicides as the 2008 crash, but the number is still likely to be significant, says Reeves.</p><p id="para200">How bad the effect is will depend on where the economic damage lands: countries with stronger social welfare provisions mitigate the knock-on impact on suicides, he says.</p><p id="para210">Need a listening ear? UK Samaritans: 116123 (samaritans.org). Visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/SuicideHelplines" id="interrefs10">bit.ly/SuicideHelplines</ext-link> for hotlines and websites for other countries.</p><p id="para220">
<disp-quote><p>Our country remains extremely well prepared, as it has been since the outbreak began</p><p><bold>Boris Johnson</bold> The UK prime minister at a press conference on 3 March</p></disp-quote>
</p></body></article>