<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4">Both the protective and pathological roles of innate immunity have been evidenced in human and experimental animals. On one hand, genetic deficiency in production of interferon or certain ISGs (e.g., MX and IFITM proteins) increases the vulnerability to IAV infection (Ciancanelli et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2015</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2016</xref>). On the other hand, genetic ablation of the pro-inflammatory cytokine IL-6 (Dienz et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2012</xref>), or chemical depletion of alveolar macrophages (Abboud et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2015</xref>), NK (Abboud et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2015</xref>) or neutrophils (Tate et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2009</xref>) in mice can exacerbate lung injury during IAV infection. These data support that both IFN response and inflammatory innate immune response are essential in protecting the host against IAV infections. However, gene expression analysis displays that early innate immunity signatures including pro-inflammatory cytokines (TNF, IL-1β, IL-6), chemokines (CCL2, CCL3, CCL4, CXCL1) and neutrophil infiltration are strongly associated with acute death of the mice infected with IAV (Brandes et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2013</xref>). In addition, deletion of pro-inflammatory cytokines IL-1, TNF and various chemokines decrease mortality in IAV-infected mice (Teijaro, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2015</xref>). Furthermore, hyper expression of pro-inflammatory cytokines and chemokines are linked to the high mortality in human cases infected with highly pathogenic influenza virus strains such as 1918 pandemic H1N1 virus and H5N1 virus (Loo and Gale, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2007</xref>; Peiris et al., 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2009</xref>). These data suggest that exaggerate inflammation during lethal infection with IAV can have fatal consequences. Therefore, benign outcomes of influenza virus infection results from inducing sufficient IFN-mediated antiviral immunity while avoiding harmful inflammatory response.
</p>
