<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Administration of mucosal vaccines via the oral route is strongly recommended because it avoids an injection, is safe and painless, and does not require professionals for delivery. However, the efficacy of oral vaccination has proven less satisfactory due to the fact that vaccine degradation occurs in the harsh environment of the gastrointestinal tract, and mucosal tolerance suppresses immune responses to a foreign antigen. Thus, oral vaccination may require highly sophisticated formulations involving approaches for cell-specific targeting and immunomodulation. In the mucosal tissues, epithelial cells are coated by a viscous fluid called mucus containing a layer of glycoproteins (mucins). The layer of mucus serves as a physical barrier between the epithelium and invaded pathogens while harboring competitive binding sites for entrapping microbes and S-IgA Abs for binding to and neutralizing pathogens. Structurally, the intestinal epithelium formed by a single-cell layer constitutes the largest and most important barrier to the entry of foreign substances and functions as a selective barrier that only allows for nutrients and electrolytes to be absorbed while preventing the entry of intra-luminal antigens, toxins, and microorganisms [
 <xref rid="B133-viruses-12-00862" ref-type="bibr">133</xref>,
 <xref rid="B134-viruses-12-00862" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>]. The selectivity of the epithelium relies on establishment of tight junctions that serve as the rate-limiting barrier of intestinal permeability. The mucosal epithelial cells can secrete antigen-degrading enzymes. Indigenous microorganisms colonizing a mucosal surface form a solid foothold for the mucosal epithelium or the mucus, thereby preventing a direct interaction between the antigens or their delivery systems and the epithelium. Given that oral vaccines are subject to a dilution prior to being absorbed in the mucosa, a degradation by proteases or nucleases present in the stomach and mucus or an exclusion by tight-junction-based barrier in the epithelium, oral vaccination requires a relatively larger amount of vaccines for eliciting effective immunity against the pathogens. However, precise quantitation of the vaccine dose required for crossing the mucosa remains a significant challenge. Generally, repeated administration of higher doses of oral mucosal vaccines or design of the vaccines mimicking the structure of immunogenic microbes may achieve an effective immunization [
 <xref rid="B134-viruses-12-00862" ref-type="bibr">134</xref>].
</p>
