<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In recent years, bats have been the focus of particular interest not just because of their ecological interest, but also for public health reasons, as they are considered to play a major role in the emergence and transmission of zoonotic viral agents. Indeed, these animals act as a natural reservoir for many viruses 
 <xref rid="pone.0087194-Calisher1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0087194-Wong1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, some of which, such as henipaviruses 
 <xref rid="pone.0087194-Luby1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0087194-Halpin1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 
 <xref rid="pone.0087194-Li1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, Ebola and Marburg virus 
 <xref rid="pone.0087194-Leroy1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0087194-Towner1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> or lyssaviruses 
 <xref rid="pone.0087194-Freuling1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0087194-Dacheux1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, cause serious human diseases. Studies based on PCR detection followed by classical sequencing approaches have demonstrated that bats naturally harbor many different viruses and have provided evidence that viral epidemics may result from the cross-species transmission of viruses from this reservoir to humans or other animals. The crossing of the species barrier by viruses is also facilitated by the expansion of the human population and the destruction of natural bat habitats, bringing bats into ever-closer contact with humans and other animals. It has been suggested that bats may harbor many other unknown, potentially epidemic viruses. However, the diversity of the global population of viruses found in bats (virome) remained little investigated until recently. The development of sequence-independent amplification approaches and their application, followed by high-throughput sequencing, to bat samples, including guano and saliva in particular, has led to the discovery of considerable viral diversity in bat species, through the identification of a large, growing number of viral species 
 <xref rid="pone.0087194-Donaldson1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0087194-He1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. However, most known bat viruses were discovered in apparently healthy bats 
 <xref rid="pone.0087194-Tse1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0087194-Chu1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0087194-Zhu1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref> or were detected directly in guano samples collected from the floors of caves harboring colonies 
 <xref rid="pone.0087194-Donaldson1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0087194-Li2" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0087194-Wu1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. To date no study has investigated the diversity of viruses in sick bats that have been in direct contact with humans. Analyses of the viromes of bats from this particularly epidemiological situation in the field, reflecting close contact with humans, constitute a crucial step in assessments of the risk of spill-over transmission, and in the prediction and prevention of viral epidemics.
</p>
