<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10">All coronavirus infections need not be diagnosed as they are self-limited and cause mild upper respiratory infection only. Clinical symptoms of coronavirus and other respiratory viruses are very mimic. Their accurate diagnosis is possible by laboratory-based assays. Initially, coronavirus can be diagnosis by virus-isolation, electron microscopy, serological methods and in later stages (after genomic sequences), molecular assays are priority. Virus isolation is a gold standard but time-consuming and high containment level required. Virus isolation is not a good method of diagnosis but produced a good amount of viruses at the end, which can be utilized for further antigenic and molecular characterizations. Electrons microscopy is costly and highly expert persons required for viral identification. Serological methods are good but pair serum required for confirmation. In the modern era of time, molecular diagnosis assays are more rapid, sensitive, specific and cost-effective for viral diagnosis [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. COVID-19 was diagnosis by Real-time RT-PCR after the availability of the full genomic sequence of the viruses [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. In India, the suspected patients are select as per country and/or WHO guidelines; the appropriate samples should be collected in the early phase of infection. The samples should collect after proper wearing of personal protective equipment (PPE) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. The collected samples should be transported in the virology laboratory in cold conditions. In the virology laboratory, the sample will be processed and standardized assay will be applied for the diagnosis. In India, All the COVID-19 diagnoses done in more than a hundred NABL accredits virology laboratories. COVID-19 is diagnosis by the Real-time RT-PCR by following the WHO protocol and ICMR guidelines.
</p>
