<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Due to the economic damage caused by enzootic H9N2, many countries including China, Israel, South Korea, Morocco, Pakistan, Egypt, Iran and UAE have adopted vaccination at either a national or local level as a key approach for preventing H9N2 disease in poultry [
 <xref rid="B30-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B203-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">203</xref>,
 <xref rid="B204-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">204</xref>,
 <xref rid="B205-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">205</xref>,
 <xref rid="B206-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">206</xref>,
 <xref rid="B207-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">207</xref>]. The most common vaccines in use are traditional inactivated vaccines, similar to those used in human seasonal vaccines. H9N2 viruses exhibit a wide antigenic variability, both between, and within lineages [
 <xref rid="B10-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B168-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">168</xref>]. Unlike human vaccines, H9N2 vaccines are generally not as regularly assessed for their efficacy against antigenically drifted viruses and consequently are far less often updated. Therefore, in many regions H9N2 viruses continue to infect and cause disease in vaccinated poultry with tentative evidence suggesting that sub-optimal use of vaccination may be driving antigenic drift and/or clade replacement, and theoretically zoonotic potential and pathogenicity [
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B103-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>,
 <xref rid="B206-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">206</xref>,
 <xref rid="B208-viruses-11-00620" ref-type="bibr">208</xref>]. Because of this, there is a real need for: (i) better understanding of the molecular determinants of H9 antigenicity, (ii) better understanding of antigenic drift and the consequences upon viral fitness and zoonotic potential and (iii) next generation vaccines that protect against multiple strains and antigenically drifted variants.
</p>
