<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Glucosidase is a type of host enzyme, liable for viral maturation and proper folding. It initiates the process of glycosylation in N-linked oligosaccharides of the viral prM and E glycoproteins [
 <xref rid="B110-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>]. DENV structural protein prM and E glycoproteins are translocated into the host endoplasmic reticulum lumen (ER). During this time, a high mannose-rich oligosaccharide -Glc-3-Man-9-GlcNAc-2- (a total 14 residue core unit) is added co-translationally [
 <xref rid="B111-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>,
 <xref rid="B112-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. The resulting N-linked glycans are generated through the help of enzyme glucosidases I and II, where glucosidase I removes the terminal α-(1, 2) linked glucose from Glc-3-Man-9-GlcNAc-2, and glucosidase II removes the second and possibly the third terminal α-(1, 3) linked glucose residues from the Glc-3-Man-9-GlcNAc-2 oligosaccharide precursor, whereby the process is denoted “glucose trimming”. After that, it leaves the protein monoglucosylated and binds to the endoplasmic reticulum chaperones (calnexin or calreticulin) for proper folding [
 <xref rid="B113-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. As DENV prME heterodimer formation is not influenced by the inhibition of glucose trimming, it helps in generating a less stable complex characterized by reduced folding efficiency. It has been shown that the folding, stability, secretion, and activity of DENV glycoproteins in the ER depends on the trimming of these N-linked carbohydrates at N-130 and N-207 [
 <xref rid="B110-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>,
 <xref rid="B112-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>,
 <xref rid="B114-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>], thus rendering the responsible cellular glucosidase a potential host target. Castanospermine, a type of naturally occurring iminosugar, and N-nonyl-deoxy-nojirimycin (NNDNJ) isolated from 
 <italic>Bacillus</italic>, are effective glucosidase inhibitors that have been indicated by both in vitro and in vivo studies in mice. The α-glucosidase inhibitor celgosivir has been shown to inhibit DENV, and treatment with celgosivir have shown to causing an improved survival rate in DENV infected mouse. The efficacy analyses were performed in patients with dengue fever [
 <xref rid="B115-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>]. The compound celgosivir is generally safe and well-tolerated but does not seem to reduce the viral load or fever burden in patients with dengue. Celgosivir derivative of 6-
 <italic>O</italic>-butanoyl is an oral pro-drug of castanospermine that can cause strong inhibition of DENV-1–4 [
 <xref rid="B115-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>,
 <xref rid="B116-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>]. Iminosugar drug UV-4, derived from deoxynojirimycin, was reported to decrease mortality in an “antibody-dependent enhancement” model of secondary DENV infection [
 <xref rid="B117-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>]. It is also noteworthy that α-glucosidase substrate mimics, such as CM 9 to 78 and CM 1018 (
 <xref rid="microorganisms-07-00296-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), are currently under development [
 <xref rid="B118-microorganisms-07-00296" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>].
</p>
