<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>RIG-I is a cytosolic sensor of short viral 5′-triphosphorylated ssRNA or dsRNA. The 5’-triphosphate-containing vRNA that is produced during viral replication is recognized by RIG-I. RIG-I uses its helicase domain to detect the 5’-triphosphate ssRNA and subsequently recruits the mitochondrial antiviral signaling protein (MAVS, also known as IPS-1) using caspase-recruitment domains (CARD). Subsequent RIG-I-MAVS signaling induces the activation of IRF3/7 and NF-κB, which then initiates the production of proinflammatory cytokines and type I IFNs. Although replication of the influenza virus occurs in the nucleus, the RIG-I signaling pathway is activated soon after infection. A recent study revealed that RIG-I is located in antiviral stress granules that consist of vRNA and proteins produced by protein kinase R (PKR) [
 <xref rid="B77-viruses-12-00504" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Interestingly, this stress granule serves as the site for detection of viral ssRNA by RIG-I. Of note, the influenza virus actually prevents the formation of these stress granules by inhibiting PKR activity in a manner dependent on functional NS1 protein [
 <xref rid="B78-viruses-12-00504" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,
 <xref rid="B79-viruses-12-00504" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Taken together, the influenza virus NS1 protein disrupts RIG-I signaling, thus suppressing IFN-α/β production [
 <xref rid="B54-viruses-12-00504" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-viruses-12-00504" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-viruses-12-00504" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-viruses-12-00504" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B64-viruses-12-00504" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. However, RIG-I-MAVS signaling does not seem to play a critical role in the defense against viral infection; survival and adaptive immune responses against the influenza virus were unchanged in MAVS-deficient mice relative to wild-type controls [
 <xref rid="B76-viruses-12-00504" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. 
</p>
