<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Members of the family Coronaviridae are enveloped and maintain a single-strand, positive-sense RNA genome ranging from 26 to 32 kb in length (Su et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). They can be classified into four genera: alpha, beta, delta and gamma, out of which alpha and beta coronaviruses (CoVs) are known to infect humans (de Wilde et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). They are circulated among humans, other mammals, and birds and can cause respiratory, enteric, hepatic and neurologic diseases (Weiss &amp; Leibowitz, 
 <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Zhu et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Even though the majority of human coronavirus infections are mild, the epidemics of two betacoronaviruses (βCoV), namely Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) and Middle East Respiratory Syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV), has caused more than 10,000 cumulative cases in the past two decades, with mortality rates of 10% for SARS-CoV and 37% for MERS-CoV (World Health Organization, 2019). In late December 2019, several local health facilities reported groups of patients with pneumonia of unknown cause, and they were found to be epidemiologically connected with the Huanan wholesale seafood market in Wuhan, Hubei province, China (Huang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). Next-generation sequencing analysis from bronchoalveolar lavage fluid samples and cultured isolates from the patients indicated a novel human-infecting coronavirus (Huang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>), officially named Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) (World Health Organization, 
 <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">2020a</xref>). Also, the World Health Organisation (WHO) has officially named the disease caused by SARS-CoV-2 as coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) (World Health Organization, 
 <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">2020a</xref>).
</p>
