<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As of 29 March 2020, there have been more than 652,000 confirmed cases of COVID-19 across 177 countries/regions, with 30,300 fatalities. China, Italy and Spain have been the most affected countries with combined fatalities of more than 19,100 patients (Johns Hopkins CSSE, 
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). On 11 March, the WHO has officially declared COVID-19 as a pandemic (World Health Organization, 
 <xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">2020c</xref>). Earlier, on 30 January 2020, the World Health Organisation (WHO) declared SARS-CoV-2 pandemic as a Public Health Emergency of International Concern (World Health Organization, 
 <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">2020e</xref>). According to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) and the WHO, the global death rate has been 3.4% (World Health Organization, 
 <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">2020b</xref>), but it varies significantly with the age of the patients (Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>). In order to control the menace caused by SARS-CoV-2, we suggest two of its indispensable druggable targets, namely 3C-like proteinase and 2′-O-ribose methyltransferase (Benkert et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Yang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). 3C-like proteinase (3CLpro) is a cysteine protease present in the Coronavirus replicase polyprotein. This protease plays a central role in viral replication and transcription functions through extensive proteolysis of two replicase polyproteins, pp1a and pp1ab (Yang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). It cleaves at least 11 inter-domain sites on the pp1a and pp1ab polyproteins to generate individual functional proteins, including an RNA-directed RNA polymerase, a helicase, an exoribonuclease, an endoribonuclease and a 2′-O-ribose methyltransferase. Also, it is excised from polyproteins by its proteolytic activity and forms a homodimer with one active site per subunit (Yang et al., 
 <xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). All of these features of 3CLpro makes it a principal drug target for SARS-CoV-2.
</p>
