<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To further test the suitability of an EDIII-based vaccine to elicit efficacious immunity against ZIKV, we constructed ZIKV-EDIII-based vaccines using three different vaccine platforms—plasmid DNA delivered by a gene gun, protein in adjuvant, and adenoviral-vectored vaccines. DNA gene gun vaccination offers the advantage of a low-cost in vivo delivery of DNA into the skin, allowing the introduction of the genetic material into cells to encode the antigen of interest. Upon production of the protein, cells like skin fibroblasts and dendritic cells initiate a systemic immune response. This design follows our previously reported tetravalent DNA EDIII-based DENV vaccine, which showed that fusion of the EDIII antigen to the dimerizing CH3 domain of the human IgG heavy chain, improved its secretion, thus increasing antigen availability, which boost the immune response when compared to EDIII, which showed lower secretory profiles [
 <xref rid="B28-vaccines-08-00307" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. As shown by our data, this design also addressed one of the main criticisms attached to genetic vaccines by bringing the immunogenicity of the candidate to levels similar to those measured when using equivalent protein-based antigens. Our previous attempts with the DENV vaccine demonstrated that three 1 μg doses of the EDIII-CH3 DNA vaccine elicited antibodies with high DENV-neutralizing activities in BALB/c mice. In contrast, although the EDIII-CH3 DNA vaccine successfully elicited antibodies against ZIKV E in high titers, which were similar to those induced by an equivalent DENV antigen [
 <xref rid="B28-vaccines-08-00307" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], the virus neutralizing capacity was only modest and notably, none of the tested sera induced 100% neutralization of ZIKV under the conditions tested. Given the disparities between the DENV and ZIKV antigens, we speculated that this could be due to an unexpected compromise regarding antigen secretion or folding in vivo, which could then lead to a limited response against particular epitopes relevant for exerting neutralization.
</p>
