<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In Arequipa Peru, the social and spatial aspects of urbanization facilitate the emergence of dog rabies and complicate its control. In 21 urban and 21 peri-urban localities in Arequipa, Peru, we found low vaccination coverage and coverage that was spatially uneven. We found a strong effect of a potential proximal determinant of participation in the MDVC: distance to the vaccination point. The unadjusted data show a clear negative gradient with higher levels of participation in the MDVC at shorter distances to the vaccination point. After accounting for other important individual- and household-level variables, distance to the vaccination point remains an important factor associated with participating in the campaign. The association between distance to and participation in the MDVC also impacts the spatial distribution of vaccination. We found areas with statistically significant lower odds of dogs being vaccinated, and the LOESS smoother maps correlated well with maps of vaccination coverage. Therefore, it seems that both fixed point and mobile team canine vaccination approaches produced spatially heterogeneous vaccination coverage. However, we found that vaccination coverage was more “patchy” in localities served by mobile vaccination teams. This combination of mobile and fixed points was used also in 2015, but the same localities are not always served with the same approach (e.g. a locality that was served with mobile teams in 2015 could be served with fixed point vaccination in 2016). As others have reported [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007600.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], there is potential that in some localities owners in 2016 expected that the MDVC would be brought to their doors and did not plan or intend to bring the dogs to the fixed points in their areas. Spatially heterogeneous vaccination coverage is undesirable for dog rabies control and elimination. Townsend et al. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007600.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>] found that such patchy coverage can "profoundly damage prospects of elimination […] by creating pockets where rabies could persist", and modeled patchy coverage within 1 km
 <sup>2</sup> cell grids. The low coverage ‘patches’ in our study had smaller areas than 1 km
 <sup>2</sup>, thus the potential for a threat to elimination efforts may be different or non-existent. However, it is unknown if these ‘patches’ are large enough to sustain rabies transmission in these densely populated areas or if there are much larger ‘patches’ in other parts of the city out of our study areas.
</p>
