<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In Australia, variable vector competence of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> populations from north Queensland for Zika has been reported [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Those populations were shown to be competent vectors for the African lineage of ZIKV [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>], but relatively inefficient vectors of a Western Pacific ZIKV strain belonging to the Asian ZIKV lineage [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Our data suggest that 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> from northern Queensland in Australia may be less susceptible to Asian ZIKV strains than to the prototype African strain [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Our findings are supported by the results of oral challenges of Australian 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> with a strain of ZIKV from the Western Pacific [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>] in which infection and transmission rates were 40 and 37% respectively, using a similar virus titre to that employed here (8.5 and 8.8 log CCID
 <sub>50</sub>/ml, for the Western Pacific and Brazilian strains, respectively). It should be noted that the titres used in both studies are higher than those expected in typical human viremias [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. However, oral challenge of Australian 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> with a lower titre of the Western Pacific ZIKV strain (5.6 log CCID
 <sub>50</sub>) resulted in only 3% of mosquitoes becoming infected [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007281.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Our study suggests that both high viremias and high disseminated threshold titres are required in order to obtain successful infection of 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> and allow viral transmission to occur. Although 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>aegypti</italic> could transmit ZIKV at moderate efficiency following challenge with a high titre, we have shown that under similar conditions, the transmission capability of Torres Strait 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> was only 10%. 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>albopictus</italic> is therefore less likely to participate in local transmission cycles than 
 <italic>Ae</italic>. 
 <italic>Aegypti</italic> in Australia.
</p>
