<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Prior to 1996, human infections with the H7 AIV subtype have been primarily due to laboratory or occupational exposures [
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Direct avian-to-human transmission of a low pathogenic avian influenza (LPAI) A/H7N7 was first confirmed in 1996 on an English woman while tending to her apparently infected pet ducks [
 <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. In 2002, LPAI A/H7N2 virus was detected in Virginia [
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] and isolated in an immunocompromised New York resident [
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]; this subtype was also found among poultry workers in Wales, England [
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Similarly, an LPAI A/H7N3 was recovered from a poultry attendant in the UK [
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] whereas retrospective serologic analysis of workers who responded during the 2002-2003 H7N3 Italian poultry outbreak identified 7 persons seropositive [
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. In contrast to these LPAI H7 strains, HPAI A/H7N3 variants were responsible for zoonotic infections among poultry workers in British Columbia, Canada [
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] and Jialisco, Mexico [
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Before 2013, the largest human H7 outbreak occurred in the Netherlands [
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] caused by an HPAI A/H7N7 tallying over 80 cases including one fatality. Up to that point, all of the H7 patients have only presented generally mild respiratory disease commonly accompanied by conjunctivitis, except for the United States cases [
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. However, pathobiology of H7 AIVs changed when human cases caused by an A/H7N9 virus emerged since late March 2013 killing a quarter of those infected [
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Unlike its A/H5N1 and A/H9N2 relatives, A/H7N9 does not induce remarkable influenza-like disease signs in afflicted poultry albeit efficient replication [
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. The pathogen, a product of multiple reassortment between strains found in migratory birds and prevailing A/H9N2 viruses in Chinese poultry [
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], does not contain the pathotypic HA cleavage motif but show indications that it can infect and replicate well in mammalian species [
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. As of writing, more than 350 cases have been confirmed with over 70 casualties mostly from mainland China. Imported cases in Hong Kong, Taiwan and a Chinese visitor in Malaysia are the only other reports outside the Chinese territory [
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], indicating that it hasn't yet gone global dissemination. Notably though, human infections with A/H7N9 viruses have been characterized by rapid progression to severe pulmonary disease and acute respiratory distress syndrome, reminiscent of human HPAI A/H5N1 disease [
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. The scale of these zoonotic infections also highlights the need for enhanced surveillance in neighboring countries. The geographic location of South Korea puts it well within the East Asian flyway of migratory waterfowls. In addition, exchange of tourists between China and Korea are constantly growing due to close proximity and improved air travel. Thus, A/H7N9 could be carried over by infected migratory wild birds and/or human traveler/visitors as what happened in the imported case of Malaysia.
</p>
