<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A previous study has shown that 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>gracilipes</italic> colonies in Penang displayed a high level of intercolonial aggression, and that high mortality was common during the intraspecific aggression assay [
 <xref rid="B16-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Our findings are consistent with this earlier study, and allow us to presume that the population structure of 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>gracilipes</italic> in this region is heterogeneous and may harbor multiple localized supercolonies. Interestingly, we found that the intercolonial aggression level appears to decrease as the latitude increases (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="insects-10-00436-f003">Figure 3</xref>; 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-insects-10-00436">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>), suggesting the presence of a latitudinal gradient of aggression level and possibly population heterogeneity as well. While the origin of 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>gracilipes</italic> remains open to debate, our data seem to favor a Southeast Asian origin for 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>gracilipes,</italic> because the supercolony structure of this ant in Penang, Malaysia resembles that in native Argentine ants, whose supercolony is generally more localized than populations in their introduced ranges [
 <xref rid="B24-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Indeed, emerging evidence has been accumulated to support this ant originating from Southeast Asia. For example, an earlier study by Ito et al. [
 <xref rid="B31-insects-10-00436" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] found several incipient colonies of 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>gracilipes</italic> that have apparently been initiated by single solitary queens independently in East Java, Indonesia, and the discovery of 
 <italic>A</italic>. 
 <italic>gracilipes</italic> queens adopting such “ancestral” founding strategy may, therefore, imply that this area and possibly other parts of Southeast Asia could be their native range. Large-scale surveys and the development of high-resolution genetic markers are urgently warranted.
</p>
