<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Population-level result evaluation was performed in relation to the concept of herd immunity. The term ‘herd immunity’ is widely used, but diversely interpreted. We used it in the sense of ‘a threshold proportion of immune individuals’ [
 <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], strictly limited to humoral antibody titres. This threshold denoting the arrest of disease spread is different for every disease and is affected by many factors; key epidemiological parameters, such as the age-specific force of infection and the basic reproduction number (
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub>) are estimated from case notification or serological data [
 <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Imperfect immunity (due to individual differences of responders), heterogeneous populations with potential non-random mixing and non-random vaccination schedules may also need to be considered [
 <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> is defined as the average number of secondary cases that result from an individual infection in a susceptible population [
 <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Estimates of 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> depend on underlying mixing assumptions. For the virus-specific 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> values shown below, the model of ‘likely mixing patterns’ was used [
 <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> estimates are highest for measles, intermediate for mumps and generally lowest for rubella [
 <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. For measles, 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> is often cited as 12–18, which implies the need for ~95% herd immunity. This means that each person with measles can infect 12–18 other individuals in a completely susceptible population. For this reason, the achievement of ≥95% of immunity across all age groups (optimal immune response followed by efficient seroconversion on population level) is the official target for measles elimination. In the literature, 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub> and HIT values are generally estimated as follows: 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0 Measles</sub> = 12–18, HIT
 <sub>Measles</sub> = 92–95%, 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0Mumps</sub> = 4–12, HIT
 <sub>Mumps</sub> = 75–86%, 
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0Rubella</sub> = 5–7, HIT
 <sub>Rubella</sub> = 83–86% [
 <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Often used models for population-level estimation are the HIT (
 <italic>I</italic>
 <sub>c</sub>); 
 <italic>I</italic>
 <sub>c</sub>  =  1 − (1/
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sub>0</sub>), and the critical vaccination coverage (
 <italic>V</italic>
 <sub>c</sub>); 
 <italic>V</italic>
 <sub>c</sub>  =  
 <italic>I</italic>
 <sub>c</sub>/
 <italic>E</italic>, where 
 <italic>E</italic> is vaccine effectiveness [
 <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>–
 <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Despite the remarkable theoretical knowledge, public health practice aims at 100% coverage, with all the doses recommended, bearing in mind that – because of the diversity of individual immune responses – 100% is never achievable.
</p>
