<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0045">Nitric oxide (NO) is a gas produced from arginine in mammalian cells by three enzymes: neuronal (nNOS), endothelial (eNOS) and inducible nitric oxide synthase (iNOS) [
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. In host cells iNOS is commonly elevated during infection by viruses, and in SARS-CoV-1 infection, NO inhibits viral replication by cytotoxic reactions through intermediates such as peroxynitrite [
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Nitrosation of reactive thiols on the surface of RBCs and on the beta chain of the hemoglobin tetramer stabilizes against hemolysis and oxidative damage, respectively [
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], conferring NO's potential in controlling SARS-CoV-2's RBC-associated pathogenic processes. Because SARS-CoV-2 infects endothelial cells, which are a major source of NO synthesis, the molecule is additionally well-placed to respond to viral attack. As discussed above, NO plays key roles in maintaining normal vascular function and regulating inflammatory cascades that contribute to ALI and ARDS when excessively activated in the context of declining endothelial function. Vasculature depleted of NO suffers from persistent inflammation and blunted delivery of oxygen and removal of toxic byproducts through stagnant blood flow into and out of hypoxic tissue [
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. NO supplementation under proinflammatory conditions prevents cytokine storm, restores the functional capillary density crucial for oxygen delivery and waste removal, prevents H/R injury and protects oxygen-sensitive organs such as the kidneys (Cabrales &amp; Friedman, Kaul &amp; Friedman, unpublished data, 2020). When ARDS is already present, NO improves arterial oxygenation and blunts pulmonary hypertension by dilating pulmonary vessels in ventilated lung parenchyma [
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. These supportive changes at the physiologic level may translate to decreased ventilator support, improved density of lung infiltrates on chest radiography and persistence of therapeutic benefits after discontinuation of NO [
 <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The vulnerable populations in the current pandemic may have lower levels of endogenously produced NO. NO generated from eNOS drops off with age, and patients with chronic vascular inflammation, such as in type 2 diabetes, metabolic syndrome, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, obesity, autoimmune disorders and hemoglobinopathies, may produce less eNOS [
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Additionally, ACE activity relative to ACE2 activity may be elevated in patients with chronic vascular inflammation [
 <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Older patients with vascular stressors from underlying chronic medical conditions may exhibit inadequate vascular NO levels, increasing their vulnerability to H/R and I/R injury. Consequently, exogenous NO for targeted patient populations may be a treatment that can reduce viral load in the lungs, prevent the chain of events that rapidly destabilizes patients to ARDS and promote clinical recovery from ARDS.
</p>
