<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Adjuvants targeting pattern-recognition receptors, such as Toll-like receptors (TLRs), are part of a broad approach to stimulate innate immune responses, thereby enhancing antigen-specific immunity and subsequently improving vaccine efficacy [
 <xref rid="B9-vaccines-08-00306" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Recently, numerous studies have shown the effects of TLR4-dependent adjuvants on improving vaccine efficacy [
 <xref rid="B10-vaccines-08-00306" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-vaccines-08-00306" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-vaccines-08-00306" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-vaccines-08-00306" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-vaccines-08-00306" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. A TLR4 agonist absorbed on alum in AS04 adjuvant was successfully used in licensed vaccines for human papillomavirus [
 <xref rid="B15-vaccines-08-00306" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] and the hepatitis B virus [
 <xref rid="B16-vaccines-08-00306" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Thus, developing TLR4 ligands as adjuvants could be beneficial to improving antiviral vaccines such as influenza vaccine. Monophosphoryl lipid A (MPL) is a detoxified derivative of the lipopolysaccharide (LPS) isolated from 
 <italic>Salmonella minnesota</italic> R595. MPL has been demonstrated to stimulate innate immunity via TLR4 [
 <xref rid="B17-vaccines-08-00306" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and promote Th1-biased immune responses [
 <xref rid="B18-vaccines-08-00306" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Even though MPL has been widely used as an adjuvant in several human vaccines [
 <xref rid="B19-vaccines-08-00306" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], the complicated purification process and prohibitive cost of MPL have precluded its use as an easy-to-use and cost-effective adjuvant. To address these limitations, 
 <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>-produced MPL (named EcML) has been previously produced by direct extraction from genetically engineered 
 <italic>E. coli</italic> [
 <xref rid="B20-vaccines-08-00306" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].
</p>
