<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0039">SARS-CoV first appeared in 2002 and rapidly spread to 32 countries and regions, after which the world then experienced the outbreak of MERS-CoV in 2012. Recently, the newly emerged SARS-CoV-2 is undoubtedly a warning. It has been confirmed that SARS-CoV-2 enters lung cells by binding to ACE2. Besides pulmonary tissue, ACE2 is also highly expressed in other tissues including bile duct, liver, gastrointestinal organs (small intestine, duodenum), oesophagus, testis and kidney 
 <xref rid="bib0042" ref-type="bibr">[42</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0117" ref-type="bibr">[117]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0118" ref-type="bibr">[118]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0119" ref-type="bibr">[119]</xref>]. Thus, these organs may also be damaged by SARS-CoV-2. Currently, SARS-CoV-2 has spread rapidly in multiple countries, caused severe illness and sustained human-to-human transmission, making it a concerning and serious public-health threat. Considering the global threat to health caused by SARS-CoV-2, effective prevention and treatment of COVID-19 pneumonia will be urgently needed. However, the development of drugs for pathogenic SARS-CoV-2 is still a major problem for humans, and there are currently no officially approved drugs to treat COVID-19. In view of the epidemiological characteristics of SARS-CoV-2, it is crucial to interrupt the spread of the virus through epidemic prevention and control methods, such as isolating infected patients and controlling the source of infection. At the same time, wild animal trafficking must be banned to reduce the spread of CoVs. In addition, it is necessary to make full use of the currently limited evidence for therapeutic drugs to develop strategies of drug application to prevent and control the transmission of SARS-CoV-2. It has been confirmed that the genome sequence of SARS-CoV-2 shares high identity with that of bat and human SARS-CoVs. A number of antiviral drugs and treatment methods for SARS-CoV infection have also been considered for the treatment and prevention of COVID-19 pneumonia.
</p>
