<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0029">The precise membrane trafficking of SARS-CoV-2 into the host cell is unknown. Nevertheless, it involves endocytic pathways, which could be targeted to prevent viral entry. A number of currently available drugs have been shown to target the endocytic pathways, largely through acidification of the endosomes. The list includes chloroquine, hydroxychloroquine, sertraline, chlorpromazine, and amiloride, among others. There has been considerable interest in the use of chloroquine and its less toxic version hydroxychloroquine, because of the initial reports on favorable clinical outcomes and the reduction in the viral load (reviewed in 
 <xref rid="bib0051" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>). However, the initial enthusiasm for the potential efficacy of hydroxychloroquine (alone or in combination with azithromycin) in the treatment of patients with COVID-19 has been dampened in the absence of compelling clinical evidence of efficacy in the observational data and small-scale randomized clinical trials 
 <xref rid="bib0052" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. There were no beneficial effects of treatment with hydroxychloroquine in the Randomised Evaluation of COVID-19 Therapy (RECOVERY) study in UK (
 <xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> ), which randomized 1,542 hospitalized patients to the hydroxychloroquine and 3,132 patients to the usual care (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.recoverytrial.net/results/hydroxychloroquine-results" id="interref0004" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.recoverytrial.net/results/hydroxychloroquine-results</ext-link>). The 28-day mortality in the hydroxychloroquine group was 25.7% as compared to 23.5% in the usual care group (hazard ratio: 1.11, 95% confidence interval [CI]: 0.98-1.26). The lack of efficacy is further compounded by the QT prolongation and potentially pro-arrhythmic side effects, observed with these drugs 
 <xref rid="bib0053" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. While a few studies have been discontinued, several large-scale randomized clinical trials are still ongoing to test efficacy of hydroxychloroquine in the treatment of patients with COVID-19.
</p>
