<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="para0020">As reported by CCTV4, 1250 medical staff in Tongxu County Hospital (Henan province) drank Chinese medicine decoctions and burned 
 <italic>Artemisia argyi</italic> in the hospital corridor. With regard to masks, disposable masks were used for medical personnel, and N95 masks were not used (Hao et al., 2012). In Jingzhou (Hubei province), the worst-hit area of the epidemic, 580 medical staff came from Jingzhou TCM Hospital, and none of them were infected by the disease. In addition, the hospital produces 25,000 preventive Chinese patented medicines for distribution to other hospitals every day (Zhang et al., 2017). In Wuhan, where the epidemic was most severe, Jiangxia Fangcai Hospital also achieved zero infections among medical staff (Seah et al., 1973). Moreover, in Huanggang, Huangshi (Hubei province), and Guangzhou (Guangdong province), TCM methods were used to prevent the epidemic, and there was zero infection among the medical staff there as well. However, more than 3000 medical staff without TCM prevention were infected. Considering the similarity between the COVID-19 epidemic and the SARS epidemic in 2003, it is pertinent to compare the outcomes among medical personnel in China. Three studies were identified including one controlled study (Lau et al., 2005) and two single cohort studies (Luo et al., 2020) conducted during the SARS epidemic. Lau et al designed a controlled study to evaluate an herbal formula for prevention of SARS (no herbal intervention in the control group) and conducted it in Hong Kong, China. The sample size was 16,437 (1063 in the herbal group and 15,374 in the control group), and all participants were hospital care workers including doctors, nurses, and other staff. The results showed that none of the participants who took a modified formula of Yupingfeng Powder and Sangju Decoction contracted SARS, whereas 64 of 15,347 (0.4%) in the control group were infected with SARS (P=0.035). There were 19 cases (1.8%) of minor adverse effects after 14 days of taking the herbal medicine, including diarrhea, sore throat, dizziness, and nausea. Both single cohort studies were conducted in Beijing, China, with sample sizes of 3561 and 163, respectively. All participants were medical staff from two hospitals in which SARS patients were recruited and treated during the study period (Luo et al., 2020). One of the studies included only first-line medical staff treating SARS. The courses of taking the herbal formulae for prevention were 6 days and 12 to 25 days for the two cohort studies, respectively. The decoctions used in these studies were both a classic formula of Yupingfeng Powder and some heat-clearing and detoxifying herbs. The results of the two studies showed that none of the participants who took the preventive herbal medicine contracted SARS.
</p>
