<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>By viewing the history of influenza virus circulation through the lens of imprinting, researchers can make assumptions about individual host imprinting and immune history. The influenza virus strain that an individual imprinted upon can be deduced by cross-referencing birth year with strain predominance [
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-11-00122" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. For example, we can conclude that people born between 1918 and 1957 were imprinted with strains of H1N1 viruses since it was the only subtype of influenza A circulating in those years [
 <xref rid="B16-viruses-11-00122" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Those born between 1957 and 1968 would have imprinted against H2N2 and those born between 1968 and 1977 imprinted against H3N2 according to circulation history. For young individuals during H3N2 and H1N1 virus co-circulation, the predominant subtype per birth year is considered to be the imprinting virus. Since there was a sequential emergence and replacement of the influenza A virus subtypes (H1N1, H2N2, and H3N2) the current population, there is much variability for imprinted immunity. Moreover, the sequential nature of influenza virus circulation has led to heterosubtypic infection-reinfections throughout history. For instance, people born in 1947 imprinted with H1N1 and were reinfected with an H2N2 strain in ~1957. This sequence of infections can represent a person born in 1947 living through 1957 and would be noted as H1N1-&gt;H2N2. Additionally, the 2009 surfacing of an antigenically novel H1N1 strain (2009 H1N1) gave opportunity for monosubtypic heterologous infection-reinfection. We refer to this as a seasonal H1N1 (sH1N1) imprinting with a 2009 H1N1 reinfection (sH1N1-&gt;2009 H1N1). Since, influenza B viruses have co-circulated during A virus flux, there is further complexity to human influenza virus preimmunity. Studies are only beginning to uncover the dynamics of infection-reinfection permutations on shaping the human preimmune background.
</p>
