<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">Guangzhou is one of largest city having the highest population density in the world. It is the capital city of Guangdong Province in southern China, located at 112°57 E to 114°3 E and 22°26 N to 23°56 N, with 10 administrative districts (Liwan, Yuexiu, Haizhu, Baiyun, Tianhe, Huangpu, Luogang, Panyu, Nansha, Huadu) and 2 satellite cities (Conghua and Zengcheng), covering 7434.40 km
 <sup>2</sup> and with a current population of more than 12.84 million and a humid subtropical climate influenced by the Asian monsoon season [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. In the past three decades, 
 <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> had been monitored as the vector for dengue transmission in Guangzhou, with no 
 <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> identified. It ranked second highest in proportion amongst all adult mosquitoes from surveillance at about 7% compared to 8% of 
 <italic>Culex fatigans</italic> which took the largest proportion. Guangzhou is the most important city in China for annual DENV transmission, accounting for more than 50% of the DENV cases in mainland China [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. DENV-1, DENV-2, DENV-3, and DENV-4 circulated sequentially in Guangzhou from initial identification in 1978 to 2013. Annual reported cases have been climbing, especially between 2010 and 2013, with reports of 59, 33, 139, and 1249 cases, respectively. Prior to the 2014 outbreak, 2013 was the largest dengue outbreak in the past decade. However, reported cases soared dramatically beyond academic and government expectation in 2014, accounting for approximately 80% of reported cases in mainland China. In order to recognize epidemic trend and provide evidence for prevention and control strategies, we investigated various data sources from the 2014 outbreak including epidemiologically relevant characteristics of cases, laboratory testing and phylogenetic analysis of E gene sequences from isolated DENV samples.
</p>
