<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The structural modeling of PeV-A1 indicates that the RGD motif is located between the icosahedral five-fold and three-fold axes on the capsid surface [
 <xref rid="B6-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B7-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. The deletion of the RGD motif results in the loss of PeV-A1 infectivity [
 <xref rid="B79-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. Therefore, several groups have investigated the role of αv ITG heterodimers in PeV-A1 infection. Based on a phage display screening, it was suggested that PeV-A1 preferentially uses αvβ1 ITG as a receptor [
 <xref rid="B18-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Experiments employing integrin-blocking monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) indicated αvβ3 ITG as the primary PeV-A1 receptor [
 <xref rid="B80-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. One report confirmed that both αvβ3 and αvβ1 integrin heterodimers were involved in PeV-A1 infection while others describe αvβ6 ITG as the high affinity receptor for PeV-A1 [
 <xref rid="B81-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>]. More recently, it was reported that PeV-A1 infection occurs via αVβ1 ITG [
 <xref rid="B82-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>]. Taken together, these results indicate that integrins facilitate PeV-A1 infection but the use of specific heterodimers may be cell line dependent. While ITGs are important for virus binding and entry in cell lines, ITGs may not be exclusive receptors in vivo. In studies on human airway epithelial (HAE) cultures, we found no effect of αv ITG blocking on PeV-A1 and PeV-A3 infection [
 <xref rid="B83-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>]. Interestingly, PeV-A1 strains lacking VP1 C-terminal RGD sequence have been isolated from a Dutch child [
 <xref rid="B84-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Furthermore, PeV-A3 and PeV-A7 to A19 lack the RGD motif and ITGs are assumed not to be involved in entry [
 <xref rid="B1-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. However, the lack of the RGD motif does not preclude ITG binding and integrin-ligand interactions can occur in a RGD-independent manner. For example, the very late antigen 2 (also known as α2β1 ITG) has been shown to mediate echovirus 1 infection in this way [
 <xref rid="B77-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>,
 <xref rid="B85-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>,
 <xref rid="B86-viruses-11-01062" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>].
</p>
