<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Not all El Niño events are the same, and their effects on weather/climate may therefore differ. In 1994 and 1999, the model predicted an epidemic year would result from the high SLP and SST indices. However, the observed dry season rainfall patterns (rainfall surplus) were inconsistent with the usual occurrences, and this may explain the lack of an epidemic situation. In addition, 2001 and 2005 were epidemic years that were not predicted by the model. In these two years, dry season rainfall showed no positive or negative specific anomalies. For 2005, these observations were consistent (moderate SLP and SST indices versus moderate dry season rainfall). However, in 2001, given the low SST and SLP indices, a wetter dry season was expected than was observed. Thus, if a large part of the dry season rainfall variability in French Guiana is driven by the SST and SLP of the targeted areas, it is not always the case. These data highlight the complexity of predicting epidemiological patterns for non-climate-contrasted years and suggests that rainfall variability is not driven only by the two large scale indicators that were identified in the present study. Nevertheless, global predictions for the 1991–2013 period were better when the SST and SLP indices were used than when the dry season rainfall index was used (
 <xref rid="pntd.0004681.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Interestingly, the years that were incorrectly classified by the model preceded the implementation of the new enhanced surveillance system in 2006. Even when epidemic years that were identified by the tercile method were confirmed by historical reports, the representativeness of the surveillance system prior to 2006 could not differentiate an increased incidence that was caused by the presence of multiple isolated clusters from a major generalized epidemic. Historical reports may have overestimated the number of epidemiological circumstances, particularly in 2005, when one additional laboratory was included in the serological diagnosis process. Furthermore, three of the four misclassified years showed intermediate incidence rates (2
 <sup>nd</sup> tercile) that corroborated our results. Specifically, the two identified false alarms (1994 and 1999) showed relatively high incidence rates for non-epidemic years. In addition, one of the two unpredicted epidemic years (2001) was associated with lower incidence rates than the other epidemic years.
</p>
