<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Antimicrob Resist Infect Control</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Antimicrob Resist Infect Control</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Antimicrobial Resistance and Infection Control</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2047-2994</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4696151</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">99</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13756-015-0099-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>APSIC Guidelines for environmental cleaning and decontamination</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>Moi Lin</given-names></name><address><email>ling.moi.lin@singhealth.com.sg</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Apisarnthanarak</surname><given-names>Anucha</given-names></name><address><email>anapisarn@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thu</surname><given-names>Le Thi Anh</given-names></name><address><email>letathu@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Villanueva</surname><given-names>Victoria</given-names></name><address><email>vicky.villanueva.rrdi@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pandjaitan</surname><given-names>Costy</given-names></name><address><email>costypandjaitan@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yusof</surname><given-names>Mohamad Yasim</given-names></name><address><email>yasim@ummc.edu.my</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Singapore General Hospital, Outram Road, 169608 Singapore </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Thammasat University Hospital, Khlong Luang District, Thailand </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>Cho Ray Hospital, H&#x01ed3; Ch&#x000ed; Minh, Vietnam </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label/>Chong Hua Hospital, Cebu City, Philippines </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label/>Association of Infection Prevention Control Nurse, Jakarta, Indonesia </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label/>University of Malaya Medical Centre, Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>29</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>58</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Ling et al. 2015</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p>This document is an executive summary of APSIC Guidelines for Environmental Cleaning and Decontamination. It describes best practices in routine cleaning and decontamination in healthcare facilities as well as in specific settings e.g. management of patients with isolation precautions, food preparation areas, construction and renovation, and following a flood. It recommends the implementation of environmental hygiene program to keep the environment safe for patients, staff and visitors visiting a healthcare facility. Objective assessment of cleanliness and quality is an essential component of this program as a method for identifying quality improvement opportunities. Recommendations for safe handling of linen and bedding; as well as occupational health and safety issues are included in the guidelines. A training program is vital to ensure consistent adherence to best practices.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Environmental cleaning</kwd><kwd>Decontamination</kwd><kwd>Environmental hygiene</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Background</title><p>Contamination of hospital equipment, medicines, and water supplies with hospital pathogens is a well-recognized cause of common-source outbreaks of infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The intent of this document is to highlight practical recommendations in a concise format designed to assist healthcare facilities at Asia Pacific region in implementing an environmental hygiene program.</p><p>This document is a summary of the APSIC Guidelines For Environmental Cleaning And Decontamination developed by the Asia Pacific Society of Infection Control (APSIC).</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Review</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Workgroup composition</title><p>APSIC convened Infection Prevention and Control experts from Asia Pacific region to develop the APSIC Guidelines For Environmental Cleaning And Decontamination. The members of this workgroup are the authors of this paper.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Literature review and analysis</title><p>For the APSIC guideline, the workgroup reviewed previously published guidelines and recommendations relevant to each section and performed computerized literature searches using PubMed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Process</title><p>The workgroup met on 2 occasions as well as discussed via email correspondences to complete the development of the guideline. Criteria for grading the strength of recommendation and quality of evidence are described in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The draft was then submitted to APSIC Executive Committee and national Infection Control societies in Asia Pacific. Comments obtained were then reviewed by the workgroup for necessary edits, following which the final copy was circulated for approval and endorsement by the APSIC Executive Committee and national societies from the Asia Pacific region.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Categories for strength of each recommendation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2">Categories for strength of each recommendation</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>CATEGORY</td><td>DEFINITION</td></tr><tr><td>A</td><td>Good evidence to support a recommendation for use</td></tr><tr><td>B</td><td>Moderate evidence to support a recommendation for use.</td></tr><tr><td>C</td><td>Insufficient evidence to support a recommendation for or against use</td></tr><tr><td>D</td><td>Moderate evidence to support a recommendation against use.</td></tr><tr><td>E</td><td>Good evidence to support a recommendation against use.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Categories for quality of evidence on which recommendations are made</td></tr><tr><td>GRADE</td><td>DEFINITION</td></tr><tr><td>I</td><td>Evidence from at least one properly randomized, controlled trial.</td></tr><tr><td>II</td><td>Evidence from at least one well-designed clinical trial without randomization, from cohort or case-controlled analytic studies, preferably from more than one centre, from multiple time series, or from dramatic results in uncontrolled experiments.</td></tr><tr><td>III</td><td>Evidence from opinions of respected authorities on the basis of clinical experience, descriptive studies, or reports of expert committees.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>General cleaning practices</title><p>Health care settings comprised areas that require either Hotel Clean or Hospital Clean based on the risk of the patient population in the area. Hotel Clean is a measure of cleanliness based on visual appearance that includes dust and dirt removal, waste disposal and cleaning of windows and surfaces. In addition to routine cleaning, additional cleaning practices and/or the use of personal protective equipment for cleaning may be required in health care settings under special circumstances. Hotel Clean is the basic cleaning that takes place in all areas of a health care setting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p><p>Hospital Clean is a measure of cleanliness routinely maintained in care areas of the health care setting. Hospital Clean is &#x02018;<italic>Hotel Clean</italic>&#x02019; with the addition of disinfection, increased frequency of cleaning; auditing and other infection control measures in client/patient/resident care areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Components of hotel clean</title><p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Floors and baseboards are free of stains, visible dust, spills and streaks</p></list-item><list-item><p>Walls, ceilings and doors are free of visible dust, gross soil, streaks, spider webs and handprints</p></list-item><list-item><p>All horizontal surfaces are free of visible dust or streaks (includes furniture, window ledges, overhead lights, phones, picture frames, carpets etc.)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Bathroom fixtures including toilets, sinks, tubs and showers are free of streaks, soil, stains and soap scum</p></list-item><list-item><p>Mirrors and windows are free of dust and streaks</p></list-item><list-item><p>Dispensers are free of dust, soiling and residue and replaced/replenished when empty</p></list-item><list-item><p>Appliances are free of dust, soiling and stains</p></list-item><list-item><p>Waste is disposed of appropriately</p></list-item><list-item><p>Items that are broken, torn, cracked or malfunctioning are replaced</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Cleaning best practices at patient care areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]</title><p>Housekeeping in the health care setting should be performed on a routine and consistent basis to provide for a safe and sanitary environment. Maintaining a clean and safe health care environment is an important component of infection prevention and control. The frequency of cleaning and disinfecting individual items or surfaces in a particular area or department depends on:<list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>Whether surfaces are high-touch or low-touch;</p></list-item><list-item><p>The type of activity taking place in the area and the risk of infection associated with it (e.g., critical care areas vs. meeting room);</p></list-item><list-item><p>The vulnerability of patients housed in the area; and</p></list-item><list-item><p>The probability of contamination based on the amount of body fluid contamination surfaces in the area might have or be expected to have</p></list-item></list></p><p>See example in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Risk Stratification Matrix to determine the frequency of cleaning (example)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Discipline</th><th>Probability of contamination</th><th>Potential for Exposure</th><th>Population</th><th>Total score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3"/><td>Light :1</td><td>High-touch : 3</td><td>Less susceptible:0</td><td rowspan="3"/></tr><tr><td>Moderate: 2</td><td>Low -touch:1</td><td>More susceptible: 1</td></tr><tr><td>Heavy: 3</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Renal</td><td>2</td><td>3</td><td>1</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>Burns</td><td>2</td><td>3</td><td>1</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>Respiratory Medicine</td><td>2</td><td>3</td><td>0</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>General Medicine</td><td>2</td><td>3</td><td>1</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>Colorectal Surgery</td><td>2</td><td>3</td><td>0</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>Oncology</td><td>2</td><td>3</td><td>1</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>Neurology and Neurosurgery</td><td>2</td><td>3</td><td>0</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>Surgical Intensive Care Unit</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>1</td><td>7</td></tr><tr><td>Medical Intensive Care Unit</td><td>3</td><td>3</td><td>1</td><td>7</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Interpretation of total score: <bold>7</bold>: <bold>High risk</bold>: clean after each case/event/procedure and at least twice per day, clean additionally as required; <bold>4</bold>&#x02013;<bold>6</bold>: <bold>Moderate Risk</bold> : clean at least once daily, clean additionally as required (e.g. Gross soiling), <bold>2</bold>&#x02013;<bold>3</bold> : <bold>Low risk</bold>: clean according to a fixed scheduled, clean additionally as required (e.g. Gross soiling)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Recommendations</title><p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Housekeeping in the health care setting should be performed on a routine and consistent basis to provide for a safe and sanitary environment. [BIII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Adequate resources must be devoted to Housekeeping Department in all health care settings that include:<list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>Single individual with assigned responsibility for the care of the physical facility;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Written procedures for cleaning and disinfection of care areas and equipment that include:<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>i.</label><p>Defined responsibility for specific items and areas;</p></list-item><list-item><label>ii.</label><p>Procedures for daily and terminal cleaning;</p></list-item><list-item><label>iii.</label><p>Procedures for cleaning in construction/renovation areas;</p></list-item><list-item><label>iv.</label><p>Procedures for cleaning and disinfecting areas contaminated with VRE and C. difficile;</p></list-item><list-item><label>v.</label><p>Procedures for outbreak management;</p></list-item><list-item><label>vi.</label><p>Cleaning standards and frequency;</p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p>Adequate human resources to allow thorough and timely cleaning and disinfection;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Education and continuing education of cleaning staff;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Monitoring of environmental cleanliness; and</p></list-item><list-item><p>Ongoing review of procedures. [BII]</p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p>If housekeeping services are contracted out, the Occupational Health and Safety policies of the contracting services must be consistent with the facility&#x02019;s Occupational Health and Safety policies. [BII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Housekeeping Department staffing levels should reflect the physical nature and the acuity of the facility; levels of supervisory staff should be appropriate to the number of staff involved in cleaning. [BIII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Non-critical medical equipment requires cleaning and disinfection after each use. [AII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Each health care setting should have written policies and procedures for the appropriate cleaning of non-critical medical equipment that clearly defines the frequency and level of cleaning and which assigns responsibility for the cleaning. [BIII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Cleaning schedules should be developed, with frequency of cleaning reflecting whether surfaces are high-touch or low-touch, the type of activity taking place in the area and the infection risk associated with it; the vulnerability of the patients housed in the area; and the probability of contamination. [BIII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>All environmental service staff entering a room, which is on Contact Precautions, must put on a gown and gloves on entering the room and must remove them and perform hand hygiene on leaving the room. [BII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>For adequate removal of C. difficile, the use of a sporicidal agent for disinfection after the room has been cleaned is needed. [BII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Housekeeping staff entering a room with Airborne Precautions must wear a fit tested N95 respirator. [BII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Housekeeping and clinical staff entering a room with Droplet Precautions must wear a surgical mask. [BII]</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Cleaning spills of blood and body substances</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Recommendations</title><p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Spills of blood and other bodily substances must be contained, cleaned and the area disinfected immediately. [BII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Absorbent disinfectant spillage granules may be more convenient to use instead of liquid disinfectant. [BIII]</p></list-item></list></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Infection control during construction and renovation</title><p>Construction and renovation activities in the hospital may be associated with transmission of pathogens such as filamentous fungi, including <italic>Aspergillus spp</italic>, <italic>Candida spp</italic>, <italic>Fusarium</italic> and also bacteria such as <italic>Legionella</italic> and <italic>Nocardia</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The most commonly reported hospital construction-related infection is <italic>Aspergillus</italic>, which represent the greatest threat to neutropenic patients.</p><p>&#x02018;<italic>Construction Clean</italic>&#x02019; is the level of cleaning performed by construction workers to remove gross soil, dust and dirt, construction materials and workplace hazards within the construction zone. This is done at the end of the day, or more frequently if needed, to avoid accumulation of dust. Hotel Clean and Hospital Clean begin where the construction site ends, i.e., outside the hoarding and are generally done by the staff of the health care setting.</p><p>Prior to the construction and renovation activities, an &#x02018;Infection Control (IC) Risk Assessment&#x02019; (Appendix A <xref rid="Sec27" ref-type="sec">1</xref>, <xref rid="Sec28" ref-type="sec">2</xref>, <xref rid="Sec29" ref-type="sec">3</xref>) must be completed. The risk assessment consists of the following 3 steps:-<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>I.</label><p>Identify the type of construction project. (<xref rid="Sec27" ref-type="sec">Appendix A1</xref>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>II.</label><p>Identify those patient areas at risk. (<xref rid="Sec28" ref-type="sec">Appendix A2</xref>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>III.</label><p>Match the type of construction activity with the patient risk group. (<xref rid="Sec29" ref-type="sec">Appendix A3</xref>)</p></list-item></list></p><p>Infection control precautions to be taken for respective class of risks are described in <xref rid="Sec29" ref-type="sec">Appendix A3.1</xref> and <xref rid="Sec29" ref-type="sec">3.2</xref></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Recommendations</title><p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Prior to any construction or renovation activity, patients who are at risk should be identified as high risk, medium risk and low risk patients. [BIII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Pre-construction and renovation consultation should be carried out in advance between all the stakeholders. [BIII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>During construction activities, it is necessary to contain or minimize dispersal of dust. [BIII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Once the project is started, the Infection Control Team shall conduct rounds in order to verify infection control compliance. [BIII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>If corrective measures are not adequate; the Head of Department of Infection Control has the authority to stop further work on the renovation/construction project until corrective measures are adequately addressed. [CIII]</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Cleaning and sanitation practices in food preparation areas</title><p>The manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions regarding the use and maintenance of equipment as well as the use of chemicals for cleaning and sanitizing food contact surfaces should be followed. Food contact surfaces such as those of sinks, tables, equipment, utensils, thermometers, carts should be washed, rinsed and sanitized before each use, between uses and anytime contamination occurs.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Recommendations</title><p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>All staff working in food preparation areas should report to work in good health and should practice good personal hygiene. [BIII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>The manufacturer's instructions regarding the use and maintenance of kitchen equipment should be followed. [BIII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>The manufacturer's instructions regarding the use of chemicals for cleaning and sanitizing food contact surfaces should be followed. [BIII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Cleaning eating utensils using the 3-compartment sink should involve the following steps:<list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>Washing with detergent</p></list-item><list-item><p>Rinsing with clean detergent</p></list-item><list-item><p>Sanitizing by chlorine or hot water [BIII]</p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p>When cleaning eating utensils using the dishwashing machine, the manufacturer's instructions should be followed for use. [BIII]</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Environmental cleaning after flood</title><p>Flood waters are characterized as either clear water, gray water, or black water [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Clear water refers to water from tap or rain water, while gray water refer to water from sinks, showers, tubs, and washers. In contrast, black water refers to flood water contaminated with waste from humans and animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. The recommended post-flood cleaning and disinfection processes are contingent upon the type of flood water and the material to be cleaned. A Spaulding classification is generally recommended for cleaning and disinfection for all healthcare equipment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Special approaches for area decontamination may be needed related to use of ultraviolet light C (UVC) and use of hydrogen peroxide vaporizers, in situations where fungal bioburden were higher than acceptable level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Recommendations</title><p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>The recommended post-flood cleaning and disinfection processes are dependent upon the type of flood water and material to be cleaned. [BIII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Cleaning processes for non-medical devices and surfaces should include detergent and water, clean water rinse, use of 10,000&#x000a0;ppm (1&#x000a0;% available chlorine) chlorine-based concentration disinfection, and air dry. An exception is use of 100,000&#x000a0;ppm (10&#x000a0;% available chlorine) chlorine-based disinfection for non-medical devices and surfaces suspected of fungal contamination. [BII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Special approaches (e.g., UVC and use of hydrogen peroxide vaporizers) can be used in situations where fungal bioburden were higher than acceptable level. [BII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>No recommendation can be made for other special approaches for area decontamination including use of ozone or other disinfectant (e.g. QUATS).</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Care and storage of cleaning supplies and utility rooms</title><p>All chemical cleaning agents and disinfectants should be appropriately labeled and stored in a manner that eliminates risk of contamination, inhalation, skin contact or personal injury. Chemicals must be clearly labeled with Safety Data Sheets (SDS) readily available for each item in case of accidents.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Recommendations</title><p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Cleaning agents and disinfectants shall be labeled with SDS information. [CIII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Cleaning agents and disinfectants shall be stored in a safe manner in storage rooms or closets. [CIII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Automated dispensing systems, which are monitored regularly for accurate calibration, are preferred over manual dilution and mixing. [BIII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Disinfectants should be dispensed into clean, dry, appropriately-sized bottles that are clearly labeled and dated; not topped up; and discarded after the expiry date. [AII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Equipment used to clean toilets:<list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>Should not be carried from room-to-room;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Should be discarded when the patient/resident leaves and as required; and</p></list-item><list-item><p>Should minimize splashing. [BIII]</p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p>Sufficient housekeeping rooms/closets should be provided throughout the facility to maintain a clean and sanitary environment. [BIII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Cleaning and disinfection equipment should be well maintained, in good repair and be cleaned and dried between uses. [BIII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Mop heads should be laundered daily and dried thoroughly before storage. [BIII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Cleaning carts should have a clear separation between clean and soiled items, should never contain personal items and should be thoroughly cleaned at the end of the day. [BII]</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Laundry and bedding</title><p>Policies and procedures should address the collection, transport, handling, washing and drying of soiled linen, including protection of staff and hand hygiene. National regulations must be followed if the facility does its own laundry.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Recommendations</title><p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>If the facility does its own laundry, national laundry regulations must be followed. [CIII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>There must be clear separation between clean and dirty laundry. [AII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>There must be policies and procedures to ensure that clean laundry is packaged, transported and stored in a manner that will ensure that cleanliness is maintained. [BII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>There must be designated areas for storing clean linen. [BII]</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Assessment of cleanliness and quality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</title><p>There are several methods for assessing environmental cleanliness:<list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>Conventional program of direct and indirect observation (e.g., visual assessment, observation of performance, patient/resident satisfaction surveys);</p></list-item><list-item><p>Enhanced program of monitoring residual bioburden (e.g., environmental culture, adenosine triphosphate - ATP-bioluminescence); and environmental marking tools (e.g., fluorescent marking)</p></list-item></list></p><p>Environmental marking measures the thoroughness of cleaning using a surrogate marking system. It involves the use of a colorless solution or Glo Germ powder or gel that is applied to objects and surfaces in the patient&#x02019;s environment prior to cleaning, followed by detection of residual marker (if any) immediately after cleaning, usually involving fluorescence under ultraviolet (UV) light. Environmental marking may be used either on a daily basis to assess routine cleaning, or prior to discharge to assess terminal cleaning.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Recommendations</title><p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>There should be a process in place to measure the quality of cleaning in the health care setting. [BII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Methods of monitoring cleanliness should include at least the conventional visual assessment and/or fluorescent marking. [BII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Results of cleaning audits should be collated and analyzed with feedback to staff, and an action plan developed to identify and correct deficiencies. [BIII]</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Staff education</title><p>Staff education, thus, plays a vital role in meeting these requirements and in educating involved healthcare personnel on various infection control aspects on hospital environmental control and cleaning, particularly in view of rapid staff turnover that occurs at many resource-limited settings.</p><p>Management and supervisory staff should receive training and education that also includes chain of infection, pest control, and outbreak response. Informal education should be complemented with in-service education on hand hygiene, appropriate and early diagnosis of infections, indications for area decontamination and hospital cleaning, and isolation precautions and policies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Ongoing staff education is important due to the new research and guidelines published every year, advancements in technology, and regulatory demands. Education should be focused on the role of environmental control to limit the spread of drug-resistant pathogens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Educational campaigns, including facility-wide, unit-targeted, and informal educational interventions, to enhance adherence to infection prevention and control can decrease MDRO transmission [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. The focus was to encourage a behavior change through improved understanding of the problem MDRO that the facility was trying to control. Whether the desired change involved hand hygiene, antimicrobial prescribing patterns, or something else, enhancing understanding and creating a culture that supported the desired behavior were viewed as essential to success.</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Recommendations</title><p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>All aspects of environmental cleaning must be supervised and performed by knowledgeable, training staff. [BIII]</p></list-item><list-item><p>Housekeeping must provide a training program which includes:<list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>A written curriculum</p></list-item><list-item><p>A mechanism for assessing proficiency</p></list-item><list-item><p>Documentation of training and proficiency verification</p></list-item><list-item><p>Orientation and continuing education [BIII]</p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p>Infection prevention and control education provided to staff working in Housekeeping should be developed in collaboration with Infection Prevention and Control and Occupational Health and Safety and must include:<list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>The correct and consistent use of routine practices</p></list-item><list-item><p>Hand hygiene and basic personal hygiene</p></list-item><list-item><p>Signage used to designate Additional Precautions in the health care setting</p></list-item><list-item><p>The appropriate use of personal protective equipment</p></list-item><list-item><p>Prevention of blood and body fluid exposure, including sharps, safety [BIII]</p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p>Housekeeping managers and supervisors must receive training and be certified. [BIII]</p></list-item></list></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec26" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p>We recommend healthcare facilities to include an environmental hygiene program as part of their Infection Control program. The goal of this program is to keep the environment safe for patients, staff and visitors. The best practices set out in the APSIC Guidelines For Environmental Cleaning And Decontamination will provide criteria for cleanliness that may be adopted by Environmental Services managers for their use or for the use of contracted service.</p></sec></body><back><app-group><app id="App1"><sec id="Sec27"><title>Appendix A1</title><p><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>STEP 1: Identify The Infection Control Risk Assessment (ICRA). TYPE OF CONSTRUCTION ACTIVITY OR PROJECT (circle type of project)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td>
<bold>Type A</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>Inspection and non</bold>-<bold>Invasive Activities</bold>
<break/>Includes but not limited to:<break/>&#x02022; Activities which do not generate dust or require cutting of walls or access to ceilings other than for visual inspection.<break/>eg. Removal of ceiling tiles for visual inspection, painting but not sanding, electrical work, minor plumbing that disrupt water supply to localized patient care area (e.g. in one room)</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>Type B</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>Small scale short duration activities which create minimal dust</bold>
<break/>Include but not limited to:<break/>eg. Activities that require access to duct spaces, cutting of walls, ceilings, sanding of walls for painting, plumbing that requires disruption to water supply of more than one patient care area (&#x0003e; two rooms) for less than 30&#x000a0;min.</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>Type C</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>Work that generates a moderate to high level of dust or requires demolition or removal of any fixed building components or assemblies</bold>
<break/>Include but not limited to:<break/>&#x02022; Sanding of walls for painting or wall covering<break/>&#x02022; Removal of floor coverings, ceiling tiles and case work<break/>&#x02022; New wall construction<break/>&#x02022; Minor duct work or electrical work above ceilings<break/>&#x02022; Major cabling activity<break/>&#x02022; Any activity that cannot be completed within a single work shift.</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>Type D</bold>
</td><td>
<bold>Major demolition</bold>, <bold>construction &#x00026; renovation projects</bold>
<break/>Includes but not limited to:<break/>&#x02022; Activities that require consecutive work shifts<break/>&#x02022; Require heavy demolition or removal of a complete cabling system<break/>&#x02022; New construction/New building project.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>Appendix A2</title><p><table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>STEP 2: Using the following Table, identify the patient risk groups affected by the activity. If more than one risk group will be affected, select the higher risk group. RISK GROUPS. IDENTIFY PATIENT AT RISK (circle area involved)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td>LOW RISK</td><td>MEDIUM RISK</td><td>HIGH RISK</td><td>HIGHER RISK</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02022; All office area<break/>&#x02022; Nonclinical areas</td><td>&#x025aa; Admitting Unit<break/>&#x025aa; Outpatient Areas<break/>&#x025aa; Food prep areas<break/>&#x025aa; Radiology<break/>&#x025aa; Nuclear Medicine<break/>&#x025aa; MRI<break/>&#x025aa; Endoscopy Unit<break/>&#x025aa; Outpatient Physical Therapy (Rehab)<break/>&#x025aa; Psychiatric Services (outpatient)<break/>&#x025aa; Cardiology services (outpatient)</td><td>&#x025aa; Trauma &#x00026; Emergency Department<break/>&#x025aa; Labor &#x00026; Delivery Ward<break/>&#x025aa; Pediatrics Wards<break/>&#x025aa; Pharmacy<break/>&#x025aa; Newborn Nursery<break/>&#x025aa; Clinical Pathology<break/>&#x025aa; Day Care Surgery<break/>&#x025aa; Central Stores<break/>&#x025aa; Laboratories<break/>&#x025aa; Medical Units<break/>&#x025aa; Surgical Units<break/>&#x025aa; Hemodialysis Unit</td><td>&#x025aa; Bone Marrow Transplant Unit<break/>&#x025aa; Burn Intensive Care Unit<break/>&#x025aa; Cardiac Cath Lab<break/>&#x025aa; Pharmacy Sterile Unit<break/>&#x025aa; Operating Rooms<break/>&#x025aa; Negative Air / Positive Air Pressure Rooms<break/>&#x025aa; Isolation Rooms (in all wards/ Units)<break/>&#x025aa; Intensive Care Units<break/>&#x025aa; Cardiac Intensive Care Unit<break/>&#x025aa; Dialysis Unit<break/>&#x025aa; PICU<break/>&#x025aa; CSSD<break/>&#x025aa; Oncology Ward<break/>&#x025aa; Any area / ward / unit caring for immunocompromised patients</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec29"><title>Appendix A3</title><p><table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>STEP 3: Match the planned Construction activity type (A,B,C,D) with the Patient Risk Group (low, medium, high, highest) to determine the Class of Precautions (1, 11, 111,1&#x000a0;V) or level of infection control activities required. RISK CLASS DETERMINATION</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2">PATIENT RISK GROUPS</td><td>CONSTRUCTION ACTIVITY</td><td>CONSTRUCTION ACTIVITY</td><td>CONSTRUCTION ACTIVITY</td><td>CONSTRUCTION ACTIVITY</td></tr><tr><td>TYPE A</td><td>TYPE B</td><td>TYPE C</td><td>TYPE D</td></tr><tr><td>Low Risk</td><td>1</td><td>11</td><td>11</td><td>111/ 1&#x000a0;V</td></tr><tr><td>Medium Risk</td><td>1</td><td>11</td><td>111 or 11</td><td>1&#x000a0;V</td></tr><tr><td>High Risk</td><td>1</td><td>11 or III</td><td>111/ 1&#x000a0;V</td><td>1&#x000a0;V</td></tr><tr><td>Highest Risk</td><td>11 or I-III</td><td>111/ 1&#x000a0;V</td><td>111/ 1&#x000a0;V</td><td>1&#x000a0;V</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Description of Required Infection Control Precautions by class: Refer Appendix A3.1 and 3.2</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Description of Required Infection Control Precautions by Class</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Pre-Construction</th><th>During Construction of Project</th><th>Upon Completion of Project</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
<bold>CLASS 1</bold>
</td><td/><td>1. Execute work by methods to minimize raising dust from construction operations<break/>2. Immediately replace a ceiling tile displaced for visual inspection</td><td>Clean work area upon completion of task.</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>CLASS 2</bold>
</td><td>1. Identify the type of construction project<break/>2. Identify those patients at risk area<break/>3. Discuss with Department of Engineering, Department of Facilities, Department of Nursing, Department of OSHA and Contractor regarding control of dust generation, patient placement and putting up of barriers<break/>4. Get infection control permit</td><td>1. Provide active means to prevent airborne dust from dispersing into atmosphere.<break/>2. Water mist for work surfaces to control dust while cutting<break/>3. Seal unused doors with duct tape<break/>4. Block off and seal air vents.<break/>5. Place dust mat at entrance and exit of work area.<break/>6. Remove or isolate air handling system in areas where work is being performed</td><td>1. Contain construction waste before transport in tightly covered containers.<break/>2. Wipe work surfaces with detergent and water/disinfectant forward areas.<break/>3. Wet mop and/ or vacuum with HEPA-filtered vacuum before leaving work area.<break/>4. Remove alterations of air handling system in the area where the work is being performed.</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>CLASS 3</bold>
</td><td>1. Identify the type of construction project<break/>2. Identify those patients at risk area<break/>3. Discuss with Department of facilities, Department of Nursing, Department of OSHA and Contractor regarding control of dust generation, patient placement and putting up of barriers<break/>4. Get infection control permit</td><td>1. Remove or isolate air handling system in area where work is being done to prevent contamination of duct system.<break/>2. Complete all critical barriers i.e., sheetrock, plywood, plastic, to seal area from non-work area<break/>3. Maintain negative air pressure within work site if necessary. Cease work immediately if negative pressure lost.<break/>4. Contain construction waste before transport in tightly covered containers.<break/>5. Cover transport receptacles or carts. Tape covering unless solid lid.</td><td>1. Do not remove barriers from work area until completed project is inspected by the Department of Engineering, Department of Infection Control, and thoroughly cleaned by Department of Facilities.<break/>2. Remove barrier materials carefully to minimize spreading of dirt and debris associated with construction.<break/>3. Vacuum work area including barriers with HEPA-filtered vacuums.<break/>4. Wet mop area with water &#x00026; detergent<break/>/disinfectant in ward areas.<break/>5. Remove alteration to the air handling system in areas where work is being performed.</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>CLASS 4</bold>
</td><td>1. Identify the type of construction project<break/>2. Identify those patients at risk area<break/>3. Discuss with Department of Facilities Department of Nursing and Department of OSHA and Contractor regarding control of dust generation, placement of patients and putting up of barriers<break/>4. Get infection control permit</td><td>1. Isolate air handling system in area where work is being done to prevent contamination of duct system.<break/>2. Complete all critical barriers i.e., sheetrock, plywood, plastic, to seal area from non-work area<break/>3. Maintain Negative air pressure within the work site. Cease work immediately if negative pressure lost.<break/>4. Contain construction waste before transport in tightly covered containers.<break/>5. Cover transport receptacles or carts. Tape covering unless solid lid.<break/>6. Seal holes, pipes, conduits and punctures appropriately.<break/>7. Construct anteroom and require all personnel to pass through this room so they can be vacuumed using HEPA vacuum before leaving the work site; or they can wear cloth or paper coveralls that are removed each time they leave the work site<break/>8. All personal entering the work site are required to wear shoe covers. Shoe covers must be changed each time the worker exits the work area.</td><td>1. Do not remove barriers from work area until completed project is inspected by Department of Engineering, Department of Infection Control and thoroughly cleaned by Department of Facilities<break/>2. Remove barrier materials carefully to minimize spreading of dirt and debris associated with construction.<break/>3. Contain construction waste before transport in tightly covered containers.<break/>4. Contain transport receptacles or carts. Tape covering unless solid lid.<break/>5. Vacuum work area with HEPA-filtered vacuums.<break/>6. Wet mop area with disinfectant.<break/>7. Remove isolation of air handling system in areas where work was performed.</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Pre-Construction</td><td>During Construction Project</td><td>Upon Completion Project</td></tr><tr><td>
<bold>CLASS 2</bold>, <bold>3 &#x00026; 4</bold>
</td><td/><td/><td>1. Put on air conditioning full blast for 2&#x000a0;days<break/>2. Lock doors to prevent intruder<break/>3. Final walk through inspection<break/>4. Observe if any dust on furniture<break/>5. Review effectiveness of any problems noted before<break/>6. Air sampling if necessary.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec></app></app-group><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Competing interests</bold></p><p>AA was supported by the National Research University Project of the Thailand Office of Higher Education Commission.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Authors&#x02019; contributions</bold></p><p>LML drafted the manuscript and AA did the initial editing before revised manuscript was seen by other authors for further comments. All authors read and approved the final manuscript and checklists.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgement</title><p>We acknowledge support through an educational grant from Advanced Sterilization Products, A Division of Johnson &#x00026; Johnson Medical ASEAN</p><p>Endorsed by:</p><p>1. Ho Chi Minh City Infection Control Society, Vietnam</p><p>2. Infection Control Association, Singapore [ICA (S)]</p><p>3. Nosocomial Infection Control Group of Thailand, Thailand</p><p>4. Philippines Hospital Infection Control Society (PHICS), Philippines</p><p>5. Association Infection Prevention Control Nurse Indonesia, Indonesia</p></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sehulster L, Chinn RY. Guidelines for environmental infection control in health-care facilities. Recommendations of CDC and the Healthcare Infection Control Practices Advisory Committee (HICPAC). MMWR Recomm Rep 2003;52 (RR-10):1&#x02013;42. Available from: http://www.cdc.gov/ncidod/dhqp/pdf/guidelines/Enviro_guide_03.pdf</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">PIDAC &#x02010; Best Practices for Environmental Cleaning for Prevention and Control of Infections (December 2009). Available from: http://www.oahpp.ca/resources/documents/pidac/Best%20Practices%20for%20Environmental%20Cleaning.pdf</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van de Mee-Marquet</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagarrigue</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Leroux</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Voyer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloc</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multiresistant Enterobacgter cloacae outbreak in an intensive care unit associated with therapeutic beds</article-title><source>Crit Care</source><year>2006</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>405</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/cc4835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16542475</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Parnell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Keer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkey</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Role of environmental cleaning in controlling an outbreak of Acinetobacter baumannii on a neurosurgical intensive care unti</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect</source><year>2004</year><volume>56</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2003.10.017</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15019221?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15019221</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruthazer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansjosten</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Barefoot</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Snydman</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of environmental contamination as a risk factor for acquisition of vancomycin-resistant enterococci in patients treated in a medical intensive care unit</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>163</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>1905</fpage><lpage>1912</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.163.16.1905</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12963563?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12963563</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livornese</surname><given-names>LL</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Samel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Romanowski</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>May</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hospital-acquired infection with vancomycin-resistant Enterococcus faecium transmitted by electronic thermometers</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>1992</year><volume>117</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-117-2-112</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1605425?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1605425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zanetti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanc</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Federli</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Raffoul</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Petignat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Maravic</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Importation of Acinetobacter baumannii into a burn unit: a recurrent outbreak of infection associated with widespread environmental contamination</article-title><source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>28</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>723</fpage><lpage>725</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/517956</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17520548?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17520548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayden</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonten</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Blom</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyle</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Vijver</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reduction in acquisition of vancomycin-resistant enterococcus after enforcement of routine environmental cleaning measures</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2006</year><volume>42</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1552</fpage><lpage>1560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/503845</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16652312?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16652312</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sample</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Gravel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Oxley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Toye</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Garber</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramotar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An outbreak of vancomycin-resistant enterococci in a hematology-oncology unit: control by patient cohorting and terminal cleaning of the environment</article-title><source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>23</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>468</fpage><lpage>470</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/502088</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12186215?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12186215</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dettenkofer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenzler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Amthor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Antes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Motschall</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Daschner</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does disinfection of environmental surfaces influence healthcare associated infection rates? A systematic review</article-title><source>Am J Infect Control</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajic.2003.07.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15057199?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15057199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwebke</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kampf</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How long do nosocomial pathogens persist in inanimate surfaces? A systematic review</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>130</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2334-6-130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16914034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neely</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Maley MPWarden</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computer keyboards as reservoirs for Acinetobacter baumannii in a burn hospital</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>1999</year><volume>29</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1358</fpage><lpage>1360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/313463</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10525257?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10525257</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rutala</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Whote</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gergen</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial contamination of keyboards: efficacy and functional impact of disinfectants</article-title><source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>27</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>372</fpage><lpage>377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/503340</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16622815?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16622815</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosokawa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamiya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contamination of room door handles by methicillin-sensitive/methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect</source><year>2002</year><volume>51</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/jhin.2002.1221</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12090803?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12090803</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarubbi</surname><given-names>FA</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Kopf</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>McGinnis</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutala</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased recovery of Aspergillus flavus from respiratory specimens during hospital construction</article-title><source>Am Rev Respir Dis</source><year>1982</year><volume>125</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><?supplied-pmid 6802046?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6802046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weems</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tablan</surname><given-names>OC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Martone</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Construction activity: an independent risk factor for invasive aspergillosis and zygomycosis in patients with hematologic malignancy</article-title><source>Infect Control</source><year>1987</year><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><?supplied-pmid 3470268?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3470268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Apisarnthanarak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Khawcharoenporn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mundy</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Black-Water Floods and Hospital-Based Postflood Mold Investigations</article-title><source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>33</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1266</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/668442</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23143369?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23143369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cozad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disinfection and the prevention of infectious disease</article-title><source>Am J Infect Control</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mic.2003.49</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12806363?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12806363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McDonnell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disinfection: is it time to reconsider Spaulding?</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect</source><year>2011</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2011.05.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21664533?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21664533</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rutala</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gergen</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Room decontamination with UV radiation</article-title><source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1025</fpage><lpage>1029</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/656244</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20804377?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20804377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Havill</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyce</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the microbiological efficacy of hydrogen peroxide vapor and ultraviolet light processes for room decontamination</article-title><source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>507</fpage><lpage>512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/665326</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22476278?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22476278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otter</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Puchowicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Salkeld</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Havill</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Feasibility of routinely using hydrogen peroxide vapor to decontaminate rooms in a busy United States hospital</article-title><source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>574</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/597544</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19415969?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19415969</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rutala</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are Room Decontamination Units Needed to Prevent Transmission of Environmental Pathogens?</article-title><source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>32</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>743</fpage><lpage>747</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/661226</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21768756?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21768756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearse</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of hydrogen peroxide vapour for environmental control during a Serratia outbreak in a neonatal intensive care unit</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect</source><year>2005</year><volume>61</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>364</fpage><lpage>366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2005.05.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16099537?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16099537</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dryden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parnaby</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dailly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis-Blues</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Otter</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hydrogen peroxide vapour decontamination in the control of a polyclonal meticillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus outbreak on a surgical ward [letter]</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect</source><year>2008</year><volume>68</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2007.11.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18192078?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18192078</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheorey</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cocks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the biological efficacy of hydrogenperoxide vapour decontamination in wards of an Australian hospital</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect</source><year>2011</year><volume>79</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2011.06.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21824681?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21824681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otter</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Tonder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Drabu</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing the biological efficacy and rate of recontamination following hydrogen peroxide vapour decontamination</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect</source><year>2007</year><volume>67</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2007.07.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17884250?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17884250</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shapey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Machin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Boswell</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activity of a dry mist hydrogen peroxide system against environmental Clostridium difficile contamination in elderly care wards</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect</source><year>2008</year><volume>70</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2008.06.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18694613?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18694613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmdahl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanbeck</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wullt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Walder</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A head-to-head comparison of hydrogen peroxide vapor and aerosol room decontamination systems</article-title><source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>32</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>831</fpage><lpage>836</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/661104</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21828962?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21828962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyce</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Havill</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dumigan</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Golebiewski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Baloqun</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Rizvani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monitoring the Effectiveness of Hospital Cleaning Practices by Use of an Adenosine Triphosphate Bioluminescence Assay</article-title><source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>30</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>678</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/598243</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19489715?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19489715</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carling</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Highlander</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved Cleaning of Patient Rooms Using a New Targeting Method</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2006</year><volume>42</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>385</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/499361</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16392086?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16392086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawar</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A systematic audit of economic evidence linking nosocomial infections and infection control interventions: 1990&#x02013;2000</article-title><source>Am J Infect Control</source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mic.2002.121099</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11988708?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11988708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilmore</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An evaluation of hospital cleaning regimes and standards</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect</source><year>2000</year><volume>45</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/jhin.1999.0717</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10833340?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10833340</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherlock</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Connell</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Creamer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is it really clean? An evaluation of the efficacy of four methods for determining hospital cleanliness</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect</source><year>2009</year><volume>72</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2009.02.013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19321226?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19321226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinbren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A modified ATP benchmark for evaluating the cleaning of some hospital environmental surfaces</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect</source><year>2008</year><volume>69</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2008.03.013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18468725?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18468725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyce</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Havill</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dumigan</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Golebiewski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Balogun</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Rizvani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monitoring the effectiveness of hospital cleaning practices by use of an adenosine triphosphate bioluminescence assay</article-title><source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>30</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>678</fpage><lpage>684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/598243</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19489715?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19489715</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Singleton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use of adenosine triphosphate bioluminescence to assess the efficacy of a modified cleaning program implemented within an intensive care setting</article-title><source>Am J Infect Control</source><year>2010</year><volume>38</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>622</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajic.2010.02.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20605265?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20605265</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carling</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Von Beheren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intensive care unit environmental cleaning: an evaluation in sixteen hospitals using a novel assessment tool</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect</source><year>2008</year><volume>68</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2007.09.015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18069083?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18069083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carling</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hylander</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An evaluation of patient area cleaning in 3 hospitals using a novel targeting methodology</article-title><source>Am J Infect Control</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajic.2005.09.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17015157?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17015157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stoessel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Truscott</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><source>National Patient Safety Goal 7: Recommendations for Compliance. <italic>Infection Control Today</italic></source><year>2009</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhinehart</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiarello</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><collab>Healthcare Infection Control Practices Advisory Committee</collab></person-group><source>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, National Center for Infectious Diseases. Management of Multidrug-Resistant Organisms in Healthcare Settings</source><year>2006</year></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>