<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>
 <bold>Standard of prevention for vaccine research and standard of care for treatment research</bold> are critical to ensure that study participants have equal access to the best‐proven standard.
 <fn id="dewb12283-note-1032">
  <label>32</label>
  <p>World Health Organization, op. cit. note 7.</p>
 </fn> This is a thorny issue for a novel pandemic like COVID‐19 since it is a new disease with no standard of prevention (other than public health measures) and care (other than intensive supportive care). In the absence of standardized regimens, the management of COVID‐19 patients has been pragmatic and individualized. The standard prevention package consists of washing hands with soap and running water for at least 20 seconds or use of hand sanitizer that contains at least 60% alcohol, where soap and water are not available; avoiding touching
 <bold> </bold>of eyes, nose, and mouth; physical distancing of at least 6 feet (2 meters); avoiding crowds and high‐ risk individuals; covering cough and sneezes; and covering mouth and nose with a facemask.
 <fn id="dewb12283-note-1033">
  <label>33</label>
  <p>Centre for Disease Control and Prevention. (2020, 24 April). How to protect yourself and others. Retrieved June 6, 2020, from 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/prevent-getting-sick/prevention.html" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019‐ncov/prevent‐getting‐sick/prevention.html</ext-link>.
  </p>
 </fn> The standard of prevention package for healthcare workers and home‐based carers involved in pre‐and or post‐exposure prophylaxis trials should include personal protective equipment. Standards of prevention and care packages for trial participants should be negotiated with community members while the protocol is being developed, and consensus should be reached on what is the best study based on evolving evidence.
 <fn id="dewb12283-note-1034">
  <label>34</label>
  <p>Haire, B., Folayan, M.O., Hankins, C., et al. (2013). Ethical considerations in determining standard of prevention packages for HIV prevention trials: Examining PrEP. Developing World Bioethics. 13(2), 87‐94.</p>
 </fn> It is also important that the trial be flexible enough to make changes to these standards as research evidence evolves. The Phambili HIV vaccine clinical trial is a best practice in this respect: its prevention package included medical male circumcision for study participants as soon as evidence emerges of its effectiveness.
 <fn id="dewb12283-note-1035">
  <label>35</label>
  <p>De Bruyn, G., Melisana, K, Metch B. (2009). P14‐07. Offering new prevention modalities in HIV vaccine trials: experience with male circumcision in the Phambili trial. Retrovirology. 6: P195.</p>
 </fn> Access to prevention and care packages for partners and family members also is important, as the risk for family members becoming infected during a vaccine trial, if the study participants become infected, is high.
 <fn id="dewb12283-note-1036">
  <label>36</label>
  <p>World Health Organization, op. cit. note 7.</p>
 </fn> For sub‐Saharan Africa, it is important to have ancillary care available for study participants who may have fever but are screened out of participating in COVID‐19 treatment trials. Research protocols should explicitly highlight consensus reached with stakeholders on the access of study participants to ancillary care and where possible, the report of the meeting with stakeholders on the decision‐making process submitted along with the research protocol for ethics committee consideration.
</p>
