<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0195">A coordinated effort by the host’s immune system is essential for battle against SARS-CoV-2. However, a dysregulated immune response has been reported in patients with COVID-19. Patients who were admitted to ICU on account of severe COVID-19 were reported to possess higher levels of IL-7, IL-2, IL-10, Granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (GCSF), Monocyte chemoattractant protein-1 (MCP-1), Tumor necrosis factor- α (TNF-α) compared with non-ICU patients suggesting a possible cytokine storm that ultimately culminates in Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS) 
 <xref rid="b0715" ref-type="bibr">[143]</xref>. Therefore, corticosteroids can be considered as an adjunct treatment option. However, currently, corticosteroid therapy is a topic of debate. Recently, Russel et al. suggested that there is no clinical evidence to support the use of corticosteroids in COVID-19 patients 
 <xref rid="b0720" ref-type="bibr">[144]</xref>. Notably, in a retrospective study, it was demonstrated that early, low-dose treatment intervention with corticosteroids was associated with quicker improvement of clinical symptoms 
 <xref rid="b0725" ref-type="bibr">[145]</xref>. Therefore, the use of corticosteroids for patients with COVID-19 is still under debate, and additional evidence is needed to be considered as a treatment intervention. Currently, a clinical trial is underway to evaluate the efficacy of dexamethasone in patients with ARDS secondary to SARS-CoV-2 infection (NCT04325061). Zhou et al. demonstrated that inflammatory and pro-inflammatory mediators like Granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF) and IL-6 are highly expressed following viral infection 
 <xref rid="b0730" ref-type="bibr">[146]</xref>. Therefore, blocking GM-CSF and IL-6 receptors can reduce the inflammatory response. In accordance with this, Mavrilimumab, a monoclonal antibody targeting the GM-CSF receptor, is currently under clinical trials (NCT04337216) to evaluate its efficacy. Clinical trials are also underway to evaluate the safety and efficacy of IL-6 receptor blockers like Sarilumab (NCT04315298), Tocilizumab (NCT04320615, NCT04315480) and Siltuximab (NCT04329650) for treating COVID-19. Baricitinib has been proposed as a potential drug for the treatment of COVID-19 
 <xref rid="b0735" ref-type="bibr">[147]</xref>. AP-2 associated protein kinase 1 (AAK1) is a promoter of endocytosis. Baricitinib is known to bind and inhibit AAK1 potently even at therapeutic doses (2 mg or 4 mg) and hence has the potential to prevent the virus entry. Moreover, it is also a known inhibitor of Janus kinases (JAK1 and JAK2), essential enzymes that are involved in signal transduction initiated by cytokines 
 <xref rid="b0735" ref-type="bibr">[147]</xref>. Therefore, inhibiting JAK enzymes contributes to its anti-inflammatory properties. However, inhibition of JAK1 and JAK2 by baricitinib appears to be a double-edged sword with respect to the treatment of COVID-19 
 <xref rid="b0740" ref-type="bibr">[148]</xref>. Interferons are essential soldiers deployed by host’s immune system in response to virus entry. Interferons mediate their antiviral effects via the JAK-STAT pathway. Hence, inhibiting JAK enzymes by baricitinib can inhibit interferon mediated antiviral response and might aid in the replication of SARS-CoV-2 
 <xref rid="b0740" ref-type="bibr">[148]</xref>. Currently, baricitinib is under clinical investigation (NCT04321993) as a potential drug for treating SARS-CoV-2 infection.
</p>
