<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0090">Further, ANG II is again metabolized to ANG III and ANG IV via various aminopeptidases [
 <xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0220" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. In addition, ANG I and ANG II are too converted to Ang-(1–7) with the help of endopeptidases and ACE-2, respectively. Lastly, Ang-(1–7) attaches to the Mas receptor (Mas-R) to wield anti-inflammatory and antifibrotic actions, stimulate the release of nitric oxide, and decrease blood pressure [
 <xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0220" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. ACE-2 has shown a variety of cardioprotective effects, including anti-thrombotic, anti- hypertrophic, anti-fibrotic, and anti-arrhythmic [
 <xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0220" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. ACE-2 is widely expressed in cardiac tissue, including cardiomyocytes, fibroblasts, and coronary endothelial cells. The number of studies has demonstrated that over-expression of ACE2 can prevent or even reverse the heart failure phenotype, whereas loss of ACE2 can enhance the progression of heart failure [
 <xref rid="bb0225" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0230" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Various research groups have documented that SARS-CoV-2 use ACE-2 as a cellular entry receptor [
 <xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0195" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] and the degree of infection caused by SARS-CoV-2 in heart or other cardiovascular tissues (potentially contributes to the myocarditis) is largely unknown. Therefore, it can be concluded that cardiovascular tissues or cells expressing ACE2 are possibly at extreme risk for SARS-CoV-2 infection. In COVID-19 patients with pre-existing CVD, the demise of ACE2 by SARS-CoV-2- via internalization mechanism has been predicted to exacerbate CVD acutely and maybe long term [
 <xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="bb0220" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>].
</p>
