<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">Foodborne illness or disease remains a major public health problem globally with substantial economic impact. It results from the consumption of contaminated food or water containing pathogenic bacteria, viruses, or parasites as well as chemical or natural toxins. Acute gastroenteritis is the most common clinical manifestation of foodborne disease, and diarrhoea, characterized by frequent loose or liquid bowel movements, is a common cause of death in developing countries and the second most common cause of morbidity and mortality in young infants worldwide with up to 0.8–1.5 million deaths each year [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. High population density, limited access to clean water, frequent flooding and poor sanitation render surface water bodies in developing countries particularly vulnerable to faecal contamination, leading to a high prevalence of diarrhoeal diseases in both children and adults when untreated water is used for food preparation or drinking. In industrialized countries, where sanitation is widely available, access to safe water is high and personal and domestic hygiene is relatively good, diarrhoeal diseases remain a significant cause of morbidity among all age groups. In the majority of cases, symptoms are brief, and patients do not require medical attention. Though typically self-limited, infectious diarrhoea episodes result in millions of physician visits annually. A range of pathogens has been associated with foodborne illness, but a handful of organisms cause the majority of acute gastroenteritis cases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. It was not until 1972 that viruses were implicated as aetiological agents in diarrhoea; Norwalk virus was identified in the faeces of patients with diarrhoea, followed by rotaviruses in 1973, and enteric adeno- and astroviruses in 1975 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].
</p>
