<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Beyond the technical aspects that we have described in detail, MGF provides a framework for adaptively managing the human dimension of interdisciplinary research collaborations. Indeed, the iterative process allows input from all disciplines at multiple points, helping to resolve or avoid altogether counter-productive situations where modellers are asked to develop a model without sufficient data or where field biologists are handed a model with inappropriate assumptions. However, even within this framework, there are critical capabilities that must be developed within the research group as a whole to ensure an efficient and durable collaboration. First, the group must define common goals and questions (Gorman 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">2012</xref>), which is not as easy to achieve as it may sound. Too often in research, interdisciplinary collaborators draw targets around their current personal research interests rather than defining superordinate goals and then agreeing on the means to achieve them. The MGF approach essentially forces participants to develop shared questions and goals before the research is undertaken. Second, members of the collaboration need to develop ‘moral imagination’ which involves seeing the problems from the perspective of other stakeholders (Gorman 
 <italic>et al</italic>. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">2012</xref>). Often researchers from different fields will have fundamentally different perspectives on how to tackle a problem, aptly described by Gorman 
 <italic>et al</italic>. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">2001</xref>) who stated that ‘most scholars like to share frameworks about as much as they like to share toothbrushes’. Hence, the third capability, developing ‘trading zones’ (Galison 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">1997</xref>), is necessary for exchanging ideas or sharing data and resources. All three of these capabilities can be facilitated by ‘interactional experts’—individuals who understand enough of the disciplinary cultures and languages to facilitate a common language, common goals, shared mental models, exchange of knowledge and a shared framework for investigation (Gorman 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">2010</xref>). Such expertise has traditionally been gained over long periods of personal collaborations, but more opportunities are now available for early-career training through formal courses and workshops. For example, in MGF, interactional experts would include veterinarians with post-graduate training in mathematical modelling, immunologists with training in ecology or mathematicians with a training in epidemiology. Both offer and demand for such interdisciplinary training need to be encouraged.
</p>
