<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2">Modelling the transmission network of infectious disease outbreaks is a very active research area important for informing control of transboundary and emerging infectious diseases such as Ebola haemorrhagic fever (in humans) and foot-and-mouth disease (in livestock populations). A number of dynamic models have recently been published that combine genomic and epidemiological data to reconstruct the network of who infected whom in outbreaks
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>. For such models to reliably inform decision-making they must be transparently validated, robust, and capable of producing accurate predictions within short data collection to inference timeframes typical of outbreak responses. Several such models have recently been assessed based on outbreak datasets simulated using very similar methods to the inferential frameworks of the models themselves
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>
 </sup>, and/or model cross-comparisons of predicted transmission networks for small clusters of infected individuals (or ‘infected premises’ in veterinary examples) such as the foot-and-mouth disease ‘Darlington cluster’ in the 2001 outbreak in the United Kingdom
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>
 </sup>. These two approaches, however, only provide a low level of ‘pseudo-validation’. The first approach is not a robust estimate of predictive performance for outbreaks arising from stochastic processes that differ from those underpinning the models themselves. The second approach does not provide a ‘gold standard’ as the true transmission network of the ‘Darlington cluster’ remains unknown, with conflicting genomic and epidemiological data. The predictive accuracy of the transmission network models thus remains unclear, particularly because it is common for different models to predict distinctly different transmission networks for the same outbreak.
</p>
