<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0010">Similar to other emerging viral infections, the 
 <italic>de novo</italic> development of antiviral drugs would inevitably lag behind the rapid progression of the epidemic [
 <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Drug repurposing is therefore a feasible strategy to quickly identify clinically approved drugs with known pharmacological properties and safety profiles that can be immediately used in clinical trial settings. A number of existing drugs, such as remedsivir, chloroquine, hydroxychloroquine, nafamostat, camostat, and ivermectin, have been reported to exhibit anti-SARS-CoV-2 activity 
 <italic>in vitro</italic> and/or in a very small number of patients [
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>]. Remdesivir is a nucleotide analogue with broad-spectrum antiviral activities including against SARS-CoV-2 [
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Chloroquine and hydroxychloroquine are mildly immunosuppressive drugs used in the treatment of autoimmune diseases and malaria that exhibited 50 % maximal effective concentration (EC
 <sub>50</sub>) at or above the peak serum concentration (Cmax) achievable with standard dosing in human [
 <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. A recent non-randomized small-scale clinical study showed that hydroxychloroquine with or without azithromycin significantly reduced the viral load and duration of virus shedding in 20 COVID-19 patients [
 <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Nafamostat and camostat are a serine protease inhibitor used in the treatment of chronic pancreatitis and reflux esophagitis [
 <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Ivermectin is a macrocyclic lactone used in the treatment of various parasitic infections [
 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. However, data from well-designed randomized controlled trials for these drugs are not yet available. Therefore, there is an urgent need to search for additional drug compounds with anti-SARS-CoV-2 activity among clinically approved drugs. In this study, we first established a robust two-tier drug screening system by combining SARS-CoV-2 enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay with cell viability assay, and then applied it to screen an FDA-approved drug compound library. We successfully identified a number of drug compounds with anti-SARS-CoV-2 activity, including bexarotene which has broad-spectrum anti-coronaviral activity and a higher Cmax to EC
 <sub>50</sub> ratio than most other reported potential anti-SARS-CoV-2 agents.
</p>
