<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although a HeV vaccine has been licensed for use in horses in Australia (Equivac
 <sup>®</sup> HeV, Zoetis, Parsippany-Troy Hills, New Jersey, USA), there are currently no NiV vaccines licensed for use in animals or humans. The Ebola virus epidemic in west Africa in 2014–2015 highlighted the need for vaccines to prevent and contain outbreaks of epidemic zoonotic diseases. In response, the Coalition of Epidemic Preparedness Innovations (CEPI) was formed and the development of a human NiV vaccine was prioritized [
 <xref rid="B24-vaccines-08-00115" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The development of a NiV vaccine for use in pigs would represent another tool to prevent and/or contain NiV outbreaks [
 <xref rid="B23-vaccines-08-00115" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Such a vaccine should be safe, efficacious (capable of providing a rapid onset of immunity and preventing NiV transmission), enable discrimination of infected from vaccinated animals (DIVA), inexpensive and amenable to surge production. Recombinant viral vectors are an attractive class of vaccine delivery systems; being safe, simple to construct and manufacture and combining the immunogenicity of live attenuated vaccines (self-adjuvanting through activation of relevant innate immune responses) with the targeted specificity/DIVA potential of subunit vaccines. A range of viral vectored NiV vaccines including adenovirus, measles virus, vesicular stomatitis virus and rabies virus have shown promising results in laboratory animal studies [
 <xref rid="B15-vaccines-08-00115" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-vaccines-08-00115" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Canarypox viruses (ALVAC) expressing NiV glycoproteins (ALVAC NiV G and ALVAC NiV F) have been shown to induce responses which protect pigs against experimental NiV challenge [
 <xref rid="B25-vaccines-08-00115" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-vaccines-08-00115" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. High titers of NiV neutralizing antibodies (nAbs) were induced with the ALVAC NiV G vaccine, while despite lower levels of nAbs induced by the ALVAC NiV F; all vaccinated pigs were protected. The failure of Equivac
 <sup>®</sup> HeV, a proven adjuvanted HeV G protein subunit-based vaccine, to protect pigs against either HeV or NiV was speculated to be due to the failure of the vaccine to induce T cell responses [
 <xref rid="B27-vaccines-08-00115" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], highlighting a need to induce both antibody and cell-mediated immunity.
</p>
