<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to serving as a protective barrier, skin has also long been known to be an important part of the immune system (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Bos and Kapsenberg, 1993</xref>). The first human vaccine, vaccinia, is administered by the ID route. Skin dermis is enriched with dermal DCs as well as Langerhans cells that are professional antigen presenting cells for immune surveillance (
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Flacher et al., 2006</xref>). In early studies, it has also been shown that influenza vaccines delivered by ID injection are safe and immunogenic in children (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Rendtorff et al., 1959</xref>). However, due to the technical difficulty of ID injection by the conventional Mantoux method as well as the small volume of vaccines that can be delivered by this route, ID injection is not widely practiced for current vaccine delivery with the exception of the BCG vaccination against Tuberculosis. More recent studies showed that administration of influenza vaccines through ID immunization required reduced vaccine doses for eliciting similar levels of immune responses as IM delivery of influenza vaccines (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Kenney et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Chiu et al., 2007</xref>). In recent studies, new technologies are being development for vaccine delivery through the ID route. A new needle-syringe device that only exposed the tip of the needle has recently been designed for easier ID injection of influenza vaccines (
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Laurent et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Holland et al., 2008</xref>), and this approach has now been approved for ID delivery of seasonal influenza vaccines. Moreover, microneedles are also under development for ID delivery of vaccines (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Gill et al., 2014</xref>). Recent studies have shown that ID delivery of influenza vaccines using microneedles is superior to the conventional IM immunization approach for inducing antibody responses to confer long lasting protection against influenza virus infection in mice (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Koutsonanos et al., 2012</xref>). We have in recent studies shown that ID delivery of adjuvanted EBOV GP or sGP protein subunit vaccines by microneedles was able to induce strong antibody responses against EBOV GP similarly to IM immunizations, and provided complete protection against lethal challenge in mice (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2018a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>). Our results from this study demonstrated that ID injection of EBOV VLPs is as effective as IM injection for eliciting immune responses in guinea pigs that are protective against lethal EBOV challenge. Further, by analyzing antibody responses after immunizations, we found that while similar levels of IgG2 antibodies against GP were induced by both IM and ID injections, ID immunization of EBOV VLPs induced significantly higher levels of IgG1 antibodies against GP than IM immunization. Moreover, our results from blocking ELISA studies show that the IgG1 antibodies induced by ID injection recognize different epitopes from the IgG2 antibodies induced by IM injection. These findings indicate that antigens delivered to dermal sites may be processed differently by local antigen presenting cells that leads to more comprehensive presentation of different epitopes for induction of immune responses. Future studies to determine the targets in GP recognized by IgG1 antibodies induced by ID immunization will reveal whether such antibodies may contribute to the control of virus infection either directly or in synergy with IgG2 antibodies and provide more effective protection against EBOV infection.
</p>
