<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We first calculated the population consensus sequences for subtypes A, D and C using the same sequences used to calculate the between-host evolutionary rates. For each of the 34 individuals in our study, we limited our analysis to sites that were fixed or nearly fixed for a single base at the first time point (&gt;99% frequency). Of these sites, we defined them to be polymorphic for a given sampling time period (between 0 and 2 years since seroconversion; between 2 and 4 years since seroconversion; or over 4 years since seroconversion) if a mutation had reached an appreciable frequency (&gt;10%) at least once during that period. For each sampling time period, we pooled data across all individuals and calculated the proportion of the changes at polymorphic sites that were towards the subtype-specific consensus for all mutations, synonymous mutations and nonsynonymous mutations (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat.1007167.g004">Fig 4</xref>). Additionally, we calculated the expected proportion of mutations towards the subtype-specific population consensus at polymorphic sites, assuming no selection, and a transition to transversion ratio of 2, thus accounting for a higher number of transitions in the absence of selection [
 <xref rid="ppat.1007167.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. The bias towards population consensus was then calculated as the proportion of mutations towards subtype-specific population consensus, divided by the expected proportion of mutations towards population consensus (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ppat.1007167.g004">Fig 4</xref>). In 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1007167.s006">S6 Fig</xref>, we also show the bias towards consensus for polymorphic sites assuming different transition to transversion ratios (0.5 and 4), and for all sites (not just polymorphic sites). In addition, we calculated the proportion of mutations towards population consensus at sites that were not at population consensus at the first time point (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="ppat.1007167.s006">S6 Fig</xref>).
</p>
