<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Female C57BL/6J mice (6–8 weeks old) were housed at 30±1°C or 22±1°C for 5 days. Mice were left untreated (Control) or feet were injected s.c. (as for CHIKV infection [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006788.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]) with 0.5 μg of poly(I:C) mixed with jetPEI transfection reagent (Polyplus Transfection, NY, USA) [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006788.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] (Treated). Twelve samples were prepared; each contained pooled RNA from 3–4 mouse feet from 3–4 different mice, with equal amounts of RNA from each foot in each pool. The 12 samples represent 3 biological replicates for each of the four conditions; (i) feet from control (C) mice housed at 30°C (30C), (ii) feet from control (C) mice housed at 22°C (22C), (iii) feet from poly(I:C)/jetPEI treated (T) mice held at 30°C (30T), (iv) feet from poly(I:C) /jetPEI treated (T) mice held at 22°C (22T). Sample preparation and RNA-Seq was undertaken essentially as described [
 <xref rid="ppat.1006788.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Briefly, feet were lacerated and placed in RNAlater (Life Technologies), homogenized in TRIzol (Invitrogen), centrifuged (12,000 g x 10 min) and RNA extracted from the supernatants as per manufacturer’s instructions. RNA samples were DNase treated using RNAse-Free DNAse Set (Qiagen) and purified using an RNeasy MinElute Kit (Qiagen). Samples were sent to the Australian Genome Research Facility (Melbourne, Australia). cDNA libraries were prepared using a TruSeq RNA Sample Prep Kit (v2) (Illumina Inc. San Diego, USA), which includes isolation of poly-adenylated RNA using oligo-dt beads. cDNA libraries were sequenced (100 bp single end reads) using the Illumina HiSeq 2500 Sequencer (Illumina Inc.). The per base sequence quality was high, with &gt;84% of bases above Q30 for all 12 samples. The primary sequence data was generated using the Illumina bcl2fastq 2.18.0.12 pipeline. After removal of Illumina adaptor/over-represented sequences and cross-species contamination, reads were mapped to the mouse genome (Mus_musculus.GRCm38) using Tophat aligner (v2.0.14). The counts of reads mapping to each known gene (with gencode annotation vM6 as reference) were summarized at gene level using the featreCounts v1.4.6-p5 utility of the subread package (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://subread.sourceforge.net/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://subread.sourceforge.net/</ext-link>). The transcripts were assembled with the Stringtie tool v1.2.4 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ccb.jhu.edu/software/stringtie/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://ccb.jhu.edu/software/stringtie/</ext-link>) utilizing the read alignment and reference annotation based assembly option (RABT).
</p>
