<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par37">Outbreaks of infectious diseases have often shown a pattern of generating a quick surge of publications on their respective topics, such that they often create an entirely new literature over a short period of time (Olijnyk 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2015</xref>; Tian and Zheng 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2015</xref>). By all measures, however, the influx of the research publications that began to emerge following the 2019 Novel coronavirus outbreak outsizes those of the previous cases in the history of coronaviruses, and perhaps arguably, in the history of infectious diaereses (Tian and Zheng 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2015</xref>). This has certainly marked a new milestone in the timeline of research on coronaviruses which dates back to 1968 
 <underline>(</underline>Almeida et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1968</xref>
 <underline>)</underline>. According to the editor-in-chief of the 
 <italic>Journal of Virology</italic>, as quoted in an article of 
 <italic>The Scientist</italic> magazine 
 <underline>(</underline>Jarvis 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2020</xref>
 <underline>),</underline> this surge of research outputs has been to the extent that has inundated established coronavirus researchers and domain experts with peer review requests to an extent that they are unable to cope. Parallel to such intensified efforts on the research, peer review and editorial fronts, widespread efforts have also been underway in synthesising, summarising and visualising these rapid developments, a pattern that has also been observed—though at much smaller scales—with respect to the previous epidemics of viral diseases (Kostoff and Morse 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2011</xref>). In line with these endeavours, this work also aimed at quantifying and analysing scientometric aspects of the Covid-19 literature in contrast with those of the previous major coronavirus diseases, i.e. SARS and MERS. The focus for sourcing these literatures has been on peer reviewed and published studies.
</p>
