<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<author-notes>
 <corresp id="cor1">
  <label>*</label>Address correspondence to Catherine E. Oldenburg, Francis I. Proctor Foundation, University of California, San Francisco, 513 Parnassus Ave., San Francisco, CA 94143. E-mail: 
  <email>catherine.oldenburg@ucsf.edu</email>
 </corresp>
 <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn1">
  <p>Financial support: The studies included in this analysis were supported by the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation (T. M. L.) and the National Eye Institute (U10 EY016214; T. M. L.). The funders had no role in the study design, analysis, interpretation of data, or decision to publish.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn2">
  <p>Disclaimer: Results presented in part at World Health Organization, Montreaux, Switzerland, March 2018.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="present-address" id="fn3">
  <p>Authors’ addresses: Catherine E. Oldenburg, Jeremy D. Keenan, Thomas M. Lietman, and Travis C. Porco, Francis I Proctor Foundation, University of California, San Francisco, San Francisco, CA, and Department of Ophthalmology, University of California, San Francisco, San Francisco, CA, E-mails: 
   <email>catherine.oldenburg@ucsf.edu</email>, 
   <email>jeremy.keenan@ucsf.edu</email>, 
   <email>tom.lietman@ucsf.edu</email>, and 
   <email>travis.porco@ucsf.edu</email>. Ahmed M. Arzika, The Carter Center, Niamey, Niger, E-mail: 
   <email>mamaneahmed@yahoo.fr</email>. Abdou Amza, Program FSS/Université Abdou Moumouni de Niamey, Program National de Santé Oculaire, Niamey, Niger, E-mail: 
   <email>dr.amzaabdou@gmail.com</email>. Teshome Gebre, The Carter Center, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, E-mail: 
   <email>tgebre@taskforce.org</email>. Khumbo Kalua, Blantyre Institute for Community Outreach and the College of Medicine, University of Malawi, Blantyre, Malawi, E-mail: 
   <email>khumbokalua@yahoo.com</email>. Zakayo Mrango, National Institute for Medical Research, Dar es Salaam, Tanzania, E-mail: 
   <email>mrango@yahoo.com</email>. Sun Y. Cotter and Kieran S. O’Brien, Francis I Proctor Foundation, University of California, San Francisco, San Francisco, CA, E-mails: 
   <email>sun.cotter@ucsf.edu</email> and 
   <email>kieran.obrien@ucsf.edu</email>. Sheila K. West, The Dana Center, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, E-mail: 
   <email>shwest@jhmi.edu</email>. Robin L. Bailey, The London School of Tropical Hygiene and Medicine, London, United Kingdom, E-mail: 
   <email>robin.bailey@lshtm.ac.uk</email>. Paul M. Emerson, The International Trachoma Initiative, Decatur and Emory University, Atlanta, GA, E-mail: 
   <email>pemerson@taskforce.org</email>.
  </p>
 </fn>
</author-notes>
