<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Cellular and tissue functions exhibit rhythmic fluctuations over the course of 24 h that impact the susceptibility to or progression of the viral infection. Several core-clock elements have been reported to modulate viral infection. BMAL1 and PER2 are regulators of antiviral immunity, as described in the previous section, and additional roles for PER1 and REV-ERBα, as well as melatonin have been highlighted, as described in the following. The seasonal variation of BMAL1 expression, reaching its lowest values in winter, seems to contribute to the high occurrence of respiratory viral diseases in this season since low 
 <italic>BMAL1</italic> expression enhances viral disease [
 <xref rid="B56-pathogens-09-00083" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-pathogens-09-00083" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. An effect of the circadian clock in viral infection was also reported for wild-type mice infected with murine herpesvirus 4 at different times of the day. The mice were kept under controlled temperature and lighting environment (12-h light/12-h darkness), and the levels of infection and spread of the virus were evaluated [
 <xref rid="B58-pathogens-09-00083" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. In mice infected at the beginning of the day, corresponding to the beginning of the resting phase of these nocturnal animals, the viral replication was increased tenfold compared to the values measured in mice infected during the night period, corresponding to the activity phase. In mice lacking 
 <italic>BMAL1</italic>, the levels of virus replication were independent of the time of day at which the viral infection was performed [
 <xref rid="B58-pathogens-09-00083" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. The effect of time of infection on virus replication was independent of the immune system, as also confirmed on single cell cultures (embryonic fibroblasts), in which several time-dependent processes (intracellular trafficking, biosynthetic processes, protein synthesis, and chromatin assembly) were involved. The obliteration of cellular circadian rhythms increased the replication of herpes and influenza A viruses, which lost rhythmic fluctuation and remained persistently high [
 <xref rid="B58-pathogens-09-00083" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. The time of day of herpes simplex virus type 2 (HSV-2) infection impacted the outcome of the pathology in wild-type mice kept under 12-h light and 12-h darkness (LD 12:12), probably due to the circadian rhythmic expression of the HSV-2 receptor in the skin Nectin1. This effect was confirmed in immunodeficient RAG2-knockout mice [
 <xref rid="B59-pathogens-09-00083" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>].
</p>
