<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Carefully designed DDI studies are a major element of clinical research of TB therapeutics for treatment and prevention of TB in HIV-infected people, including HIV-infected adults and children [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002882.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>]. DDIs may be bidirectional, and the potential impact of host genetics is difficult to predict from small PK studies alone. To facilitate enrollment of HIV-infected individuals, DDI studies should be conducted early in drug development and/or nested in major trials [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002882.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. The Phase III randomized ACTG 5279 trial, “Short-Course Rifapentine/Isoniazid for Treatment of Latent TB in HIV-Infected Individuals” (NCT01404312)[
 <xref rid="pmed.1002882.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], is an example of a nested DDI study: the first 90 participants that were on efavirenz-based ART and randomized to the rifapentine arm entered into a semi-intensive PK study [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002882.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] and were evaluated for PK/PD and potential HIV virologic failure to confirm that efavirenz PK and ART outcomes remained adequate. As in this example, the risk to a TB trial may be lower if PK of an HIV drug is the concern, particularly for shorter periods of TB drug use. If the potential DDI involves one of the TB drugs and may affect the randomized comparison, then an alternative trial design might be used: HIV-infected individuals could be excluded from randomization to the TB intervention but entered into a parallel PK cohort to evaluate the DDI. Once the potential DDI has been resolved, including by testing different drug dosing, randomization of HIV-infected individuals might proceed expeditiously. Alternatively, an observational study could be conducted whereby HIV-infected people who are on a targeted HIV drug and start a TB drug of interest would undergo PK/PD evaluations. IMPAACT P1026s (NCT00042289) uses this design to evaluate routinely used dosing of ART and TB (DS and DR TB) drugs during pregnancy in HIV-infected and uninfected women. The key is to have an ongoing, approved protocol in place that allows for targeted drugs to be studied without needing to develop a new study for each potential DDI. Irrespective of the design used, the respective advantages and disadvantages of intensive versus sparse drug sampling should be considered to facilitate rapid enrollment and availability of information about potential DDIs.
</p>
